<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond Ireland to a Wider Yet Often Bleak World</title>
    <meta content="20ARTS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dublin Writers' Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Impac Dublin Literary Award 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ireland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lavery, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barker, Nicola</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0D71531F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond Ireland to a Wider Yet Often Bleak World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Brian Lavery</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lavery, Brian</byline>
      <dateline>DUBLIN, June 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brian Lavery Arts Abroad column on literary scene in Ireland; cites Dublin Writers' Festival, four-day event featuring some 40 contemporary novelists and poets; notes award of International Impac Dublin Literary Award, world's largest prize for single work of fiction, to novelist Nicola Barker; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A stone's throw from Davy Byrne's pub, where fans of James Joyce celebrated ''Ulysses'' on Friday night, St. Anne's Church was packed straight  up to the organ pipes with more than 700 people waiting to hear Irish authors read from their work at the Dublin Writers' Festival.</p>
        <p>Before stepping to the microphone, the writer Colum McCann asked one of the festival organizers if he could  read a letter by Joyce. It was a fair question: on June 16, or Bloomsday, this city delights in celebrating Joyce, its most famous prodigal son. But Pat Boran, who helped found the festival four years ago, made it quite clear that Leopold Bloom was not welcome at this particular party, warning with some choice Irish obscenities, ''Don't you dare.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A stone's throw from Davy Byrne's pub, where fans of James Joyce celebrated ''Ulysses'' on Friday night, St. Anne's Church was packed straight  up to the organ pipes with more than 700 people waiting to hear Irish authors read from their work at the Dublin Writers' Festival.</p>
        <p>Before stepping to the microphone, the writer Colum McCann asked one of the festival organizers if he could  read a letter by Joyce. It was a fair question: on June 16, or Bloomsday, this city delights in celebrating Joyce, its most famous prodigal son. But Pat Boran, who helped found the festival four years ago, made it quite clear that Leopold Bloom was not welcome at this particular party, warning with some choice Irish obscenities, ''Don't you dare.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boran is not alone among Irish writers who want to keep their distance from what has become the Disney World atmosphere of Bloomsday, with literary tourists re-enacting scenes in Victorian era bowler hats and frilly blouses. So the festival managed to give Joyce a quick nod, then nimbly step out from under his shadow.</p>
        <p>Jack Gilligan, the festival director, said: ''There are other great contemporary writers out there. We don't have to wait for them to die to celebrate them.'' To that end, the festival featured about 40 contemporary novelists and poets from Ireland as well as a handful from Denmark, England, Germany and Lebanon.</p>
        <p>The four-day event opened with Doris Lessing, who engaged in a lively conversation with the audience of 300 that upstaged her reading of her new novel.</p>
        <p>Less mainstream material proved popular as well, including a reading by children's authors. A session of material written in Gaelic drew a full house.</p>
        <p>On Saturday night, the spotlight shifted somewhat from the Writers' Festival, which began on Thursday and ended on Sunday, to the International Impac Dublin Literary Award. In its fifth year, the award is gaining recognition for its $:100,000 Irish ($120,000) prize money, the world's largest prize for a single work of fiction. By comparison, Britain's prestigious Booker Prize offers around $25,000.</p>
        <p>''I think all of these awards should be more substantial,'' said James B.  Irwin Sr., founder of the American management consultancy IMPAC, which set up the award with an endowment of $1.5 million. Thanks to his grandfather, who emigrated from Ireland to the Bronx, Mr. Irwin holds dual citizenship and chose to locate Impac's European headquarters in Dublin more than 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>The company ceded administration of the award to the Dublin public  libraries. Libraries around the world nominate works of fiction, which are  then narrowed to a short list and deliberated by a panel of judges.</p>
        <p>During the buzz of Bloomsday activity, Impac mostly kept to itself. Its  glittery award ceremony was run with no reference to the Dublin Writers' Festival. Guests at the black tie award ceremony were greeted by a corps of bagpipe players, followed by actors on stilts coated in gold and silver body paint.</p>
        <p>Nicola Barker, the British writer,  won for her 1998 novel ''Wide Open.''  John Hume, the Nobel Peace Prize winner for his efforts to broker a solution in Northern Ireland, presented  the literary award at the Irish Museum of Modern Art here. Toni Morrison and Philip Roth had been on the short list for the prize. Ms. Barker read from ''Wide Open'' at the festival's closing event. Mr. McCann had flown in from New York because his 1998 novel, ''The Other Side of Brightness,'' was on the short list for the Impac prize. Last year's winner, Andrew Miller, read from an unpublished manuscript entitled ''Oxygen'' and answered audience questions with Colm Toibin, one of Ireland's most accomplished contemporary novelists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hume's presence at the ceremony and Mr. Toibin's seat on the judging panel reaffirmed that the award is more than just an international literary event that happens to take place in Dublin; it is a festival  that celebrates Irish writing, allowing the nation's authors to stand up to the legacy of Joyce as well as another figure dominating Ireland's cultural landscape, Frank McCourt. Mr. McCourt's work has in some ways made it harder for younger Irish writers to work with the country's best-known literary themes, from rural poverty to alcoholism to family strife.</p>
        <p>Ireland is experiencing both  peace and economic prosperity for the first time in modern history, which means a transition for its literature after centuries of suffering and struggle. Still, a handful of Irish playwrights -- including Sebastian Barry and Martin McDonagh, both Broadway favorites -- continue to explore the harsh conditions of decades gone  by.</p>
        <p>The up-and-coming generation of Irish writers were born during the 1960's, left the country during the 80's and have since returned. To some, the Irish novel has become an international novel, Mr. McCann said. His book ''The Other Side of Brightness,'' for instance, explores the history of the New York City subway from the point of view of what he calls international mongrels: manual laborers digging the tunnels and  homeless people living beneath the  streets.</p>
        <p>His forthcoming work opens in a devastating Russian winter during World War II, as the Red Army retreats towards Moscow. Anne Enright, who also read on Friday night, recently signed an American publishing deal for her novel ''What Are You Like?,'' the tale of a young Irish woman's life as an immigrant in New York.</p>
        <p>Ireland is like Cuba, said Mr. Toibin, 45. The first thing you want to do on a small island is escape it. To see the world is indeed a type of intellectual exile. Mr. McCann says he now  lives on the Upper West Side of Manhattan because of curiosity, not because he cannot find a job in Dublin.</p>
        <p>It is also becoming apparent that Irish writers today are generally not drinkers. The writers' pub, the deadly pint and chaser of their forebears, have been supplanted by home life and parenthood. The embrace of such a lifestyle may pose a threat to what the Dublin poet Paul Durcan, calls ''that will to die,'' which in the popular imagination still remains essential to the Irish creative mind.</p>
        <p>ARTS ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
