<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y20BRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DE1231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>VATICAN: REVEALING SECRET -- The Vatican said it would issue the full text of the so-called Secret of Fatima, with a commentary, next Monday. The Vatican disclosed in Fatima on May 13 that the secret predicted the 1981 assassination attempt on John Paul II. Many students of the Fatima secret expressed skepticism about the interpretation, so the release of the text will be closely followed by conspiracy theorists. The Vatican is expected to release a photocopy of the original handwritten secret put to paper by Sister Lucia decades after she said she witnessed the Virgin deliver the prophecy in 1917.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>VATICAN: REVEALING SECRET -- The Vatican said it would issue the full text of the so-called Secret of Fatima, with a commentary, next Monday. The Vatican disclosed in Fatima on May 13 that the secret predicted the 1981 assassination attempt on John Paul II. Many students of the Fatima secret expressed skepticism about the interpretation, so the release of the text will be closely followed by conspiracy theorists. The Vatican is expected to release a photocopy of the original handwritten secret put to paper by Sister Lucia decades after she said she witnessed the Virgin deliver the prophecy in 1917.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>ITALY: BERLUSCONI CLEARED -- The center-right opposition leader Silvio Berlusconi, 63, was cleared of charges that he bribed judges in Rome in 1990 on the way to buying Mondadori, a major publishing house. Mr. Berlusconi, a media tycoon, was also cleared last month of tax corruption charges by an appeals court in Milan. He still faces other trials, ranging from charges of illegal political contributions to false accounting in the acquisition of a player for his soccer team, AC Milan.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>GREECE: EURO MEMBERSHIP -- Greece was approved by the European Union for membership in the euro-zone, or single currency union, starting Jan. 1. The approval, at a meeting of European leaders in Portugal, came two years after rejection of the country's application because of its ''poor economic performance.''</p>
        <p>Anthee Carassava (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: NEW BACTERIUM DEATH -- An infection that has killed at least 35 heroin addicts in Scotland, Ireland and northern England has claimed a life on England's southern coast. A man who died in Brighton on May 15 was found to be infected with the clostridium bacterium that causes the disease, said a spokesman for the East Sussex, Brighton and Hove Health Authority. More than 60 cases have been confirmed.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>UNITED NATIONS</p>
        <p>NEW PEACEKEEPING CHIEF -- A French expert on European defense has been appointed head of United Nations peacekeeping operations. Jean-Marie Guehenno, board chairman in Paris of the Institute of Advanced Studies in National Defense, was picked to succeed Bernard Miyet, another French defense expert whose term ends on Oct. 1. Mr. Guehenno, 50, has been France's ambassador to the Western European Union and is the author of a 1995 book, ''The End of the Nation State,'' in which he argues that the strength of individual countries is dwindling in a global age.</p>
        <p>Barbara Crossette (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: REBELS ASK RANSOM -- Muslim rebels who have held 21 mostly foreign hostages in a jungle camp for two months are demanding at least $1 million in ransom for each of them, an aide to President Joseph Estrada said. The rebels have previously said they want a separate state in the southern Philippines and protection of their fishing rights.</p>
        <p>Seth Mydans (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: SUHARTO PROTESTS -- Former President Suharto has protested to the United Nations that the house arrest imposed on him three weeks ago violates his human rights, his lawyers said. The former president is under investigation for corruption; President Abdurrahman Wahid said a deal is being discussed under which Mr. Suharto would repay the government in return for his freedom.</p>
        <p>Seth Mydans (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>ETHIOPIA: PULLOUT ANNOUNCED -- The day after signing a cease-fire with Eritrea, Ethiopia said it was complying with the plan's terms by withdrawing from the western Eritrean town of Teseney. The town is much farther inside Eritrea than the 15.5-miles permitted by the accord. Eritrea, meantime, began repatriating Ethiopians displaced into Eritrea.</p>
        <p>Ian Fisher (NYT)</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: OBSERVERS BARRED -- Zimbabwe has refused to allow 10 Kenyan and 7 Nigerian members of a European Union-sponsored observer mission to monitor elections this weekend, an election official said. The official, who declined to be identified, said the election directorate had questioned the observers' eligibility to monitor the June 24-25 polls, saying neither Kenya nor Nigeria are European Union members.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>HAITI: RUNOFF POSTPONED -- The Provisional Electoral Council said it had indefinitely postponed the runoff legislative and municipal elections scheduled for Sunday, as street protests raged on. The council also confirmed the results of the May 21 round of voting, in which the party of former President Jean-Bertrand Aristide won 16 of 27 Senate seats.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: SUMMIT SOUGHT -- Israel wants President Clinton to convene a ''working summit'' with Prime Minister Ehud Barak and the Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat within a few weeks, Danny Yatom, Mr. Barak's chief security adviser, told foreign reporters. Israel believes that White House-sponsored talks could produce a detailed outline for final compromises on a range of crucial issues, a senior official said.</p>
        <p>William A. Orme Jr. (NYT)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: 3 PALESTINIANS FREED -- More than a month after a Palestinian street uprising that demanded the release of prisoners, Israel released three in what it called a good-will gesture. Palestinian officials called it far too few too late.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: SETTLERS PROTEST -- Settlers rallied near Parliament to protest what they expect will be significant concessions of West Bank land to the Palestinians. Schoolchildren joined their parents for the protest, and they eventually marched to Prime Minister Ehud Barak's residence.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
