<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Allied Domecq could end up with some popular brands if a big spirits merger goes through.</title>
    <meta content="Y20PLA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seagram Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vivendi Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Canal Plus Sa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Allied Domecq Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E5D81231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Allied Domecq could end up with some popular brands if a big spirits merger goes through.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Constance L. Hays</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brands like Chivas Regal, Martell cognac and Capital Morgan rum will be on the block if Vivendi, Canal Plus and Seagram agree to merge; many distilled spirits experts say Allied Domecq will be probable new owner; chart (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BRANDS like Chivas Regal, Martell cognac and Captain Morgan rum will be on the block if Vivendi and the Seagram Company do in fact agree to merge. But which distilled spirits company is likely to wind up as their new owner?</p>
        <p>Many industry experts say Allied Domecq would be the probable winner. Allied is the second-largest company in the highly fragmented world of spirits, behind Diageo of Britain, which, after it was formed by the merger of Guinness and Grand Metropolitan in 1998, became the industry leader with about 9 percent of the global market. The next handful of companies control market shares less than half that size, with even smaller stakes held by others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BRANDS like Chivas Regal, Martell cognac and Captain Morgan rum will be on the block if Vivendi and the Seagram Company do in fact agree to merge. But which distilled spirits company is likely to wind up as their new owner?</p>
        <p>Many industry experts say Allied Domecq would be the probable winner. Allied is the second-largest company in the highly fragmented world of spirits, behind Diageo of Britain, which, after it was formed by the merger of Guinness and Grand Metropolitan in 1998, became the industry leader with about 9 percent of the global market. The next handful of companies control market shares less than half that size, with even smaller stakes held by others.</p>
        <p>The Seagram brands are expected to bring more than $7 billion, roughly equal to Allied Domecq's sales last year. The sale of the brands has been proposed by Vivendi management to rid the new deal of $6.6 billion in debt.</p>
        <p>For Allied, which now owns brands like Beefeater gin and Ballantine's Scotch, taking on the new brands would not be impossible, particularly if the deal mixes stock and debt. That, at least is what a group of Salomon Smith Barney analysts wrote in a note to investors last week. Doing so might strengthen the management pool for the two companies, they added. ''Seagram's U.S. management is very strong,'' they wrote, ''and Allied's management in Europe is by far superior.''</p>
        <p>The analysts estimated that the Seagram brands were worth about 10.5 times their earnings before taxes, which are expected to total $723 million when the fiscal year ends this month. That works out to $7.6 billion.</p>
        <p>Berkshire Hathaway, the investment company led by Warren E. Buffett, bought more than 33 million Allied shares this spring, or 3 percent of the company -- an investment that caused a flurry at Allied, sending its share price up briefly.</p>
        <p>Diageo could also buy the brands, and would not run into significant antitrust hurdles except in the United States and Canada. Such issues, experts say, could be sidestepped by disposing of whiskey, gin and Scotch brands now sold in those markets.</p>
        <p>A third possibility is for the Bronfman family to hold on to the division. With about 23 percent of Seagram shares in the family's hands, the sale of the company would leave them with $7 billion.</p>
        <p>''While the current Seagram C.E.O., Edgar Bronfman, has been driven by the media business in recent years, this strategy has arguably failed, and the older family members of Seagram's management might well wish to retrench to the original spirits activity,'' the Salomon Smith Barney analysts wrote in their note to investors. ''Certainly these older family members see more value in drink than Edgar appears to see.''</p>
        <p>A person close to the family said such a move was unlikely.</p>
        <p>Also for sale is about 30 percent of Vivendi's water business, run by its Generale des Eaux division. ''The opportunity for water, globally, is pretty strong,'' noted Michael Bellas, chief executive of Beverage Marketing, a database and consulting company in New York. Last March, Vivendi paid a hefty $6.2 billion for US Filter, a California supplier of industrial water-purification equipment that also has a small consumer bottled-water unit. At the time of that deal, Vivendi was the biggest player in the fast-growing $300 billion water treatment industry.</p>
        <p>The spirits business has helped support other Seagram divisions for years, several industry experts said yesterday. In the recent past, brands that did not perform well were scrapped so the company could focus almost exclusively on high-priced, superpremium products, and the appeal of these brands to young adults has improved in the last year or two.</p>
        <p>''There's been a little bit of a resurgence'' in drinks sold in bars and restaurants, Mr. Bellas said. ''They were up about 1 percent, after being down all through the 1980's and 1990's.''</p>
        <p>If the brands are sold to one of Seagram's competitors, that could shake up the long-slumbering spirits industry, one of the more fragmented industries worldwide.</p>
        <p>Unlike the soft drink industry -- in which Coca-Cola holds a commanding 51 percent worldwide share and Pepsi has 21 percent, according to Beverage Digest, a trade newsletter -- the spirits business has not had any kind of transforming consolidation of brands or distributors. Many predicted a wave of consolidation after the formation of Diageo, but for various reasons no such trend emerged.</p>
        <p>Overseas, companies like Seagram and Allied Domecq control much of their distribution. In the United States, regulations forbid companies that own liquor brands to own their distributors as well. Along with the brands it owns outright, Seagram controls worldwide distribution rights for Absolut vodka.</p>
        <p>Other companies that are expected to take a look at the Seagram brands include Bacardi-Martini, the privately held owner of Bacardi rum, Dewar's Scotch and Martini &amp; Rossi vermouth. While Bacardi has made acquisitions in the recent past, buying Bombay gin from Diageo after the merger with Grand Met, the company took a sphinxlike stand yesterday when asked if it was interested in the Seagram properties. ''We are always looking for opportunities to enhance our portfolio,'' a company spokesman said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Additional contenders could include Brown-Forman , the American maker of Jack Daniel's and Southern Comfort, as well as Pernod Ricard S.A., the French owner of the Ricard pastis brand. Pernod Ricard tried to sell its Orangina soft drink brand to Coca-Cola in 1997 to concentrate on spirits. But the deal was rejected last year by French regulators, who said it would give Coca-Cola too much of the market.</p>
        <p>Neither Pernod, which is only a $3.5 billion company, nor Brown-Forman, with sales of about $2 billion, could swing the Seagram acquisition on its own. But like so many other industries, from computers to grocery stores, the spirits business has started to see strength in scale -- the bigger the better.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
