<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Egan Installed; He Cites Hope To Be Teacher</title>
    <meta content="20EGAN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000623T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="A NEW ARCHBISHOP: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Edward M (Archbishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koch, Edward I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dinkins, David N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scalia, Antonin (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schumer, Charles E (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schemo, Diana Jean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E4D71231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Egan Installed; He Cites Hope To Be Teacher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schemo, Diana Jean</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Consecration of Edward M Egan as New York's ninth Roman Catholic archbishop culminates in second and far more elaborate Mass for 4,000 people at St Patrick's Cathedral; ceremony is attended by 8 American cardinals, 18 archbishops, nearly 100 bishops and 900 priests, as well as Hillary Rodham Clinton, US Repr Rick Lazio, US Sen Charles Schumer, Mayor Rudolph Giuliani, former Mayors David N Dinkins and Edward I Koch and US Supreme Court Justice Antonin Scalia; ceremony described; Egan delivers homily in Spanish and English, emphasizing his role as teacher of faith and values; makes plea for social justice, and against discrimination, abortion and euthanasia; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five weeks after bidding farewell to Cardinal John J. O'Connor, New York's rich and powerful returned to St. Patrick's Cathedral yesterday to see his successor, Edward M. Egan, installed as New York's ninth archbishop, in a ceremony that reflected  many of the elements that would inevitably shape his tenure.</p>
        <p>The consecration of Archbishop Egan, which began with a vespers service attended by 2,700 Roman Catholics on Sunday evening, culminated in yesterday's far more elaborate Mass for 4,000, with 8 American cardinals, 18 archbishops, nearly 100 bishops and 900 priests in attendance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five weeks after bidding farewell to Cardinal John J. O'Connor, New York's rich and powerful returned to St. Patrick's Cathedral yesterday to see his successor, Edward M. Egan, installed as New York's ninth archbishop, in a ceremony that reflected  many of the elements that would inevitably shape his tenure.</p>
        <p>The consecration of Archbishop Egan, which began with a vespers service attended by 2,700 Roman Catholics on Sunday evening, culminated in yesterday's far more elaborate Mass for 4,000, with 8 American cardinals, 18 archbishops, nearly 100 bishops and 900 priests in attendance.</p>
        <p>Also on hand were Hillary Rodham Clinton, the first lady, and her rival for the Senate, Representative Rick A. Lazio; Gov. George E. Pataki, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, former Mayors David N. Dinkins and Edward I. Koch; and Justice Antonin  Scalia of the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>The ceremony, five weeks to the hour after Cardinal O'Connor's funeral, seemed to complete a transition that began with the cardinal's  struggle with brain cancer.</p>
        <p>The ceremony enabled Edward Michael Egan to start putting his personal stamp on his service in New York. He selected majestic works by Mozart and Beethoven to guide the Mass of his consecration, the readings were offered in Spanish and English in acknowledgment of the archdiocese's increasingly multicultural face, and his homily emphasized his role as a teacher of faith and values. [Transcript of homily, Page B10.]</p>
        <p>The pageant was stirring. More than 1,000 priests and bishops wore white for the occasion, making the long procession from the Catholic Center on First Avenue to St. Patrick's seem like a white banner unfurled between the administrative and spiritual hearts of the New York Archdiocese. The archdiocese is shepherd to 2.4 million Catholics in Manhattan, the Bronx and Staten Island, and in seven counties north of the city.</p>
        <p>Overwhelmingly, the priests in attendance had hair the color of the white robes, a sign of how swiftly the clergy in New York is aging as young men choose not to enter the priesthood in sufficient numbers. The average age of priests in the archdiocese is over 60, and of 851 diocesan priests in New York, nearly 250 are retired or otherwise inactive.</p>
        <p>Archbishop Egan's success in recruiting young men for the priesthood while he was bishop of Bridgeport, Conn., is believed to have played a role in the pope's decision to name him to head the church in New York.</p>
        <p>The archbishop wore a gold, green and red stole over his off-white surplice, covered with a pectoral cross from a young man who became a priest under Archbishop Egan's guidance and then died soon after of leukemia.</p>
        <p>The archbishop's arrival at the back doors of St. Patrick's shortly after 2 p.m. brought wave upon wave of applause as he strode smiling down the center aisle, the applause cresting as he reached the sanctuary.</p>
        <p>Perhaps mindful of the task ahead, not just in recruiting but in reorganizing an archdiocese that has undergone vast demographic changes in recent years, he seemed more daunted than delighted through much of his consecration yesterday.</p>
        <p>His homily, which likened the Basilica of SS. John and Paul in Rome to the cathedral in New York, did not wander off into amusing asides, and the new archbishop smiled little. One noteworthy exception came as the soprano Renee Fleming sang Mozart's ''Exsultate Jubilate,'' when the archbishop closed his eyes and swayed for a moment, as if transported. If the Mass had been a meal, Ms. Fleming's music was undoubtedly dessert for the archbishop.</p>
        <p>Archbishop Egan noted that the basilica in Rome dated from the fourth century and was built atop the house where the saints lived. Because they had refused to offer sacrifices to pagan gods, they were executed by the Emperor Julian in 361. The archbishop said he loved the basilica because ''it sums up for me what parishes and dioceses are all about.''</p>
        <p>He continued: ''We are communities that are built on uncompromising acceptance of all that the Lord has revealed. This is our foundation. Our strength is grounded in our faith.''</p>
        <p>The archbishop also made a plea for social justice, and against discrimination, abortion and euthanasia, that drew spontaneous and sustained applause from the crowd. ''May we allow the sick and disabled to be neglected?'' he asked. ''May we stand idly by while the being within the mother is killed, even though no one has ever been able to prove that it is other than a human being with an inalienable right to life? May we look the other way when the elderly are put to death because someone questions the quality of their life?''  To each question, he said, the answer must be a ''resounding no.''</p>
        <p>The new archbishop, a canon lawyer and classical pianist, made his mark in Bridgeport by effectively combatting the diocese's poor financial straits, in part by successful fund-raising among the wealthy and corporate donors. Archbishop Egan eagerly pumped the hands of the prominent and powerful in the front rows yesterday, and then dashed out the great back doors of the cathedral as the chorus of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony played over loudspeakers, filling Fifth Avenue. There, he went to the police barricades, holding high his crosier, and began shaking the hands of well-wishers with his free hand.</p>
        <p>''Across the street,'' an aide prompted the archbishop. He swung around, looked up and waved to the onlookers there, and the gesture was greeted with cheering and applause.</p>
        <p>Hundreds had stood in the street throughout the service, straining through the honking horns and passing buses to hear the service through loudspeakers on the cathedral's facade. Many were tourists or passers-by who stopped when they recognized what was happening. Others said they made it a point to be as near as possible to their new church leader, even if it meant standing behind a barricade.</p>
        <p>''I think it's beautiful, even though I'm not inside,'' said Felicita Santiago, 63, of Queens. ''I'm not inside, but I feel like I'm a part of it.''</p>
        <p>Stephanie Whittier of the Upper East Side said as she left the cathedral: ''This is so exciting. This is so exciting.'' Asked why, she said, ''It's so exciting because we have a new archbishop to replace Cardinal O'Connor, who we loved so much.''</p>
        <p>She said she was impressed by the diversity of the service, which alternated English and Spanish readings and offered texts in both languages. The Mass also featured a prayer in Portuguese, Creole, Vietnamese, Russian and other languages.</p>
        <p>The Bronx borough president, Fernando Ferrer, said that Archbishop Egan's message and his Spanish came across well. ''I told him his Spanish was pretty good,'' Mr. Ferrer said, adding that he enjoyed the homily even though it focused more on Rome than on the Bronx. ''He made, I thought, a very interesting connection between Rome and New York, and his message was about the foundation of our faith. I thought it was very appropriate and very good.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ferrer sat in the third row of pews, beside three of his likely opponents in next year's Democratic primary for mayor, the public advocate, Mark Green; the city comptroller, Alan G. Hevesi; and Speaker Peter  F. Vallone of the City Council.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vallone said that since he attended Mass every day, he explained the ceremony to his rivals. ''They were very, very respectful,'' he said. ''When I go to a synagogue, they do the same for me.''</p>
        <p>A NEW ARCHBISHOP: THE OVERVIEW  Correction:  June 23, 2000, Friday  An article on Tuesday about Archbishop Edward M. Egan's Mass of Installation and an article on Sunday about preparations for the ceremony both misstated the route of an outdoor procession in Manhattan. Before walking to St. Patrick's Cathedral for the Mass on Monday, more than 1,000 priests and bishops assembled at the Palace Hotel, behind the cathedral on Madison Avenue, not at the Catholic Center at 56th Street and First Avenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 23, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about Archbishop Edward M. Egan's Mass of Installation and an article on Sunday about preparations for the ceremony both misstated the route of an outdoor procession in Manhattan. Before walking to St. Patrick's Cathedral for the Mass on Monday, more than 1,000 priests and bishops assembled at the Palace Hotel, behind the cathedral on Madison Avenue, not at the Catholic Center at 56th Street and First Avenue.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
