<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Student Prayers Must Be Private, Court Reaffirms</title>
    <meta content="20PRAY$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE SUPREME COURT: THE RELIGION ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prayers and Prayer Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, John Paul (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Religion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prayers and Prayer Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE6D81231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Student Prayers Must Be Private, Court Reaffirms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court strongly reaffirms earlier decisions against officially sponsored prayer in public schools, ruling 6-3 that prayers led by students at high school football games are unconstitutional; majority decision by Justice John Paul Stevens says even when attendance is voluntary and when decision to pray is made by students, delivery of pre-game prayer has improper effect of coercing those present to participate in act of religious worship; ruling centers on case from small school district in South Texas, typical of communities across South where practice of prayers at school functions has persisted as officials have tried to navigate obstacle course created by previous decisions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Strongly reaffirming its earlier decisions against officially sponsored prayer in public schools, the Supreme Court ruled today that prayers led by students at high school football games are no exception: as officially sanctioned acts at events that students feel great social pressure to attend, they are unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>The 6-to-3 majority opinion by Justice John Paul Stevens said that even when attendance was voluntary and when the decision to pray was made by students, ''the delivery of a pregame prayer has the improper effect of coercing those present to participate in an act of religious worship.'' [Excerpts, Page A22.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Strongly reaffirming its earlier decisions against officially sponsored prayer in public schools, the Supreme Court ruled today that prayers led by students at high school football games are no exception: as officially sanctioned acts at events that students feel great social pressure to attend, they are unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>The 6-to-3 majority opinion by Justice John Paul Stevens said that even when attendance was voluntary and when the decision to pray was made by students, ''the delivery of a pregame prayer has the improper effect of coercing those present to participate in an act of religious worship.'' [Excerpts, Page A22.]</p>
        <p>The case came from a small school district in South Texas, typical of communities across the South where the practice of prayer at graduations, assemblies and athletic contests has persisted as officials have tried to navigate the obstacle course created by Supreme Court and lower court decisions.</p>
        <p>In this case, the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit, in New Orleans, had ruled that students could offer prayers at graduations -- where members of the clergy cannot, under a 1992 Supreme Court decision -- but not in the ''far less solemn and extraordinary'' setting of a football game.</p>
        <p>The decision today did not explicitly address graduation ceremonies, but the majority's analysis cast serious doubt on the increasingly popular practice of student-led graduation prayers. The justices have been asked to hear a challenge to an Alabama law, upheld last year by a federal appeals court, that permits ''student-initiated voluntary prayer'' at graduations as well as other events.</p>
        <p>While the decision today was not a surprise, given the justices' evident skepticism about the Santa Fe Independent School District's prayer policy when the case was argued in March, it was nonetheless notable in several respects. One was the majority's firm rejection of the school district's central argument in defense of its policy: the prayers were private student speech that could not be attributed to the school district itself and could not be considered an unconstitutional ''establishment'' of religion in violation of the First Amendment.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the district had argued, to hold that students could not express their religious views would create a separate First Amendment problem, amounting to the censorship of religious speech in a public forum.</p>
        <p>But this was not private speech, and a football game was not a public forum for unbridled free expression, Justice Stevens said. ''These invocations are authorized by a government policy and take place on government property at government-sponsored school-related events,'' he said, adding that any member of the audience would perceive the student prayer as stamped with the school's ''seal of approval.''</p>
        <p>Justice Stevens added: ''Contrary to the district's repeated assertions that it has adopted a 'hands-off' approach to the pregame invocation, the realities of the situation plainly reveal that its policy involves both perceived and actual endorsement of religion.''</p>
        <p>He noted that in contrast to a public forum, in which contrasting views are welcome, the Santa Fe policy ''allows only one student, the same student for the entire season, to give the invocation.'' He said the policy clearly indicated, without saying so explicitly, that what was expected was a religious message, ''suggesting that a solemn, yet nonreligious, message, such as commentary on United States foreign policy, would be prohibited.''</p>
        <p>In an acerbic dissenting opinion, Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist said the majority opinion ''bristles with hostility to all things religious in public life.''</p>
        <p>Chief Justice Rehnquist said that ''neither the holding nor the tone of the opinion is faithful to the meaning of the Establishment Clause,'' at least as understood by George Washington, who proclaimed a day of ''public thanksgiving and prayer'' at the request of ''the very Congress which passed the Bill of Rights.''</p>
        <p>The chief justice said the majority was adopting so rigid a view of church-state separation that ''under the Court's logic, a public school that sponsors the singing of the national anthem before football games violates the Establishment Clause'' because the concluding verse contains the phrase ''And this be our motto: 'In God is our trust.' ''</p>
        <p>Justices Antonin Scalia and Clarence Thomas joined the chief justice's dissenting opinion. The majority opinion was joined by Justices Sandra Day O'Connor, Anthony M. Kennedy, David H. Souter, Ruth Bader Ginsburg and Stephen G. Breyer.</p>
        <p>Justice Stevens appeared to go out of his way to refute the dissenters' accusation that the majority was hostile to religion. ''By no means,'' he said, did the Constitution ''impose a prohibition on all religious activity in our public schools'' or stop ''any public school student from voluntarily praying at any time before, during, or after the school day.'' He added: ''But the religious liberty protected by the Constitution is abridged when the state affirmatively sponsors the particular practice of prayer.''</p>
        <p>The case, Santa Fe Independent School District v. Doe, No. 99-62, began in 1995 when two families, one Mormon and the other Catholic, sued to stop a variety of religious practices in the 4,000-student district near Galveston, Tex. Permitted by the Federal District Court to proceed anonymously because of the possibility of harassment, the plaintiffs won an initial ruling that prompted several changes in the school district's policy as the litigation continued.</p>
        <p>The dissenting justices objected today that the majority lacked a basis for striking down the policy, which had never taken effect, on its face, but should let it take effect and see if any problems developed. But the majority declared firmly that there was no need to wait. In fact, Justice Stevens said, the election system itself was part of the constitutional problem ''because it establishes an improper majoritarian election on religion'' and ''encourages divisiveness along religious lines.''</p>
        <p>Also notable was the majority's rejection of the school district's effort to describe the policy as a ''content-neutral'' effort to provide a solemn atmosphere at football games. ''We refuse to turn a blind eye to the context in which this policy arises,'' Justice Stevens said, ''and that context quells any doubt that this policy was implemented with the purpose of endorsing school prayer.''</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, who signed the state's brief in support of the school district, called the ruling ''disappointing.'' In a statement put out by his office in Austin, Mr. Bush said: ''I support the constitutionally guaranteed right of all students to express their faith freely and participate in voluntary, student-led prayer.''</p>
        <p>Julie Underwood, general counsel of the National School Boards Association, praised the decision and said she would advise school districts that they should now regard student-led graduation prayers as unconstitutional as well. ''This decision emphasizes that we don't have prayer at school sponsored events, period,'' she said in an interview, adding: ''Children shouldn't be made to feel excluded or coerced.''</p>
        <p>THE SUPREME COURT: THE RELIGION ISSUE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
