<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders Considering Options With No. 1 Pick in the Draft</title>
    <meta content="20ISLE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kellner, Jenny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1DB1231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders Considering Options With No. 1 Pick in the Draft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY KELLNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kellner, Jenny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Islanders say they are quite willing to trade first pick in National Hockey League's entry draft next weekend, but only if right deal comes along (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Islanders are quite willing to trade the first pick in the National Hockey League's entry draft next weekend, but only if the right deal comes along.</p>
        <p>''Our needs are a skilled center man, speed and scoring on the wing, and a hammer from the point on the power play, and I don't want someone in their 30's,'' Islanders General Manager Mike Milbury said. ''We've had one proposal on the pick that was pretty close.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Islanders are quite willing to trade the first pick in the National Hockey League's entry draft next weekend, but only if the right deal comes along.</p>
        <p>''Our needs are a skilled center man, speed and scoring on the wing, and a hammer from the point on the power play, and I don't want someone in their 30's,'' Islanders General Manager Mike Milbury said. ''We've had one proposal on the pick that was pretty close.''</p>
        <p>The youthful Islanders, who won just 24 games last season, could get even younger should they keep the top pick, which they won in a lottery June 1. The last time the team picked first in the draft was 1973, when it chose Denis Potvin, the cornerstone of the Stanley Cup teams of 1980 to 1984.</p>
        <p>On Saturday in Calgary, Alberta, the Islanders must decide whether to draft the Slovak left wing Marion Gaborik, Boston University goalie Rick DiPietro or Wisconsin left wing Dany Heatley, or to trade the pick for a young first-line forward. Other options include trading down -- no lower than the fifth pick over all, Milbury said -- or packaging the pick in a trade with a player on the roster.</p>
        <p>If nothing happens, Milbury says he will still be satisfied.</p>
        <p>''If we go to the draft and pick No. 1, we're happy,'' he said. ''We'll have a player with a chance to play this year and a chance to be a significant player down the line.''</p>
        <p>Milbury, who also said the Islanders would be active in seeking trades and in signing free agents next month, made a prediction on the number of players he hoped to bring in.</p>
        <p>''I'm hoping that by mid-July we will have at least four new faces and hopefully, if I'm lucky, more,'' Milbury said. ''There are very few players who are untouchable.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>General Manager MIKE MILBURY said that because KENNY JONSSON was coming off a one-goal season, he should not expect a raise. Jonsson, the captain, also had 24 assists in 65 games. . . . The new ownership team of CHARLES WANG and SANJAY KUMAR plans to use chartered flights next season. The owners, who also plan to improve the locker room, are looking into building a year-round practice facility within 20 miles of Nassau Coliseum. ''I'm very comfortable with the fact that these guys mean business,'' Milbury said of the new owners, who gave him the go-ahead to pick up the $1.5 million option on right wing MARIUSZ CZERKAWSKI, who had a career-high 35 goals, and to re-sign ERIC CAIRNS, who had 196 penalty minutes in 67 games last season. . . . The Islanders will hold an interactive draft-day party for fans at Nassau Coliseum starting 10 a.m. Saturday.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
