<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="20TRN.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DF1331F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND INDIANS--Agreed to terms with OF Kenneth Folsom, OF Rashad Eldridge, LHP Adam Cox and LHP Victor Kleine. Signed OF Robert Womack and C Mike Ernst to minor league contracts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND INDIANS--Agreed to terms with OF Kenneth Folsom, OF Rashad Eldridge, LHP Adam Cox and LHP Victor Kleine. Signed OF Robert Womack and C Mike Ernst to minor league contracts.</p>
        <p>National League  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Signed LHP Ryan Carter and assigned him to Batavia of the New York-Penn League. Signed RHP Keith Bucktrot, 1B Carlos Rivera and C Mark McRoberts and assigned them to the Phillies of the GCL.  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Agreed to terms LHP Mark Phillips. Purchased the contract of RHP Brian Tollberg from Las Vegas of the PCL. Sent RHP Rodrigo Lopez outright to Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>Pacific Coast League  CALGARY CANNONS--Signed LHP Erik Plantenberg.  Atlantic League  ABERDEEN ARSENAL--Signed RHP Derek Gaskill.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL  United States Basketball League</p>
        <p>FLORIDA SEA DRAGONS--Activated G MArk Jones. Released F Godfrey Thompson.  LONG ISLAND SURF--Placed G Patrick Collins and G Lamar Parker on the inactive list. Activated G Brian Ehlers, F John Strickland and F Troy Bowers.  NEW JERSEY SHORECATS--Activated G-F Ray Tutt. Placed F Hakeem Ward on the inactive list.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  Canadian Football League</p>
        <p>HAMILTON TIGER-CATS--Released DB Larry Moore, DB Jocelyn Borgella, DT Doug Madoski, LB Phillip Thompson, LB Olivier Lefebvre, DL Jean-Daniel Roy, OL Doug Van Moorsel and OL Brad Chalmers.  WINNIPEG BLUE BOMBERS--Released DB Jason Dandridge and DB Andrae Holland.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League</p>
        <p>MINNESOTA WILD--Named Jacques Lemaire coach.</p>
        <p>International Hockey League</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI CYCLONES--Announced the resignation of John Hamel, assistant director of media relations.</p>
        <p>Central Hockey League</p>
        <p>INDIANAPOLIS ICE--Re-signed D Dan Cousineau for the 2000-01 season.  MEMPHIS RIVERKINGS--Named Doug Shedden coach and director of hockey operations.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS  United States Olympic Committee</p>
        <p>USOC--Named Benita Fitzgerald Mosley director of public relations programs and Gail Dent manager of public relations programs. Promoted J. Michael Wilson, director-visitor center and community relations, to director of athlete relations.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>BEMIDJI STATE--Named Jeff Mitchell women's soccer coach.  CURRY--Named Dan Morgan head trainer.  FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON--Named Rich Mosca offensive coordinator.  MAINE--Named Jody Bennett and Dana Smith women's assistant basketball coaches.  MISERICORDIA--Named Mark Stauffer women's soccer coach and intramural director, Christine Lardon women's basketball coach and coordinator of athletic facilities and Mary Kate Madden field hockey coach and women's lacrosse coach.  MISSOURI-KANSAS CITY--Named Dean Demopoulos men's basketball coach.  SOUTHWEST TEXAS--Named Donyale Canada coordinator of women's basketball operations.  YOUNGSTOWN STATE--Named Andy Johnston men's assistant baseketball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
