<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Tiger Woods Approaches High Tide</title>
    <meta content="20VECS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E0DF1231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="818" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Tiger Woods Approaches High Tide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column discusses Tiger Woods record breaking victory in US Open golf championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WATCHED some golf on Sunday. Really. Right after the Spain-Slovenia soccer game, that is.</p>
        <p>There on the tube was a most stunning impression, visual and olfactory -- the lush swell of the Pacific Ocean, throbbing against the cultivated lawns of a golf course called Pebble Beach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WATCHED some golf on Sunday. Really. Right after the Spain-Slovenia soccer game, that is.</p>
        <p>There on the tube was a most stunning impression, visual and olfactory -- the lush swell of the Pacific Ocean, throbbing against the cultivated lawns of a golf course called Pebble Beach.</p>
        <p>Smell-o-vision. This was a new one on me. You could inhale the aroma of thick kelp and foamy saltwater surging alongside the course.</p>
        <p>''Aha, maybe you ought to play golf,'' said my wife, who wonders what I will do with my spare time in the very distant future.</p>
        <p>''Nah,'' I said. ''I just want to walk along the ocean like we did last summer on Big Sur.''</p>
        <p>Besides, who would dare dream about committing golf after watching Tiger Woods?</p>
        <p>How could it possibly be good for the golf industry to let this man perform in public?</p>
        <p>It was not hard to imagine, late Sunday night, the wracking sound of men and women taking baseball swings with their golf clubs against the nearest sugar maple or loblolly pine.</p>
        <p>Come to think of it, some of the also-rans in the United States Open would not have been blamed if they had hurled their entire kits into the Pacific Ocean. What's the point? Why go on?</p>
        <p>If it was not clear before Sunday evening, it is obvious now. Tiger Woods dominates sport -- not merely his sport, but sport in general -- as completely as anybody we have seen in a long, long time.</p>
        <p>Tiger Woods has stolen this spring from everybody else -- Shaq, Kobe and Reggie out in L.A. last night, Martin Brodeur performing kick saves 'round midnight, Edgar and Pedro and Conchita and all the other Martinezes, whoever it was who won the French tennis, the three Triple Crown horses.</p>
        <p>He stole it with his composure and his compact power. If you could tear yourself away from gazing at the sea, it was all Tiger, all day, all weekend.</p>
        <p>You could imagine producers screaming: ''Stay with him! Stay with him!'' at their camera operators, trying to capture every precious shot, since there were not that many.</p>
        <p>The camera just adores him -- trim and young, as athletic as an Olympic swimmer, as feral as a Tomba or a Hamm.</p>
        <p>The great golfers before him were not mistaken for athletes, not the wiry Ben Hogan or the avuncular Arnold Palmer or the ursine Jack Nicklaus, but this young man just bristles with quiet energy. One could envision him as a whippet of a second baseman, with a bit of pop in his bat, his throws not skulling anybody in the box seats.</p>
        <p>When he twists his slender body, not much ripples inside the mulberry shirt, but the ball bounces far ahead of drives by fleshier men.</p>
        <p>As he walks down the fairway, he barely acknowledges the gallery, his attention focused inward in what seems to be a permanent state of grace.</p>
        <p>Because there is no defense in golf, virtually no teamwork, he is out there alone, on some new frontier of excellence.</p>
        <p>The closest thing to Tiger Woods in recent decades has been Secretariat barreling through the 1973 Triple Crown, winning the Belmont by 31 lengths, so far ahead that the other horses could only surmise by his hoof prints that they were indeed in a race.</p>
        <p>Michael Jordan? He swaggered and stuck out his tongue and took over a game, but there were roustabouts who could knock him off his spot occasionally, and sometimes he would just plain miss. Frustrated golfer and baseball player that he is, Michael knows nobody commands a sport the way Tiger Woods does.</p>
        <p>Oh, pitchers throw the odd perfect game, but they are one-day wonders. Lawrence Taylor was the most dominant football player of his time, but L. T. did not play offense -- a failure of imagination of his coaches and not his own doing, to be sure.</p>
        <p>Diego Armando Maradona could dish out one spectacular pass that beat Brazil in a World Cup game, but only after this addled genius had lain in the weeds for the other 89 minutes. Reggie Jackson hit three homers in a World Series game, but he struck out a lot.</p>
        <p>Wayne Gretzky? There was a lot of Tiger Woods in him. Cool. Excellent. Smart. Decent. But he had his Messiers and his Fuhrs and his Coffeys and his Semenkos on his side.</p>
        <p>Tiger has no opposition, only a field. Ali had Frazier. Navratilova had Evert. DiMaggio had Williams and Musial. McGwire has Sosa.</p>
        <p>Tiger has only himself and his caddie and his touch and his inner light, but that is quite enough. Even the pungent Pacific Ocean swirls in for a closer look.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
