<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Carpeted Sweatshop? Chase Says So in Lease War</title>
    <meta content="20BUIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1208860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chase Manhattan Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tahari, Elie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DC1231F933A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1260" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Carpeted Sweatshop? Chase Says So in Lease War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on five-month court battle between Chase Manhattan Bank and fashion designer Elie Tahari; bank has chargethatd Tahari's sample making operation in bank's landmark five-story glass building in midtown Manhattan is firetrap; Tahari contends bank is trying to break lease and then sell building for tidy profit; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is not unusual these days for a well-known fashion designer to be accused of running a sweatshop, but Elie Tahari may be the first to face that charge from a bastion of global capitalism.</p>
        <p>In a five-month court battle, Chase Manhattan Bank has asserted that Mr. Tahari's sample-making operation in the bank's landmark five-story glass building at Fifth Avenue and 43rd Street is a firetrap. Earlier this month, a judge shut down the Tahari operation until the dispute could be resolved. The two sides are scheduled to file additional court papers today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is not unusual these days for a well-known fashion designer to be accused of running a sweatshop, but Elie Tahari may be the first to face that charge from a bastion of global capitalism.</p>
        <p>In a five-month court battle, Chase Manhattan Bank has asserted that Mr. Tahari's sample-making operation in the bank's landmark five-story glass building at Fifth Avenue and 43rd Street is a firetrap. Earlier this month, a judge shut down the Tahari operation until the dispute could be resolved. The two sides are scheduled to file additional court papers today.</p>
        <p>The arguments of Chase's lawyers echo  antisweatshop campaigns by labor unions, church groups and others against apparel makers like Nike, Kathie Lee Gifford and Donna Karan. But in a twist worthy of a city where real estate is king, the garment workers' union has jumped to Mr. Tahari's defense, saying the designer runs not a sweatshop but the best sample room in the city. They say the bank is trying to break Mr. Tahari's lease in a building that it hopes to sell for a tidy profit.</p>
        <p>Bank executives say they are only concerned about safety, but the designer has a letter from the city's Buildings Department stating that the operation is in compliance with the building code and has adequate fire safety equipment.</p>
        <p>''This is about corporate greed,'' said Mr. Tahari, a onetime electrician whose popular line of women's suits earned him the nickname King of the Jacket.</p>
        <p>''Chase has put many employees out of work who need their paycheck every week to feed their families,'' he said. ''If they continue their actions, there'll be hundreds more out of work at the factory, and that's why the union is outraged.''</p>
        <p>The prospect of no spring Tahari line has also concerned Philip Miller, the chairman of the Saks Fifth Avenue retail chain, who has called on his friend William B. Harrison Jr., the chairman of Chase Manhattan, to bring the lease dispute to a quick resolution.</p>
        <p>In an e-mail message to Mr. Harrison, the Saks chairman assured him the Tahari sample room was not a sweatshop, a term used by Chase's lawyers in a court hearing, and suggested that the fire safety issues were an attempt to ''weaken the terms and conditions of Tahari's current lease.'' Mr. Miller declined to comment last week and played down his role in the dispute.</p>
        <p>On June 7, with the two sides at an impasse, Judge Betty Weinberg Ellerin of the Appellate Division of the State Supreme Court in Manhattan closed the sample room until the issues could be resolved in court. Mr. Tahari said 40 workers were put out of work immediately. Now his designers have little to do, and factory and distribution workers could soon lose their jobs as well, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tahari said Chase had notified him that unless he signed a new lease stripping him of many rights under his current lease, the bank would begin eviction proceedings. Under the existing lease, which has nine years remaining, he pays $28 a square foot in rent, about $15 less than what the bank could get if the space were to be put on the market today. Mr. Tahari also has the right to lease any vacant space that comes up in the building at 90 percent of the market rate.</p>
        <p>Some urban planners and labor activists said that the Tahari-Chase battle demonstrated the problems faced by manufacturers in a city where real estate prices had skyrocketed. Garment shops, printers and other manufacturers are being displaced in the garment district south of Times Square, in Chinatown and elsewhere by corporate tenants and dot-com companies willing to pay higher rents.</p>
        <p>''The biggest pressure on garment manufacturing today is real estate, not global competition,'' said Jonathan Bowles of the Center for an Urban Future, a nonprofit research and advocacy group. ''If they're thrown out of work, people in this industry cannot simply knock on the door of a Wall Street firm and land a job tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>With little vacant space available in Manhattan, telecommunications companies are now pushing into industrial neighborhoods in Brooklyn and Queens, driving out manufacturers who cannot afford higher rents.</p>
        <p>''There are many endangered workers in this great city with the same concerns as the Tahari workers,'' said Jay Mazur, president of Unite, which represents thousands of garment workers in New York City. ''All over the city, the jobs of thousands of garment workers are threatened by a real estate crisis absolutely not of their own making.''</p>
        <p>But Chase executives deny that the lease dispute has anything to do with the pending sale of the building at 510 Fifth Avenue. ''Because of fire safety issues, the court has ordered Tahari to cease certain operations,'' Judy Miller, a spokeswoman for Chase,  said on Friday. ''We would like to work out a solution to enable Tahari to resume those operations. We have made a proposal that we think would make it possible to do so.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tahari, who has leased space in the building since 1996, has a design studio on the fifth floor and offices and a sample room on the third floor that consists of 18 sewing machines, a cutting table and four steam irons.</p>
        <p>In court papers filed in February, Chase said the designer was ''conducting a clothing-manufacturing operation'' on the third floor in violation of his lease and the building code. Also, the bank said, Mr. Tahari had failed to install a sprinkler system, which is required of manufacturing operations.</p>
        <p>The bank has asserted that Mr. Tahari was in default on his lease. It has demanded that he install a sprinkler system, in addition to signing the new lease.</p>
        <p>But in a Jan. 14 letter to Mr. Tahari's architects, Ronny A. Livian, the borough commissioner at the Department of Buildings, said his department had no objection to the sample-making operations, because it accounted for less than a quarter of the space on the third floor and, therefore, was in compliance with the building code. Mr. Livian added that the sample area did not require additional fire safety equipment.</p>
        <p>The carpeted, brightly lighted sample room bears little resemblance to the cramped and dirty sweatshops that still exist in Chinatown and the garment district. The clothing patterns stitched together in the sample shop are sent to factories for production.</p>
        <p>Last Wednesday, 100 sewing machine operators, designers, supervisors and distribution workers for the Tahari operation paraded into the Chase branch office on the lower two floors of the building on the southwest corner of Fifth Avenue and 43rd Street, blowing tin whistles and chanting, while their employer negotiated fruitlessly with Chase executives downtown.</p>
        <p>''This is a very nice place to work,'' said Tina Chang, a demonstrator. ''We've been here four years. All of a sudden we got dangerous?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
