<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fuel Bills Empty Poor Pockets, Left Unfilled by Boom</title>
    <meta content="09ENER" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/09/national/09ENER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2D71E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fuel Bills Empty Poor Pockets, Left Unfilled by Boom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <dateline>BROOKLYN, Iowa</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Millions of low-income Americans, rural and urban poor alike, find selves unprotected from effects of rising gasoline, heating fuel and electric prices that have done little to change consumption of middle class and affluent; mounting prices inflict painful choices on poor, especially in areas lacking public transportation; graph of how low-income Iowans deal with inability to pay heating bills; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every weekday, Darrell Messersmith helps his wife, Donna, into their 1989 Chevrolet Caprice, loads her wheelchair and cane into the trunk and drives 22 miles to a hospital in Grinnell. Since  having a stroke in May, Mrs. Messersmith, who is 54, has spent a few hours there each afternoon learning to walk and talk again.</p>
        <p>Once middle class, the couple was already sliding down the economic ladder, living on Mr. Messersmith's $1,300 monthly disability check after he was hurt on the job a few years back. So when gasoline prices spiked to $1.80 here this summer, the 220 miles a week of commuting to the hospital took food out of their mouths. And with natural-gas prices projected to drive the heating bill up by almost 50 percent this winter, the Messersmiths expect to cut deeper.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every weekday, Darrell Messersmith helps his wife, Donna, into their 1989 Chevrolet Caprice, loads her wheelchair and cane into the trunk and drives 22 miles to a hospital in Grinnell. Since  having a stroke in May, Mrs. Messersmith, who is 54, has spent a few hours there each afternoon learning to walk and talk again.</p>
        <p>Once middle class, the couple was already sliding down the economic ladder, living on Mr. Messersmith's $1,300 monthly disability check after he was hurt on the job a few years back. So when gasoline prices spiked to $1.80 here this summer, the 220 miles a week of commuting to the hospital took food out of their mouths. And with natural-gas prices projected to drive the heating bill up by almost 50 percent this winter, the Messersmiths expect to cut deeper.</p>
        <p>''We can't get all the food we want,'' Mr. Messersmith, 55, said.  ''We've eliminated almost all meat. We will probably cut back more on food. That's the first place you cut back on.''</p>
        <p>The Messersmiths are among millions of low-income Americans, the  rural and urban poor alike, who are untouched by the flourishing economy and, as a result, unprotected from the effects of rising fuel and utility prices.</p>
        <p>The middle class and the affluent -- despite significant increases in the cost of gasoline, heating fuels and electricity after years of relatively low prices -- in the main have not changed their driving habits or let their homes become uncomfortably warm. Indeed, their seemingly insatiable demand for fuel has helped push prices even higher.</p>
        <p>But for the poor, mounting fuel prices and heating bills inflict painful choices, especially in cities without adequate public transportation and in small towns and suburbs where distances make driving a necessity.</p>
        <p>Here in Iowa, according to a new study by the State Department of Human Rights, many low-income families who faced higher rates for natural gas during last year's relatively mild winter cut back on food, health care, phones and electricity to pay for heat. With prices rising, the department says that situation could worsen this year.</p>
        <p>''Low-income people feel the most pain, whether we're looking at heating oil or gasoline or what we expect with natural gas in the winter,'' said Dan W. Reicher, assistant United States energy secretary and head of the Office of Energy Efficiency. ''People have had to choose between heating and eating.''</p>
        <p>High utility and gasoline bills have begun to erode the budgets of the poor at a time when federal assistance programs have shrunk. This year, Congress allocated $1.1 billion to the Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Program, which helps poor families with heating bills and home repairs improve energy efficiency. That is about half the financing the program received in 1985 -- only 33 percent, if inflation is taken into account. The program has no budget for determining how many people need aid, or how many are going without.</p>
        <p>Those most vulnerable to fuel price increases are people on fixed incomes, like retirees, and the working poor, most of whom receive little or no state assistance.</p>
        <p>In San Diego, where electric bills have more than doubled this summer, about 27 percent of the 900,000 families affected by the higher prices fall into these groups.</p>
        <p>In New York, deregulation has freed utilities to raise electric rates an average of 30 percent this summer. Mike Zevon has moved in with his disabled mother in Forest Hills, Queens, for fear she could not make ends meet on her monthly assistance payment of $490.</p>
        <p>The $1,400 a month that Mr. Zevon takes home from his job as a social worker helps. But the family's electric bill more than doubled, to $240, in June, and gasoline in the neighborhood has risen to $1.99 a gallon, from $1.49 a year ago.</p>
        <p>''By the end of the week, we scrounge for change to fill the tank,''  Mr. Zevon, 29, said.</p>
        <p>The squeeze will get tighter on low-income New Yorkers in October,  when annual rent increases go into effect for rent-stabilized apartments. After authorizing increases of 2 percent to 4 percent each of the last four years, the city's Rent Guidelines Board voted a 4 percent to 6 percent rise this year, based primarily on the higher cost of heating oil. The decision affects about 600,000 households.</p>
        <p>Lower-than-normal temperatures have allowed the northern Midwest, including Iowa, to escape high utility bills so far this summer. But the region has weathered some of the steepest increases in fuel costs.</p>
        <p>In May, just as Mrs. Messersmith was felled by her stroke, gasoline in Brooklyn rose to about $1.80 a gallon; Mr. Messersmith, a former truck driver, was spending about $400 a month to visit his wife at a hospital in Des Moines, about 75 miles east. The price of gasoline has since declined all over the region, falling to about $1.49 a gallon, but that is 40 cents a gallon more than Mr. Messersmith paid a year ago.</p>
        <p>High gasoline prices in the Midwest prompted the federal government to investigate accusations of price-gouging by oil companies. But most analysts believe that gasoline prices have risen mainly because of the demand bred by economic growth. Salaries have grown faster than the rate of inflation, which means consumers can afford more. So while Americans grumble about fuel prices, the most recent survey of motorists by the American Automobile Association indicated that few are driving less.</p>
        <p>And though the affluent use more energy in their homes, the poor bear the impact of higher prices. In 1998, a middle-class family spent 2.6 percent of its net income on heating bills, according to the federal heating assistance program, while the typical low-income family spent 10.1 percent. In Iowa, the Department of Human Rights study found that low-income residents last winter devoted nearly 20 percent of their income to heating costs; the Messersmiths, for example, spent 19 percent of their income on propane for their home.</p>
        <p>''Around the country, there's an affordability crisis among low-income people,'' said Jerry McKim, the author of the Iowa report.</p>
        <p>In the Iowa study, released in June, more than 12 percent of the 3,661 respondents said they cut back on food this past winter to pay fuel bills. More than 1 in 5 said they had gone without medical care. Nearly a third said they had not paid other bills to keep up with heating costs.</p>
        <p>Poverty stays hidden amid the pin-dot towns and prim clapboard homes of Marshall, Tama and Poweshiek Counties, about 80 miles north and east of Des Moines. The lush sea of soybean and corn gives no hint of the many family farms that have closed or are about to. The counties, neighbors, are poorer than most in the state. The meatpacking plants and other factories that employed residents have shut down or cut back.</p>
        <p>Gale Gies feels lucky that she drives only 30 miles a day round trip from her house in Garwin, in Tama County, to her job in the town of Tama. As a counselor with the Mid-Iowa energy assistance program, she helps low-income families apply for federal aid. But Mrs. Gies, 37, turns to the state for the same help she pursues for clients. Her husband, Alan, has been unable to work for three years because of degenerative arthritis, she says. Because he was denied federal disability assistance, the Gieses and their three children make do on Mrs. Gies's small salary.</p>
        <p>To make ends meet after paying rent and fuel, the Gieses go without.</p>
        <p>''Alan spends a lot of time in pain, because I can't afford his medicine,'' said Mrs. Gies, sitting on her porch one afternoon. ''The muscle relaxants and pain relievers for his back would cost $60 a month, and that's $60 we just don't have.''</p>
        <p>Two years ago, when the Messersmiths were healthy, they earned about $3,000 a month. But Mr. Messersmith's disability payments after his injury went to the wrong address, and by the time he corrected the oversight, a bank had foreclosed on the couple's house in Des Moines. They moved to a trailer on land here in Brooklyn they bought years ago, on the edge of a ravine choked with hickory and wild daisies, and now they are slowly building a house with the help of their grown sons.</p>
        <p>This summer, the house remains little more than a shell, as Mr. Messersmith, a round-faced man with a firecracker laugh, takes care of his wife. Her right side is paralyzed, so she relies on a wheelchair and speaks with normal intonation but in unrecognizable half-words.</p>
        <p>The couple spends $300 on building materials every month and a similar amount on Mrs. Messersmith's medicines. Last winter, the Messersmiths received about $300 from the federal assistance program, enough to cover one month's propane bill.</p>
        <p>They expect to apply for aid again.</p>
        <p>''I had been able to do anything I wanted before, and now it's hard,'' Mr. Messersmith said, ''because I've gone from being independent to, now, I need to ask for help.''</p>
        <p>He looked at his wife and patted her hand as she sat quietly in her wheelchair. ''So I guess in one form, I understand how she feels.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
