<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="09FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1D61E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1190" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>U.S. to Send Troops To Train African Force  The Clinton administration plans to send hundreds of American soldiers to Nigeria this month to train and equip West African forces that will be dispatched to Sierra Leone to bolster beleaguered government troops and United Nations peacekeepers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>U.S. to Send Troops To Train African Force  The Clinton administration plans to send hundreds of American soldiers to Nigeria this month to train and equip West African forces that will be dispatched to Sierra Leone to bolster beleaguered government troops and United Nations peacekeepers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Deadly Blast in Central Moscow  A bomb exploded in a pedestrian underpass at Pushkin Square at the height of the evening rush hour, killing 8 people and wounding 11. No one claimed responsibility, but the mayor called it a ''terrorist act'' with a ''Chechen trace.'' The Chechen president rejected such speculation.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Pinochet Stripped of Immunity  The Chilean Supreme Court issued a ruling to divest Gen. Augusto Pinochet of his senatorial immunity, removing a giant legal hurdle to charging the former dictator with involvement in the kidnapping, torture and murder of thousands of people.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>U.S. Drug Fighter Visits Mexico  Barry McCaffrey, the United States director of drug policy, praised the transition team assembled by President-elect Vicente Fox and said he shared Mr. Fox's opposition to a program under which the State Department evaluates interdiction efforts and can impose economic sanctions on countries found lacking.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Malaysian Ex-Official Convicted  Former Deputy Prime Minister Anwar Ibrahim, once a rising star in Asian politics, was found guilty of sodomy and sentenced to nine years in prison. Mr. Anwar, 52, was previously convicted of corruption.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Kashmir Peace Hopes Fade  The militant group Hizbul Mujahedeen ended its cease-fire. It wants Pakistan to be allowed into any talks, which India refuses to do.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Shootout in Tokyo  A shootout between members of a right-wing group and gangsters erupted in an upscale business district. Five people were wounded.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Reformist Paper Shut in Iran  Iran's last major reformist newspaper, Bahar, was closed by the hard-line judiciary two days after the country's top religious leader intervened to block legislation aimed at restoring a free press.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-19</p>
        <p>Gore and Lieberman Make Tolerance the Centerpiece  Vice President Al Gore formally introduced Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut as his Democratic running mate, portraying the selection of Mr. Lieberman, an Orthodox Jew, as a measure of his devotion to tolerance and his willingness to break barriers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The selection of Senator Lieberman has prompted a barrage of anti-Semitic comments in online chat rooms and on Internet message boards, leading some online services to start purging offensive postings.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>On some issues, including those that affect the insurance industry, Mr. Lieberman has been much more of a business ally than Mr. Gore. Mr. Lieberman has also been an ally of other companies that Mr. Gore has blasted in recent speeches, including pharmaceuticals.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>The announcement that her husband would be Vice President Gore's running mate thrust Hadassah Lieberman into the type of highly public role she has worked hard to avoid as a political spouse.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Reform Party in Chaos  The Reform Party split apart, as a faction opposed to Patrick J. Buchanan's presidential candidacy stormed out of a meeting of party leaders and vowed to proceed on its own, perhaps as a new party. Each group later declared itself the true Reform Party.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Protection for Horseshoe Crab  Federal officials announced plans for an 1,800-square-mile sanctuary from Delaware Bay out into the Atlantic to protect the rapidly dwindling stock of horseshoe crabs whose blood is used in pharmaceutical research and is vital to the annual migration of a dozen species of shorebirds. Commerce Secretary Norman Y. Mineta also ordered Virginia to join the other Atlantic states in recognizing an emergency in the horseshoe crab population.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>No Clemency for Texas Inmate  The Texas Board of Pardons and Paroles has turned down a request for clemency from Oliver Cruz, who was sentenced to death for the rape and murder of an Air Force enlisted woman. Mr. Cruz, who defense psychologists say is mentally retarded, is to be executed at 6 p.m. today.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Real Estate Prices Level Off in Manhattan  Several yardsticks indicate that Manhattan real estate prices appear to be flattening, which experts link to the technology-heavy Nasdaq stock market's decline that began in April, and to the half-percentage-point interest rate increase in May.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Putting the Blame on Con Ed  Governor Pataki signed a bill that forces the utility to repay the more than $100 million it assessed customers in expenses arising from a nuclear accident in February; the legislation also bars Con Ed from collecting tens of millions more. The utility said it would sue to overturn the law.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Heat Evacuation in Harlem  Hundreds of people in a 30-story public housing tower were evacuated from their steamy apartments after a malfunctioning electrical transformer in the building led officials to cut the power, shutting off air-conditioning, fans and elevators on one of the hottest days of the year.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Seeking Lieberman's Help  Hillary Rodham Clinton said she wanted Senator Joseph I. Lieberman to campaign with her, predicting that his presence on the Democratic national ticket would increase turnout in New York and lift her candidacy.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Coach Has Cancer Treatment  Mel Stottlemyre, the Yankees' pitching coach, left the team on Monday and might be out at least 10 days for bone marrow cancer treatment.</p>
        <p>D3</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C18-19</p>
        <p>Michael Meyer  A playwright and teacher whose translations of the plays of Ibsen and Strindberg are performed throughout the English-speaking world and who also wrote biographies of both playwrights, he was 79.</p>
        <p>C19</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18</p>
        <p>Phone Company Stock Falters  Shares of Verizon lost $5.8125, or 13.8 percent, to close at $42.0625. Verizon, in the third day of a walkout by 86,000 workers, said it would not be able to meet financial goals. It also said it would acquire control of NorthPoint Communications, a high-speed Internet provider, a deal that would further dilute earnings.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>The company reported 455 strike-related incidents of assault, harassment and vandalism.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Cisco Sales Surge  Cisco Systems, reporting after the markets closed, said quarterly sales had gained 61 percent, as the company continued to be the leading supplier of the necessary hardware for the the Internet.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>More Delays at United Airlines  The world's largest airline canceled more than 200 flights nationwide, disrupting service for thousands of passengers for the fourth consecutive day partly because many of its pilots, whose contract expired in April, are refusing to work overtime.</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A20-21</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. Gore's campaign; the Western fires; more executions in Texas; fair disclosure on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E7  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
