<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BULLETIN BOARD</title>
    <meta content="09BULL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilgoren, Jodi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zernike, Kate</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education/Columns/Bulletin Board</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3DA1E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BULLETIN BOARD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JODI WILGOREN, KATE ZERNIKE and KAREN W. ARENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilgoren, Jodi; Arenson, Karen W; Zernike, Kate</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bulletin Board column on events and news concerning schools and colleges (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another Yalie at, or Near, the Top</p>
        <p>Not for nothing did Yale hire a spokesman with experience in the White House. LAWRENCE J. HAAS, who worked in the Office of Management and Budget and was Vice President Al Gore's communications director, had an all-politics-is-local spin on Mr. Gore's selection of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman as running mate. As a result of that pick, a Yalie will be on the winning national ticket, Mr. Haas declared in an e-mail message (either Mr. Lieberman, '64, Law '67; or George W. Bush, '68). And, he pointed out, there has been an alumnus in one of the top two spots since 1980 (George Bush, '48, 1981-93; Bill Clinton, Law '73, since 1993).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Another Yalie at, or Near, the Top</p>
        <p>Not for nothing did Yale hire a spokesman with experience in the White House. LAWRENCE J. HAAS, who worked in the Office of Management and Budget and was Vice President Al Gore's communications director, had an all-politics-is-local spin on Mr. Gore's selection of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman as running mate. As a result of that pick, a Yalie will be on the winning national ticket, Mr. Haas declared in an e-mail message (either Mr. Lieberman, '64, Law '67; or George W. Bush, '68). And, he pointed out, there has been an alumnus in one of the top two spots since 1980 (George Bush, '48, 1981-93; Bill Clinton, Law '73, since 1993).</p>
        <p>At Last, the School Year's Over</p>
        <p>As other students think about heading back to classes, those at the John A. Reisenbach Charter School in Harlem were just celebrating end of the year graduation day yesterday. Reisenbach, one of the first two start-up charter schools in New York City, has a longer day than the typical public school (8:30 a.m. to 6 p.m. instead of to 3 p.m.) and a longer year (205 days instead of 180).</p>
        <p>Adding Depth to Fathom.com</p>
        <p>Fathom.com, the for-profit Internet site developed by Columbia University and five other institutions, will announce today that it is adding four  high-profile partners: the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, the American Film Institute, the University of Chicago and RAND. The Web site (www.fathom.com) will offer courses, books, trips and other educational material, some of it for a fee and some at no charge. ANN KIRSCHNER, Fathom's chief executive, said that the site was not ready to announce a starting date yet.</p>
        <p>Remembering a City College Official</p>
        <p>The corner of 143rd Street and Convent Avenue  in Manhattan near City College will be named after W. HAYWOOD BURNS, former dean of the City University of New York School of Law at Queens College. Mr. Burns, who was killed in a car crash in South Africa four years ago, spent 10 years at City College, where he served as vice provost and dean for urban and legal programs. The street-naming ceremony will be at 10 a.m. tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Doing Something About the Weather</p>
        <p>Being able to predict the weather is one thing; coping with its impact is something else. The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration is giving $42 million over five years to Columbia University's International Research Institute for Climate Prediction so it can help other nations -- especially poor ones -- prepare for drought, floods, hurricanes and other dire weather. ''Climate prediction is not enough,'' said Dr. ANTONIO DIVINO MOURA, director of the institute, which is based in Palisades, N.Y.</p>
        <p>JODI WILGOREN, KATE ZERNIKE and KAREN W. ARENSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
