<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pinochet Ruled No Longer Immune From Prosecution</title>
    <meta content="Y09PIN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Santiago (Chile)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pinochet Ugarte, Augusto (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lagos, Ricardo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Izurieta, Ricardo (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile/Santiago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amnesties and Pardons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Torture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFDB1E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="997" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pinochet Ruled No Longer Immune From Prosecution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>SANTIAGO, Chile, Aug. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chilean Supreme Court divests Gen Augusto Pinochet of his senatorial immunity, removing legal hurdle to charging former dictator with role in kidnapping, torture and murder of thousands of people during his 17-year rule; demonstrators hail decision, Santiago; decision, which also ratifies legal doctrine that anyone who disappeared during dictatorship and is still missing is victim of ongoing kidnapping not covered by amnesty, will likely lead to prosecution of dozens of other retired military and police officers; ruling provokes veiled sniping between Pres Ricardo Lagos, Socialist, and army commander Gen Ricardo Izurieta, who has tried to coexist with civilian presidents and keep right-wing elements at bay; Izurieta makes provocative visit to Pinochet's home to express army's support for him; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Chilean Supreme Court issued its ruling today to divest Gen. Augusto Pinochet of his senatorial immunity, removing a giant legal hurdle to charging the former dictator with involvement in the kidnapping, torture and murder of thousands of people during his 17-year rule.</p>
        <p>The announcement, which was widely expected, was greeted here with the uncorking of bottles of Champagne by hundreds of cheering demonstrators, who waved black-and-white photographs of their dead or missing loved ones. It also provoked some thinly veiled sniping between President Ricardo Lagos -- the first Socialist to govern Chile since the Pinochet coup overthrew President Salvador Allende in 1973 -- and the army commander, who strongly defended the former dictator's place in history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Chilean Supreme Court issued its ruling today to divest Gen. Augusto Pinochet of his senatorial immunity, removing a giant legal hurdle to charging the former dictator with involvement in the kidnapping, torture and murder of thousands of people during his 17-year rule.</p>
        <p>The announcement, which was widely expected, was greeted here with the uncorking of bottles of Champagne by hundreds of cheering demonstrators, who waved black-and-white photographs of their dead or missing loved ones. It also provoked some thinly veiled sniping between President Ricardo Lagos -- the first Socialist to govern Chile since the Pinochet coup overthrew President Salvador Allende in 1973 -- and the army commander, who strongly defended the former dictator's place in history.</p>
        <p>General Pinochet is still a long way from serving time in prison, or even being tried. Conservative lawmakers said they would introduce legislation exempting him from facing a trial because of his health. He has diabetes and circulatory problems and has had three strokes.</p>
        <p>His family also takes the position he should not stand trial because of the illnesses. The family said today that it would fight a legal battle to prevent General Pinochet, 84, from being examined to determine if he is mentally fit to stand trial, which the family considers humiliating.</p>
        <p>Because of his status as a retired general, General Pinochet has the right to choose the location of his interrogation by prosecutors. That privilege could allow him to specify that his questioning take place within a military building in an attempt to pit the armed forces against the government.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the decision today was more than symbolic in importance because it will likely lead to the prosecution of dozens of other retired military and police officers for the executions and disappearances of more than 3,000 people.</p>
        <p>The decision not only stripped General Pinochet of his immunity, but it also ratified a legal doctrine that considers anyone who disappeared during the dictatorship and has not been found to be a kidnapping victim. Since the kidnapping would be considered still in progress, it could not be covered by an amnesty decreed while General Pinochet was in power. The amnesty granted immunity for political crimes committed during the early years of his government.</p>
        <p>Judge Juan Guzman, who is serving as the prosecutor, has based his case against General Pinochet on the workings of a death squad led by aides close to him in the first months after the 1973 coup. The death squad has been held responsible for the disappearance of scores of people, 19 of whom are still missing and therefore are considered kidnapping victims.</p>
        <p>Today's decision provoked a bitter polemic between President Lagos and Gen. Ricardo Izurieta. Since he replaced General Pinochet as commander in chief of the army in early 1998, General Izurieta has attempted  both to coexist with two civilian presidents and to keep right-wing elements at bay.</p>
        <p>He made a provocative visit to General Pinochet at his home today, saying, ''The Chilean Army wanted to express its support at this difficult time.'' When asked by reporters if his visit had the government's approval, he shot back, ''As commander in chief, I do what I have to do.''</p>
        <p>Without mentioning General Izurieta by name or criticizing his visit, President Lagos clearly responded to the general's remarks, saying, ''The command of our country rests on what I decide.'' He added, ''Today our obligation is to respect the judges and guard our own conduct as the world is watching us.''</p>
        <p>In recent days top military commanders have warned that a ruling against General Pinochet could inhibit military officials from coming forward with information about those who had disappeared -- something the military pledged earlier this year that it would do. But today General Izurieta said the armed forces would comply with its promise.</p>
        <p>General Pinochet's lawyers and other supporters contended that the court decision was totally political because, they said, everyone knew that the people who had disappeared were dead and that many could never be found because their bodies had been dumped into the ocean.</p>
        <p>''It's an absurd decision based on a falsehood,'' said Senator Jorge Martinez Bush, a conservative ally of the former dictator. ''This is a judicial fiction that will freeze the relationship between the civilian leadership and the military.''</p>
        <p>The 14-to-6 Supreme Court vote upholding a lower court ruling was more one-sided than the tally was reported to be a week ago, when the outcome of the secret deliberations was reported in some detail in the local press.</p>
        <p>''This is an important precedent for the entire world that human rights is a basic foundation of democracy,'' said Juan Bustos, one of the lawyers who argued before the court in favor of stripping the immunity that General Pinochet was granted when he became a senator for life in 1998, under a provision in the Constitution written during his rule.</p>
        <p>Judge Guzman will now lead a formal criminal investigation against the former dictator. The prosecutor has not made clear how he will proceed, but he is expected to order that General Pinochet undergo medical tests to assess his mental fitness to face trial. Then he will probably demand that the retired general answer a series of questions.</p>
        <p>There have been 157 criminal claims filed against General Pinochet by human rights groups, families of those who disappeared and torture victims. But the case against him picked up momentum only after he was arrested in London two years ago on a Spanish warrant. He has faced legal troubles ever since he was released by the British authorities for health reasons, and allowed to return home in March.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
