<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="09MBRF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E2DE1F3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: GREENWICH VILLAGE DEMOLITION -- A state judge allowed some work to proceed on a block near Washington Square Park that includes the former home of Edgar Allan Poe, but he continued to delay its demolition. Supreme Court Justice Robert D. Lippman scheduled an Aug. 22 hearing for further arguments in the case. Meanwhile, New York University School of Law may remove asbestos from several buildings on West Third Street between Thompson and Sullivan Streets in preparation for demolition, the judge ruled. Preservation groups fighting demolition were encouraged by the decision, but a lawyer for the school said the delay was unjustified.</p>
        <p>Nina Siegal (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: GREENWICH VILLAGE DEMOLITION -- A state judge allowed some work to proceed on a block near Washington Square Park that includes the former home of Edgar Allan Poe, but he continued to delay its demolition. Supreme Court Justice Robert D. Lippman scheduled an Aug. 22 hearing for further arguments in the case. Meanwhile, New York University School of Law may remove asbestos from several buildings on West Third Street between Thompson and Sullivan Streets in preparation for demolition, the judge ruled. Preservation groups fighting demolition were encouraged by the decision, but a lawyer for the school said the delay was unjustified.</p>
        <p>Nina Siegal (NYT)</p>
        <p>MASTIC: SUFFOLK CRIME SPREE -- Four men were arrested Monday after a three-hour spree through Suffolk County that left two men injured, one critically, and seven others robbed at gunpoint, the police said. The incidents began around midnight Sunday in Mastic, when four men robbed a pedestrian of $80, then robbed others, including a man standing at an A.T.M. machine, a delivery-truck driver, and several gas station clerks of $1,300 and various items, including sneakers and a baseball hat, the police said. In Bellport, one of the men gunned down Lashon Washington, 26, hitting him once in the neck, the police said. Mr. Washington was in stable condition at a local hospital.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>HAUPPAUGE: DNA INDICTMENT -- The Suffolk County district attorney, James M. Catterson Jr., announced a 17-count criminal indictment yesterday against an unidentified rapist linked by DNA evidence to six rapes that were committed in Babylon between July 1992 and August 1995. Mr. Catterson said evidence, including semen, produced a DNA profile that fit only one person in 742 billion. Suffolk authorities sought the indictment before the statute of limitations for rape expired. Such John Doe indictments are rare, but have been filed in New York City and Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>John Rather (NYT)</p>
        <p>WATERLOO: SUFFRAGIST HOUSE SAVED -- Hunt House, where in 1848 the world's first women's rights convention was conceived, became a part of the Women's Rights National Historical Park yesterday when President Clinton signed a law allowing the government to buy the house. Preservationists saved the home from possible demolition last year. The home, where five women organized a convention in nearby Seneca Falls, is to be open for public tours.</p>
        <p>Glenn Collins (NYT)</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN: INDICTMENT IN WATKINS KILLING -- A Brooklyn grand jury indicted a man on murder charges yesterday in the killing of Amy Watkins, a 26-year-old graduate student who was stabbed to death during a robbery on a street in Prospect Heights a year and a half ago. Prosecutors said the man, Felix Rodriguez, 20, left, helped another man rob Ms. Watkins. He was formally charged with second-degree murder, while the other man, David Jamison, 27, faces a charge of first-degree murder. Mr. Jamison appeared in the Brooklyn Criminal Court yesterday and was ordered to go before the grand jury next week.</p>
        <p>Alan Feuer (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRONX: BLOCK PARTY SHOOTING -- The police have arrested a second suspect in connection with a fatal gun battle at a block party in the Bronx early Sunday morning. The suspect, David Richards, 20, of 4002 Carpenter Avenue, was arrested Monday night. He is being charged with second-degree murder, criminal possession of a weapon and several counts of assault, the police said. Another man, Damien Elliot, 18, was arrested at the scene and charged with criminal possession of a weapon. One person died and seven suffered gunshot wounds.</p>
        <p>Elissa Gootman (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: SCHOOL SEX ABUSE CONVICTIONS -- Two former sixth-grade boys charged with raping a 9-year-old girl last April in a stairwell at Community School 200 in Harlem were convicted on Friday of second-degree sexual abuse, a misdemeanor. The incident led to the dismissal of the girl's teacher and the disciplining of other school officials. Sentencing of the two boys, whose names were not released because of their age, is scheduled for Sept. 7 in Manhattan Family Court. The boys were free on probation pending a mental health evaluation.</p>
        <p>Edward Wyatt (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: SIEGEL EXPLORES CANDIDACY -- Norman Siegel, executive director of the New York Civil Liberties Union, has applied to the city's Board of Elections to form a committee to explore running for the office of public advocate next year. Mr. Siegel, 56, has headed the civil liberties group for 15 years. He said a decision was months away.</p>
        <p>Jonathan P. Hicks (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY --</p>
        <p>COLTS NECK: HIGH WINDS DAMAGE 50 HOUSES -- The winds that tore through Colts Neck and Marlboro Township Monday evening, damaging several thousand trees, were ferocious but did not constitute a tornado, the National Weather Service said yesterday. The winds were clocked at 75 to 90 miles per hour but blew in a straight line, not in a tornado's swirling pattern, said Harry Woodworth, a meteorologist. About 50 houses were damaged by falling trees or limbs. No injuries were reported.</p>
        <p>Robert Hanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>HOBOKEN: CAR JUMPS CURB AND KILLS MAN -- A 49-year-old Florida man was killed yesterday when an out-of-control car jumped onto the sidewalk and struck him in front of an outdoor cafe and a fruit stand, the police said. The authorities did not release the name of the man killed as he walked near First and Washington Streets at about 4 p.m. Two men who were eating at a table outside the Fatay Malasyian restaurant were also injured. The men, who were not identified, were taken to Jersey City Medical Center in Jersey City. Their conditions were unavailable last night. One other woman was injured by glass sent flying when the car crashed into the window of the fruit stand, the police said. The driver of the Ford Mustang that went out of control was identified by police as Stewart Tewkesburg, 50, of Matawan. The police said he may have suffered a seizure before losing control of the car. (AP)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: HELP FOR GAMBLERS --Gamblers unable to control their urges may soon be able to lock themselves out of Atlantic City. Under a plan announced by the Division of Gaming Enforcement on Monday, gamblers who register with the state and submit a photograph would allow casino security officers to bar them from the premises. The plan is being studied by the Casino Control Commission.</p>
        <p>Andrew Jacobs (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
