<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FirstEnergy Acquires GPU in $4.5 Billion Cash-Stock Deal</title>
    <meta content="Y09UTI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gpu Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Firstenergy Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5DB1E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FirstEnergy Acquires GPU in $4.5 Billion Cash-Stock Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE with ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FirstEnergy Corporation, Ohio-based utility company, will acquire to acquire GPU Inc of Morristown, NJ, for $4.5 billion in cash and stock; acquisition will make FirstEnergy sixth-largest energy concern in US (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The FirstEnergy Corporation, an Ohio-based utility company, agreed yesterday to acquire GPU Inc. of Morristown, N.J., for $4.5 billion in cash and stock.</p>
        <p>The acquisition would make FirstEnergy the sixth-largest energy concern in the United States, based on customers served. Its increased size and scale would also give it the potential to produce and distribute electricity more efficiently, industry analysts said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The FirstEnergy Corporation, an Ohio-based utility company, agreed yesterday to acquire GPU Inc. of Morristown, N.J., for $4.5 billion in cash and stock.</p>
        <p>The acquisition would make FirstEnergy the sixth-largest energy concern in the United States, based on customers served. Its increased size and scale would also give it the potential to produce and distribute electricity more efficiently, industry analysts said.</p>
        <p>The deal, approved by the boards of both companies, could save the combined company $150 million the first year, a FirstEnergy spokesman said.</p>
        <p>FirstEnergy is based in Akron, Ohio, and primarily serves the Cleveland, Akron and Toledo markets and western Pennsylvania. GPU, best known for its past ownership of the Three Mile Island nuclear plant, provides power to central and coastal New Jersey, as well as the northwestern part of the state and eastern and central Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>The deal allows FirstEnergy, which generates electricity, operates a transmission grid and servesclients, to double its customer base to about 4.3 million and to establish itself firmly on the East Coast. GPU, for its part, will receive a significant premium on its equity as part of the deal. FirstEnergy is offering $36.50 for each share of GPU common stock, which rose 75 cents yesterday, to $31.4375 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>GPU, which divested itself of nearly all its power plants, would have access to FirstEnergy's power generation and would also be able to buy power more cheaply as part of a bigger company, changes that could translate into lower rates for its current customers in western New Jersey and eastern Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Together with last week's announcement of a union between the FPL Group of Florida and Entergy, based in New Orleans, the FirstEnergy acquisition may signal the start of another round of consolidation in the electric utility industry, which was reshaped last year by more than two dozen mergers.</p>
        <p>Share prices of many utilities have risen substantially since the start of the year, increasing the temptation for management to find buyers for their companies. Utilities also realize that in the wake of last year's mergers, bigger companies have more opportunities to cut costs, to market their electricity more aggressively and to negotiate better deals for the purchase of power.</p>
        <p>''They need to be big to implement the most efficiencies and have the economies of scale,'' said Barry M. Abramson, senior utility analyst at PaineWebber.</p>
        <p>Consumer advocates in New Jersey expressed guarded optimism over the sale of GPU. Blossom Peretz, the ratepayer advocate for the state of New Jersey, a position appointed by the governor, said rates charged by GPU and other New Jersey utilities were relatively high, but that GPU had built a solid reputation as a company that cooperates with customers and regulators. The state ratepayer's office said it wanted to find out if GPU would be able to buy cheaper energy as part of a larger company with better purchasing power. Ms. Peretz also said her office expected FirstEnergy to share with its customers any savings made from the merger.</p>
        <p>''We're also concerned that none of the merger-related costs go to ratepayers,'' Ms. Peretz said, ''and that there be no rate shocks due to the deal.''</p>
        <p>The market, however, had a negative reaction to the deal. When word of a possible acquisition leaked out Monday, most analysts downgraded their ratings of FirstEnergy, citing the burdens the company will have to take on in purchasing GPU. Both companies are growing at a rate of 4 percent to 5 percent a year, lagging behind many other utilities that show double-digit growth.</p>
        <p>FirstEnergy, which has no current debt on the parent company level, will have to incur debt to make the acquisition. ''Financing for the cash portion of the transaction is going to come from a combination of public debt and bank financing,'' said Richard Marsh, the chief financial officer of FirstEnergy, during a conference call with analysts.</p>
        <p>Moreover, FirstEnergy will assume GPU's $7.4 billion in debt, which the latter acquired through a series of overseas investments that are faltering.</p>
        <p>GPU entered the retail energy field in Australia at the height of the market, but sold its venture recently for a loss. It also bought into the British market at a time when industry observers felt that utilities would be hit by a rate cut -- which is what happened. And GPU sold its generation business before power generators began making hefty profits because of high demand.</p>
        <p>Because it shed most of its generation capacity, GPU is also short of power in Pennsylvania, a gap that FirstEnergy, whose own capacity is stretched in summer, will have to address.</p>
        <p>Shares of FirstEnergy closed down 0.3 percent, or 6.25 cents, closing at $25.3125 yesterday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
