<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Decisions on Running Mates Rarely Prove Decisive</title>
    <meta content="Y09ASSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONTEXT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFDB1E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Decisions on Running Mates Rarely Prove Decisive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Impact on presidential races of choice of running mates discussed in light of Vice Pres Al Gore's selection of Sen Joseph I Lieberman; such choices generally produce transient bounce in polls, but have little lasting impact; most of debate about choice focuses on candidate's ability to boost ticket, not candidate's ability to serve as president, even though many vice presidents become or run for president; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore's selection of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut as his running mate on Monday, the frenzy of speculation that preceded it and the outpouring of analysis that has followed it raise a number of insistent questions.</p>
        <p>First of all, do such selections ever decide presidential elections? Do they make any difference at all, either to the national popular vote or in individual states? Or are they merely something to keep politicians and journalists busy, now that the nominating races end so soon and conventions decide almost nothing?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore's selection of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut as his running mate on Monday, the frenzy of speculation that preceded it and the outpouring of analysis that has followed it raise a number of insistent questions.</p>
        <p>First of all, do such selections ever decide presidential elections? Do they make any difference at all, either to the national popular vote or in individual states? Or are they merely something to keep politicians and journalists busy, now that the nominating races end so soon and conventions decide almost nothing?</p>
        <p>The candidate making the choice usually gets an uptick in the polls after it becomes known. Gov. George W. Bush of Texas benefited from the customary bounce after he chose Dick Cheney, and Mr. Gore closed the gap with Mr. Bush after choosing Mr. Lieberman, at least according to an overnight USA Today/CNN/Gallup survey.</p>
        <p>But such changes are almost always transient.</p>
        <p>''I think political scientists pretty much agree that in the long run, in November, these choices have very little impact,'' said Paul C. Light of the Brookings Institution, a student of the vice presidency. ''Maybe you pick up half a percentage point, or even a whole one, with a good selection and lose about the same with a bad one.''</p>
        <p>That is not to say, of course, that selecting a running mate has no meaning. Since World War II, five vice presidents have moved into the Oval Office -- Harry S. Truman, Lyndon B. Johnson, Richard M. Nixon, Gerald R. Ford and George Bush. Two others have been nominated for president, only to lose in November -- Hubert H. Humphrey and Walter F. Mondale.</p>
        <p>But much of the debate about whom to choose usually centers not on the capacity of the prospective choice to serve as president, an issue of transcendent significance, but on his or her capacity to improve the performance of the ticket at the polls, an issue of considerably less importance.</p>
        <p>George Bush's choice of Dan Quayle in 1988, viewed in hindsight by most politicians as a major gaffe, did no overwhelming harm to the Republican cause. But exit polls nonetheless suggested that Mr. Quayle was a distinct liability, especially when compared with the Democratic vice-presidential nominee, Lloyd M. Bentsen. He may have cost the Republicans as much as four percentage points, which could have proved decisive in a closer race.</p>
        <p>Traditionally, presidential nominees often chose running mates to appeal to swing states or to sections of the country where they themselves were weak. The most successful example of that in the modern era, it is often said, was John F. Kennedy's selection of Johnson in 1960, because it caused Texas to vote Democratic. But that view is challenged by revisionist historians.</p>
        <p>The Kennedy-Johnson ticket, like the pairing of Adlai E. Stevenson and Estes Kefauver on the unsuccessful 1956 Democratic ticket, was an effort to provide not only geographical balance but also ideological balance. In choosing Mr. Quayle, Mr. Bush sought something else: generational balance.</p>
        <p>But those modes of selection have gone out of style in more recent elections. Warren Christopher, the former secretary of state, who conducted the vice-presidential searches for Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore, said in an interview earlier this summer that the Clinton choice put a new emphasis on the personal relationship between the candidates.</p>
        <p>President Clinton chose Mr. Gore, a man from the same part of the country as he -- indeed, from an adjacent state -- and from the same part of the ideological spectrum. This year, two candidates from states with relatively few electoral votes were chosen -- Mr. Cheney from Wyoming and Mr. Lieberman from Connecticut -- and both of them are close ideological fits with the men with whom they are running.</p>
        <p>Both provided a kind of inoculation. Mr. Cheney, well seasoned in government, lent the inexperienced Governor Bush some needed weight. Mr. Lieberman, a politician known for his independence and for his criticism of Mr. Clinton's sexual peccadilloes, lent Mr. Gore some cover from those who think he has marched in lock step with Mr. Clinton, regardless of the issues.</p>
        <p>''People suspect vice presidents,'' Mr. Light said. ''Remember Hubert? He was seen as Johnson's captive until he showed his mettle in the speech in Salt Lake City where he broke free on Vietnam. It came too late to save him. Well, I think that Lieberman could be Gore's Salt Lake City, but earlier.''</p>
        <p>Vice-presidential nominees used to be chosen at conventions; in the days, ending about a quarter century ago, when conventions rather than primaries chose the presidential nominees, it was considered poor form to talk about running mates until your own nomination was official. The first breach in tradition came in 1976, when Ronald Reagan, seeking to halt Mr. Ford's march toward the Republican nomination and to dampen talk that Mr. Reagan was too conservative to win in November, stipulated that if nominated he would choose Senator Richard S. Schweiker of Pennsylvania, a moderate, as his running mate.</p>
        <p>He never got the chance. Mr. Ford was nominated after all.</p>
        <p>In 1984, Mr. Mondale, hoping to get voters to give him a second look, despite Mr. Reagan's popularity, chose Geraldine A. Ferraro before the convention and promptly announced the choice -- a dramatic one, because she was the first woman on a major national ticket. Yet the race quickly regained its equilibrium.</p>
        <p>The choice of a running mate has been a kind of litmus test of judgment for many years, because it is always the first major decision a candidate makes. But now that early selection has become the pattern, the choice seems to have gained additional importance.</p>
        <p>''Viewed narrowly, it is still not decisive at the ballot box,'' said Prof. Michael Nelson of Rhodes College in Memphis, another vice-presidential scholar. ''But now that it comes on the eve of the convention, the selection of a running mate shapes the media coverage of the candidate and his party.''</p>
        <p>Another element has changed. The new system gives a presidential nominee plenty of time to vet, and then to carefully consider, the possibilities before him. In the old days, the choice was often made late at night, in a hurry, by ad hoc groups of insiders -- ''Bogsat,'' as the political consultant Douglas Bailey once termed them, a ''bunch of guys sitting around a table.'''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONTEXT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
