<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCaffrey Voices Confidence in Mexico's Anti-Drug Efforts</title>
    <meta content="Y09MEXI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccaffrey, Barry R (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox, Vicente</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Ginger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E1DA1E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCaffrey Voices Confidence in Mexico's Anti-Drug Efforts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINGER THOMPSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thompson, Ginger</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Aug. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gen Barry R McCaffrey, visiting Mexico as United States drug policy director, lauds Pres-elect Vicente Fox's transition team; says he shares Fox's opposition to American drug-certification program but sees no chance that Congress will end it soon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In one of his last official visits here as the United States director of drug policy, Gen. Barry R. McCaffrey, praised the transition team of President-elect Vicente Fox and said he shared Mr. Fox's opposition to the American drug-certification program.</p>
        <p>But General McCaffrey, who has long expressed misgivings about the program, said there was no chance that Congress would end it in the near future. ''Zero,'' he said, to a question at a news briefing. At most, he said, the program might die a kind of natural death as the Organization of American States begins drawing up plans next year for multinational drug evaluation that would open all member governments' drug programs to scrutiny.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In one of his last official visits here as the United States director of drug policy, Gen. Barry R. McCaffrey, praised the transition team of President-elect Vicente Fox and said he shared Mr. Fox's opposition to the American drug-certification program.</p>
        <p>But General McCaffrey, who has long expressed misgivings about the program, said there was no chance that Congress would end it in the near future. ''Zero,'' he said, to a question at a news briefing. At most, he said, the program might die a kind of natural death as the Organization of American States begins drawing up plans next year for multinational drug evaluation that would open all member governments' drug programs to scrutiny.</p>
        <p>''I actually believe,'' General McCaffrey said, ''that the certification process is slowly disappearing under the evidence that multinational cooperation better serves the interests of the American people than confrontation.''</p>
        <p>Under the program, created by Congress in the 1980's, the State Department evaluates other countries' interdiction efforts and can impose economic sanctions on countries that do receive certification. Most Latin American governments view the program as interventionist and lopsided, because it does not allow for scrutiny of American efforts to combat consumption.</p>
        <p>General McCaffrey, who arrived on Monday for a series of meetings, including visits with Mr. Fox's chief security and law enforcement advisers, praised the president-elect for seeking greater cooperation among countries in the fight against drugs. He said he was confident that Mexico's efforts would not be weakened by Mr. Fox's plans to limit the military's role gradually.</p>
        <p>General McCaffrey has long praised the Mexican military as a crucial element of the battle because of its successes in destroying marijuana crops and in confiscating drug shipments that travel through Mexico on the way to the United States. At least 60 percent of all cocaine that enters the United States is widely thought to pass through Mexico.</p>
        <p>''My judgment is that President-elect Fox and this team that we are working with are pragmatists,'' General McCaffrey said to reporters at the United States Embassy. ''They are determined to go down in history as Mexican patriots. I cannot believe they will do anything that doesn't make sense to them. They have got large new visions. And what we are going to do is listen to what they say and be supportive of their emerging strategies.''</p>
        <p>Soon after his election on July 2, Mr. Fox announced plans to reorganize the justice system to resemble United States agencies. At the same time, he announced plans to lobby Washington to end the drug-certification program. That will be among the topics to be discussed this month when Mr. Fox travels to the United States to meet President Clinton, Vice President Al Gore and the Republican presidential candidate, George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>A member of Mr. Fox's transition team said even though ending certification seemed unlikely, Mexico was determined to stop it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
