<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crossing the Tightrope From Algeria to France</title>
    <meta content="09FAUD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Central Park Summerstage</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faudel (Singer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Central Park Summerstage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED6113CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crossing the Tightrope From Algeria to France</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles reviews performance by Algerian rai singer Faudel at Central Park SummerStage concert; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the front of the audience for the concert by Faudel, some people waved Algerian flags; others sang along in French. Near the back, a group of white-robed women ululated between songs and loudly cheered some of Faudel's Arabic lyrics. It was a victorious crossover for rai, the music that came out of Algeria and has thrived with the French pop audience.</p>
        <p>Every crossover song is a cultural negotiation: a choice of tempos, rhythms and instruments, of what language to use and what to say. Rai itself began as a hybrid, placing Arab-inflected melodies atop imported funk and pop. It started with a lot of dinky keyboard sounds; now, as it has moved into Parisian pop, it has kept adding more international elements, from flamenco to reggae.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the front of the audience for the concert by Faudel, some people waved Algerian flags; others sang along in French. Near the back, a group of white-robed women ululated between songs and loudly cheered some of Faudel's Arabic lyrics. It was a victorious crossover for rai, the music that came out of Algeria and has thrived with the French pop audience.</p>
        <p>Every crossover song is a cultural negotiation: a choice of tempos, rhythms and instruments, of what language to use and what to say. Rai itself began as a hybrid, placing Arab-inflected melodies atop imported funk and pop. It started with a lot of dinky keyboard sounds; now, as it has moved into Parisian pop, it has kept adding more international elements, from flamenco to reggae.</p>
        <p>Faudel, a 22-year-old singer, is already a pop star in France. At Central Park SummerStage on Sunday afternoon, his band often started songs with an improvisatory prelude for oud or violin, followed by an instrumental melody suggesting Algerian roots. Rhythm kicked in with a drum kit and the quick pattering of a derbuka (hand drum), then Faudel began singing in a husky, imploring voice.</p>
        <p>His melodies soon resolved into foursquare phrases, catchy to European and American ears and harmonized by guitar and keyboard, but answered by responses from the oud or violin. And the beat became a clear pop 4/4. As songs continued, Faudel soared away from the melody with improvisational flourishes.</p>
        <p>His lyrics switched between Arabic and French, sometimes in the same song; he sometimes urged fans, ''Jump! Jump!'' in English, like a rapper. Faudel's European hits are sung in French, and they're love songs, insisting that the singer's love has turned his whole world inside-out. The chorus of ''Tellement N'Brick'' took on a reggae bounce; ''Dis-Moi'' had a lighter version of the Bo Diddley beat. ''Omri'' used brisk guitar strumming and a quasi-rumba piano solo in clear imitation of the Gipsy Kings. They could almost be French pop songs if not for the turns and quavers of Faudel's singing.</p>
        <p>Rai is still the voice of a minority: of frustrated youth in Algeria and of immigrants in France. But Faudel's crossover takes for granted that he can also speak to the pop mainstream, at least in France, and to do so he's willing to dilute the music's Algerian side. He brings rai right up to the edge of assimilating into European pop but rarely goes too far; it's a balancing act that's not as guileless as it sounds.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
