<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scourge of Stars, Rich Spouse's Nightmare</title>
    <meta content="09PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Law</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Raoul Felder</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wadler, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Felder, Raoul Lionel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DB1E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scourge of Stars, Rich Spouse's Nightmare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE WADLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wadler, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column discusses career of divorce lawyer Raoul Felder; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU ready for the show? Because the set is waiting for you. The office door of Philip Marlowe, Private Detective, is on one side; the office of Sam Spade, Criminal Investigator, is on the other, and in the center, befitting the star, is the name of Raoul Felder, in gold. Trompe l'oeil, the doors of Marlowe and Spade, though Europeans have been known to get confused.</p>
        <p>This is not a cheap gag -- we are talking office space on the 30th floor on Madison Avenue -- but Mr. Felder, matrimonial lawyer to the stars, is doing well. We could let him discuss the art in his office, the Groz, the Picasso; or permit him his old trick of beguiling the adversary into a sense of superiority with a self-deprecating comment regarding his accomplishments or health. (Today's: ''You have allergies? My sinuses are killing me.'')</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU ready for the show? Because the set is waiting for you. The office door of Philip Marlowe, Private Detective, is on one side; the office of Sam Spade, Criminal Investigator, is on the other, and in the center, befitting the star, is the name of Raoul Felder, in gold. Trompe l'oeil, the doors of Marlowe and Spade, though Europeans have been known to get confused.</p>
        <p>This is not a cheap gag -- we are talking office space on the 30th floor on Madison Avenue -- but Mr. Felder, matrimonial lawyer to the stars, is doing well. We could let him discuss the art in his office, the Groz, the Picasso; or permit him his old trick of beguiling the adversary into a sense of superiority with a self-deprecating comment regarding his accomplishments or health. (Today's: ''You have allergies? My sinuses are killing me.'')</p>
        <p>But because this is Mr. Felder, gallantly looking out for the rights of single mothers in the case of the Brazilian lingerie model Luciana Morad vs. Mick Jagger (''The wrinkly rocker, I called him. That's a nice phrase.'') by seeking $35,000 a month in child support, let's cut to the chase.</p>
        <p>Mr. Felder, you've got a lot of rich, spoiled people for clients ---- ''Yeah,'' interrupts Mr. Felder, agreeably. ''They usually go together, by the way, those two adjectives. I had very little choice in my career. A Jewish boy growing up in Brooklyn, it was doctor, lawyer or, if you weren't so bright, selling shirts.''</p>
        <p>But you didn't have to do this kind of law.</p>
        <p>Deadpan, which Mr. Felder does as well as his pal Jackie Mason:</p>
        <p>''Yeah. It was the money.''</p>
        <p>Now playing, in one of the longest-running shows in town, our own matrimonial song and dance man, Raoul Felder. How old are you getting to be, Mr. Felder? ''Sixty-three. That's a lie,'' he says, trimming three years.</p>
        <p>The National Law Journal called him a ''publicity machine extraordinaire,'' and some say his wife and partner, Myrna Felder, is the superior legal tactician. But Mr. Felder's friend and frequent adversary, Eleanor B. Alter, calls him ''terrific at what he does, who knows how to negotiate.''</p>
        <p>And, given his public relations philosophy -- ''I knew and still know how to use the media'' -- he will rarely show offense.</p>
        <p>Mr. Felder, you seem very often to get the fiscal have-nots. Mick Jagger's girlfriend and not Mick. Why?</p>
        <p>''Men, particularly wealthy men, usually have regular lawyers. The women go with a name they see in the newspapers.''</p>
        <p>So you don't feel bad that Mick didn't call?</p>
        <p>''No. When you represent men -- I don't like to mention names, but I represented Brian De Palma and Richard Harris years ago, when they were big stars -- they come in with a gang of their sycophants, they're used to ordering people around. They have these guys: 'Yeah, baby. Go, baby. Great idea, baby.' The wife starts out tabula rasa, she listens to the lawyer. Do you come with a troop of retainers when you go to any other professional? You go to a doctor, you don't take a press agent.''</p>
        <p>IT is possible there is some genuine melancholy here. Growing up poor in Williamsburg, Mr. Felder had an elder brother who had been sent to the country to escape an epidemic of infantile paralysis and there contracted polio, an event which could instill in anyone an appreciation of the dark ironies of life. That brother, the legendary songwriter Doc Pomus, who died in 1991, wrote the hits ''This Magic Moment'' and ''Save the Last Dance for Me.''</p>
        <p>Raoul Felder begins legal life as a federal prosecutor.</p>
        <p>How does he become a divorce lawyer?</p>
        <p>''It's a boring story,'' Mr. Felder says. ''Thankfully it's short.''</p>
        <p>We'll make it even shorter. Mr. Felder represents a pal in a divorce, and The Daily News writes it up.</p>
        <p>''The first year I made $50,000,'' he says. ''I'd been making $11,000 a year in the prosecutor's office. It was a great way to make money. It's not a religious endeavor.''</p>
        <p>Struggling with the allergies. ''I'm passing away. I got to take a spray up my nose. I'll show you the bottle, I want you to know it's not crack cocaine.''</p>
        <p>A brief adjournment, after which Mr. Felder is asked about a framed front page from a British tabloid, about a consultation with Diana, Princess of Wales.</p>
        <p>''I can't comment,'' Mr. Felder honks. ''I get consulted by a lot of people, make a lot of enemies. One enemy I made for no reason at all was the poor kid that got killed in the plane crash, John Kennedy, when the rapist was being tried. Remember his cousin William Kennedy Smith, he was a rapist, tried in Florida?''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Smith was acquitted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Felder continues speaking about the trial, undeterred.</p>
        <p>''I made a statement, 'This could turn out to be the fall of the house of Kennedy.' After the rapist was acquitted I get flowers like you send for a dead person and a note that says, 'We're still standing, baby,' and signed 'John.' I didn't quite believe it. I called one of the columnists and said, 'You check it out,' and it was him, the flowers were charged to Mrs. Kennedy's account.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Felder did not need to send that to the papers. He could have checked it all out himself.</p>
        <p>A look innocent of any ulterior motive, which you might believe, if you had been declared brain dead.</p>
        <p>''If I call, maybe I could con them out of it if I wanted to spend the time. If a newspaper calls up they can get it easier.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
