<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Firefighters Feeling Strain Across West</title>
    <meta content="09FIRE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Western States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Darby (Mont)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Idaho</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Forest Service (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milloy, Ross E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5D71E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1293" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Firefighters Feeling Strain Across West</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSS E. MILLOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Milloy, Ross E</byline>
      <dateline>DARBY, Mont., Aug. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wildfires are raging out of control in 12 Western States, leaving Forest Service officials scrambling for manpower and resources to combat worst fire season in over 50 years; officials say situation will only worsen until it either rains or snows; fires have destroyed over 50 homes in Darby, Montana, and forced evacuation of two Montana communities; maps show spread of wildfires in Idaho and Montana; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Surrounded by swirling wood smoke, and with forest fires crackling on a hillside just over the horizon, Craig Bobzien waved an arm over acres of equipment and exhausted firefighters in the Bitterroot Valley fire camp near here.</p>
        <p>''It's not enough. It's just not nearly enough,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Surrounded by swirling wood smoke, and with forest fires crackling on a hillside just over the horizon, Craig Bobzien waved an arm over acres of equipment and exhausted firefighters in the Bitterroot Valley fire camp near here.</p>
        <p>''It's not enough. It's just not nearly enough,'' he said.</p>
        <p>With fires raging out of control in a dozen Western states, Forest Service officials like Mr. Bobzien are scrambling to find the manpower and resources needed to combat the worst fire season in more than 50 years.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Bobzien tramped through the muddy fire camp at the Western edge of the state, row after row of military-style tents stretched over several acres: a hospital tent, operations tent, mess tent, even a finance tent to keep track of all the money being spent to fight the fires.</p>
        <p>''I've got more than 60 fires going just in the district that I manage, which is around a half-million acres. At least 130,000 acres of that area is on fire right now,'' said Mr. Bobzien, a Forest Service ranger for the Sula and Darby districts. ''Until we get rain or snow, it will only get worse.''</p>
        <p>Jack Sept, chief of external affairs at the National Interagency Fire Center in Boise, Idaho, said, ''We've got something going here that we've never seen before. We have most of the West burning all at once, and it's really straining our resources to keep up.''</p>
        <p>The center, which coordinates the federal response to major fire scenes, reported that eight people -- ''two civilians and six in the line of duty'' -- had already been killed, though officials cautioned that they were still gathering data.</p>
        <p>While there is no one explanation of why the fires are so pervasive this year, Mr. Bobzien speculated that they were at least in part a result of previous firefighting successes. That is, the Forest Service can generally suppress most natural fires very quickly, but as a consequence a buildup of combustible fuel occurs over decades -- a tinderbox awaiting a season of hot, dry weather as this summer.</p>
        <p>In Montana, officials said more than 4,000 people were fighting fires across the state. More than 50 homes near Darby have been destroyed in the last two days, and officials have evacuated the communities of Springer and Laird Creek.</p>
        <p>Betty and Charles Theis had just moved to Springer in June, but today they are living at an evacuation center in Hamilton, wondering if they still have a home.</p>
        <p>They were part of a caravan of 60 cars, led by a truck with a snowplow, that fought their way out of Springer Sunday night.</p>
        <p>''We'd had fires all around us for a week, then suddenly we were told to get out,'' Mrs. Theis recalled. ''As we left, there were flames on all sides of us, roaring up the mountain, and the road was covered with rocks and fallen trees. At one point, a flaming log came rolling down the hill and slammed into one of the cars ahead of us.''</p>
        <p>The wildlife, too, was trying to escape, she said. ''We saw four bears, and tons of deer running in all directions. And, when we got to the mouth of the valley, all the wild sheep had come down from the hills and they were just huddled there together by the road, shuddering.''</p>
        <p>With hot, dry weather blanketing most of the country from the Pacific Ocean to the Rocky Mountains -- and no rain in the forecast -- firefighters are battling blazes in Alaska, Arizona, California, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, New Mexico, Oregon, Utah, Washington and Wyoming.</p>
        <p>In California alone, officials are combating 12 separate forest fires, including a 72,000-acre blaze in the Sequoia National Forest.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, fire officials said that more than four million acres have burned this year, despite government expenditures of $500 million to fight the fires.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bobzien said the heavily forested mountains around this river valley were the Forest Service's No. 1 priority for the moment. ''We've got several thousand people living in a long, narrow valley with really only one highway in or out,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That highway, U.S. 93, was closed this morning south of Darby, and the route north was jammed with evacuees and flatbed trailers hauling in earthmoving equipment to fight the fires.</p>
        <p>Thick smoke cut visibility to less than 100 yards at the Forest Service's forward fire camp, and buses shuttled exhausted firefighters back and forth between the blazing hills and their tents.</p>
        <p>Nearly 500 families were also evacuated today from communities around Hamilton, 10 miles north of here, local officials said.</p>
        <p>''We call it mandatory evacuation, but we're not forcing anyone to leave,'' said Bobby Kitchens, an information officer for the Forest Service. ''If they won't go, the deputies get their Social Security number and contact information for their next of kin.''</p>
        <p>Charlie Baughman was visiting his daughter on Laird Creek on Sunday when, he said, fire officials told them ''If you don't leave now, you won't get out.''</p>
        <p>''We had a huge firestorm coming over the mountain on both sides of the road as we got out. It sounded like the roar of a jet plane, with flames 60 or 70 feet high, and the wind was howling like a hurricane, but hot,'' he said. ''The whole mountain was on fire in a matter of minutes.''</p>
        <p>The Interagency Fire Center said that firefighters had come from as far away as Australia, New Zealand and Hawaii. At least 1,200 military personnel are also fighting the fires, and President Clinton met with some of them today in Boise.</p>
        <p>Rex B. Mann, an area commander for the Forest Service brought in from Kentucky to help fight the Montana fires, said skilled firefighters were in short supply.</p>
        <p>''We can't take full advantage of the military unless we have trained and experienced people to lead them. And there aren't anywhere near enough skilled firefighters around to deal with the magnitude of these fires,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mann said staff reductions at the federal level had undercut the Forest Service's ability to deal with multiple fires in multiple locations the nation is experiencing this summer. And, he said, the worst is yet to come.</p>
        <p>''Our fire season usually doesn't start until about now or slightly later,'' said Mr. Mann, a 33-year veteran with the Forest Service. ''We're going to have to take a whole new strategy in the next 10 days if we're going to beat this thing.''</p>
        <p>That new strategy might include concentrating personnel and equipment on certain areas. ''We'll have to make some tough decisions about what fires we have a chance of stopping and which ones we've got to let burn out,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mann said the top priority would be to protect people and developed property, and institutional assets like parks and preserves. After that, he said, the choices get harder.</p>
        <p>''We may not have enough people and equipment to even protect our priorities,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
