<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revival Time in Nashville</title>
    <meta content="09WED1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D61E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="596" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revival Time in Nashville</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds Vice Pres Al Gore's groundbreaking choice of Sen Joseph I Lieberman as running mate gives his campaign needed sense of completeness and purpose</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If Al Gore wins this election, he may well look back on yesterday's boisterous gathering in Nashville as the moment the campaign became truly his own and not merely an extension of the Clinton presidency. The presence of Senator Joseph Lieberman on the rostrum, standing side by side with Mr. Gore in matching white shirtsleeves, seemed to stir both men and give the Gore campaign a jolt of energy and passion. This was partly the result of Mr. Lieberman's own boyish delight at having been chosen as Mr. Gore's running mate and his obvious relish for the political combat ahead. But the mere fact that Mr. Gore had made a groundbreaking choice was itself an important event, giving the campaign a sense of completeness and purpose it had missed.</p>
        <p>This is now Al Gore's campaign, and it could not have been an accident that President Clinton's name was not mentioned once in nearly 50 minutes of speechmaking from Mr. Gore, Mr. Lieberman and their wives. Clearly the Gore-Lieberman strategy will be to distance themselves from Mr. Clinton on the character issue while clinging to the fact that he has bequeathed them a strong economy on which to base their campaign. Mr. Lieberman, in fact, spoke glowingly of the millions of new jobs created in the last eight years and borrowed a line that the senior George Bush used to good effect in his 1988 presidential campaign: ''If you have to change horses in midstream, doesn't it make sense to get on the one that's going in the right direction?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If Al Gore wins this election, he may well look back on yesterday's boisterous gathering in Nashville as the moment the campaign became truly his own and not merely an extension of the Clinton presidency. The presence of Senator Joseph Lieberman on the rostrum, standing side by side with Mr. Gore in matching white shirtsleeves, seemed to stir both men and give the Gore campaign a jolt of energy and passion. This was partly the result of Mr. Lieberman's own boyish delight at having been chosen as Mr. Gore's running mate and his obvious relish for the political combat ahead. But the mere fact that Mr. Gore had made a groundbreaking choice was itself an important event, giving the campaign a sense of completeness and purpose it had missed.</p>
        <p>This is now Al Gore's campaign, and it could not have been an accident that President Clinton's name was not mentioned once in nearly 50 minutes of speechmaking from Mr. Gore, Mr. Lieberman and their wives. Clearly the Gore-Lieberman strategy will be to distance themselves from Mr. Clinton on the character issue while clinging to the fact that he has bequeathed them a strong economy on which to base their campaign. Mr. Lieberman, in fact, spoke glowingly of the millions of new jobs created in the last eight years and borrowed a line that the senior George Bush used to good effect in his 1988 presidential campaign: ''If you have to change horses in midstream, doesn't it make sense to get on the one that's going in the right direction?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman, the first Senate Democrat to rebuke Mr. Clinton for his behavior in the Lewinsky affair, said nothing yesterday about the president's conduct. But by his words, and references to his devout faith as an Orthodox Jew, he made clear he was ready to provide a firewall against Republican claims that only a Bush-Cheney victory could restore dignity and integrity to the White House. His wife, Hadassah, added to the sense of high purpose by describing how her parents had nearly perished in the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman seemed comfortable sharing his religious commitment in public, invoking God about a dozen times in his speech and pointedly referring to Mr. Gore as one who had ''never, never wavered in his responsibilities as a father, as a husband, and yes, as a servant of God Almighty.'' On a tactical level his affirmations of faith should help put the Democrats in a stronger competitive position with religious voters, but Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman must be careful not to let their campaign take on a theocratic tone reminiscent of the Republican alliance with the religious right.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman's presence does not, of course, guarantee Mr. Gore smooth sailing. Many liberals will not be happy with his stout defense of the insurance and pharmaceutical industries, or his support of school vouchers. Organized labor, despite the United Auto Workers' endorsement yesterday, is not happy with Mr. Lieberman's firm commitment to free trade. His legislative record will be subject to even more careful screening in the days ahead. But given his independent turn of mind and the sense of gravity and rectitude he brings to the ticket, Mr. Lieberman has gotten the attention of the Republicans and invigorated his own party as the Democrats head to their convention in Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
