<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets' O'Sullivan Has Tough Act To Follow as the Long Snapper</title>
    <meta content="09JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Sullivan, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6D71E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets' O'Sullivan Has Tough Act To Follow as the Long Snapper</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses play of long snapper Dennis O'Sullivan at New York Jets training camp; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dennis O'Sullivan was an impressionable rookie last year. The first thing he heard in the Jets' training camp was: ''Make sure the holder doesn't have to twirl the laces.''</p>
        <p>For O'Sullivan, the idea of snapping a football while an opponent was trying to knock his helmet off was hard enough. But to hike the ball with the laces facing up so that it could be spotted perfectly for the place-kicker?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dennis O'Sullivan was an impressionable rookie last year. The first thing he heard in the Jets' training camp was: ''Make sure the holder doesn't have to twirl the laces.''</p>
        <p>For O'Sullivan, the idea of snapping a football while an opponent was trying to knock his helmet off was hard enough. But to hike the ball with the laces facing up so that it could be spotted perfectly for the place-kicker?</p>
        <p>''I said, 'What are you, nuts?' '' O'Sullivan recalled today.</p>
        <p>Obviously, not. That's what it takes to be a long snapper in the National Football League.</p>
        <p>During the off-season, O'Sullivan displaced the team incumbent, John Hudson, who the Jets said never made a bad snap in four seasons -- about 600 attempts for punts, extra points and field goals.</p>
        <p>But O'Sullivan comes cheaper. He will earn $193,000 -- the minimum for a first-year player (he was on the practice squad last year). Hudson would have earned the veteran minimum of $440,000.</p>
        <p>That does not sound like much when millions are spent fielding a team.</p>
        <p>''But that much money is almost as much as your entire practice squad will earn,'' said Bill Parcells, the Jets' director of football operations. ''The entire five-man squad will cost about $300,000. You take $250,000 from here, $250,000 from there -- wherever you can get it because of the salary-cap strictures.''</p>
        <p>Hudson is back home on the farm in Paris, Tenn., snapping the ball every day and waiting for a phone call, in case O'Sullivan is injured or the youngster performs horribly Saturday night in the third preseason game, at Baltimore.</p>
        <p>O'Sullivan expects to do the job, though, which will earn him more than $1,000 a snap, about $12,000 a game.</p>
        <p>''I was just thinking today, 'Is there anything in sports similar to what I do?' '' O'Sullivan said. ''People ask me what I do, and I tell them I'm a football player, but that I'm also a long snapper. And sometimes they don't know what that means. So I tell them I'm the guy who throws the ball between his legs to the punter.''</p>
        <p>There is more to him than that, though. A graduate of Tulane, he was an intern for one summer for Gov. George Pataki. His mother, Ann, a former councilwoman from Stony Point, N.Y., is a special assistant to the governor and recently took on the added duties of working closely with Libby Pataki, the state's first lady. O'Sullivan's father, Jim, is a retired New York City police officer.</p>
        <p>''I think working in the governor's office has given me a sense that I like helping people,'' said O'Sullivan, a graduate of North Rockland High School in Rockland County, N.Y. ''I've been around politics a long time. I worked on the governor's campaign, and I've been intrigued with it.''</p>
        <p>At Tulane, he was a defensive lineman and a snapper. The Jets converted him to the offensive line. He is 6 feet 3 inches and weighs 285 pounds, and he may actually see duties other than snapping. The special teams coach, Mike Sweatman, said today that he is using O'Sullivan on the wedge on kick returns.</p>
        <p>Hudson never played when he was not snapping. Indeed, while all around him was chaos, Hudson calmly spread his legs on the sidelines and made make-believe snaps.</p>
        <p>It is unlikely O'Sullivan will see any action as an offensive lineman, though. The Jets have a very able first-string unit, and they have some depth there as well.</p>
        <p>Still, in today's two-a-day workouts in high heat and humidity, O'Sullivan worked with the offensive linemen as well as handled the snaps. Center Kevin Mawae is listed as the backup snapper, but Mawae has told the coaches that he does not want to snap the ball. O'Sullivan does most of the work.</p>
        <p>''Explode, Sully, don't extend so much,'' the line coach Bill Muir cautioned during the drills. Muir watches O'Sullivan more closely than most in trying to create an N.F.L. lineman.</p>
        <p>''I think he does a good job,'' Coach Al Groh said. ''He's a football player, that's the first thing to know about him.''</p>
        <p>O'Sullivan has had one bad snap this summer -- a high ball to punter Tom Tupa in the opening preseason game against the Saints. Tupa's punt was returned for a touchdown.</p>
        <p>O'Sullivan claimed he has forgotten about the snap. Perhaps he has.  ''He's not content to be just a snapper,'' Groh said. ''Football is still a game of toughness.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Left cornerback AARON GLENN sprained his left ankle in the morning workout. The Jets did not indicate whether it would keep him out of Saturday's game. If it does, the rookie TONY SCOTT, a sixth-round pick, might fill in. He has moved up to starting nickel back. . . . The Jets will travel to Baltimore by train, leaving Friday -- the first time since at least 1963 the team will have taken a train, according to a club spokesman. . . . Linebacker COURTNEY LEDYARD broke up a pass intended for MIKE STACK. Actually, it bounced off Ledyard's helmet. ''Way to use your head, Courtney,'' Coach AL GROH shouted. . . . Meanwhile, the top draft pick SHAUN ELLIS continues to get scolded at every opportunity by the defensive line coach, RAY HAMILTON.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
