<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Charter School Begins: Sisulu and the Gladiator</title>
    <meta content="09LESS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000825T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LESSONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7DF1F3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Charter School Begins: Sisulu and the Gladiator</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anemona Hartocollis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lessons column discusses success of Sisulu Children's Academy, public subsidized charter school in Harlem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS school districts from New York City to Dallas to Inkster, Mich., experiment with handing over the worst schools to private managers in a last-ditch effort to save them, the experience of the Sisulu Children's Academy in Harlem may offer some insight into how well this new tactic will work.</p>
        <p>Sisulu, founded by a Wall Street financier who half-jokingly compares himself to the heroic, persecuted protagonist in the movie ''Gladiator,'' opened last fall. It was one of New York City's first two charter schools (publicly subsidized yet independent), and the only one being operated with the intention of making a profit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS school districts from New York City to Dallas to Inkster, Mich., experiment with handing over the worst schools to private managers in a last-ditch effort to save them, the experience of the Sisulu Children's Academy in Harlem may offer some insight into how well this new tactic will work.</p>
        <p>Sisulu, founded by a Wall Street financier who half-jokingly compares himself to the heroic, persecuted protagonist in the movie ''Gladiator,'' opened last fall. It was one of New York City's first two charter schools (publicly subsidized yet independent), and the only one being operated with the intention of making a profit.</p>
        <p>A look back at Sisulu's first year suggests, not surprisingly, that private management is no magic bullet. Two of 12 teachers were let go during the year, and three will not have their contracts renewed next year. (Administrators point out that they were able to act decisively to remove bad teachers because there was no contract with the teachers' union.)  Sisulu went up only to second grade in its first year, so there are no test scores to compare it with other Harlem schools.</p>
        <p>If there is an obvious academic difference, at this early stage, between Sisulu and conventional public schools, it is just what one might expect from a school run by a businessman: vigilance for the bottom line and a concern for the customers -- parents and schoolchildren -- all too rarely seen in the traditional school.</p>
        <p>On the last day of school, every student at Sisulu (named for the South African apartheid foe Walter Sisulu) went home carrying a complimentary copy of one of E. D. Hirsch's ''core knowledge'' series of books. James Banks, a second grader, walked away with ''What Your Second Grader Needs to Know,'' filled with enough lessons in history, math and literature to keep him busy all summer. His mother was thrilled. The school also sent home a sort of yearbook, long obsolete in most no-frills poorer elementary schools, full of photographs of students, samples of their work and testimonial letters from parents.</p>
        <p>Most Sisulu parents sent their children to this new charter school in a search for a better education than they could find in existing public schools, and, after the first year, most believe they have found it. Of the 90 parents who responded to a school survey (250 children are enrolled), 88 said Sisulu was either ''a lot'' or ''a little'' better than the nearby public schools.</p>
        <p>''I'm very convinced that it's a good social mission,'' said Steven B. Klinsky, founder of Victory Schools, the company that manages Sisulu. ''I would like to see it get to the point where it will cover expenses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Klinsky is already wealthy from his previous life as a corporate raider and has a well-documented altruistic side: seven years ago he started an after-school program in the East New York section of Brooklyn, in memory of his brother. As the head of New Mountain Capital, a private equity firm, he certainly doesn't need to turn a profit at Sisulu to make a living. But that doesn't mean he isn't trying.</p>
        <p>Sisulu is what a loss leader might be in the retailing business, the price of penetrating the market and achieving brand-name recognition before expanding. To his frustration, Mr. Klinsky says, he hasn't made a penny of profit yet.</p>
        <p>His company is reimbursed at the annual rate of $6,000 a student, about 40 percent less than a conventional New York City public school. To collect an additional $2,700 stipend for special education, he would have to take special-ed children out of their regular class for more than half the time, which he has so far refused to do.</p>
        <p>It would also be prudent to buy, rather than lease, a building, but he has not been able to fit it into his business plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klinsky says he feels like the gladiator in the movie, who, having  to fight the emperor, does so only after defeating a series of other foes, and then while badly wounded.</p>
        <p>In the end, of course, the gladiator wins, and Mr. Klinsky could, too. In part, it's the Amazon.com principle. As the first to enter the market, he captures as much market share as he can, making it harder for newcomers to survive. Already, he has received permission to start two new charter schools on Long Island.</p>
        <p>If he's lucky, he becomes so big that the government can't get rid of him. His constituents, the parents, will defend him; he will lobby the government to change the financing formula. With so much potential power, no wonder that other major lobbying group, the United Federation of Teachers, doesn't like him.</p>
        <p>Soon he'll be going national, and his stock will soar. Unless, of course, it turns out that charter schools are even less of a magic bullet than anyone thought.</p>
        <p>LESSONS E-mail: anemona@nytimes.com</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 25, 2000, Friday  The Lessons column on Aug. 9, about the progress of the Sisulu Children's Academy, a charter school in Harlem, referred incorrectly to the business of its founder, Steven B. Klinsky. He has negotiated buyouts of corporations but is not a corporate raider who has engaged in hostile takeovers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 25, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>The Lessons column on Aug. 9, about the progress of the Sisulu Children's Academy, a charter school in Harlem, referred incorrectly to the business of its founder, Steven B. Klinsky. He has negotiated buyouts of corporations but is not a corporate raider who has engaged in hostile takeovers.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: anemona@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
