<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boom . . . Boom</title>
    <meta content="09YANK$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DE1F3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1052" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boom . . . Boom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Oakland Athletics, 4-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Justice remembers hitting the ball in the bottom of the ninth inning last night. He remembers touching second base, and the two girls happily running onto the field.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, it's a blur.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Justice remembers hitting the ball in the bottom of the ninth inning last night. He remembers touching second base, and the two girls happily running onto the field.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, it's a blur.</p>
        <p>It all happened so fast. Oakland led, 3-2, and the Athletics' closer, Jason Isringhausen, jogged in from the bullpen to pitch the Yankee ninth, and threw exactly two pitches, two fastballs.</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams hit the first for a game-tying home run, and before Williams put away his equipment, Justice launched Isringhausen's next pitch for a game-winning home run at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>It happened so fast that the first time Williams sees a replay of Justice's home run will be the first time he ever sees it.</p>
        <p>Two pitches, two home runs; this is how the Yankees stunned Oakland, 4-3, and prevented their losing streak from stretching to four games. ''I've seen back-to-back home runs,'' said Derek Jeter, the Yankees' shortstop. ''But not two pitches, bottom of the ninth, game over.''</p>
        <p>Roger Clemens was in the trainers' room at the time. Before the Yankees batted in the ninth, it appeared that all that remained of his evening was a dunk of his arm in stinging ice water, and glum thoughts.</p>
        <p>He had pitched well for seven innings, but he allowed a freakish inside-the-park two-run homer in the fifth when Eric Chavez's drive hit the top of the center-field wall, bounced high into the air and away from Williams. Clemens allowed a conventional home run to Ramon Hernandez, the next batter. Back-to-back bombs, and Oakland led, 3-1.</p>
        <p>The Yankee hitters could do nothing against Barry Zito, the Oakland starter, a young left-hander who seems destined for great things. He has a prominent birthmark on his left wrist, and when he was young, he asked his mother why it was there. Because your left hand is going to be special, she replied, and his mother was right.</p>
        <p>Zito is one of the few left-handers who throws a true curveball, and he really confused the Yankees' hitters, mixing it with a changeup and a good fastball as he allowed just two hits over the first six innings. He was relieved by Jim Mecir in the seventh, after Justice singled home the Yankees' second run, and the Yankees loaded the bases with one out.</p>
        <p>Scott Brosius struck out, Luis Sojo was due to bat and a hulking and familiar figure emerged from the Yankees' dugout to pinch-hit: Jose Canseco. The crowd roared, the reflections of flashbulbs flickered on the broad back of his jersey, and Canseco deliberately donned his protective equipment before taking two massive practice swings.</p>
        <p>On a 2-1 pitch, Mecir jammed Canseco with a fastball, Canseco swung, the head of his bat flew about 120 feet in foul territory on the third base side, while the ball flared harmlessly to right, an inning ending pop-out.</p>
        <p>But Oakland flubbed a couple of scoring chances in the eighth and ninth, and the Yankees were still down a run in the bottom of the ninth, when Isringhausen appeared. He has 25 saves, on the power of his fastball and the sharpness of his breaking ball. He throws gas, Justice said later, with respect.</p>
        <p>Williams walked to the plate, looking for that fastball. Isringhausen threw it, and later, Williams used both hands to describe the placement of the pitch: right over the middle of the plate, square in the middle of the strike zone.</p>
        <p>''Like a bull's-eye,'' Williams said.</p>
        <p>He made imperfect contact, the ball soaring high to right field -- but there was no doubt he had hit it far enough to carry beyond the right-field wall. Williams bounced around the bases, jogging on his toes, like a sprinter. The Yankee players rushed to the front of the dugout to greet him. Justice waited at home plate.</p>
        <p>As Williams descended into the dugout, the crowd was roaring, and Justice prepared to step into the batter's box. He was ready to hit, but his name had not been announced over the public address system. He turned and asked Dana DeMuth, the home plate umpire, if he could hit, and DeMuth waved him to the plate.</p>
        <p>Behind him, Williams was accepting congratulations from teammates. Clemens had jumped off a trainers' table, raising his right arm out of the bucket of ice. Don Zimmer, the Yankees' bench coach, turned to Manager Joe Torre and said, ''Just two pitches, that's it.''</p>
        <p>He was speaking hopefully, of course; it was an idle wish. Two home runs on two pitches. No one could remember seeing that before.</p>
        <p>Justice was looking for a fastball to drive. Isringhausen threw a fastball, Justice's right foot flicked forward and he whipped the bat through the strike zone. Williams's head was down in the dugout, for he was putting his helmet away, and he turned in time to see the ball zooming over the infield.</p>
        <p>There was no question, Justice said later, that the ball was going to go over the head of the center fielder. The only question was whether it would get high enough, for Justice had hit the ball so hard.</p>
        <p>''That might've been the hardest he's hit a ball since he's been here,'' Torre said of the outfielder obtained from Cleveland in late June.</p>
        <p>Terrence Long, the Oakland center fielder, took a couple of steps toward the wall, stopped and watched Justice's 30th home run land among the fans.</p>
        <p>Justice rounded second. The two girls jumped out of the stands and ran into left field. Clemens yelled and screamed. The loge section of Yankee Stadium quivered, literally. Justice crossed home plate and was pounded on top of the helmet by teammates, until he spun away, laughing.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
