<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Politics of Adulthood</title>
    <meta content="09PURD$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Jedediah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DC1E3CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Politics of Adulthood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jedediah Purdy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Jedediah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jedediah Purdy Op-Ed article holds American desire to grow up is theme of presidential race; drawing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>America wants to grow up. Underneath the barbs and platitudes, that is the theme of this presidential campaign. Maybe it came out of polls. But probably not. It has the ring of an unexpected truth, the kind of thing a speechwriter, or even a candidate, sometimes intuits and finds a way to express.</p>
        <p>The theme got under way with Bill Bradley's candidacy, which was about the idea that a prosperous America could afford to pursue higher goals through politics. Mr. Bradley proposed that self-interest left people cold in the end, and that economically comfortable voters were looking for ways to reduce poverty, create equality of opportunity and address racial division. We'd had our good times, and now was the time to act like adults.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>America wants to grow up. Underneath the barbs and platitudes, that is the theme of this presidential campaign. Maybe it came out of polls. But probably not. It has the ring of an unexpected truth, the kind of thing a speechwriter, or even a candidate, sometimes intuits and finds a way to express.</p>
        <p>The theme got under way with Bill Bradley's candidacy, which was about the idea that a prosperous America could afford to pursue higher goals through politics. Mr. Bradley proposed that self-interest left people cold in the end, and that economically comfortable voters were looking for ways to reduce poverty, create equality of opportunity and address racial division. We'd had our good times, and now was the time to act like adults.</p>
        <p>The growing-up issue survived the Bradley campaign. Karenna Gore Schiff, a visible spokeswoman for her father, has made her trademark a call to her peers to surrender their ''ironic detachment,'' the emblematic adolescent attitude, and dare to get passionate about presidential politics. Worldly wise indifference can be fun for a while, but no one knows better than a recent Harvard graduate, like Ms. Gore, that it's kid stuff.</p>
        <p>George W. Bush has defused questions about his own maturity by appearing front and center in the campaign for national adulthood. His acceptance speech at the Republican  Convention took over Mr. Bradley's theme wholesale. Governor Bush, who by several accounts finished his adolescence some 20 years after many of his peers, couched his ''prosperity with a purpose'' theme in an exhortation to his generation to prove itself, to ''reclaim some essential values, to show we have grown up before we grew old.''</p>
        <p>His generation ''tested limits'' in its youth, he said, but is now coming to ''a responsibility era.'' That phrase animated the final minutes of Mr. Bush's speech and captured his idea that individuals, religious organizations, corporations and presidents must temper their appetites and self-interest with a sense of duty to children, neighbors, the needy, the nation, the natural world. Everyone must begin acting like a grown-up.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Gore seemed to answer Mr. Bush's challenge by naming a running mate who is more associated with positions of moral responsibility than almost any other politician today. In fact, if there has been a criticism of Senator Joseph Lieberman this week, it is that he becomes sanctimonious about higher purposes.</p>
        <p>The politics of adulthood is resonant for more than one reason. The most obvious is the adolescent behavior of the Clinton administration. These eight years have seen undisciplined appetites, ceaseless experiments with looks and attitudes, and a desperation to please that sometimes reverses itself into towering arrogance. People learn to expect these irritations from their children, but not from their leaders.</p>
        <p>A deeper reason is the widespread perception that, indeed, prosperity is not enough. People who have provided for themselves and their families are looking for ways to contribute to larger communities, to give back and to put new meaning in their work. Others are noticing that, as the country's wealth increases, its inequalities grow more stark and unsettling. People worry that ''They got rich and threw a lot of parties'' is not history's highest benediction.</p>
        <p>Many young voters take personal maturity and responsibility seriously. Children of divorce, now coming to adulthood in force, object to both hasty marriages and self-indulgent departures. Even anti-sweatshop activists and youthful union organizers read up on personal investment and build accounts for retirement, their children's education, or just security.  Thirty years ago this would have seemed premature middle age. Today it has become common-sense behavior. It is always reassuring to hear politicians echo common sense.</p>
        <p>Yet there is a risk for candidates in too loudly enunciating the politics of adulthood. Personal responsibility is as desirable in citizens and leaders as in friends and family. But the main work of politics is not to produce virtue, and personal virtue does not of itself produce good politics. Saying that corporations must be ''responsible to leave the air and waters clean,'' as Mr. Bush did in his acceptance speech, is a reason to pass strong and efficient environmental laws, not a substitute for them.</p>
        <p>Politics matters because government enables us to do things together that none of us could do alone: protect the environment, keep the workplace safe, guard public health, and address poverty and inequality on a national scale. Leading decent, successful lives may not, by itself, make a good society.</p>
        <p>That is precisely why so many people now feel that prosperity is not enough. When politicians only urge us to lead better lives, and promise to do the same themselves, they may end up amplifying the discontent that they set out to solve.</p>
        <p>Jedediah Purdy, a student at Yale Law School, is the author of ''For Common Things: Irony, Trust and Commitment in America Today.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jedediah Purdy, a student at Yale Law School, is the author of ''For Common Things: Irony, Trust and Commitment in America Today.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
