<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yogurt This Is Not</title>
    <meta content="09MYJO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MY JOB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yoga</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">England, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mohn, Tonya</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Yoga</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE5DB103CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yogurt This Is Not</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ENGLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">England, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack England describes job as yoga instructor in Port St Lucie, Fla; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I teach every day, seven days a week. I'm on stage three or four nights a week in different shows. I do things that 16-year-old girls can't do. I didn't start yoga until I was about 50, and I'm 79 now.</p>
        <p>Some people are frightened by the word yoga. They think I'm going to twist their mind or something. We don't do the meditation here; we do the physical aspects of yoga. Stretching is something that you can do all your life -- in your 70's, 80's and 90's. There's no bouncing, no jumping. When you stretch, your veins and arteries become more elastic, improving your circulation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I teach every day, seven days a week. I'm on stage three or four nights a week in different shows. I do things that 16-year-old girls can't do. I didn't start yoga until I was about 50, and I'm 79 now.</p>
        <p>Some people are frightened by the word yoga. They think I'm going to twist their mind or something. We don't do the meditation here; we do the physical aspects of yoga. Stretching is something that you can do all your life -- in your 70's, 80's and 90's. There's no bouncing, no jumping. When you stretch, your veins and arteries become more elastic, improving your circulation.</p>
        <p>I remember I was warming up once in one of the conference rooms here and I saw some people go by. I brought one leg straight up over my head and touched the wall behind me, parallel to my ear, and I heard the child say to her mother: ''Look. That man has only one leg.''</p>
        <p>And that exercise is really so simple. Some of the stuff I do is even more surprising to people. I've got a board that I made so I can get up on a headstand in a water ski show I'm in on Monday afternoons. As we go past the audience, I'm in a shoulder stand. Then I come into splits, then lotus up and down. I'm down in a wake so you don't see my head. The announcer is saying, ''He is now holding his breath for 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 minutes.'' Of course, I'm breathing all the time, but you can't see that 'cause you can't see my head.</p>
        <p>During the Korean War, I was shot down and I fractured my back, so I lost a year out of my life in the hospital. As a result of physical therapy, I became more conscious of my body, so somebody took me to a yoga class one day. I didn't know yoga from yogurt. But I worked on these various different aspects of flexibility, and it just got easier and easier. It changed my life.</p>
        <p>I retired after 44 years as an electronic engineer with the Department of Defense and started traveling around the world going to different health spas and yoga ashrams, getting ideas for something that I would like to own, and I dropped in at Club Med Ixtapa, in Mexico. I put on a yoga demonstration, and they asked me to stay. That was 16 years ago.</p>
        <p>Most disease is stress-related. It's usually the damn job or the boss. Learn how to calm yourself down, breathe abdominally like a baby in a crib. When you suck in that stomach all the time, that's creating tension and stress.</p>
        <p>When men have their first heart attacks and survive, they go off to a health spa, and for the first times ever they eat the right food. All of a sudden they get their bodies back to their skinny high-school weight, and they get one more chance to get it right.</p>
        <p>I once said to a woman, ''Keep your husband thin and you will keep him longer.'' She whispered in my ear, ''I don't want to keep him any longer.'' The world is filled with widows. Just load your husband up with eggs and red meat, keep him smoking and you can finish him off before he reaches 50!</p>
        <p>MY JOB Written with Tanya Mohn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Written with Tanya Mohn.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
