<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Out of a Pit, the Essence of Almond</title>
    <meta content="09PITS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apricots</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1D9113CF93AA3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Out of a Pit, the Essence of Almond</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on cooking with apricot pits; recipes; drawing (M)5</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is the perfect dessert for someone who likes to fool guests. It looks like ordinary ice cream, the color of butter, with the flavor of almonds.</p>
        <p>But not regular almonds. Almonds that could have come from a faraway place or an unusual variety of tree. You can keep them guessing forever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is the perfect dessert for someone who likes to fool guests. It looks like ordinary ice cream, the color of butter, with the flavor of almonds.</p>
        <p>But not regular almonds. Almonds that could have come from a faraway place or an unusual variety of tree. You can keep them guessing forever.</p>
        <p>If they come up with the correct answer, have them pick your lottery numbers, too.</p>
        <p>The secret is apricot pits.</p>
        <p>The pits of apricots, nectarines, peaches and plums all contain a kernel that tastes astonishingly like an almond. Not a sweet almond, but one with a rounded nutty flavor that ends bitter. And they can be used in ways other nuts cannot.</p>
        <p>I first had the ice cream at Blue Hill in Greenwich Village. The chefs, Dan Barber and Alex Urena, got the idea from Pierre Reboul, pastry chef at Vong in Midtown. Their version is milky and light. Mr. Reboul's is custardy. Both are unforgettable.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reboul tried it after recalling how a single kernel gave his mother's apricot jam a perceptible scent when he was a child in France. Infusing cream, milk and eggs with kernels brought out the flavor even more.</p>
        <p>Lindsey Remolif Shere, a former pastry chef at Chez Panisse in Berkeley, Calif., tried the same thing with ice cream more than 15 years ago. She knew that apricot pits flavored Italian amaretti and creme de noyaux, a liqueur that takes its name from the French word for fruit stones. She added the kernels to canned apricots and substituted them for almonds in cookies.</p>
        <p>Ms. Shere cracks the pits with a nutcracker to retrieve the seeds, which she then toasts lightly and crushes with a mortar and pestle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reboul crushes the stones with their seeds in a heavy-duty food processor, then puts everything into the milk and cream infusion, straining out the fragments before churning. All these techniques work (smashing with a hammer is fun), but crushing makes the infusion stronger. Toasting the kernels deepens the flavor.</p>
        <p>At Vong, the apricot pit ice cream is called bitter almond ice cream so customers are not wary. Fruit pits contain cyanide.</p>
        <p>''It's the plant's way of protecting its young, making the seeds poisonous to animals, so the animals don't choose it as a tasty snack,'' said Shirley O. Corriher, a biochemist and the author of ''Cookwise'' (William Morrow, 1997). But she said that using the kernels as an aromatic is much less risky, and that it would take a lot of kernels to harm an adult. (A derivative of bitter apricot kernels called laetrile was actually once touted as a curative for cancer, but was proved useless.)</p>
        <p>Apricot pit ice cream is not a flavor children would appreciate. It is best served in small amounts. The ice cream is powerful but one-dimensional and comes to life only with other flavors. Ms. Shere serves it with lemon ice cream, berries, fruit pies and chocolate or caramel desserts.</p>
        <p>The recipe seems ridiculous at first. It calls for about 45 apricots. But you can mix apricot pits with those from plums, nectarines and peaches. And you can save them in the refrigerator or freezer until you have enough.</p>
        <p>Just be sure to taste as you cook: seeds vary widely in strength. Ms. Shere said that when substituting fruit kernels for almonds in a recipe, she usually uses one-eighth the volume of the almonds. But when I tried her recipe for biscotti, half the volume was just enough.</p>
        <p>''If you have a good almond extract,'' Ms. Shere said, ''you get that flavor, but you don't get any of the roundness of flavor that you get from the pits themselves, because with them you get a nutlike flavor.''</p>
        <p>It is a subtle difference. But one worth cracking 45 pits to discover.</p>
        <p>APRICOT PIT ICE CREAM  Adapted from Vong  Time: 45 minutes, plus overnight chilling and churning time</p>
        <p>45 to 50 apricot pits (4 1/2 ounces)  2 cups milk  1 1/2 cups heavy cream</p>
        <p>1/4 cup plus 3 tablespoons sugar  7 egg yolks.</p>
        <p>1. Wrap apricot pits in a heavy dish towel. On the floor or on a sturdy cutting board, crack pits open using a hammer or a meat mallet, exposing kernels. Watch your fingers.</p>
        <p>2. In a medium saucepan, combine apricot kernels and shells with milk and heavy cream. Bring to a boil; turn off heat, and let cool. Chill overnight in refrigerator.</p>
        <p>3. The next day, bring the milk mixture to a boil again and strain through a fine sieve. Meanwhile, in a large bowl, whisk together the sugar and the yolks until light and fluffy. Whisk about  1/2 cup hot milk into the egg mixture, and then whisk the egg mixture into the milk. Pour into a large saucepan, place over medium-low heat and, stirring constantly with a wooden spoon, cook until thick enough to coat the back of the spoon. Remove from heat immediately. Let cool, and then strain.</p>
        <p>4. Pour into an ice cream maker, and follow manufacturer's instructions.</p>
        <p>Yield: one quart.</p>
        <p>AUNT VICTORIA'S BISCOTTI  Adapted from ''Chez Panisse Desserts,'' by Lindsey Remolif Shere (Random House, 1994)  Time: about an hour</p>
        <p>1 ounce (about  1/4 cup) apricot, peach or nectarine kernels (from about 40 pits, cracked open with a hammer; discard pit shells)</p>
        <p>1/2 cup unsalted butter</p>
        <p>3/4 cup sugar  2 eggs  1 tablespoon plus 1 teaspoon grappa  1 teaspoon anise extract  1 teaspoon aniseed  2 cups plus 2 tablespoons flour  1 1/2 teaspoons baking powder</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon salt.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Place kernels on a baking sheet, and toast in oven until they smell nutty, about 5 minutes. Remove from oven, and let cool. Chop finely.</p>
        <p>2. In bowl of a mixer fitted with a paddle, cream butter until fluffy. Add sugar, and cream again until fluffy. Beat in eggs until mixture is smooth. Beat in grappa, anise extract and aniseed. In another bowl, mix flour, baking powder and salt. Beat them in just until mixed. Stir in chopped kernels.</p>
        <p>3. Lower oven temperature to 325. Set an oven rack in upper third of oven. On a lightly floured board, make rolls of dough an inch or so thick and the length of your baking sheet. Set them on the sheet 2 inches apart, and bake on the oven rack until they are set and lightly browned on top, about 25 minutes. Cool rolls on a rack 5 minutes, and slice diagonally  1/2 inch thick.</p>
        <p>4. Lay slices back on baking sheet, and return to 325-degree oven for 5 minutes to dry them. Turn slices, and dry 5 minutes more. Cool on a rack, and store in a tightly covered container. The flavor improves if cookies are stored a few days.</p>
        <p>Yield: about 4 1/2 dozen cookies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
