<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coast Guard Choreographs Harbor's Biggest Gathering</title>
    <meta content="03SAIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fort Wadsworth (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opsail 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York Harbor</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coast Guard (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EED81239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coast Guard Choreographs Harbor's Biggest Gathering</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coast Guard team at Fort Wadsworth on Staten Island carefully choreographs gathering of ships for OpSail 2000 in New York Harbor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Precisely at 11 a.m. Saturday, the  Nassau, an amphibious-helicopter carrier, passed under the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge into Upper New York Bay. The ship was headed for its turn at the diesel ballet, a maneuver in which four tugboats nudge their hulking gray partner into its appointed anchorage southwest of Red Hook, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>The low-slung black tugs, engines thrumming and wakes bulging, pushed and spun the 820-feet-long ship against a light breeze and tide until it could tie down, one link at a time, to four buoys, completing a procedure called a four-point mooring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Precisely at 11 a.m. Saturday, the  Nassau, an amphibious-helicopter carrier, passed under the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge into Upper New York Bay. The ship was headed for its turn at the diesel ballet, a maneuver in which four tugboats nudge their hulking gray partner into its appointed anchorage southwest of Red Hook, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>The low-slung black tugs, engines thrumming and wakes bulging, pushed and spun the 820-feet-long ship against a light breeze and tide until it could tie down, one link at a time, to four buoys, completing a procedure called a four-point mooring.</p>
        <p>The routine was repeated again yesterday with the aircraft carrier John F. Kennedy, 990 feet long, and the Mount Whitney, a 620-feet-long command and control ship. The procedures, particularly with such enormous ships in congested tidal waters, required a degree of choreographic precision that makes young deck officers pace.</p>
        <p>Far from this action, in a small room at Fort Wadsworth on Staten Island, a team of Coast Guard men and women paced as well, observing the maneuvers on television monitors and radar screens. After years of Coast Guard preparation, the harbor traffic for OpSail 2000 had begun, and the people in the Vessel Traffic Center, as the room is known, were in the early stages of the most demanding test in the center's history.</p>
        <p>The Vessel Traffic Center is one of four major command posts in place for the OpSail celebrations on Independence Day. Others will be at the command and control center inside 1 Police Plaza, the City Office of Emergency Management's so-called bunker on the 23rd floor of 7 World Trade Center and a temporary Navy center on Pier 94 on the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Of all these command posts, the Coast Guard's is the only one that functions at full strength all year, every hour. It is the maritime counterpart of an airport air traffic control tower, a place from which the comings and goings of all vessels in the Port of New York are assisted, supervised and meticulously recorded. It monitors harbor traffic by remote radar and live television cameras mounted along the waterways, and keeps in touch with each vessel by VHF radio or cellular phone.</p>
        <p>The center's core purpose is to prevent nautical disasters like the Exxon Valdez spill in Alaska in 1989 or the most notorious case in recent decades in New York, the crash of a container ship, Sea Witch, with the oil tanker Esso Brussels.</p>
        <p>The Sea Witch struck the tanker at night in the Narrows and the two ships locked together, creating a drifting inferno that eventually grounded in Gravesend Bay, Brooklyn. The collision occurred in 1973, before the port's Vessel Traffic Center opened.</p>
        <p>The center was first used in 1976, and during the OpSail events of the next few days, it will try to maintain order over what is expected to be the largest number of ships and boats ever to gather in New York.</p>
        <p>On a typical day, the operators help about 750 port crossings by large vessels, serving as a sort of information clearinghouse on events in the port. But that's a typical day. As the OpSail celebration gains momentum, the Coast Guard expects to see something unprecedented.</p>
        <p>Thirty more naval vessels are to pass through the Narrows today, a number of tall sailing ships will also be making their way into Upper New York Bay today, and all these vessels will be converging tomorrow with hundreds of security vessels and tens of thousands of pleasure craft.</p>
        <p>Taken together, the radar signatures of the pleasure craft -- tiny white blips -- will overwhelm the center's radar monitors with a solid field of interference. ''You'll have virtually complete whiteout,'' said Lt. Cmdr. Christopher Nichols, the Vessel Traffic Center's supervisor.</p>
        <p>To help maintain order, the Coast Guard will complement the center with a strong presence on the water: more than 200 boats or cutters, supervised by a command ship, the buoy tender Willow, anchored just south of Governors Island. The Vessel Traffic Center will also receive a video transmission from a blimp.</p>
        <p>The Coast Guard also hopes that routine port traffic -- the container ships, oil tankers and fuel barges -- will stay away until the celebrations end. It has issued a 24-hour restriction against commercial traffic, beginning at 6 a.m. tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Inside the center on Saturday, three operators peered at the radar screens for a finely detailed overview of more than 40 nautical square miles, an area that includes New York City, Perth Amboy, Newark and Elizabethport, and extends from Sandy Hook, N.J., to the Throgs Neck Bridge on the East River and to the Holland Tunnel ventilators on the lower Hudson.</p>
        <p>On the screens, the outline of each segment of waterway glowed brightly. The water showed up as black. Each of the dozens of vessels traveling through the port was illuminated by its own computerized icon, which, with a click, revealed the vessel's course, speed and destination.</p>
        <p>The operators passed along all manner of nautical information in quick, dispassionate bits: floating debris in this channel, proceed with care; two vessels approaching Hell Gate, both will wait for you to pass; and on and on.</p>
        <p>Although similar to an air traffic control tower, the Vessel Traffic Center has a crucial difference: it cannot ordinarily tell vessels what to do. Ultimate responsibility for a ship and its actions rests with each skipper and crew.</p>
        <p>As the Nassau wheeled slowly in the bay outside, Petty Officer First Class Matthew Starace watched the screens closely. He was midway through a 12-hour shift, simultaneously monitoring and talking with 13 ships and tugs traversing the East River, as well as 9 more at anchor.</p>
        <p>By tomorrow, his clean screen will be a mass of white. Talking to a tug-and-barge as it approached Hell Gate, he spoke into his headset with the practiced composure of a mortician. It was a tone of voice, Coast Guard officials say, they hope continues through OpSail.</p>
        <p>''One of the secrets of this job,'' Petty Officer Starace said between conversations with skippers out on the harbor, ''is just staying calm.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
