<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Media Talk; NBC Official Rebuked for Lack of 'Reality'</title>
    <meta content="03NBC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000704T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cbs Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sassa, Scott M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Welch, John F Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Who Wants to Be A Millionaire (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Survivor (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1DF1239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Media Talk; NBC Official Rebuked for Lack of 'Reality'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NBC denies speculation that Scott Sassa may be fired as president of its West Coast division in wake of criticism he received from John F Welch, chairman of General Electric, NBC's parent, for not following CBS and ABC into the hot programming trend of reality shows like Who Wants to Be a Millionaire and Survivor; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is Scott Sassa, the president of NBC's West Coast division, in so much trouble with the network's management that he is about to be fired?</p>
        <p>Not at all, say a wide range of senior NBC executives. The officials were put on the defensive last week when The New York Post published an article saying that John F. Welch Jr., the chairman of General Electric, NBC's parent, had criticized Mr. Sassa during a tense senior management meeting last Tuesday. The article said that Mr. Sassa would be out in a matter of days. Dismissing the threat to Mr. Sassa, Kassie Canter, the corporate spokeswoman for the network said, ''The Post dredged up a six-week-old rumor.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is Scott Sassa, the president of NBC's West Coast division, in so much trouble with the network's management that he is about to be fired?</p>
        <p>Not at all, say a wide range of senior NBC executives. The officials were put on the defensive last week when The New York Post published an article saying that John F. Welch Jr., the chairman of General Electric, NBC's parent, had criticized Mr. Sassa during a tense senior management meeting last Tuesday. The article said that Mr. Sassa would be out in a matter of days. Dismissing the threat to Mr. Sassa, Kassie Canter, the corporate spokeswoman for the network said, ''The Post dredged up a six-week-old rumor.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Hollywood had been rife with rumors for many weeks of Mr. Sassa's imminent departure -- always steadfastly and authoritatively denied by NBC executives.</p>
        <p>But The Post report had its biggest fact right. NBC did have an executive meeting last week, and Mr. Welch did have occasion to ''beat up'' Mr. Sassa, as one executive put it, as well as some other NBC division heads.</p>
        <p>Mr. Welch was unhappy with the entertainment division that Mr. Sassa directs for not following the lead of ABC and CBS into the hot programming trend of reality shows like ''Who Wants To Be a Millionaire'' and ''Survivor.''</p>
        <p>NBC's president, Bob Wright, had already expressed dissatisfaction with the division's reluctance to enter the reality race. Last December, just after ''Millionaire'' emerged as a force that would overwhelm prime time, Mr. Wright was voicing concern about a then-obscure show CBS had purchased called ''Survivor.''</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Wright's anxiety, NBC still did nothing to try to buy the rights to myriad other reality formats being offered to the networks. NBC's entertainment executives have said they had no special budget to buy summer programs, making it impossible to get in on the intense bidding for shows like ''Big Brother,'' for which CBS paid $20 million and which makes its debut on Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>But one senior NBC executive said, ''That didn't mean they couldn't get 'The Mole'. '' That reality show, set for January, was snapped up by ABC. Mr. Welch also expressed concern in last week's meeting because NBC seemed to have few promising shows lined up to take advantage of the upcoming promotional platform of the Summer Olympics in September. NBC's coming fall series have not received strong advance notices.</p>
        <p>So while reports of Mr. Sassa's shaky status may have been the product of some nasty efforts to undermine him, the pressure on him is only going to increase. ''We know the fall season is crucial,'' one senior NBC entertainment division executive said. ''If we don't have a hit or two, things could get really ugly in October.''</p>
        <p>BILL CARTER</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 4, 2000, Tuesday  An article in Business Day yesterday about criticism within NBC of the performance of Scott Sassa, president of the NBC television network's West Coast division, imprecisely summarized a portion of an article in The New York Post about him last Friday. The Post article cited an unidentified person as saying that Mr. Sassa might leave his job within days, and it quoted an NBC spokeswoman as denying reports that Mr. Sassa had been asked to resign. The Post article did not say conclusively that Mr. Sassa would be out of his job within days.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 4, 2000, Tuesday  An article in Business Day yesterday about criticism within NBC of the performance of Scott Sassa, president of the NBC television network's West Coast division, imprecisely summarized a portion of an article in The New York Post about him last Friday. The Post article cited an unidentified person as saying that Mr. Sassa might leave his job within days, and it quoted an NBC spokeswoman as denying reports that Mr. Sassa had been asked to resign. The Post article did not say conclusively that Mr. Sassa would be out of his job within days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 4, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about criticism within NBC of the performance of Scott Sassa, president of the NBC television network's West Coast division, imprecisely summarized a portion of an article in The New York Post about him last Friday. The Post article cited an unidentified person as saying that Mr. Sassa might leave his job within days, and it quoted an NBC spokeswoman as denying reports that Mr. Sassa had been asked to resign. The Post article did not say conclusively that Mr. Sassa would be out of his job within days.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>Correction: July 4, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day yesterday about criticism within NBC of the performance of Scott Sassa, president of the NBC television network's West Coast division, imprecisely summarized a portion of an article in The New York Post about him last Friday. The Post article cited an unidentified person as saying that Mr. Sassa might leave his job within days, and it quoted an NBC spokeswoman as denying reports that Mr. Sassa had been asked to resign. The Post article did not say conclusively that Mr. Sassa would be out of his job within days.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
