<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Computers Idle in Class, Training for Teachers Becomes Priority</title>
    <meta content="03COMP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harmon, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0D91239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Computers Idle in Class, Training for Teachers Becomes Priority</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY HARMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harmon, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City public school teachers attend Introduction to the Internet course at Queens school to learn how to put computer tools to good use in their classrooms; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The teachers who gathered on Thursday in Room 313 at Public School 122 in Astoria, Queens, for the first day of a workshop called Introduction to the Internet were model students. They studied their list of vocabulary terms like ''home page'' and ''modem.'' They raised their hands. And when the workshop leader asked a question, they tried to answer:</p>
        <p>''How do we get from one place to another on the Internet?'' queried Doreen Rose, a technology specialist for the Board of Education.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The teachers who gathered on Thursday in Room 313 at Public School 122 in Astoria, Queens, for the first day of a workshop called Introduction to the Internet were model students. They studied their list of vocabulary terms like ''home page'' and ''modem.'' They raised their hands. And when the workshop leader asked a question, they tried to answer:</p>
        <p>''How do we get from one place to another on the Internet?'' queried Doreen Rose, a technology specialist for the Board of Education.</p>
        <p>''With a mouse?'' ventured one elementary school teacher.</p>
        <p>''Clicking?'' suggested another.</p>
        <p>The correct answer was ''hypertext links,'' and if some fidgeting occurred during the subsequent explanation, Ms. Rose was not inclined to send anyone to the principal. It was, after all, their first day of summer vacation.</p>
        <p>While the Clinton administration praises the growing number of wired schools and computer classrooms, many teachers say they are frustrated by their own inability to put their new tools to good use. And with scant time given to training in the school year, thousands of educators around the country are using their time off this summer to confront what they identify as their greatest deficiency: technology literacy.</p>
        <p>''How do I work with the kids when I don't have the background myself?'' said Lorraine Attias, a fifth-grade teacher in Astoria who regarded the four computers that appeared in her classroom last year with a mixture of fear and longing. ''A year ago I knew nothing.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Attias has since taken several courses with Ms. Rose, for which she gets credits toward a salary increase, and her class now uses computer software to produce a monthly newsletter. But some educators say the smattering of official training combined with voluntary seminars is not enough to ensure that the promise of applying information technology to learning -- and the billions spent on it so far -- will be realized.</p>
        <p>''We are seeing lots of schools where they have the equipment, and very frequently it's either underused or not used at all,'' said Vicki Rafel, a vice president of the National PTA. ''We see it in the rural areas and inner cities but also in the suburbs.''</p>
        <p>That, it seems, is largely because teachers do not know what to do with it. A study last year by Market Data Retrieval, an educational research company, found that 61 percent of the elementary and secondary teachers surveyed felt either ''not at all prepared'' or only ''somewhat prepared'' to integrate technology into classroom instruction.</p>
        <p>According to the report, which recorded 1,576 responses to a questionnaire mailed to 9,000 elementary and secondary school teachers, those who had received 11 or more hours of technology training over the previous year were far more likely to use technology in the classroom than teachers who had received less. About one-fourth of the teachers said they had received no technology training during the previous year. The average number of hours of instruction was five.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Clinton administration awarded $75 million in grants to teachers' colleges and other institutions to train new teachers in technology. And Linda Roberts, the director of the Office of Education Technology for the United States Department of Education, said that as the teaching work force turned over, there would be a natural rise in the level of technology proficiency.</p>
        <p>''The younger teachers that are coming into our schools have already grown up with the technology,'' Ms. Roberts said. ''They seem to be able to more quickly appropriate it and find applications that can support their teaching in the classroom.''</p>
        <p>But as the three million teachers in the nation's public schools seek to assimilate the alien machines materializing in their classrooms, there is also a mounting debate about how, what or whether to teach the teachers. If teachers are by and large going to have to spend their own time learning how to use computers, they are going to have to first believe that doing so is a worthwhile endeavor. Not all are convinced.</p>
        <p>''Computers do not change the thinking process,'' said Claire Dusek, a history teacher at El Dorado High School, east of Sacramento, who is the recipient of a technology grant under California's ''digital high school'' program. She sees the primary value of teaching technology as pragmatic: to get jobs when they graduate, her students need to know how to use programs like PowerPoint, Microsoft's program for business presentations.</p>
        <p>Still, Ms. Dusek said she planned to spend time this summer reviewing notes from the technology training sessions she had taken during the year. ''There's just not much time to learn,'' she said, ''and it's hitting us straight between the eyes.''</p>
        <p>For some, it may simply be a question of conquering their own pride. ''It's intimidating,'' said Michelle Finnegan, who is preparing this summer to teach for the first time in a wired school next year, Springfield Gardens High School in Queens. ''We're teachers, so we're supposed to know what we're doing. With this, we don't.''</p>
        <p>Sylvia Spaine, a seventh-grade Spanish teacher at I.S. 126 in Astoria, who let the four computers in her classroom stand idle all of last year, agreed. ''You have to be ready to learn,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Often, students know more than their teachers when it comes to computers. The key, said Ms. Attias of Astoria, is to let them help. ''A lot of times I'll say, 'Oh my God, what did I do?' and they'll say, 'You have to do this,' '' she said. ''I'm not embarrassed by it.''</p>
        <p>But Barbara Radecki, a fifth-grade teacher in Coolidge, Ariz., said  some teachers in her rural district had chosen not to apply for a grant that would have given them computers and training. ''What has concerned me is the teachers at my school who are threatened by it so they don't want to do it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Radecki spent the previous week in a program run by the Intel Corporation, which has announced plans to spend $35 million over the next three years to train 500 ''master teachers'' in the United States, each of whom will go back to their district and train 20 others. Although the master teachers get a stipend, their trainees are not paid. Instead, they get software donated by Microsoft.</p>
        <p>The Intel program is intended to help teachers recognize how the Internet has affected traditional teaching. In the fifth grade, for instance,  reports about states have become as simple as a visit to a Web site like www.50states.com, where the given bird, flag and capital can be copied and pasted in about five minutes. The Intel program also addresses concerns about pornography and how to steer children away from offensive sites.</p>
        <p>''What we need to do now is not just be information gatherers but interpret, think about it in a different way,'' said Judi Yost, a senior trainer for the Institute of Computer Technology, a nonprofit educational organization that designed the curriculum for Intel. ''Maybe we compare two states. Maybe you are a company deciding what state to be based in and you need to research three states and explain why you chose one.''</p>
        <p>But the real motivation for computer novices or technology skeptics to seek out training usually comes from their students' unfettered enthusiasm for most anything having to do with technology.</p>
        <p>''The kids love it,'' said Cayce Byman, a third-grade teacher at Kramer Elementary School in Dallas who attended a three-day class sponsored by her school district last week on how to use a digital camera, and who plans to take other technology courses this summer. ''The thing is, they all learn differently. Not all of them understand when I write something on the board, or put in a video. This gives them a new way to absorb information.''</p>
        <p>Yet with 95 percent of schools now connected to the Internet and the Clinton administration requesting $933 million for technology investment in schools in the 2001 budget, some educators fear that the scope of teacher training is being viewed far too narrowly.</p>
        <p>''It's the teaching practice that needs to be considered, not just computer instruction,'' said Phillip Davies, infrastructure manager for the Center for Collaborative Education, a nonprofit group that has wired 40 New York public schools and set up dozens of classrooms with computers, only to see them go unused. ''Mostly,'' Mr. Davies said, ''they just sit in the corner.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
