<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 24, a Political Veteran, Vacuum Cleaner to Platform</title>
    <meta content="Y03LIV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Andrei Cherny</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cherny, Andrei</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6DB1239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 24, a Political Veteran, Vacuum Cleaner to Platform</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives profile of Andrei Cherny, 24, who is writing Democratic Party platform as platform director; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SO how did you spend the summer after seventh grade?</p>
        <p>Mowing lawns? Rereading ''Born Free'' at summer school? Andrei Cherny had grander plans for his vacation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SO how did you spend the summer after seventh grade?</p>
        <p>Mowing lawns? Rereading ''Born Free'' at summer school? Andrei Cherny had grander plans for his vacation.</p>
        <p>The year was 1988 and he had recently read Theodore H. White's ''The Making of the President, 1960.'' (No comic books for this preteenager.) Inspired by that portrait of John F. Kennedy, he volunteered to work on the Los Angeles campaign of another Massachusetts-bred, Harvard-trained candidate for president, Michael S. Dukakis.</p>
        <p>A skeptical campaign official asked what he would like to work on. ''Foreign policy,'' 12-year-old Andrei confidently replied. The official offered a vacuum cleaner instead. By fall, he had graduated from doing floors to stuffing envelopes and answering phones.</p>
        <p>But from that modest beginning came more precocious things. By his senior year at Harvard, Mr. Cherny was writing speeches for President Clinton. A week after graduation, he became a senior speech writer for Vice President Al Gore. At 23, he edited a big-thought magazine for the Democratic Leadership Council, the party's leading centrist organization. And at 24, he wrote a book describing the new politics of the new economy.</p>
        <p>Now, a month from reaching the ripe old age of 25, Mr. Cherny is writing the Democratic platform, a 20,000-word spiritual guide to the party's political soul that dedicated Democrats will fuss and bicker over all summer, whether or not voters pay any attention to it in the fall.</p>
        <p>''I think there are a lot of people who really do look at the platform,'' Mr. Cherny said. ''Perhaps especially in this day and age, it's an important way of saying: here's what the Democratic Party stands for, here's what we've done and what we're going to do.''</p>
        <p>As platform director, Mr. Cherny joins the ranks of other platform writers with silky prose and grand ideas who later became leading policy makers within the party. In 1984, it was Susan Estrich, who managed the 1988 Dukakis campaign. In 1992, it was Bruce Reed, now a top domestic policy adviser to Mr. Clinton. And in 1996, it was Mr. Reed and Elaine Kamarck, who is now policy director for the Gore campaign.</p>
        <p>As any of those people could tell you, platform writing is its own special art form. The prose must be pithy, elegant and inspiring. And the wording must deftly skip across the ideological minefields that have surrounded Democratic and Republican platforms of the past.</p>
        <p>For instance, when Senator Edward M. Kennedy challenged President Jimmy Carter in 1980, a combative Kennedy team -- which included the mayor of Cincinnati, Jerry Springer -- produced 25 minority reports on the platform. Things got so testy that a Kennedy adviser named Paul Tully nearly came to blows with a Carter delegate named Mario M. Cuomo.</p>
        <p>This year, after former Senator Bill Bradley yielded early in the primaries, the intraparty struggle is much quieter. To be sure, gay rights activists, environmentalists and union leaders are laboring behind the scenes to insert pet phrases into Mr. Cherny's draft. But the process, he insists, has been remarkably consensual and free of acrimony.</p>
        <p>''Certainly trade is one place where there's been some debate,'' he said. ''But it's not like you have these groups at each other's throats. You have the single goal of winning in November.''</p>
        <p>A gentle platform process would befit Mr. Cherny's unassuming style. Lanky and soft-spoken, he fills his spare time, what little there is, with history books, films and, he confesses, ''junk TV'' shows like ''Ally McBeal'' and ''Friends.'' In his cluttered office at the Democratic National Committee, a photograph of his favorite scholar-writer-politician, Winston Churchill, sternly stares down from the white wall.</p>
        <p>THE older of two sons born to immigrants from Czechoslovakia, Mr. Cherny was raised in the Valley Village section of Los Angeles, a heavily minority, working-class community. His father, a schoolteacher, and mother, a psychotherapist, are proud of his achievements, he says, but not overly awed by the company he keeps.</p>
        <p>''They still expect me to pick up my socks and wash the dishes when I'm home,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cherny first caught the eye of Democratic heavyweights during his senior year at Harvard, when Donald Baer, then the White House communications director, read a piece he had written for the student newspaper, The Crimson, analyzing President Clinton's landslide victory of 1996.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baer showed the article to the president, who liked it so much he made it required reading for his cabinet and cribbed part of a sentence for his second inaugural address. ''We need a new government for a new century, a government humble enough not to try to solve all our problems for us but strong enough to give us the tools to solve our problems for ourselves,'' the line from the address went.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baer commissioned Mr. Cherny to write speeches for Mr. Clinton during his final semester at Harvard. After graduation, he moved to Washington to write for Mr. Gore, an author and former reporter whom Mr. Cherny found to be a perfectionist about language.</p>
        <p>''We would bring him drafts, he'd sit down and change every word, and then some,'' Mr. Cherny said. ''In the end, they were his speeches.''</p>
        <p>A year ago, Mr. Cherny returned to California, where he managed to work as a part-time policy adviser to the speaker of the State Assembly while attending Boalt Hall, the law school at Berkeley, and writing a book. The book, ''The Next Deal,'' will be published by Basic Books this winter.</p>
        <p>And what if there is a Gore administration? Mr. Cherny says he wants to return to California, finish law school and become a criminal prosecutor. ''When the convention approves the platform, my job is done,'' he said. But the hesitation in his voice suggested that he senses this will not be his last stint in Washington.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
