<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moodie Maintains Cool in First Victory</title>
    <meta content="03LPGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoprite Lpga Classic</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moodie, Janice</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFD91239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moodie Maintains Cool in First Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>ABSECON, N.J., July 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janice Moodie wins ShopRite LPGA Classic; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taking a two-shot lead into today's final round of the ShopRite L.P.G.A. Classic, Janice Moodie of Scotland said that she had been ''chopping at the door'' on the tour without much success.</p>
        <p>The door burst open this afternoon when Moodie fended off pursuit from a group of golfers, including Juli Inkster, and won her first Ladies Professional Golf Association Tour victory. She shot two-under-par 69 in a round that included four birdies and two bogeys for a total of 10-under 203 and a winner's purse of $165,000. Moodie either led the field or was tied for the lead each day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Taking a two-shot lead into today's final round of the ShopRite L.P.G.A. Classic, Janice Moodie of Scotland said that she had been ''chopping at the door'' on the tour without much success.</p>
        <p>The door burst open this afternoon when Moodie fended off pursuit from a group of golfers, including Juli Inkster, and won her first Ladies Professional Golf Association Tour victory. She shot two-under-par 69 in a round that included four birdies and two bogeys for a total of 10-under 203 and a winner's purse of $165,000. Moodie either led the field or was tied for the lead each day.</p>
        <p>The 27-year-old Moodie won by two shots over Pat Hurst, who shot 64, and Grace Park, who had a 67.</p>
        <p>Before today's victory in the $1.1 million tournament, the richest 54-hole event on the Tour, Moodie's best results in her three years on tour were three second-place finishes.</p>
        <p>She gained the victory by refusing to buckle when Inkster tied for the lead early in the round.</p>
        <p>After Inkster birdied the first hole and Moodie bogeyed the second to bring about a three-way tie that included Hurst, Moodie responded with consecutive birdies on the third and fourth holes and never trailed after that. Inkster, last week's winner of the McDonald's L.P.G.A. Championship and twice the victor in this tournament, faded with bogeys on the fifth and seventh holes. Moodie had a bogey on No. 6, but birdies in the 4-foot range at Nos. 8 and 9 put her ahead by two shots.</p>
        <p>Moodie was at 10-under at the turn and had a pleasant walk the rest of the way on the 6,051-yard Bay Course of the Seaview Marriott resort.</p>
        <p>Her putter and short game were outstanding. She made a 4-foot par saver at No. 10 and a 6-footer at the next hole after blowing a birdie attempt past a tough pin placement. Moodie also made par savers in the 3- to 5-foot range at Nos. 13, 15 and 16. She pumped her fist every time she made a putt.</p>
        <p>''I putted solidly the last eight or nine holes to save par,'' Moodie said. ''I just decided to ride with it. It was fantastic walking up on 18 and getting that kind of reception by the crowd.''</p>
        <p>Inkster shot 70 and finished tied for fourth along with Michelle Estill (68) and Vickie Odegard (70), who made the cut for only the second time in her 16 events this season.</p>
        <p>Hurst, who won this year at the Electrolux U.S.A. Championship, started the day at one-under, but birdies in five of the first seven holes applied pressure on Moodie.</p>
        <p>The 64 by Hurst, the rookie of the year in 1995 after a successful amateur career, was her best round of the year and tied for the lowest score in the last round of this event, which celebrated its 15th anniversary. She had eight birdies and just one bogey, on the second hole, the most difficult one on the course.</p>
        <p>''If you told me at the start of the day I would finish in the top 10, I would have been happy,'' Hurst said. ''To finish second is really a bonus.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>JANICE MOODIE joined KATHRYN MARSHALL (who won in 1995 in Toledo) as the only Scots to win on the L.P.G.A Tour. . . . Moodie is the third straight foreign player to win the event. ANNIKA SORENSTAM of Sweden won two years ago, and SE RI PAK of South Korea won last year. . . . JEAN BARTHOLOMEW of Garden City, N.Y., shot five-under 66 on the strength of birdies on the last four holes. She had a total of seven birdies with two bogeys for a total of 209.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
