<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tough Act to Follow for Heinrichs</title>
    <meta content="03SOCC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heinrichs, April</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5D81239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tough Act to Follow for Heinrichs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>FOXBORO, Mass., July 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on April Heinrichs's pruning of US women's soccer team roster in her first months as coach of World Cup-winning team; photos; 15 of 18 members of 2000 Olympic team are still expected to be players from World Cup team (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Euphoria over winning the 1999 Women's World Cup was quickly tempered for the Americans by a coaching change and a contract dispute with the United States Soccer Federation. What had seemed certain was no longer certain. Invincibility was replaced by insecurity.</p>
        <p>April Heinrichs, one of the early stars of the women's national team, replaced Tony DiCicco as coach in January and bluntly told the veterans, ''I don't care if you've played in three World Cups, if I feel you are past your peak, I will release you.'' In her first game as coach, she did not start the captain, Carla Overbeck, or midfielder Michelle Akers, considered the greatest player in the women's game. ''Are you putting me out to pasture?'' a perplexed Akers asked Heinrichs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Euphoria over winning the 1999 Women's World Cup was quickly tempered for the Americans by a coaching change and a contract dispute with the United States Soccer Federation. What had seemed certain was no longer certain. Invincibility was replaced by insecurity.</p>
        <p>April Heinrichs, one of the early stars of the women's national team, replaced Tony DiCicco as coach in January and bluntly told the veterans, ''I don't care if you've played in three World Cups, if I feel you are past your peak, I will release you.'' In her first game as coach, she did not start the captain, Carla Overbeck, or midfielder Michelle Akers, considered the greatest player in the women's game. ''Are you putting me out to pasture?'' a perplexed Akers asked Heinrichs.</p>
        <p>Quickly, the coach cut five veterans who were not contending for starting positions.</p>
        <p>Had she been hired by the federation to clean house?</p>
        <p>''We had gone through this huge ugly brawl over the contract and all we had been hearing was, 'They don't want you guys anymore, you create too many problems,' '' the co-captain Julie Foudy said. ''We were like, 'Is she listening to them, does she believe that, did they pick her because of that?' We didn't think so, but I don't think she understood how nervous we were about that.''</p>
        <p>On Monday night, the American women will face Brazil in a rematch of the World Cup semifinal here in the championship match of the Concacaf Women's Gold Cup at Foxboro Stadium. The teams also played to a 0-0 tie in a Gold Cup group match last Wednesday.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, the early fears were unfounded. Heinrichs said she never intended to do any clear-cutting of the American roster, merely some necessary pruning. Fifteen of the 18 members of the 2000 Olympic team are expected to be players from the World Cup team. And Heinrichs has become widely popular for her competitiveness and for her encouragement of the players to be creative and take risks.</p>
        <p>Still, the Americans face difficult questions as they try to repeat as Olympic champions at the 2000 Games in Sydney, Australia, in September: Can they survive a difficult draw that features their toughest rivals, Norway and China, in the first two matches? Can they win on the road after winning the 1996 Olympics and the 1999 World Cup at home? Can they compensate for injuries that have affected the spine of their defense -- Akers (shoulder surgery), Overbeck (knee surgery) and goalkeeper Briana Scurry (shinsplints)? Can they remain focused on soccer while also enjoying the endorsement and public-appearance bounty of a World Cup victory?</p>
        <p>''The Olympics are going to be our biggest challenge,'' Foudy said. ''There are a lot of people tugging at the team, so many demands. It's been a major topic of conversation. It requires that much more focus, that much more dedication and commitment to saying, 'No, I can't do this.' If it's not going to help you in September, say no now. This is the last time we'll all be together. We want to go out with a bang, not with regrets. Everyone asks if we'll be complacent, but that's not us. We've worked harder this year than we ever have.''</p>
        <p>A year after the World Cup, attendance has inevitably dropped at the national team's matches, but Foudy said that people still frequently approached the players in airports and high-fived them and congratulated them on the victory. ''I'm amazed at the depth of people we've reached, from Midwesterners who never watched a soccer match to Nascar-type guys,'' she said. ''I think it's going to have a big impact on kids for years to come.''</p>
        <p>With her exultant, jersey-removing celebration at the conclusion of the penalty-kick shootout against China in the World Cup final, Brandi Chastain has entered the national lexicon as an answer on ''Who Wants to be a Millionaire'' and a question to the finalists in the Junior Miss America pageant. The pageant contestants criticized Chastain, but she said she had no regrets.</p>
        <p>''I'm not unhappy I did it,'' she said. ''It was a liberating moment for myself, and I hope it was a liberating experience for other people.''</p>
        <p>Five reserves from the World Cup team have been dropped from the pool of Olympic players -- goalkeepers Saskia Webber and Tracy Ducar, midfielder Tiffany Roberts, forward Danielle Fotopoulos and, most notably, midfielder Tisha Venturini, who scored two goals on four shots in the World Cup. Of the younger players brought in, the most significant has been goalkeeper Siri Mullinix, who has started in Scurry's absence and has performed assertively in patrolling the penalty area and beyond.</p>
        <p>''I think we've got depth at every position that we've never had before,'' said Heinrichs, who coached the past four years at the University of Virginia.</p>
        <p>Scurry, Overbeck and Akers are expected to be back with the team this month, but Akers remains the biggest question mark. At 34, she continues to suffer from chronic fatigue syndrome and is recovering from surgery to repair a dislocated shoulder. She has not played with the team since the World Cup, and Lorrie Fair has assumed her spot in defensive midfield.</p>
        <p>Elite players can take significant time off and still retain their skills, Heinrichs said, which Akers has done in the past.</p>
        <p>''It is our hope that she can do that again,'' Heinrichs said. ''On the other hand, she battles chronic fatigue and she hasn't been with the team in 11 months. That's like Steve Young taking a year off and jumping back in in the middle of the season when the 49ers are 6-5 and making a playoff run. That's a concern. But Michelle certainly has a presence just being on the field. There's value in that.''</p>
        <p>Her shoulder surgery in April was complicated by a fracture and nerve damage, Akers said. She will not be completely healed for the Olympics but will be healthy enough to play, she said. Akers also struggled to regain her energy after the World Cup and even considered retirement in early April. In a way, the shoulder surgery restored her motivation, she said.</p>
        <p>''I feel the fire is back,'' Akers said. ''I've trained my fanny off. My health is good. I'm confident that, if given the chance to play in, I can be a starter for the team.''</p>
        <p>Apprehension about Heinrichs as coach began to dissolve in March, when the team traveled to the Algarve Cup tournament in Portugal. Heinrichs got to know the players, they got to know her. The day before the final against Norway, she had the team play an amusing game of soccer golf, complete with props and a team manager who carried a tray of sparkling water around the course as if she were a waiter.</p>
        <p>''Tony was great,'' defender Kate Sobrero said of DiCicco, who led the team to victory in the 1996 Olympics and the 1999 World Cup. ''He took this team farther than anyone ever had. But change makes you better. It's good to have April. She wants you to take risks, and gives you the freedom to do that.''</p>
        <p>Heinrichs, who is 36 and a native of Littleton, Colo., is a seminal figure in American soccer, the first woman elected to the sport's national hall of fame. She was captain of the American team that won the inaugural Women's World Cup in China in 1991, playing forward with Akers and Carin Gabarra in an alignment known as the triple-edged sword, fronting a relentless attack that outscored the opposition 74 goals to 5 during qualifying and the final round of the tournament.</p>
        <p>''April set the foundation for this team,'' Foudy said. ''All the principles we live by -- the work rate, the mentality, the teamwork, all the things that have made us successful -- stem from her days as captain.''</p>
        <p>Anson Dorrance, who recruited Heinrichs to the University of North Carolina and later made her captain of the national team, frequently tells the story of how Heinrichs upset the older players at Carolina with her ferocious play as a freshman.</p>
        <p>''What are you going to do about April?'' one player said to him.</p>
        <p>''Clone her?'' he thought to himself.</p>
        <p>She became a star by racing through cultural red lights that hindered women from being overly aggressive on the soccer field and by dispelling the conventional wisdom that women had trouble competing against friends for fear of destroying their personal relationships.</p>
        <p>''I was driven to compete, driven to want to win, and the consequences never occurred to me,'' Heinrichs said. ''I didn't feel constricted by social norms or constrained by criticism. In fact, I felt the opposite. I felt my acceptance as a person came through my athleticism. It wasn't until I was 22 or 23 that I separated my athletic identity from my personal identity and realized they weren't tied in.''</p>
        <p>Foudy, who played four seasons with Heinrichs on the national team, said she had never met so competitive a person.</p>
        <p>''We were on the road, on one of our first trips, and we were playing Pictionary,'' Foudy said. ''I was on her team, and she was screaming: 'Draw faster! What is it you're drawing, I can't tell!' She was intent on winning this game as if her life depended on it. On the field, I knew what she was like, but this was a whole new level. Obsessed with winning Pictionary.''</p>
        <p>It is in this aggressive image that Heinrichs wants to mold the national team for its run at an Olympic gold medal, bringing an attacking style that she likens to the Phi Slama Jama days of basketball at the University of Houston. It was the way the Americans played during her own days on the national team.</p>
        <p>''At practice, we used to pick teams and play, and my first pick would always be April,'' Foudy said. ''I didn't care if she had two broken legs, a straitjacket, crutches, I'd take her first. Even if she couldn't play, she'd be on the sidelines screaming to get everyone going.''</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
