<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Advertising; Estee Lauder, BMW, MySimon.com and Hibernia make new account assignments.</title>
    <meta content="03ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Estee Lauder Companies</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">A/R Media</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bayerische Motorenwerke Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Daniel Advertising</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Finance.com</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kirshenbaum Bond &amp; Partners</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mysimon.com Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Burnett, Leo, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hibernia Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Doner, W B, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EEDF1239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Advertising; Estee Lauder, BMW, MySimon.com and Hibernia make new account assignments.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New account assignments are announced by big advertisers: Estee Lauder to A/R Media, BMW of North America to Washington Daniel Advertising, Finance.com to Kirshenbaum Bond &amp; Partners, MySimon.com to Leo Burnett USA in Chicago and Hibernia Corp to Doner in Southfield, Mich (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR agencies large and small, the second half of 2000 is beginning the same way the first half ended, with a flurry of account assignments from advertisers in major categories like beauty products, automobiles, dot-coms and banking.</p>
        <p>Estee Lauder in New York, the cosmetics and fragrance giant, named A/R Media in New York to assist its in-house team with the creative development of a new national campaign. It marks the first time in several years that Lauder has sought creative direction from outside the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR agencies large and small, the second half of 2000 is beginning the same way the first half ended, with a flurry of account assignments from advertisers in major categories like beauty products, automobiles, dot-coms and banking.</p>
        <p>Estee Lauder in New York, the cosmetics and fragrance giant, named A/R Media in New York to assist its in-house team with the creative development of a new national campaign. It marks the first time in several years that Lauder has sought creative direction from outside the company.</p>
        <p>The campaign will continue to feature Elizabeth Hurley, the actress who serves as the public ''face'' of Lauder, in ads that are expected to be shot by the fashion photographer Steven Meisel. The new work is planned to start in January.</p>
        <p>A/R Media, headed by Alex Gonzalez and Raoul Martinez, specializes in designer fashion advertising for apparel marketers like Dolce &amp; Gabbana, Missoni, Emanuel Ungaro, Valentino and Versace.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of parallels and similarities between fashion and beauty,'' said Donna Laveran, a spokeswoman for Lauder. ''A/R is a name known in the fashion and beauty worlds.'' A/R was chosen after a six-month review, she added, declining to disclose the other participants.</p>
        <p>Though a budget for the campaign is not being disclosed, Lauder spent $116.2 million last year on advertising, according to Competitive Media Reporting in New York, which tracks ad spending.</p>
        <p>Bates Worldwide in New York, part of the Cordiant Communications Group, remains the agency of record for Lauder, handling duties like media planning and buying.</p>
        <p>On the automotive front, BMW of North America in Woodcliff Lake, N.J., named Washington Daniel Advertising in Chicago as its first agency of record for so-called diversity marketing initiatives aimed at African-Americans and other consumers. Billings were not disclosed.</p>
        <p>The company is hoping that Washington Daniel can help ''to extend our brand to a more diverse audience,'' said Jim McDowell, vice president for marketing at BMW of North America. Other clients of Washington Daniel include Anheuser-Busch and I.B.M.</p>
        <p>Fallon Minneapolis, part of the Fallon Worldwide unit of Publicis S.A., handles general market advertising for BMW.</p>
        <p>Turning to other account assignments, Finance.com in Long Island City, Queens, a Web site offering financial and investment advice that is part of the e-Citi operation of Citibank, named Kirshenbaum Bond &amp; Partners in New York to handle its first account. Spending was estimated at $35 million.</p>
        <p>The decision came after a review that had been narrowed to Kirshenbaum Bond and four undisclosed agencies. Kirshenbaum Bond handles another assignment for Citibank, the American Airlines AAdvantage credit card program.</p>
        <p>Kirshenbaum Bond was also being considered in a review for the United States account of Citibank, which has been handled by the New York office of Young &amp; Rubicam Advertising. The review for that account, with billings estimated at $48 million, was narrowed last week to two agencies, the daily fax edition of the trade publication Advertising Age reported: Fallon Minneapolis and three offices of TBWA/Chiat/Day, part of the TBWA Worldwide unit of the Omnicom Group. Citibank is owned by Citigroup.</p>
        <p>In another dot-com decision, MySimon.com in San Francisco, an online comparison shopping service that is part of CNET Networks, named Leo Burnett USA in Chicago, part of the Leo Burnett Company unit of the B Com3  Group, to handle its account, which had been at Bigelo &amp; Partners  in San Francisco. Billings were estimated at $15 million.</p>
        <p>The MySimon.com decision came after a three-week review that had been narrowed to Burnett and three undisclosed agencies based in the Bay Area.</p>
        <p>And the Hibernia Corporation in New Orleans, which operates banks in Louisiana and Texas, named Doner in Southfield, Mich., to handle its account, which had been at Caldwell VanRiper/MARC in Indianapolis, part of MARC USA. Billings were estimated at $15 million to $20 million.</p>
        <p>The decision came after a review that had been narrowed to Doner and two other agencies. One was McCann-Erickson Southwest in Dallas, part of the McCann-Erickson Worldwide Advertising unit of the McCann-Erickson World Group, which is owned by the Interpublic Group of Companies. The other was Publicis in Dallas and New York.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
