<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BORDER BALLOTING</title>
    <meta content="03BORD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212352"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEXICO ELECTION: BALLOTING AT THE BORDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tijuana (Mexico)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico/Baja California/Tijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E1D71239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1311" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BORDER BALLOTING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>TIJUANA, Mexico, July 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thousands of Mexicans living in United States cross border to vote at special out-of-district polling places in Tijuana and other border cities, drawn by possibility that governing party could lose presidency; election dominates Tijuana, with long lines at polling places and no drinking allowed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They began arriving before dawn, crossing south over the border in cars and pickup trucks and small caravans, with an unusual degree of optimism in their hearts and their voter registration cards in their wallets.</p>
        <p>They were Mexicans who live in the United States returning to elect a new president, drawn by the possibility that the somewhat paradoxically named Institutional Revolutionary Party would lose the presidency for the first time since it was founded 71 years ago. Since Mexico does not have absentee ballots, they had to come from as far away as San Francisco, Washington and Chicago to cast their ballots at special polling places for out-of-district voters that were set up here and in several other cities along the 2,000-mile border.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They began arriving before dawn, crossing south over the border in cars and pickup trucks and small caravans, with an unusual degree of optimism in their hearts and their voter registration cards in their wallets.</p>
        <p>They were Mexicans who live in the United States returning to elect a new president, drawn by the possibility that the somewhat paradoxically named Institutional Revolutionary Party would lose the presidency for the first time since it was founded 71 years ago. Since Mexico does not have absentee ballots, they had to come from as far away as San Francisco, Washington and Chicago to cast their ballots at special polling places for out-of-district voters that were set up here and in several other cities along the 2,000-mile border.</p>
        <p>''We all want change,'' said Ramiro Ramirez, a 48-year-old mechanic from Fontana, Calif., who arrived late Saturday night to ensure that he would get a good spot in line at one of the special polling sites today. Mr. Ramirez, who left his home state of Michoacan for the United States as a child, said he had made the trip today because he is thinking of his own future.</p>
        <p>''We all left because of the same problems,'' he said. ''But I would like to go back someday. And if the government changes, if things get better, if there's work, I will return.''</p>
        <p>By the time his turn came here, at 9 this morning, to pick up a paper ballot, fill it out in a cardboard booth behind a plastic curtain that said ''The Vote is Free and Secret,'' and stuff the folded ballot into a cardboard box with a clear plastic window on each side, roughly 250 people were waiting behind him, many of them from California as well.</p>
        <p>Their polling place, outside an all-night drugstore, was one of 15 in Tijuana where Mexicans away from home could vote. They wore cowboy hats and Dallas Cowboys hats, pearl-buttoned shirts and Hard Rock Cafe T-shirts, cowboy boots and Air Jordans. They came, they said, out of a belief that this election would be different from those in the past that were tainted by fraud. An opposition candidate, Vicente Fox Quesada, was virtually tied in the polls with the nominee of the governing party, Francisco Labastida Ochoa.</p>
        <p>The vote is to be counted for the first time by an autonomous group, the Federal Elections Institute, rather than by a branch of the government controlled by the governing party. And many Mexicans north of the border were the targets of advertising and even campaign stops by the candidates.</p>
        <p>''I think change is really possible this time,'' said Gabriel Castellanos, 26, who arrived here at 6:30 a.m. after driving down from Huntington Beach, Calif., with his wife, Miriam Sanchez, 19, to vote for Mr. Fox.</p>
        <p>Fausto Soriano, 60, who came from San Francisco with four friends to vote for Mr. Fox, said, ''I think this will be a cleaner election.''</p>
        <p>The election dominated Tijuana this weekend. There were the long lines at polling places, and most striking of all, there was no drinking allowed. The government imposed a  dry law until after the elections.</p>
        <p>It was quite a switch for a place that began its rapid growth, from a village to a city of 1.5 million people, during Prohibition, when Californians made this a favorite place for a boozy weekend getaway.</p>
        <p>Without the usual rowdy revelry, the voters stood out even more than usual. The great fear expressed among them was that there would not be enough ballots to go around; an old voting-law reform, aimed at preventing fraud by ballot-stuffing, limits the number of ballots at each polling place to 750.</p>
        <p>With only 15 sites in Tijuana where people could vote away from home, the maximum number of ballots available to them here would be 11,250. And some of those would be cast by people who live in Mexico -- soldiers, business travelers, people who moved but had not registered their new addresses.</p>
        <p>That is why Jacqueline Vargas, 26, set her alarm clock at home in Garden Grove, Calif., for 3:40 a.m. She was so worried about oversleeping that she awakened on her own at 2:30. Ms. Vargas, who left her home in Monterrey four years ago for a marketing job in the United States, said she had followed the campaign online.</p>
        <p>''After I graduated from the university, my aim was to move abroad as soon as I could,'' she said. ''I didn't like the situation either politically or economically. I didn't see much future for myself there.''</p>
        <p>Mexicans living in the United States were assiduously courted for their votes this year for the first time. ''The democratic process of Mexico is finally permeating north of the border, making us Mexican citizens aware of what's happening politically in our country,'' said Luis Pelayo, the president of the Hispanic Council in Chicago, who helped organize several caravans to cross the Texas border.</p>
        <p>Of the estimated 10 million Mexicans who live in the United States, 1.5 million are believed to be eligible to vote. No one expected that many people to cross the border to vote -- in fact, fewer than 75,000 ballots were available at the special polling sites.</p>
        <p>But the Mexicans living in the United States were wooed not only for their votes but also for their influence. Many of them still hold sway in the villages they left behind and with the families they support with money each month. By some estimates, Mexicans abroad send $7 billion home each year. They like to point out that this makes them Mexico's third highest source of income, after petroleum and tourism.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Vargas called home, she said, she was disappointed when her father told her that he would vote for the governing party. ''He just told me, 'They've done so much for us,' '' she said. ''I couldn't believe it.''</p>
        <p>It was a sore point among many Mexicans in the United States that Mexico lacks an absentee ballot. A bill that would have created one stalled last year in the Senate, which is controlled by the governing party. Party officials said they supported the concept of an absentee ballot but  there was not enough time to create a fair system. Their opponents accused them of scuttling the measure out of fear that people who had to leave Mexico to find good jobs would vote them out of office.</p>
        <p>Raul Ross Pineda, who lives in Chicago and is taking the unusual step of running for the Mexican Congress this year to represent the interests of Mexicans abroad, wrote a book on the issue called ''Vote Without Borders,'' to call for an absentee ballot.</p>
        <p>''Legally we are Mexican citizens; we have the right to vote, we love Mexico, we have families there that we sustain,'' Mr. Ross said. ''We are not asking for any special privilege.''</p>
        <p>But without the absentee ballot, many Mexicans living north of the border simply took to the road. ''Look at this,'' said Hector Alvarado, 45, from Maywood, Calif., pointing to a line of Mexicans from the United States that stretched nearly an entire city block here. ''This isn't a rock concert or a football match. These are people who want to vote.''</p>
        <p>THE MEXICO ELECTION: BALLOTING AT THE BORDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
