<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="03DIGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7DD1239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>U.S. Investigating Conduct Of Adviser to Kazakhstan  Federal prosecutors are investigating whether an American trade consultant funneled millions of dollars in payments from major oil companies like Phillips Petroleum and Mobil to Kazakhstan officials who are his clients, according to a Justice Department document.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Justice Department asked Swiss authorities for help in investigating the financial activities of James H. Giffen, a prominent consultant for trade deals in Russia and former Soviet republics. [Page C2.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>U.S. Investigating Conduct Of Adviser to Kazakhstan  Federal prosecutors are investigating whether an American trade consultant funneled millions of dollars in payments from major oil companies like Phillips Petroleum and Mobil to Kazakhstan officials who are his clients, according to a Justice Department document.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Justice Department asked Swiss authorities for help in investigating the financial activities of James H. Giffen, a prominent consultant for trade deals in Russia and former Soviet republics. [Page C2.]</p>
        <p>3 Officials to Lead Oracle Day to Day  After the abrupt resignation of Oracle's president, Raymond J. Lane, the day-to-day operation of the company is now in the hands of three executives: Gary L. Bloom, 38, Oracle's top marketer and executive vice president; Jeffrey O. Henley, 54, the chief financial officer; and Safra Catz, 38, a former investment banker, now an executive vice president. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Online Grocers Still Face Hurdles  The announcement last week that Webvan had agreed to pay $1.2 billion for HomeGrocer.com showed that online grocers are realizing that there is strength through scale but that significant kinks in the business continue to present big challenges to its long-term viability. New Economy. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Netease Dampens Spirits in China  The poor debut on Friday of the Chinese Internet company Netease.com -- whose American depository receipts opened at $15.50 but fell to $12.125 on Nasdaq -- has sent shudders through China's Internet entrepreneurs, who see an overseas listing as their only hope. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Two More Points in Privacy Debate  When the online privacy debate peaked earlier this year, the watchwords were ''notice'' and ''choice.'' Consumer groups demanded that online advertising companies give consumers more notice when tracking their behavior and give them the choice to avoid such tracking. But two other principles have received scant air time: giving consumers ''access'' to data collected on them and providing them with the ''security'' that the data is kept private. Bob Tedeschi: E-Commerce Report. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Microsoft to Honor Its Engineers  To reward its brightest technologists, Microsoft plans to announce a distinguished engineer program today, initially honoring 16 of the company's best designers. [C5.]</p>
        <p>CNN to Broaden Online Presence  Spurred by declining ratings during slow news periods, CNN's parent company, the Turner Broadcasting System, announced last week that it would broaden the network's online presence to include research tools and more in-depth coverage. The result would be a wealth of information from a combination of on-air and online sources. Turner will spend $1.2 billion the next five years to enlarge its downtown Atlanta headquarters and build and renovate parts of offices and studios elsewhere in the city. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Telefonica Bolsters Control of Units  Telefonica, Spain's largest phone operator, has increased control of its Argentine and Brazilian units after most investors swapped stock in the units for the company's shares. [C5.]</p>
        <p>U.S. Markets to Close Early  The stock market and other financial markets in the United States will close at 1 p.m. today and will be closed tomorrow in observance of the Fourth of July. Most overseas markets, however, will be open both days. United States markets will reopen on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
