<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Oil Consultant Faces Inquiry on Kazakh Deals</title>
    <meta content="03OIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kazakhstan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giffen, James H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nazarbayev, Nursultan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kazakhstan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Kazakhstan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DD1239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Oil Consultant Faces Inquiry on Kazakh Deals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal prosecutors are investigating whether James H Giffen funneled millions of dollars in payments from major oil companies to Kazakhstan officials who are his clients; Giffen has been an important adviser to Pres Nursultan A Nazarbayev of Kazakhstan over the last decade (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal prosecutors are investigating whether an American trade consultant funneled millions of dollars in payments from major oil companies to Kazakhstan officials who are his clients, according to a Justice Department document.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Justice Department asked Swiss authorities for help in investigating the financial activities of James H. Giffen, a consultant for trade deals in Russia and the former Soviet republics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal prosecutors are investigating whether an American trade consultant funneled millions of dollars in payments from major oil companies to Kazakhstan officials who are his clients, according to a Justice Department document.</p>
        <p>Last month, the Justice Department asked Swiss authorities for help in investigating the financial activities of James H. Giffen, a consultant for trade deals in Russia and the former Soviet republics.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, Mr. Giffen has been an important adviser to President Nursultan A. Nazarbayev of Kazakhstan, a role that has taken on larger significance in recent talks between the oil-rich Central Asian nation and the world's major energy companies. The inquiry also comes as the United States, Russia and Iran are competing to win Kazakh approval for oil export routes for the country's oil reserves.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department suspects Mr. Giffen of depositing $60 million in payments from units of major oil companies like Phillips Petroleum, Amoco and Mobil, into Swiss bank accounts on behalf of Mr. Nazarbayev, as well as other Kazakh officials and their families.</p>
        <p>Investigators say the money was then funneled to the officials through shell companies in Switzerland and the British Virgin Islands. The transfers took place between March 1997 and September 1998 and may have violated the Foreign Corrupt Practices Act as well as racketeering statutes, the document said.</p>
        <p>''Giffen was the intermediary in these transfers and used the Mercator Corporation, which he controls, to facilitate these transfers,'' according to a 17-page Justice Department document, signed by John E. Harris, the acting director of the criminal division's international affairs office.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department did not say whether the oil companies themselves were also possible targets of the investigation, which was first reported on Friday night on the Web site of The Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giffen was traveling abroad today and was not available for comment. But Mark J. MacDougall, a lawyer at Akin, Gump, Strauss, Hauer &amp; Feld in Washington, who is representing Mr. Giffen, said he had not been notified by the Justice Department of any inquiry.</p>
        <p>''Mercator Corporation has had a longstanding official relationship with the Republic of Kazakhstan and its emerging oil industry,'' Mr. MacDougall said in a statement. ''Although these transactions are complicated, they have been documented in great detail and closed with full disclosure to everyone involved.''</p>
        <p>Messages left at the Kazakh Embassy were not returned today, and no one answered at the Kazakh Consulate in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nazarbayev has been president of Kazahkstan since the huge  but sparsely populated former Soviet republic of 16.8 million people gained independence in 1991. Under Mr. Nazarbayev's semiauthoritarian rule, Kazakhstan has sought to exploit its large oil reserves to build an economy independent from Russia.</p>
        <p>Last May, a consortium of nine foreign energy companies found oil in a huge Caspian Sea field and began drilling to determine how much exists. Mr. Nazarbayev was so optimistic at the time that he predicted the field, called Kashagan, would help Kazakhstan export as much oil as Saudi Arabia by 2015 -- eight million barrels a day.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
