<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Rural Life; Summer on the Wing</title>
    <meta content="03MON3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swallows (Birds)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DC1239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Rural Life; Summer on the Wing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VERLYN KLINKENBORG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Verlyn Klinkenborg The Rural Life column on his yearning for barn swallows to join other insect eaters at farm</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At first light, about 4 o'clock, the bats begin fluttering at the roof ridge, slipping into the house through a bat-stained crack between clapboards. It is just enough noise to wake me up, and for a moment I lie there, watching the dark shapes against the false dawn outside. The bats nest somewhere in the ceiling above my head, just beyond a layer of Sheetrock and insulation, and that is somehow satisfying, like having a chicken coop in the rafters.</p>
        <p>It is pleasant to pretend that wildness stops at the front door in the country, but it really doesn't. In April, I started seeds under a lamp in the basement, and when the seedlings were just ready to be pricked out and potted on, the mice one night grazed them down to bare stubs. A fox took a seat in the driveway the other morning and looked at the kitchen as if he expected to come in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At first light, about 4 o'clock, the bats begin fluttering at the roof ridge, slipping into the house through a bat-stained crack between clapboards. It is just enough noise to wake me up, and for a moment I lie there, watching the dark shapes against the false dawn outside. The bats nest somewhere in the ceiling above my head, just beyond a layer of Sheetrock and insulation, and that is somehow satisfying, like having a chicken coop in the rafters.</p>
        <p>It is pleasant to pretend that wildness stops at the front door in the country, but it really doesn't. In April, I started seeds under a lamp in the basement, and when the seedlings were just ready to be pricked out and potted on, the mice one night grazed them down to bare stubs. A fox took a seat in the driveway the other morning and looked at the kitchen as if he expected to come in.</p>
        <p>At night, flying insects clatter and whir against the screen of a lighted window, and sometimes the bats pick them off the screen, their wings just brushing it as they fly past. It comes as a surprise to realize once again how full the night is with insects in late June. When you drive at night, moths come flaring into the headlights like stones skipped down the highway. Last week I walked down to the mailbox long after dark, and out in the open, where the darkness lessened, I saw an atmosphere full of insects drifting past, like the metropolitan scene in a science fiction movie, with airborne traffic vectoring this way and that. Twice in the past week I found the corpse of a luna moth on the ground. It seemed less like the remains of a personal moth-death than the wreck of a pale-green, iridescent, freight-carrying kite. As full as the air is of insects, it is that full of insect-eaters, too.</p>
        <p>But as far as I can tell, no one is eating the slugs. We try very hard not to. We wash the lettuce from the garden three or four times, picking carefully over each leaf before we spin it dry. Somehow the profusion of slugs this year is emblematic of the damp, dark weather that has clung to this small farm since April. Slugs are a kind of animate precipitation, aqueous sloths. The garden is flecked with them in early morning, and after you have tossed a few of them into the nettle-patch, the revulsion they cause dies away, until one turns up on the salad plate.</p>
        <p>What we are missing here, in this kingdom of airborne bugs, is barn swallows. I don't know where they are. The barn is ready and waiting. There are open pastures, and there are horses. There is an overhead wire to perch on and gape at the world from. We don't spray, and we don't knock down swallow nests. So where are the birds? Phoebes take bugs on the wing, and so do the few tree swallows who live around here, and of course the bats. But it is not the same. Some quality about this place, some aspect of its rusticity, will not be official until the barn swallows move in.</p>
        <p>VERLYN KLINKENBORG</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
