<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Miami, an Imported Mob Scene</title>
    <meta content="03MIAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami Beach (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami (Fla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Forge (Restaurant) (Miami Beach)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paciello, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malnick, Shareef</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malnick, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lansky, Meyer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feuer, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EED91239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Miami, an Imported Mob Scene</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FEUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feuer, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reputed gangsters from Brooklyn flock to Miami Beach as sunnier version of old neighborhood, often gathering at Forge restaurant; photo; steak house was opened in 1950's by Alvin Malnick, lawyer for Meyer Lansky, and is now owned by son Shareef Malnick, who has appeared in court to show support for his friend Chris Paciello, handsome nightclub owner and alleged member of vicious Bensonhurst Mafia crew; Russian and Israeli criminals who also have ties to Brooklyn have joined scene in recent years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One summer day in 1999, three men sat on the sun-splashed deck of Shooters Restaurant in Miami Beach, flipping through their menus and gazing at the lazy currents of the Intracoastal Waterway.</p>
        <p>They had arrived that day, the authorities say, on the glistening yacht of their host, Chris Paciello, a handsome South Beach nightclub owner as famous for his suntanned biceps as for his glamorous friendships with celebrities like Madonna. Throughout the meal, his boat -- a bright, white 50-footer -- bobbed at its berth in gentle waves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One summer day in 1999, three men sat on the sun-splashed deck of Shooters Restaurant in Miami Beach, flipping through their menus and gazing at the lazy currents of the Intracoastal Waterway.</p>
        <p>They had arrived that day, the authorities say, on the glistening yacht of their host, Chris Paciello, a handsome South Beach nightclub owner as famous for his suntanned biceps as for his glamorous friendships with celebrities like Madonna. Throughout the meal, his boat -- a bright, white 50-footer -- bobbed at its berth in gentle waves.</p>
        <p>The scene, as described by an internal Miami Beach Police Department memorandum, was so quintessentially South Florida, with its idling power boat and alfresco lunch, that it could have been photographed for a Dade County travel brochure. But through the eyes of the investigators watching that day, it was all about a place on the water farther up the coast: Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paciello was soon to be charged with abetting murder as a member of a vicious Bensonhurst Mafia crew. One of his guests that day was Alphonse Persico, who the authorities say is the acting boss of the Colombo crime family and keeps an apartment in Park Slope. The second guest was yet another Brooklyn transplant: Andrew Dohler, an undercover agent posing as a crooked Florida police officer, who had started his career in, all of places, the 75th Precinct station house in East New York.</p>
        <p>Brooklyn mobsters -- and the officers who chase them -- have been flocking to Miami ever since the first palm trees were planted here on Ocean Drive. As anyone who has seen ''The Godfather'' knows, the criminal link between the two locales has been tightly woven since at least the 1950's, when Meyer Lansky established his illicit beachhead on the Atlantic in hopes of cracking the Cuban gambling trade.</p>
        <p>Apart from Mr. Paciello and his  friends, the authorities say there are many notorious and recent examples of Brooklyn gangsters heading south. In December 1996, Nicholas Corozzo, the heir to the Gambino family throne, was arrested near a beach resort in Key Biscayne in nothing more than his bathing trunks. And on June 22 of this year, more than a dozen members of what is known as the South Florida crew of the Colombo family were arrested in the Miami area on charges of extortion, money laundering, illegal gambling, credit card fraud and dealing in counterfeit drivers' licenses.</p>
        <p>''From a gangster point of view, they just can't help themselves -- they have to go,'' said Tom Cash, the former special agent in charge of both the Miami and New York offices of the Drug Enforcement Administration. ''Miami is everything Brooklyn is not. It's sunny. The water is warm. The imported cannolis aren't as good as on 18th Avenue in the old neighborhood, but, really, they're not that bad.''</p>
        <p>Miami has become such a destination for Brooklyn mobsters -- ''it's their second stop after Bensonhurst,'' said one federal prosecutor -- that it even has a local restaurant said to be favored by New York wise guys and their retinues. According to former and current mob investigators, gangsters vacationing or doing business in Miami are likely to wind up at a velvet-roped, steak-and-lobster place called the Forge.</p>
        <p>The Forge, which attracts what one investigator called ''men with big cigars and women with tiny resumes,'' was opened in the 1950's by Alvin Malnick, a lawyer who worked closely with Mr. Lansky. These days, the Forge is owned by Mr. Malnick's son, Shareef, who appeared in federal court in Miami last year at a detention hearing to show his support for his good friend Chris Paciello. Neither Shareef Malnick nor his father returned telephone calls seeking comment about the Forge.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday nights, in particular, the Forge is packed with fleshy, older men in silk shirts or double-breasted suits who spend good money buying drinks for the women who hover around them like hummingbirds. On a recent night, after a couple of salsa numbers, the D.J. spun ''Volare.'' The big-screen television showed the New York-Miami playoff basketball game. The customers cheered for the Knicks each time they put one through the hoop.</p>
        <p>''The Forge is sort of like Sparks Steak House South,'' Mr. Cash said, referring to the New York mob landmark where Paul Castellano, the Gambino family boss, was killed in 1986. ''It's been absolutely infamous over the years.''</p>
        <p>There was a time when the Brooklyn mob presence in Miami was strictly La Cosa Nostra -- guys whose pinky rings clinked on their daiquiri glasses -- but in recent years, Russian and Israeli criminals with ties to neighborhoods like Brighton Beach and Borough Park have also made the trip, investigators say. The faces may be new, but the offenses they are said to commit -- money laundering, cigarette and drug smuggling, extortion, promoting prostitution -- have long been staples of organized crime.</p>
        <p>According to federal agents, a noted Russian mobster once bragged that he had as many as 600 soldiers in southern Florida, a great number of whom had passed through Brooklyn. Until two or three years ago, according to a federal indictment, the point man for the Russian Mafia in Miami was a onetime Brighton Beach furniture store owner named Ludwig Fainberg.</p>
        <p>Court papers say that Mr. Fainberg, who moved from Brooklyn to Florida in 1989, ran a remarkably eclectic criminal empire out of two businesses he owned in Miami: a strip club near Miami International Airport called Porky's and a borscht-and-blini restaurant in North Miami Beach called Babushka.</p>
        <p>The 1997 indictment charged Mr. Fainberg with drug trafficking, money laundering, counterfeiting, even with trying to secure a decommissioned Russian submarine for the drug lords of the Cali cartel of Colombia. But while many of the crimes he is said to have committed -- shipping bootleg cigarettes from Miami to New York, for example -- are a testament to his roots in both places, the long investigation that eventually led to his racketeering conviction in 1998 was the strongest evidence.</p>
        <p>When the government began to move against Mr. Fainberg in 1995, there was no place better than New York to turn for help. To infiltrate his cadre of Russian-speaking friends, investigators recruited a Brooklyn informer named Gregory Roizis to work in tandem with an undercover D.E.A. agent, Alexander Yasevich, who also hailed from Brighton Beach. As luck would have it, said Brent Eaton, the agent who ran the investigation for the D.E.A., the two men already knew each other from New York. As a child, Mr. Yasevich had attended a summer camp that Mr. Roizis ran in Brighton Beach.</p>
        <p>Weeks after the partners were reunited, the government sprang its Brooklyn-based trap. Mr. Roizis was instructed to hang out in Babushka, and on the appointed night, Mr. Yasevich walked in. Then, the government says, as Mr. Fainberg watched, the two men greeted each other in mock surprise. They bear-hugged, speaking Russian, and loudly reminisced about Brighton Beach. Mr. Fainberg fell for the act completely.</p>
        <p>''It was the perfect introduction,'' Mr. Eaton said.</p>
        <p>The Israeli gangsters have also made their presence felt in Florida, prosecutors and federal agents said. The Israelis are said to be specialists in the illegal importation of the nightclub drug Ecstasy and, according to a recent D.E.A. intelligence brief, ''tend to recruit couriers within their own ethnic and religious communities,'' in neighborhoods like Williamsburg and Borough Park.</p>
        <p>In one recent case, two young Hasidic men, Shimon Levita, 19, and Simcha Roth, 20, were found guilty of organizing a stable of Hasidic couriers from Brooklyn for an Israeli man named Sean Erez, who ran a ring that routinely shipped thousands of Ecstasy pills from manufacturers in Amsterdam to distributors in Miami  Beach. In a similar but unrelated case being prosecuted in the Brooklyn courts, Israeli mobsters have been charged with using strippers from New York bars like Scores and Tens to shuttle Ecstasy from Europe to Miami and other cities.</p>
        <p>Investigators suggest several reasons for the longstanding criminal connection between Brooklyn and Miami. They say that Miami, long an ''open city'' where no one criminal enterprise has exercised complete control, is an easy place for out-of-towners to set up shop. They say that the city's lucrative night life has long attracted criminal types. And they say that the police departments that patrol the shore have a fractured and unfocused approach to attacking organized crime.</p>
        <p>But the most persuasive reason may also be the simplest, investigators say. New Yorkers -- from Donald Trump to everyone's Aunt Frieda -- have always traveled to Miami in winter for a dose of ultraviolet rays.</p>
        <p>''This place is heaven for these guys,'' said Diana Fernandez, an assistant United States attorney in Miami, who prosecuted Mr. Fainberg. ''They consider their apartments in Miami to be like dachas. It has palm trees and sand. It's like vacationland to them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
