<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Incumbents Try to Reclaim Seats</title>
    <meta content="Y03HOU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BATTLE FOR THE HOUSE/Incumbent vs. Ex-Incumbent" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE HOUSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kentucky</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">baesler, scotty</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">fletcher, ernie (repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harman, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">kuykendall, steven t (repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, Richard A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holt, Rush D (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kentucky</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3DA1239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Incumbents Try to Reclaim Seats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>BALD KNOB, Ky.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican and Democratic leaders, battling for control of House, have enticed former House members in Kentucky, California, and New Jersey to run for seats they left in unsuccessful bids for other offices; Scotty Baesler, Democrat, seeks Kentucky seat now held by Rep Ernie Fletcher, Republican; Jane Harman, Democrat, challenges Rep Steven T Kuykendall in California; Republican Richard A Zimmer challenges Rep Rush Holt, Democrat, in New Jersey; former incumbents, all in hotly contested races, have been promised restored seniority and prized committee assignments; table; graphs; maps; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scotty Baesler hates fund-raising. Driving all day on the campaign trail wears him out. He has never had a real passion for writing legislation. And when he worked in Washington a few years ago, he longed for the weekends to return to his sprawling 250-acre farm near here.</p>
        <p>So why is the 58-year-old former three-term Democratic Congressman, fresh from a bout with prostate cancer, running hard to win back his old job on Capitol Hill?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scotty Baesler hates fund-raising. Driving all day on the campaign trail wears him out. He has never had a real passion for writing legislation. And when he worked in Washington a few years ago, he longed for the weekends to return to his sprawling 250-acre farm near here.</p>
        <p>So why is the 58-year-old former three-term Democratic Congressman, fresh from a bout with prostate cancer, running hard to win back his old job on Capitol Hill?</p>
        <p>''I miss it, and I miss setting the agenda,'' drawled Mr. Baesler, after greeting old friends and wolfing down a ham-and-cheese sandwich at Wright's Grocery in this hamlet, which is barely a curve in the road. ''Democrats need six more folks to take back control, and I want to be one of them.''</p>
        <p>Representative Ernie Fletcher, the freshman Republican who holds the seat Mr. Baesler gave up two years ago to run a failed Senate bid, has another theory: ''It's clear this is a fallback position for him. Scotty's getting a reputation for being a perennial candidate.''</p>
        <p>In the battle for control of Congress, three of the most hotly contested House races this year involve former incumbents who quit to run unsuccessfully for other offices, and are now trying to reclaim their old seats.</p>
        <p>Besides Mr. Baesler's bid here for Kentucky's Sixth District, Jane Harman, a former three-term Democrat, is challenging Representative Steven T. Kuykendall, a freshman Republican, for California's 36th District.  And in New Jersey, Republican Richard A. Zimmer is trying to recapture the 12th District seat he relinquished in 1996, now held by Representative Rush Holt, a freshman Democrat.</p>
        <p>With Republicans clinging to a narrow six-seat margin in the House, one or two of these tight races could spell the difference between serving in the majority or serving in the minority. To entice the former members, party leaders have promised to restore their House seniority, dangled prized committee assignments and recruited state officials to beg them to return.</p>
        <p>And for good reason. The powers of incumbency, including paid government staff and free postage for mailings, are so potent that defeating a sitting member of Congress has become very difficult.</p>
        <p>In 1998, 98 percent of all incumbents seeking re-election won their races, and not since 1974 has the re-election rate for incumbents dipped below 90 percent.</p>
        <p>But in races pitting incumbents against former incumbents, the odds for challengers jump dramatically because they are often just as well known and well financed as the sitting members. Moreover, of all incumbents, freshmen are the most vulnerable because they often have not yet built a reputation in their districts.</p>
        <p>''Former incumbents know how to raise money, they know their districts as well as anybody and they've been winners before,'' said Representative Patrick J. Kennedy of Rhode Island, chairman of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee. ''They're more sophisticated than your average candidate.''</p>
        <p>Representative Thomas M. Davis III of Virginia, chairman of the National Republican Campaign Committee, agreed but warned of a potential pitfall: ''If they left a seat for another job, they're saying they didn't like that job.''</p>
        <p>This year's comeback candidates said they were not looking to leap back into the fray of electoral politics until they were courted by party bosses.</p>
        <p>After losing a Democratic primary for governor two years ago, Ms. Harman settled into an intellectually stimulating life teaching public policy at the University of California at Los Angeles. She spent more time with her husband and teenage children. She took up golf.</p>
        <p>Yet when Gov. Gray Davis of California and party elders in Washington came calling, offering her plum seats on the commerce and intelligence committees, and the chance to help put Democrats back in charge, she said she could not resist.</p>
        <p>''The quality of life in the Congress stinks,'' said Ms. Harman, recalling the red-eye flights from the West Coast, late work nights and partisanship that has only worsened since she left.</p>
        <p>''On the other side of the ledger is the future of public policy in this country. And I'm a policy addict.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zimmer said that campaign wars were also far from his mind.  Since losing a bitter Senate race in 1996 to then-Representative Robert G. Torricelli, Mr. Zimmer has practiced law, taught politics at Princeton University's Woodrow Wilson School of Public and International Affairs, and spent time at his 25-acre farm in Hunterdon County.</p>
        <p>But two years ago, after Mr. Holt upset Representative Mike Pappas, a Republican, Mr. Zimmer said that Speaker J. Dennis Hastert and Republican leaders in New Jersey  urged him to run again. ''Denny told me that control of the House was on a razor's edge,'' said Mr. Zimmer, who  defeated Mr. Pappas in June in a primary battle of former incumbents.</p>
        <p>Republicans see Mr. Holt's seat as one of their top priorities, and each candidate expects to raise about $2.5 million in one of the nation's most expensive races. ''It's going to be difficult because Rush is a bright, hard-working candidate,'' said Mr. Zimmer, a social moderate who supports gun control and abortion rights. ''But I have a record of being effective.''</p>
        <p>Back here in the rolling bluegrass country of central Kentucky, Mr. Baesler and Mr. Fletcher offer a contrast in styles. Mr. Baesler, a former University of Kentucky basketball star and mayor of Lexington for a decade, has a country-boy manner and homespun humor. His favorite jibe at Mr. Fletcher is that ''Ernie is all hat and no cattle.'' Mr. Baesler is so frugal that he slept on a cot in his Washington office when he served in Congress rather than renting an apartment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fletcher, 47, is a family doctor and former Air Force fighter pilot with a polished presence. He concedes that Mr. Baesler is well known in the community, but more for what he did as mayor in the 1980's than as a Congressman in the 1990's. ''Folks see Scotty as a fish out of water up here,'' Mr. Fletcher said.</p>
        <p>That is just a taste of the sniping in a rematch of a 1996 race that Mr. Baesler won by 12 percent. Even Mr. Baesler does not put much stock in that margin. Mr. Fletcher was barely known and poorly financed then.  Now, he has built strong ties in his district and is amassing a $1.5 million campaign war chest. Mr. Baesler said he expects to raise the same.</p>
        <p>''You cannot imagine how nasty it's going to be or how expensive it's going to be,'' Mr. Baesler told a $200-a-person reception in the Governor's Mansion in Frankfort.</p>
        <p>The race has already taken a few weird twists.</p>
        <p>The state's largest physicians group has supported a tobacco farmer (Mr. Baesler) over a doctor (Mr. Fletcher). The doctors are angry at Mr. Fletcher because he opposes the patients' bill of rights in Congress, but Mr. Fletcher has the backing of cigarette manufacturers, whom Mr. Baesler has criticized for buying foreign tobacco.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baesler is a fiscal conservative who supports gun control and abortion rights, two issues that Mr. Fletcher strongly opposes. The National Rifle Association and religious conservatives have vowed to defeat Mr. Baesler. Each side has traded radio ads, with a television bombardment expected this summer.</p>
        <p>The election outcome probably will turn on rural areas like this.</p>
        <p>Step inside Wright's Grocery, where Ronald Wright, the store's 61-year-old owner, recalls when Mr. Baesler made sure that Mr. Wright's brother, stricken with leukemia, received his Social Security checks on time.</p>
        <p>''I feel like I asked him for something and he helped,'' said Mr. Wright. ''I'm going to vote for him.''</p>
        <p>Contested Races</p>
        <p>For all the attention the presidential race has received this year, the battle for control of the House of Representatives is shaping up as an equally significant political struggle. The Republicans hold a slim six-seat majority, and a few critical races could tip the balance either way. Between now and November this series will examine many of the contested races around the country.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE HOUSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
