<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When 'Slightly Better' Means a Great Deal</title>
    <meta content="03CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE0DF1239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When 'Slightly Better' Means a Great Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott bridge column on questions between partners (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is unlikely that Alfred, Lord Tennyson, had bridge or even whist in mind when he wrote, ''For all my mind is clouded with a doubt.'' We all spend much of our bridge lives clouded in doubt, and whenever possible try to arrange for partner to make the crucial decision for us.</p>
        <p>This is common enough at low levels, but experts often pass the buck when the partnership is committed to slam. A bid of five no-trump, following four no-trump, for example, asks about kings, but otherwise is a grand slam force, inquiring about trump honors, when a trump suit has been clearly agreed. When neither of these applies, the bid simply shows doubt, and asks partner to select the appropriate strain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is unlikely that Alfred, Lord Tennyson, had bridge or even whist in mind when he wrote, ''For all my mind is clouded with a doubt.'' We all spend much of our bridge lives clouded in doubt, and whenever possible try to arrange for partner to make the crucial decision for us.</p>
        <p>This is common enough at low levels, but experts often pass the buck when the partnership is committed to slam. A bid of five no-trump, following four no-trump, for example, asks about kings, but otherwise is a grand slam force, inquiring about trump honors, when a trump suit has been clearly agreed. When neither of these applies, the bid simply shows doubt, and asks partner to select the appropriate strain.</p>
        <p>Much more rarely, it is possible to express doubt at the seven-level, and the diagramed deal is an example. North and South were Bob Morris and Eddie Wold of Houston, who were en route to victory in the Canadian National Championships in Toronto this year.</p>
        <p>The first two rounds of bidding showed that there was a fit in two suits, but spades were provisionally chosen. When North later bid four no-trump, using Roman Keycard Blackwood, his partner could respond five clubs. This showed zero or three key cards, with the spade king counting together with two aces. Five no-trump asked South to show a specific king, and he therefore bid six clubs.</p>
        <p>Now North wanted to play a grand slam, but was not sure whether it should be in spades or diamonds. The solidity of the suit was the issue, so when North bid seven clubs, indicating a cloud of doubt, South knew what to do. He bid seven spades, because he had the spade jack but lacked the diamond jack. Holding the diamond jack, he would have bid seven of that suit, and North would have claimed after the first trick.</p>
        <p>Seven spades was slightly superior to seven diamonds, with a five-three fit rather than a five-four fit. And the ''slightly'' turned out to matter. After a trump lead, South drew trumps and cashed the club king. He then cashed the diamond ace, and was delighted to see West discard. Now he crossed to the diamond king, threw a diamond on the club ace and reverted to diamonds. A ruff established dummy's last diamond, which  provided a discard for the potential heart loser and brought home the grand slam. In the replay North-South reached seven diamonds and perhaps thought they were unlucky to fail. In a sense they were, but they were, just slightly, in the wrong grand slam and were heavily punished.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
