<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deadly Journeys</title>
    <meta content="03MON2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dover (Eng)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4DB1239F930A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deadly Journeys</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on death of 58 Chinese immigrants found suffocated in airless container truck in Dover, Eng; calls for international cooperation to crack down on rising global traffic in illegal aliens; also calls for moves to help victims of trade</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The death of 58 Chinese immigrants found suffocated in an airless container truck at the port of Dover, England, last month provided stark witness to the rising global traffic in people who illegally cross borders and whole continents in search of a better life. The Chinese immigrants reportedly traveled for four months by way of Russia and Central Europe to get from their home in China's Fujian province to England. They represented only a tiny part of the flow of millions making dangerous journeys to distant lands.</p>
        <p>In 1993, 10 Chinese immigrants died trying to swim to shore when the Golden Venture, a ship carrying nearly 300 immigrants from southern China, ran aground off Queens. In 1995, 18 Sri Lankans were found dead in a container truck in Hungary. In 1998, seven Mexicans died in the California desert, abandoned by smugglers. Reports of these catastrophes, however, have not discouraged other people from migrating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The death of 58 Chinese immigrants found suffocated in an airless container truck at the port of Dover, England, last month provided stark witness to the rising global traffic in people who illegally cross borders and whole continents in search of a better life. The Chinese immigrants reportedly traveled for four months by way of Russia and Central Europe to get from their home in China's Fujian province to England. They represented only a tiny part of the flow of millions making dangerous journeys to distant lands.</p>
        <p>In 1993, 10 Chinese immigrants died trying to swim to shore when the Golden Venture, a ship carrying nearly 300 immigrants from southern China, ran aground off Queens. In 1995, 18 Sri Lankans were found dead in a container truck in Hungary. In 1998, seven Mexicans died in the California desert, abandoned by smugglers. Reports of these catastrophes, however, have not discouraged other people from migrating.</p>
        <p>The trade in illegal migration is growing partly because more countries have tightened legal avenues for immigration, as has happened in Europe. The fall of the Berlin Wall is often cited as a factor because it opened Central and Eastern Europe as a migration route. But there are few reliable statistics in this field, and even categorizing criminal activities can be difficult since the illegal transport of people can vary from individuals paying smugglers to help them cross borders to individuals who are kidnapped or trapped into slavery by traffickers for the sex industry. The common characteristic is that all of the trade operates underground, with victims who are in no position to report abuse. Evidence that the industry exists tends to surface only when smuggled migrants are found dead, or when those in bondage manage to escape.</p>
        <p>Conservative estimates suggest that some 700,000 women and children are illegally transported for sexual and labor exploitation each year, with at least 50,000 brought into the United States. The total number of migrants smuggled across borders is more than four million a year worldwide.</p>
        <p>The International Organization for Migration estimates that roughly 400,000 people are smuggled into Western Europe alone each year. Smuggling into the United States has also increased. The Immigration and Naturalization Service has found that illegal border crossers are relying more heavily on smugglers, and that the number of smuggled people apprehended has risen from 138,000 in 1997 to 247,000 in 1999.</p>
        <p>Fighting this trade is extremely difficult, in part because governments know so little about these cross-border enterprises. Even with the arrest of the Dutch truck driver and several others in connection with the Dover case, there is scant information about that operation. Still, it is clear the smugglers had to be part of a sophisticated, highly flexible network that could manage the trip across two continents. Their profits are high. Chinese migrants are thought to pay at least $25,000 to be smuggled to Europe. The global trade is believed to be worth more than $7 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Not much can be done in the short term to deal with the main factors, poverty and persecution, that lie at the root of these sad migrations. Nor can any single country combat transnational trafficking by itself. It will take the cooperation of countries that are part of migration pipelines in both investigations and prosecutions. The European Union, in the wake of the deaths in Dover, may well be pushed to consider a common asylum policy. Many countries need to enact anti-trafficking laws. Much more also needs to be done to help victims of this trade, who could, if protected, testify against traffickers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
