<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Williams Hurt; Pettitte Wins Again</title>
    <meta content="05YANK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Royals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Kansas City Royals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2DA1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Williams Hurt; Pettitte Wins Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Kansas City Royals, 4-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An inning or two passed before all of Bernie Williams's teammates realized that he had been removed from tonight's game after he strained his rib cage again. They will all be fully aware of his status, however, if the injury lingers into next month.</p>
        <p>The Yankees believe he will recover before the postseason, but rib-cage injuries are delicate and another setback could be serious. They won without Williams tonight, 4-3, barely holding their slim lead against the Kansas City Royals through anxious moments in the eighth and ninth innings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An inning or two passed before all of Bernie Williams's teammates realized that he had been removed from tonight's game after he strained his rib cage again. They will all be fully aware of his status, however, if the injury lingers into next month.</p>
        <p>The Yankees believe he will recover before the postseason, but rib-cage injuries are delicate and another setback could be serious. They won without Williams tonight, 4-3, barely holding their slim lead against the Kansas City Royals through anxious moments in the eighth and ninth innings.</p>
        <p>Andy Pettitte improved his record to 17-7, Jorge Posada had three hits and increased his batting average to .301, and David Justice drove in a run, his 100th of the season. But the Yankees (77-57) tend to think big picture -- as in the playoffs and the World Series -- and Williams's status seemed to dominate the thoughts of Manager Joe Torre after the game. ''At this time,'' Torre said, he does not think Williams's injury will linger. ''If it goes a week and he's still hurting, then you wait and see.''</p>
        <p>The switch-hitting Williams initially strained the right side of his rib cage on Aug. 18 and missed little more than a week before returning to the lineup -- primarily as a right-handed hitter, because the strain bothered him more while batting from the left side. Williams said tonight that when he returned, he felt strong and he was swinging hard; Torre wondered aloud after tonight's game if Williams might have been more sore than he was letting on.</p>
        <p>Batting in the first inning, Williams swung at and missed Mac Suzuki's first pitch, a split-finger fastball, and felt a pain in his side. Torre did not notice Williams's physical reaction to the discomfort, but the trainer Gene Monahan did, and when Williams returned to the dugout after playing defense in the bottom of the first inning, Torre cornered Williams and essentially forced him into confessing his pain.</p>
        <p>''It's very frustrating,'' Williams said. ''It's certainly very bad timing. We'll see how I feel tomorrow. I'm taking it on a daily basis.''</p>
        <p>Williams figures to miss at least the next five games, when the Yankees face right-handed starters, and probably more, in light of the Yankees' six-game lead over Boston in the American League East and Torre's dedication to getting the team prepared for the postseason. He has stressed to all his players that they must be honest about their ailments now. ''We don't have time to get something well, if we have a major problem,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Pettitte said it ''would be a huge blow to us'' to lose Williams for a long time, ''banged up as it is in the outfield.'' Right fielder Paul O'Neill is limping with a hip pointer, and Justice, the left fielder, is playing despite a strained right groin.</p>
        <p>Williams's injury will almost certainly end his bid to surpass one of Mickey Mantle's notable achievements. Mantle drove in 130 runs in 1956, setting a major league season record by a switch-hitter, and San Diego's Ken Caminiti tied that mark in 1996. Williams had 80 runs batted in over 83 games at the All-Star Game break, and now he has 111 R.B.I. with 28 games to play -- and he will miss some or most of those games.</p>
        <p>Pettitte can still reach a personal milestone, now that he is within three victories of 20 for the season, but tonight's victory did not come easily. Working quickly, Pettitte allowed eight hits in seven innings, six of those to the No. 3 and No. 4 batters for Kansas City, Mike Sweeney and Jermaine Dye.</p>
        <p>The Yankees led, 4-2, in the eighth. Johnny Damon doubled to lead off, however, and after Pettitte struck out Carlos Beltran, Sweeney and Dye were due to hit again. Torre went to the mound. ''What are the odds?'' Pettitte asked about the chances of allowing more hits to Sweeney and Dye, but Torre was unimpressed, calling on Jeff Nelson.</p>
        <p>Nelson, one of those chastised by George Steinbrenner last week, allowed Damon to score on Sweeney's infield single and prompted separate meetings with Posada and the pitching coach Mel Stottlemyre before striking out Joe Randa to end the eighth. Nelson lurched off the mound happily, waving his arms; Nelson needed that outing, Torre mused.</p>
        <p>Mariano Rivera took over for the ninth, and his relative vulnerability was apparent again. There were a leadoff single and a two-out walk, and the pinch-hitter Wilson Delgado -- formerly with the Yankees this season -- beat out an infield hit. Bases loaded, Sweeney at the plate. Rivera opened with a high fastball, and Sweeney hacked confidently at it, fouling it off, an uncharacteristically aggressive swing against the Yankees' closer. With two strikes, Sweeney smashed a liner to center, directly at Clay Bellinger, who had replaced Williams in center.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Reliever RAMIRO MENDOZA threw three innings in a simulated game. Although he said he had little success getting his sinker, his signature pitch, to sink, he does feel he will be able to pitch in a couple of days, if he does not have a setback returning from tendinitis in his right shoulder.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
