<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology's Gender Gap</title>
    <meta content="05TUE3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/05/opinion/05TUE3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228122"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4D61E30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="386" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology's Gender Gap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial laments fact that fewer women are entering booming technology fields; says technology industry badly needs more workers and that women represent major untapped source of talent that could solve shortage (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The barriers that keep minorities from enjoying full access to the technological revolution have been widely commented on. Less talked about is another ''digital divide,'' the fact that fewer women are entering today's booming technology fields.</p>
        <p>Studies show that women are active users of the new technology and that female Internet users slightly outnumber male users. But the paucity of women creating that technology is cause for concern. The most recent National Science Foundation statistics show that between 1984 and 1997, the proportion of women receiving bachelor's degrees in computer science dropped from 37 percent to 27 percent. Currently, women make up only 20 percent of the information technology work force.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The barriers that keep minorities from enjoying full access to the technological revolution have been widely commented on. Less talked about is another ''digital divide,'' the fact that fewer women are entering today's booming technology fields.</p>
        <p>Studies show that women are active users of the new technology and that female Internet users slightly outnumber male users. But the paucity of women creating that technology is cause for concern. The most recent National Science Foundation statistics show that between 1984 and 1997, the proportion of women receiving bachelor's degrees in computer science dropped from 37 percent to 27 percent. Currently, women make up only 20 percent of the information technology work force.</p>
        <p>Because the industry serves the broader needs of society, the technology workplace ought to reflect the interests of both men and women. The technology industry badly needs more workers. Women represent a major untapped source of talent that could solve the shortage.</p>
        <p>Why are there few women in these fields? One reason is that girls receive little encouragement to explore computers early in their schooling. Most computer games are male-oriented, and there are few female role models in technical industries. Women who perform well in high school math and science are often put off by male-dominated lecture halls in college. Women who do end up joining the technology work force have complained about a lack of opportunity for advancement and an absence of support and mentoring.</p>
        <p>Changes in grade school curriculums could help redress the imbalance by, for example, using computer programs as tools and teaching aids in all disciplines, from history to music to biology. Mentoring programs at all levels of education, from middle school to college, can also provide women with needed support. The National Science Foundation is dedicating $2 million in grant money to find  ways of increasing women's participation in technological fields. Without this and other steps, women will continue to be discouraged from entering the world of high technology.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
