<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="05MBRF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5DA1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Steve Strunsky</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>SOUTH PLAINFIELD: GIRL HURT BY PARADE FLOAT  A 10-year-old girl was seriously injured at a Labor Day parade when she fell beneath a flatbed trailer carrying cheerleaders from the Pop Warner youth football league. The girl, Shakera Jones of South Plainfield, ran toward the float carrying a bottle of water for a friend riding on it, slipped or lost her balance, and was run over by the rear wheels, said Lt. Paul Brembt of the South Plainfield Police. She was in critical condition after surgery, Lieutenant Brembt said. He said the driver of the float, Mark Tomei of South Plainfield, was hospitalized with chest pains. No summonses were issued.  Robert Hanley (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>SOUTH PLAINFIELD: GIRL HURT BY PARADE FLOAT  A 10-year-old girl was seriously injured at a Labor Day parade when she fell beneath a flatbed trailer carrying cheerleaders from the Pop Warner youth football league. The girl, Shakera Jones of South Plainfield, ran toward the float carrying a bottle of water for a friend riding on it, slipped or lost her balance, and was run over by the rear wheels, said Lt. Paul Brembt of the South Plainfield Police. She was in critical condition after surgery, Lieutenant Brembt said. He said the driver of the float, Mark Tomei of South Plainfield, was hospitalized with chest pains. No summonses were issued.  Robert Hanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>WEST LONG BRANCH: FRESHMAN LUXURY  A housing shortage at Monmouth University here means that 120 freshmen have been assigned to live in a hotel in town with private baths, air-conditioning and other amenities not found on campus. The college will provide shuttle and security services. But feelings were mixed as the students, about 10 percent of the freshman class, moved into the Esplanade Hotel on Sunday. Although ''the accommodations here are much better,'' Nicole Sagui told The Asbury Park Press, ''I'd rather be in a dorm, and my campus experience may now be a little bit different.''  (AP)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: CUNY PROGRESS REPORT  The City University of New York is about to issue a brief progress report promoting its accomplishments since the appointment a year ago of Matthew Goldstein, left, as chancellor and Herman Badillo and Benno C. Schmidt Jr. as chairman and vice chairman of the board. Among the accomplishments cited are: the tests it has imposed to assure students' competence;  its efforts to hire new professors; and its partnerships with the Board of Education. The university's lean finances are not addressed, but two of CUNY's former critics, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and Gov. George E. Pataki, express their confidence in the university.  Karen W. Arenson (NYT)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: HEARING FOR LENNON'S KILLER  Mark David Chapman, who fatally shot John Lennon outside his Manhattan apartment building in 1980, is scheduled for his first parole hearing next month. Mr. Chapman, 45, who was sentenced to 20 years to life in prison at Attica, could be released by December. He works as a clerk in the law library at Attica Correctional Facility, and has expressed regrets for the killing.  (AP)</p>
        <p>SYRACUSE: IMMUNIZATION HEARING  A federal judge is to decide whether a 5-year-old girl can enter kindergarten without the required immunizations. The girl's mother, Kelly Turner, whose church, the Congregation of Universal Wisdom, opposes immunizations, asked Judge Frederick Scullin of Federal District Court in Syracuse to order the Liverpool School District to let her daughter enter school when classes begin today. District officials contend that the church, founded by a chiropractor, is not a legitimate religion. Judge Scullin signed an order last week allowing the girl, Victoria, to go to school at least until the case is heard on Monday.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW WINDSOR: OFFICER'S SON KILLED  The 5-year-old son of a New York City police officer died Sunday, apparently after firing his father's loaded weapon, the police said. The New Windsor Police Department is investigating reports that the officer, David Reveille, placed his loaded .38-caliber revolver on top of the refrigerator, and that his son David apparently pulled up a stool, retrieved the gun and fired it. The child died from a gunshot wound in the stomach at Good Samaritan Hospital in Suffern, the hospital said.  Elissa Gootman (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: BOX CUTTERS SOLD ILLEGALLY  Of the 59 stores visited in a recent undercover investigation, 16 sold box cutters to teenagers illegally, the city consumer affairs commissioner, Jane Hoffman, said yesterday. Under a 1998 city law, the minimum age at which one may buy a box cutter is 21, yet the police seized 850 of them in city schools last year, she said. None of the 11 Manhattan stores sold cutters to undercover teenagers, Ms. Hoffman said, but 5 out of 10 on Staten Island did.  (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>WINDSOR: STANDOFF ENDS IN DEATH  A 45-year-old man died after an eight-hour standoff with the police yesterday that ended when the house where he had barricaded himself went up in flames, the police said. The man, Stephen Pawlicki, barricaded himself about 8:30 a.m. during a domestic dispute, the police said. Later, neighbors heard gunshots, but Mr. Pawlicki's wife, who said the man was armed with two handguns, was able to crawl out of the house through a window. The police said they were talking with Mr. Pawlicki by telephone until about 3 p.m., when a fire they believe he set began to burn out of control. The cause of death has not been determined.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>STAMFORD: A MASS FOR JANITORS  Our Lady of Montserrat Roman Catholic Church held a Labor Day Mass on behalf of two union janitors caught in a struggle between their union and their employer. Local 531 of the Service Employees International Union is seeking a new contract for janitors at Temco Building Maintenance, many of whom are paid $6.15 an hour with no benefits, said Autumn Weintraub, a union organizer. She said the two had been fired on Aug. 25 for seeking help for a new contract from a Temco client in Stamford, G.E. Capital. Ms. Weintraub said that 47 Temco janitors, mainly Hispanic immigrants, at three office buildings have struck in solidarity. Temco said in a statement that the workers had not been fired, but had been suspended with pay, for letting a union organizer posing as an employee into a company work site.  (NYT)</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: ARRAIGNMENT IN TWO DEATHS  A young man wanted in connection with the shooting death of two women and the wounding of another was returned to Connecticut yesterday and is to be arraigned in Hartford today, the police said. The man, Jessie Campbell, 20, of Bloomfield, was arrested last month in Michigan on capital felony murder charges. The police said he killed Latasha Logan, 20, the mother of his 4-year-old son, and Desire Privette, 19, and wounded her aunt, Carolyn Privette, 39, as they sat on a porch in the Asylum Hill section of Hartford on Aug. 26.  (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
