<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Style Fantasies Show the Influence Of a Photographer's Stark Reality</title>
    <meta content="05DRES$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/05/living/05DRES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">diCorcia, Philip-Lorca</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED71E30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1298" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Style Fantasies Show the Influence Of a Photographer's Stark Reality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses work of fashion photographer Philip-Lorca diCorcia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the half-dozen or so fashion shoots he has done, most of them for W magazine during the past few years, Philip-Lorca diCorcia has staged unnerving narratives like one titled ''A Perfect World,'' in which things don't seem perfect at all. Here, a patrician housewife, frozen looking, her face harshly lighted, appears as if she'd need no more than a few shots of Tanqueray and a splash of Schwepps to push her into doing something Medea-like. In another series, set in Havana, a model is cast as a disconsolate-looking Batista-era office worker who is equally blank in her nighttime job as a call girl. Should the reader forget that there are dresses to be looked at, the text alerts you: ''Havana was once a nightclub hot spot. These days, it's the perfect backdrop for sober day clothes or racy little evening looks. Think brief, briefer, briefest.''</p>
        <p>Fashion copy generally borders on the ludicrous -- all the more so when appended to Mr. diCorcia's pictures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the half-dozen or so fashion shoots he has done, most of them for W magazine during the past few years, Philip-Lorca diCorcia has staged unnerving narratives like one titled ''A Perfect World,'' in which things don't seem perfect at all. Here, a patrician housewife, frozen looking, her face harshly lighted, appears as if she'd need no more than a few shots of Tanqueray and a splash of Schwepps to push her into doing something Medea-like. In another series, set in Havana, a model is cast as a disconsolate-looking Batista-era office worker who is equally blank in her nighttime job as a call girl. Should the reader forget that there are dresses to be looked at, the text alerts you: ''Havana was once a nightclub hot spot. These days, it's the perfect backdrop for sober day clothes or racy little evening looks. Think brief, briefer, briefest.''</p>
        <p>Fashion copy generally borders on the ludicrous -- all the more so when appended to Mr. diCorcia's pictures.</p>
        <p>Mr. diCorcia has worked as an art photographer for well over 20 years, and for most of that time he has had nothing to do with fashion. But the fashion world, now so busy appropriating his disquieting style, has decided it wants to have something to do with him.</p>
        <p>Now 47, Mr. diCorcia came of age at the same time as Nan Goldin, a photographer with whom he has maintained a long and strained friendship. Although Mr. diCorcia's dispassionate family pictures and surreal street photography have been the subject of exhibitions around the world, including a 1993 show at the Museum of Modern Art, he never received the kind of widespread attention that Ms. Goldin did for her emotionally charged images of battered women and drug addicts. Mr. diCorcia's exposure through fashion has made him a cult figure. In recent years, the price of his prints has tripled. ''Everyone I know wants to buy him,'' said Alice George, the photo editor of Details magazine and a private curator.</p>
        <p>''I've come into a good position by default,'' Mr. diCorcia said recently, ''because people are so hyperbolic. The few things that speak quietly stand out now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. diCorcia is a beneficiary of fashion photography's ever-increasing infatuation with the art world, which in more vulgar instances has resulted in images like the ones of a male midget dressed in Gucci that the artist Andres Serrano shot for the September issue of Flaunt magazine. Four years ago, Dennis Freedman, the creative director of W, who was a fan of the pictures Mr. diCorcia took of his family during the 1970's and 80's, approached him about doing fashion photography; he offered him carte blanche.</p>
        <p>Despite his fortuitous position, however, Mr. diCorcia, who lives in New York and visits a double-wide trailer he keeps in the Catskills, is disdainful of both the art and fashion worlds, and the cozy bed they now share. ''Most art dealers are indistinguishable from fashion people,'' he said. ''They're in the Hamptons. They embody the same kind of materialism. Everybody's downtown in Prada. Fashion needs credibility, art needs money and what the two worlds really share is a complete denial of history.''</p>
        <p>As Jason Schmidt, a former assistant and now a photographer himself, put it, Mr. diCorcia ''is the most cantankerous, wonderfully embittered person in the world.''</p>
        <p>And perhaps not completely without reason. Picking up a fashion magazine nowadays has become, to some extent, a reflexive exercise in surveying the influence Mr. diCorcia's work has had on those who take pictures and those who publish them. ''I'm attracted to the narrative, to the fact that the pictures are somewhat dangerous and very American and completely unsentimental,'' said Justine Parsons, a young fashion and portrait photographer, who freely admits to the impact Mr. diCorcia has had on her work.</p>
        <p>Young photographers seem to fear nothing so much at the moment as seeming sentimental. Most often, it is the stylistic elements of Mr. diCorcia's work that they plunder -- the dramatic lighting that articulates a subject's blank face, the setups meant to suggest the deadening or horrific aspects of domestic life.</p>
        <p>It is impossible, for example, to look at Steven Meisel's shoot in July's Italian Vogue of a model wandering aimlessly about a suburban house, staring out beyond the furniture and appliances, and not think of a well-known picture by Mr. diCorcia of his brother Mario looking into a refrigerator and taking stock of a lot more than what's in it.</p>
        <p>Occasionally, the sampling is even more literal, as in last fall's Kate Spade ad campaign that featured a photo by one of Mr. diCorcia's former assistants, Alexei Hay, which was a nearly exact replica of one of Mr. diCorcia's ''Perfect World'' pictures. Mr. Hay has described, in the July-August issue of Brill's Content, how the Kate Spade art directors showed him the diCorcia shoot and suggested he imitate it.</p>
        <p>Representatives for Kate Spade did not return calls.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Freedman's view, Mr. diCorcia, who is known to friends as P. L., has been copied with varying degrees of talent. ''You can imitate someone's work superficially, but you can't imitate the intelligence of someone's pictures,'' he said. Of a new ad for Chloe, shot by Taryn Simon and reminiscent of Mr. diCorcia's work, Mr. Freedman said, ''I just think it's sad.''</p>
        <p>What the acolytes generally miss is the tension Mr. diCorcia creates in his pictures. His subjects often appear to want to be somewhere else, but the world he creates with his camera is so rigidly defined, so locked up, it is impossible for the viewer to imagine where that somewhere else could be.</p>
        <p>Mr. diCorcia was born in Hartford, the son of an Italian-American father and a mother who left the family when he was very young. ''She was very erudite,'' Mr. diCorcia said. She attached names of poets and scholars to all her children. He is named Philip-Lorca for Federico Garcia Lorca. He has a sister named Auden.</p>
        <p>In the late 70's, Mr. diCorcia attended graduate school in fine arts at Yale, where he currently teaches photography. With a grant from the National Endowment for the Arts in 1989, he embarked on his ''Hustler'' series. For this project, he sought out young men on Santa Monica Boulevard in Los Angeles and photographed them in scenes -- motel rooms, outside fast-food restaurants -- that were prearranged with the help of an assistant. The bleak-looking men may or not have been hustlers; the point of the pictures is that they appear to be social documents but are in fact inventions.</p>
        <p>Mr. diCorcia's wife at the time, Noemi Bonazzi, said that during the late 80's and early 90's, her husband often became discouraged and found it difficult to promote his work. ''He doesn't have a scheming mind,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Eventually, the couple and their infant son moved to Naples, Italy, for a sabbatical. ''He was really at a low point,'' Ms. Bonazzi said. ''He didn't know what to do with himself. He'd say, 'Is it ever going to happen?'  Not long after the couple returned to New York, in 1996, Ms. Bonazzi said, things started to turn around, with Mr. diCorcia's inclusion in the Whitney Biennial and the start of his fashion work.</p>
        <p>And for all his orneriness, Mr. diCorcia seems proud of his fashion photography. ''It's not the sub line to the stuff at Pace,'' he said, referring to the gallery that represents him. ''It's not the Miu Miu.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
