<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hormone Replacement Therapy: Why They Do It, or Avoid It</title>
    <meta content="05INTR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000908T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Menopause</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Estrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">muha, laura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DuMont, Beryl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hills, Diane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landy, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quintana, Valerina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldman, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lang, Debra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Therapy and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Estrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Menopause</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Estrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Menopause</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hormones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDA1E30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hormone Replacement Therapy: Why They Do It, or Avoid It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA MUHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">muha, laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Menopausal women weigh a number of factors in deciding whether or not to undergo estrogen replacement therapy; six women tell how they made their decisions; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For many menopausal women, the question of whether to take hormones is one of the most crucial health decisions of their middle years -- and one of the most confusing.</p>
        <p>Yes, the hormones relieve the hot flashes and the night sweats that plague many women during menopause, and they protect against brittle bones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For many menopausal women, the question of whether to take hormones is one of the most crucial health decisions of their middle years -- and one of the most confusing.</p>
        <p>Yes, the hormones relieve the hot flashes and the night sweats that plague many women during menopause, and they protect against brittle bones.</p>
        <p>But does they prevent heart disease as researchers have long believed or do they make no difference to a woman's heart disease risk, as some studies are now hinting? And what about breast cancer? With some studies indicating long term use may slightly increase a woman's risk and others failing to find any increase, where does the truth lie and how much should women worry? Then there are the questions of weight gain and mood swings. While many women believe that estrogen replacement makes them gain weight but soothes their moodiness, these effects are not found in scientific studies. ''You find yourself trying to decide which is the lesser of the evils,'' said Beryl DuMont, 55, an office administrator from North Hanover, N.J., and one of a half-dozen women who recently discussed their feelings about hormone replacement therapy.</p>
        <p>''Do you take estrogen to prevent one problem and risk getting another one that you don't have and might otherwise never get?'' Mrs. DuMont wondered. She stopped her first hormone treatment because of a  bad reaction but is considering a second.</p>
        <p>Estimates of the number of women who take or have taken hormones for the symptoms of menopause range from 10 percent to more than 40 percent, with factors as diverse as education and geography playing roles. One study published last year in The Annals of Internal Medicine found that college-educated women and those living in the South and West were significantly more likely to use hormones than those living in the Northeast and Midwest.</p>
        <p>But according to the American College of Preventive Medicine, only about a third of women who use hormones take them as prescribed, something that may reflect women's fears about the side effects of such medication.</p>
        <p>What is known is this: In the short-term, hormone replacement therapy controls the hot flashes, night sweats and vaginal dryness experienced by many women during menopause. In the long term it also decreases a woman's risk of osteoporosis, the brittle-bone disease that can lead to life-threatening fractures. Estrogen also appears to increase a woman's level of good cholesterol and reduce the bad, while promoting blood clotting.</p>
        <p>However, numerous studies have pointed to a link between a slightly higher risk of breast cancer and hormone use, and two reports published this year suggest the risk is greatest in women taking both estrogen and progestin, as opposed to estrogen alone.</p>
        <p>That came as a surprise to many researchers who had believed estrogen was the primary culprit in the breast cancer-hormone link. It also was demoralizing because progestin is given in combination with estrogen specifically to lower the risk of endometrial cancer, a risk that increases more than tenfold when a woman takes estrogen alone.</p>
        <p>Also this year, one of the most widely held assumptions about hormone replacement therapy -- that it helps prevent cardiovascular disease -- was called into question. Just two weeks ago, researchers reported that estrogen did nothing to slow the progression of heart disease in women whose arteries had already been partly blocked by it. Whether estrogen prevents heart disease remains unanswered.</p>
        <p>More definitive results will come in 2005, when results from the first large-scale, long-term study of hormone use become available. But that comes as small comfort to women now trying to decide whether to take, or continue taking, hormones.</p>
        <p>Some try to circumvent the issue by experimenting with estrogens derived from plant sources, believing that these so-called natural estrogens are less likely to cause long-term side effects than synthetic estrogens. Yet there is little research to prove either effectiveness of the herbs or the lack of side effects, said Dr. Lila Nachtigall, a professor of obstetrics and gynecology at the New York University College of Medicine and one of the nation's leading experts on hormone replacement therapy.</p>
        <p>''Women think that if it's over the counter or herbal or called a nutrient, that means it's safe,'' Dr. Nachtigall said. ''They don't realize that it doesn't have F.D.A. approval; they don't know that it can be sold without quality control, without science.''</p>
        <p>In the end, the decision a woman makes can involve any number of factors: her personal and family health history, her physical symptoms, her feelings about taking medication, her doctor's opinion and how much she trusts it, what friends have told her about their experiences during menopause.</p>
        <p>What follows is what some women had to say.</p>
        <p>Beryl DuMont, 55  North Hanover, N.J., office assistant, Scottish Widows Investment Management</p>
        <p>I get migraines, which have always been linked to my period. It used to be three a year, but when I started menopause last year, I started getting them every week.</p>
        <p>My gynecologist said estrogen might help and rattled off a whole ream of other benefits, too: it's supposed to help your bones, your general well-being.</p>
        <p>I was concerned because seven years ago I had a breast lump removed; it was benign, but at that time, the surgeon said to me, ''Under no circumstances go through any form of hormone replacement therapy.''</p>
        <p>When I asked my gynecologist about it, though, she said that just because I started taking hormones didn't mean I had to stay on them. That was a good point, and probably why I finally said, ''Yes, I'll try it.''</p>
        <p>She prescribed the estrogen patch; I was supposed to use it for three or four weeks, then add progesterone. But when I read the brochure that came with the package, I got nervous. It talks about breast cancer and endometrial cancer, which scared me because I have endometriosis. But I thought, ''My doctor knows my medical history, and she's still recommending that I try it, so I guess it must be O.K.''</p>
        <p>The problem was, I didn't feel better while I was taking it. I was irritable, even more tired than I had been, and I kept waking up at night, although whether that was because of the estrogen itself or because I was afraid of it, I'm not sure.</p>
        <p>Finally, after a month, I got a migraine that didn't go away for five days; my hands were also swollen and tingly. I called the doctor's office and they said I was having a reaction and that I should stop.</p>
        <p>Now I'm in limbo. I just do not know what to think about this stuff. I'm supposed to go back to the doctor next month, and I haven't ruled out giving hormones another try.</p>
        <p>But in the meantime, I'm going to talk to my pharmacist; he's big on alternative medicine, and I thought I would ask him for something herbal. I know it's unproven, but so many people are doing all right with it; maybe it will help me, too.</p>
        <p>Diane Hill, 52  Monroe, La., lawyer</p>
        <p>I started taking hormones five years ago. My doctor was the one who brought it up. It was the first time I'd gone to her, and when she took my history, she asked me about symptoms of estrogen loss. At the time, I was having hot flashes; they weren't keeping me up at night, but I was waking up in a pool of water.</p>
        <p>My doctor said she recommended hormone replacement therapy, and gave me some samples. After I tried them for a while, I went ahead and filled the prescription.</p>
        <p>I do feel better physically, but the truth is, I'm concerned about taking this drug. I'm not a person who readily takes prescription medicine for anything, and when I first got the samples, I read all the package inserts and looked it up in medical journals, so I'm aware of some of the medical dangers of taking hormones. On the other hand, estrogen loss seems to be a precursor for osteoporosis and some of the other deficiency ailments of the aged, and therefore I think there are some benefits to having [supplemental] estrogen in my system.</p>
        <p>Actually, I don't take it as prescribed. I take it three days a week, and on the other days, I'm using soy and herbs -- black cohosh specifically -- which I learned about in my reading. I feel better about herbal supplements, because they're natural, not synthetic. They do help, but not enough for me to completely cut out the hormones.</p>
        <p>I've haven't told my doctor exactly what I'm doing; I don't think she'd approve. All I've said is that I'm not taking the hormones every day, but that I am taking them regularly. I think she suspects, but she doesn't ask questions.</p>
        <p>I hope that I will be able to drop the usage to one to two days a week, but right now I'll stay on them. It's probably been a year since I've fiddled with it. I seem to have a good combination now, where I can take it three days a week and go about my business.</p>
        <p>I'm still experimenting with my body to see what I need, and I'll probably continue the estrogen until I find some other way of accomplishing my goals -- of feeling as healthy as I did 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>Ann Landy, 58  Oakton, Va., senior associate with Caliber Associates, a behavioral research firm</p>
        <p>In a lot of ways, the choices were easier a decade ago, when I started taking hormones. Back then, it wasn't ''should we or shouldn't we?''; it was, ''Oh my God, there's something that can help!'' The recommendation from my physician was, ''Take this.'' So I did.</p>
        <p>Now, there's so much information out there that it's gotten very confusing. For instance, there's heart disease in my family, and for a long time I thought I was protecting myself against it by taking hormones. I've been very disappointed to read the latest studies that say that may not be the case -- although I'm still not convinced we have the full picture. Earlier this year, I went off hormones for three months; I was concerned because my breasts were always swollen and tender, and I weighed 20 pounds more than I did when I started.</p>
        <p>Almost immediately, the tenderness and swelling went away, and I dropped four pounds. But the night sweats and hot flashes -- one of the reasons I started taking hormones in the first place -- returned with a vengeance.</p>
        <p>Not long after that, I had to take a business trip, and I was miserable. Every two hours, I had a hot flash. I perspired so much that my suit was soaked; I was so embarrassed. I thought, ''Enough already!'' and went back to the doctor.</p>
        <p>He gave me a prescription for Prempro, and I started taking it again -- but only every other day, which seems to control the hot flashes without causing other symptoms. That's something I decided to do on my own, though. The prescription is for every day, and I haven't been back to the doctor to say, ''Is this O.K.?''</p>
        <p>There are probably good reasons for me to be taking this. Around the time I started menopause, I had a bone density study that showed some loss. But I still worry. I recently had a Pap test that showed atypical cells. Even though a repeat didn't find any sign of a problem, I can't help being concerned. Is there a connection to the hormones? Should I get off this stuff?</p>
        <p>I haven't made up my mind as to how long I'll stay on hormones. I'd like to try discontinuing them periodically to see what the impact is. In the meantime, I just hope I'm doing the right thing.</p>
        <p>Valerina Quintana, 51  Tucson, Ariz., director of the University of Arizona Career Development Center</p>
        <p>I'm not a person who likes taking medication. I keep a small bottle of aspirin in my medicine chest, but it usually expires before I get through it. So when I started menopause two years ago, I thought, ''O.K., this is a natural part of life, I can get through it naturally.''</p>
        <p>My problem was the mood swings. Outside, I was the picture of calmness and coolness, but inside, I was going crazy. I'd go to social functions and have to leave, because I felt weepy. Once, I was driving and I couldn't remember how to get where I was going. Another time, I forgot the name of a colleague I had worked with for eight years.</p>
        <p>My primary care physician gave me a prescription, but I put off getting it filled because I didn't like the idea of taking synthetic hormones. Then I went to a lecture by a naturopath about natural hormone replacement therapy. I really liked what I heard. Afterward, she gave everyone a free 30-minute consultation. She told me, ''You look healthy; you should be able to go through this with herbs.'' She suggested chaste berry and dong quai, but when I tried them, I felt like I needed something more. So I went to a compounding pharmacy [a pharmacy that makes up its own drugs from approved ingredients]. The pharmacist asked about the frequency of my symptoms and came up with a prescription based on that; she called my doctor to get his O.K.</p>
        <p>Now I take a daily troche containing tri-estrogen with progesterone, but they're natural, plant-based phytoestrogens, instead of being molecularly altered so they can be copyrighted. I also use a testosterone cream that I rub into my arms; it's also from natural sources, not artificial ones.</p>
        <p>Within a month, the mood swings started evening out and the hot flashes went away, although I will admit that my memory hasn't improved as much as I'd hoped; I recently started taking ginkgo biloba to see if that would help. The best part is that I don't have any side effects. My friends who are taking synthetic hormones say their breasts swell, and they sometime have spotting, but I don't have any of that.</p>
        <p>I feel really good about what I'm doing. I like the fact that my prescription is based on my symptoms, so it's uniquely my own; when you go to a doctor, they give you the same prescription as everyone else, and we're all different.</p>
        <p>Cathy Goldman, 59  Forest Hills, N.Y., retired</p>
        <p>There's one simple reason I'm not taking hormones: family history.</p>
        <p>My brother died of prostate cancer, and my mother, who's 89, had breast cancer.</p>
        <p>I have her body: we're both short, broad-boned women. When I look at her I think, ''What happened to her could happen to me.''</p>
        <p>Plus, I'm at high risk because I got my period at a very early age and never had children. So why take more chances?</p>
        <p>I've talked it over with my doctor, but she's never pushed me one way or the other. The last time I went in, I was having a lot of mood swings; I told her, ''I can't stand this; maybe I should go on hormones.'' She said she had no objection to my trying it for six months as long as I had a mammogram before and after. She gave me the prescription, but I just didn't have the guts to fill it.</p>
        <p>My sister-in-law was on hormone replacement therapy; she got breast cancer.</p>
        <p>My sister-in-law's sister was on hormone replacement therapy; she got breast cancer.</p>
        <p>I thought: ''What do I need this for? It's not worth the risk.''</p>
        <p>One gynecologist -- a friend, not the one that I go to -- said that if I were at risk of osteoporosis, it would be a different story. But when I had a bone scan, probably about five years ago, my doctor laughed and said, ''There are people who would kill for your bones,'' because they're so thick and heavy.</p>
        <p>Heart disease is a very big issue for me because my father died of it but I have been increasing my aerobic activity, going to the gym and doing things like that to counteract that risk.</p>
        <p>I'm also lucky because hot flashes have never been as much of an issue for me as they are for some women.</p>
        <p>I hate them, but when one hits, splashing my face with ice water is usually enough to relieve it. I know one woman who had to take a change of clothes with her to restaurants, because she'd get drenched. My whole outlook on hormones might have been different if that had happened to me.</p>
        <p>The other good thing is that I was retired by the time I started menopause, so I could tough it out in private.</p>
        <p>I sold advertising for one of the networks, and it would have been very difficult meeting with clients and dealing with hot flashes at the same time.</p>
        <p>Debra Lang, 54  Huntington Woods, Mich., assistant superintendent for elementary education, Bloomfield Hills school district</p>
        <p>I've been on hormone replacement therapy for six or seven years. What drove me to it were the hot flashes. You're burning up from the inside out, turning beet red, and you get horrible sleep disturbances. I have a demanding job, and I can't perform in peak condition when I'm exhausted.</p>
        <p>Within a few weeks [of starting on hormones], the hot flashes stopped. But the real surprise was how much it improved the quality of my life in ways I hadn't expected.</p>
        <p>I'd been having memory problems; I'd forget words or switch them around, which was debilitating, since I give a lot of speeches as part of my job. But I never associated the problem with menopause until I started taking estrogen and realized that I was no longer having trouble.</p>
        <p>The other problem I hadn't attributed to menopause was depression. I chalked it up to my kids growing up and leaving home. But as soon as I started on hormones, that disappeared, too, and my energy returned. I did have problems with breakthrough bleeding, which isn't something you want to deal with after you haven't had your period for a while.</p>
        <p>They tried a D. &amp; C., then increased my progestin, but I gained a lot of weight. I seriously considered going off hormones because of that, but I kept coming back to how  much better it made me feel. Now I'm taking a new drug, femhrt, which is a synthetic and has a smaller dose of progestin. I'm feeling much better.</p>
        <p>But I will admit the breast cancer piece is worrisome. The only person in my family who had it was my maternal aunt, and I decided she was far enough removed in the family tree to not make that a major factor in my decision.</p>
        <p>But my friends and I talk about the risk a lot. We can get really philosophical that more of us are going to die from heart disease, but the truth is, we still worry, and all of us are going to wonder if we made the  right decision if we get breast cancer.</p>
        <p>The way I've dealt with it is to step back and look at the whole picture. I've concluded that my quality of life is so good I'm not willing to give that up for what may be in the future. Instead, I try to get mammograms regularly, do monthly self-examination -- and stay on top of the literature.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 8, 2000, Friday  Credits in Science Times on Tuesday for two pictures of women with an article about views of hormone replacement therapy misspelled the surname of a photographer. He is Michael Geissinger, not Guissinger.</p>
        <p>In addition, two credits with the article were reversed. The picture of Valerina Quintana was by Norma Jean Gargasz; the one of Ann Landy was by Mr. Geissinger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 8, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>Credits in Science Times on Tuesday for two pictures of women with an article about views of hormone replacement therapy misspelled the surname of a photographer. He is Michael Geissinger, not Guissinger.</p>
        <p>In addition, two credits with the article were reversed. The picture of Valerina Quintana was by Norma Jean Gargasz; the one of Ann Landy was by Mr. Geissinger.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
