<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Power in TV Confessions</title>
    <meta content="05SCHL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Court TV (Network)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schlieff, Henry</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Confessions (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7DA1330F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Power in TV Confessions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Henry Schleiff</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Court TV chairman and chief executive Henry Schleiff on reality-based television programs defends network against criticisms of its Confessions series, which plays taped confessions of murderers and other violent felons; says providing unsettling but unfiltered look into part of criminal justice system is both logical and appropriate since transparency, particularly as it appplies to government, is important ingredient of democracy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The success of shows like ''Survivor'' has many wondering where reality television is headed. This question has recently come up with our own program, ''Confessions,'' which takes an unfiltered look at convicted murderers and other violent felons.</p>
        <p>Reality television actually comes in two forms. The first, which might be called ''manufactured reality,'' includes shows like ''Survivor'' and ''Big Brother'' in which real people (as opposed to actors) are taped in contrived environments, often with Hollywood production techniques.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The success of shows like ''Survivor'' has many wondering where reality television is headed. This question has recently come up with our own program, ''Confessions,'' which takes an unfiltered look at convicted murderers and other violent felons.</p>
        <p>Reality television actually comes in two forms. The first, which might be called ''manufactured reality,'' includes shows like ''Survivor'' and ''Big Brother'' in which real people (as opposed to actors) are taped in contrived environments, often with Hollywood production techniques.</p>
        <p>The second, ''unmanufactured reality,'' allows the camera to record real events and presents them with little editing. Examples include widely applauded programming, like Katie Couric's colonoscopy on ''Today,'' as well as controversial programming, like Dr. Jack Kevorkian's lethal injection of a patient on ''60 Minutes.''</p>
        <p>Court TV, whose purpose is to cover the full spectrum of crime and justice issues, has been in the business of unmanufactured television since 1991, when it first began providing live courtroom coverage. Recently, however, we have been criticized for our new series that plays the taped confessions of convicted murderers and other violent felons. The issue is whether this format contributes to the public's understanding of its criminal justice system or whether the show simply taps an audience that has a prurient interest in violent crimes.</p>
        <p>Court TV is judged by its ratings, but we also carefully consider the benefits and the context of each show. And we believe that it is fair to reveal a part of the criminal justice system -- the confession -- that has not been seen to this degree before. The show provides insights into the criminal mind, and it fuels legitimate debate about issues like capital punishment and the usefulness of confessions.</p>
        <p>Yes, the confessions of criminals are, by their nature, unsettling. But providing an unfiltered look into this part of the criminal justice system is both logical and appropriate. Transparency, particularly as it applies to our government, is an important ingredient of democracy.</p>
        <p>Moreover, all cases on ''Confessions'' have been fully adjudicated and are part of the public record. They have been provided to us by police departments and prosecutors around the country.</p>
        <p>At the same time, we agree that some concerns about the show are legitimate. As a result, we have decided to air, after the show's premiere, an additional half-hour discussion of the issues that it raises. Additionally, a Web site will provide in-depth interpretation and analysis.</p>
        <p>Shows like ''Survivor'' make viewers relatively comfortable, because they provide a Hollywood-produced version of life. A show like ''Confessions'' is more troubling because, in fact, it provides a true picture of the world in which we live. The real world is both good and bad, and there is value in seeing both.</p>
        <p>Henry Schleiff is chairman and chief executive officer of Court TV.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Henry Schleiff is chairman and chief executive officer of Court TV.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
