<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Magical Finish to a Record Meet for Bailey</title>
    <meta content="05RACI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diana Handicap</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DD1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Magical Finish to a Record Meet for Bailey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y., Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Perfect Sting wins Diana Handicap at Saratoga; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jerry Bailey had three wishes today.</p>
        <p>He wanted to break his own record for victories by a jockey at a Saratoga meeting. He also wanted to win at least two races this afternoon to bring his total to 50. Most of all, he wanted to close out the meeting with a bang by riding Perfect Sting to victory in Saratoga's final race of the summer, the Diana Handicap, at one and an eighth miles on the turf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jerry Bailey had three wishes today.</p>
        <p>He wanted to break his own record for victories by a jockey at a Saratoga meeting. He also wanted to win at least two races this afternoon to bring his total to 50. Most of all, he wanted to close out the meeting with a bang by riding Perfect Sting to victory in Saratoga's final race of the summer, the Diana Handicap, at one and an eighth miles on the turf.</p>
        <p>Mission accomplished, not that there was much doubt.</p>
        <p>Bailey won the third race, a mile-and-an-eighth allowance, on Ground Storm, for his 49th victory to break the meet record he set here in 1997. It came on a Bill Mott-trained horse, giving Mott 17 victories for the meet to top the trainer standing.</p>
        <p>''He's been a big part in my success,'' Bailey said of the trainer after the record-breaking ride.</p>
        <p>Then, after a couple of near misses, it was down to the Diana, with No. 50 still a victory away.</p>
        <p>Bailey notched it, but he had to work for it.</p>
        <p>''I think that was my best effort and her best effort,'' he said after guiding Perfect Sting out of trouble to a three-quarters of a length victory over License Fee in the $500,000, Grade II race.</p>
        <p>Perfect Sting's trainer, Joe Orseno, would later complain that Alberto Delgado, the rider on Colstar, the horse outside of Perfect Sting, was more concerned with boxing Bailey in than riding his own horse.</p>
        <p>But once again, Bailey found a way, as he usually does. Whenever Bailey has needed a hole to open up in front of him this summer, almost without fail, one has -- usually with just enough room for Bailey's mount to squeeze through.</p>
        <p>And when the hole opened up for Perfect Sting, Bailey found it. Again.</p>
        <p>For Perfect Sting, a brilliant  4-year-old filly, it was her fourth graded stakes victory in a row as she continued to press her case for an Eclipse award as the top grass filly.</p>
        <p>As for Bailey, who has won six Saratoga riding titles in seven years, he augmented his reputation as the top jockey in North America, if not the world, right now.</p>
        <p>And yet -- after years of toiling to get where he is in a career that began at a New Mexico quarter-horse track -- Bailey is also the first to acknowledge that it will not be long before he considers stepping down.</p>
        <p>''I always picked age 45 as the time to look at it and assess it and see how I feel,'' said the Texas-born Bailey, who turned 43 last Tuesday. ''And that is because I had looked over the years at a lot of great riders. And it seemed to me that at about age 45, for whatever reason, that is when their business started to diminish.''</p>
        <p>Angel Cordero Jr., was one of the riders Bailey said he watched closely into his 40's. ''Jerry is in the same position I was five years before I retired,'' said Cordero, who retired at 49 in 1992. ''You want to ride, but you don't want to ride every ride.''</p>
        <p>That Bailey would even acknowledge thinking about retirement sounded strange. The jockey's star is anything but in decline. At the Belmont spring meet, Bailey won a remarkable 38.6 percent of his mounts (66 of 171).</p>
        <p>''You can't rank rider against rider,'' said Cordero, who won 14 Saratoga riding titles, including 11 in a row. ''It's like ranking horses in different years. It would be unfair. But no matter how you look at it, you are going to have to put Bailey in the top 10.''</p>
        <p>Cordero, who is now a jockey agent, placed Bailey in the same pantheon as Bill Shoemaker, Eddie Arcaro, Jorge Velasquez, Manuel Ycaza, Braulio Baeza, Johnny Longden, Laffit Pincay Jr. and himself.</p>
        <p>Not everyone is full of unabashed praise. Ask some of his rivals why Bailey is considered the best in the business, and many will mention that he almost always has the best mounts to choose from.</p>
        <p>But, as Cordero said: ''Before he rode the best horses, he had to ride some bad horses. And he must have won with them to get where he is now. He paid his dues.''</p>
        <p>In time, the recognition came. Bailey was inducted into the National Museum of Racing and Hall of Fame in 1995. He has won three Eclipse awards as the nation's top jockey. He was Cigar's regular rider when Cigar tied Citation's 16-race winning streak. Bailey has won four Breeders' Cup Classics, including one on Cigar. He has won the Kentucky Derby twice, with Sea Hero and Grindstone, the Preakness twice, with Hansel and Red Bullet, and the Belmont once, with Hansel.</p>
        <p>''If there's one goal left for me to attain, I'd love to win a Triple Crown,'' he said. ''I don't know how Arcaro won two.''</p>
        <p>As good as Bailey has been on the dirt, he is regarded as even better on the turf. Bailey agrees. But whatever the surface, Bailey has earned the reputation as a superior positional rider. ''He has this special knack for always being in the right place at the right time,'' said the trainer Todd Pletcher, who finished second to Mott in the trainer standing here with 13 victories.</p>
        <p>Pletcher said his father, Jake, gave Bailey his first job at a racetrack, walking horses at Centennial Park in Colorado. These days, the younger Pletcher offers Bailey employment every time he can.</p>
        <p>''When the money's down, he's the man,'' Pletcher said. ''He's not hustling any mounts. He's in demand.''</p>
        <p>Mott described Bailey as being methodical and studious in his preparation for a race. ''He knows the other riders and what their habits are,'' Mott said. ''He once told me that horses might change from race to race. But riders don't.''</p>
        <p>And that is why Bailey waits so patiently for the horses in front of him to part. There are times when even other riders will concede that Bailey has had that sort of touch. ''It was like, 'How does that happen?' '' Richard Migliore said, referring to Bailey's winning trip on Hap in the Fourstardave on Aug. 26. ''Not one, but two horses opened the way up for him.'' Migliore had to settle for second.</p>
        <p>Was it any wonder, then, that another hole opened for Bailey today?</p>
        <p>FINISH LINES</p>
        <p>Despite being plagued by inclement weather, Saratoga's 36-day meet set an attendance record of 978,321, up 6.3 percent from last year.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
