<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Los Angeles Journal; The Battle of the Hollywood Bowl</title>
    <meta content="Y05BOWL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hollywood Bowl (Calif)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Conservasncy</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Philharmonic Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Terry, Don</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4D71E30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Los Angeles Journal; The Battle of the Hollywood Bowl</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON TERRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Terry, Don</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Plans by Los Angeles Philharmonic Assn to demolish recognizable shell of 71-year-old Hollywood Bowl, which is acoustical nightmare, and replace it with state-of-the-art 21st-century version costing $18 million is opposed by Los Angeles Conservancy, which says all alternatives to demolition should be examined since much of city's history has already been bulldozed under seeminglly endless rivers of freeway and acres of development; parade of musical legends that has performed in shell since construction in 1929 noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No one has conducted more performances at the Hollywood Bowl, under the stars and with the Santa Monica Mountains as a backdrop, than John Mauceri. ''The Bowl,'' Mr. Mauceri, conductor of the Hollywood Bowl Orchestra, said the other day, ''is magic.''</p>
        <p>But there have been too many nights in the middle of a concert when Mr. Mauceri has had to pick up the telephone at the conductor's stand on stage and whisper into the mouthpiece to the sound engineer that he is having trouble hearing the trumpets or the trombones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No one has conducted more performances at the Hollywood Bowl, under the stars and with the Santa Monica Mountains as a backdrop, than John Mauceri. ''The Bowl,'' Mr. Mauceri, conductor of the Hollywood Bowl Orchestra, said the other day, ''is magic.''</p>
        <p>But there have been too many nights in the middle of a concert when Mr. Mauceri has had to pick up the telephone at the conductor's stand on stage and whisper into the mouthpiece to the sound engineer that he is having trouble hearing the trumpets or the trombones.</p>
        <p>For while the Bowl may be magic, the acoustics, Mr. Mauceri says, are simply terrible in its music shell, one of the most recognizable structures on the city's sprawling landscape. ''It's extremely problematic,'' he said, ''when the orchestra can't hear itself.''</p>
        <p>''Over the decades,'' Mr. Mauceri said of the shell, ''all kinds of things have been put on it, glued on it and hung from it to improve the acoustics. Nothing has worked.''</p>
        <p>The 71-year-old shell is also too small for a 100-piece orchestra, and so about a third of the musicians are forced to sit outside it. Further, it is covered in asbestos and lead paint, and its roof leaks.</p>
        <p>So the time has come, say Mr. Mauceri and the Los Angeles Philharmonic Association, the Bowl's manager,  for the shell to be demolished and replaced with a state-of-the-art 21st-century version costing $18 million.</p>
        <p>The money was approved by voters in 1996, and the Los Angeles County Board of Supervisors is to discuss the association's plan on Sept. 12. If the board approves, the project should be completed in 2002, and a shell 30 percent larger but otherwise looking very much like the current one will be standing in its place.</p>
        <p>But just hold your baton a few beats, says the city's preservation movement. So much of the city's history has already been bulldozed under the seemingly endless rivers of freeway and acres of development that the Los Angeles Conservancy has come out against tearing down yet another piece of the past.</p>
        <p>''We believe that the shell is the most identifiable icon of the entire Bowl facility,'' said Ken Bernstein, the conservancy's director of preservation issues. ''We are not trying to stand in the way of quality music. We're just trying to raise the right questions and ensure all the alternatives to demolition are examined.''</p>
        <p>Since the current semicircular shell was erected in 1929, a parade of musical legends have performed on its stage, from Jascha Heifetz and Vladimir Horowitz to Frank Sinatra and Ella Fitzgerald to Bob Dylan and the Beatles. There are dance performances, too, and artificial stars light up the sky over the Bowl when the city comes together every Fourth of July to celebrate.</p>
        <p>With all that in its past, ''we believe this is a very, very serious step to lose the shell that has defined the Bowl for 71 years,'' Mr. Bernstein said.</p>
        <p>In the last few days, the conservancy has had its first chance to study the philharmonic's environmental impact study on the demolition and its review of alternatives. Mr. Bernstein, for one, is impressed. ''At this point,'' he said, ''it does appear somewhat clearer it may be difficult to reconcile saving the shell with other needs.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Bernstein said, the group remains officially opposed to demolition, at least for now. ''This is a difficult issue,'' he said. ''It's a wonderful place to listen to music, and we're not disrespectful of the acoustical issues. But the shell is an icon.''</p>
        <p>Patricia Mitchell, chief operating officer of the philharmonic, said the current shell was actually the Bowl's fourth since the first concert there, in 1922. The shell before this one was designed by Lloyd Wright, the eldest son of Frank Lloyd Wright; it was built in 1928 but lasted only one season before deterioration set in and it was demolished.</p>
        <p>The current shell, made of a cement-asbestos mixture on a steel frame, was erected in 1929 and, the Bowl's souvenir book says, has become ''an architectural icon as recognizable as the Eiffel Tower or the Statue of Liberty.''</p>
        <p>But it is not the shell where musicians spent summer evenings helping their audiences forget economic depression or world war. Over the years, the shell has had several major face lifts, including the installation of a reflecting pool that remained for a time right in front. (''It didn't work,'' Ms. Mitchell said. ''The moisture from the water made it difficult for the instruments to keep tuned.'')</p>
        <p>Mr. Mauceri, who has conducted more than 200 performances at the shell in the last 10 years, said he agreed with the preservation movement that too much of old Los Angeles had been replaced by new, here-today-gone-tomorrow Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''I'm very sympathetic to preserving the cultural history of Los Angeles,'' he said. ''But I think this is a case of misplaced concern. At what point in its history do you preserve the shell? The 1970 version? The 1980 version? The 1949 version? This is not the shell that Lloyd Wright designed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
