<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dokic Ignores Father, Then Loses to Williams</title>
    <meta content="05OPEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS: U.S. OPEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Serena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davenport, Lindsay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3DA1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dokic Ignores Father, Then Loses to Williams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Serena Williams and Lindsay Davenport advance to women's quarterfinals of US Open tennis; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jelena Dokic built a fortress these past six days, shutting out her unruly father's ejection from the United States Open and then dealing with its lonely consequences by striking the ball without forgiveness.</p>
        <p>The 17-year-old Dokic seemed to gather strength in solitude while her father and coach, Damir, stayed at his Manhattan hotel. He was still there yesterday when she ran smack into the strongest player in the women's game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jelena Dokic built a fortress these past six days, shutting out her unruly father's ejection from the United States Open and then dealing with its lonely consequences by striking the ball without forgiveness.</p>
        <p>The 17-year-old Dokic seemed to gather strength in solitude while her father and coach, Damir, stayed at his Manhattan hotel. He was still there yesterday when she ran smack into the strongest player in the women's game.</p>
        <p>Under the broiling sun in Arthur Ashe Stadium, Dokic matched Serena Williams's blistering power with her own in their fourth-round tug of war. And then, in one tantalizing and telling moment, having come back to take a lead in the first-set tie breaker against the defending United States Open champion, Dokic struck a backhand that she thought was a winner.</p>
        <p>The ball, which on television replays appeared to have caught the outside of the line, was called out. Dokic mildly protested, but she would never be the same, her stone resolve crumbling. She had one more set point, at 7-6, yet Williams fought that third one off as well to win the tie breaker, 9-7, and then ripped through Dokic's shell in the second set for a 7-6 (7), 6-0 victory.</p>
        <p>''Maybe that's what turned the whole set around, the whole match,'' Dokic said later about the point at 6-5. That point, though, was just the first pull.</p>
        <p>When she lost the first set, that unraveled her for the rest of the match, as she started the second set completely dispirited.</p>
        <p>''I think it's always hard to come out, especially after you lost the first set,'' Dokic said. ''Maybe you feel like it's slipping away a little bit when you did have a chance. If I was in the situation again, maybe I would have won the set, would have been a different story.''</p>
        <p>Instead, her turbulent and enigmatic story ends, for now, at the fourth round of the Open, an understandable exit for a player ranked No. 43 against the world's sixth-ranked player.</p>
        <p>In the quarterfinals, Williams will play Lindsay Davenport, whom she has beaten in their last five meetings. Davenport was a 6-0, 6-4 winner over Justine Henin.</p>
        <p>Dokic reached the semifinals at Wimbledon by turning aside yet another embarrassing public incident from her father, who was escorted off the grounds for a day when he crushed a reporter's cell phone and started yelling about the Queen.</p>
        <p>And at the Australian Open, Damir Dokic got into a scuffle with an Australian television crew off the grounds, and in the summer of 1999 he was ejected from a tournament in England for drunken and disorderly behavior.</p>
        <p>The Women's Tennis Association Tour is investigating Damir Dokic's pattern of oral abuse, and could elect next week to ban him from the Tour as his daughter's coach.</p>
        <p>''Whatever the decision is, I'm just going to have to deal with it when it comes to that,'' Jelena Dokic said, and then repeated another familiar refrain she has used since last Wednesday, when her father sparked an ugly confrontation over a $12.50 piece of salmon.</p>
        <p>''You've got to block things out,'' Dokic said. ''You've got to go out on the court. You know, you've got to be able to just play the game whether something's happening or not.''</p>
        <p>But while Williams's father and coach, Richard, watched the match from the players' box in the stadium, Dokic was without any visible support. Against players ranked below her, she could support herself well enough.</p>
        <p>''I think whether anybody is around or not, I played well in the two previous matches,'' she said. ''You know, it's different playing Serena. You've got to lift your level up a bit.''</p>
        <p>Williams, her biceps and quadriceps bulging from her black and lilac dress, struck 10 of her personal-best 14 aces in the first set. But her power was also inconsistent; she had 24 unforced errors in the first set, nerves gripping her. ''I did not move up to the ball,'' Williams said. ''I was playing too cautious.''</p>
        <p>That was until she realized she was about to lose the set. She raced to a 4-1 lead in the tie breaker and seemed to relax as Dokic ripped five straight points to give herself two set points; Williams was not ready to concede anything.</p>
        <p>''I'm a real fighter,'' Williams said. ''At that point when I was down, 6-4, in the tie break, I was thinking, 'Well, all I have to do is get the ball back in play and make her play.' ''</p>
        <p>Ahead by 6-5, Dokic was locked in her strategy of attacking Williams, going for every shot, when the lines official called her backhand out. Dokic approached the chair umpire on the changeover, but the umpire let the call stand.</p>
        <p>But after Williams tied the score, Dokic hit a forehand that was called in, and this time, Williams did not agree. ''You win some, you lose some,'' Williams said. ''That's just how it is.''</p>
        <p>But even if she would have lost that tie breaker, Williams said she would not have been as deflated as her opponent. ''I would have come out even stronger in the second set because I tend to play a little better when I'm down,'' she said. Williams has not lost a set yet this tournament and is 14-1 in three years at the Open.</p>
        <p>''Maybe it could have been a tougher match,'' Dokic admitted. ''That's where experience comes into play. The more you play, the more experienced you are.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS: U.S. OPEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
