<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Online Deliveries Lighten Burden for the Disabled; Empowerment, Not Just Convenience, For an Unexpected Class of Consumer</title>
    <meta content="05HAND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0DC1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Online Deliveries Lighten Burden for the Disabled; Empowerment, Not Just Convenience, For an Unexpected Class of Consumer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses how online services that deliver groceries and other goods have become blessings to disabled; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mary West stumbled across YourGrocer.com, an online grocery store, one afternoon a few years ago and quickly became a fan of its fresh blueberry muffins and fast deliveries.</p>
        <p>Ordering her groceries by computer made Ms. West like any other shopper, and for this she was grateful. Now, Ms. West, who is blind, does not stand out the way she once did in D'Agostino's or Gristede's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mary West stumbled across YourGrocer.com, an online grocery store, one afternoon a few years ago and quickly became a fan of its fresh blueberry muffins and fast deliveries.</p>
        <p>Ordering her groceries by computer made Ms. West like any other shopper, and for this she was grateful. Now, Ms. West, who is blind, does not stand out the way she once did in D'Agostino's or Gristede's.</p>
        <p>''I was looking for a place to do a lot of my shopping,'' said Ms. West, 35, ''because I am visually impaired and I can't read labels and things on the grocery shelves.'' In the past, she had to rely on the help of store clerks and friends to shop for groceries and perform other tasks.</p>
        <p>Before she had access to online delivery services, shopping had become so difficult that she had given up, ordering her favorite, although much less healthful, takeout instead.</p>
        <p>''It really helps me out because I have a bad back, bad knees, diabetes and I can't really go the supermarket anymore,'' said Ms. West, who lives in Chelsea. ''Four or five years ago I was not able to cook my own food because I did not have any, so I was ordering out, and that was not helping my health or my pocketbook.''</p>
        <p>Now she uses special voice recognition software to surf the Web for everything from dishwashing detergent to vegetables.</p>
        <p>People like Ms. West, who have a temporary or permanent disability that makes it difficult to handle everyday chores on their own, are increasingly using online delivery services to rent movies, pick up cleaning supplies and buy groceries.</p>
        <p>The advantages of information technology are pronounced in places like Manhattan, advocates for the disabled say, because crowded streets, the lack of access for the handicapped to cabs and subway stations, and other factors complicate their lives.</p>
        <p>To the disabled, the growth of online delivery services has been empowering. To their advocates, it represents progress. To some owners of such businesses, it has become another piece of a shrewd business equation. Noble as it may be to help the disabled like rent a movie from Blockbuster or buy fresh vegetables on their own, to J.  Maxwell Enoch, the chief executive of YourGrocer. com, it is about capitalizing on a market his company's founders did not even envision.</p>
        <p>''Undoubtedly, the sort of people we are talking about have found a way to our service,'' Mr. Enoch said, ''and it is very meaningful to them.''</p>
        <p>People with permanent disabilities, like Ms. West, and those who are temporarily off their feet, like women recovering after childbirth and runners with sprained knees, have created a new marketing niche for Mr. Enoch's company, which is based in Eastchester, N.Y., and serves New York City and some of its suburbs.</p>
        <p>''In Manhattan, you are held hostage by the D'Agostinos and the Gristedes of the world,'' Mr. Enoch said in a recent interview. He noted that those grocery stores are often busy and cannot provide much attention to a disabled customer. Even when the handicapped are able to navigate these stores, he added, they often have difficulty getting the items back home. ''A lot of the things we carry are heavy,'' Mr. Enoch said, and for the disabled, the benefits of delivery are magnified.</p>
        <p>Executives of similar online delivery services said they were not necessarily trying to attract disabled customers when they started operating. Most of the businesses, based in Manhattan's Silicon Alley, focused on reaching young urban professionals, appealing to a simple desire for convenience.</p>
        <p>''We go where the customers lead us,'' said Skip Trevathan, the chief operating officer at Kozmo.com, which is based in Manhattan and delivers many items, including toilet paper and movies, in cities across the country. ''It obviously was in the thinking behind the business model, but only in a narrow sense of people who were homebound for a few days because of something like pregnancy or an injury.''</p>
        <p>That vision has expanded, Mr. Trevathan added. Now, the first page of Kozmo's employee training manual includes a letter from a disabled customer, Cameo C. Massey. Ms. Massey, a single mother in Seattle who suffers from Epstein-Barr syndrome and has severe nerve damage from troublesome surgeries, wrote about her difficulties doing everyday chores.</p>
        <p>''I find myself at the mercy of my own limitations,'' Ms. Massey wrote. ''Your service has helped make my life filled with more quality time. By being able to order books, magazines, movies, games and food from Kozmo, I find that I am able to feel more in touch and up to date with normal people.''</p>
        <p>Many disabled New Yorkers echo those sentiments. Ms. West, who teaches at the Computer Center for the Visually Impaired People at Baruch College, said that for the first time in her life, she ''can handle everything like a sighted person.''</p>
        <p>Kozmo.com officials said they believed that as more disabled Americans gain access to computers, they would increasingly rely on online delivery services. A recent Harris poll conducted for the National Organization on Disability and financed by Aetna U.S. Healthcare found that adults with disabilities were twice as likely as the nondisabled to report that the Internet had significantly improved their lives. But the poll also found that only 43 percent of the disabled respondents had access to the Internet, compared with 57 percent of the nondisabled respondents.</p>
        <p>For its part, Kozmo.com has begun a campaign with the National Cristina Foundation, a nonprofit organization that brings computer technology to the disabled, to deliver donated computers to the doorsteps of disabled Americans.</p>
        <p>In a partnership with General Motors, Kmart and Microsoft, Heidi Van Arnem, a Birmingham, Mich., entrepreneur who has been a quadriplegic since 16, began a national campaign this year, the 10th anniversary of the passage of the Americans With Disabilities Act, to draw attention to what she calls the ''disability divide.''</p>
        <p>In a speech she gave when the campaign started, Ms. Van Arnem, the chief executive of I-Can Online, which provides consultant services to commercial Web sites trying to reach the disabled, said, ''Disabilities disappear with advancements in technology.'' But the fact that the people who benefit most are the ones most likely not to have a computer is frustrating, she said.</p>
        <p>She added that the online companies beginning to cater to the disabled ''represent a growing awareness that there is great opportunity to reach the 85 percent of people with disabilities who are not online yet, and whose lives stand to be enhanced by connecting to the Internet.''</p>
        <p>Robert Harvey, the president of I-Can Online, said in a recent interview that the disabled population is ''the most underserved and underattended market in the country'' because the disabled ''are just not in public view. But they spend a trillion dollars a year on our economy.''</p>
        <p>Fifty-four million Americans, about 20 percent of the population, have disabilities, according to the latest Census Bureau data. There are about 5.6 million disabled people in New York City and its suburbs.</p>
        <p>Most online delivery companies, Mr. Harvey said, began with a ''throw seeds out and watch to see if anything will sprout'' approach and quickly found that the disabled could become one of their most solid customer bases. Their success has caused other businesses to ''think about this population and how they want to reach them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Despite the advantages that the Internet offers to the disabled, technological problems persist. For example, the National Federation of the Blind has sued America Online, claiming that AOL violates the Americans With Disabilities Act because its software is incompatible with many voice recognition programs, known as assisted technology. The suit is pending.</p>
        <p>And advocacy groups have begun lobbying for an amendment to the Americans With Disabilities Act that would require online companies to give the handicapped access to the Internet, given the importance the medium has become in commerce and communication.</p>
        <p>Several companies, including YourGrocer.com, UrbanFetch.com and Amazon.com, have had to deal with similar technical issues. Even I-Can Online had problems, since corrected, that made it difficult for voice recognition software to read its Web pages. The software allows users to control their computers with their voices instead of keyboards. The computer also reads text from Web pages, if they are formatted properly.</p>
        <p>''It did not take us long to realize that we could not be the advocates for people with disabilities and not have ramps for our own people,'' said Mr. Harvey, the president of I-Can. ''One of the elements we now put in our contracts is that the companies will work to make their sites more accessible.''</p>
        <p>Many online delivery companies have found, Mr. Harvey said, that improvements that make it easier for the disabled to use their sites can also appeal to nondisabled customers. For example, voice recognition software compatibility could be helpful to someone trying to shop on the Web while driving a car.</p>
        <p>The challenges notwithstanding, Ms. West sees the improvements for disabled people as a monumental and empowering turning point. ''It evens the playing field,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
