<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cincinnati Has Answers For the New-Look Army</title>
    <meta content="05COLL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Cincinnati</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Military Academy (West Point, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DB1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cincinnati Has Answers For the New-Look Army</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>CINCINNATI, Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cincinnati defeats Army, 23-17, in college football; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They had  something old  an 0-4 record in season openers away from West Point. They had a bunch of new stuff -- a head coach for one, Todd Berry, who brought a one-back, multiple-spread offense to put the ball in the air. They had something borrowed -- a gray stripe added to each jersey sleeve to represent the United States Corps of Cadets, as well as the uniforms worn by its championship teams of the 1940's.</p>
        <p>In the end, the new-look Army Black Knights had something to be blue about, though, as their multiweapon attack came up short against their Conference USA rival Cincinnati, 23-17, before 23,311 here at Nippert Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They had  something old  an 0-4 record in season openers away from West Point. They had a bunch of new stuff -- a head coach for one, Todd Berry, who brought a one-back, multiple-spread offense to put the ball in the air. They had something borrowed -- a gray stripe added to each jersey sleeve to represent the United States Corps of Cadets, as well as the uniforms worn by its championship teams of the 1940's.</p>
        <p>In the end, the new-look Army Black Knights had something to be blue about, though, as their multiweapon attack came up short against their Conference USA rival Cincinnati, 23-17, before 23,311 here at Nippert Stadium.</p>
        <p>While the Black Knights were intent on showing the new wrinkles in their offense, the Bearcats, behind running backs Ray Jackson and DeMarco McCleskey, rolled up a ground game like the Army of old. The twosome combined for 198 yards, and Jackson blew through the middle of the Black Knight defense for a 37-yard touchdown run.</p>
        <p>But it was Cincinnati's quarterback, Deontey Kenner, who undid Army with a time-killing 9-play, 78-yard drive. He ended it by rolling right and slinging a 12-yard pass to a wide-open Jason Collins Baker in the end zone to give the Bearcats a 20-17 lead with six minutes left in the game.</p>
        <p>Kenner, a senior, was 18 of 29 for 239 yards as he continued his pursuit of virtually all of Cincinnati's career passing records.</p>
        <p>''Our offense was rolling,'' said Army linebacker Brian Zickefoose, who had 10 tackles. ''We just didn't get it done on defense. Those two big backs wore us down late, and their passer picked us apart.''</p>
        <p>Over the summer, the Army Athletic Association, after a marketing study, unveiled a new logo -- a sleek knight on horseback over the word Army -- and a plan to build a consistent brand image. The Army athletic teams would always be called the Black Knights, and the once preferred use of the Cadets discouraged.</p>
        <p>The biggest change, however, was made the previous year. when Coach Bob Sutton was replaced after back-to-back 3-8 seasons. In came Berry, who in 1999 had taken Illinois State to the best finish in school history, 11-3, and the semifinals of the Division I-AA playoffs.</p>
        <p>One of the first things the 39-year-old Berry did was scrap the earthbound wishbone offense that had rolled Army to four national rushing titles. Despite the cosmetic homage to history -- the gray stripe worn by the Heisman Trophy winners Doc Blanchard and Glenn Davis and the jerseys without names -- Army started its 111th season a thoroughly modern team.</p>
        <p>Its first two plays of the game were passes, though quarterback Chad Jenkins failed to connect with receivers. And, after Cincinnati place-kicker Jonathan Ruffin booted his third field goal of the day, a 26-yarder with 31 seconds to play, the Black Knights tried a cross-field, backward pass on the ensuing kickoff return.</p>
        <p>The play went nowhere.</p>
        <p>''We fired every bullet we had and didn't leave anything in our bag,'' Berry said. ''At times, you could tell our guys weren't completely comfortable with everything we were doing. I've got very bright young men out there, and they're going to get better. I think you could see that they were having fun out there.''</p>
        <p>There were also many encouraging performances turned in by Army players, though the team's 243 yards of total offense was far below the 323 rushing yards they averaged last year in the wishbone. After a 2-of-8 first half, Jenkins, a junior, went 12 of 21 and led scoring drives of 80 and 95 yards. He spread the ball to four receivers and showed a deft touch when he found the junior Omari Thompson on a 31-yard crossing pattern.</p>
        <p>Jenkins even gave Army a 17-13 lead early in the fourth quarter when he rolled right and tossed a swing pass to running back Michael Wallace, who rushed for 894 yards last year but had never caught a pass in his career at Army.</p>
        <p>''It felt great,'' Wallace, a senior, said after his first reception turned out to be a touchdown. ''I like running the ball, but it's nice to be swung out wide and have a chance to get it and run.''</p>
        <p>Nearby, tight end Clint Dodson smiled. He had a reason to. He had 6 catches for 44 yards -- 5 more than he had all of last season. The new logo, new uniform and especially the new offense is fine with him.</p>
        <p>''We lost today, and it hurts,'' he said, ''but once we figure this all out I think we're going to be a dangerous team.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
