<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Speed Helps Rams Squeak by Broncos</title>
    <meta content="05RAMS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Rams</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denver Broncos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Denver Broncos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/St. Louis Rams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E0DA1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Speed Helps Rams Squeak by Broncos</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St Louis Rams defeat Denver Broncos, 41-36; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rams threw a pregame party tonight. It featured eight cannon shots, each one sounding like a stick of dynamite being detonated. There were fireworks, rock music and the St. Louis owner, Georgia Frontiere, raising the Lombardi Trophy above her head and giving it a smooch.</p>
        <p>It was a beautiful scene for the sellout crowd at the Trans World Dome until Denver Coach Mike Shanahan nearly ruined everything with a masterful game plan of aggressive offense and relentless, ball-hawking defense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rams threw a pregame party tonight. It featured eight cannon shots, each one sounding like a stick of dynamite being detonated. There were fireworks, rock music and the St. Louis owner, Georgia Frontiere, raising the Lombardi Trophy above her head and giving it a smooch.</p>
        <p>It was a beautiful scene for the sellout crowd at the Trans World Dome until Denver Coach Mike Shanahan nearly ruined everything with a masterful game plan of aggressive offense and relentless, ball-hawking defense.</p>
        <p>Led by quarterback Brian Griese, the Broncos took a 1-point lead with six minutes left. But the speed of the Rams -- overpowering and practically unstoppable -- helped them avoid an embarrassing season-opening loss. St. Louis beat Denver, 41-36, in one of the most exciting regular-season games in 10 years.</p>
        <p>St. Louis looked as if it might cruise after a gorgeous 72-yard touchdown run by Marshall Faulk and a dazzling 80-yard touchdown catch by wide receiver Az-Zahir Hakim. The score was 35-20 with 4 minutes 2 seconds remaining in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>But Griese showed why he might do just fine in his second year as John Elway's replacement. He threw a 7-yard score to Desmond Clark to make the score 35-27, and then Denver managed a 36-yard field goal by Jason Elam to cut the score to 35-30.</p>
        <p>Then disaster struck for the Rams. Kurt Warner, last season's most valuable player, tried to squeeze a pass on the left sideline to Torry Holt. The throw was intercepted by cornerback Terrell Buckley, who returned it untouched 32 yards for a touchdown. Denver led by 36-35.</p>
        <p>Faulk made another spectacular run, this time for 30 yards, which put St. Louis at the Denver 1-yard line. Fullback Robert Holcombe ran it in from there and, after a failed 2-point conversion, the Rams led by 41-36 with 2:58 left.</p>
        <p>Griese finally ran out of miracles. On third-and-21 at Denver's 27-yard line, he was sacked by defensive lineman Kevin Carter for a 12-yard loss. Then on fourth down, Griese was hit in the back by defensive end Grant Wistrom, which rocked Griese so hard the ball went fluttering into the air and landed harmlessly on the ground. Game over.</p>
        <p>Warner completed 25 of 35 passes for 441 yards and three touchdowns, two of them covering 152 yards in the third quarter on throws in the flat.</p>
        <p>Griese was 19 of 28 for 307 yards, throwing for two touchdowns and running for a third.</p>
        <p>Terrell Davis, who missed 12 games games last season with a knee injury, rushed for 34 yards on 9 carries before leaving the game in the second quarter with a twisted left knee. His replacement, Olandis Gary, rumbled for 80 yards on 13 carries.</p>
        <p>For a defending champion, the Rams have received surprisingly little respect. Many in football, and the news media, believe Washington and Tampa Bay might be better than St. Louis and are picking one of those teams as top candidates to reach the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>The early part of the game showed how difficult it is for a team to defend its title. Defensively, Denver used a mixture of secondary coverages, including a healthy dose of man-to-man, always dangerous against the game's fastest fleet of wide receivers. The Broncos did not seem to care.</p>
        <p>Offensively, Denver was even more aggressive. On its first touchdown drive, there was a lot of Davis, but Shanahan also took the shackles off Griese, allowing him to throw deep. The Broncos took a 7-0 lead when Griese scored on an 8-yard bootleg with 10:05 left in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>That trend continued later in the game when Griese launched a perfect long pass to wide receiver Rod Smith for 47 yards after Smith had beaten double coverage. The play led to a 32-yard field goal by Elam, which was important, because on the previous series, Hakim scored on a blistering 86-yard punt return that was keyed by terrific blocking.</p>
        <p>Last year during the Rams' championship run, such a play would have deflated most teams and started a St. Louis point-scoring buffet. The Broncos, however, refused to be intimidated, even with Davis on the sideline with a twisted left ankle. When St. Louis scored on an 89-yard drive that ended in a Faulk 5-yard touchdown run, making the score 14-10, Griese countered with his best set of plays of the night. On a third-and-8, he kept the offense on the field with a 26-yard scramble.</p>
        <p>Later in the drive, with the Denver churning along smoothly, St. Louis went with an all-out blitz to disrupt Griese's timing. Griese read it the way the man he replaced -- Elway -- would have. He made the correct hot read to Smith, who caught the quick pass at the 20-yard line then burst up the middle for the 25-yard touchdown and 17-14 Denver lead.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINT</p>
        <p>MIKE MARTZ, who replaced the retired DICK VERMEIL, won his coaching debut.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
