<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seven Days, Six Nights, One Author; If You Liked the Book, You'll Love the Tour Guide</title>
    <meta content="05TOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/05/arts/05TOUR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EED91E30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seven Days, Six Nights, One Author; If You Liked the Book, You'll Love the Tour Guide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Avid readers are taking part in travel vacations led by favorite authors; self-help authors and writers with spiritual bent head list of writers leading such tours; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paperback books have long made popular traveling companions, but in this year of haute vacations truly avid readers bring their favorite authors on journeys along with the antacid tablets and rollaway luggage.</p>
        <p>For the package price of $2,650 plus additional airfare to India, would-be travelers can glimpse one of the fabled wonders of the world (the Taj Mahal) while led by one of the wonders of the advice best-seller list (Deepak Chopra).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paperback books have long made popular traveling companions, but in this year of haute vacations truly avid readers bring their favorite authors on journeys along with the antacid tablets and rollaway luggage.</p>
        <p>For the package price of $2,650 plus additional airfare to India, would-be travelers can glimpse one of the fabled wonders of the world (the Taj Mahal) while led by one of the wonders of the advice best-seller list (Deepak Chopra).</p>
        <p>Or they can join a roving-reading club guided personally by Wayne W. Dyer, the author of self-help books like ''Your Erroneous Zone,'' on an autumn trip to the Umbrian hills of Italy and the mystical hometown of St. Francis of Assisi. On the 11-day, $3,947 tour of Italy and France, Mr. Dyer pledges to share his ''insights and experiences of some of what life has taught me'' and an intimate Yom Kippur dinner in the unlikely village of Lourdes, with its Roman Catholic shrine.</p>
        <p>''I generally avoid tours like the plague,'' said John McShane, a Dallas lawyer and loyal reader of Mr. Dyer's books. Yet Mr. McShane is poised to join the coming European trip after savoring an excursion with Mr. Dyer to Peru's Machu Picchu in May and an earlier backpacking safari in Tanzania with Richard J. Leider, the self-development author.</p>
        <p>For Mr. McShane, these intellectual flights to far-off places are the only chance to ''get to know your favorite author as a human being.''</p>
        <p>Such curiosity is drawing travelers to locations they had no intention of visiting. It's their opportunity to join an instant book tour and to observe the mettle of literary heroes as they deal with missing buses, lost tickets or a spontaneous decision by fellow travelers to marry on the Nile.</p>
        <p>The list of writers who are turning tours into reading vacations is dominated by self-help authors like Mr. Chopra and writers with a spiritual bent like Neale Donald Walsch, the author of ''Conversations With God,'' who in June took readers on an eight-day tour of Peru timed to coincide with the summer solstice sunrise over Machu Picchu. But there are also published historians and even a poet who are leading people on tours ripped from their chapters, whether it be a stroll down Shankill Road in Belfast, where violence erupted this summer among Protestant paramilitary groups, a trip to Colonial Williamsburg in Virginia or a moonlit meeting at the Jefferson Memorial in Washington.</p>
        <p>Authors have long trolled for readers on luxury cruises, delivering lectures and then moving on. But these tours are far more physically and mentally demanding, with authors expected to offer daily workshops and to play the role of host, one as genial as Fantasy Island's Mr. Roarke.</p>
        <p>In November, Mr. Chopra, the best-selling sage of alternative medicine, is taking about 350 of his readers on the road in two separate tours, to Israel and his native India. He will lead travelers on a pilgrimage that includes a de rigueur stop at the Taj Mahal along with less standard perks like yoga sessions and daily primordial sound meditation with Mr. Chopra himself.</p>
        <p>The tour, which is featured on the author's Web site, www.chopra.com, also promises the possibility that participants will meet the Dalai Lama (''subject to his holiness's schedule''). The reading requirement for the trip is, naturally, Mr. Chopra's latest title, ''How to Know God: The Soul's Journey Into the Mystery of Mysteries.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chopra said he started leading tours to places like Egypt, Bali and India about six years ago. Typically his trips are a mix of tourism and daily workshops on spiritual themes. Most of his trips have been organized by travel operators, but his latest tour to India is organized by the author's California-based Chopra Center for Well Being.</p>
        <p>The transcontinental book tours do sap ''a lot of energy,'' Mr. Chopra said. ''But it gives me a lot of fulfillment to take people to places where wisdom traditions were, in a sense, born. Last year I took a group of people to Egypt, and we sailed along the Nile for a week. I was able to explain to my readers the sources of my information.''</p>
        <p>Most of these tours are organized by a handful of travel operators like Visions Travel in Los Angeles, Power Places in St. Croix and Cross Cultural Journeys in Sausalito, Calif. Visions Travel started its literary matchmaking service early in 1979, but initially it could attract only lesser-known authors, said Abbas Nadim, the company's founder and president.</p>
        <p>''There's been a shift in the last five years, with more mainstream authors who are interested in doing this,'' said Mr. Nadim, who is constantly trolling for authors to join tours. ''It's no longer New Age per se -- the crystal and U.F.O. authors. Before, our clients used to be mostly middle-aged divorcees, 90 percent of them women. But now, with a new breed of authors like Deepak Chopra and Marianne Williamson, we're getting more professionals and couples.''</p>
        <p>Typically, the authors strike individually tailored deals with travel operators, charging a fee for participating or taking a percentage of the profits plus, in some cases, free accommodations for themselves and family members, Mr. Nadim said. Certain writers also place restrictions on the number of fellow travelers, to as low as 15, but others are willing to lead tours with as many as 400.</p>
        <p>Such crowds can be a little disconcerting for some authors, although the large group is divided into subsets. Mr. Walsch, a former radio personality who has had a string of best sellers with his ''Conversations With God'' series, said he had participated in his first tour in June at the invitation of Power Places with 150 travelers.</p>
        <p>He is scheduled to lead a retreat in Bali next May, but he said that in the future he would probably limit his participation in tours. ''It feels like it's the only one I will do; I wouldn't want to do more than one a year,'' Mr. Walsch said. ''I want people to come see me for $20 a lecture rather than $3,000 for a tour. It's kind of a high-end activity, and I realized after I finished the experience that it was lovely, but only for those readers who can afford it, and that's a small percentage of my readers.''</p>
        <p>Other tours are purposely kept small. Frank Costello, the author of three books on Irish history and a former press secretary to Ray Flynn, the former Boston mayor, is currently helping to lead a tour of Northern Ireland with 15 travelers who range in age from their late 20's to early 70's and include a teacher, a judge, an investment banker and a lawyer. The theme of the trip is the exploration of the political divide in Northern Ireland. The seven-day tour has taken the group on a stroll of Shankill Road with helicopters hovering overhead, as well as to a lunch in Derry with John Hume, a winner of the 1998 Nobel Peace Prize for his efforts to broker a solution in Northern Ireland.</p>
        <p>''The whole thing is a work in progress,'' said Mr. Costello, who is involved in a tour for the first time. ''It will give me future ideas for writing, and it's prompting other topics I can write about.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''If I have to describe what it's like for me, I'm quite tired. It is a performance that requires stamina and the focus of a lot of people asking questions and asking them sometimes twice. It makes you a better listener because you've got to stay ahead of the game.''</p>
        <p>In contrast, Mr. Leider, the author of books like ''Repacking Your Bags'' and ''The Power of Purpose,'' said he was reinvigorated by his 23-day trips into the Tanzanian bush, where his dozen readers can reflect on their lives amid the rhythms of African life, hunting game with local tribes or digging for tubers.</p>
        <p>The friendships that develop between like-minded readers are almost as critical to the trip as an author's participation.</p>
        <p>Beth Zacher, 39, a massage therapist from Venice, Calif., had no desire to travel to Egypt but bought a ticket to join a tour of more than 400 people led by Caroline Myss, author of self-help books like ''Why People Don't Heal and How They Can'' and ''Anatomy of the Spirit: The Seven Stages of Power and Healing.''</p>
        <p>''I went by myself because I had a friend who had to cancel,'' said Ms. Zacher, who will follow the same author to Ireland this month. ''I didn't want to go alone, but it turned out to be an incredible experience for me. I was thrilled because it really brought me into the group. I made a couple of lifelong friends on the journey.'' It was on that trip that two of Ms. Zacher's fellow travelers spontaneously decided to marry on a boat in the Nile.</p>
        <p>Many of the travelers sign up for more trips. Visions Travel estimates that as many 70 percent of its clients return for other book tours.</p>
        <p>Daisy Kennedy, a time-share saleswoman in Brigantine Island, N.J., has joined her favorite author, Marianne Williamson, on four trips -- to Egypt, Bali, Alaska and Greece -- and has plans to take part in the author's ''Rebirth of a Nation'' tour of Williamsburg, Va., and Washington in late October. That tour will also feature the writer and historian R. B. Bernstein.</p>
        <p>''I've done the other kind of package tours that are like 20 different countries in 32 hours,'' Ms. Kennedy said. ''But they're not memorable because there's no connection with the others. You tend to be an individual, whereas with Marianne everybody knows everyone in three days and it becomes a family.''</p>
        <p>Jim Curtan, 59, is a veteran of three Myss tours. But Mr. Curtan, a retired personal manager from Los Angeles, confessed that he wasn't comfortable with some spiritual seekers drawn by the author's message of healing. ''I come from eight years of Jesuit education, and I'm not much into that stuff,'' he said. ''Caroline attracts her share of the New Age seekers. I just don't hang out with them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Curtan has signed up for Ms. Myss's tour of Ireland even though he only recently recovered from breaking an ankle on a hiking trip during his last tour with her, in May, to Machu Picchu. He said he would like to take more book tours because of the chance to be ''stimulated intellectually, spiritually, to have good conversations.''</p>
        <p>''It's like giving my spirit a real workout,'' he said. But there's no ticket for his true desire.</p>
        <p>An avid fan of Harry Potter novels, Mr. Curtan said that what he really yearned for was a magical tour: joining the young wizard's creator, the author J. K. Rowling, for a disappearance at platform 9 3/4 for a scenic ride on the scarlet steam engine of the Hogwarts Express.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
