<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MetroStars Must Plug Their Hole in the Goal</title>
    <meta content="05SOCC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EFDA1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1048" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MetroStars Must Plug Their Hole in the Goal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on MetroStars preparing for Major League soccer playoffs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the injured Mike Ammann out for the season and Tim Howard joining the United States Olympic team, the MetroStars will finish the regular season this week and go into next week's playoffs with two unproven goalkeepers.</p>
        <p>General Manager Nick Sakiewicz said yesterday that Paul Grafer would start in goal tonight against Miami at Giants Stadium in East Rutherford, N.J., and that his backup would be Russell Payne. Both keepers have played this season in the A-League, which is one level below Major League Soccer. Sakiewicz said he had no idea what the goalkeeping combination would be for the game at New England Saturday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the injured Mike Ammann out for the season and Tim Howard joining the United States Olympic team, the MetroStars will finish the regular season this week and go into next week's playoffs with two unproven goalkeepers.</p>
        <p>General Manager Nick Sakiewicz said yesterday that Paul Grafer would start in goal tonight against Miami at Giants Stadium in East Rutherford, N.J., and that his backup would be Russell Payne. Both keepers have played this season in the A-League, which is one level below Major League Soccer. Sakiewicz said he had no idea what the goalkeeping combination would be for the game at New England Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Sakiewicz was unhappy that his team would have to share Grafer with the Long Island Rough Riders. M.L.S. has exclusive rights to A-League players.</p>
        <p>''Sharing him is better than not having him at all,'' Sakiewicz said of Grafer. ''I think the league will have to look into the agreement with the A-League. The fortunate thing right now is that there is no direct conflict'' between the two teams' schedules.</p>
        <p>Payne, who plays for the Boston Bulldogs, is staying with the MetroStars, but he is apparently rated lower than Grafer. Sakiewicz said the team would be considering at least one other goalkeeper this week.</p>
        <p>Lothar Matthaus, who missed Saturday's 4-1 loss in Miami with a hamstring injury he sustained in practice, will play tonight. Sakiewicz said that Matthaus was rested on Saturday for precautionary reasons.</p>
        <p>Miami, with 38 points, is one of five teams fighting for three playoff spots in the 12-team league. New England (42), and Dallas and Colorado (40), have the edge. New England plays its two remaining games at home.</p>
        <p>WORLD CUP QUALIFYING</p>
        <p>The Americans' 1-0 victory over Guatemala on Sunday in Washington did not come without a price. Earnie Stewart and Eddie Lewis drew cards and will miss the next qualifying game, against Costa Rica on Oct. 11 at Columbus, Ohio, but it could have been a lot worse.</p>
        <p>Claudio Reyna, the Americans' captain, could have sustained a serious injury in the 77th minute after a tackle by Everaldo Valencia that left cleat marks on Reyna's left knee. Reyna, who had a constructive game in midfield, was carried off in a stretcher and was replaced by Carlos Llamosa.</p>
        <p>''I was really scared,'' Reyna said afterward, when it was determined that his injury was a bruise. ''I didn't know if anything was wrong with my knee. One of his legs went in knee high. He was clearly going in trying to injure me.''</p>
        <p>Valencia's cleats-up tackle on Reyna was much worse than the elbow by Lewis on Fabricio Benitez. But the Mexican referee, Ulises Rangel, ejected Lewis in the 65th minute, leaving the Americans a man short, and made no call against Valencia, who had been given a yellow card two minutes earlier.</p>
        <p>Brian McBride, who scored the winner in the 72nd minute after a precision pass by Cobi Jones from the right side, put the Americans in position to advance to next year's regional finals. Six countries will compete in a round-robin tournament to determine the three that will represent the region in the final stages of the 2002 World Cup in Japan and South Korea.</p>
        <p>Coach Bruce Arena started nine European-based players, but it was two members of M.L.S. teams, McBride of the Columbus Crew and Jones of the Los Angeles Galaxy, who produced the precious goal for the Americans. Alan Rothenberg, one of the league's founders, made sure to point that out after the game, which attracted a sellout crowd of 51,996.</p>
        <p>It was Arena's decision to insert Jones and Lewis that paid dividends for the Americans, who had trouble breaking down the well-organized Guatemalan defense. Jones's brilliant pass to McBride offset Lewis's disastrous mistake that led to his ejection.</p>
        <p>''I felt so bad,'' Lewis said. ''I was in the locker room thinking the game was going to end in a tie and it was my fault. The coach sent me in to help the team and I get thrown out.''</p>
        <p>Lewis will miss the Costa Rica game for his ejection, while Stewart will sit out for getting a yellow card in the 32nd minute, his second yellow card in qualifying, which means an automatic one-game suspension.</p>
        <p>A victory against Costa Rica or at Barbados Nov. 15 in their last game in the group is what the Americans need to be assured of a place in the final round in the region, where they will have to play the likes of Mexico, Honduras and undefeated Jamaica and Trinidad and Tobago, besides Costa Rica.</p>
        <p>CORNER KICKS</p>
        <p>The organizers of the Olympics in Australia announced yesterday that there was no need for a new site for the soccer tournament. They said the field at Canberra's Bruce Stadium would be resodded in time for the tournament after the turf that was put down a month ago did not take.  Atletico Madrid, relegated from the elite of Spanish soccer for the the first time in 66 years, got an early taste of the harsh realities of life in the second division. Its theme of preseason publicity was Just One Short Year in Hell, but it lost, 4-1, to Levante on Sunday in its opening game.  A team from Moldova, Constructorul-93 Chisinau, was banned from European competitions for a year by Europe's governing body yesterday for incidents in last month's game against CSKA of Bulgaria. After the 3-2 loss to CSKA, an official of the Moldovan entourage threatened the assistant referee with a gun.  F.C. Porto of Portugal was fined $28,990 after its supporters threw stones, coins and cigarette lighters at match officials at the end of a Champions' League qualifier against Anderlecht of Belgium.</p>
        <p>ALEX YANNIS</p>
        <p>SOCCER: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
