<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WORLD BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y05BRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EEDC1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1138" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WORLD BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeanne Moore</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: LAWMAKER TO QUIT -- Mo Mowlam, the former Northern Ireland secretary whose popularity among the Labor Party faithful and with the public has regularly exceeded that of Prime Minister Tony Blair, said she would not run for re-election to Parliament in the vote expected later this year. Reported to be unhappy at being replaced in the Ulster job in 1999 and given a marginal cabinet position, she said, ''I have several years of my working life left and want to do something different before I finally retire.''</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: LAWMAKER TO QUIT -- Mo Mowlam, the former Northern Ireland secretary whose popularity among the Labor Party faithful and with the public has regularly exceeded that of Prime Minister Tony Blair, said she would not run for re-election to Parliament in the vote expected later this year. Reported to be unhappy at being replaced in the Ulster job in 1999 and given a marginal cabinet position, she said, ''I have several years of my working life left and want to do something different before I finally retire.''</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>KOSOVO: PENALTIES FOR ESCAPE -- Bernard Kouchner, the chief United Nations administrator for Kosovo, the Serbian province, suspended the director of a detention center after 15 Kosovo Serbs facing charges of genocide escaped, and warned that other United Nations personnel could be disciplined. Two of the Serbs who fled the prison were recaptured.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: BOMB BLASTS -- Bomb attacks ascribed to criminal turf battles hit two cities, killing three people. The police said there was no apparent link between the two explosions, in an outdoor market in the industrial city of Ryazan and a boutique in St. Petersburg.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>SWITZERLAND: BANKS CRITICIZED FOR ABACHA LINK -- The country's banking watchdog rebuked six of the country's banks, including Credit Suisse Group, for accepting some of the $670 million in deposits linked to the late Nigerian dictator Sani Abacha. However, it imposed no penalties; they are not allowed under current Swiss law. The Nigerian government is trying to recover an estimated $3 billion in suspected embezzled state funds sent abroad during General Abacha's 1993-98 rule.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Olson (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>COLOMBIA: WORDS OF PEACE, ACTS OF WAR -- Fierce clashes between government troops and FARC rebels continued, despite the announcement on Sunday that the government and FARC had agreed to begin cease-fire talks on Sept. 22. More than 100 people have died since the FARC launched an offensive after President Clinton's visit on Aug. 30.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>CANADA: PLEA FOR FORGIVENESS -- The Anglican, Roman Catholic, Presbyterian and United churches plan to make a public apology today to Eskimos and Indians who suffered from decades of abuse by white church officials. Several churches, including those making the apology, have been sued in recent years for the physical and sexual abuse of children who attended church-run schools mainly in western Canada that were abolished in the early 1970's.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>CHINA: CHRISTIANS CHARGED -- Formal criminal charges were brought against 85 of the 130 evangelical Christians arrested during an illegal worship service two weeks ago in central China, a human rights monitor in Hong Kong said. The large-scale prosecutions could not be independently verified but, if they proceed, they would represent a stepping-up of the government's longtime struggle against defiant Christian groups. In recent years, while fines and temporary detention have been used to harass underground churches, relatively few leaders are known to have been formally charged and jailed.</p>
        <p>Erik Eckholm (NYT)</p>
        <p>MYANMAR: DISSIDENT UNDER WRAPS -- The opposition leader Daw Aung San Suu Kyi was kept confined to her home in the capital, Yangon, as the military government mounted a crackdown against its opponents. Diplomats said the gate to Mrs. Aung San Suu Kyi's residence had been padlocked since she was forcibly returned Saturday after a nine-day stand-off with the authorities in her car outside Yangon. The government denied that she and other leaders of her party were under house arrest, but said they had been asked to stay home while it investigated reports that some opposition members were involved in ''terrorist activity.''</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>JAPAN, RUSSIA: NO TREATY SOON -- President Vladimir V. Putin, in Tokyo for talks with Prime Minister Yoshiro Mori, rejected the latest Japanese call for sovereignty over four disputed islands, dimming hope for a peace treaty this year. The islands, which are known to Russians as the southern Kurils and to Japanese as the Northern Territories and lie north of Japan near Russia's Far East, were occupied by Soviet troops toward the end of World War II. The two sides had agreed three years ago to write a treaty by the end of 2000, but progress has been stymied by the deadlock over the islands.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>INDIA: 'WEEPING' GODDESS -- Worshipers, hungry to witness a miracle, have been flocking to temples in the city of Hyderabad after reports that statues of the goddess Durga have been shedding tears. The crowds have snarled traffic in the capital of Andhra Pradesh, the scene of recent heavy flooding and political unrest.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAQ: SCHOOL FEES -- Iraq's government, which had formerly offered free education from kindergarten through university, has begun charging students to attend classes at public schools. The economy has been undermined by international sanctions imposed to punish Iraq for invading Kuwait in 1990.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>BURUNDI: POST-ACCORD FIGHTING -- At least 60 people have died in fighting between Hutu rebels and government soldiers in the week since the signing of a peace agreement to end Burundi's seven-year civil war, officials said. At least 200,000 people, most of them civilians, have been killed in a conflict that erupted in 1993 after the assassination of Burundi's first democratically elected president, of the Hutu ethnic majority.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
