<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Contest for Albany Seat Hinges on a Veteran Legislator's Relevance</title>
    <meta content="05PRIM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="NEW YORK PRIMARY: 141st Assembly District" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buffalo (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eve, Arthur O (Assemblyman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peoples, Crystal D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Buffalo</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFDB1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Contest for Albany Seat Hinges on a Veteran Legislator's Relevance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <dateline>BUFFALO, Sept. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series on primary elections throughout New York State examines Democratic race for 141st Assembly District in Buffalo between incumbent Assemblyman Arthur O Eve and Crystal D Peoples; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By noon, Assemblyman Arthur O. Eve had already put in a full morning of campaigning and seemed more than a bit weary. He had spent hours today shaking the hands of supporters and had just completed a caravan through the humid streets of Buffalo with a dozen cars carrying loudspeakers imploring people along the way to vote for him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eve, 67, a veteran of Buffalo politics, the deputy speaker of the State Assembly and the longest serving member of that legislative body, is now fully immersed in the fight of his political life. After more than three decades of a political career that began when Lyndon B. Johnson was president and Nelson A. Rockefeller was governor, Mr. Eve has had to campaign with an intensity that, by his own admission, he has never had to employ before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By noon, Assemblyman Arthur O. Eve had already put in a full morning of campaigning and seemed more than a bit weary. He had spent hours today shaking the hands of supporters and had just completed a caravan through the humid streets of Buffalo with a dozen cars carrying loudspeakers imploring people along the way to vote for him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eve, 67, a veteran of Buffalo politics, the deputy speaker of the State Assembly and the longest serving member of that legislative body, is now fully immersed in the fight of his political life. After more than three decades of a political career that began when Lyndon B. Johnson was president and Nelson A. Rockefeller was governor, Mr. Eve has had to campaign with an intensity that, by his own admission, he has never had to employ before.</p>
        <p>In a three-way race in the Sept. 12 Democratic primary, Mr. Eve's major challenger is Crystal D. Peoples, 48, the majority leader of the Erie County Legislature. Ms. Peoples has defied expectations in earlier races by winning as the consummate outsider backed by a strong grass-roots group of supporters. In her campaign, Ms. Peoples acknowledges with admiration Mr. Eve's years of public service, but she insists that his methods are outdated and that he has become ineffective.</p>
        <p>The themes being evoked against Mr. Eve in his 18th campaign reflect a trend that is dominating several of the races in the state in this year's primary season. Several black incumbents, like Mr. Eve, who came of political age during the civil rights movement are now facing vigorous challenges from insurgents who are depicting these political stalwarts as tired legislators with an antiquated approach to governing.</p>
        <p>The technique is not only a hallmark of the campaign against Mr. Eve here along the streets of Buffalo's largely black East Side. It is also being used with great fanfare in primary races in New York City, against such longtime members of Congress as Major R. Owens and Edolphus Towns of Brooklyn and against others in Assembly races.</p>
        <p>''In different parts of the country, there are incumbents who came to power in the early wave of majority black districts who have not faced serious competition for a long period of time,'' said John H. Mollenkopf, director of the Urban Research Center at the City University of New York's Graduate Center.</p>
        <p>''And they are therefore in varying degrees of contact with their base,'' Mr. Mollenkopf said. ''And that makes them vulnerable to challenges to somebody who decides that what was great for the civil rights era is not appropriate for today.''</p>
        <p>The evidence that Mr. Eve is taking this race seriously is abundant. He has summoned several elected officials here to campaign on his behalf, including State Comptroller H. Carl McCall, United States Representative Charles B. Rangel of Harlem, Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver and Representative Maxine Waters of California.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Eve's son Eric, who ran Vice President Al Gore's primary campaign in New York State, is now helping his father's re-election effort.</p>
        <p>In one appearance before voters after another, Arthur Eve says that his years in office have produced landmark legislation, effective programs sponsored by the state and millions of dollars for community organizations throughout the 141st Assembly District which he represents.</p>
        <p>He takes particular pride, for example, in his role in establishing the Educational Opportunity Program, which helps economically disadvantaged students attend the State University of New York, and in sponsoring bills that require affirmative action on state-financed projects.</p>
        <p>''We've been able to put a lot of institutions in this community over 34 years,'' Mr. Eve said today, sitting in a campaign office buzzing with volunteers. ''We have been instrumental in bringing in money for housing. We have developed training programs, educational programs and many other programs. I've tried to create institutions that will last long after Arthur Eve is gone from the scene.''</p>
        <p>He points out that with the reapportionment of legislative districts within a year or two, western New York is likely to lose at least one Assembly seat because of declining population. He says his seniority will ensure that this largely black corner of the region will be remembered by legislators who carve districts based in part on incumbents' length of service.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Peoples says that none of those programs nor the pipeline of state money has made a difference on the East Side of Buffalo. She points to the once-thriving commercial district along Jefferson Avenue, where there are now as many shuttered businesses as open ones. She points out that there is but one supermarket in the entire district of 120,000 residents and that the streets are in dire need of repairs and the schools in need of upgrading.</p>
        <p>''I give him all due respect for his length of service and the sacrifices he has made,'' she said. ''But that doesn't automatically make him the elected official to stay in power for life. I'm also running because the social agenda of the 60's is old and should be over with. We have to focus on economic issues now.''</p>
        <p>She added that the conditions in the 141st District present the most salient argument for Mr. Eve's retirement. ''If our community were booming, if everyone was doing well and if our streets and schools were in good shape, then you could make an argument for keeping him in office,'' she said. ''But that's not what's happening here.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Peoples has emerged as a formidable candidate, in part because of her involvement with the political organization called Grassroots. The organization has made a name for itself because of its success at registering thousands of voters and placing several of its members in elected office, notably Ms. Peoples and Byron W. Brown, a member of the Buffalo Common Council who is now challenging a state senator, Alfred T. Coppola.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peoples, a former elementary schoolteacher who has served on the County Legislature for five years, has been a relentless campaigner. She has walked the streets of the district night and day, from senior centers and public housing complexes to Gigi's, a soul food restaurant, where she greeted people over their morning grits and eggs. She wears a T-shirt bearing her name on the front and the slogan ''Keeping It Real'' on the back. She has raised about $40,000 for the campaign, she said, and has an army of volunteers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eve has put together his own battalion of campaign troops, some from outside Buffalo, and has raised about $60,000. His campaign officials have studied the races of other longtime incumbents under attack by younger challengers, like Mr. Rangel's 1996 race against Adam Clayton Powell IV.</p>
        <p>The competitiveness of the campaign has led him not only to defend his record, but also to undertake a vigorous campaign schedule, like that of Ms. Peoples.</p>
        <p>''She has name recognition because she is a public official,'' Mr. Eve said on a recent morning. ''And so I have to campaign in a way that enables me to get my message out. This is the greatest challenge I have ever had.''</p>
        <p>The candidates' campaign commercials seem to be broadcast incessantly on some of Buffalo's radio stations. Campaign posters are on storefront windows, lawns and buildings throughout the district.</p>
        <p>The prominence of those signs is symbolic of how divisive this race has been in Buffalo, particularly in the city's black neighborhoods. (The third candidate in the primary is Samuel A. Herbert.)</p>
        <p>Some, like Mr. Brown, the Common Council member and State Senate candidate, say they appreciate the work Mr. Eve has done over the years, but find Ms. Peoples's message far more captivating. ''She is articulate, charismatic, and makes a good point,'' said Mr. Brown, who was once an aide to Mr. Eve. ''I feel it's time for a change.''</p>
        <p>Others, like Beverly A. Gray, another Common Council member, say they are disturbed to see that a man who has achieved such seniority and has been such a symbol of black political power in western New York has been forced into a highly competitive primary.</p>
        <p>''Many of us are appalled at this,'' Ms. Gray said. ''Arthur Eve has a history of creating great educational programs. He has dedicated himself to this community. And this primary is terrible because it has divided our community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Eve, who left segregated Miami to work in a Chevrolet assembly plant in Buffalo before entering politics, says he wants to continue in office because ''this city has been so good to me, and I want to continue giving back to this community.''</p>
        <p>The characterizations of him as an ineffective relic from another era, Mr. Eve said, ''used to bother me, especially because they came from people who were helped by the very educational programs that I helped to create.''</p>
        <p>Speaking slowly, with a hint of melancholy, Mr. Eve said, ''That used to bother me, but it doesn't anymore. I just tell myself that it's just politics.''</p>
        <p>New York Primary</p>
        <p>Articles in this series are examining individual primary contests in Congressional and local districts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
