<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knoblauch Just Wants To Quiet Doubters</title>
    <meta content="05PINS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knoblauch, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7DA1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knoblauch Just Wants To Quiet Doubters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Status of injured New York Yankees infielder Chuck Knoblauch discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch found no simple way to describe his desire to play again when he had a conversation with Brian Cashman, the Yankees' general manager, on Sunday. Knoblauch finally settled for an analogy. ''Imagine something you want more than anything else in the world,'' he said to Cashman. ''That's how much I want to play again.''</p>
        <p>There is nothing in Knoblauch's resume that would suggest he might exaggerate the seriousness of pain or injury, as George Steinbrenner intimated last week. Say this for Steinbrenner: When he made the calculated decision to cast doubt on Knoblauch's professional integrity, he was taking aim at a player renowned for his resilience and toughness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch found no simple way to describe his desire to play again when he had a conversation with Brian Cashman, the Yankees' general manager, on Sunday. Knoblauch finally settled for an analogy. ''Imagine something you want more than anything else in the world,'' he said to Cashman. ''That's how much I want to play again.''</p>
        <p>There is nothing in Knoblauch's resume that would suggest he might exaggerate the seriousness of pain or injury, as George Steinbrenner intimated last week. Say this for Steinbrenner: When he made the calculated decision to cast doubt on Knoblauch's professional integrity, he was taking aim at a player renowned for his resilience and toughness.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch, bothered by a sore elbow since July 24, worked out extensively this afternoon, Manager Joe Torre standing close behind him as he fielded ground balls and threw, and Knoblauch could play again in a day or two. Knoblauch said he felt encouraged, and Torre saw much improvement and has hope that Knoblauch will play regularly again. ''I'd still rather have Jeter hitting second and Knoblauch leading off,'' Torre said. ''Maybe we will.''</p>
        <p>Ray Knoblauch, the father of the second baseman, was a well-respected and established member of Houston's amateur baseball community, and he raised his son to practice and play with an old-fashioned work ethic. If you joined a team, you were expected to be available for every game; summer vacations or camps were not an acceptable excuse.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch had back spasms in his first full year of professional baseball and was out for two weeks, and after breaking into the majors in 1991 and playing 151 games that year, he never missed more than 12 games in any season. He had never been on the disabled list until early last month.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch's durability has gone beyond playing virtually every day. Early in his career, Knoblauch began digging into the batter's box with both feet and refusing to move them. If a pitcher throws inside, Knoblauch turns his torso a bit or drops his left elbow to protect his left side. But his feet are planted, and Knoblauch has consistently ranked among the American League leaders in being hit by pitches.</p>
        <p>''The pitcher tries to own both sides of the plate, he won't give in and give any ground,'' Knoblauch explained. ''So why should I, as a hitter, give any ground? I don't try and get hit by pitches. I just stand where I stand. If they just miss inside, they're going to hit me.''</p>
        <p>Roger Clemens said: ''If anybody needs to wear those elbow protectors, he would be one of them. His arms are right on the inside corner, and he gets hit a lot there.''</p>
        <p>Playing second base and being the target of base runners trying to break up double plays, Knoblauch has played his entire career as a target. In 1999, Knoblauch took a throw at second base in Minnesota, stepped away from the bag and was leveled at the knees by the Twins' Corey Koskie. Knoblauch writhed on the ground, and teammates were convinced his left knee had been torn apart. But Knoblauch limped onto the team plane later that day and returned to the lineup after missing only a few days.</p>
        <p>When Knoblauch's throwing problems erupted at the end of last season and in the playoffs, he was the subject of intense scrutiny, enemy fans jeering every time the ball was hit in his vicinity. Knoblauch blocked out that attention, however, and batted .333 in the League Championship Series against Boston and .313 in the World Series. ''That guy is tough,'' said Luis Sojo, the Yankees' infielder. ''Anybody else would've taken their bats and gone home.''</p>
        <p>In the aftermath of some terrible throws in a game against the Chicago White Sox in May, a frustrated Knoblauch speculated that he would quit if he could not solve his throwing trouble. The comments might be at the root of Steinbrenner's doubts about Knoblauch's willingness to play -- that, and the fact that team doctors cannot identify the source of the pain Knoblauch feels.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner's comments have placed him in a no-lose situation. If Knoblauch does not play regularly the rest of the season, Steinbrenner can always maintain he was right about Knoblauch, that his injury was not as serious as he contends. If Knoblauch moves back into the lineup for good later this week, Steinbrenner can say his words pushed the second baseman back onto the field.</p>
        <p>''I'll say this -- I don't need any motivation or pep talks,'' Knoblauch said. ''I don't need them now and I've never needed them. If I needed motivation or pep talks, I wouldn't have had the major league career I've had.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
