<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bridgestone Agrees to Recall 62,000 Tires in Venezuela</title>
    <meta content="Y05TIR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venezuela</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7DB1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bridgestone Agrees to Recall 62,000 Tires in Venezuela</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela, Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bridgestone/Firestone agrees to recall 62,000 tires that Venezuelan government says have defects that appear to have played role in deaths of at least 60 people in automobile accidents; Venezuelan government praises company, which accounts for about half of all tires sold in Venezuela; will push ahead with its investigation into accusations that Bridgestone knew of defects its tires manufactured in Venezuela and US and tried to cover them up (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Facing the threat of criminal and civil actions here, Bridgestone/Firestone agreed today to recall 62,000 tires that the Venezuelan government says had defects that appear to have played a role in the deaths of at least 60 people in automobile accidents.</p>
        <p>Samuel Ruh Rios, director of the Consumer Defense and Education Institute, a government agency, announced the measure at a news conference here and praised the company, which accounts for about half of all tires sold here, calling its action ''a good sign.'' But he made it clear that Venezuela intends to press ahead with its investigation into accusations that Bridgestone knew of defects in tires manufactured here and in the United States and tried to cover them up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Facing the threat of criminal and civil actions here, Bridgestone/Firestone agreed today to recall 62,000 tires that the Venezuelan government says had defects that appear to have played a role in the deaths of at least 60 people in automobile accidents.</p>
        <p>Samuel Ruh Rios, director of the Consumer Defense and Education Institute, a government agency, announced the measure at a news conference here and praised the company, which accounts for about half of all tires sold here, calling its action ''a good sign.'' But he made it clear that Venezuela intends to press ahead with its investigation into accusations that Bridgestone knew of defects in tires manufactured here and in the United States and tried to cover them up.</p>
        <p>''This measure in no way exonerates Firestone from what we have been pointing out, which is the shared responsibility of Firestone and Ford in the design and selection of an inadequate tire,'' Mr. Ruh said. He added that the prosecutor general would determine what further action Venezuela's government would take.</p>
        <p>''With this, the Venezuelan consumer has won a battle'' and been ''somewhat compensated,'' Mr. Ruh added. ''But the consumer and Indecu,'' the Spanish-language acronym by which the agency is known, ''are still on a war footing because we do not feel satisfied by this type of action.''</p>
        <p>All but a handful of the fatal accidents being investigated by the consumer protection agency occurred when Ford Explorer sports utility vehicles with Firestone tires went out of control and flipped over on highways here after their tires shredded or exploded. For that reason, Mr. Ruh said today, Ford also has a moral and financial responsibility to Venezuelan consumers.</p>
        <p>''We suggest to the Ford Motor  Company that they study a series of measures to see if they too can aid in the search for the truth,'' he said. ''We don't blame the tire alone'' for the accidents, he added, saying that an appropriate response by Ford would be to ''withdraw this model, substitute them and pay owners'' some form of compensation.</p>
        <p>The two varieties of Wilderness AT tires to be replaced, at a cost estimated at $6.4 million, include, but are not limited to, those often used on Ford Explorers. Mr. Ruh said the tire replacement program would begin on Thursday and continue for about a month and that it would affect not only Ford Explorers and other sports utility vehicles but also some pickup trucks.</p>
        <p>Telephone calls made to the Bridgestone/Firestone plant in Valencia, about 90 miles southwest of here, were referred to the company's public relations representatives here, and Ford did not respond to requests for comment. A Firestone representaive, Milagros Hinojosa, confirmed the tire recall but deferred further comment until after publication of an announcement that she said would be published in Venezuelan newspapers on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Bridgestone/Firestone and Ford  have been under mounting fire here since Venezuelan officials began their inquiry, alerted by a similar investigation in the United States. Mr. Ruh said the Firestone recall marked a significant shift from the company's previous position, which was that ''only 3,000 tires imported from the United States in 1995'' had the manufacturing defects and that tires made in Venezuela did not.</p>
        <p>''We continue to investigate, because we continue to receive new complaints'' of faulty tires on Ford Explorers, Jorge Dominguez, chief of the consumer protection agency's investigative division, said in an interview this morning.</p>
        <p>The agency now estimates the number of accidents that occurred after Firestone tires shredded at 74 and says that at least 60 Venezuelans died as a result.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruh said that while his agency did not have the power to file criminal or civil charges, both Ford and  Bridgestone/Firestone would be sent citations on Tuesday ordering them to participate in a ''conciliation process'' at the consumer protection agency's offices here next week. The purpose, he said, is to see if the companies are willing to provide compensation to complainants.</p>
        <p>If that process fails, Mr. Ruh said, the government would then begin an administrative procedure that could result in fines of up to $11,600 per violation. But that money would paid into the government's coffers, not to the victims of tire blowouts on highways here or to their survivors.</p>
        <p>Last week, the consumer protection agency recommended to the office of the federal prosecutor that an investigation into possible criminal negligence on the part of both Ford and Bridgestone/Firestone be started. In addition, lawyers here have said they plan to file civil damage suits here and in the United States on behalf of people injured or killed in Firestone tire blowouts.</p>
        <p>Such a process, however, promises to be long and difficult. Venezuela has virtually no consumer liability legislation, its courts are notoriously corrupt and lawyers say that the regulations accompanying a new Constitution approved last December have made it even harder than in the past for victims who win civil actions to recover damages from those responsible for their losses.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
