<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israel Loosens Telephone Monopoly's Grip</title>
    <meta content="Y05PHO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slowdowns and Job Actions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bezeq (Israeli Telephone Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orme, William A Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Orme, William A Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3D71E30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israel Loosens Telephone Monopoly's Grip</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM A. ORME Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Orme, William A Jr</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli government is ending state company's monopoly on domestic telephone and Internet service, a step that sets stage for company's sale to private investors later this year; telephone company, Bezeq, now faces competition for first time in Israel's local telephone and high-speed Internet market; government plans to divest its majority stake in $5 billion enterprise; unionized telephone workers protest decision with partial work stoppage, but government vows to proceed with plans to grant telephone and data transmission licenses to new wireless networks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Israeli government announced today that it was ending the state telephone company's monopoly on domestic telephone and Internet service, taking a long-resisted deregulatory move that sets the stage for the company's sale to private investors later this year.</p>
        <p>Bezeq, the state-owned telephone company, will now face competition for the first time in Israel's local  telephone and high-speed Internet market, just months before the government plans to divest its majority stake in the $5 billion enterprise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Israeli government announced today that it was ending the state telephone company's monopoly on domestic telephone and Internet service, taking a long-resisted deregulatory move that sets the stage for the company's sale to private investors later this year.</p>
        <p>Bezeq, the state-owned telephone company, will now face competition for the first time in Israel's local  telephone and high-speed Internet market, just months before the government plans to divest its majority stake in the $5 billion enterprise.</p>
        <p>Unionized telephone workers protested the decision with a partial stopping of work, but the government vowed to proceed with plans to grant telephone and data transmission licenses to new wireless networks and long-established cable television operators.</p>
        <p>''The market is now completely open,'' Communications Minister Benjamin Ben-Eliezer declared after signing a decree setting out the new rules for the industry.</p>
        <p>Bidders for the new 15-year telecommunications licenses must be at least 20 percent Israeli-owned and must provide service within a year of approval, the minister said.</p>
        <p>The state monopoly on domestic telephone and Internet service has come under intensifying criticism as a costly anomaly for a country that is a spawning grounds for digital telecommunications technologies and that had long since opened its long-distance and mobile phone service to fierce internal competition.</p>
        <p>''We still don't have high-speed Internet access, we don't have cable modems, we don't have all these things we hear and read about,'' said Katrin Lemter, a telecommunications industry analyst at Bank Hapaolim in Tel Aviv.</p>
        <p>The battle over domestic telephone deregulation and the privatization of Bezeq pits its powerful government-allied union against the politically influential cable television operators, whose regional monopolies have become the cash-rich keystones of diversified media empires.</p>
        <p>Though the cable companies won this round, they cannot offer phone service unless the parliament amends current telecommunications laws -- a protracted process even if Prime Minister Ehud Barak manages to keep his minority coalition in power to the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''Assuming there is a government, it could take several months,'' Ms. Lemter said. ''If there is no government, it could take anything.''</p>
        <p>Before then, foreign telecommunications companies are expected to enter the marketplace with new fixed-point wireless systems for household telephone and high-speed Internet service. The government said that within a month it expects to issue tenders for networks using wireless local loop and multipoint distribution systems, both of which permit wireless phone service from fixed locations.</p>
        <p>Though Bezeq still hopes to be the first to offer a new high-speed Internet connection to its customers, the government has not yet decided whether this would give it an unfair advantage over new entrants in the deregulated telecommunications market. Cable television companies may also be authorized to provide high-speed Internet service in the coming weeks, Mr. Ben-Eliezer said today.</p>
        <p>Bezeq has already weathered the loss of its long-distance monopoly and is one of three competitors in Israel's cutthroat cellular phone market. Analysts say its stock is undervalued compared with that of European state phone companies with similar reach and revenues, but still-unresolved regulatory issues make it difficult to assess Bezeq's market value to foreign investors, they say.</p>
        <p>''The sad thing is that Israel has no clear concept for the telecommunications business, no official policy, no white papers, no green papers, nothing,'' said David Boaz, a former Finance Ministry official who is now a private industry consultant.</p>
        <p>The sale of a majority stake in Bezeq would represent the first major privatization initiative by the Barak administration, which inherited several stalled divestiture plans from the previous government. Minority government holdings in commercial banks are being gradually sold off through the stock market, but resistance from unions and from within the prime minister's own party have effectively halted plans for the deregulation and eventual privatization of state-owned military companies and the national power company.</p>
        <p>Israel's airline, El Al, once seen as the next candidate for privatization, also now appears to be likely to remain in state hands for some time. El Al's chief executive quit last week after four years on the job, complaining in his resignation letter that the Barak administration was not pursuing the sale to private investors that was announced by the previous government. That plan was abandoned under pressure from Orthodox Jews, who objected to permitting new owners to operate flights on the Jewish Sabbath.</p>
        <p>In the Bezeq privatization, the government first plans to sell a small stake through a stock offering to finance a fund for pensions and severance payments for workers who might lose their jobs under private management. Then it wants a ''strategic investor'' -- a foreign telecommunications giant with an Israeli minority partner -- to acquire its remaining 50 percent holding.</p>
        <p>But the Bezeq union has promised to fight privatization unless it is satisfied with the new pension fund arrangements -- and unless Bezeq gets a head start in the race to provide high-speed Internet access. The union has wide support in the parliament's finance committee, which must approve any privatization deal.</p>
        <p>''We're afraid that once the company's status changes, new owners will come, as we have seen in previous instances, and will try to change existing agreements,'' the head of the Bezeq workers' union, Shlomo Kfir, said today. ''That's why we want to safeguard the rights of employees and retired employees. Without that I don't think that we'll agree to any measure -- neither competition nor privatization.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
