<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Groh Controls Emotions At an Emotional Time</title>
    <meta content="05JETS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Bay Packers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Groh, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Green Bay Packers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3DA1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Groh Controls Emotions At an Emotional Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets coach Al Groh discusses season-opening victory over Green Bay Packers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For prodigious emotion, the Jets have Vinny Testaverde, who wept as he sat at his locker after Sunday's victory at Lambeau Field.</p>
        <p>For stoicism, the Jets have Al Groh. But after his first victory as a National Football League head coach, Groh stood on the field at the the game shaking his players' hands. But that, he said today, was not an unusual gesture, and was not in recognition of the significance of the moment. It was merely a show of appreciation for a job well done.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For prodigious emotion, the Jets have Vinny Testaverde, who wept as he sat at his locker after Sunday's victory at Lambeau Field.</p>
        <p>For stoicism, the Jets have Al Groh. But after his first victory as a National Football League head coach, Groh stood on the field at the the game shaking his players' hands. But that, he said today, was not an unusual gesture, and was not in recognition of the significance of the moment. It was merely a show of appreciation for a job well done.</p>
        <p>''It's really genuine,'' Groh said. ''I removed my personal feelings from that game. I don't have any Al Groh feelings about it. The only feelings I have are what the coach of the Jets would have about it. I didn't have trouble going to sleep. The problem was staying asleep very long. There was still enough energy to wake me up pretty early.''</p>
        <p>Bill Parcells used to have trouble sleeping after games, too. But with Parcells staying at home rather than accompanying the team to Green Bay, Groh had taken one imperceptible step from Parcells's shadow if only because he so steadfastly does not behave like Parcells. For all his gruffness, Parcells's rubbery face usually betrayed his feelings. Groh unleashed a few smiles after the Green Bay game, gave a vote of approval to his defense, which held the Packers to only 211 yards total offense, and its coordinator, Mike Nolan, today and that was about it.</p>
        <p>He spoke to Parcells at length this morning about the game and then explained why Parcells was not in Green Bay for the debut of the man he hand-picked as his successor.</p>
        <p>''It was kind of a personal decision,'' Groh said. ''But Bill's support has been among the strongest that have happened to me. I pay more attention to Bill's presence than anyone else does.''</p>
        <p>Groh will get no relief this week from those who seek to make him a star in a turgid soap opera. On Monday, the Jets (1-0) play New England (0-1), a franchise whose recent history is so tightly bound with Parcells and the Jets that it is practically New York North and that is now coached by the man who set in motion one of the most bizarre episodes in the Jets' weird history.</p>
        <p>Naturally, Groh, who was Parcells's defensive coordinator and linebackers coach in New England, claims to feel nothing special about the prospect of facing Bill Belichick, who quit as the Jets' head coach only about 24 hours after Parcells had publicly retired, and whom Groh calls a friend. Parcells chose Groh after Belichick said he did not want to be the ''HC'' of the ''N.Y. Jets,'' as his famous scribbled resignation note put it. Now, of course, Belichick, who designed the defense the Jets use today, has extraordinary knowledge of the Jets' personnel and tendencies. Groh, too, knows many of the players in New England and said he would not try to block out how deeply he knows Belichick and the way he thinks.</p>
        <p>To add more sizzle, Parcells, in an interview recently, made a thinly veiled suggestion that perhaps Belichick had something in the works with the New England owner Robert Kraft long before he resigned. The Tuna Bowl is about to get another course. And Groh is not biting.</p>
        <p>''It's the same feelings I had coaching against Green Bay,'' Groh said. ''I don't have any personal feelings about it. I'm just trying to coach the team. Bill and I visited at the league meetings in the spring. I consider Bill a colleague and a guy I experienced a lot of good Sundays with. It would be foolish to block it out. I tried to figure out how Mike Sherman thinks, getting ready for that game. This is a game about people, not just plays. You always factor in how decision makers think. The more you know, the better off you are. It's better than being in the dark.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>There seems to be some confusion about what kind of knee injury running back CURTIS MARTIN sustained. Coach AL GROH told reporters Monday that Martin took a helmet to his left knee. But on Sunday, the Jets announced the injury as a twisted knee. Martin was treated on the bench and returned to catch the game-winning touchdown. . . . When the rookie CHAD PENNINGTON was listed as the Jets' third quarterback for the Green Bay game, people wondered when he had returned to practice from a sprained knee. Groh said that while Pennington was involved in practice, he had not taken any snaps. Still, Pennington's recovery seems ahead of schedule. The Jets expected him to be out until October. . . . To make room for tackle JUMBO ELLIOTT, who served a one-game suspension last week, the Jets waived tight end JAKE MORELAND.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
