<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="05PUBL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228150"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rose Center for Earth and Space (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cronkite, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vidal, Gore</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Chita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ladd, Cheryl</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Best Man, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Anything Goes (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Annie Get Your Gun (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4DC1F30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column; Walter Cronkite discusses making voice-over for revival of Gore Vidal's The Best Man; Chita Rivera joins cast of Cole Porter's Anything Goes; Thomas O'Brien, 8, is two millionth visitor to Rose Center for Earth and Space at American Museum of Natural History; Cheryl Ladd to make her debut in Annie Get Your Gun; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Voice Sounds Familiar</p>
        <p>''This is WALTER CRONKITE with the news from Philadelphia,'' the stentorian voice boomed over the speakers in the recording room on West 17th Street. ''How bizarre; it sounds just like Walter Cronkite,'' the theatrical director in the control room, ETHAN McSWEENY, joked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Voice Sounds Familiar</p>
        <p>''This is WALTER CRONKITE with the news from Philadelphia,'' the stentorian voice boomed over the speakers in the recording room on West 17th Street. ''How bizarre; it sounds just like Walter Cronkite,'' the theatrical director in the control room, ETHAN McSWEENY, joked.</p>
        <p>''I've spent years trying to imitate him,'' said the man in the headphones, who was, in fact, Walter Cronkite. Under Mr. McSweeny's direction, he finished recording a voice-over, an offstage narrative written some time ago by GORE VIDAL for a revival of ''The Best Man.'' Mr. Vidal's 1960 political satire about the race for the presidency has its first preview tonight for a Sept. 17 opening.</p>
        <p>Then the 83-year-old broadcaster, who retired as the CBS Evening News anchor in 1981, phoned Mr. Vidal at his house in Ravello, Italy. He teased the author that he ought to revise the wording of the voice-over to reflect the changes in American conventions since 1960. ''Do whatever makes you feel comfortable,'' Mr. Vidal invited.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Cronkite rewrote his lines on the spot, then re-recorded them: ''This is Walter Cronkite. Political conventions today aren't what they used to be. There was a time when politics played openly on the convention floor for the elucidation, delight and possibly the dismay of the American people. This is the way it was in 1960.''</p>
        <p>Just Call Her Rita</p>
        <p>The cast of COLE PORTER's ''Anything Goes'' confronted the solemn business of its initial rehearsal on a recent morning, and the actress starring in the role of Reno Sweeney, CHITA RIVERA, rose to introduce herself. ''Hi, I'm RITA MORENO,'' she said, breaking the ice and breaking up the cast of 25 with her reference to the musical-theater star with whom she is most persistently confused.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rivera, who is 66, gathered with the cast in a rehearsal room last week to give the theater community a foretaste of the new production, which opens tomorrow night at the Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn, N.J., and runs until Oct. 15.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rivera recalled that Ethel Merman, who created the role of Reno Sweeney, was the star of ''my very first show,'' she said, '' 'Call Me Madam,' back in, it must have been, 1952.'' In this production, Ms. Rivera is ''much more of a dancing Reno Sweeney'' than Ethel Merman, she said, adding: ''Would anyone think I could sing like her?''</p>
        <p>Big Bang Bash</p>
        <p>It seems that 8-year-old THOMAS O'BRIEN of Branford, Conn. has outpaced the likes of KEVIN BACON, FRANCIS FORD COPPOLA, KATIE COURIC, DUSTIN HOFFMAN, HENRY KISSINGER, STEVE MARTIN, ROBERT REDFORD, ROBIN WILLIAMS, ROY SCHEIDER and STEVEN SPIELBERG.</p>
        <p>Like Thomas, all of these bold-facers have been planetarium visitors since the Feb. 19 debut of the new $210 million Rose Center for Earth and Space at the American Museum of Natural History.</p>
        <p>Thomas's coup? Last week, he became the two millionth visitor to the  planetarium.</p>
        <p>Once More, 'Angel' To Get Her Gun</p>
        <p>When CHERYL LADD makes her debut on Broadway tomorrow night, starring in ''Annie Get Your Gun,'' audiences will see an Annie Oakley who is no stranger to a rifle.</p>
        <p>In Huron, S.D., Ms. Ladd used to hunt with her father, MARION, ''who hunted pheasant,'' she said, ''and if it hadn't been for that, we wouldn't have had any meat on the table in some of those tough winters.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ladd, who replaces BERNADETTE PETERS in ''Annie,'' will take the lead in the show at the Marquis Theater until Jan. 28.</p>
        <p>Ironically, during the four years until 1981 that Ms. Ladd played Kris Munroe, the comic-relief rookie on the television series ''Charlie's Angels,'' ''I only got to shoot my gun twice,'' she said.</p>
        <p>GLENN COLLINS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
