<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</title>
    <meta content="27KIDS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DF1131F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF POR QUINLY,''  an undersea adventure with music, tomorrow and Nov. 4 at 11 a.m. The play is by Quincy Long, with music by Michael Silversher, and directed by Kathleen Dimmick. Atlantic Theater Company, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea. Tickets: $10; $5 for children under 12. Reservations: (212) 691-5919.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF POR QUINLY,''  an undersea adventure with music, tomorrow and Nov. 4 at 11 a.m. The play is by Quincy Long, with music by Michael Silversher, and directed by Kathleen Dimmick. Atlantic Theater Company, 336 West 20th Street, Chelsea. Tickets: $10; $5 for children under 12. Reservations: (212) 691-5919.</p>
        <p>''FRANKENSTEIN: THE ROCK MUSICAL,'' William Electric Black's rock 'n' roll version of Mary Shelley's 1816 romantic novel, with music ranging from rock to reggae to New Orleans honky-tonk. Thursdays through Saturdays at 10 p.m.; Sundays at 5 p.m. Through Nov. 19. Tickets: $15. Tickets: (212) 475-7710.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK GREAT HALLOWEEN PARTY, tomorrow from 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. in Central Park; enter the park at 72nd Street and Fifth or Central Park West. There will be pumpkin giveaways, costume-making, theater performances, a dress your pet-for-Halloween contest, in-line skating, puppet shows and a haunted house. Information: (888) 697-2757.</p>
        <p>''CHELSEA PIERS HALLOWEEN CARNIVAL,'' tomorrow from noon to 4 p.m. at Pier 62, 23rd Street and the Hudson River. Geared to children ages 5 to 14, the event features sports-related and carnival games, pumpkin decorating, face painting, a ''Haunted Ship'' and costumed characters. The day concludes with the costume parade. (More than 900 children took part last year.) Rain or shine. Information: (212) 336-6881. Free.</p>
        <p>''FESTIVAL OF FALLING LEAVES,'' tomorrow and Sunday from 1 to 5 p.m. at the Staten Island Children's Museum, Snug Harbor Cultural Center, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Livingston, featuring a ''Ghouls and Fools'' costume parade, traditional harvest wreath-making, traditional Native American ghost stories and Mexican Day of the Dead crafts and activities. Youngsters, who should come in costume, can get a monster makeover and participate in scarecrow stuffing and pumpkin decorating. Free with admission: $4, free for members and children under age 2. Information: (718) 273-2060.</p>
        <p>''GHOULS AND GOURDS.'' Halloween festivities Sunday from noon to 4 p.m. at the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, 1000 Washington Avenue, Prospect Heights, will feature a costume parade, a haunted children's garden, face painting and pumpkin decorating ($2 fee). Youngsters can tour the haunted children's garden house or investigate the compost creepy-crawlies in the worm composting exhibition. Admission: $3; $1.50 for students and the elderly; free for children 15 and under; free on Tuesdays, except holidays, and free from 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. Information: (718) 623-7333.</p>
        <p>''HALLOWEEN AT CHILDREN'S MUSEUM OF THE ARTS,'' 182 Lafayette Street, SoHo, Sunday, from noon to 5 p.m. From noon to 3 p.m. youngsters can build a haunted castle, a monster mummy and sorcerers' wands and hats. Admission: $5. The annual Trick or Treat parade is free and begins at 3 p.m., with more than 30 stores and restaurants distributing candy. Information: (212) 274-0986.</p>
        <p>HALLOWEEN FAMILY DAY CONCERT, featuring the Queens Symphony Orchestra, Sunday at 2 p.m. at Queens College's Colden Center, Kissena Boulevard at the L.I.E., Flushing Queens. Stravinsky, Ravel and Tchaikovsky are on the program. The musicians will be dressed as scary monsters. Audience members should come in costume, and there will be a prize for the scariest. Tickets: $20 and $25; $17.50 for students and the elderly; $10 for children under 10. Information: (718) 786-8880.</p>
        <p>''HALLOWEEN HI-JINKS,'' Sunday from 1 to 3 p.m., at the Mount Vernon Hotel Museum and Garden, 421 East 61st Street, Manhattan, featuring 19th-century activities like fortune-telling games, bobbing for apples and storytelling inspired by Celtic harvest festivals. Youngsters 3 to 12 should wear costumes for a costume parade. Tickets: $6; $4 for children under 12 and museum members. Advance tickets advised. Information: (212) 838-6878.</p>
        <p>''HALLOWEEN ON HAUNTED WALK,'' Sunday from 2 to 4 p.m., features Ralph Lee's Halloween puppets and other spooky creatures lurking in the trees, peeping from the rocks and creeping through the bushes of the New York Botanical Garden, 200th Street and Kazimiroff Boulevard, Fordham, the Bronx, The cast of characters will include a walking pumpkin, tap-dancing skeletons, wizards, phantoms, ghosts and goblins. Revelers should come in costumes. Admission: $1 plus garden admission: $3; students and the elderly, $2; children 2 to 12, $1; under 2, free; free Saturdays from 10 a.m. to noon. There are also special garden-package and combination rates available, which include the Everett Children's Adventure Garden and the Conservatory. Information: (718)  817-8700.</p>
        <p>''HALLOWEEN ON THE HUDSON: ANNUAL MORAN'S MONSTER MASH.'' The Battery Park City Parents Association's annual Halloween parade for children begins at 11:15 a.m. tomorrow at Au Bon Pain, at the corner of South End Avenue and Liberty Street, World Financial Center, ending at Edward Moran Bar and Grill, 4 World Financial Center, 250 Vesey Street. The party, which runs from noon to 4 p.m., will include a magic show, pumpkin carving, scary stories and creepy games. Information: (212) 945-2600. Free.</p>
        <p>''HAUNTED HOUSE,'' today through Tuesday from 3:30 to 6:30 p.m. at the Queens County Farm Museum, 73-50 Little Neck Parkway, Floral Park, Queens. Admission: $5; $4 for groups of 20 or more. Reservations required. Not recommended for children under 5. Information: (718) 343-2005. Sunday from 11 a.m. to 4 p.m., the annual Children's Fall Festival, including visits to the haunted house, sack races, pony rides, scarecrow making and a petting zoo. Admission: $2. Free parking. Information: (718) 347-3276.</p>
        <p>''HORROR ON THE HUDSON.'' The New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, near 77th Street, will present a festival, featuring ghoulish storytelling, creepy crafts and a special constructed Haunted Kid City in the lower level of the museum, Sunday from 1 to 4 p.m. The storytelling will feature headless horsemen and moonless nights on the banks of the Hudson River, with inspiration from the museum's current exhibition ''Intimate Friends: Thomas Cole, Asher Durand and William Cullen Bryant,'' founders of the Hudson River School. Youngsters will also play games for prizes, including pinning the head on the headless horseman. Free for children 12 and under accompanied by an adult. Otherwise, adult admission: $5. Information: (212) 873-3400, extension 0.</p>
        <p>''MONSTER MASH AND HARVEST FESTIVAL,'' tomorrow night from 6:30 to 8:30, at the Brooklyn Children's Museum, 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Mark's Avenue, Crown Heights. Activities include performances by Jerry Joy Music, Spiderwoman Theater and the Mohawk Singers and Dancers. There will also be mask-making, storytelling, apple cider-tasting, a haunted house and scary exhibitions. Tickets: $5; $25 for a family of 6. Information: (718) 735-4402.</p>
        <p>''PETER AND THE WOLF,'' a new musical adaptation set to music by Prokoviev, presented by the Pushcart Players, tomorrow at 11 a.m. and 1 p.m. at the Queens Theater in the Park, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Exit 9E off the Grand Central Parkway. Tickets: $8; $6 for members. Information: (718) 760-0064.</p>
        <p>''WILLIAM SHAKESPEARE'S HAUNTED SHIP.'' Shakespeare is appearing on the tall ship Peking (made up to look like a spooky ghost ship), docked at Pier 17 at the South Street Seaport, South and Fulton Streets, at 5, 7 and 9 p.m. through Tuesday. The show -- featuring Shakespeare's scarier creations, including Richard III, the witches from ''Macbeth,'' and the ghost of Hamlet's father -- is a cross between a haunted-house tour and a Shakespearean spoof and is presented by the Faux-Real Theater Company. Tickets: $20; $15 age 12 and under for youngsters. Information: (212) 981-8250.</p>
        <p>Exhibitions</p>
        <p>''GOOD GRIEF!'' Charlie Brown and his creator, Charles M. Schulz, are the stars of this exhibition, in which families are invited to inhabit a life-size version of the ''Peanuts'' comic strip. Activities include video games, a psychotherapy session at Lucy's booth (cost: 5 cents) and a crawl through the Great Pumpkin Patch. Children's Museum of Manhattan, Tisch Building, 212 West 83rd Street. Beginning tomorrow through Tuesday, the museum will celebrate Halloween with a Peanuts ''Great Pumpkin'' festival, including a shadow puppet-making workshop; story readings by the author Michael Rex tomorrow and with the storyteller LuAnn Adams on Tuesday; feats of magic with Marco the magician (tomorrow, Sunday and Tuesday at 2 p.m.), and Halloween tunes by Jerry Joy Music (tomorrow, Sunday and Tuesday at 3 p.m.). Admission will be free on Tuesday. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free with museum admission: $6; $3 for the elderly; infants, free. Information: (212) 721-1234.</p>
        <p>Zoos</p>
        <p>''BOO AT THE ZOO,'' at the Central Park Zoo and Tisch Children's Zoo, Fifth Avenue at 64th Street, Manhattan, tomorrow and Sunday from 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Highlights include costumed characters, face painting, crafts and storytelling. Free with zoo admission: $3.50; the elderly, $1.25; children 3 to 12, 50 cents; under 3, free. Admission includes entry to the nearby Tisch Children's Zoo. Information: (212) 861-6030.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
