<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="27MBRF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/nyregion/27MBRF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E3DA1E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>HAUPPAUGE: CELL-PHONE CALL BAN SIGNED  County Executive Robert J. Gaffney of Suffolk County yesterday signed what is believed to be the nation's first countywide ban on driving with a hand-held cellular phone. The bill, which the County Legislature passed Oct. 3, prohibits using a cell phone while driving, unless it has an earpiece or can act like a speakerphone. Emergency calls are exempted from the ban, which takes effect next Jan. 1, 2001, and carries a $150 fine.</p>
        <p>Tina Kelley (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: TERROR TRIAL SET  A federal judge in Manhattan set a trial date of April 17, 2001, for two men charged with assisting in a terrorist plot involving an attempt by a group of Algerians to smuggle powerful explosives into the United States near Seattle. The defendants, Abdel Ghani Meskini, left, and Mokhtar Haouari, have each pleaded not guilty to the charges and are being held without bond. Earlier this week, a federal judge ruled that statements Mr. Meskini gave the authorities after he was arrested in Brooklyn on Dec. 30 could be used at trial. Mr. Meskini had sought to suppress those statements.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Weiser (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>HAUPPAUGE: CELL-PHONE CALL BAN SIGNED  County Executive Robert J. Gaffney of Suffolk County yesterday signed what is believed to be the nation's first countywide ban on driving with a hand-held cellular phone. The bill, which the County Legislature passed Oct. 3, prohibits using a cell phone while driving, unless it has an earpiece or can act like a speakerphone. Emergency calls are exempted from the ban, which takes effect next Jan. 1, 2001, and carries a $150 fine.</p>
        <p>Tina Kelley (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: TERROR TRIAL SET  A federal judge in Manhattan set a trial date of April 17, 2001, for two men charged with assisting in a terrorist plot involving an attempt by a group of Algerians to smuggle powerful explosives into the United States near Seattle. The defendants, Abdel Ghani Meskini, left, and Mokhtar Haouari, have each pleaded not guilty to the charges and are being held without bond. Earlier this week, a federal judge ruled that statements Mr. Meskini gave the authorities after he was arrested in Brooklyn on Dec. 30 could be used at trial. Mr. Meskini had sought to suppress those statements.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Weiser (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: TERM-LIMIT MEASURE  Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani fueled speculation yesterday that the City Council would try to end term limits for its members through a public referendum before the 2001 general election. ''Something should be done about the whole city government going out of existence in one day,'' the mayor said, adding that ''you probably have to change it through a vote of the people.'' Under term limits, 36 of the current 51 City Council members cannot run for re-election. Mr. Giuliani said he would not support any term-limit change to allow his own re-election.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Lueck (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: MAN KILLED IN CLUB  A 52-year-old Queens man was shot and killed early yesterday during the robbery of a Cambria Heights barbershop that is also an after-hours gambling club, the authorities said. The man, Ilvoius Lafalaise of Hollis, was among 11 people inside the La Belle Creole Barbershop on Linden Boulevard when the robbers, at least one of whom was armed with a pistol, burst in about 2:30 a.m. The robbers herded the patrons into the basement and ordered them to take off their clothes and lie down. It was unclear why the robbers shot Mr. Lafalaise, the police said.</p>
        <p>William K. Rashbaum (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: ANTI-MONEY-LAUNDERING GRANT  The United States Justice and Treasury Departments yesterday announced the award of $450,000 to the New York State attorney general's office and the state police to help state and local law enforcement officials develop new approaches to attack money laundering and other financial crimes. Officials said the New York State Police received $300,000 and the New York State attorney general's office received $150,000.</p>
        <p>William K. Rashbaum (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>PARSIPPANY: HOSPITAL DEATH  Investigators are looking into the death yesterday of a patient from Greystone Park Psychiatric Hospital. Luis Rodriguez, 50, a Greystone patient since 1997, was hospitalized on Monday at Morristown Memorial Hospital after he began vomiting blood. Prosecutors said that a patient told Greystone employees that he saw another patient beating Mr. Rodriguez. Both the State Department of Human Services and the Morris County prosecutor are investigating the death. Last April, Gov. Christine Todd Whitman ordered that the hospital, which has</p>
        <p>JERSEY CITY: BRIDGE IS REVAMPED  The State Department of Transportation plans to make improvements to Route 7 near the Wittpenn Bridge, which was the scene of two crashes earlier this month that killed five people and critically injured another one. In both accidents, cars on the bridge, which crosses the Hackensack River, were struck by oncoming trucks as they reached a curve in the four-lane roadway. The department will erect a concrete barrier to separate the opposing traffic and will narrow the curve to one lane from two.</p>
        <p>Maria Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW BRUNSWICK: POLICE OPERATED BROTHEL  A Middlesex County jury convicted two New Brunswick police officers yesterday of operating a brothel in a warehouse in the city. The defendants, Detective James Marshall and Sgt. Marco Chinchilla, face multiyear prison terms after being convicted on all three charges they faced: promoting prostitution, conspiracy and official misconduct. The jury deliberated less than eight hours over two days before returning guilty verdicts against the officers and three others.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: WHITMAN TO GIVE G.O.P. RESPONSE  Gov. Christine Todd Whitman will deliver the Republican response to President Clinton's weekly radio address tomorrow. Republican members of Congress and governors take turns delivering the radio remarks, according to a spokesman for the Republican Governors Association.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>NEW HAVEN: YALE BUILDING PLAN  Yale University plans to spend $250 million to construct a building and renovate other space for its art, architecture and drama programs over the next 8 to 10 years, the university said yesterday. Earlier this year, Yale announced that it would spend $1 billion to upgrade and expand its science, engineering and medical facilities. The university has already received $20 million from Sid R. Bass, the Texas billionaire and former Yale trustee, to help pay for the latest project, which will renovate 500,000 square feet and add 275,000 feet for classrooms and other space.</p>
        <p>Karen W. Arenson (NYT)</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: OPINION POLL OF WOMEN  A majority of women in Connecticut feel they are not benefiting from the strong national economy, according to a new survey. When asked whether ''the current economic boom reached people like you and your family,'' 57 percent of women surveyed said no. The survey, conducted for the state's Permanent Commission on the Status of Women and for other organizations, also found that 57 percent of women said they were having more difficulty juggling family and work than they had four years ago. The telephone poll of 400 women was taken Sept. 14-17.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
