<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Injury-Depleted Flyers Hand the Rangers Their Third Consecutive Defeat</title>
    <meta content="27RANG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/sports/27RANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E0DB1E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Injury-Depleted Flyers Hand the Rangers Their Third Consecutive Defeat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Oct. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philadelphia Flyers defeat New York Rangers, 3-0, Philadelphia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Nothing's written in stone,'' Mark Messier said after the Rangers were beaten, 3-0, by the Philadelphia Flyers tonight. ''Nothing says anybody has to play anywhere.''</p>
        <p>Messier was referring to the Rangers' lines, which Coach Ron Low juggled in the third period, something Low said he would probably do again when the Rangers are host to the Pittsburgh Penguins on Friday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Nothing's written in stone,'' Mark Messier said after the Rangers were beaten, 3-0, by the Philadelphia Flyers tonight. ''Nothing says anybody has to play anywhere.''</p>
        <p>Messier was referring to the Rangers' lines, which Coach Ron Low juggled in the third period, something Low said he would probably do again when the Rangers are host to the Pittsburgh Penguins on Friday night.</p>
        <p>That would be likely to mean the end, at least for now, of the Czech Line, the Rangers' most productive threesome a season ago.</p>
        <p>''That very well may happen tomorrow night,'' Low said after the Rangers had lost for the fifth time in six games.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, we played quite well together last year,'' said center Petr Nedved, referring to himself and his Czech linemates Jan Hlavac and Radek Dvorak.</p>
        <p>''But we're struggling this year and we're not winning right now,'' Nedved added. ''Sometimes changes happen.''</p>
        <p>For the second consecutive game, the Rangers lost to an injury-depleted Flyers team that had won one of its first eight games before taking two in three nights from the Rangers.</p>
        <p>Brian Boucher had a shutout, his first this season, stopping 32 shots. The Rangers, who opened the season with a pair of victories, have now lost three straight.</p>
        <p>They have lost all four games in which they have allowed the first goal, as they did again tonight.</p>
        <p>Meet the new Rangers. Same as the old Rangers.</p>
        <p>The game marked the National Hockey League debut of the 22-year-old defenseman Mike Mottau, who won the Hobey Baker Award -- hockey's equivalent of the Heisman Trophy -- at Boston College last season.</p>
        <p>Mottau admitted that he was a bit nervous this afternoon.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, I'll get a bump in right off the bat and get the nerves out,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mottau was paired with Rich Pilon, and the two skated five shifts in a first period dominated by the Flyers.</p>
        <p>The Rangers' defense was not the problem, as it was Tuesday night at Madison Square Garden. It was the offense. For most of the first period, the Rangers fought -- for the most part in vain -- to extricate themselves and the puck from their own zone.</p>
        <p>For the third consecutive game, the Rangers allowed the first goal. This time, it came at 7 minutes 7 seconds, from a player who had not scored a goal in the N.H.L. since Nov. 8, 1998, from a defenseman who had never scored a goal for the Flyers: Michal Sykora.</p>
        <p>Sykora was the beneficiary of a circle-to-circle pass from Paul Ranheim, who threaded it through four Rangers while New York had its fourth line on the ice. Rangers goalie Mike Richter, who was making his second start this season, seemed as surprised as anyone that the pass found its way through the slot. As Sykora one-timed the puck behind Richter, Richter still had his back toward the left wing circle, where Sykora had wound up to shoot the puck.</p>
        <p>That was it for the Flyers' offense for the first two periods. And yet Philadelphia, which had snapped a seven-game stretch without a victory with Tuesday's 5-4 victory, took a 1-0 lead into the final period.</p>
        <p>It could have been more had the Rangers not killed off a boarding major by Eric Lacroix, who was also assessed a game misconduct at 12:04 of the first period for his hit from behind on the Philadelphia rookie Justin Williams. Williams was sent into the boards visor-first.</p>
        <p>The second period belonged to the Rangers, just as it did Tuesday night. The Rangers peppered Boucher with 14 shots in 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>Boucher, who last season led the league in goals-against average as a rookie, came into the game a fragile -- and frustrated -- goaltender. Over the Flyers' first six games, he had a 4.52 goals-against average. Last season, with his 1.91 goals-against average, Boucher had become the first rookie since the 1950-51 season (Terry Sawchuk and Al Rollins) to play at least 25 games and have a goals-against average under 2.00.</p>
        <p>Tonight, Boucher turned in a performance reminiscent of last season.</p>
        <p>The Flyers gained a two-goal edge when Rick Tocchet beat Richter with a backhand from the low slot, just off the right wing post, at 5:21 of the final period. Daymond Langkow added an empty-net goal at 19:40.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>MICHAL GROSEK was re-inserted into the lineup after a one-game absence as a healthy scratch. Grosek skated with ADAM GRAVES and MIKE YORK. . . . MARK MESSIER, obviously still feeling the effects of a virus, skated between VALERY KAMENSKY and THEO FLEURY again. . . . MIKE MOTTAU on his seven-game stint at Hartford of the American Hockey League: ''I fought it a little bit at the beginning. I just had to settle in. I was trying to do something special every time instead of making the simple play.'' Mottau said he wanted to try to keep it simple with the Rangers. The rookie was on the ice for RICK TOCCHET's third-period goal. Once RICH PILON had crossed over on Mottau (Pilon was playing the left side tonight, Mottau the right) to bang RUSLAN FEDOTENKO along the back boards, Mottau attempted to scramble over to pick up Tocchet, but he was too late.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
