<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Twofold Mission Of Piety and Pop</title>
    <meta content="27GOSP$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/arts/27GOSP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gospel Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gospel Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2DC1131F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Twofold Mission Of Piety and Pop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers Critic's Notebook on gospel music performances in Brooklyn; photos; list (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At 9 p.m. on a recent Monday, cars were double-parked along Rogers Avenue in the Flatbush section of Brooklyn. No action disturbed the street; the nearest bodega was quiet, and no one loitered on the corner at Martense Street. But behind the doors of the storefront Resurrection Temple of the Lord, a mighty noise ignited, lighted by the spirit of devotion.</p>
        <p>The 65 youthful members of the New York State Haitian Interdenominational Mass Choir stood at the front of the low-ceilinged sanctuary, learning how to breathe. Dickson Guillaume, the group's 31-year-old leader, instructed them through a headset, speaking in English and Creole.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At 9 p.m. on a recent Monday, cars were double-parked along Rogers Avenue in the Flatbush section of Brooklyn. No action disturbed the street; the nearest bodega was quiet, and no one loitered on the corner at Martense Street. But behind the doors of the storefront Resurrection Temple of the Lord, a mighty noise ignited, lighted by the spirit of devotion.</p>
        <p>The 65 youthful members of the New York State Haitian Interdenominational Mass Choir stood at the front of the low-ceilinged sanctuary, learning how to breathe. Dickson Guillaume, the group's 31-year-old leader, instructed them through a headset, speaking in English and Creole.</p>
        <p>''Everybody move, O.K.?'' he said, as the vocal exercises gave way to a chorus of ''God Will Take Good Care of You.'' The singers, faces bright, rocked and beckoned toward friends sitting in the pews. ''I want everybody to step out of themselves!'' Mr. Guillaume shouted, urging on the mounting, beautiful din.</p>
        <p>It was one of those scenes explorers of musical back roads dream of: an authentic experience, devoid of the hype that pollutes mainstream pop. Here was a dedicated minister, a technician at a communications company by day, leading a band of spiritually vivified young people toward musical glory. Yet later, in a telephone interview, Mr. Guillaume revealed that his choir wasn't as unknown as it seemed that night.</p>
        <p>''It's a community choir,'' he said of the group, which he founded 10 years ago. ''We sing on weekends at various churches. We've also sung backup for Brandy, for Boyz II Men and on the Rosie O'Donnell show.'' The choir has also performed in festivals at Lincoln Center and Cornell University.</p>
        <p>It says something about contemporary gospel music's role in American pop that this grassroots ministry in a part of Brooklyn where few nonresidents venture has taken its members to such glamorous stages. Gospel exists in a vital world of its own, giving succor to Christian worshipers whose price of admission is belief. But this highly involving music also attracts secular listeners, who enjoy its spontaneity and recognize it as the foundation of rock 'n' roll.</p>
        <p>Sounds of Praise gospel brunch series, a new program at the Brooklyn Academy of Music, seeks to unite those two experiences of gospel: as worship and as art form. The Haitian Interdenominational Mass Choir is to perform in January as part of the series, which takes place on occasional Sundays in the BAMcafe.</p>
        <p>This season the series also features more established gospel artists, from the Institutional Radio Choir of the Institutional Church of God in Christ, based in Fort Greene, Brooklyn, which first performed at the academy in 1983 as part of the Obie Award-winning ''Gospel at Colonus,'' to Gary Anglin of Christian Life Center in the Brownsville section, a rising star who has worked with the likes of Stevie Wonder and Bebe and Cece Winans. It offers an excellent window onto gospel's evolution.</p>
        <p>''Gospel is widely accepted,'' said the Rev. C. E. Williams Jr., whose Institutional Radio Choir has sung extensively for secular audiences, most famously as part of ''Gospel at Colonus.'' ''It's really what they call 'the now music.' It's a good-feeling music. If things are not just right with you, that kind of music will just lift you to what you ought to be feeling.''</p>
        <p>The form of this inspiration depends on the setting. A recent evening rehearsal at the choir's Adelphi Street storefront was a family reunion and a prayer meeting as well as a vocal training session; it exemplified how gospel serves its own. The group whipped through its program with aplomb, slipping wholesome jokes and pertinent prayers in between the stunning solos.</p>
        <p>Shari Turner, a former member visiting from her new home in Atlanta, offered a prayer that was also a gossipy update on her life. When the mighty-voiced Janet Napper led the night's final circle of song, her thanks and supplications were particular to this group, who generated the fire of her praise.</p>
        <p>Most pop fans don't experience gospel this way. They witness it as an  element adding authenticity to a star turn. The average fan of Mary J. Blige, the queen of hip-hop soul, might hear the church in her voice but wouldn't venture to a service to discover the roots of her style. Gospel may be embraced in the abstract, but its full expression remains hidden to most Americans.</p>
        <p>A Borough of Churches</p>
        <p>This parallel existence is particularly felt in Brooklyn, the borough of 13,000 churches. Arts lovers may flee to Lincoln Center for cultural edification on Saturday night, unaware that they can find equal reward at Christian Life Center in Brownsville on Sunday morning.</p>
        <p>Observing this divide, Karen Brooks Hopkins, the president of the Brooklyn Academy of Music, and Joseph V. Melillo, its executive producer, saw a chance to use gospel to further their goal of making their multifaceted space the main destination for Brooklyn audiences.</p>
        <p>''We knew there was great gospel music in Brooklyn, and that if we could bring it in, it would not only make this music more available to everyone, but it would also be great for the music,'' Ms. Hopkins said. ''We wanted to create a live experience where the music would have the absolute highest-quality presentation available. It would bring in people who are more comfortable here than in church. And it attracts those people who are more comfortable in church, whom we want coming here.''</p>
        <p>A Musical Bear Hug</p>
        <p>Gospel's straightforwardness makes it hard to resist; it's like a musical bear hug. The academy's staff knew that most people would  appreciate the warmth but worked hard to prevent any misunderstanding on either side of the exchange.</p>
        <p>The Sounds of Praise series, which began on Sept. 24 and runs on intermittent Sundays at 2 p.m., is emerging as a model of the integration of secular and sacred arts. Besides attracting a new audience that may then explore the academy's movie theaters, cafe music and mainstage performances, it allows artists otherwise pushed to the pop background to share their art fully.</p>
        <p>The series was organized by Limor Tomer, curator for BAMcafe, and Syndi Graham, who is active in Brooklyn's world of gospel music. It  was carefully planned to support the complicated goal of presenting Christian music in a nondenominational space. ''Limor and Syndi went to church all summer,'' Ms. Hopkins said. ''They learned about the best format, the best presentation style. They met with pastors, people who run gospel associations. They curated this series, learning about the best presentation concept to achieve our community goals.''</p>
        <p>The academy also marketed the brunches to local churchgoers. The series' sponsor, Stern's, the department store, has a branch in the nearby Atlantic Mall, popular with residents of Fort Greene and Prospect Heights. Dr. Paul Smith, an academy board member and pastor of the First Presbyterian Church in Brooklyn Heights, kept local ministers informed about the series. Gospel radio personalities were enlisted as hosts for the brunches, and some tickets were distributed to the churches involved in the programs.</p>
        <p>This was a community effort, down to the choice of fried chicken on the brunch menu created by Tentation, the academy's caterers. So far, the care has paid off. The mood at the brunches has been joyful and conflict-free, uniting a mixed audience with artists who uniformly see this series as a way to spread the Word.</p>
        <p>''It gave us a chance to present ourselves to our community,'' said Mr. Williams, whose choir performed on Oct. 8. ''That Sunday evening we had a 6 o'clock service, and people were pouring in here. So it must have registered very positively! I felt very justified, I guess is the word. It kind of lent an acceptance or a favor to what we're doing.''</p>
        <p>Highlighting artistry that flourishes right in the academy's back yard, the series explores the identity of contemporary gospel as both show business and prayer. The series opened with the foot-stomping classic songs of the Rev. Timothy Wright, whose graceful approach to preaching, touched with humor, established a precedent of easy good will. At that first show, Jaron Lanier, the virtual reality pioneer, was seen receiving a blessing. The composer Philip Glass visited for the Institutional Radio Choir's show two weeks later. These avant-garde stars are part of the academy's usual audience, but for the brunches they were sharing long tables with local lay ministers and deaconesses.</p>
        <p>The scheduled performers expressed no worries about reaching skeptics in the crowd. ''I have music that relates to all types of crowds,'' said Mr. Anglin, who will present his highly polished version of praise with an ensemble from the Christian Life Center on Nov. 12. ''To me, it's ministry, whether it's a secular place or a church setting. People still want to hear what you have to say in song. If it's positive, then it can reach someone. I know there will be all types of people there. My purpose is to do what I do best.''</p>
        <p>Exploring Gospel Fusion</p>
        <p>That Mr. Anglin and his peers can so readily step into the academy reflects changes within musical ministry. A trip to Christian Life Center, where Mr. Anglin, a suave baritone,  sings every weekend to prepare the faithful for the words of the Rev. Dr. A. Bernard Sr., shows how modern congregations have learned from the larger world.</p>
        <p>Closed-circuit television allowed those sitting in the back (and in the annex, since this church's membership of more than 3,000 has outgrown its current building) to see every emotion on their leaders' faces. As Dr. Bernard offered his self-help-influenced sermon, churchgoers dutifully took notes. After Mr. Anglin sang a smooth ballad, the cheers seemed directed equally at Jesus and at the loveman doing his will.</p>
        <p>''I listen to Luther Vandross, Brian McKnight,'' Mr. Anglin said when asked about his secular influences. ''I listen to how they deliver a song and use it in my ministry, but I use it my way. If you're brought up learning things positive, it's O.K. to listen to secular music because a lot of secular music is positive.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Anglin and the groups he leads at the Christian Life Center (including the hip-hop-based Logos) represent the most contemporary aspect of gospel fusion. Every choir in the academy's series works the equation in a different way. Like the Haitian Interdenominational Mass Choir, the Direct Messengers, who will appear on Dec. 17, add Caribbean rhythms and vocal techniques. Thrashing Wonders, the 36-year-old a cappella group that raised the roof last Sunday, keep gospel's link to doo-wop and classic soul alive. Voices of Citadel, the choir belonging to the Citadel of Praise church, led by the versatile choirmaster James Hall and the young minister Kevin Bond, also uses the spark of soul to enliven its sound.</p>
        <p>Song as Worship</p>
        <p>A recent meeting in the Bedford-Stuyvesant basement where Citadel gathers revealed another aspect of gospel's wide appeal. This congregation has existed only three years, since Dr. Bond left Institutional to form it. (Brooklyn's gospel scene sometimes seems to be one tight family. Mr. Guillaume, the Haitian Interdenominational Mass Choir's leader, received a similar education in the Worship and Praise choir, led by Citadel's Mr. Hall.) Some of Citadel's choir members are serious amateurs. Part of the thrill their music offers comes from watching people discover the beauty of their own voices.</p>
        <p>Halfway through the practice session, Nedra Natal performed a solo. This young woman began tentatively, flubbing a note, her eyes downcast. Her choir mates shouted encouragement; one took her hand. She picked up the tempo, gained strength. ''I've got to hold on!'' she wailed. The choir erupted into applause, led by the few small children scampering around the room.</p>
        <p>This was the essence of gospel: one woman supported to go beyond what she thought was her limit. ''It gives them this thing that they're singing,'' Mr. Hall said later. ''All these years they knew they couldn't sing, but they're getting up with this choir and they know it sounds good. By being with those who sing, they learn. And then it's spirit-filling. It's a form of worship, and it gets really  . . . we cry, and we get happy and we worship God.''</p>
        <p>Sounds of Praise at the Brooklyn Academy of Music offers that experience in a new setting, with the worship part, if not entirely optional, defined openly.</p>
        <p>''So much of the music that we put on all of our stages has to do with spiritual themes,'' Ms. Hopkins noted, citing recent examples like Kurt Weill's ''Eternal Road,'' an opera about Jewish history, and Mr. Glass's Buddhist-inflected symphonies. ''We are comfortable presenting all kinds of music with all kinds of messages. We have to be free to let the music be.''</p>
        <p>Spreading the Word</p>
        <p>The events and groups in the article on gospel music. Unless noted, admission is free; churches accept donations.</p>
        <p>SOUNDS OF PRAISE, BAMcafe, Brooklyn Academy of Music, 30 Lafayette Avenue, at Ashland Place, Fort Greene. This gospel brunch series generally runs alternate Sundays at 2 p.m. through June. Remaining performances this year will feature Gary Anglin (Nov. 12); Voices of Citadel with James Hall (Nov. 26); the Direct Messengers (Dec. 17). Admission, $20; $15 for children 6 to 12 years old; free for children 5 and younger. Reservations: (718) 636-4139.</p>
        <p>''GOSPEL SATURDAYS,'' Stern's, third-floor atrium, Atlantic Center Mall, 625 Atlantic Avenue, at Flatbush Avenue, Fort Greene, Brooklyn. Tomorrow at 2:30 p.m., the choir from the Bedford Central Presbyterian Church. Nov. 4, the Concord Baptist Church of Christ choir. Information: (212) 946-4655.</p>
        <p>INSTITUTIONAL RADIO CHOIR, Institutional Church of God in Christ, 170 Adelphi Street, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718) 625-9175. The choir appears at the church every Sunday at noon. It will also perform at the New York Society for Ethical Culture, 2 West 64th Street, Manhattan, on Nov. 11 at 7 p.m. Tickets; $22. Information: Rainbow Music, (212) 864-5262.</p>
        <p>VOICES OF CITADEL, Citadel of Praise and Worship, 1313 Bedford Avenue, at Atlantic Avenue, Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, (718) 622-5931. The choir can be heard Sunday mornings at 11. It will also appear this Sunday at 7 p.m. at the Full Gospel Assembly, 131 Sullivan Place, between Bedford and Rogers Avenues, Crown Heights, and on Nov. 26 as part of the Sounds of Praise gospel brunch at the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
        <p>GARY ANGLIN, Christian Life Center, 1400 Linden Boulevard, between Rockaway Parkway and Rockaway Avenue, Brownsville, Brooklyn, (718) 272-0303, Extension 1400. He appears most Sundays at 9 and 11 a.m. He will also appear on Nov. 12 at 2 p.m. at the Sounds of Praise gospel brunch at the Brooklyn Academy of Music.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK STATE HAITIAN INTERDENOMINATIONAL MASS CHOIR. The choir will perform Nov. 18 at 7 p.m. at the Baptist Temple, 360 Schermerhorn Street, downtown Brooklyn. Tickets: $30 in advance, $35 at the door. Information: (212) 539-8886 or Betty's Gospel Den, (718) 398-7205.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
