<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="27FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFDC1E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Internal Tensions Divide Ivory Coast Protesters  People who toppled Gen. Robert Guei in an uprising turned furiously against one another, and the deadly clashes quickly took on religious and ethnic overtones and spread to smaller cities. The violence followed disputed elections in which Laurent Gbagbo, who is backed by security forces, was declared the victor.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Internal Tensions Divide Ivory Coast Protesters  People who toppled Gen. Robert Guei in an uprising turned furiously against one another, and the deadly clashes quickly took on religious and ethnic overtones and spread to smaller cities. The violence followed disputed elections in which Laurent Gbagbo, who is backed by security forces, was declared the victor.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Note From Sub's Doomed Crew  Russian divers recovered the remains of Lt. Capt. Dimitri Kolesnikov, the commander of the turbine room on the sunken Russian submarine Kursk, and found a note stuffed in his pocket that revealed that 23 of the Kursk's 118 crewmen survived the sinking, at least for a while.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bomber Dies in Gaza Blast  A Palestinian suicide bomber headed toward an Israeli Army outpost in the Gaza Strip but killed only himself as a backpack filled with explosives apparently detonated prematurely. The attempted attack raised anxiety in Israel that the violence was shifting to a new phase of terrorism.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Pope's Wartime Role Studied  Jewish and Catholic scholars, dissatisfied with published Vatican documents on Pope Pius XII's actions in World War II, asked for access to closed Vatican archives. In a preliminary report, the panel said published documents did not ''put to rest significant questions about the role of the Vatican during the Holocaust.''</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Britons Misled on 'Mad Cow'  A three-year inquiry found that British officials consistently misled the public over 10 years by playing down the possibility that mad-cow disease could be transmitted to humans. So far, 77 Britons have died.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Cuban Leader in Venezuela  Fidel Castro began his first official visit to Venezuela in four decades. He and President Hugo Chavez, an ally and friend, are expected to sign an agreement to let Cuba import oil from Venezuela at a discount.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Peru Spy Chief on the Run  President Alberto K. Fujimori intensified the manhunt for the former spy chief Vladimiro Montesinos.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A18-29</p>
        <p>Budget Deals Are Seen As Devouring the Surplus  Analysts from both major political parties say that by the time Congress and the Clinton administration finish wrangling over this year's federal budget, more than 40 percent of the surplus that the two presidential candidates are counting on for their proposals may have been spent.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Bush Raises Character Issue  Gov. George W. Bush, campaigning in western Pennsylvania, questioned the integrity, courage and moral character of Vice President Al Gore and called the presidential race a matter of values.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Veiled Appeal to Nader Bloc  Vice President Al Gore, campaigning in Madison, Wis., a college town where Ralph Nader enjoys strong support, promoted his ''progressive values'' to more than 30,000 people, speaking ardently to issues that have moved Nader supporters but uttering Mr. Nader's name only once.</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>The Field of Battle Is Widening  The number of states that are tossups in the presidential race is growing, with 18 now in play, a departure from the norm at this stage of a campaign, when less than a dozen are typically left to fight over.</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Moving to Limit Steel Imports  The Clinton administration, reacting to pre-election pressure from steel companies, unions and members of Congress, promised to take steps toward new limits on steel imports.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>House Acts on Taxes and Budget  The House, voting 237 to 134, approved a $37.7 billion spending measure and a package of tax cuts and reimbursements to hospitals, nursing homes and H.M.O.'s, despite a veto threat from President Clinton.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Disbarment Trial Will Wait  An Arkansas court official said the judge handling President Clinton's disbarment proceeding would not schedule the trial for this year.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Hidden Car Loan Fees Assailed  The practice of car dealers' adding points to finance charges without notifying car buyers is coming under legal attack in at least five states -- California, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Tennessee and Texas -- an investigation by The New York Times and ABC News has found.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-13</p>
        <p>New Jersey Senate Hopeful Gets 11th-Hour G.O.P. Aid  Republican officials in Washington, buoyed by polls suggesting that Representative Bob Franks is now within striking distance of Jon S. Corzine in their Senate race, sent $600,000 to help him pay for television ads.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Lazio Assails Foreign Policy  Representative Rick A. Lazio said Clinton administration weakness and indecision had undermined the United States' credibility and contributed to turmoil in China, Russia and the Middle East. But Mr. Lazio avoided any mention of his Senate rival, Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>A Nominee for Lincoln Center  A search committee will recommend that the performing arts center choose as its next president Gordon J. Davis, 59, the chairman of Jazz at Lincoln Center. Mr. Davis would lead the organization's $1.5 billion reconstruction of the deteriorating 1960's West Side arts campus.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Trouble in Silicon Alley  Dot-coms in New York City have laid off about 3,000 people in recent months, a couple of companies have gone bankrupt and stocks have plunged. The turmoil has been a comedown for an industry that once held itself up as the city's hottest and coolest sector.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>NASA's New Plans  The space agency announced a revised program for Mars exploration that calls for six flights in the next seven years.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-34; E35-52</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Med School Applications Drop  The number of students applying to medical schools shrunk by 25 percent in the last four years. Experts cite disenchantment with managed health care and more lucrative opportunities in other fields.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-16  Food Makers to Merge  Kellogg, the maker of Eggo waffles and Rice Krispies cereal, said it would acquire Keebler Foods for $3.86 billion in cash.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Airlines Consider New Alliance  British Airways is in talks with Delta Air Lines and Air France about joining their international alliance, a move that would be expected to break up British Air's troubled partnership with American Airlines.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Fund Manager Closing His Shop  Jeffrey N. Vinik said he would shut down his $4.2 billion Boston fund, one of the nation's largest hedge funds, and return investors' money by year's end. Mr. Vinik, 41, said he wanted to spend more time with his family. As of Oct. 20, his fund was up 45.6 percent after fees this year.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-12</p>
        <p>Yanks Win Subway Series  The Yankees won their third straight World Series by beating the Mets,  4-2, at Shea Stadium in Game 5.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: There goes the surplus; a pernicious secrecy bill; for Congress from New York.  Columns: Gail Collins, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E49  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E34  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>B13</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
