<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Race That Isn't What Was Expected</title>
    <meta content="27FIRS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/nyregion/27FIRS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seltzer, Regina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grucci, Felix J Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DB1E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Race That Isn't What Was Expected</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <dateline>YAPHANK, N.Y., Oct. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Review of race for House in First Congressional District, Suffolk, between Regina Seltzer, Democrat, and Felix J Grucci Jr, Republican town supervisor of Brookhaven; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This was going to be one of the war zones in the battle for control of Congress, where the Republican-turned-Democrat was expected to battle a powerful local Republican. But that was before the Sept. 12 Democratic primary, when a pro-bono environmental lawyer who works out of her own kitchen unseated the incumbent, Michael P. Forbes, who switched parties last year.</p>
        <p>Now the contest between Regina Seltzer, the Democrat who beat Mr. Forbes by 35 votes, and Felix J. Grucci Jr., Brookhaven town supervisor, is attracting more yawns than buzz outside the First Congressional District on eastern Long Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This was going to be one of the war zones in the battle for control of Congress, where the Republican-turned-Democrat was expected to battle a powerful local Republican. But that was before the Sept. 12 Democratic primary, when a pro-bono environmental lawyer who works out of her own kitchen unseated the incumbent, Michael P. Forbes, who switched parties last year.</p>
        <p>Now the contest between Regina Seltzer, the Democrat who beat Mr. Forbes by 35 votes, and Felix J. Grucci Jr., Brookhaven town supervisor, is attracting more yawns than buzz outside the First Congressional District on eastern Long Island.</p>
        <p>So when about 30 people turned out todayfor Ms. Seltzer's political gathering outside Mr. Grucci's fireworks plant here, it looked more like a glimmer of what might have been than a moment in the hotly contested race that everyone had expected.</p>
        <p>''People had been talking about it'' since Mr. Forbes left the Republican Party in July 1999, said Amy Walter, Congressional campaign editor for the Cook Political Report, a nonpartisan Washington newsletter analyzing elections. Now, she said, it is ''the race that dare not speak its name, over at Democratic headquarters.''</p>
        <p>Jim Wilkinson, communications director for the National Republican Congressional Committee, put it even more bluntly: ''The race is over. Felix Grucci is going to be a great congressman. When Michael Forbes lost, the Democrats were left with an underfunded, unknown, fifth-tier candidate.''</p>
        <p>News of her political demise has not reached Ms. Seltzer and her supporters. Some of them were at the news conference organized by her campaign to celebrate her concern for the environment, to point out the pollution investigation of her opponent's factory being conducted by the Suffolk County Health Services Department, and to receive the Long Island Sierra Club's endorsement.</p>
        <p>Ms. Seltzer said in an interview that she had done the impossible before, referring to her primary victory, and said no one should think the race is over.</p>
        <p>''They're in for a big surprise when I get to Congress,'' said Ms. Seltzer, who was a Brookhaven town councilwoman from 1975 to 1979.  ''They think he makes fireworks,'' she added, implying that her environmental plans, should she get to Congress, would be more impressive. ''I've had it with politics as usual.''</p>
        <p>In Washington, Mr. Forbes disclosed today that he had decided to give $250,000 from his campaign fund to the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee. Mr. Forbes has endorsed Ms. Seltzer but there is no indication that the money will go to her race.</p>
        <p>''We are confident they will put it to good use,'' said Mr. Forbes's chief of staff, David Williams. ''He is thoroughly committed to helping ensure that the Democrats are in the majority in the next session of Congress, and he is confident they will be.''</p>
        <p>At her news conference, Ms. Seltzer, 71, said she had raised $200,000 for the campaign, mostly in $5 and $10 payments. Mr. Grucci, 47, has raised $1.3 million, said Jesse Garcia, his communications director.</p>
        <p>''She's never going to match Felix's money,'' said Richard H. Schaffer, chairman of the Suffolk County Democratic Committee. ''But with all the enthusiasm for a refreshing campaign, I think she can pull off a surprise upset.''</p>
        <p>Others are not so sure.</p>
        <p>''We had the race tilting Republican even when Forbes was in the race,'' said Stuart Rothenberg, editor of the Rothenberg Political Report in Washington, who added that the Seltzer-Grucci race looked like one of the ''Republican slam-dunk takeovers.'' (The Long Island district includes Brookhaven, parts of Smithtown and all of the five East End towns.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Walter said that Ms. Seltzer faced many problems, saying she started ''at the end of September with no money, no name ID, no base, and no political team but for her bike and some pamphlets.'' The Democrats had started out thinking the seat was winnable, but by mid to late September, she said, the party found itself with limited funds and a need to keep ''as many seats in play as possible.'' She said they must have wondered, ''Is this really a great place to spend another couple million dollars?''</p>
        <p>Still, Democratic politicians are not yet ready to surrender Mr. Forbes's seat.</p>
        <p>''The Republican nominee is currently under investigation for polluting Long Island groundwater, and has a history of corruption and mismanagement in his tenure as Brookhaven supervisor,'' said John Del Cecato, spokesman for the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee. ''Reggie Seltzer has proven to be a tireless campaigner, and she'll provide a stark contrast with the anti-environmental record that Felix Grucci brings to the campaign.''</p>
        <p>Local politics in Brookhaven have been touched by accusations of corruption for five decades, and the former county and town Republican Party leader and Mr. Grucci's political mentor, John Powell, was convicted of extortion last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grucci's spokesman, Mr. Garcia, dismissed Mr. Del Cecato's criticism. ''It shows the Democratic Congressional Committee is out of touch, their candidate is not connecting, and that's why the Democrats will be rejected this November,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia pointed with pride to Mr. Grucci's environmental record as town supervisor. ''He authored, lobbied and successfully saw passed the first environmental bond act, for $10 million, in the history of the town government,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But on the side of the road in Yaphank, the race was still on after the news conference was over. It had been the kind of friendly gathering when even someone's Golden Retriever wore a Seltzer sandwich board for a bit. ''Now let's get back to stuffing envelopes,'' said Carlo Oliveri of Wading River, one of Ms. Seltzer's volunteers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
