<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Undecided Voters Remain Skeptical On Soft Money Pact in Senate Race</title>
    <meta content="27UNDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/politics/27UNDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Undecided: The Soft Money Issue" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4DC1E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Undecided Voters Remain Skeptical On Soft Money Pact in Senate Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some undecided voters say that soft-money deal between candidates for United States Senate in New York has backfired, drawing more attention to fund-raising activities of Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A Lazio than if they had quietly raised and spent millions and not made an issue of it; photos (Ninth article in series Undecided: The Soft Money Issue)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The soft-money deal between the candidates for the United States Senate in New York has backfired, some undecided voters say, drawing more attention to the fund-raising activities of Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio than if they had quietly raised and spent millions and not made an issue of it.</p>
        <p>''They're both saying, 'I have more integrity; I want to stop this,' '' said Bob Harrison, a high school social studies teacher in Amsterdam, N.Y. ''But neither of them are following through.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The soft-money deal between the candidates for the United States Senate in New York has backfired, some undecided voters say, drawing more attention to the fund-raising activities of Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio than if they had quietly raised and spent millions and not made an issue of it.</p>
        <p>''They're both saying, 'I have more integrity; I want to stop this,' '' said Bob Harrison, a high school social studies teacher in Amsterdam, N.Y. ''But neither of them are following through.''</p>
        <p>Tom Smith, who works at a Wal-Mart near Saugerties, pointed to the same disconnect. ''Publicly, they say soft money is no good,'' Mr. Smith fumed. ''But privately they say, 'Give me all you've got.' ''</p>
        <p>Doug Taggart, vice president of a Wall Street financial services concern, said he was offended enough to consider not voting. The soft-money pledge was political theater, Mr. Taggart said, pointing to subsequent disclosures: Mrs. Clinton's use of a White House invitation list for campaign solicitations; Mr. Lazio's spending of money from the Republican National Committee for television commercials; and both candidates' attendance at fund-raisers to harvest soft money for their allies.</p>
        <p>The latest fuss, concerning $50,000 from a Muslim group that Mrs. Clinton says she will return, might have passed without remark but for the context. ''On the surface, it's not that big a deal,'' Mr. Taggart said. ''But my question is, if it wasn't publicized, would she have given the money back? One gets cynical when there's such a long track record of egregious behavior.''</p>
        <p>These three undecided voters, part of a panel whose members have been sharing their thoughts on the Senate race with The New York Times for 10 months, have more in common than their perception that both Mrs. Clinton and Mr. Lazio have behaved hypocritically.</p>
        <p>All of them understand, in broad strokes, that soft money is less regulated and more easily abused than other contributions, even if they are shaky on the technicalities of the candidates' pledge. All know that money can decide an election, leaving officeholders beholden to big donors.</p>
        <p>''Would there be AK-47's out in the streets if the National Rifle Association wasn't cozy with Congress?'' Mr. Taggart asked. ''Would health care plans, good or bad, have passed if it weren't for the insurance lobby and the H.M.O.'s? You can go down the list. This is common-sense stuff.''</p>
        <p>All see the pledge proposed by Mr. Lazio -- to ban use of soft money, largely unregulated donations, for radio and television ads -- as a way of putting Mrs. Clinton at a financial disadvantage while staking out the moral high ground. ''It was just a way to limit her war chest,'' Mr. Harrison said. ''She has more to lose, so he's not the wholesome boy he wants us to think he is.''</p>
        <p>All say that the candidates struck such a narrow bargain that they left room for misconduct. They cite Mrs. Clinton's use of a White House invitation list, which she said was an honest mix-up. ''Should we call it a brain cramp?'' Mr. Smith asked. ''A senior moment? It wasn't a legitimate oops, that's for sure. She was seeing what she could get away with.''</p>
        <p>And all think the candidates have been silent on the subject of campaign-finance overhaul legislation, a noteworthy misperception among otherwise well-informed voters. Mr. Lazio has voted twice for such a bill in Congress, and Mrs. Clinton has endorsed it.</p>
        <p>''I haven't heard them say anything about it,'' said Mr. Taggart, the most diligent newspaper reader in the group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harrison, a registered Republican; Mr. Smith, a registered Democrat; and Mr. Taggart, an independent, are among a group of undecided voters culled from early New York Times/CBS News polls. The original panel of 11 has been winnowed to these 3, who say their minds are still not made up with Election Day near.</p>
        <p>Two of the voters dropped out in May, unhappy with how the newspaper portrayed them. Tom Beck, a Long Island guidance counselor, cast his lot with Mr. Lazio, a familiar congressman from a neighboring district, as soon as Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani withdrew as the Republican candidate. Two lifelong Democrats, Charlene Clinton, a mother from Buffalo on public assistance, and Dave Temkin, a telecommunications expert from Queens, settled on Mrs. Clinton in mid-September.</p>
        <p>The latest to make up their minds, barring dramatic new circumstances, are Cathy Harrison, a nurse; Karl Schwartz, a computer consultant from Staten Island; and Barbara Smith, who inserts circulars in a weekly newspaper and also works in a day care center.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Harrison, a lifelong Republican and the wife of Bob Harrison, has swung back and forth, leaning toward Mrs. Clinton after the candidates' first debate because of her assured presentation on upstate economic issues. But she has now landed in more familiar partisan terrain, choosing Mr. Lazio because of the first lady's ''background, the corruption and everything with her husband.'' In a nutshell, Mrs. Harrison said, ''I'd rather know I voted for a good person.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwartz, too, has chosen Mr. Lazio because he sees this as a one-issue campaign. Mr. Schwartz's wife, Joanne, has non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, and he has been preoccupied with cancer. Mr. Lazio has been a sponsor of legislation to help poor women with breast and cervical cancer and, even more important to Mr. Schwartz, the congressman won an award from the Lymphoma Research Foundation of America.</p>
        <p>Despite her customary loyalty to the Republican Party, Mrs. Smith, the wife of Tom Smith, has been inching toward Mrs. Clinton since the beginning of the campaign. The first lady's compassion for the less fortunate impresses her, Mrs. Smith said. She said she also admired Mrs. Clinton's demeanor during her very public marital difficulties, and how she handled the subject when it was raised in debates.</p>
        <p>Neither Mrs. Harrison nor Mrs. Smith knows or cares much about campaign finance. But the rest of the panel defies the conventional wisdom that voters are not interested, capable of understanding or swayed by how candidates raise and spend money.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwartz said that ''campaign finance reform is the most important mechanistic change we can make to rescue the political future of America.'' And Mr. Taggart said that nothing is more important than campaign finance reform when electing someone to the Senate, which he calls ''the special-interest, favor-cutting branch of government.''</p>
        <p>There is a risk for candidates when voters know a lot, but not everything, about campaign finance activity. Sometimes, accustomed to misconduct, they will mistakenly assume a partisan fund-raising group is affiliated with the candidate who shares its views.</p>
        <p>This is the case with Mr. Harrison, who has received strident fund-raising literature from the Emergency Committee to Stop Hillary Rodham Clinton, also known as the Conservative Leadership Political Action Committee. ''Wherever Hillary goes, corruption, crime and cover-up follow,'' the  mailing said, while seeking a contribution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harrison was unaware that the Lazio campaign had disavowed the committee. So the letter, copies of which were sent both to him and his wife, made him angry. He noted the return address. ''Just a post office box,'' he said. ''Who are these guys? They're sure taking away from the image of Lazio as an honest candidate.''</p>
        <p>Undecided  The Soft Money Issue</p>
        <p>This is the ninth article in a series following a group of New York State voters as they make up their minds on which candidate to support for the United States Senate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
