<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Sure Takes More Than a Dollar and a Dream</title>
    <meta content="27LUCK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/arts/27LUCK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ephron, Nora</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Travolta, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kudrow, Lisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lucky Numbers (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE6DC1131F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Sure Takes More Than a Dollar and a Dream</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews movie Lucky Numbers, directed by Nora Ephron; John Travolta and Lisa Kudrow star; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The blazing chartreuse early-1970's Buick Riviera that Russ Richards (John Travolta) drives in ''Lucky Numbers'' may be fashionable now, but it's a full-bore eyesore in Harrisburg, Pa., in 1988, when this picture takes place. Russ, a star weatherman on local television, is even more profligate with his money than he is with his smile. His livelihood is probably causing him more pain than pleasure, since he is reporting on the unseasonably warm weather that is causing the slow death of his sideline snowmobile business. He can see a family loading a swimming pool onto the roof of its station wagon through the window of the showroom where his Yamahas sit.</p>
        <p>''Lucky Numbers'' is a weak-witted comedy on the loser culture for which its writer, Adam Resnick, has displayed a taste in the last few years, starting with his work on the cult classic television series ''Get a Life,'' which starred Chris Elliott as a surly, arrogant, overage paper boy who still lived with his parents. Mr. Resnick also wrote and directed one of the weirdest movies of the last decade, ''Cabin Boy,'' a postmodern freakout starring Mr. Elliott as a privileged man-boy in a Richie Rich outfit and wig and featuring a terrifically vivid David Letterman as a mean-spirited sailor who must have been conceived as the evil twin of the guy on the Old Spice commercials. (That film probably still causes fights between its adherents and opponents, the nine people who actually caught it in theaters.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The blazing chartreuse early-1970's Buick Riviera that Russ Richards (John Travolta) drives in ''Lucky Numbers'' may be fashionable now, but it's a full-bore eyesore in Harrisburg, Pa., in 1988, when this picture takes place. Russ, a star weatherman on local television, is even more profligate with his money than he is with his smile. His livelihood is probably causing him more pain than pleasure, since he is reporting on the unseasonably warm weather that is causing the slow death of his sideline snowmobile business. He can see a family loading a swimming pool onto the roof of its station wagon through the window of the showroom where his Yamahas sit.</p>
        <p>''Lucky Numbers'' is a weak-witted comedy on the loser culture for which its writer, Adam Resnick, has displayed a taste in the last few years, starting with his work on the cult classic television series ''Get a Life,'' which starred Chris Elliott as a surly, arrogant, overage paper boy who still lived with his parents. Mr. Resnick also wrote and directed one of the weirdest movies of the last decade, ''Cabin Boy,'' a postmodern freakout starring Mr. Elliott as a privileged man-boy in a Richie Rich outfit and wig and featuring a terrifically vivid David Letterman as a mean-spirited sailor who must have been conceived as the evil twin of the guy on the Old Spice commercials. (That film probably still causes fights between its adherents and opponents, the nine people who actually caught it in theaters.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Resnick relishes the lowlifes he creates, his own Bizarro Universe version of a Coen brothers movie. The Harrisburg of ''Lucky Numbers'' is like the small town where ''Groundhog Day'' was set, and the film is fascinated with small-time crooks who can't stay out of their own way, like the punks in most of the Coens' films.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Resnick's distinctiveness, a tall-tale heartiness that can also be a form of exclusion, has been replaced by the patronizing tone of the film's director, Nora Ephron. This is her ''Fargo,'' and Harrisburg is a tacky trash outpost where the criminals are so undertalented that they probably aspire to incompetence.</p>
        <p>In the end, Ms. Ephron's sourness of tone is different from Mr. Resnick's; it feels like a novel adventure in slumming. She seems to condescend to the characters, peering at them with an arched eyebrow in scenes like the one in which Russ, with his Julius Caesar haircut and bright blue jacket that screams 80's, pulls into his reserved parking spot at ''Harrisburg's trendiest bistro'' --  Denny's -- and takes up space in a voluminous booth. Or when the oafish Walter (Michael Moore), who's even more small-time than anyone in Harrisburg, waddles off a bus while ''Big Spender'' blares on the soundtrack.</p>
        <p>Russ is desperate for cash, and Gig (Tim Roth), the gentleman hood who runs a strip joint where the dancers never quite get around to taking off their clothes, makes a suggestion that comes out of his worldview. ''Robbery isn't like brain surgery,'' he muses. ''It's like a visit to the podiatrist.'' The idea is for Russ to stage a burglary of his snowmobile business, a plan that's horribly botched by Dale (Michael Rapaport), a violent thug -- he's called Dale the Thug -- who drives a Ford Maverick that gives off so much exhaust that it seems to have a wood-burning engine.</p>
        <p>After that scheme falls apart, Russ persuades his girlfriend, Crystal (Lisa Kudrow), host of the mini-show in which the state lottery numbers are selected, to help him rig the lottery. The scheme picks up obstacles faster than gum on the sole of a shoe collects pebbles, and it doesn't help that the plan becomes the worst-kept secret since Three Mile Island (which can be seen in the montage of Russ's news program). The station manager, Dick (Ed O'Neill), finds out and tries to blackmail Russ and Crystal, a plan that leads to its own set of complications.</p>
        <p>''Lucky Numbers,'' loosely based on an early 80's Pennsylvania lottery scandal (the same source for the Michael Keaton vehicle ''The Squeeze''), extorts a few laughs, primarily with Ms. Kudrow's anomalous timing. Her Crystal has a peevish, greedy streak and blurts out whatever angry remark is rattling around in her almost empty head. When she sits in bed preening after sex, she's basking in her own afterglow; she doesn't need anyone else.</p>
        <p>Whatever one's feelings about the Coens, ''Lucky Numbers'' shows just how hard their type of picture is to pull off, and luck has nothing to do with it.</p>
        <p>''Lucky Numbers'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has strong language, sexuality and violence, including blows dealt by a baseball-bat-wielding thug.</p>
        <p>LUCKY NUMBERS</p>
        <p>Directed by Nora Ephron; written by Adam Resnick; director of photography, John Lindley; edited by Barry Malkin; music by George Fenton; production designer, Dan Davis; produced by Andrew Lazar, Jonathan D. Krane, Sean Daniel and Ms. Ephron; released by Paramount Pictures. Running time: 100 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: John Travolta (Russ Richards), Lisa Kudrow (Crystal), Tim Roth (Gig), Ed O'Neill (Dick), Michael Rapaport (Dale), Daryl Mitchell (Chambers), Michael Moore (Walter), Bill Pullman (Lakewood).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
