<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dearth of Ads Makes Race in Kansas a Snooze</title>
    <meta content="Y27DOD$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/politics/27DODG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FORGOTTEN STATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kansas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EEDC1E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1571" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dearth of Ads Makes Race in Kansas a Snooze</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>DODGE CITY, Kan., Oct. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bush and Gore campaigns and two major parties have surgically sliced up advertising map to rare level, spending more than $100 million thus far to run commercials in only about 20 states in which polls show contest to be close; Kansas is not one of them; Kansas, with 6 electoral votes and strong Republican voting tradition, will almost certainly go for Bush; residents of other states are being inundated with campaign spots, but Kansans have not seen one; lack of campaign on the air makes campaign seem more of abstraction to many in state; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seldom is heard a discouraging word about the presidential candidates in these parts. Then again, not much of anything is said about them at all.</p>
        <p>The airwaves of southwestern Kansas are commercial free at least as far as the Bush and Gore campaigns are concerned. There are no 30-second spots with a grinning Gov. George W. Bush on television here, no soft-focus montages of a glad-handing Vice President Al Gore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seldom is heard a discouraging word about the presidential candidates in these parts. Then again, not much of anything is said about them at all.</p>
        <p>The airwaves of southwestern Kansas are commercial free at least as far as the Bush and Gore campaigns are concerned. There are no 30-second spots with a grinning Gov. George W. Bush on television here, no soft-focus montages of a glad-handing Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Medicare lockboxes? Compassionate conservatism? Prescription drug plans? Local viewers may have some familiarity with these terms, but not because they receive the commercial reminders that are inundating television watchers elsewhere. Absent, too, are the visages of gubernatorial and United States Senate contenders (Kansas has none this year), and the Congressional race is a snooze: the area's Republican House member, Jerry Moran, has only third-party opposition.</p>
        <p>So even as viewers in cities like Grand Rapids, Mich., and Tampa, Fla., find themselves in the eye of a perfect advertising storm, people in places like Dodge City sit in a virtual advertising blackout. A result is that voters here talk as if the election were a faraway event, like the Subway Series. Many have opinions and know who they want to vote for, but they tend to sound more resigned and a lot less engaged than many of their counterparts elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''You wouldn't hardly know that there's a presidential campaign on,'' said Gerald Schmitt, the mayor of Dodge City. ''I think a lot of the people feel a 'what is the use?' type of thing. Nobody asks us what we think. We sit here and observe what's happening, but there's nothing we can do.''</p>
        <p>From here, the campaign seems a bit of a blur. ''Gosh, people don't talk about it much here,'' said Lawrence Daniels, the Democratic chairman of Ford County, which includes Dodge City.</p>
        <p>Through no fault of its own, this is the land that advertisements forgot. In a frontier city that is synonymous with the saloon brawls and gunfights of the Old West -- the town seal, after all, features a pair of six-shooters, and the main thoroughfare is Wyatt Earp Boulevard -- the race for president on the air is anything but a shootout. It is as quiet here, in fact, as the graves on Boot Hill.</p>
        <p>''I can honestly tell you I have not seen a presidential ad, Republican or Democrat,'' said David Rebein, a Dodge City lawyer who is likely to have made a receptive audience for the Republican spots: He is the local party chairman. Mr. Daniels, his Democratic counterpart, said he had  seen a few of the commercials, but only because he was on a business trip to Missouri.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daniels added that he felt so detached from the race that he did not even respond when the Gore campaign offered to send him some yard signs. He says he may even vote for Ralph Nader, the Green nominee.</p>
        <p>With its strong Republican voting tradition and the near certainty that it will go for Mr. Bush, Kansas might as well be in the South Pacific as in the middle of the country, for all the attention paid to it. Not even a distant relation of Mr. Gore or Mr. Bush, residents say, has come to campaign in the cattle-and-grain belt of southwest Kansas.</p>
        <p>But the region is by no means unique. The Bush and Gore campaigns and the two major parties have surgically sliced up the advertising map to a rare level this year, spending well more than $100 million thus far to run commercials in only about 20 states in which the polls show the contest to be close. Kansas is not one of them. Indeed, even though the presidential contest is the closest in decades, nearly half of the nation's top 75 media markets have not broadcast a single presidential commercial. As a result, the nation has been divided into electronic haves and have-nots.</p>
        <p>Consider, for example, New Jersey, which has no network affliates of its own and is served by the largest and fourth-largest media markets in the nation. Southern New Jersey is being deluged with advertising because it is in the media orbit of Philadelphia, in the swing state of Pennsylvania. But northern New Jersey sees virtually no presidential spots, because New York City is in a state considered safe for Mr. Gore. (New Jersey itself, initially thought to be a swing state, seems safely in Mr. Gore's column.)</p>
        <p>Kansas, too, is a state divided. Its eastern counties, which get their local television from Kansas City, Mo., another hot presidential media market, have more in common with advertisement-saturated cities like Detroit and Milwaukee than with parched places like Dodge City.</p>
        <p>''The process effectively takes half the country and says, 'You're just spectators,' '' said Kathleen Hall Jamieson, dean of the Annenberg School for Communication, who has studied what happens to voter interest in the absence of political commercials.</p>
        <p>While some people might view a dearth of paid political announcements as a blessing, Dr. Jamieson and others say commercials are crucial in invigorating local partisans and local news outlets -- and in creating genuine interest in the democratic process.</p>
        <p>Without the spots, a campaign can feel a bit like a movie without the soundtrack. ''They're mobilizers, motivators, stimulators,'' said Ken Goldstein, a political science professor at the University of Wisconsin who studies political advertising. ''We decry the ads, we whine about the attack advertising, but study after study shows that people exposed to it hold more knowledgeable opinions. It stimulates the electorate.''</p>
        <p>Many people in Dodge City, a town of about 25,000 whose largest industry is meat packing, say they would not mind if the election was a bit more stimulating. But at this peak moment of this tight presidential campaign, the local channels, based in Wichita, 150 miles to the east, are chockablock with spots for the Galichia Medical Group and Skaggs Motors and one station's Super Doppler 12 weather radar. The only race of any intensity on television is a State Senate contest between the Republican incumbent Tim Huelskamp and his Democratic opponent, Steve Irsik.</p>
        <p>''That's where the heat is,'' said Mike Schwanke, a reporter here for KWCH, the CBS affiliate in Wichita.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwanke has seen those candidates' spots, but virtually none for the next occupant of the White House.</p>
        <p>''The only time we'll see a commercial,'' he explained, ''is when the news picks up one that someone somewhere has griped about.''</p>
        <p>It is not, of course, only through commercials that people learn about a campaign, and it is not necessarily lavish attention that propels voters to the polls in large numbers. Diana Carlin, professor of communication studies at the University of Kansas, said that western Kansans historically turned out for elections in greater proportions than the nation as a whole, even though the state was often written off early in a campaign.</p>
        <p>Still, the lack of a campaign on the air sends signals in a place like Dodge City, where many residents do get the message that their votes do not count quite as much as those in swing states. That inevitably makes a campaign seem more of an abstraction, and the process appears to have less vitality.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't seem to be focused on us,'' Virgil Nason, a retired school assistant principal, said as he finished his coffee at a McDonald's across the street from Dodge City's chief tourist attraction, the Boot Hill museum. ''I don't think it's that people here don't care. But Kansas is not a key state. It's not going to make the difference in terms of the electoral vote.''</p>
        <p>Kansas has just six electoral votes.</p>
        <p>Steve and Lavonda Cobb, who grow grain on 2,500 acres 50 miles southeast of Dodge City, see the lack of attention going much deeper than commercials. They themselves have mostly tuned out the campaign, they say, because neither candidate seems very interested in issues important to farmers, like reducing trade barriers. ''In general, farm people don't give a darn anymore,'' Mr. Cobb said, ''since they're not considered a part of the process.''</p>
        <p>Local residents like Gladys Reece, retired from the J. C. Penney's here, and Walter Page, a retired plasterer, and his wife, Virginia, who works for a title search company, said that they had gleaned a lot about the presidential candidates from the debates, and that that helped them decide whom to support; Ms. Reece is leaning toward Mr. Gore, while the Pages favor Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>But Jim Geis, who owns the McDonald's, said he lamented the arm's length at which the campaigns hold places like Dodge City.</p>
        <p>Mr. Geis spoke wistfully of a time when politics seemed more tangible and urgent. Gazing over at a group of older men, morning regulars in his establishment, he said, ''About politics, I don't think they think they can touch it anymore.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FORGOTTEN STATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
