<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rivera and Rest of Pen Did Job When Needed</title>
    <meta content="27BULL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/sports/27BULL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Mariano</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6D91E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rivera and Rest of Pen Did Job When Needed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankee closer Mariano Rivera gains his second save of World Series, and a record-setting seventh World Series save (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Mariano Rivera, who etched his name deeper into the World Series record book last night as perhaps the greatest relief pitcher in Series history, the key word was relief. It was relief that poured freely from him as he exhaled, screamed to the sky and raised his arms as Mike Piazza's long fly ball settled into the glove of Bernie Williams for the final out of the Series.</p>
        <p>Rivera, with his second save of the Series, and a record-setting seventh World Series save, wrapped up the Yankees' 4-2 victory, standing on the mound in exhilaration as he had in each of the last two season-ending victories. ''This is my third one on the field,'' Rivera said as he danced from family member to friend on the field, nearly an hour after the end of the game. ''I'll tell you what, it feels good.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Mariano Rivera, who etched his name deeper into the World Series record book last night as perhaps the greatest relief pitcher in Series history, the key word was relief. It was relief that poured freely from him as he exhaled, screamed to the sky and raised his arms as Mike Piazza's long fly ball settled into the glove of Bernie Williams for the final out of the Series.</p>
        <p>Rivera, with his second save of the Series, and a record-setting seventh World Series save, wrapped up the Yankees' 4-2 victory, standing on the mound in exhilaration as he had in each of the last two season-ending victories. ''This is my third one on the field,'' Rivera said as he danced from family member to friend on the field, nearly an hour after the end of the game. ''I'll tell you what, it feels good.''</p>
        <p>Rivera had pitched two innings to close out the Yankees' Game 4 victory on Wednesday night, and now, less than 24 hours later, he walked to the mound after the Yankees slipped in front in the top of the ninth inning in the decisive fifth game. He struck out the pinch-hitter Darryl Hamilton to start the inning, and then after a walk to Benny Agbayani, he got the dangerous Edgardo Alfonzo on a routine fly to right. Piazza, who had already homered twice in the Series, connected on a fastball and sent it on a line to deep center field, but Williams eased under it just in front of the warning track.</p>
        <p>''I knew right away,'' Williams said, Champagne pouring over him as he spoke in the cramped locker room. ''I knew he didn't hit it.''</p>
        <p>Catcher Jorge Posada added: ''We got the out. That's all that matters.''</p>
        <p>The save finished off a strong seven-inning performance by Andy Pettitte, who did not allow an earned run and lowered his earned run average in the Series to 1.98, and Mike Stanton, who pitched a scoreless eighth inning to earn his second victory of the Series. While the Yankees bank on Rivera to shut the door, in this Series they received a top to bottom effort. Pettitte did not get a decision in the Series, but battled Mets starter Al Leiter through Game 1 and this game to a draw.</p>
        <p>In Pettitte's final inning last night, with Joe Torre hoping to get him through the seventh inning because of a weary bullpen, he surrendered a leadoff single, but got out of the inning, striking out cleanup hitter Todd Zeile on a 3-2 curveball and then fanning Robin Ventura, also on a 3-2 pitch.</p>
        <p>For Rivera, the Series found him in the odd position of adjusting on the run. Despite his staggering success, the Yankees felt the Mets had found a way to weaken him and they tweaked and tightened his performance, which resulted in a pair of saves.</p>
        <p>When Rivera came to the mound in the eighth inning of Game 4 on Wednesday night, the Mets knew that he was difficult to hit, but they also knew what he was going to throw, or at least they thought they did. Rivera went through the Mets lineup, retiring the heart of the order in the in the eighth inning, and then catching Benny Agbayani and Matt Franco looking at third strikes in the ninth.</p>
        <p>''He lives with that hard, cut fastball,'' Franco said. ''He gets lefties with it time after time. You see it every night on TV. I just told myself I wasn't going to get beat by that pitch. He threw one 92 miles per hour on the outside part of the plate. I was not looking for that pitch. He threw some great pitches on the outside part of the plate, exactly where I wasn't looking.''</p>
        <p>In the World Series, Stanton compiled a 2-0 record with a 0.00 earned run average, numbers even better than Rivera. But in the end, it is Rivera who the Yankees turn the ball over to, no matter how well Stanton and Nelson throw.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the success could have happened without Mo,'' Torre said. ''You talk about how many times have you argued that pitchers and everyday players, if you trade one for the other, who gets the better deal. But when you're dealing with a closer like Mo, he's like an everyday player because he plays five days a week.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
