<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leiter Travels the Distance But Goes One Out Too Far</title>
    <meta content="27RAFA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/sports/27RAFA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leiter, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E4D91E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leiter Travels the Distance But Goes One Out Too Far</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets pitcher Al Leiter comments on emotional Game 5 he pitched in World Series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets finally gave Al Leiter the chance to decide a game himself. Now, Leiter has all winter to relive the ninth inning of Game 5 of the World Series.</p>
        <p>Leiter left Game 1 with a 3-2 lead only to see closer Armando Benitez blow the save in the ninth inning before the Yankees won in 12 innings. Afterward, Leiter tried to put another lost postseason opportunity in diplomatic terms. The only way a starting pitcher doesn't have to rely on others, Leiter said, is to do the job himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets finally gave Al Leiter the chance to decide a game himself. Now, Leiter has all winter to relive the ninth inning of Game 5 of the World Series.</p>
        <p>Leiter left Game 1 with a 3-2 lead only to see closer Armando Benitez blow the save in the ninth inning before the Yankees won in 12 innings. Afterward, Leiter tried to put another lost postseason opportunity in diplomatic terms. The only way a starting pitcher doesn't have to rely on others, Leiter said, is to do the job himself.</p>
        <p>Bobby Valentine gave Leiter that opportunity last night. With two outs and runners on first and second in the ninth inning, Valentine had John Franco warming in the bullpen, but left the veteran in to pitch to Luis Sojo who had entered the game in a double switch the previous inning. Sojo's single gave the Yankees a 4-2 lead they held onto to capture the Subway Series, four games to one.</p>
        <p>Sojo swung at a first-pitch slider from Leiter, his 142nd pitch of the game, and hit a chopper up the middle. Leiter lunged to his left, shortstop Kurt Abbott dove to his right and second baseman Edgardo Alfonzo made one final dive. Jay Payton fielded the ball in short center field and threw home. The throw was perfect, but Mike Piazza was playing behind the plate and Jorge Posada, running from second base, slide in front of Piazza. The ball deflected off Posada's left thigh and rolled into the Mets' dugout. Payton's error also scored Scott Brosius for a 4-2 Yankees lead.</p>
        <p>Valentine had come out to argue with umpires at second base before approaching the mound. He took the ball from his pitcher and Leiter began his slow walk to the dugout, with his glove tucked between his right arm and side. Leiter navigated the dugout steps and plopped onto the bench. He took off his cap, ran his hand through his soaked hair and stared at the ground. Then, each player in the dugout came over, patted him on the back and retreated.</p>
        <p>''Congratulations on a great season, a great job,'' Valentine told him.</p>
        <p>The Mets left the game in the hands of their ace, the boy from the Jersey Shore who grew up cheering for Tom Seaver. Leiter thought about his childhood as a Mets fan, about the Subway Series, about coming up with the Yankees. All his emotions flooded his system. Leiter is an expressionist pitcher, who lives off the energy he burns. At that moment, he had no outlet for his feelings.</p>
        <p>''I was upset,'' Leiter said. ''I've never been so emotional in a baseball game. I've always had the ability to put this all in perspective and realize to me it's just a baseball game. It's not life or death. It's not a world issue that affects people in a life or death situation. It's a game played between lines. You're supposed to have fun.''</p>
        <p>Leiter couldn't overcome the frustration of not getting the third out.</p>
        <p>Leiter struck out the first two batters of the ninth inning and thought he had struck out Posada for the third out. But Posada would cap a nine-pitch at-bat with a walk, resisting the out by fouling off three pitches with two strikes. Leiter was upset at himself and allowed a single to Brosius on a 1-1 slider. That is Leiter's best pitch and the Yankees were awaiting it.</p>
        <p>Leiter denied he was tired and said he was grateful to Valentine for leaving him in. He has still not won a postseason game in 11 starts.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to finish that game, no doubt about that,'' Leiter said. ''I told him yesterday, 'Leave me in there. 150 pitches, I don't care.' This is a decent career. I've thrown the ball pretty well. I don't care. I just wanted to be out there.''</p>
        <p>The pitching coach, Dave Wallace, declined to answer what went into leaving Leiter in the game. ''Don't ask me that one on the last day,'' Wallace said, as he pointed toward the manager's office and walked into the trainer's room.</p>
        <p>Valentine said he left in Leiter because he did not want Franco pitching three consecutive days and liked how he pitched to Posada.</p>
        <p>''I thought that striking out those first two guys and the pitches he threw to Posada made me think he had plenty,'' Valentine said. ''I was wrong. It was the wrong decision, obviously. If I brought somebody else in, they definitely would have gotten the guy out and we'd still be playing.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
