<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Video Releases</title>
    <meta content="27VIDB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Frequency (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Thomas and the Magic Railroad (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Return to Me (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">But I'M A Cheerleader (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDE1131F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Video Releases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brief reviews of films now released on video: Frequency, Thomas and the Magic Railroad, Return to Me and But I'm a Cheerleader; photo</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frequency</p>
        <p>One night, while fooling around on a short-wave radio in the old family homestead in Queens, a morose New York City policeman, John Sullivan (Jim Caviezel), finds himself in communication with his father, Frank (Dennis Quaid, left, with Daniel Henson), a firefighter who died in a warehouse blaze 30 years ago. Yes, it's Dad, all right, broadcasting from an era when he taught little John how to ride a bike and play ball. With his gift of hindsight, John helps Frank to sidestep death, but in the process they create a new existence full of fresh perils to be overcome by the closeness of family ties. ''If it all sounds horribly icky,'' Stephen Holden wrote in The New York Times, '' 'Frequency' gets away with much of its sentimentality simply by piling it on so aggressively.''</p>
        <p>2000. New Line. $107.37; DVD, $24.98. 100 minutes. Closed captioned. PG-13. Release date: Oct. 31.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frequency</p>
        <p>One night, while fooling around on a short-wave radio in the old family homestead in Queens, a morose New York City policeman, John Sullivan (Jim Caviezel), finds himself in communication with his father, Frank (Dennis Quaid, left, with Daniel Henson), a firefighter who died in a warehouse blaze 30 years ago. Yes, it's Dad, all right, broadcasting from an era when he taught little John how to ride a bike and play ball. With his gift of hindsight, John helps Frank to sidestep death, but in the process they create a new existence full of fresh perils to be overcome by the closeness of family ties. ''If it all sounds horribly icky,'' Stephen Holden wrote in The New York Times, '' 'Frequency' gets away with much of its sentimentality simply by piling it on so aggressively.''</p>
        <p>2000. New Line. $107.37; DVD, $24.98. 100 minutes. Closed captioned. PG-13. Release date: Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>Thomas and the Magic Railroad</p>
        <p>Thomas, the tank engine from the PBS children's series ''Shining Time Station,'' tries to be really useful as he chugs between the real-life community of Shining Time and the imaginary island of Sodor. The task is to prevent steam engines like himself from being ground to scrap by a mean diesel. Mr. Conductor (Alec Baldwin), a miniature figure of almost crazed good cheer, is there to help, but it is up to another engine named Lady, her somber keeper (Peter Fonda) and his spirited granddaughter (Mara Wilson) to save the day. It's too late for an ''extremely poky movie'' (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
        <p>2000. Columbia Tristar. $22.96; DVD, $24.95. 89 minutes. Closed captioned. G.</p>
        <p>Return to Me</p>
        <p>The recipient of a heart transplant from a woman killed in a car crash, Grace Briggs (Minnie Driver),  writes a thank you note to the donor's husband, Bob Rueland (David Duchovny). Later the two meet in a restaurant run by Grace's grandfather (Carroll O'Connor). Bob, a designer and builder, could use a lift out of his bereavement, and Grace needs a boyfriend to go along with her restored health.</p>
        <p>Weightless when it means to be magical, Bonnie Hunt's film ''is a piece of fruit gone soft from being on the vine too long'' (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>2000. MGM. $107.37; DVD, $24.98. 116 minutes. Closed captioned. PG. Release date: Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>But I'm a Cheerleader</p>
        <p>When Megan (Natasha Lyonne), a high school cheerleader, exhibits alternative sexual tendencies, she is shipped off to True Directions, a heterosexual rehab camp run by the tight-jawed Mary (Cathy Moriarty). Ms. Lyonne delivers a real performance in her little girl's croak of a voice, as do Clea DuVall as the requisite tough girl and Katharine Towne, who plays a doleful camper with a sly, sportive spark. But this is a film with a crushingly obvious idea, ''so campy it reflexively sends an elbow to its own ribs'' (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>2000. Universal. $99.36; DVD, $24.98. 84 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a theater release, appeared on television or been on videocassette in earlier editions.</p>
        <p>LES BONNES FEMMES, EVA and IL GRIDO. Three films from major directors find them in good form, if not at their most towering. In Claude Chabrol's ''Bonnes Femmes'' (1960, 95 minutes, in French with English subtitles), four Paris shop girls look for love in the 1960's. Jeanne Moreau has the title role in Joseph Losey's ''Eve'' (1962, 103 minutes), about a Welsh writer (Stanley Baker) who has it all but still craves a jaded woman who whacks him around with a riding crop. In Michelangelo Antonioni's ''Grido'' (1957, 115 minutes, in Italian with English subtitles), a factory worker named Aldo (Steve Cochran) has it no easier with the lusty Irma (Alida Valli), who dumps him. Kino. $24.95 each VHS; DVD, $29.95 each. Information: (800) 562-3330.</p>
        <p>SPIRIT OF BEBOP, ZOOT SIMS QUARTET and L.A.-ALL STARS. The jazz pianist Barry Harris is the subject of ''Spirit of Bebop'' (1999, 55 minutes), a walk through his career accompanied by some of the best-known musicians of the 1950's and 60's. ''Zoot Sims Quartet'' (1970, 28 minutes) features the group at Dante's in Los Angeles and includes a performance by the Shelly Manne Quartet. Big Joe Turner and Hampton Hawes are the headliners in ''L.A. All-Stars'' (1970, 28 minutes), also with the Les McCann trio. Three cassettes, $19.95 each. Rhapsody Films. Information: (860) 434-3610.</p>
        <p>A CHRISTMAS CAROL. Patrick Stewart stars in the TNT production, which stays remarkably faithful to the book. (2000, 50 minutes.) Warner. $14.95; DVD, $19.98.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
