<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mets Lose Series, But Their Pride Is Intact</title>
    <meta content="27METS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/sports/27METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4D91E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mets Lose Series, But Their Pride Is Intact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets have their pride intact, despite losing World Series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It said ''National League Champs'' on the board posted in the hallway of the clubhouse. It was blank underneath. For the Mets, there are no more games or workouts on the schedule. They lost the World Series last night, falling by 4-2 to the Yankees in Game 5.</p>
        <p>There were programs and bats, posters and photos, baseballs and Champagne bottles, all bearing signatures in shiny gold ink. The team in the room had won something, had something real to celebrate. But this was not the time for that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It said ''National League Champs'' on the board posted in the hallway of the clubhouse. It was blank underneath. For the Mets, there are no more games or workouts on the schedule. They lost the World Series last night, falling by 4-2 to the Yankees in Game 5.</p>
        <p>There were programs and bats, posters and photos, baseballs and Champagne bottles, all bearing signatures in shiny gold ink. The team in the room had won something, had something real to celebrate. But this was not the time for that.</p>
        <p>To look around the room 10 minutes after the last out was to see 10 players sitting silently. Turk Wendell, in full uniform, held his head in his hands. So did Joe McEwing, who had also not undone a single button. Dennis Cook and Lenny Harris also had not begun to undress, and they stared from their chairs.</p>
        <p>The veteran reserve Darryl Hamilton sat alone in a corner by the trainer's room, sighing, an empty look on his 35-year-old face. The veteran catcher Todd Pratt surveyed the room, hands on his head. The only voice came from Robin Ventura, the classy third baseman who was the first Met to speak to reporters.</p>
        <p>''You're as disappointed as can be right now,'' Ventura said. ''So it's hard to look back and smile. But the guys did a really good job this year.''</p>
        <p>Slowly, the Mets filtered into the main dressing area. Manager Bobby Valentine, still in uniform after a session in a separate interview room, spoke with closer Armando Benitez in his office.</p>
        <p>Benitez had blown the save in the first game of this taut World Series, in which every game was decided by one or two runs. It would have been easy to focus on the missed chance in Game 1, but this was a series of near-misses for the Mets, and the collective impact of those games is what will haunt them this winter.</p>
        <p>If the games had all been blowouts, Wendell said, ''I'd be like, Geez, how did we get here?' But all these games could have gone either way. They could have swept us in four. We could have swept them in four. We get a break, and it's a totally different situation. It was just unfortunate we didn't capitalize on some things.''</p>
        <p>The Mets ultimately succumbed to Mariano Rivera, the extraordinary closer who got Mike Piazza to fly out to deep center field to end the game. The Shea Stadium crowd of 55,292 shrieked as the ball left Piazza's bat.</p>
        <p>''He came up with a man on base, down by two,'' Mets General Manager Steve Phillips said. ''It seems to me that's supposed to be part of the script.''</p>
        <p>In four of the last five seasons, of course, the script has ended with the Yankees celebrating a World Series title. Playing the victim was especially difficult for the Mets.</p>
        <p>''A little bit,'' reliever John Franco said, when asked if it hurts more to lose to the Yankees. ''They're our cross-town rivals. But there were other teams that lost to them and went out in four straight. We battled them every game, and it could have gone either way.''</p>
        <p>Ventura, who batted .150 (3 for 20) in the series, also stressed that point.</p>
        <p>''There's a certain amount of luck involved in baseball,'' he said. ''I don't necessarily think the gap's so big that it was just domination. Our team's good, their team's good. They got it done, and sometimes luck helps, too.</p>
        <p>''Those are the things you always think of when you come that close - the would've, could've, should'ves always come into your thoughts.''</p>
        <p>Franco, who has been with the Mets since 1990 but is now a free agent, said he had no special emotions because this may have been his last game as a Met. There are eight other potential free agents from this team -- Kurt Abbott, Derek Bell, Mike Bordick, Mike Hampton, Harris, Bobby J. Jones, Rick Reed and Turk Wendell -- and the makeup of the 2001 Mets could be very different.</p>
        <p>''We lost to a very good team,'' Phillips said. ''We played them as tough as we could possibly play them. We have a strong nucleus, and there's no reason we can't be back again next year and learn from this and hopefully win.''</p>
        <p>Franco said he has not thought that far ahead, and he rattled off a list of things to be proud of about this season.</p>
        <p>Franco mentioned the young players who became major contributors, like Benny Agbayani and Jay Payton. He spoke of Benitez, who set a franchise record with 41 saves in his first full season as Franco's successor. He credited Al Leiter, Mike Hampton, Rick Reed and Bobby Jones. He could have gone on.</p>
        <p>''There's nobody in here that should be ashamed of the season we had,'' Franco said. ''It was just that the Yankees were a little bit better.''</p>
        <p>Said Valentine: ''I couldn't ask anything more of a group of guys. I couldn't ask for a better effort, for better preparation, for better camaraderie. They're the National League champs. I think that they were champs this World Series, and I'm extremely proud of them.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
