<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bid Made for Piece of Ailing Irish Phone Company</title>
    <meta content="27EIRC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/business/27EIRC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7DB1131F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bid Made for Piece of Ailing Irish Phone Company</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRIAN LAVERY</byline>
      <dateline>DUBLIN, Oct. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One year ago, 500,000 Irish retail shareholders in Eircom P.L.C., the former state telephone company, saw the 42-year-old entrepreneur Denis O'Brien as a persistent threat to their investment.</p>
        <p>His company, Esat Telecom, consistently challenged Eircom with price competition and court actions in what was once Eircom's monopoly market. Eircom has faced growing difficulties since January, when Mr. O'Brien sold Esat to British Telecom, and Eircom stock spent the rest of the year at or below its initial public offering price. Eircom shares closed today at 3.23 euros ($2.67). The I.P.O. price was 3.90 euros ($3.23).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One year ago, 500,000 Irish retail shareholders in Eircom P.L.C., the former state telephone company, saw the 42-year-old entrepreneur Denis O'Brien as a persistent threat to their investment.</p>
        <p>His company, Esat Telecom, consistently challenged Eircom with price competition and court actions in what was once Eircom's monopoly market. Eircom has faced growing difficulties since January, when Mr. O'Brien sold Esat to British Telecom, and Eircom stock spent the rest of the year at or below its initial public offering price. Eircom shares closed today at 3.23 euros ($2.67). The I.P.O. price was 3.90 euros ($3.23).</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. O'Brien became a possible savior to those shareholders when he bid 2.25 billion euros ($1.85 billion), or 1 euro a share, to acquire the fixed-line assets of his old archrival.</p>
        <p>''The fixed-line business is not viable as a stand-alone public company,'' Mr. O'Brien said calmly at a news conference with his Irish business partners. ''We want to get back into the market and have some more fun.''</p>
        <p>Eircom made no official statement on the offer, which is considered friendly. The chairman of Eircom, Ray MacSharry, did send Mr. O'Brien a letter in response, asking for more details on his proposals.</p>
        <p>Since it coincides with Eircom's negotiations to sell its mobile subsidiary, Eircell, to Vodafone, the deal would effectively break Eircom into several parts. The bid does not cover Eircom's multimedia and directory holdings, which the company has said it will float in a separate offering early next year.</p>
        <p>Eircom's fixed-line assets are usually seen as undesirable legacy hardware -- miles of copper buried underground, in an era of wireless communications. Without Eircell, ''it's not a compellingly attractive target,'' said Justinian Clifford-Bowles, a telecommunications analyst with Commerzbank in London.</p>
        <p>But analysts also said that Mr. O'Brien's bid was too low. Even 3 billion euros ($2.5 billion), or 1.35 euros a share, would be ''a fairly cautious valuation,'' said Jemma Houlihan, an analyst with the Dutch bank ABN-Amro in Dublin, because Eircom has very little debt. ''I think the directors would find it difficult to recommend a bid of just 1 euro per share,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Brien said he plans to use the network for broadband Internet technologies like digital subscriber lines, or D.S.L. High-speed Internet access is still unavailable in Ireland, despite Eircom's often stated plans to introduce a commercial D.S.L. service.</p>
        <p>Eircom shareholders are likely to vote on the deal at an emergency general meeting before the end of the year. The only other time such a meeting has taken place, when Eircom reported its annual results in September, more than 3,000 retail investors attacked the company board for five hours, with epithets including ''crooks'' and ''cowards.''</p>
        <p>In the summer of 1999, the Irish government persuaded one in every seven Irish citizens to buy Eircom shares. For the great majority of those retail investors, it was the first time they had bought stock.</p>
        <p>''We were assured by the government and by the company that we were onto a bonanza,'' said Sean Cody, 69, a retiree who invested the equivalent of about $6,500 of his pension funds. ''We lost out.''</p>
        <p>The slide in Eircom's share price throughout this spring -- caused by increasing competition in the Irish market and international distaste for the telecom sector -- has created a growing sense of frustration among investors, who feel duped by the government. The government saw a profit of more than 4 billion Irish pounds ($4.3 billion) on the sale.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of anger that, in my opinion, is quite easily understood. If I were you, I'd be equally angry,'' the chief executive of Eircom, Alfie Kane, said at a meeting last month after several shareholders demanded that Mr. MacSharry pass him the microphone. Mr. Kane's tempered and sympathetic speech, initially in defense of his 300,000 Irish pound ($327,000) salary, was received with scattered applause. He also pointed out that the company's finances had improved significantly, despite the stock's poor performance. After-tax profits more than doubled in the year to March 2000, from 78 million euros ($65 million) to 180 million euros ($150 million). Revenues grew 10 percent, to almost 2 billion euros ($1.65 billion).</p>
        <p>The combined 1.7 million-Irish pound ($1.85 million) bonuses awarded to Mr. Kane and the chief financial officer, Malcolm Fallen, illustrate the company's public relations difficulties. The bonuses were linked to their performance before and during the initial stock offering. But the bonuses were announced in the days leading up the public meeting, when bitter shareholders were least eager to hear it. An executive incentive plan and employee share option plan were also approved at the meeting.</p>
        <p>The publicity war heats up when Eircom deals with the Irish government, its former owner. The government now must force Eircom to deal with the rigors of competition, in a local market where 70 telecommunications licenses have been issued since December 1998.</p>
        <p>''It's taken them by surprise that they have to fight for things now, instead of just being entitled to it,'' said Paul Phelan, a technology analyst with Davy Stockbrokers in Dublin, part of the Bank of Ireland Group. Competitors include WorldCom, Colt Telecom of the United Kingdom, and after it acquired Ireland's Esat Telecom earlier this year, British Telecom.</p>
        <p>Irish and European Union regulations require Eircom, as the incumbent former monopoly, to sell network capacity to competitors at a 23 percent discount. The company says this allows the competition to avoid the cost of building lines and other equipment.</p>
        <p>Eircom says it has had difficulty providing enough capacity within the specified time frame. The company says it may soon fight a court battle with the government regulator over the fines it faces for missing deadlines.</p>
        <p>''We do believe that the regulatory environment has become very difficult for Eircom,'' a company spokesman, Gerry O'Sullivan, said.</p>
        <p>The relationship reached a new low last month when Mary O'Rourke, the government minister responsible for liberalizing the telecommunications sector, refused to shake Mr. Kane's hand in front of Irish TV cameras. Mr. Kane is credited with starting the bad blood by publicly asserting that the government set the initial stock price too high.</p>
        <p>All that could be settled by Mr. O'Brien, whose quiet voice and boyish smile have already won over some Irish hearts. ''I'd like to see them accept his offer,'' said Jean Dolan, 59, a retired singing instructor who borrowed about $10,500 to buy Eircom shares in the I.P.O. in July 1999. ''I think Denis O'Brien would be the man to take it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
