<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="27MOVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFD61031F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. Ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on Page 15.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>* ''BAMBOOZLED,'' starring Damon Wayans, Savion Glover and Jada Pinkett-Smith. Written and directed by Spike Lee (R, 135 minutes). Mr. Lee's answer to ''Network'' is a scaldingly funny satire of the television industry in which a failing network hits the ratings jackpot with an old-time black minstrel show that resurrects offensive stereotypes. Accepted as hip, ironic and liberating by mainstream audiences but reviled by black militants, it starts a national craze for wearing blackface. If this messy cinematic collage goes every which way, its anger at a television industry that largely excludes blacks and whose black programming (in the director's view) perpetuates minstrelsy is right on target. Mr. Wayans plays the black Harvard-educated executive who dreams up this Frankenstein monster of a show (Stephen Holden).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. Ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on Page 15.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>* ''BAMBOOZLED,'' starring Damon Wayans, Savion Glover and Jada Pinkett-Smith. Written and directed by Spike Lee (R, 135 minutes). Mr. Lee's answer to ''Network'' is a scaldingly funny satire of the television industry in which a failing network hits the ratings jackpot with an old-time black minstrel show that resurrects offensive stereotypes. Accepted as hip, ironic and liberating by mainstream audiences but reviled by black militants, it starts a national craze for wearing blackface. If this messy cinematic collage goes every which way, its anger at a television industry that largely excludes blacks and whose black programming (in the director's view) perpetuates minstrelsy is right on target. Mr. Wayans plays the black Harvard-educated executive who dreams up this Frankenstein monster of a show (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>''BEDAZZLED,'' starring Brendan Fraser, Elizabeth Hurley and Frances O'Connor. Directed by Harold Ramis (PG-13; 105 minutes). This sprightly, amusing bit of devilment (a remake of a 1967 picture with British spoofsters Dudley Moore and Peter Cook) stars Mr. Fraser as Elliot Richards, a geeky, luckless doofus, and Ms. Hurley as the Devil. In exchange for a lien on Elliot's immortal soul, Ms. Mephistopheles turns him into a Colombian drug trafficker, an N.B.A. superstar and a famous writer, among other things. Each scenario, meant to bestow on Elliot the love of a pretty co-worker (Ms. O'Connor), goes comically awry. The original ''Bedazzled'' was cheekily blasphemous; this version, true to the spirit of the age, is somewhat pious, but it's nonetheless reasonably good fun (A. O. Scott).</p>
        <p>''BILLY ELLIOT,'' starring Gary Lewis, Julie Walters and Jamie Bell. Directed by Stephen Daldry (R, 90 minutes). Mr. Daldry's debut feature tells the story of an 11-year-old coal miner's son in northern England who dreams of becoming a ballet dancer. The movie holds few surprises; you always know where it's going, and sometimes you can predict exactly what the characters are going to say. But Mr. Daldry finds honest feeling and dramatic integrity in shopworn material, and the cast, notably Mr. Lewis as Billy's father, Ms. Walters as his teacher and young Jamie Bell as Billy himself, help rescue the movie from its most hackneyed impulses (Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''THE CONTENDER,'' starring Gary Oldman, Joan Allen, Jeff Bridges and Christian Slater. Written and directed by Rod Lurie (R, 132 minutes). A political thriller pumped up with as much dramatic juice as ''The Contender'' doesn't have to be believable to be gripping. If this lurid Washington yarn about a sex scandal that threatens to destroy the hand-picked nominee (Ms. Allen) of the liberal President (Mr. Bridges) to fill a vacated vice presidential slot clanks with tin-eared oratory and preposterous plot turns, it keeps you on the edge of your seat. Scenery-chewing performances by Mr. Oldman (as the scrofulous, misogynist congressman who leads the smear campaign), Mr. Bridges as a Clinton-Johnson presidential amalgam and Ms. Allen as the dignified and high-principled nominee contribute to the fun (Holden).</p>
        <p>* ''DR. T AND THE WOMEN,'' starring Richard Gere, Kate Hudson, Laura Dern, Helen Hunt, Shelley Long and Farrah Fawcett. Directed by Robert Altman (R, 122 minutes). Like last year's ''Cookie's Fortune'' (which was also written by Anne Rapp), Mr. Altman's new comedy has a mellow, rambling feel. The keen edge of social criticism that characterized masterpieces like ''Nashville'' and ''The Player'' has been blunted somewhat, but Mr. Altman remains an unparalleled choreographer of chaos. Mr. Gere, playing a harried, gentlemanly Dallas gynecologist, is virtually the only man in the movie, and his generous performance anchors the film and provides a foil for wonderful supporting turns by Ms. Hudson, Ms. Dern, Ms. Hunt and Ms. Long (Scott).</p>
        <p>''LOST SOULS,'' starring Winona Ryder and Ben Chaplin. Directed by Janusz Kaminsky (R, 102 minutes). Most of the neighborhoods in which ''Lost Souls'' plays are bound to be scarier than this horror movie retread, and it's probably a bad idea to release an ''Exorcist'' remake while the original is enjoying a 25th anniversary rerelease. Ms. Ryder is part of a team of renegade religious professionals and Catholic priests -- the X-Fathers -- performing exorcisms to prevent the birth of Satan. Mr. Chaplin may just be that person, though his career as a smug author exploiting the lives of serial killers should probably tag him as the personification of Evil. Mr. Kaminsky, the talented cinematographer who shot ''Saving Private Ryan'' and ''Schindler's List,'' makes his directorial debut with this feature, which has intriguing visual details. To those who wonder why, we can only suppose that perhaps the Devil made him do it (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''MEET THE PARENTS,'' starring Robert De Niro, Blythe Danner, Ben Stiller and Teri Polo. Directed by Jay Roach (PG-13, 105 minutes). Mr. De Niro's scowl has become the kind of cultural shorthand that generally presages entry into the Smithsonian, where it can lie in state next to the Fonz's jacket, Archie Bunker's chair and Cher's hair. He uses it in this likable paranoid comedy, in which he plays every guy's worst nightmare: the father of his girlfriend. Mr. Stiller is the nervous, eager-to-please boyfriend, and the story plays out in a rustic suburban scenario that's too quiet: Martha Stewart's ''Night of the Living Dead'' (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''PAY IT FORWARD,'' Kevin Spacey, Helen Hunt, Haley Joel Osment, Jon Bon Jovi and Angie Dickinson. Directed by Mimi Leder (PG-13; 155 minutes). Three good actors -- Mr. Osment, Mr. Spacey and, especially, Ms. Hunt -- are wasted in this aggressively well-intentioned exercise in spiritual fraudulence. Mr. Osment plays a saintly Las Vegas seventh grader who concocts a scheme to make the world a better place. Ms. Hunt is his alcoholic mother and Mr. Spacey his scarred, sarcastic social studies teacher. The movie is so thumpingly melodramatic, and its surprise ending so vile in its manipulations, that it gives being nice a bad name (Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''REQUIEM FOR A DREAM,'' starring Jared Leto, Ellen Burstyn, Jennifer Connelly and Marlon Wayans. Directed by Darren Aronofsky (not rated, 102 minutes). Mr. Aronofsky's adaptation of the Hubert Selby Jr. novel is both a knockout and a downer. ''Requiem'' looks at the lives of four addicts (played by Mr. Leto, Ms. Burstyn, Ms. Connelly and Mr. Wayans) connected to one another by the bonds of love, friendship and family; it also emphasizes that the rituals of consumption are as important as the addiction. The tumble of imagery is powerful, almost overwhelming, and totally under the director's control, and though the material is bleak, ''Requiem'' offers the compensating high from an instinctive filmmaker (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''THE YARDS,'' starring Mark Wahlberg, Charlize Theron, Joaquin Phoenix and James Caan. Written and directed by James Gray (R, 115 minutes). An amalgam of ''The Godfather'' (its candlelit mood and score), a Sidney Lumet-styled urban-realist drama (its  Queens setting) and a vintage Warner Brothers ex-con melodrama (its hokey ending), ''The Yards'' is a film whose epic ambitions remain unrealized. Mr. Wahlberg is a good-hearted ex-convict sucked back into crime who becomes the fall guy for evil deeds committed by a corrupt family that runs a business repairing subways cars. Mr. Phoenix, as his ruthless best friend who becomes his nemesis, gives an incendiary performance and is the best thing in the movie (Holden).</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>''THE BRITISH NEW WAVE: FROM ANGRY YOUNG MEN TO SWINGING LONDON.'' It's back to the tumultuous days of England in the 1950's and 1960's in the three-week series of 35 features and short films that opens today at Film Forum. Here again are actors like Laurence Harvey, Richard Burton, Claire Bloom, Julie Christie, Alan Bates, Rita Tushingham and Vanessa and Lynn Redgrave; writers like John Osborne, Shelagh Delaney, Harold Pinter and Alan Sillitoe; and directors like Lindsay Anderson, Tony Richardson, Karel Reisz and John Schlesinger. Fueling their creativity was a post-World War II Britain of angry and alienated young working-class people alive with sexuality and devoid of the polished veneer of the old upper-class. On the menu are memorable films like ''Saturday Night and Sunday Morning,'' ''The Entertainer,'' ''The Servant,'' ''If,'' ''Darling,'' ''Alfie,'' ''The Loneliness of the Long Distance Runner'' and ''Tom Jones.'' The time machine to this remarkable period gets under way today and tomorrow with a double feature of Jack Clayton's ''Room at the Top'' (1959), with Laurence Harvey and Simone Signoret, and Tony Richardson's ''Look Back in Anger,'' with Richard Burton and Claire Bloom in the screen adaptation of John Osborne's hit play. The series continues through Nov. 16 at Film Forum, 209 West Houston Street, in the South Village. Tickets: $9; $5 for members. Screening schedule and information: (212) 727-8110 (Lawrence Van Gelder).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
