<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="27DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0DD1E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kellogg Plans to Acquire Keebler for $3.86 Billion  Kellogg, the maker of Eggo waffles and Rice Krispies, agreed to acquire Keebler Foods for $3.86 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal would combine the world's leading breakfast cereal company with the second-largest cookie and cracker maker in the United States, and bring together several widely recognized marketing icons, including Tony the Tiger, Snap, Crackle and Pop and the Keebler Elves. Shares of Kellogg rose $1.56, to $24.31, while Keebler rose $1.06, to $40.44. [Page C2.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kellogg Plans to Acquire Keebler for $3.86 Billion  Kellogg, the maker of Eggo waffles and Rice Krispies, agreed to acquire Keebler Foods for $3.86 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal would combine the world's leading breakfast cereal company with the second-largest cookie and cracker maker in the United States, and bring together several widely recognized marketing icons, including Tony the Tiger, Snap, Crackle and Pop and the Keebler Elves. Shares of Kellogg rose $1.56, to $24.31, while Keebler rose $1.06, to $40.44. [Page C2.]</p>
        <p>Early Claims on Budget Surplus  Congress and the Clinton administration are still wrangling over the final pieces of this year's federal budget, but by the time they are finished they could spend more than 40 percent of the surplus that the two presidential candidates are counting on to pay for their own proposals, analysts from both parties said. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Limits Promised on Steel Imports  The Clinton administration has promised to take the first steps toward imposing new limits on steel imports. [A20.]</p>
        <p>Vinik to Close $4.2 Billion Fund  Jeffrey N. Vinik, manager of one of the nation's largest hedge funds, said that he would shut down his $4.2 billion fund and return his investors' money by the end of the year to spend more time with his family. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Nasdaq Closes Up After Early Dive  Stocks ended mixed after a volatile session in which the Nasdaq composite index fell more than 140 points before rebounding in the afternoon to close 42.61 points, or 1.32 percent, higher at 3,272.18. The Dow Jones industrial average gained 53.64 points, or 0.52 percent, to 10,380.12, but the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 0.46 point, to 1,364.44. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Europeans Criticize Hong Kong  In a report adopted by the European Parliament, Hong Kong came under fire for allowing Li Ka-shing, 72, and his family to amass undue influence over the city's commercial life and its stock market. Saying the Li family's companies accounted for up to a third of Hong Kong's total market value, the report expressed concern that the city was no longer a level playing field. [C4.]</p>
        <p>DaimlerChrysler Profit Falls 78%  DaimlerChrysler said that its third-quarter profit fell by 78 percent because of a loss of $512 million at the Chrysler Group in the United States, and executives said that the bad times might continue well into next year. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Law Firm Awards $35,000 Bonuses  A leading Wall Street law firm, Sullivan &amp; Cromwell, announced that its first-year lawyers, most of whom began practicing law last fall at an annual salary of $125,000, will receive a bonus of $35,000 this year. That is more than double the $15,000 that first-year associates received last year. [B3.]</p>
        <p>Measure to Halt Phone Deal Dropped  Deutsche Telekom won a battle in its effort to enter the United States when Congress abandoned legislation that would have blocked its proposed deal for VoiceStream Wireless. [C8.]</p>
        <p>A Gerbil-Free Campaign for Go.com  Cliff Freeman &amp; Partners, the agency responsible for the gerbil-launching ads for Outpost.com, is taking a more direct approach for promoting the revamping of the Go.com Web site. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [C9.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
