<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burkittsville Revisited, With More Mind Games</title>
    <meta content="27BLAI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/arts/27BLAI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berlinger, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Book of Shadows: Blair Witch 2 (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EFDF1131F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burkittsville Revisited, With More Mind Games</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews movie Book of Shadows: Blair Witch 2, directed by Joe Berlinger; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whether or not it flies at the box office, ''Book of Shadows: Blair Witch 2'' (the sequel to ''The Blair Witch Project'') can't be written off as a weak, half-hearted effort to eke out a few more dollars from last year's blockbuster cinematic jack-in-the-box. The $10 million follow-up to the Little $30,000 Movie That Could is a clever if muddled collection of riffs on the Blair Witch juggernaut, dressed up with intellectual pretensions by Joe Berlinger, who directed this film with a chortling zest.</p>
        <p>Once the movie is over and you're sitting around with friends unraveling its inconsistencies (and, oh, how the film's releasing company, Artisan Entertainment, is hoping you will!), don't blame yourself if none of it adds up. The movie is best appreciated as an amusing smart-aleck joke directed at a clued-in cult audience that can't get enough of the original movie's supernatural mind games. How large is that cult audience? This weekend's box-office figures will tell whether last year's Hollywood answer to the pet rock craze can be spun off into a franchise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whether or not it flies at the box office, ''Book of Shadows: Blair Witch 2'' (the sequel to ''The Blair Witch Project'') can't be written off as a weak, half-hearted effort to eke out a few more dollars from last year's blockbuster cinematic jack-in-the-box. The $10 million follow-up to the Little $30,000 Movie That Could is a clever if muddled collection of riffs on the Blair Witch juggernaut, dressed up with intellectual pretensions by Joe Berlinger, who directed this film with a chortling zest.</p>
        <p>Once the movie is over and you're sitting around with friends unraveling its inconsistencies (and, oh, how the film's releasing company, Artisan Entertainment, is hoping you will!), don't blame yourself if none of it adds up. The movie is best appreciated as an amusing smart-aleck joke directed at a clued-in cult audience that can't get enough of the original movie's supernatural mind games. How large is that cult audience? This weekend's box-office figures will tell whether last year's Hollywood answer to the pet rock craze can be spun off into a franchise.</p>
        <p>And speaking of pet rocks, through the Internet you can still buy collections of sticks and stones ostensibly gathered from the Black Hills around Burkittsville, Md., where both movies are set. In the movie, Jeff (Jeffrey Donovan), the sequel's prime mover, has a whole warehouse stocked with Blair Witch bric-a-brac that he markets online.</p>
        <p>Months before its release, the original ''Blair Witch Project'' tantalized prospective audiences with the remote possibility that the film might be a crude home movie left behind by a group who disappeared without a trace. The opulent sequel (filmed with lots of blazing Halloween oranges) plays similar mind games in a documentary prologue in which actual residents (or are they?) of Burkittsville are interviewed about the impact of the Blair Witch phenomenon on their community. Most are quite grumpy about it.</p>
        <p>The intellectual kernel of ''Book of Shadows'' is a Marshall McLuhan-esque assertion dropped early in the film by Jeff, who leads a group of four Blair Witch fanatics into those scrubby Black Hills. ''Film lies,'' he declares. ''Video tells the truth.'' At that moment the character becomes a mouthpiece for the director, who bases the story's surprise ending on this dubious premise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berlinger may be the ideal director for the project, since his earlier work has demonstrated a singular fascination with the ways filmmaking technology affects our perceptions of reality. His ''Paradise Lost'' documentaries, which investigated murder and religious fanaticism in a small Southern town, were true stories but filmed and edited with a gaudy panache that gave them the look and dramatic structure of fiction. ''Book of Shadows,'' which has a similarly lurid flavor, is a facetious exhibition and critique of technological trickery. Why, the movie wonders, should we trust the reality of a grainy home video more than crisp 35-millimeter images? Is technological crudeness synonymous with imagistic purity?</p>
        <p>Jeff and his party are far from your average tourists. In a screeching, head-banging, padded-cell flashback, we discover that Jeff has only recently been discharged from a mental institution. Erica (Erica Leerhsen) is a practicing Wiccan incensed by the original movie's portrayal of witchcraft as evil. (Yet in some scenes she appears almost demonically possessed.) Hard-as-nails Kim (Kim Director) is a Goth enthusiast who dresses like Elvira and has strange intuitions that prove unnervingly accurate.</p>
        <p>The most ''normal'' of the five are Stephen (Stephen Barker Turner) and his pregnant girlfriend, Tristen (Tristen Skyler), graduate students writing a book about the Blair Witch. But they, too, have agendas. Tristen insists that the myth, like so much folklore, must have some basis in fact, while Stephen, a diehard rationalist, is convinced the Blair Witch legend is nothing more than mass hysteria.</p>
        <p>When the party reaches one of the Blair Witch sites, the five have a nasty run-in with a rival tour, which Jeff sends elsewhere. Once the interlopers have departed, Jeff's group proceeds to have a wild party. The next morning, they are stunned to find all their video equipment destroyed and the tapes of the night's activities buried but intact. And in the first indication that a curse might have been laid on them while they slept, Tristen spontaneously miscarries.</p>
        <p>The situation quickly worsens. After Tristen has been treated in the hospital, the group returns to Jeff's warehouse and begins playing the videotapes in search of clues. What the tourists discover is a mysterious and frightening time gap. At the same time, they begin having terrifying hallucinations.</p>
        <p>Although ''Book of Shadows'' doesn't go in for the usual blunt horror movie shocks, it succeeds in being moderately scary. As the tourists' everyday reality is invaded by terrifying hallucinatory flashes of Blair Witch mythology, ''Book of Shadows'' evokes mass hysteria as a horror-film fright show, cleverly even slipping in visual homages to everything from ''The Omen'' to ''The Night of the Living Dead.'' It all culminates in a gory (but discreetly filmed) orgy of Manson Family-esque butchery.</p>
        <p>For all its clever notions, ''Book of Shadows'' often seems more like a montage of pasted-together images than a coherent horror story. It also has some grating tonal incongruities.  The buffoonish local sheriff (Lanny Flaherty) has it in for Jeff, and whenever he appears, the movie loses its hip, tongue-in-cheek edge.</p>
        <p>So does ''Book of Shadows'' prove that video tells the truth while film lies? Let's put it this way: the videos that supposedly document the worst-case scenario of what happened that night are tucked inside one very slick and manipulative film.</p>
        <p>''Book of Shadows: Blair Witch 2'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has scenes of violence, nudity and profanity.</p>
        <p>BOOK OF SHADOWS  Blair Witch 2</p>
        <p>Directed by Joe Berlinger; written by Dick Beebe and Mr. Berlinger; director of photography, Nancy Schreiber; edited by Sarah Flack; music by Carter Burwell; production designer, Vince Peranio; produced by Bill Carraro; released by Artisan Entertainment. Running time: 90 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jeffrey Donovan (Jeff), Tristen Skyler (Tristen), Stephen Barker Turner (Stephen), Erica Leerhsen (Erica), Kim Director (Kim) and Lanny Flaherty (Sheriff Cravens).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
