<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jewish and Catholic Scholars Seek Pius XII's Files</title>
    <meta content="Y27JEW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/27/world/27JEWS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Catholic-Jewish Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pius Xii (Pope) (1876-1958)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E0D61131F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jewish and Catholic Scholars Seek Pius XII's Files</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, Oct. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Panel of Jewish and Catholic scholars formed 11 months ago to research role of Pope Pius XII during Holocaust asks for access to closed Vatican archives; International Catholic-Jewish Commission says the 11 volumes of documents published by Vatican do not put many significant questions to rest (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dissatisfied with published Vatican documents on the role of Pope Pius XII during World War II, a panel of Jewish and Catholic scholars asked today for access to closed Vatican archives.</p>
        <p>''He was through and through a diplomat, but that simply didn't work when confronted with the Nazi machinery,'' Eva Fleischner, a Catholic on the six-member committee, said of Pius XII at a news conference here today. But, she noted, ''so many other world leaders failed as much as the pope.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dissatisfied with published Vatican documents on the role of Pope Pius XII during World War II, a panel of Jewish and Catholic scholars asked today for access to closed Vatican archives.</p>
        <p>''He was through and through a diplomat, but that simply didn't work when confronted with the Nazi machinery,'' Eva Fleischner, a Catholic on the six-member committee, said of Pius XII at a news conference here today. But, she noted, ''so many other world leaders failed as much as the pope.''</p>
        <p>The panel, the International Catholic-Jewish Commission, was formed 11 months ago by the Vatican and Jewish groups to sort out accusations that Pius XII did not speak out forcefully enough against the Holocaust.</p>
        <p>In a preliminary report today, the commission said the 11 volumes of documents published by the Vatican do not ''put to rest significant questions about the role of the Vatican during the Holocaust,'' adding, ''No serious historian could accept that the published, edited volumes could put us at the end of the story.''</p>
        <p>The record of Pius XII has been deeply contested since the 1960's, and the dispute was revived last year with the publication by Viking of ''Hitler's Pope: The Secret History of Pius XII,'' a scathing biography by John Cornwell that accused Pius XII of anti-Semitism. The Vatican, which heatedly disputes Mr. Cornwell's interpretation, had hoped to beatify Pius XII this year, but those plans were put aside after heavy lobbying by Jewish groups and others involved in interfaith dialogue.</p>
        <p>In the preliminary report, which was issued on the Internet on Wednesday, the scholars, three Jews and three Catholics, posed a sample of 47 questions that they said illustrated the gaps in the available material. In one, referring to funds used to help refugees from Nazi Germany that had been raised by the United Jewish Appeal, the scholars asked, ''Is there further documentation as to why this money was allocated to the attempted rescue of converted Jews rather than Jews?''</p>
        <p>The Web site with the report is www.bnaibrith.org/cpp/randa /vatican.html.</p>
        <p>The Vatican reacted cautiously. Its spokesman, Joaquin Navarro-Valls, issued a statement on Wednesday saying, ''In a series of questions, the scholars indicate areas in which they consider progress in this regard would require further study.''</p>
        <p>The Vatican has allowed scholars to examine archival material only up to 1922, saying more recent papers have yet to be properly classified. But because of the intense interest in World War II, the Vatican began selecting materials it deemed relevant, and those were published in 11 volumes between 1965 and 1981.</p>
        <p>The Catholic scholars who took part in the study were Ms. Fleischner, professor emeritus at Montclair State University in New Jersey; the Rev. Gerald P. Fogarty of the religious studies department at the University of Virginia; and the Rev. John Morley of Seton Hall University, South Orange, N.J. The Jewish scholars were Michael Marrus of the University of Toronto, Bernard Suchecky of the Free University of Brussels and Robert Wistrich of Hebrew University, Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Many doubt that the Vatican will open up the World War II files soon.</p>
        <p>''We still have not opened the archives pertaining to Pius XI, though, I must say, it is high time for that,'' said the Rev. Pierre Blet, a Jesuit historian who is the last surviving member of the Vatican team that assembled the 11-volume history. He was referring to Pius XII's predecessor, who reigned from 1922 to 1938.</p>
        <p>''I recognize it is a slow process,'' Father Blet said. ''But they'll just have to wait.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
