<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES</title>
    <meta content="27SPAR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242172"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3DE1131F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="5471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>ALICE AUSTEN HOUSE, 2 Hylan Boulevard, Rosebank, Staten Island. This 17th-century farmhouse, converted to a Victorian cottage in the 19th century, was the home of the photographer Alice Austen. ''Ferryboat,'' photographs by Charles Martin, through Dec. 31. Tomorrow night at 7:30, ''Halloween Mystery Night,'' party and festivities. Admission: $12; $10 for members. Reservations required. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $2; children 12 and under, free. Information: (718) 816-4506.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>ALICE AUSTEN HOUSE, 2 Hylan Boulevard, Rosebank, Staten Island. This 17th-century farmhouse, converted to a Victorian cottage in the 19th century, was the home of the photographer Alice Austen. ''Ferryboat,'' photographs by Charles Martin, through Dec. 31. Tomorrow night at 7:30, ''Halloween Mystery Night,'' party and festivities. Admission: $12; $10 for members. Reservations required. Hours: Thursdays through Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $2; children 12 and under, free. Information: (718) 816-4506.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 34-12 36th Street, at 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. ''Lon Chaney: Man of a Thousand Faces,'' through Sunday. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., George Hill's ''Tell It to the Marines'' (1927); at 4 p.m., Jack Conway's ''While the City Sleeps'' (1928). Sunday at 2 p.m., Tod Browning's ''West of Zanzibar'' (1928); at 4, Conway's ''Unholy Three'' (1930), Chaney's only talking film. Repertory nights: tomorrow and Sunday night at 6:30, Mario Bava's ''Black Sunday'' (1960). All activities are free with museum admission unless otherwise indicated. Admission: $8.50; the elderly and students, $5.50; ages 5 to 18, $4.50; 4 and under, free. Information: (718) 784-0077.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. The Arthur Ross Terrace, a new one-acre public space with ginkgo and pagoda trees, has  opened, with the same hours as the museum. ''Vikings: The North Atlantic Saga,'' details Scandinavian life a millennium ago and focuses on Viking contributions to other civilizations; through Jan. 21. ''Iceland, Land of the Vikings,'' large-format images of Iceland's natural environment; through Jan. 14. ''The Butterfly Conservatory: Tropical Butterflies Alive in Winter,'' live multicolored butterflies from Africa, Asia and the Americas on view in the rain forest of the Butterfly Conservatory; through May 28. Tickets, which include museum admission: $15; $11 for students and the elderly; $9 for children, 2 to 12; under 2 free. Advance tickets: (212) 769-5200. ''Fighting Dinosaurs: New Discoveries From Mongolia,'' featuring one of the most famous fossil finds in the world; through Sunday. Imax films are ''To Be an Astronaut'' and ''Dolphins.'' In the Imax Theater tonight and tomorrow night at 9, ''Laser Aerosmith in 3-D''; at 10, ''Laser Led Zeppelin.'' Laser show tickets: $12. Museum hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 8:45 p.m. Admission (suggested donation): $10 for adults; $7.50 for students and the elderly; $6 for children. Combination tickets are available. Information: (212) 769-5100; advance tickets: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY'S ROSE CENTER FOR EARTH AND SPACE, Central Park West at 81st Street. This 333,500-square-foot, seven-floor, 120-foot-high exhibition and research center includes the new Hayden Planetarium, the Cullman Hall of the Universe and the Gottesman Hall of Planet Earth. The Hayden Planetarium contains the Space Theater, presenting ''Passport to the Universe,'' and the Big Bang Theater, featuring narrated visual and audio effects simulating the beginning of the universe. The Cullman Hall, a 7,000-square-foot permanent exhibition hall on the bottom level, illustrates processes that led to the creation of the planets, stars, galaxies and universe. ''Starry Nights: Fridays Under the Sphere,'' with the Steve Turre Quartet, from 6 to 8 p.m., with cash bar and tapas. ''Full Moon: Apollo Mission Photographs of the Lunar Landscape,'' from NASA's Apollo missions to the moon; through January. Hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays to 8:45 p.m. Space shows run throughout the day. Suggested admission to the American Museum of Natural History, which includes the Rose Center: $10; for students and the elderly, $7.50; children 12 and under, $6; under 2, free. Admission to the museum, the Rose Center and the Hayden Planetarium space show: $19; students and the elderly, $14; children 12 and under, $11.50; under 2, free. Information: (212) 769-5100. Reservations: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>HISTORIC RICHMONDTOWN, Staten Island Historical Society, 441 Clarke Avenue, Richmondtown. Today from 3:30 to 5 p.m., ''Halloween in Richmond Town,'' children 2 and older and their families can trick or treat throughout the village; there will also be games, a costume parade with prizes and refreshments. Prepaid reservation required: $7; $3 for children. Tomorrow night from 7:30 to 9, ''All Hallows Eve Camp Fire,'' ghost stories. Prepaid reservations required: $7; $3 for children. Guided tours are available. Hours: Wednesdays through Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $4; the elderly, children 6 to 18 and students, $2.50; 5 and under, free. Information: (718) 351-1611.</p>
        <p>MERCHANT'S HOUSE MUSEUM, 29 East Fourth Street, East Village. This preserved late Federal brick home with a Greek Revival interior, once owned by Seabury Tredwell, a wealthy hardware dealer, was built in 1832.  ''Minard Lafever and His Circle: The Diffusion of Grecian Architecture in the United States, 1830-60,'' an architectural exhibition, including models, drawings, photographs and books. ''Grecian Architecture in the United States: 19th-Century Revival to 21st-Century Practice, tomorrow and Sunday, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., a symposium featuring workshops, lectures and tours. Admission: $100 for tomorrow; $85 for Sunday; $165 for both days. Tours, Saturdays and Sundays; a self-guided tour is available on weekdays. Hours: Thursdays through Mondays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; students and the elderly, $3; members, free. Information: (212) 777-1089.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF CHINESE IN THE AMERICAS, 70 Mulberry Street, Chinatown. Tomorrow from 2 to 4 p.m., a conversation with Gish Jen and Billie Tsien, part of a conversation series with artists. Free with admission. ''Chinatowns in North America,'' a new CD-ROM installation featuring photographs by William Chu; on permanent display. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, noon to 5 p.m.; closed on holidays. Admission: $3; the elderly and students, $1; 12 and under and museum members, free. Information: (212) 619-4785.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street. The museum collects, preserves and presents material related to the city's history. Sunday at 2 p.m., ''From Ellis Island to J.F.K.: New York's Two Great Waves of Immigration,'' lecture by the author Nancy Foner. ''The New York Century: World Capital, Hometown,'' through Feb. 4. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., a panel discussion with the filmmaker Brent Sterling, whose series of short documentaries for PBS are in the exhibition ''The New York Century.'' Hours: Tuesdays, 10 a.m. to 2 p.m., for registered groups only; Wednesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $7; the elderly, students and children, $4; families, $12. Information: (212) 534-1672.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF JEWISH HERITAGE: A LIVING MEMORIAL TO THE HOLOCAUST,  18 First Place, at West Street and Battery Place, Battery Park City, Lower Manhattan. Artifacts, documents, photographs, videos and film clips are included in exhibitions on the Holocaust and on Jewish life before and after World War II. Hours: Sundays through Wednesdays, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays until 8 p.m.; Fridays and the eves of Jewish holidays, 9 a.m. to 3 p.m.; closed Saturdays. Admission: $7; students and the elderly, $5; children 5 and under, free. Tickets can be bought in advance through Ticketmaster, (212) 307-4007, or by calling the museum on the day of the visit, (212) 945-0039. Information: (212) 509-6130.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF TELEVISION AND RADIO, 25 West 52nd Street, Manhattan. ''Monster in the Box: Horror on Television,'' a series focusing on five decades of the genre, through Dec. 10. This weekend it will focus on the relationship between horror and humor, featuring episodes of the ''The Munsters,'' ''The Addams Family'' and ''The Simpsons''; Fridays at 7 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays at 4 p.m.; Thursdays at 6 p.m. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m.; Thursdays until 8 p.m. On Fridays the theater is open until 9. Admission: $6; students and the elderly, $4; 12 and under, $3. Information: (212) 621-6800.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>QUEENS BOTANICAL GARDEN, 43-50 Main Street, Flushing. Sunday from noon to 4 p.m., Bonsai Society of Greater New York's annual show. Free. Tomorrow from 10 a.m. to noon, backyard composting demonstration. Free. Hours: daily, 8 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 8 a.m. to 7 p.m.; closed Mondays. Garden admission is free. On weekends a trolley runs to Flushing Meadows-Corona Park. Information: (718) 886-3800.</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL, West 249th Street and Independence Avenue, Riverdale, the Bronx. ''Beneath the Bark, Under Leaf and Log,'' an outdoor installation by Sylvia Benitez; through Monday. ''From Wilderness to Garden,'' miniature landscapes by Amanda Crandall; through Nov. 12 in the Wave Hill House Gallery. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., garden demonstration of harvesting, drying and storing herbs. Tomorrow from 1 to 4 p.m., community volunteer project of planting oaks in Riverdale Park. Sunday at 2 p.m., hearthside reading, with Jay Parini, most recently the author of a book on the poet Robert Frost. Reservations required: extension 308. Tomorrow from 1 to 4 p.m., visitors can work alongside foresters to prune, plant and clear excess vegetation. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 9 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Admission: $4; students and the elderly, $2; Saturdays, free until noon. Information: (718) 549-3200; reservations: extension 213.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
        <p>''NOT QUITE THE NYC MARATHON,'' Central Park. A five-kilometer run. Begins Sunday at 9:30 a.m. on the West Drive at 69th Street. Sponsored by the New York Road Runners Club and Arthur Andersen. Proceeds from pledges will benefit Dress for Success New York. Registration fee: $17, $12 and $10 for junior and senior club members. Advance registration fee, $22, $15 for club members, $12 for junior and senior club members. Information: (212) 860-455.</p>
        <p>ON THE STREET</p>
        <p>WALL STREET COMMUNITY DAY FESTIVAL SERIES, from South to Water Streets. Today, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by Community Board No. 1.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON PLACE FALL FESTIVAL, from Grove to Macdougal Streets. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 7 p.m. Sponsored by St. Joseph's Church.</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON SQUARE FESTIVAL, Waverly Place, from Broadway to Fifth Avenue, Greenwich Village. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Greenwich Village Community Republican Club.</p>
        <p>GREAT THIRD AVENUE FESTIVAL, from 23rd to 34th Streets, Manhattan. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by Our Lady of the Scapular and St. Stephan's Church.</p>
        <p>VANDERBILT YMCA SECOND AVENUE FESTIVAL, from 46th to 56th Streets, Manhattan. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Vanderbilt YMCA.</p>
        <p>27TH VILLAGE HALLOWEEN PARADE, Avenue of the Americas, from Spring Street to 23rd Street, Greenwich Village. Tuesday at 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>15TH PARK SLOPE HALLOWEEN PARADE, Seventh Avenue, from 12th Street to Berkeley Place, Brooklyn. Tuesday at 7 p.m. Sponsored by the Park Slope Civic Council.</p>
        <p>EVENTS</p>
        <p>FIFTH FALL CELEBRATION, Hunter College, 68th Street between Park and Lexington Avenues. Continues today and tomorrow with lectures, concerts, screenings, a walking tour and a health fair. Most events are free. Today 2:30 to 7 p.m.; tomorrow, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Information: (212) 650-3737.</p>
        <p>''CRYPT CRAWL: A CATHEDRAL TOUR,'' Cathedral of St. John the Divine, Amsterdam Avenue and West 112th Street, Morningside Heights. A candlelight tour. Tomorrow at 10:30 a.m. and 1 and 3 p.m. Fee, $5. Reservations: (212) 932-7347.</p>
        <p>''GHOST TALES,'' Provincetown Playhouse, 133 Macdougal Street. A free program of spooky stories from around the world told by Laura Simms. Sunday at 3 p.m. Information: (212) 998-5867.</p>
        <p>ANNUAL MONSTER MASH, World Financial Center, Liberty Street, Lower Manhattan. A daylong event for families with pumpkin carving, storytelling, face painting and a party and parade. Tomorrow, noon to 4 p.m. Sponsored by the World Financial Center, Edward Moran Bar and Grill and the Battery Park City Parents Association. Information: (212) 945-2600.</p>
        <p>ANNUAL HALLOWEEN HAUNTED WALK AND CARNIVAL, Prospect Park, Brooklyn. Tomorrow, noon to 3 p.m. The walk, which takes place on Lookout Hill, will feature Count Dracula, the Wicked Witch and the Headless Horseman; the carnival on the nearby Nethermead will feature miniature golf, football, races and a ring toss. Sponsored by the Prospect Park Alliance. Admission by donation. Information: (718) 965-8999.</p>
        <p>CELEBRATION OF JEWISH ARTS AND CRAFTS, Henry Street Settlement, Abrons Art Center, 466 Grand Street, Lower East Side. With crafts, music, storytelling and demonstrations. Sunday, 11:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Free admission. Information: (212) 598-0400.</p>
        <p>''DAY OF YIDDISH ART AND CULTURE,'' Eldridge Street Synagogue, 12 Eldridge Street, Lower East Side. With music, lectures, readings and food. Sunday, noon to 5 p.m. Sponsored by the Eldridge Street Project. Information: (212) 219-0903.</p>
        <p>EDNA ST. VINCENT MILLAY INDUCTION, Cathedral of St. John the Divine, 1047 Amsterdam Avenue, at 112th Street, Morningside Heights. The poet, who died in 1950, will be inducted into the Poets' Corner at the church. Previous inductees include Mark Twain, Washington Irving, Edgar Allan Poe, Emily Dickinson, Ernest Hemingway, T. S. Eliot and Herman Melville. Sunday at 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>24TH VILLAGE HALLOWEEN COSTUME BALL, Theater for the New City, 155 First Avenue, at East 10th Street, East Village. Tuesday. Outdoor events, which are free, begin at 4 P.M. Indoor entertainment begins at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15. Reservations recommended: (212) 254-1109.</p>
        <p>WALKING TOURS</p>
        <p>''CHINATOWN.'' A walking tour with stops at the Lin Tse-Hsu Memorial and sites associated with Dr. Sun Yat-sen and Yung Wing. Meets tomorrow at 1 p.m. at the southwest corner of Canal and Lafayette Streets. Sponsored by the Big Onion Walking Tours. Fee: $10, $8 students and the elderly. Information: (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>''EDGAR ALLAN POE AND HIS GHOSTLY FRIENDS,'' Greenwich Village and East Village. Explore the neighborhoods and learn about the ghosts of Poe, Peter Stuyvesant and others. Meets tomorrow and Sunday at 2 and 6 p.m. and at 6 p.m. on Tuesday outside the Second Avenue Deli, 156 Second Avenue, at 10th Street. Fee: $12. Sponsored by Dr. Phil's New York Talks and Walks. Information: (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>LONG BEACH TO ROCKAWAY BEACH, Long Island and Queens. A 10-mile walk along the beach and boardwalk, from Long Beach on Long Island to the Rockaway Peninsula. Meets tomorrow at 9:45 a.m. at the information window on the lower level at Penn Station. Fee, $3. Sponsored by the Outdoors Club. Information: (718) 435-4994.</p>
        <p>MEXICAN FOOD AND CULTURE IN SUNSET PARK, Brooklyn. Combines a discussion of immigration with stops at restaurants and markets. Meets tomorrow at 1 p.m. on the corner of Fourth Avenue and 45th Street. Sponsored by the Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment. Fee, $8; $6 for Center members; $5 for students and the elderly. Information: (718) 788-8500, extension 401.</p>
        <p>HISTORIC GREEN-WOOD CEMETERY, Brooklyn. A tour of the historic cemetery sprinkled with ghost tales. Meets tomorrow and Sunday at 1 p.m. inside the gate at Fifth Avenue and 25th Street. Led by Jeff Richman. Fee, $10. Information: (631) 549-4891.</p>
        <p>''GOTHAM CITY GHOST TOUR,'' Greenwich Village. Covers historic and infamous spots, including the cemetery at St. Mark's Church  and the burial ground at Washington Square Park. Tomorrow and Sunday at 4 p.m. and Monday and Tuesday at 6:15 p.m. Sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours. Fee, $12. Meeting  place and reservations: (212) 465-3331.</p>
        <p>''WHERE THEY CAME TO REST: FOUR DOWNTOWN GRAVEYARDS'' focuses on early graveyards and the New Yorkers buried there. Meets tomorrow at 1 P.M. at Trinity Church, Broadway and Wall Street. Fee, $12. Sponsored by Joyce Gold History Tours of New York. Information: (212) 242-5762.</p>
        <p>''GHOSTLY GREENWICH VILLAGE.'' The tour includes Mark Twain's house and the sites of public executions. Meets tomorrow at 6 p.m. and Sunday at 2 p.m. at the Washington Arch. Fee: $10. Sponsored by Street Smarts N.Y. Information: (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>''GREENWICH VILLAGE GHOSTS GALORE.'' Stops at the sites of the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire and the Hanging Elm as well as a haunted firehouse. Meets tomorrow at 1:30 p.m. on the southwest corner of Eighth Street and Fifth Avenue. Fee, $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Information: (212) 265-2663.</p>
        <p>''ALL HALLOW'S EVE GREEN-WOOD CEMETERY,'' Brooklyn. A walk through the fall foliage with stops at the grave sites of noted people. Sunday at 10 a.m. and 1 p.m. Sponsored by the Cooper Union. Fee, $25. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 353-4195.</p>
        <p>ASTORIA. An all-day walk through this Queens neighborhood passes the Steinway Mansion, Lent Homestead and Socrates Sculpture Garden and returns via Roosevelt Island. Lunch in a Greek taverna or bring your own to eat in the park. Meets Sunday at 10:15 a.m. in front of the Burger King on Ditmars Boulevard. Fee: $3 nonmembers. Sponsored by the Outdoors Club and Shorewalkers. Information: (718) 463-5729 before 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>''MACABRE GREENWICH VILLAGE.'' Answers questions like: Who was hanged at Washington Square Park? What graveyard inspired Edgar Allan Poe? And what sites are visited by the ghost of a firefighter? Meets Sunday at 1 P.M. at the Washington Arch. Fee: $12. Sponsored by Joyce Gold History Tours. Information: (212) 242-5762.</p>
        <p>HAUNTED MIDTOWN AREA, Manhattan. With stops at a ''haunted'' theater, courtyard and hotel. Meets Sunday at 2 p.m. on the southwest corner of 58th Street and Seventh Avenue. Fee, $5. Sponsored by Adventure on a Shoestring. Information: (212) 265-2663.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
