<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amazon.com Surpasses Wall St. Forecast</title>
    <meta content="Y25AMA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/technology/25AMAZ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amazon.com Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6DE1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amazon.com Surpasses Wall St. Forecast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amazon.com beats Wall Street expectations, posting higher sales and lower loss than expected in third quarter; company lost $241 million, 22 percent more than the $197.1 million it lost in year-earlier quarter; sales rose 79 percent, to $638 million, from a year earlier (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amazon.com beat Wall Street's expectations yesterday, posting higher sales and a lower loss than expected in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>The company lost $241 million in the quarter, 22 percent more than the $197.1 million it lost in the year-earlier quarter. On a per-share basis, the loss was 68 cents a share, compared with 59 cents in 1999.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Amazon.com beat Wall Street's expectations yesterday, posting higher sales and a lower loss than expected in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>The company lost $241 million in the quarter, 22 percent more than the $197.1 million it lost in the year-earlier quarter. On a per-share basis, the loss was 68 cents a share, compared with 59 cents in 1999.</p>
        <p>Excluding the cost of stock options, noncash charges and losses from its investments, Amazon lost $68 million. That was 25 cents a share, well under the 33 cents analysts had forecast.</p>
        <p>The company posted sales of $638 million, up 79 percent from a year earlier. The sales figure included $20 million worth of toys that Amazon sold to Toysrus.com, which is taking over Amazon's online toy store. Even after deducting that shift, the company's sales beat analysts' forecast of sales around $600 million.</p>
        <p>''They are definitely demonstrating that they are likely to be the disproportionate beneficiary of the shakeout in online shopping coming, even as there is an increase in consumer interest in online shopping,'' said Lauren Levitan, an analyst with Robertson Stephens.</p>
        <p>Although shares of Amazon were up as much as $1.50 earlier in the day, they closed down 44.25 cents at $29.5625. In after-hours trading, the shares rose to $33.31.</p>
        <p>The company's gross profit margin, or its sales minus the cost of goods sold and the cost of shipping them to buyers, rose sharply to 26 percent from 20 percent a year earlier. The company said it had been able to use its growing size to demand better prices from suppliers and had increased the efficiency of its shipping operation.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Amazon has been raising prices, especially for books, which it had been selling at deep discounts. For example, best sellers are now offered at 40 percent off, rather than 50 percent off.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in a conference call with investors, the company said it had shifted the focus for its book, music and video business in the United States from sales growth to profit growth. Sales in those categories increased by 33 percent, to $400 million, a far slower pace than Amazon's other business lines. But they produced an operating profit of $25 million in the latest quarter, compared with a $100,000 loss a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Sales in the company's other business lines in the United States -- including mainly electronics, toys, tools and kitchen equipment -- increased ninefold, to $150 million, with the growth fueled mainly by consumer electronics, the company said. Those businesses lost $54 million.</p>
        <p>Ms. Levitan said the rapid growth of electronics was a mixed blessing for Amazon, especially given that the large electronics chain stores were running into difficulty this year.</p>
        <p>''Consumer electronics could be their Waterloo,'' she said. ''It's a tough category with lower margins, higher shipping costs and the potential for inventory problems.'' She noted, moreover, that Sony, far and away the largest electronics manufacturer, would not sell directly to Amazon. That means that Amazon cannot obtain many Sony products and must buy what it can from wholesalers at higher costs than its competitors.</p>
        <p>Amazon's overseas activities in Germany, France and Britain had sales of $88 million, up 120 percent. They lost $40 million.</p>
        <p>The company said it had added 2.8 million customers in the quarter, for  a cumulative total of 25 million. Of those, 3.9 million customers are of its overseas units.</p>
        <p>In the conference call, company officials took pains to counter fears that Amazon, like many smaller online companies, was in danger of running out of cash. Its cash and marketable securities declined by only $8 million, to $900 million in the quarter. It expects that balance to rise to more than $1 billion at year-end, then fall to $700 million at the end of the first quarter. That swing will come from the fact that Amazon, like most retailers, receives payments from customers immediately but does not pay its suppliers for several months. It said that it would start generating cash from operations for the rest of next year.</p>
        <p>The company estimated that its sales in the fourth quarter would be between $950 million and $1.05 billion. That figure does not include another $100 million to $150 million of toy sales that will be booked by Toysrus.com. Amazon receives a commission of under 10 percent on those sales. The company had sales of $676 million in the fourth quarter of 1999.</p>
        <p>That would give Amazon sales of about $2.7 billion in 2000. It said also that it expected to post sales of $4 billion in 2001 and that its operating losses next year would be less than $160 million, or 5 percent of sales.</p>
        <p>In its earnings announcement, the company said it had received ''informal inquiries'' from the Securities and Exchange Commission about the way it accounts for relationships with other online merchants. Companies like Drugstore.com and Ashford.com have agreed to pay Amazon for links from its site, and in many cases those payments are in the form of stock rather than cash. Amazon said it had hired outside appraisers to help determine the value of that stock.</p>
        <p>In the most recent quarter, the company booked $30 million in revenue from these companies, which it calls the Amazon Commerce Network. Of that, two-thirds was in stock rather than cash. Separately, it took a charge of $68 million to reflect the decline in the value of its holdings in these companies.</p>
        <p>Ms. Levitan said she hoped that the S.E.C. inquiry would force Amazon to increase its disclosures about the components of these deals.</p>
        <p>''They need to open the black box it has become,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
