<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Filling the Peruvian Niche on Avenue A</title>
    <meta content="25UNDE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/living/25UNDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="$25 AND UNDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cocina Cuzco (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/$25 and Under</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD81431F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Filling the Peruvian Niche on Avenue A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov, in $25 and Under column, reviews Cocina Cuzco, Peruvian restaurant in East Village (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PERUVIAN cuisine is a melting pot of Asian, European, African and ancient American influences, so it's not so improbable that a Malaysian is behind Cocina Cuzco, a new Peruvian restaurant in the East Village. Hann Low, the owner, has no connection with Peru, though. He enjoyed the food at Chicama, Douglas Rodriguez's nuevo Latino restaurant specializing in Peruvian ceviches, and believed there would be a niche for this sort of food on Avenue A.</p>
        <p>Mr. Low's record as a restaurateur is mixed. He owns the generally dull Lemongrass Grill chain of Thai restaurants. But he has branched out successfully into other cuisines, including Korean, at Jin Dal Lae, an excellent restaurant on the Upper West Side. Cocina falls into Jin Dal Lae's category of striving for authenticity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PERUVIAN cuisine is a melting pot of Asian, European, African and ancient American influences, so it's not so improbable that a Malaysian is behind Cocina Cuzco, a new Peruvian restaurant in the East Village. Hann Low, the owner, has no connection with Peru, though. He enjoyed the food at Chicama, Douglas Rodriguez's nuevo Latino restaurant specializing in Peruvian ceviches, and believed there would be a niche for this sort of food on Avenue A.</p>
        <p>Mr. Low's record as a restaurateur is mixed. He owns the generally dull Lemongrass Grill chain of Thai restaurants. But he has branched out successfully into other cuisines, including Korean, at Jin Dal Lae, an excellent restaurant on the Upper West Side. Cocina falls into Jin Dal Lae's category of striving for authenticity.</p>
        <p>Cocina offers half a dozen ceviches, the marinated raw seafood dishes that show off the extraordinary variety of seafood along the Peruvian coast. The selection is not exotic but includes some excellent choices like ceviche de concha ($8.95), clams marinated in lime and served on the half shell, covered with cilantro and tiny cubes of pickled onions and peppers. A huge mixed platter ($10.95) includes flounder, shrimp, squid and octopus. Each ceviche comes with slices of yam and yuca as well as cancha, the crunchy roasted corn kernels that go brilliantly with the soft seafood.</p>
        <p>Other traditional Peruvian appetizers include tender cooked octopus ($7.50) in a sauce of rosemary and olive oil, with an almost extraneous side of pureed olives. Papas a la huancaina ($4.95), sliced potatoes served cold under a cheese sauce, is galvanized by aji amarillo, a mild chili that turns the sauce a bright yellow. Tamalitos verdes ($4.95), Peruvian tamales made with cornmeal, bite-size roast pork and cilantro sauce, are tame by comparison.</p>
        <p>The chef, Silvino Sagni, has had long restaurant experience in Peru, and his main courses demonstrate many sides of Peruvian cuisine. Lomo saltado ($8.95), stir-fried beef flavored with soy and onions and served over rice and French fries, shows the influence of the Chinese laborers who came to Peru a century ago. The influence of former African slaves can be seen in red snapper ($12.95), crusted in thin slices of sweet potatoes, making it crisp on the outside and moist within. It's served with rice and beans, excellent fried yuca and salsa criolla, or marinated sweet onions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sagni's other fine main courses include juicy chicken ($8.95; $4.95 a half), marinated in citrus and spices and then cooked on a rotisserie. Skirt steak ($13.95) is chewy and full of flavor, and so is roasted pork ($9.95), served with rice, yams and salsa criolla.</p>
        <p>Cocina could pay a little more attention to its pisco brandy cocktails, which taste as if powdered mixes were used, and to chicha morada, a traditional beverage brewed from purple corn and flavored with cinnamon. (The flavor ought to be more intense.) Desserts ($4.25 each), though, are delicious, like bread pudding flavored with dulce de leche, and mazamorra morada, a kind of gelatin version of chicha morada.</p>
        <p>Cocina's dining room is simple and pleasant but has a major drawback. While I am told that it used to be a Japanese restaurant, it somehow reeks of stale tobacco smoke. I'm all for turning a light on Peruvian cooking. Let's let some air in as well.</p>
        <p>Cocina Cuzco  55 Avenue A, at Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 529-3469.</p>
        <p>BEST DISHES: Ceviches, octopus with rosemary, papas a la huancaina, lomo saltado, red snapper crusted with sweet potato, rotisserie chicken, skirt steak, roasted pork, all desserts.  PRICE RANGE: Appetizers, $2.95 to $9; main courses, $8.95 to $13.95.  CREDIT CARDS: Cash only.  HOURS: Sunday through Thursday, 5 p.m. to midnight. Friday and Saturday, to 1 a.m.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Everything is on one level.</p>
        <p>$25 AND UNDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
