<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Hoping Kickoff Unit Will Slow Down the Eagles</title>
    <meta content="25GIAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/sports/25GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Eagles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Philadelphia Eagles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE2D71531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Hoping Kickoff Unit Will Slow Down the Eagles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Giants preparing for game against Philadelphia Eagles (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a team that symbolizes perfectly how professional football is played these days -- with winning or losing often dependent on lucky bounces or gusts of wind -- the Giants are working feverishly on their kicking game this week to get that bounce and offset that wind.</p>
        <p>They are 5-2, but on Sunday the Giants face the Philadelphia Eagles, a team that is one of football's best at running back kickoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a team that symbolizes perfectly how professional football is played these days -- with winning or losing often dependent on lucky bounces or gusts of wind -- the Giants are working feverishly on their kicking game this week to get that bounce and offset that wind.</p>
        <p>They are 5-2, but on Sunday the Giants face the Philadelphia Eagles, a team that is one of football's best at running back kickoffs.</p>
        <p>To add to the vagaries, Coach Jim Fassel is not sure who will kick off for his team Sunday at Giants Stadium: Brad Daluiso, the veteran who is still bothered by a weak leg following knee surgery 11 months ago, or the younger and healthier Jaret Holmes.</p>
        <p>Both are kicking in practice this week. Daluiso often whispers in Holmes's ear, telling him about the Meadowlands' tricky winds. And Holmes, who like the rest of the team cannot practice on Giants Stadium's new, but problematic, grass, is trying to get his footing right.</p>
        <p>Fassel said he was unlikely to suit up both players. But which one will he choose? ''I'd like to make the decision Sunday, but I'll make it Friday,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Whoever is the Giants' kicker, he faces this problem: The Eagles are the third-best team in the National Football League at getting good field position on a kickoff. Their average offensive drive starts on their 32-yard line.</p>
        <p>''This will be the 18th time I've faced Brian Mitchell,'' Daluiso said of the star kick returner who used to play for the Redskins and became an Eagle this season. ''We talk before the games and I tell him, 'Take it easy on me,' but he never does.''</p>
        <p>Nor does Mitchell take it easy on anyone else. With a 28-yard return average, Mitchell is second in the National Football Conference, a bad omen for the special-teams-challenged Giants.</p>
        <p>The Giants have been the worst team at defending against kickoffs in the league; opponents start, on average, on the 34-yard line.</p>
        <p>Nine years ago, Daluiso was among the pioneers in specialty place-kickers. He was hired for the length of his kickoffs. At first, the Giants did not even have him kick field goals. Now, however, Daluiso often cannot even reach the end zone on kickoffs.</p>
        <p>''We'll have to evaluate it every week,'' Fassel said of his kickers, and Daluiso in particular. ''We need to get the ball in the end zone. Brad has to prove to me he is ready.''</p>
        <p>Against the Cowboys two weeks ago, none of Daluiso's five kickoffs made it into the end zone, and Dallas routinely produced big runbacks. In fact, the biggest return of the year against the Giants was produced by the Cowboys' Jason Tucker, who ran back a kickoff 90 yards before he was halted at the 2-yard line.</p>
        <p>Daluiso came into this season having created touchbacks on 40 percent of his kickoffs. In his 5 kickoffs against Dallas, the Cowboys ran back a total of 205 yards.</p>
        <p>It has been a hard year for Daluiso. After months of trying to work his surgically repaired knee back into shape, he injured a hamstring, and that in turn caused a strained back. Fassel immediately brought in Holmes, who was on the practice squad last year. Holmes kicked in two games, getting some distance in his kickoffs; he reached the end zone all three times against the Tennessee Titans and converted a pair of field-goal attempts at Atlanta, before Daluiso returned to face Dallas.</p>
        <p>So Holmes's future is uncertain. ''I haven't taken a lease,'' he said, ''I'm still paying week to week on an apartment.''</p>
        <p>The rest of this season could well be a tryout for next year for both kickers. Daluiso is 32 and his contract is up after this season. The Giants have already shown confidence in Holmes, who is 24.</p>
        <p>''He's young,'' Daluiso said. ''I'm not as young. But there are some definite positives. My knee is getting better. We knew it would be a long process. In the last week and a half I changed my workout program to more of what I've done in the off-season.''</p>
        <p>He is working now on strength as well as on agility, since he obviously does not yet have the power back in his leg. He says that with another off-season, he thinks his leg strength will be completely restored.</p>
        <p>So now the paradox is that Daluiso must learn again what used to come naturally -- kickoffs. ''I had to learn how to kick field goals when I came into the league,'' he said. ''I had never done it. The field goals now are not the problem. The deep kicks are.</p>
        <p>''I'm not at the point of being exceptional, which is where I was,'' he said. ''I'm at the point of being average.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Since the National Football League introduced the bye week, the Giants have been pro football's best at winning the game before the bye; they are 11-1. But what about after the bye? They are one of the worst at 2-9. . . . The game Sunday against Philadelphia, which completes the Giants' first-half season, will mark the 132nd time they have faced the Eagles. The rivalry began in 1933, starting with a 56-0 Giants victory that was sandwiched between games with the Boston Redskins and the Brooklyn Dodgers.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
