<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Take Steaming Seriously? Chefs Do</title>
    <meta content="25WELL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/living/25WELL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING WELL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Eating Well</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E1DF1531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Take Steaming Seriously? Chefs Do</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marian Burros</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marian Burros article on steaming food, a treasured, time-honored way to to cook, and one that happens to use no fat; notes that technique is being adopted by great chefs across country; photos; recipes (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TODAY'S buzzwords for menu writers are roasted, grilled and braised. No steaming on that list. It has fallen victim to its own virtuous image: these days, steaming sounds like deprivation cuisine; too healthy, too boring.</p>
        <p>But all across the country, great chefs are quietly steaming away. If they are trying to save anyone's heart, it's not the main reason.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TODAY'S buzzwords for menu writers are roasted, grilled and braised. No steaming on that list. It has fallen victim to its own virtuous image: these days, steaming sounds like deprivation cuisine; too healthy, too boring.</p>
        <p>But all across the country, great chefs are quietly steaming away. If they are trying to save anyone's heart, it's not the main reason.</p>
        <p>Steaming happens to be a treasured, time-honored way to cook, and one that happens to use no fat. It  produces tender, moist fish, chicken and vegetables, leaving them bright and full of flavor and not waterlogged, as boiling or even poaching does. Now, chefs are taking steaming even further, using unusual liquids, flavoring them with aromatic vegetables and spices, and infusing simple foods with a depth of flavor and complexity.</p>
        <p>But they also appreciate the purity of the technique, which preserves the flavor and appearance of fine ingredients. And for foods where a soft, silken texture is important, there's no better method.</p>
        <p>Not that most chefs would ever say so on their menus. But they steam shrimp rolls, mushrooms, potatoes to be mashed, even foie gras. And they have developed techniques that take steaming well beyond simply laying food in a basket over simmering water in a covered pot.</p>
        <p>''Steaming gives you the ability to infuse flavors and maintain the critical juices,'' said David Bouley, who uses the technique at Bouley Bakery and Danube in TriBeCa for everything from skate to green beans. The way he does it, flavors are steeped in because he adds aromatics, either directly to his fish or vegetables, or in the water that creates the steam.</p>
        <p>Eric Ripert of Le Bernardin says there is nothing better than steaming for nonfatty fish like halibut; it seals in the succulence and adds texture. ''When the steam is full blast, it creates a kind of crust on the outside and preserves the inside,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>In his landmark book, ''Cuisine Minceur'' (William Morrow, 1976), Michel Guerard wrote that steaming ''is a process filled with fragrances that also causes the fat to 'sweat' out of food while preserving the nutritive elements (minerals, vitamins) and the original, essential flavors.''</p>
        <p>The technique essentially involves putting food over simmering liquid in a sealed pot, with or without a special steamer basket. The food never comes in contact with the hot water producing the steam. Chefs have advanced the method by using plastic wrap, both to protect the food from the water and to seal in herbs or aromatics to season the main ingredient. Wayne Nish of March in Midtown makes shrimp rolls of ground shellfish with tarragon that he seals in plastic and steams until firm, then serves in slices as hors d'oeuvres with lemon wedges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bouley steams food in plastic but leaves the wrapper partly open so that the steam penetrates. For his skate dish, he lays chamomile leaves, a paste of orange rind and sugar and a bit of olive oil on the fish and tops it with very thin slices of cucumber cut to look like scales.</p>
        <p>With asparagus and green beans, Mr. Bouley wraps them in plastic with garlic, juniper berries, star anise, lemon rind and a little oil, and steams them. To make a complete meal, a chicken fillet can be put on top. Vegetables alone take about 10 minutes; with the chicken, about 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>Unlike Mr. Ripert, who relies on high heat for steaming, Mr. Bouley steams the vegetables slowly; after the water reaches the boiling point, he turns down the heat. The result, he said, is ''the most sophisticated flavor on the vegetables, and it beats blanching them and shocking them.''</p>
        <p>On Le Bernardin's current menu, Mr. Ripert is featuring steamed halibut served with celeriac puree, striped bass topped with roasted foie gras and grapes, and black bass with cilantro, ginger and crab vermicelli in citrus broth.</p>
        <p>Flavorings like garlic, onions, herbs and spices can also be added to the simmering liquid. The French chef Jacques Maniere, the author of ''Cuisine a la Vapeur,'' translated into ''The Art of Cooking With Steam'' (William Morrow, 1995), wrote that the most effective way to impart flavor to steamed food is to lay it on a bed of aromatic herbs and vegetables, rather than putting the aromatics in the liquid.</p>
        <p>Steaming can be done in pots designed for it that contain a basket to hold the food, on a collapsible steamer basket in a pot or skillet, or on a plate set over simmering liquid. A tight-fitting lid is crucial. Or as Mr. Guerard wrote, ''The right pot to steam in is any pot the food will fit into.''</p>
        <p>Steaming can also be done in the oven, en papillote, with the food encased in parchment paper or aluminum foil. No water is used; juices from tomatoes or wine or the food itself create the steam.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nish says that steaming is the only method by which he cooks salmon, because the fish remains soft and moist, unlike when it is grilled or sauteed. He serves it with a cream sauce made with 30-year-old Scotch -- not exactly designed for dieters.</p>
        <p>He also steams chanterelles, because they remain firm and look better than they do after sauteing, which leaves them limp.</p>
        <p>Michel Richard at Citronelle in Washington loves the steamed version of pot-au-feu, the melange of chicken and vegetables in rich broth. ''If you put a chicken in a liquid medium, it dilutes the flavor,'' he said. ''When you steam it, there is more concentration of the flavors of the chicken and the vegetables, and the meat is firmer.''</p>
        <p>He steams whole heads of cauliflower, for 15 to 20 minutes, because they stay white; he steams leeks, cut into slices to preserve their flavor. He even steams the potatoes he mashes -- unpeeled and whole, they cook in 35 to 45 minutes -- because they do not absorb water. ''If you boil them, they become like a sponge,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Talking about steaming makes him think of the famous dish in which the technique that many people think of as pedestrian is combined with two of the world's great luxuries. One of France's foremost contemporary chefs, Bernard Loiseau, steams a hen after inserting black truffles under the skin of the marinated bird and stuffing it with a vegetable and foie gras mixture. The foie gras and truffles suffuse the chicken with an ineffable flavor and perfume.</p>
        <p>With steaming, you can afford to add a little of that unused fat in the sauce, or why not a spoonful of foie gras?</p>
        <p>STEAMED CHICKEN WITH FENNEL AND GARLIC  Adapted from Citronelle, Washington  Time: 1 1/2 hours</p>
        <p>40 cloves of garlic, peeled  2 sprigs thyme  2 fennel bulbs, thinly sliced crosswise  3 cups chicken stock or canned broth  1 lemon, cut in half  1 teaspoon aniseed  1 4-pound whole chicken</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon coriander seeds, crushed  Salt and freshly ground black pepper.</p>
        <p>1. In the lower part of a large steamer, combine garlic, thyme, fennel, chicken stock, lemon and aniseed.</p>
        <p>2. In the upper part of the steamer, place  chicken and sprinkle with coriander seeds and salt and pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>3. Fit steamer pieces together, and cover tightly. Place over high heat to bring to a boil, then simmer for 1 hour.</p>
        <p>4. Check to see if chicken is throughly cooked by slicing into joint where leg meets breast. Meat should be white and juices should run clear. If necessary, steam for an additional 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>5. Set top half of steamer aside. Bring vegetable mixture to a boil, and reduce by one-third. Remove lemon and thyme sprigs. To serve, cut chicken into four pieces. Place a serving in each of four large soup plates, and top with vegetables and broth.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>STEAMED SHRIMP ROLLS WITH TARRAGON  Adapted from March  Time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>1 pound large shrimp, shelled  3 tablespoons fresh tarragon leaves, finely chopped  Sea salt  Lemon wedges, for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. Place shrimp in a food processor, and pulse until finely chopped but not pureed.  Mix in tarragon and salt to taste.</p>
        <p>2. Lay out four pieces of plastic wrap (each about 8 inches square), and spoon  1/4 of  mixture into center of each. Shape each mound into a roll about 1 inch thick. Roll up tightly in plastic, twisting ends to seal. Rolls may be refrigerated for up to 12 hours.</p>
        <p>3. To cook rolls, place 2 inches of water in  bottom of a steamer and bring to a boil.  Place plastic-wrapped rolls in top half of  steamer. Cover, and reduce heat to medium-low. Steam until shrimp rolls are opaque and firm, about 10 minutes. Remove from heat, and cool to room temperature.</p>
        <p>4. To serve, unwrap rolls and slice  1/4- to  3/8-inch thick. Arrange slices on a platter, overlapping in a spiral pattern, and garnish with lemon wedges.</p>
        <p>Yield: 60 pieces (10 to 12 servings).</p>
        <p>CLEAR STEAMED SALMON WITH GINGER AND BLACK BEANS  Adapted from ''China Moon'' by Barbara Tropp (Workman Publishing, 1992)  Time: 1 hour</p>
        <p>10 ounces fresh spinach, stems removed</p>
        <p>3/4 cup Chinese rice wine or dry sherry</p>
        <p>3/4 cup dry white wine</p>
        <p>1/4 cup reduced-sodium soy sauce</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon hot chili oil  1 1/2 tablespoons coarsely chopped Chinese black beans (available at Asian markets or specialty food stores)  2 tablespoons finely chopped cilantro leaves and stems  2 tablespoons plus 1 teaspoon toasted sesame oil  3 quarter-size pieces of ginger, smashed  1 large clove garlic, peeled and smashed</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon sugar  1 1/2 to 2 pounds skinless, boneless salmon fillets, cut into four portions  1 small red onion, peeled and sliced thin.</p>
        <p>1. Blanch spinach in boiling water just until  leaves wilt, about 5 seconds. Drain, and plunge into ice water. Drain thoroughly.</p>
        <p>2. Combine rice wine, white wine, soy sauce, chili oil, black beans, cilantro, 2 tablespoons  sesame oil, ginger, garlic and sugar. Allow to stand for 5 to 10 minutes. Arrange salmon in a single layer in a shallow baking dish, and spoon marinade on top. Marinate for 20 minutes, turning once. Reserve  1/4 cup of  marinade, then drain fish, allowing some of  marinade ingredients to cling to fish. (Recipe may be prepared up to this point 24 hours ahead of time. Cover and refrigerate all ingredients. Bring to room temperature before using.)</p>
        <p>3. Place two inches of water in lower part of a large steamer. Bring to a boil. In top part of steamer, place a shallow heatproof plate at least 1 inch deep. Brush plate with remaining sesame oil. Spread spinach evenly on plate, and top with onion. Place fish on top, and drizzle each portion with about 1 tablespoon of reserved marinade.</p>
        <p>4. Place top part of steamer on lower part, and cover tightly. Steam fish over high heat until a knife tip inserted in thickest portion shows it to be medium-rare, 10 to 12 minutes for a 1-inch-thick fillet. To serve, place equal portions of fish and vegetables on four serving plates, and top each fillet with a bit of  juice from steaming plate.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>EATING WELL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
