<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fit of All Fits Brings Out True Contenders</title>
    <meta content="25FREE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/sports/25FREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Dolphins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Miami Dolphins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DF1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fit of All Fits Brings Out True Contenders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses New York Jets victory over Miami Dolphins; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before one of the greatest comebacks in National Football League history, there was one of the greatest tirades.</p>
        <p>With his flatline Jets trailing the Miami Dolphins, 23-7, at halftime on Monday night, Coach Al Groh had one of those out-of-body explosions in the locker room. He kicked chairs, tossed laundry baskets and spewed more foul language than Chris Rock during his standup routine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before one of the greatest comebacks in National Football League history, there was one of the greatest tirades.</p>
        <p>With his flatline Jets trailing the Miami Dolphins, 23-7, at halftime on Monday night, Coach Al Groh had one of those out-of-body explosions in the locker room. He kicked chairs, tossed laundry baskets and spewed more foul language than Chris Rock during his standup routine.</p>
        <p>Groh's anger was so intense that it shocked his players, who are used to seeing the coach's calm, measured demeanor.</p>
        <p>The outburst worked, shaking Jets players out of their slumber and propelling the team toward a 30-point scoring bonanza in the fourth quarter and a historic 40-37 comeback victory in overtime.</p>
        <p>With the astonishing victory, comes the prize. There are currently only three serious candidates for coach of the year: Minnesota's Dennis Green, whose Vikings are 7-0, Oakland's Jon Gruden, whose Raiders are 6-1, and Groh, whose Jets are 6-1.</p>
        <p>Green is the front-runner, but Groh is right behind him. Other than Green, no other coach has pushed all the right buttons as Groh has. The Jets have emerged as a serious Super Bowl contender, despite losing their head coach (Bill Parcells), their defensive coordinator (Bill Belichick) and their star wide receiver (Keyshawn Johnson).</p>
        <p>Groh's halftime chitchat was a perfect example of how almost everything he has done has worked. Six Jets players recounted what happened in the locker room. They said the coach walked into the locker room and immediately began screaming and wildly cursing. He chastised the team for sloppy play, not singling out an individual player, but blaming the entire team. He said the team had been prepared by the coaching staff for what Miami would do, and that it was the players' fault for not executing the game plan.</p>
        <p>''He said things you couldn't put in an R-rated movie,'' center Kevin Mawae after the game.</p>
        <p>Several minutes into his speech, Groh's face turned beet red, the players said, and he was screaming so loudly that spit was coming out his mouth. One player said he seriously thought Groh was going to have a seizure or heart attack.</p>
        <p>Then Groh started tossing objects. At one point, he was so angry he seemed to lose control. He kicked over a chair that tumbled several feet across the locker room and almost struck several players, the players said. Then Groh threw an industrial-sized laundry basket, slamming it into the ground.</p>
        <p>''There was some stuff thrown,'' receiver Wayne Chrebet said. ''He knows we were a lot better than that and it hurt him to watch us play that bad. Groh got us riled up.''</p>
        <p>Several players were in the trainer's room working on injuries, out of view of Groh. But they could still hear him screaming, along with the sound of chairs clanging and laundry baskets bouncing off the floor.</p>
        <p>''You're disgracing yourselves,'' one player quoted Groh as saying. ''You're disgracing this organization and you're disgracing the National Football League. The nation is watching a bunch of pathetic losers.''</p>
        <p>Another player contends that Groh said, ''If I could, right now, I would cut all of you.''</p>
        <p>Then, suddenly, you could hear a pin drop, and Groh left the room. The coach had caught the attention of his players.</p>
        <p>''Al went crazy on us and we deserved it,'' quarterback Vinny Testaverde said.</p>
        <p>Of course a good, old-fashioned tirade by a head coach is nothing new. But some tirades are better and more sincere than others. Groh's seemed to be heartfelt, high voltage and, most important, effective.</p>
        <p>When asked had he ever seen Groh that angry before, safety Victor Green said: ''Never. I have never seen him that fired up. I have never seen any head coach on any level that angry. But what he did worked.''</p>
        <p>Parcells had some good rants himself, but Groh's even surpassed some of those.</p>
        <p>For his part, Groh played down the situation.</p>
        <p>''I had a little performance at halftime that proved I didn't think it was over,'' he said. ''I sang them a lullaby at halftime.''</p>
        <p>Yeah, a lullaby with rap lyrics.</p>
        <p>But Groh's tirade was not the only one the night. In the first half Mawae brought together the entire offense, chastising his teammates for lackluster play.</p>
        <p>''I was livid,'' Mawae said.</p>
        <p>The reason professional football is perhaps the most emotional of all sports is because the game is so furious and intense and things can sway from disaster to ecstasy in a matter of minutes. Most of the time the role of a coach is overrated. It is the players who usually win or lose a game.</p>
        <p>But occasionally a coach, particularly a good one like Groh, can spark something and pull a team out of the abyss. Sometimes it's a smart play added to a game plan.</p>
        <p>Or sometimes it's the strength of his lungs.</p>
        <p>ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
