<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Click On, and Send Those Unwanted Pounds Off Into Cyberspace</title>
    <meta content="25DIET$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tufts University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nutrition Navigator (Web site)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freudenheim, Milt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E0DB103FF936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Click On, and Send Those Unwanted Pounds Off Into Cyberspace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIA MILLER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Online dieting regimens, so-called e-diets, promise to assist the overweight with weight-loss; Tufts University's Nutrition Navigator Web site rates free sources of e-diets; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE only way to lose weight is to eat fewer calories and exercise more.'' This was my father's diet mantra during our teenage years. Back then, my sister and I were inevitably seduced by the latest diet du jour -- Atkins, Beverly Hills, Scarsdale or our own Tab Soda Diet. Dad's slow and steady approach wasn't as much fun.</p>
        <p>He's right, of course. But as most everyone knows, eating fewer calories and exercising more is easier said than done.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE only way to lose weight is to eat fewer calories and exercise more.'' This was my father's diet mantra during our teenage years. Back then, my sister and I were inevitably seduced by the latest diet du jour -- Atkins, Beverly Hills, Scarsdale or our own Tab Soda Diet. Dad's slow and steady approach wasn't as much fun.</p>
        <p>He's right, of course. But as most everyone knows, eating fewer calories and exercising more is easier said than done.</p>
        <p>Online diets, also called e-diets, can make it easier. ''The potential is enormous,'' said Dr. Kelly Brownell, director of the Yale Center for Eating and Weight Disorders. ''There is the ability to serve more people at a fraction of the cost, 24-hour access and matching sources to the individual.''</p>
        <p>E-diets can be helpful in several ways, starting with convenience. Register at a site like Cyberdiet.com, and you can get everything from moral support in a chat room to the number of calories in a steamed frog leg (52.9), even at 3 a.m.</p>
        <p>Another factor is anonymity. The potential to feel embarrassed is reduced online, which means you might also be more honest. Instead of standing in front of a group of fellow dieters to get weighed, you can confess your caloric sins in cyberspace, where there are no names, just handles (and I don't mean love handles).</p>
        <p>If you'd like to join an e-diet site, one helpful place to look is the Nutrition Navigator, from the Tufts University Center on Nutrition (www.navigator.tufts.edu). It offers ratings and descriptions of the best nonprofit diet and nutrition Web sites along with links to those sites.</p>
        <p>The Nutrition Navigator's intent is to rate only the free sites. But several of them charge for some services. One such site is eFit.com, which offers diet plans that range from $69 to $199. And Nutrio.com has a ''Platinum'' upgrade, for those ''really committed to losing weight,'' at $99 a year.</p>
        <p>After registering at a site, you can usually fill out a questionnaire that asks about lifestyle, height and weight. Those factors are then used in compiling a customized meal plan. Many have a calculator for body mass index, a number derived from a formula based on weight and height. A figure of 18.5 to 25 is normal, 25 to 29 is overweight and above 30 indicates obesity.</p>
        <p>If you insist on trying out a fad diet, Cyberdiet.com's ''Diet Detective'' gives a rundown of the pros and cons of many of the latest popular diets.</p>
        <p>Dr. Louis Aronne, an obesity expert who runs the Comprehensive Weight Control Program at New York Presbyterian Hospital, warns of the need to ''stay away from the snake oil salesmen.'' Sites with testimonials or those that try to sell you a magic formula are better left alone. The easiest way to recognize a less credible weight-loss site is to consider whether its promises seem too good to be true. ''A safe rate of weight loss is one to two pounds a week,''  Dr. Aronne said. ''With anything more, you are not likely to keep the weight off.''</p>
        <p>Obesity has become such a serious health problem in America that the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute of the National Institutes of Health is getting into the act with a Web site called Aim for a Healthy Weight (www.nhlbi.nih.gov/index.htm). According to the site, more than half of all Americans, 97 million people, are overweight or obese.</p>
        <p>The site offers a section that helps assess  whether you are overweight and gives advice on picking a weight-loss program and information about nutrition labeling on foods. There is also a section for doctors on treating obesity.</p>
        <p>As for the next phase, ''There are many interesting possibilities as time goes on,'' Dr. Aronne said. ''Who knows, maybe in the future when you walk into a McDonald's, the global positioning system will notify a dietitian who can e-mail you on your Palm Pilot and suggest that you leave immediately.''</p>
        <p>Or it will notify my father.</p>
        <p>HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
