<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Loves to Swap. She Loves to Swap. Where's the Profit?</title>
    <meta content="25WHIT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Barter</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Barter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DE103FF936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1390" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Loves to Swap. She Loves to Swap. Where's the Profit?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trading all manner of second-hand goods over Internet thrives and grows; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH a sports card collection that fills his basement and a desire to refine it, Jeff Tidwell, a steelworker in Granite City, Ill., sees potential in swap sites on the Internet.</p>
        <p>''Trading is more fun than buying,'' said Mr. Tidwell, who, with only about 10 trades under his belt, is still a novice. ''It's worked out.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH a sports card collection that fills his basement and a desire to refine it, Jeff Tidwell, a steelworker in Granite City, Ill., sees potential in swap sites on the Internet.</p>
        <p>''Trading is more fun than buying,'' said Mr. Tidwell, who, with only about 10 trades under his belt, is still a novice. ''It's worked out.''</p>
        <p>Trading baseball cards and every manner of stuff has long appealed to people of all ages. As with many popular consumer pastimes, numerous Web sites are helping people pursue their hobbies online. But the challenge for swap sites, as with so many other Internet businesses, is how to turn them into moneymaking ventures.</p>
        <p>Internet analysts estimated that about $1 billion worth of secondhand goods would be exchanged online this year, but pure swapping -- where people with haves and wants are brought together for a simple exchange of goods -- is proving a difficult-to-impossible format on which to build a lucrative business.</p>
        <p>Unlike eBay, the model several companies have used in setting up their revenue stream based on transactions, swap-site entrepreneurs quickly found it hard to profit from trading where value is low or tied to arbitrary opinions of worth.</p>
        <p>Some 20 consumer-to-consumer swapping sites opened on the Internet earlier this year, according to e-commerce analysts, with about five of those sites coming to the forefront. And even those that have found some success have adapted their model in an effort to make money. Some have chosen to focus on specific areas of trading, like music and entertainment, while others are experimenting with pricing models or eliminating trading fees to attract users.</p>
        <p>''Clearly the existing swapping players have not figured out exactly the business they are going to end up in,'' said Mark Gambale, an e-commerce analyst with Gomez Advisors in Lincoln, Mass. ''What they've found is that existing transacting fees from swapping will not keep them in business for the long term.''</p>
        <p>Swap.com, which is now Spun.com, is a good example. Swap went on the Internet the day after Christmas last year. That was no coincidence, said Bill Keenan, who has served as chief executive for both companies. Swap reasoned that it would be a great time to open such a site because people would have unwanted gifts that they would wish to trade.</p>
        <p>But within two months they saw trouble, Mr. Keenan said. ''We noticed that there were three things that were a problem,'' he said. ''Ultimately, one party didn't trust the other party to ship the goods. The second thing was neither party trusted the other party that they were going to ship good goods. The third was we didn't involve the age-old thing that has been used for years -- U.S. dollars.''</p>
        <p>For example, he said, is a bike worth 13 CD's or 14 CD's? And though they had originally thought of charging some transaction fee, they decided against it, Mr. Keenan said.</p>
        <p>Swap, which had been intended for youths, soon found itself looking for a new model. It merged with Spun.com, an online music exchange that offers traders immediate credit for the items they are swapping, and refined its focus to swapping digital entertainment items like CD's, DVD's and electronic games.</p>
        <p>When items are traded, Spun.com's software immediately declares a value for them; then those dollars can be used to trade any item in its inventory. Spun.com serves both as a clearinghouse and as a warehouse, sending swappers the items they want and a postage-paid mailer.</p>
        <p>''Swap doesn't work,'' Mr. Keenan said. ''We recognized that early on.''</p>
        <p>But at SwitcHouse, which, with more than two million items listed, is considered one of the largest personal swapping sites, developers would disagree. Although they eliminated trading fees in September, announcing ''lifetime free trading,'' they continue to think there are profits to be made.</p>
        <p>Arra Yerganian, the chief executive at SwitcHouse, said that he believed the company's unique ''click to list'' cataloging system, which enables swappers to simply click on the items they have or want, provided an easy-to-use venue that would continue to be popular with traders. But he said that SwitcHouse was not trying to be all things to all people.</p>
        <p>The company is focusing its efforts on attracting men 18 to 24, the idea being that they are playing video games at a rapid clip and will want to trade them when they tire of them.</p>
        <p>Currently, about 70 percent of the transactions on the site are trades and the rest are sales, Mr. Yerganian said. Revenue comes from a 10 percent fee on sales, as well as from advertising.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Yerganian is also building on the site's potential profits by eventually selling data to other companies. The plan is not to sell specifics about user behavior, but about their wants and haves. For example, he said, the company already has 15,000 people listed who want a Sony PlayStation 2 when it comes out Oct. 26.</p>
        <p>''That's the kind of information Sony would want,'' said Mr. Yerganian, who has a video-game marketing background.</p>
        <p>Bob Bahramipour, a vice president for business development at SwitcHouse, described the movement among various sites as ''putting your bets down in different parts of the business.'' SwitcHouse is betting that it can profit from selling information that can be gleaned from people's postings. Spun is moving more toward a bricks-and-mortar approach, warehousing people's goods and actually reselling traded items. Another top player, WebSwap, is offering a variety of pricing systems. It recently added a format called ''garage sale,'' where prices of unsold goods go down every hour.</p>
        <p>To some extent, e-commerce analysts said, swap sites have had to react to eBay's purchase of Half.com, which, with eight million listings of items at half price, cuts into the territory of these various pricing models.</p>
        <p>''The consumer definition of swapping is much broader than a narrow transaction,'' said Jan Gullett, the chief executive of WebSwap. ''We started with a notion of starting a local community-based marketplace. We define swapping broadly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gullett said that about a quarter of the transactions on the site were goods for goods and that the rest were sales. Ultimately, he noted, his site is about dynamic pricing and creating new concepts for selling.</p>
        <p>IF making money is proving tricky for swap site developers, industry advisers said they believe the traffic can support at least some of the swap sites.</p>
        <p>''I think people are on the strong end of the frugality scale,'' said Vernon Keenan, who operates a market research firm in San Francisco specializing in e-commerce (and is not related to Bill Keenan of Spun.com).  ''Some people are excited to get value out of a good that they otherwise would have disposed of.''</p>
        <p>Manny Rabara, SwitcHouse's top swapper turned employee (he was hired as a graphic artist), wouldn't argue with that. He has completed almost 700 swaps since early this year, and his goal is to hit 1,000 before the year is out.</p>
        <p>''Just today, with someone in Argentina, I gave away my 98 Degrees CD for a soundtrack -- I think from 'The Fabulous Baker Boys,' '' Mr. Rabara said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>He traded a couple of CD's for a videotape of ''The Little Mermaid'' for his 2-year-old daughter, and he's working on obtaining a trade to get ''The Little Mermaid II: Return to the Sea.''</p>
        <p>''I'm what you call a swapaholic,'' he said. ''It's my form of day trading. I do it all day long.''</p>
        <p>He even has strategies for obtaining items he doesn't want so he can trade them for things he does.</p>
        <p>''Right now on my list there are 20,000 things I want,'' Mr. Rabara said. ''I'm going for a Palm Pilot.''</p>
        <p>In fact, he confided that he was hoping for one that's Web-enabled.</p>
        <p>''Then I can even do this walking around the grocery store,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
