<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Ridicules Gore's Proposals for Tax Cuts</title>
    <meta content="25BUSH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tennessee</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Knoxville (Tenn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wisconsin</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Milwaukee (Wis)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jacksonville (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Jacksonville</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin/Milwaukee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee/Knoxville</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5DA1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Ridicules Gore's Proposals for Tax Cuts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>JACKSONVILLE, Fla., Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush, campaigning in Chicago suburb and in Knoxville, Tenn, mocks Vice Pres Al Gore's tax cutting proposal and touts his own as better; begins day in Milwaukee, Wis, and ends it in Jacksonville, Fla; excerpt from remarks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas sought today to make a mockery of his Democratic opponent's proposal for tax cuts, portraying it as a loopy marvel of convolution and asserting that his own, vastly more expensive plan was better.</p>
        <p>In remarks in Knoxville, Tenn., this afternoon and in a suburb of Chicago this morning, Mr. Bush said the conditions and qualifications layered into Vice President Al Gore's ''targeted'' tax cuts would exclude too many taxpayers and give the government too much control over people's lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas sought today to make a mockery of his Democratic opponent's proposal for tax cuts, portraying it as a loopy marvel of convolution and asserting that his own, vastly more expensive plan was better.</p>
        <p>In remarks in Knoxville, Tenn., this afternoon and in a suburb of Chicago this morning, Mr. Bush said the conditions and qualifications layered into Vice President Al Gore's ''targeted'' tax cuts would exclude too many taxpayers and give the government too much control over people's lives.</p>
        <p>''Let me ask you a question,'' Mr. Bush said to several hundred people  inside a school in Arlington Heights, Ill. ''How many of you own hybrid electric-gasoline engine vehicles?'' His question was met by laughter.</p>
        <p>''That's one of the criterion necessary to receive tax relief,'' he added, referring to an element of Mr. Gore's environment and energy plan that proposes to reward people who buy such vehicles with one-time tax credits of $1,000 to $6,000.</p>
        <p>''How many of you own a rooftop photo-voltaic system?'' Mr. Bush then asked, ridiculing Mr. Gore's suggested tax credit for people who put solar panels on the roofs of their houses or businesses. ''If you had one, you'd get tax relief.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was selectively homing in on some of the more obscure tax cuts that Mr. Gore has proposed, and he seemed to revel mischievously in doing so. His frisky mood also spilled over into a warning that he issued to President Clinton about getting involved in the campaign.</p>
        <p>Answering a question that alluded to Mr. Clinton's affair with a White House intern, he said, ''I'm not running against President Clinton.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush stumbled over his next phrases and time references. ''That's a chapter -- the last chapter -- of the 20th, 20th, the 21st century that most of us would rather forget,'' he continued, then corrected himself.</p>
        <p>''The last chapter of the 20th century,'' he said. ''This is the first chapter of the 21st century. I don't think there's a lot of politics to be gained by talking about him. As a matter of fact, I think most Americans would rather move on, and that's what I'm going to do.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''If he decides he can't help himself, and gets out there and starts campaigning against me, the shadow returns. I may say something in defense of my record.''</p>
        <p>During a long day that began in Milwaukee and ended here in Jacksonville, Mr. Bush's itinerary reflected both the significant successes and nagging worries of his campaign.</p>
        <p>In Wisconsin and Tennessee, he was campaigning in states that were expected to tilt Democratic but have not done so. But Mr. Bush has not built the kind of lead in Florida that many political analysts envisioned, and a rally in Jacksonville tonight was to be followed on Wednesday by a bus trip through the state.</p>
        <p>President Clinton, who defeated Mr. Bush's father, former President Bush, in 1992, also seemed to hover over the Jacksonville event. In introducing Mr. Bush, his brother, Gov. Jeb Bush of the Florida, talked of the need to elect ''someone of integrity, someone of honor and decency.''</p>
        <p>And then the Texas governor said he and his brother ''were raised right.'' He added, ''We were raised by two parents who taught us to tell the truth.'' With that statement he may have been tying together and tweaking Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore, and he went on to deride Mr. Gore as ''a man prone to exaggeration.''</p>
        <p>In an interview tonight on the ABC News program ''Nightline,'' Mr. Bush said he would welcome -- and could capitalize on -- a decision by Mr. Gore to use Mr. Clinton in his campaign.</p>
        <p>''It would remind people that my opponent was not standing on his own,'' Mr. Bush said. ''There must be something amiss, if after having stiff-armed a president so to speak, all of a sudden they urge him to come back in the waning days of the campaign.''</p>
        <p>All day, Mr. Bush, who is grappling with Mr. Gore for undecided swing voters, invited ''open-minded Democrats'' and independents to support him, and in Arlington Heights, he cast himself as a practical centrist in  answers to questions about abortion and gun control.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bush opposes abortion in most cases, he said, ''This is an issue where good people can disagree and still be allies.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush's chosen focus was on taxes. He is proposing a sweeping cut of an estimated $1.3 trillion over 10 years, and it reduces the rates for taxpayers in every bracket. The largest savings, in raw dollar terms, go to the wealthiest Americans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is proposing a cut of $500 billion that principally applies to people in households with annual incomes under $100,000 and is largely delivered through tax credits and deductions for certain spending.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said the proposal was too selective and intricate.</p>
        <p>But Kym Spell, a spokeswoman for the Gore campaign, said, ''Maybe a $500 billion tax cut for average working families is too complicated for George W. Bush, but most Americans understand it.''</p>
        <p>In His Own Words</p>
        <p>GEORGE W. BUSH  Remarks yesterday at the Thomas Middle School in Arlington Heights, Ill.:</p>
        <p>''People know we can do better in Washington. People in this state know that there's a better way. People know that we can lift this nation's spirits and achieve what we want to achieve. But I'll tell you what else I hear: that people realize there is a philosophical difference between me and my opponent. There's a big difference between what we believe. The best way to summarize it is this way: I'm running against a man who trusts Washington, D.C., to make decisions on behalf of Illinois folks. He may try to hide from that philosophy, but that's what he believes, if you listen to the policies.</p>
        <p>After all, he's a person who wants to increase the size of the federal government, the largest we've seen since the 60's. He wants to increase the size and scope of the federal government more than Walter Mondale and Michael Dukakis combined. That's pretty big. He wants to increase the size of the federal government three times more than President Clinton did.</p>
        <p>That's a difference of opinion. Perhaps the best way to focus on that difference is to talk about tax relief. The best way to show that I trust the people and he trusts the government is to talk about my tax relief plan.</p>
        <p>First, it's important to understand there's a surplus, but the surplus, the projected surplus, will exist after budgets have grown, after, over the next 10 years, the baseline of the budgets are increased and there's still money, which leads me to believe that the people aren't under-taxed. They're overtaxed.</p>
        <p>The people of this country pay more in federal, state and local taxes than they do in food, in housing, in clothing. I want you to think about that. We got a tax burden on the working people of this country that is larger than what it takes for the basic necessities to live. That's not right. The percentage of G.D.P. of our taxes is the highest it's been since World War II. ''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
