<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watch These Mice Nibble Through Red Tape</title>
    <meta content="25GOVT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4DC103FF936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1385" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watch These Mice Nibble Through Red Tape</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN JR.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Citizens and corporations transact business of all types with federal government through governmental Web sites; government administers about 20,000 sites, containing 100 million pages; article describes 'dot-gov', expanding realm of interacting with government through Internet; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the Web pages of the Occupational Health and Safety Administration, a worker worried about safety on the job can file a complaint with little more than a click of the mouse.</p>
        <p>On the same site, an employer can use custom-built software to make sure that the company is complying with federal safety regulations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the Web pages of the Occupational Health and Safety Administration, a worker worried about safety on the job can file a complaint with little more than a click of the mouse.</p>
        <p>On the same site, an employer can use custom-built software to make sure that the company is complying with federal safety regulations.</p>
        <p>At Internet sites like this one, the world of dot-com meets the less familiar but expanding world of dot-gov, providing places where citizens and corporations can do business with the government.</p>
        <p>It is a world of opportunity for the government and the people it likes to think of as its customers, both of whom can save time and money by doing business online.</p>
        <p>But is all this online activity truly cutting red tape, or just converting it into electronic streamers and strewing them around a new, virtual bureaucracy?</p>
        <p>''Dot-gov isn't keeping pace with dot-com,'' said Patricia B. Wood of the National Partnership for Reinventing Government, a White House project to improve efficiency in government. ''Citizens can't find what they don't know to look for.''</p>
        <p>In all, the government has about 20,000 Web sites with 100 million pages, but many are arranged in hierarchies that mirror the bureaucratic structures of agencies, rather than by functions that citizens and businesses are most interested in.</p>
        <p>Information and activities are often duplicated on different sites, which probably should be expected from a government that has 12 agencies overseeing food safety under 35 different laws.</p>
        <p>So the explosion of dot-gov activities, which used to be little more than a way of publishing government documents but has become a way of doing business with the government, seems to be creating business models -- and opportunities.</p>
        <p>There are at least three models for providing government services via the Web.</p>
        <p>One simply turns paperwork into interactive Web pages, letting users go online to obtain and fill out forms.</p>
        <p>A second model is creating opportunities for consultants, software designers and other private companies that consult and often join as partners with government entities to offer online services.</p>
        <p>The third model, not yet common but seen by many as the ideal, would let users choose the most convenient way to gain access to government Web sites. For example, a person could go to a preferred portal -- Yahoo, for instance -- and find both government and other information.</p>
        <p>No matter which model prevails, it already seems clear that the public is demanding more and more government services online. At least two out of three adults with online access have conducted an electronic transaction with the government at least once, according to a recent study commissioned by the National Information Consortium, which provides government agencies with services like managing online portals and software applications. Almost one in five adults who use the Internet have conducted an online transaction with the government in the last 30 days.</p>
        <p>''Citizens and businesses are more satisfied with their e-government experience than with traditional government service delivery,'' according to the consortium's report, which was conducted by the Momentum Research Group of Cunningham Communication in Austin, Tex.</p>
        <p>Some of the ways people work with the government online are obvious, others less so.</p>
        <p>This year, about 33 million taxpayers filed their 1999 returns online. The office of student financial aid at the Department of Education processed more than 670,000 applications online during the 1998-99 application cycle. And about 34,000 people filled out census forms online.</p>
        <p>Other examples are less well known.</p>
        <p>Nine federal district and bankruptcy courts allow people to initiate cases or file pleadings electronically. And the Geological Survey recently became the first federal agency to fully automate its hiring process.</p>
        <p>On the Small Business Administration's ''business adviser'' Web page, companies and employees can obtain a Bureau of Export Administration application for licenses to export certain computers, register trademarks with the Patent and Trademark Office, apply for citizenship with the Immigration and Naturalization Service, apply for financing from the Export-Import Bank, apply for a pilot's license from the Federal Aviation Administration or register with Selective Service.</p>
        <p>Even people without access to the Internet at their homes and offices are able to find government services online, often using kiosks set up in places like shopping malls.</p>
        <p>A terminal at a Safeway store in northeast Washington -- one of thousands of kiosks planned for communities, both rural and urban, where Internet access has been slow in coming -- provides more than 150 federal, state and local government services in a touch-screen format. An organization called the Urban Cool Network plans to put up more than 3,200 kiosks in shopping malls in urban areas where there are few home computers. GS Planet, another private organization, plans to put them in train and bus stations.</p>
        <p>Government agencies are also setting up kiosks. An Immigration and Naturalization Service kiosk at a supermarket in East Dallas logged more than 22,000 uses in its first month, according to the National Partnership for Reinventing Government.</p>
        <p>But there are concerns. At least two-thirds of Internet users doubt that the government will keep records confidential. ''Trust is the most critical issue facing the adoption of e-government,'' the report for the information consortium said.</p>
        <p>Researchers at Brown University who surveyed more than 1,800 government Web sites, most of them operated by the states, found that only 5 percent of them display information about their security policy, and only 7 percent have a statement of privacy policy.</p>
        <p>Even so, a survey by Dell Computer found that 90 percent of the public would like to obtain their driver's licenses and license plates online, and 70 percent would like to pay traffic tickets that way.</p>
        <p>In Virginia, the Department of Motor Vehicles is moving in that direction. Six hundred pages on its Web site allow people to do almost anything they used to complain about standing in line to do.</p>
        <p>THAT is a classic example of the first model of online government: simply replacing a line at the motor vehicles agency with an online experience. But what about a more complex interaction, like dealing with the Environmental Protection Agency? There are ways to file reports online, but it is never going to be as simple as renewing a driver's license.</p>
        <p>This is where the private companies have stepped in. EHSmanager.com, a new company based in Overland Park, Kan., is a model of that approach. The company calls itself the first online, one-stop shop for environmental, health and safety information and management services.</p>
        <p>In some cases, states have joined with private companies to provide online services. The National Information Consortium, for example, typically sets up local subsidiaries to contract with a state, develop an Internet portal and make information, applications and other transactions available. In return, the company takes a share of the fees charged for certain transactions.</p>
        <p>In another case, FirstGov, a federal government Web portal, is being financed through a foundation created by Eric Brewer, one of the founders of the search engine company Inktomi. It is supposed to allow users to search every federal Web page.</p>
        <p>But FirstGov also plans to allow other Web pages to use and display its content, as long as they post a certification on their sites and adhere to a set of conditions, like publishing the data ''as is,'' eschewing advertising on the pages that contain federal information and protecting users' privacy.</p>
        <p>That is a sign that the third model of e-government is taking hold: letting Web users go to their favorite portal, whether Yahoo, their college Web page, America Online or their stockbroker's page, and keeping government and personal information together in one place.</p>
        <p>''Here's where the lines between government and the private sector begin to blur,'' according to a report by Tom Unruh, an  analyst at the National Governors Association. ''From the citizen's point of view, it's not important to go to the state Web site to handle their business with the government.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
