<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boiling Down the Old Broadway Melodies</title>
    <meta content="25SONG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/arts/25SONG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loesser, Frank (1910-69)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walton, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Noll, Christiane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DE1531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boiling Down the Old Broadway Melodies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews concert tribute to Frank Loesser at Alice Tully Hall, part of Lincoln Center's American Songbook series; photo of Jim Walton and Christiane Noll (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Lincoln Center announced its American Songbook series three years ago, its plan to have an informal repertory company of America's finest pre-rock singers perform popular standards with a full orchestra sounded irresistible, if a bit vague. The laudable goal was to devote the same attention and expertise to popular music that Lincoln Center had brought to jazz. If successful, the series's main concerts at Alice Tully Hall would be glorious musical convocations that illuminated pop history in new ways and built bridges between the past and present.</p>
        <p>Sadly, it hasn't turned out that way. So far the concerts, although reasonably entertaining, have been far from glorious. Many big-name singers have shown up, and the orchestra has played decently enough. But from the beginning, the concerts have played like deluxe, formulaic cabaret tributes massaging the nostalgia of an old-guard theater audience in dully predictable ways.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Lincoln Center announced its American Songbook series three years ago, its plan to have an informal repertory company of America's finest pre-rock singers perform popular standards with a full orchestra sounded irresistible, if a bit vague. The laudable goal was to devote the same attention and expertise to popular music that Lincoln Center had brought to jazz. If successful, the series's main concerts at Alice Tully Hall would be glorious musical convocations that illuminated pop history in new ways and built bridges between the past and present.</p>
        <p>Sadly, it hasn't turned out that way. So far the concerts, although reasonably entertaining, have been far from glorious. Many big-name singers have shown up, and the orchestra has played decently enough. But from the beginning, the concerts have played like deluxe, formulaic cabaret tributes massaging the nostalgia of an old-guard theater audience in dully predictable ways.</p>
        <p>It didn't have to be that way. As the City Center's dazzling Encores! series has proven with its concert resurrections of vintage musical comedies, the past can be brought thrillingly alive. By contrast, attending the American Songbook series has often felt like visiting a museum where the same old Impressionists are exhibited the same old way. And in its season-opening concert on Friday, the series hit rock bottom with an ill-conceived, lifeless celebration of the work of Frank Loesser.</p>
        <p>In dreaming up ''Heart and Soul: The Songs of Frank Loesser,'' someone had the dreadful idea of telescoping four Loesser shows -- ''Where's Charley?,'' ''Guys and Dolls,'' ''The Most Happy Fella'' and ''How to Succeed in Business Without Really Trying'' -- into the concert equivalent of Reader's Digest Condensed Books. Or to put it more accurately, the Cliff Notes for those condensed books. That meant not only having a main character from each show tell its story in rushed, hard-to-follow blocks of narrative exposition but also abbreviating some of the songs by omitting second and third verses.</p>
        <p>The unfortunate narrators had the impossible task of telling the stories in character as though they were remembering events of long ago, then re-enacting those events. Although the 11 performers sang professionally, the excruciating self-consciousness of the format precluded any possibility of dramatic spontaneity. In one number after another, the director Gabriel Barre herded the performers into contorted, arthritic tableaus that made you wince at the artificiality of it all.</p>
        <p>Although Loesser's lyrics showed a fantastic ear for American comic vernacular, his ironic wise-guy humor failed to register here except in the most cartoonish ways. The robust pop arias from ''The Most Happy Fella,'' while competently sung by Christine Andreas, Shuler Hensley (who played Tony as a buffoonish caricature) and Tom Wopat, lacked passion. The atmosphere was so deadly that even the sporadic attempts of the singer Lillias White to inject some jazzy playfulness into the proceedings thudded against a wall of tension.</p>
        <p>So where is the American Songbook series to go from here? Wherever that may be, it has to re-discover the joy and humor in the music it is celebrating and to dispense with the starch and solemnity once and for all.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
