<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial Real Estate; Redeveloping Space to Keep Manufacturing Jobs</title>
    <meta content="25REAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/nyregion/25REAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greenpoint Manufacturing and Design Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siwolop, Sana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sweeny, J David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7D71531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial Real Estate; Redeveloping Space to Keep Manufacturing Jobs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANA SIWOLOP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Siwolop, Sana</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commercial Real Estate column on Greenpoint Manufacturing and Design Center Development Corp opening new manufacturing center in Greenpoint section of Brooklyn; organization head J David Sweeny comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Greenpoint Manufacturing and Design Center opened in 1994, supporters of manufacturing in New York City cheered: what had once been a decrepit rope factory on the Brooklyn waterfront had been turned into a low-cost home for light manufacturing companies and artisans.</p>
        <p>When the center opened, the nonprofit development organization behind the project, the Greenpoint Manufacturing and Design Center Development Corporation, said it was looking at other old industrial sites to renovate in an effort to stem the migration of manufacturing jobs from the city. Now the organization, which typically redevelops properties that private developers might find unprofitable, is starting to translate those intentions into reality. Last month, it opened a second manufacturing center in Brooklyn and announced plans to develop seven more projects in the next three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Greenpoint Manufacturing and Design Center opened in 1994, supporters of manufacturing in New York City cheered: what had once been a decrepit rope factory on the Brooklyn waterfront had been turned into a low-cost home for light manufacturing companies and artisans.</p>
        <p>When the center opened, the nonprofit development organization behind the project, the Greenpoint Manufacturing and Design Center Development Corporation, said it was looking at other old industrial sites to renovate in an effort to stem the migration of manufacturing jobs from the city. Now the organization, which typically redevelops properties that private developers might find unprofitable, is starting to translate those intentions into reality. Last month, it opened a second manufacturing center in Brooklyn and announced plans to develop seven more projects in the next three years.</p>
        <p>According to J. David Sweeny, the corporation's chief executive, the new centers will give the city up to 1.5 million square feet of new manufacturing space, enough to help create 2,500 to 3,500 manufacturing jobs.</p>
        <p>The group's newest manufacturing center is in an 80,000-square-foot building at 810 Humboldt Street in Greenpoint. The two-story building, which was built in 1961, had been used as a warehouse and bowling alley but was largely unused for the last three years.</p>
        <p>Last May, Mr. Sweeny's group bought the building for $4.3 million from the Commodore Manufacturing Corporation, a Brooklyn-based distributor of Christmas ornaments. Then his group began a $2 million renovation to prepare it for tenants by mid-August.</p>
        <p>The building had a lot going for it, said Curtis Cravens, the director of development and government relations at the Mr. Sweeny's organization. It was in sound structural shape, and it is close to a number of important transportation points, like the Queens-Midtown Tunnel, as well as to two subway stations, Nassau Avenue and Greenpoint Avenue, both seven blocks away.</p>
        <p>The inside of the building, however, was another story. According to Mr. Sweeny, it was essentially open space that needed to be subdivided into 12 smaller spaces. But the interior also needed new electrical wiring, heating, ventilation and windows, as well as new interior doors and walls.</p>
        <p>All 12 of the building's spaces, ranging from 4,000 to 20,000 square feet, have been leased, to 10 woodworking concerns and one garment company that makes quilts and curtains. There will also be space, Mr. Cravens said, for a services shop where tenants will be able to use equipment like spray painting booths.</p>
        <p>One of the tenants on Humboldt Street is a woodworking business owned by Weber Roberts and Brooks Crane, a husband-and-wife team that makes custom cabinetry and furniture. Mr. Roberts said they are paying an annual rent of $9 a square foot for 4,350 square feet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts and Ms. Crane used to lease space for their business at 60 Broadway Street in Williamsburg.  But they lost their space on Sept. 4. Their former landlord, Mr. Roberts said, ''was trying to get high-tech companies into the building at $30 a square foot; we were paying $6 a square foot.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeny said his organization decided to gear the Humboldt street building to woodworkers after receiving numerous phone calls from local artisans -- mostly in Manhattan and Brooklyn -- who were either losing their work spaces or who could not find new space.</p>
        <p>''The screams came the loudest and with the most frequency from the woodworkers, so we decided to solve their problems first,'' he said. He added that rents at the property were in the $6-to-$9 range, which is 30 percent to 50 percent less than similar space in Manhattan and 10 percent less than the market rate in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Woodworking concerns and artisans also account for the tenants at the first manufacturing center that Mr. Sweeny's organization opened in Brooklyn, in 1994. That building, at 1155 Manhattan Avenue, is being converted into a co-op for its 72 tenants, who together employ 500 people.</p>
        <p>Eventually, Mr. Sweeny's organization hopes to help other types of manufacturers at the centers that it is still developing.</p>
        <p>The group is in negotiations on two of the properties. One of them is a four-story, 115,000-square-foot building at 37-24 24th Street in Long Island City. According to Mr. Sweeny, it would provide ideal space for garment manufacturers. The second property is a 65,000-square-foot building at 191 Harrison Avenue in Williamsburg that the organization hopes to renovate for Arlington Press, a local company that makes pharmaceutical insert labels.</p>
        <p>The Greenpoint nonprofit group has acquired, or is in contract on, five other properties, Mr. Sweeny said.</p>
        <p>While he could not disclose details on one of them, because of a confidentiality agreement, he said that the four other properties were a vacant 65,000-square-foot former candy factory at 132 Harrison Place in East Williamsburg, scheduled to be ready for occupancy by small food manufacturers by the end of the year; an 80,000-square-foot, mill-style building at 37 Greenpoint Avenue whose tenant base has not yet been determined; a 24,000-square-foot vacant loft building at 7 St. Nicholas Avenue in East Williamsburg that will probably be used for industrial tenants; and a 70,000-square-foot industrial building at 130 North Fourth Street in the Williamsburg area that will be marketed to upscale food producers and distributors who are looking for adjacent retail space.</p>
        <p>Kathryn Wylde, the president of the New York City Investment Fund, founded by Henry R. Kravis, the financier, to invest in projects to promote the city's economy, said that last month her fund gave Mr. Sweeny's group a $1 million loan.</p>
        <p>''We're generally not a real estate investor, but we see our investment in them as having a real multiplier effect,'' she said. ''They are going to create the infrastructure that is going create hundreds of businesses, which, in turn, are going to employ thousands of people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
