<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Subway Series Ratings Need Lift</title>
    <meta content="25SAND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/sports/25SAND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001031T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fox Entertainment Group Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4DD1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Subway Series Ratings Need Lift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article contends that barring miraculous surge of viewing nationwide, World Series between New York Yankees and New York Mets will most likely become lowest-rated World Series in history (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barring a miraculous surge of viewing nationwide, the Subway Series will most likely become the lowest-rated World Series in history, falling behind the Yankees-Padres matchup of 1998.</p>
        <p>A World Series between two New York teams was not expected to post scintillating ratings, but the results for Games 1 and 2 are below expectations at Fox.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barring a miraculous surge of viewing nationwide, the Subway Series will most likely become the lowest-rated World Series in history, falling behind the Yankees-Padres matchup of 1998.</p>
        <p>A World Series between two New York teams was not expected to post scintillating ratings, but the results for Games 1 and 2 are below expectations at Fox.</p>
        <p>The 12.0 rating, with a 21 share, is 18 percent below the 14.6/25 generated for the first two games of the 1999 World Series by NBC last season when the Yankees played the Atlanta Braves. (Each rating point equals about 1.02 million television households. The share is the percentage of televisions in use that are tuned to a particular program.)</p>
        <p>Unless markets nationwide begin viewing in droves thus far unseen, the battle for New York by the Yankees and the Mets will generate a lower rating than the 14.1 of two years ago.</p>
        <p>''I don't believe the ratings reflect the real number of people watching Saturday and Sunday nights,'' said David Hill, the chairman of the Fox Television Sports Group, who voiced the dissatisfaction felt by networks about the methodology employed by Nielsen Media Research to determine the ratings. ''But the good thing is, advertisers know that, too.''</p>
        <p>The falling World Series ratings cap a year in which some major sports events suffered major ratings declines. The National Basketball Association finals fell 18 percent to an 11.7. The final game of the National Collegiate Athletic Association men's basketball tournament also took an 18 percent tumble, to a 14.1.</p>
        <p>The Summer Olympics from Sydney, Australia, stumbled even further, posting a 36 percent decline to a 13.8 from their performance in Atlanta -- and 21 percent below NBC's own optimistic projections.</p>
        <p>What's going on? Experts point to predictable reasons like the proliferation of channels on cable and satellite television and the exploding popularity of the Internet. Despite lower ratings, sports remain popular with advertisers because they generally deliver young male viewers.</p>
        <p>''Monday Night Football,'' ABC's premier sports property, remains a potent advertising vehicle despite declining ratings. But even the promotional boost of adding Dennis Miller as a commentator in the booth has not prevented the program's 7 percent ratings slide, to a 12.6.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the interest in sports has declined, but we can get sports in more ways and more varieties than we used to,'' said Stacey Lynn Koerner, the vice president for broadcast research of TN Media, an advertising-buying agency. ''We're also in a world where everything is hyped to the nth degree, which makes it harder for these events to stand out.''</p>
        <p>Amid declining ratings, networks must satisfy themselves with improving demographics, the statistical tools they use to woo advertisers. Fox is pleased that ratings for men 18 to 34 years old are up by 6 percent from last year's World Series and by 12 percent from 1998.</p>
        <p>But another factor bedeviling sports ratings is how sharply lower the final national Nielsen ratings have been this year than the preliminary ''overnight ratings'' that measure viewing only in 49 major markets that make up 66 percent of the TV households in the United States.  For Game 2 of the World Series, the 15.2 overnight rating sank by 17 percent to a 12.6 national rating. For the same game last season, the overnight fell by 5 percent to a 15.0 national rating.</p>
        <p>Even if the enormous 42.1 rating in the New York market skewed the overnight rating, Fox is dissatisfied that Nielsen Media Research adequately measures sports viewing. ''The national rating looks as if nobody outside the metered markets is watching,'' Hill said. ''It's mathematically impossible.''</p>
        <p>For the N.B.A. finals this past season, the 13.8 overnight rating slipped by 16 percent to an 11.6 national Nielsen rating In 1999, the overnight-to-national drop was only 4 percent. ''It's not rational that this is happening at this time, in this year, across the board,'' said Ken Schanzer, the president of NBC Sports.</p>
        <p>The N.C.A.A. men's tournament is a rarity that has seen its national rating increase from the overnights, reflecting its strong appeal to rural viewers. But last season, it dipped from a 14.4 overnight to a 14.1 national rating. In 1997, though, the 18.0 overnight jumped to an 18.9 national.</p>
        <p>Jack Loftus, a spokesman for Nielsen, said it has done nothing different in selecting its sample of households for the national rating that would cause the declines.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES  Correction:  October 31, 2000, Tuesday  An article on Wednesday about a decline in television ratings for sports events misstated the figure and the change for this year's National Basketball Association finals on NBC. The rating was 11.6, not 11.7; it was a 2.7 percent increase from last year's, not an 18 percent drop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 31, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article on Wednesday about a decline in television ratings for sports events misstated the figure and the change for this year's National Basketball Association finals on NBC. The rating was 11.6, not 11.7; it was a 2.7 percent increase from last year's, not an 18 percent drop.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
