<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Woman Long Dutiful, At Last Able to Speak Out</title>
    <meta content="25SALA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/arts/25SALA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Masterpiece Theater's American Collection (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cora Unashamed (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2DF1531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Woman Long Dutiful, At Last Able to Speak Out</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews Cora Unashamed, television drama that is first in Masterpiece Theater's new American Collection series, which draws from American literature rather than English or European (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''Cora Unashamed'' the image of dried, brown leaves appears repeatedly to remind viewers that death is in the air, literally and spiritually. The music by Patrice Rushen often controls the emotional calibration.</p>
        <p>These dense atmospherics dominate this adaptation of a Langston Hughes short story, the first in ''Masterpiece Theater'' 's new American Collection series, which draws from American literature rather than English or European. Sometimes it feels as if there isn't enough oxygen for the characters to breathe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''Cora Unashamed'' the image of dried, brown leaves appears repeatedly to remind viewers that death is in the air, literally and spiritually. The music by Patrice Rushen often controls the emotional calibration.</p>
        <p>These dense atmospherics dominate this adaptation of a Langston Hughes short story, the first in ''Masterpiece Theater'' 's new American Collection series, which draws from American literature rather than English or European. Sometimes it feels as if there isn't enough oxygen for the characters to breathe.</p>
        <p>Set in a small town in Iowa during the Depression, the story follows its heroine Cora's conversion from dutiful repression to expressed outrage, when her white employer's small-minded righteousness results in tragedy.</p>
        <p>The scenario is strangely muted on the question of race after raising the issue at the outset. In the opening scene, Cora has given birth and her mother says ominously, ''Nothing good can come out of white and colored love.'' Many sad things do come to pass, but none of them are really related to ''white and colored love.'' The drama's pivotal act of bigotry is directed at a local Greek family, not Cora's, which is the only African-American family in town.</p>
        <p>Cora's brief affair with a white man, which produced the child she adored, has been transformed into treacly flashbacks. The screenwriter Ann Peacock has turned this man, Joe, whom Hughes described briefly as ''big and strong and careless as the horses he took care of, smelling like the stable,'' into a poet.</p>
        <p>The characters are drawn starkly, especially the servant and her boss. Cora is noble and wise, even when she finally explodes, which doesn't give the capable Regina Taylor much room to maneuver. Her employer, Lizbeth Studevant, is selfish, neurotic and obsessed with status. But while her characteristics are defined, her character isn't. The fine actress Cherry Jones is left to find new ways to perfect her scowl.</p>
        <p>The master of the house fares better. Michael Gaston is suitably clumsy and vague in the smaller role of Arthur Studevant, a man who is cowed by his wife but still seems to love her, for reasons that aren't obvious. He seems weak but decent, a man inclined to do the right thing, unless doing so will cause discomfort.</p>
        <p>He compliments Cora's biscuits, which his wife pronounces ''too salty.'' When sorrow strikes the housekeeper, he offers genuine words of comfort without having to think about it, while Mrs. Studevant's attempt at compassion remains stymied after much thought. Yet he hesitates to contradict her, preferring to look the other way, even when he knows her actions are twisted.</p>
        <p>''Cora'' captures the strain in this stuffy household, dominated by a woman accustomed to having her orders obeyed without question. Given the time and place, and the prevailing social order, it doesn't occur to Cora to object, until Mrs. Studevant's wrongheaded sense of propriety becomes disastrous to her own family.</p>
        <p>Presented as a drama of female suffering, strength and intolerance, ''Cora'' is often moving and has some strong scenes. But too frequently the slender narrative succumbs to pretty pictures cast in ''meaningful'' light, which soften and sentimentalize the blunt social commentary of Hughes's short but incisive story.</p>
        <p>MASTERPIECE THEATER'S AMERICAN COLLECTION  Cora Unashamed  PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 9)</p>
        <p>Adapted by Ann Peacock from the Langston Hughes short story ''The Ways of White Folks''; Deborah M. Pratt, director; music by Patrice Rushen; Marian Rees, Anne Hopkins and and Stephen Kulczycki, executive producers for ALT Films; Ron Colby, co-producer; Rebecca Eaton, series executive producer. Produced by ALT Films and WGBH Boston.</p>
        <p>WITH: Regina Taylor (Cora Jenkins), Cherry Jones (Lizbeth Studevant), Michael Gaston (Arthur Studevant), C. C. H. Pounder (Ma Jenkins) and Molly Graham (Jessie Studevant).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
