<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT&amp;T Board Said to Meet On Overhaul</title>
    <meta content="Y25TEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/business/25TELE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6DE1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1235" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT&amp;T Board Said to Meet On Overhaul</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>AT&amp;T Corp's board meets on details to overhaul company and complete necessary documents; plan calls for AT&amp;T's cable television and wireless communications units to be set up as separate companies, while new stock will be created to track performance of AT&amp;T's consumer long-distance unit; that would leave core operation, to be represented by AT&amp;T's current stock, most of company's communications network and unit that serves business customers; hart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After approving a plan to overhaul AT&amp;T on Monday, the company's board met yesterday to nail down the details and complete the necessary legal documents, people close to the company said.</p>
        <p>The plan calls for AT&amp;T's cable television and wireless communications units to be set up as separate companies, while a new stock would be created to track the performance of AT&amp;T's consumer long-distance unit, the people said. That would leave as the core operation, to be represented by AT&amp;T's current stock, most of the company's communications network and the unit that serves business customers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After approving a plan to overhaul AT&amp;T on Monday, the company's board met yesterday to nail down the details and complete the necessary legal documents, people close to the company said.</p>
        <p>The plan calls for AT&amp;T's cable television and wireless communications units to be set up as separate companies, while a new stock would be created to track the performance of AT&amp;T's consumer long-distance unit, the people said. That would leave as the core operation, to be represented by AT&amp;T's current stock, most of the company's communications network and the unit that serves business customers.</p>
        <p>The moves, which AT&amp;T is expected to  announce as soon as today, would be carried out over the next 12 to 24 months, the people close to the company said.</p>
        <p>An AT&amp;T spokeswoman declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Despite a major, court-supervised breakup in 1984 and a voluntary one in 1996, AT&amp;T is still the nation's biggest communications company. That may no longer be the case after the new breakup plan is carried out.</p>
        <p>Here is a look at some of the main challenges each of AT&amp;T's major units has faced recently, as well as the likely prospects and opportunities after the overhaul:</p>
        <p>CABLE -- AT&amp;T's expansion into the cable television business has been the most visible move by C. Michael Armstrong, who took over as AT&amp;T's chairman three years ago. With its acquisitions of Tele-Communications Inc. and the MediaOne Group, the company has become the nation's biggest cable provider, aiming to provide packages of interactive television, telephone service and high-speed Internet access over cable lines.</p>
        <p>But a big part of some investors' impatience with AT&amp;T has stemmed from the perception that the company has reaped the fruits of that strategy as quickly as it could. At the end of the second quarter, the company was delivering local phone service over cable lines to about 224,000 customers; when it announces its quarterly financial results today, the company is expected to update those customer figures.</p>
        <p>It is possible that separation from AT&amp;T could lead the cable unit to de-emphasize cable telephone service. Without access to the cash flow generated by the consumer long-distance business, a phone-via-cable service may become too costly for the company and too expensive for customers.</p>
        <p>In addition, because the Bell local phone giants no longer appear serious about delivering television over phone lines, there would be less competitive pressure for the cable company to provide phone service. And yet, the growth potential for the business of delivering phone calls may be too attractive to pass up.</p>
        <p>It remains to be seen what links a separate cable unit would have to the rest of AT&amp;T. In any case, delivery of Internet service over cable systems is likely to remain an attractive business.</p>
        <p>WIRELESS -- AT&amp;T's wireless unit, along with its partners, had almost 14 million subscribers at the end of the second quarter, placing it among the top five wireless carriers in the nation. Concerned that investors were not granting AT&amp;T full credit for its wireless business, the company offered a new stock to track the wireless unit in April.</p>
        <p>That stock has not fared well. After being offered to the public at $29.50, the wireless shares closed yesterday at $21.63. But it would be unfair to interpret that weakness entirely as a judgment on the prospects for AT&amp;T's wireless operation.</p>
        <p>For one thing, stocks in the entire wireless sector (as well as many other high-technology precincts) have taken a beating over the last few months. For another, AT&amp;T sold only about 16 percent of the tracking shares to the public and it has been unclear just how the other 84 percent will be distributed to AT&amp;T shareholders -- an uncertainty that will probably be cleared up today. This 84 percent ''overhang'' has also weighed down the stock.</p>
        <p>''With or without this corporate structure, the fundamentals of the company are solid,'' said John M. Bensche, a wireless analyst at Lehman Brothers. ''If they can clear up the distribution issue, whether distribute the rest of the stock or spin the whole thing off, it removes a significant obstacle to price appreciation in the stock,'' Mr. Bensche said.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS SERVICES -- In recent years, the part of AT&amp;T that serves business customers was one of the company's big success stories -- particularly the unit that runs a corporate customer's complete communications network. But over the last year the unit has stumbled badly in some fairly mundane but important ways.</p>
        <p>For instance, as AT&amp;T set up an international joint venture with British Telecommunications, AT&amp;T fumbled the handoff of some of its biggest customers to the joint venture.</p>
        <p>The business-services unit has also narrowly missed some financial targets.</p>
        <p>But the main damage, from Wall Street's standpoint, has been psychological: Investors were counting on the business division to fire on all cylinders while AT&amp;T ventured into cable. Fairly or not, many investors appear to worry that Mr. Armstrong has not been adequately minding the shop as he ranged afield.</p>
        <p>As the core of a pared AT&amp;T, the business unit may be able to return to its former glory.</p>
        <p>CONSUMER LONG-DISTANCE -- Historically the heart of AT&amp;T, the consumer long-distance business has lately caused the company considerable heartburn. A year ago, most everyone in the communications industry expected the unit's revenue to shrink a bit -- but not at an annual rate of as much as 7 percent, which it has in recent quarters.</p>
        <p>In recent years, even as the consumer long-distance unit slowed its growth and began to shrink, AT&amp;T was still able to increase the unit's profit margins by cutting back on marketing and advertising. This year, on revenue of perhaps $19 billion, the unit will probably produce about $8 billion in cash flow -- or earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization. That would compare with cash flow of less than $8 billion last year on revenue of about $22 billion.</p>
        <p>Still considerable, that cash has underwritten many of AT&amp;T's investments -- a house bank the wireless and cable companies would no longer be able to draw on, at least in the same way. And yet, moving the consumer unit onto its own ledger, and monitoring it with its own tracking stock, would mean the core business-customer unit would be able to report more robust growth. In addition, much of the company's debt could be expected to be assigned to the consumer unit, freeing up the balance sheets of the other operations.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T's long-distance customers -- corporate or residential -- would probably not perceive much immediate impact from AT&amp;T's new structure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
