<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investors Pay $48 Million For 15% of Nasdaq Japan</title>
    <meta content="25JAPA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241678"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nasdaq-Japan Stock Market</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Assn of Securities Dealers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Softbank Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DD1531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investors Pay $48 Million For 15% of Nasdaq Japan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nasdaq Japan, fledgling stock market that is joint venture of National Association of Securities Dealers and Softbank Corp, sells 15 percent stake to group of foreign and domestic brokers; Softbank raises 5.25 billion yen, or about $48 million, which it plans to use largely for working capital and to develop computer systems it will need to expand Japanese small-stock market (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nasdaq Japan, the fledgling stock market that is a joint venture of the National Association of Securities Dealers and the Softbank Corporation, has sold a 15 percent stake to a group of foreign and domestic brokers.</p>
        <p>The company, Japan's leading Internet investor, raised 5.25 billion yen, or about $48 million, that it plans to use largely for working capital and to develop the computer systems it will need to expand the Japanese small-stock market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nasdaq Japan, the fledgling stock market that is a joint venture of the National Association of Securities Dealers and the Softbank Corporation, has sold a 15 percent stake to a group of foreign and domestic brokers.</p>
        <p>The company, Japan's leading Internet investor, raised 5.25 billion yen, or about $48 million, that it plans to use largely for working capital and to develop the computer systems it will need to expand the Japanese small-stock market.</p>
        <p>Perhaps more important, the investment is a step toward more closely aligning the interests of Nasdaq Japan with those of the investment group, which includes Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, Daiwa Securities and UBS Warburg.</p>
        <p>Nasdaq Japan has had difficulty winning the support of Japanese brokerage houses. And while foreign firms have backed it, their power as underwriters of Japanese stocks -- and thus their ability to bring new business to market -- is limited by weak distribution systems here and the dominance of the Japanese.</p>
        <p>Richard Barolotta, Nasdaq Japan's chief financial officer, said the investors were in effect offering more than money. ''These are the leading securities firms of Japan and around the world,'' he said, ''and can provide a tremendous amount of support and counsel to us as we continue to grow.''</p>
        <p>The securities firms, many of which have faced daunting challenges as underwriters here, see their investment as a way of nurturing a market that may eventually provide a place to float shares in new companies and a means for them to bring down the barriers that have long kept them from gaining a significant share of the Japanese equity underwriting market.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq Japan market opened in June with an initial investment of 600 million yen -- now about $5.5 million -- from Softbank and Nasdaq in the United States, an investment that now looks cheap when compared to the price that newer investors paid for their stock.</p>
        <p>Softbank and Nasdaq paid 50,000 yen for their shares, the minimum allowed under the Japanese Commercial Code, while the new investors are paying 2.5 million yen for each of their shares -- a solid endorsement of the new market.</p>
        <p>Nasdaq Japan, which seeks to become the market of choice for vibrant young Japanese companies seeking to list their shares, has suffered some because its liquidity, or the ability to buy and sell stock at any time, is limited by constraints from the commercial code.</p>
        <p>The 10 securities firms that bought a few less than 200 shares each will sit on an advisory council that will elect one director to represent them on Nasdaq Japan's seven-member board. The other seats are divided evenly between Softbank and the National Association of Securities Dealers.</p>
        <p>Three other firms -- the Goldman Sachs Group, Nomura Securities and Kokusai Securities -- opted for smaller stakes and no formal board representation.</p>
        <p>Part of the proceeds will be used to pay off loans made to Nasdaq Japan by the two venture partners and debts owed to vendors. Mr. Barolotta said the majority of the new money would be used for working capital.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
