<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Porter, an Icebreaker, Please, and Step on It</title>
    <meta content="25MAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/arts/25MAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241668"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reza, Yasmina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bates, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Atkins, Eileen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Unexpected Man, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EFDE1531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Porter, an Icebreaker, Please, and Step on It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Yasmina Reza play The Unexpected Man, at Promenade Theater; photo of Alan Bates and Eileen Atkins (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shall we start with Eileen Atkins's right leg? It is, like her left leg, slender and shapely, and it has no doubt served this fine actress well over the years as something to stand on. But in ''The Unexpected Man,'' the cigarette-slim play by Yasmina Reza that opened last night at the Promenade Theater, Ms. Atkins turns her right leg into something far more resonant: an index of the vanity, anxiety and authority of the woman she is playing.</p>
        <p>She does this simply by pointing her right toe outward and shifting her weight, with the leg at a comely distance and at an angle from its partner. This small physical adjustment makes Ms. Atkins look as cosmopolitan as an Erte fashion illustration, and it defines her character as someone for whom stylish affectation has become a reflex.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shall we start with Eileen Atkins's right leg? It is, like her left leg, slender and shapely, and it has no doubt served this fine actress well over the years as something to stand on. But in ''The Unexpected Man,'' the cigarette-slim play by Yasmina Reza that opened last night at the Promenade Theater, Ms. Atkins turns her right leg into something far more resonant: an index of the vanity, anxiety and authority of the woman she is playing.</p>
        <p>She does this simply by pointing her right toe outward and shifting her weight, with the leg at a comely distance and at an angle from its partner. This small physical adjustment makes Ms. Atkins look as cosmopolitan as an Erte fashion illustration, and it defines her character as someone for whom stylish affectation has become a reflex.</p>
        <p>Now consider Alan Bates's shoulders. They are more formidable than one remembers their being from those 1960's movies (''Georgy Girl,'' ''King of Hearts'') that made Mr. Bates a countercultural movie idol. He doesn't do anything very flashy with them -- just some curving, flexing and shrugging.</p>
        <p>And yet those shoulders are displayed like both a well-polished badge of self-regard and a No Trespassing sign. Here, clearly, is a fellow who struts his importance while pretending he does not.</p>
        <p>Oh, the pleasures of watching performers of this caliber preen. Ms. Atkins and Mr. Bates bring to ''The Unexpected Man'' an armory of precision weapons accumulated during lives in the theater. So what if you've seen them deployed before? (Ms. Atkins's angled-leg business was also a highlight of ''Indiscretions'' on Broadway five years ago.) Under the fine-tuned direction of Matthew Warchus, these stars unpack their arsenals like peacocks spreading their tails.</p>
        <p>This suits Ms. Reza's urbane comedy, which examines the amour-propre and existential worries of a pair of worldly strangers on a train. It should also be pointed out that without such actorly embellishment, ''The Unexpected Man'' would probably evaporate before your eyes. Ms. Reza is the French dramatist responsible for ''Art,'' the anatomy of a three-sided friendship that became a huge international success. ''Art'' chronicled the drifting apart into lonesomeness of men who thought they knew one another well; ''Man,'' previously seen in London with Ms. Atkins and Michael Gambon, follows the same formula in reverse -- that of two people who don't know each other at all moving toward a moment of connection.</p>
        <p>The plays share a raised middlebrow sensibility that presents home truths with a satisfied air of intellectual discovery and takes pleasure in gently puncturing human pride. Those expecting to laugh steadily as they did at ''Art,'' however, should know that ''Man'' isn't nearly as audience-friendly. It is more formal in its structure, a series of alternating interior monologues, and more pointed in its cosmic concerns. This means that its air of importance is more glaringly out of proportion to what it ultimately has to say.</p>
        <p>The basic setup for ''Man'' is an archetype used in everything from television variety shows to soapy romance movies. A man and a woman sit opposite each other in a train; each thinks about the other and what the other is thinking.</p>
        <p>In this variation, the pair has the surface glamour of couples in television commercials for things like exotically flavored coffees and expensive automobiles. They also have literary cachet: he is a famous novelist, and she is one of his most devoted and, it would seem, insightful readers.</p>
        <p>Whatever suspense the play has hinges on two questions: Will the woman, who has recognized the novelist, dare to read his latest book (also titled ''The Unexpected Man'') in his presence? Will they actually speak before the train out of Paris reaches Frankfurt?</p>
        <p>Before any answers are given, he will talk at length about his digestive problems and his insomnia; his frustration with his vocabulary, his critics and his daughter's lover. She, in turn, will ponder the recent death of a friend and the ways in which the novelist's works have reflected and informed her life.</p>
        <p>A brooding sense of isolation hangs over these spoken thoughts. The woman muses poetically on a photograph in the train compartment, conveniently showing two people unaware of each other's existence. He speaks of ''a splinter of life among so many others, a tiny pinprick in time, amid so much pointed loneliness.''</p>
        <p>As a philosopher, neither is thrilling company. They don't begin to have the goofy vitality of, say, the frantic intellectuals of Eric Rohmer's movies -- people whose obsessions, however irritating, generate some energy.</p>
        <p>The idiosyncrasies of Ms. Reza's characters have instead a quality of secondhand chic, like knockoffs of Chanel suits. The references to Brahms sonatas, Thai restaurants and cinquecento painting dangle like unclipped price tags.</p>
        <p>So do some of the more grating lines: ''Neurotics are the cream of humanity,'' for example. (The smooth translation is by Christopher Hampton, who also did the English text of ''Art.'') Ms. Reza treads on dangerous ground when she has the novelist complain about laughter in the theater that is ''congratulating itself for being intelligent enough to know why it's being laughed.''</p>
        <p>If Ms. Atkins and Mr. Bates smell something stale here, they don't let on. They seem to be having a marvelous time wandering through the manicured mazes of their characters' self-consciousness. What's more, they have been given the most impeccable platform imaginable for such swaggering: a glossy, moody convergence of set and costumes (Mark Thompson), lighting (Hugh Vanstone), sound effects (Mic Pool and David Bullard) and cinematic music (Gary Yershon).</p>
        <p>As he demonstrated with ''Art,'' Mr. Warchus knows how to keep minimalism from seeming static and how best to bring out his performers' eloquent body language. It is especially fun to watch Mr. Bates, last seen on a New York stage in ''Butley'' in 1973, catching his reflection in the mirrored train window as the novelist ponders his own bitterness. He also zestily shows off his leonine voice, amply confirming his character's assertion that ''our family's been stentorian for generations.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Atkins is sexy, stately and sly all at once, and she measures out emotions with an elegance that miraculously seems as sincere as it is studied. She is marvelous, in the play's best single speech, describing a long flirtation that goes sour when her character's platonic lover becomes a family man. Her affronted air of dismay conveys exactly how betrayals are often most deeply felt in small gestures.</p>
        <p>All the same, what I really can't stop thinking about is the angle of Ms. Atkins's right leg, which is all the more noticeable for her wearing white stockings. It says much about ''The Unexpected Man'' that such purely physical details are what cling to the memory.</p>
        <p>THE UNEXPECTED MAN</p>
        <p>By Yasmina Reza; translated by Christopher Hampton; directed by Matthew Warchus; sets and costumes by Mark Thompson; lighting by Hugh Vanstone; sound by Mic Pool and David Bullard; original music by Gary Yershon; production stage manager, Michael Brunner; general manager, Peter Bogyo; associate producer, Sonny Everett. Presented by Julian Schlossberg, Ben Sprecher, Ted Tulchin and William P. Miller, in association with Aaron Levy and Morton Wolkowitz. At the Promenade Theater, 2162 Broadway, at 76th Street.</p>
        <p>WITH: Alan Bates (the Man) and Eileen Atkins (the Woman).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
