<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Swaggers, But America Shrugs</title>
    <meta content="Y25REA$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/sports/25REAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Dirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE0DB1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1224" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Swaggers, But America Shrugs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Dirk</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses lack of interest outside of New York in Subway Series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Karen Warner, a die-hard Chicago baseball fan, confesses that she has been touched by the mystique and glory of the vaunted Subway Series in New York.</p>
        <p>''Let me put it this way,'' said Ms. Warner, 38, who lives a block from Wrigley Field and dresses her dog, Elvis, in a Cub kerchief: ''It turns my stomach.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Karen Warner, a die-hard Chicago baseball fan, confesses that she has been touched by the mystique and glory of the vaunted Subway Series in New York.</p>
        <p>''Let me put it this way,'' said Ms. Warner, 38, who lives a block from Wrigley Field and dresses her dog, Elvis, in a Cub kerchief: ''It turns my stomach.''</p>
        <p>In the rest of America, so distant from the Center of the Universe, not everyone is humming along to Frank Sinatra.</p>
        <p>''They're just so proud of themselves, those New Yorkers,'' said Jean Waters, 43, a business executive in Omaha. ''This glorification of New York. I mean, they were pretty pleased with themselves already. Now there's just one more thing that's so wonderful about them. It's a little obnoxious.''</p>
        <p>It is not that people do not care about the World Series, judging from dozens of interviews around the country. Indeed, it is the rare fan who claims to have ignored every bit of the games between the Yankees and the Mets. As everyone has heard, time and time and time again, this is baseball history in the making.</p>
        <p>It's just a little galling, that's all.</p>
        <p>Mike Rosa, 25, a Boston Red Sox fan who lives in Medford, Mass., got an e-mail message from a friend last week that read, ''Let's get ready for the game on Saturday, the Mets-Yankees Subway Series!''</p>
        <p>He wrote back: ''I would rather be hit by that subway train.''</p>
        <p>There are, too, some real measures of interest to examine. Although the Subway Series is clearly captivating television viewers in the New York metropolitan region, it has not dazzled the country. In fact, the national Nielsen ratings for the first two games have placed this World Series on track to be the lowest-rated ever.</p>
        <p>After two games, the rating is averaging a 12.0 nationally, down 18 percent from a 14.6 during the World Series between the Yankees and the Atlanta Braves last year. Each national rating point equals an estimated 1.02 million television households.</p>
        <p>In the New York market, Game 1, on Saturday, produced a 41.6 rating, or about 2.88 million television households, a performance followed in Game 2 on Sunday with a 42.1, or 2.92 million homes, the most-watched local prime-time program since the finale of ''Seinfeld'' in 1998.</p>
        <p>But across the country, viewership has been far less impressive, with the highest rating outside New York coming from nearby Hartford, which posted a 21.9 for Game 1. In other major markets, the Game 2 ratings included a 13.5 in Los Angeles, a 9.8 in Chicago and a 13.6 in Boston.</p>
        <p>And according to a New York Times/CBS News poll, most Americans do not really care who wins the Series. Twenty percent are rooting for the Yankees and 20 percent prefer the Mets, while 58 percent said they did not care. The last time The Times and CBS News asked the nation for its preference in the World Series was in 1987 when the St. Louis Cardinals were playing the Minnesota Twins, and only 37 percent said they did not care.</p>
        <p>In Chicago, which has not had a World Series winner since the Bolshevik Revolution, in 1917 -- that was the White Sox; the Cubs last won it in 1908 -- it is particularly difficult to be gracious about two New York teams in the Series. But people try.</p>
        <p>Bob Morand, a 40-year-old executive recruiter, whose broken heart has not completely mended since the tragedy of 1969, when the Cubs collapsed in September and lost the National League East title to the Mets, says he considers the Subway Series to be something special.</p>
        <p>''Some people like to bad-mouth New York,'' he said. ''But deep down inside, if you're really a baseball fan, you've got to think this is pretty exciting.''</p>
        <p>The Series, of course, has also sounded a call to former New Yorkers, people who might now live and work in California or Colorado, but who might remember a childhood afternoon spent at Yankee Stadium or a night a month ago spent, say, in a bar in Queens.</p>
        <p>John Keiley, 40, sold his Queens sports bar in Queens and arrived in Denver four months ago.</p>
        <p>''I almost can't talk about it,'' said Mr. Keiley, a lifelong Met fan who manages Big Bill's New York Pizza in Denver. Mr. Keiley, crushed that he wasn't back home, said he watched Game 1 and Game 2 in his pizzeria while in contact with friends at a bar in Forest Hills, Queens. ''Thank God for cell phones,'' he said. ''Once I hear their voices, I can feel the juice. It's not like I'm by myself.''</p>
        <p>Here in Chicago, as civic boosters like to point out, people do see the potential appeal of an intracity Series, for this city had one. It's just that very few people are alive who can recall it. (The Cubs and the White Sox met in the Series in 1906.)</p>
        <p>And it will happen again in Chicago, said Mr. Morand, the executive recruiter, who borrowed a line from the colorful broadcaster Jack Brickhouse to explain the Cubs' slump: ''Anybody can have a bad century.''</p>
        <p>Veronica Boone, 38, a hotel worker in Chicago, said she did not have another century to wait around.</p>
        <p>''I'm now a Yankees fan,'' she said. ''Why not?'' she added as her friends clucked disapprovingly. ''They're winners. I'm tired of being with the losers. Go Yankees.''</p>
        <p>In the South, where many people cheer for the Braves, a team that virtually owned the National League through the 1990's, the New York-New York Series is not merely a disappointment. It is a fraud.</p>
        <p>''You've got this second-place team in there,'' said Stephanie Harris, a bartender in Macon, Ga., noting that the Mets finished behind the Braves in the standings, but qualified for the playoffs as a wild-card team. ''Everybody just hates that.''</p>
        <p>Dominique Morgan, a 23-year-old paralegal in Chicago, said it seemed a bit untoward for the Yankees to win so much.</p>
        <p>''Shouldn't they spread the wealth a little?'' she said. ''They've had their turn.''</p>
        <p>And Rich Buendorf, 34, a developer of low-income housing in Chicago, said it was difficult to side with either the Yankees or the Mets. ''I like the underdog,'' he said. ''But when it's New York and New York, where's the underdog?''</p>
        <p>For some fans outside New York, there were some silver linings to grasp.</p>
        <p>Ian McLaughlin, 24, a construction worker in Boston, said he and his friends would be pulling for the Mets to topple the hated Yankees.</p>
        <p>But it was the Mets who spoiled the World Series for the Red Sox in 1986. ''That's how much we hate the Yankees,'' he said, ''that we're willing to overshadow '86.''</p>
        <p>Laura LaBarbera, a 36-year-old public relations manager in Chicago, said she was looking, with some amusement, to New Yorkers' turning on one another.</p>
        <p>''In other cities, there would be euphoria if their team won the World Series,'' she said. ''But in this case, it's going to cause divisions.''</p>
        <p>A smile danced across her face. Soon, she noted, half of those New Yorkers -- who now seem so smug, so jubilant, so superior -- are going to be losers.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
