<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dr. Spock Lives On in Books; Coming Soon, the Web Site</title>
    <meta content="25BREK$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brekke, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spock, Benjamin (1903-98)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgan, Mary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2DA103FF936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dr. Spock Lives On in Books; Coming Soon, the Web Site</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BREKKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brekke, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>MENLO PARK, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gentle directives to parents given over many years by pediatrician Dr Benjamin Spock form basis for new Web site, DrSpock.com; his widow, Mary Morgan, zealously pursues perfecting site; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DR. BENJAMIN SPOCK'S most widely quoted advice is contained in the very first words of ''The Common Sense Book of Baby and Child Care,'' the 1946 volume that redefined child-rearing in America. ''Trust yourself,'' he told parents. ''You know more than you think you do.''</p>
        <p>Spock's famously gentle directives made him a global publishing phenomenon. By the time he died in 1998 at age 94, ''Baby and Child Care'' had sold more than 50 million copies. Among baby boomers, he was equally renowned as a principled political activist for his leadership in the movement to end the Vietnam War.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DR. BENJAMIN SPOCK'S most widely quoted advice is contained in the very first words of ''The Common Sense Book of Baby and Child Care,'' the 1946 volume that redefined child-rearing in America. ''Trust yourself,'' he told parents. ''You know more than you think you do.''</p>
        <p>Spock's famously gentle directives made him a global publishing phenomenon. By the time he died in 1998 at age 94, ''Baby and Child Care'' had sold more than 50 million copies. Among baby boomers, he was equally renowned as a principled political activist for his leadership in the movement to end the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>Now, though, the doctor's name has been turned into a brand and a Web site, DrSpock.com. And his teachings have been taken into a realm -- the online content business -- that is devoid of the nurturing, patience and good sense he counseled. Investors who a year ago were soothed by the prevailing dot-com wisdom -- ''Trust us! There will be profits!'' -- have recoiled from content-driven ventures.</p>
        <p>If anything, the retreat from content has been more punishing for health-information Web sites, like DrKoop.com, WebMD.com and PlanetRx.com, than it has been for the sector as a whole.</p>
        <p>''This is not a good time to be entering the media-driven content market, and in the health space, specifically,'' said Elizabeth Boehm, an analyst with the health care group of Forrester Research, the consulting company in Cambridge, Mass. ''This is in part because of the attention that the flailing e-health sites have attracted, and in part because the ad model doesn't work.''</p>
        <p>One of the flailingest of them all is DrKoop.com, where wild overoptimism combined with poor management to tarnish a ''brand name'' founder. The company that originated the site, named for Dr. C. Everett Koop, the outspoken former United States surgeon general, raised $88.5 million in an initial public offering in June 1999. The cash was gone in less than a year.</p>
        <p>The company's management made deals to spend nearly $150 million over three years to be a health-information provider to the Disney Company's Go.com and to America Online. In September 1999, an article in The New York Times raised questions about a potential conflict of interest when it disclosed that unknown to the site's users, the doctor received commissions on product sales there. Dr. Koop's contract has been changed to eliminate such commissions, the company said in the same article. Development of online personal medical records, an important adjunct to the company's content business plan, hit a dead end.</p>
        <p>DrKoop.com's shares fell below $1. The company is now in the hands of venture capitalists, who have vowed to wring profits from the site.</p>
        <p>''The industry is certainly a challenging one to make a business-model rationale for,'' said Claudine Singer, a research director and senior analyst at Jupiter Research, an Internet consulting company based in New York. Most consumer-focused health-information sites have depended on advertising revenue for a big slice of their income; Jupiter projects that advertising spending in the sector will total $700 million by 2004. ''That's just not enough to stay the red ink,'' Ms. Singer said.</p>
        <p>With the market's lack of confidence in content investments and with the demonstrated hazards of trying to turn a mix of health information and e-commerce into profits, why would anyone start a venture built on the wisdom of a deceased pediatrician? Especially when other sites -- BabyCenter.com, Parent Soup.com and Parenting.com (a site featuring material from Time Inc.'s group of magazines on child-rearing), to name a few -- have well-established claims in the infant/parent/advice/commerce territory.</p>
        <p>The answer, found in the cramped upper floor of a dingy two-story cinder-brick-and-aluminum bank building in downtown Menlo Park, Calif., has two distinct segments. DrSpock .com embodies a business rationale based half on enduring faith that a ''killer brand'' will overcome all obstacles and half on enduring commitment on the part of Dr. Spock's widow, Mary Morgan, to see his work brought to new generations.</p>
        <p>Ms. Morgan, a board member and the company's vice president for publishing, brings a nearly religious zeal to the job of making sure DrSpock.com stays true to the spirit of her late husband's work.</p>
        <p>''I look at Ben's face, his picture, every morning, and I say, 'It's with great love and great respect that I honor your work,' '' Ms. Morgan said.</p>
        <p>She has rented an apartment a few blocks from the start-up's office so that she can work there every day. Ms. Morgan said that some of the problems on Dr. Koop's site were caused by the fact that day-to-day operations were handled by executives in Austin, Tex., while Dr. Koop lived in New Hampshire. ''I come to this place at 6 o'clock in the morning,  I open it up, and the people here see me here every single day,'' she said. ''The reason I'm so avid about that is that I want to make sure Ben's spirit will be in this company.''</p>
        <p>DrSpock.com -- its motto is ''Trust yourself'' -- was founded late last year and soon found itself caught in the market downturn. The company obtained $2 million in seed capital, then investor money dried up.</p>
        <p>The founding chief executive, who had talked about a company that would go public with a valuation in the billions, left. The staff -- a mix of seasoned pediatricians and longtime journalists -- worked for stock while new cash was sought. The site, originally scheduled to open last spring, took its first halting steps the last day of September with no advertising and no signed partnerships in place. And the enterprise is already contemplating a name change -- to the Doctor Spock Company, perhaps -- to free itself from the stigma of a dot-com identity.</p>
        <p>Douglas Lee, 35, a former health-industry venture capitalist and father of an 18-month-old daughter, became DrSpock's chief executive in May. When discussing the company's foundation and future, Mr. Lee repeatedly mentions its brand name.</p>
        <p>Dr. Spock's cultural renown ''is a penny from heaven,'' Mr. Lee said, adding, ''To have a leading brand be available and put a brand-new business strategy behind it without conflict is a once-in-a-lifetime thing.''</p>
        <p>The business plan -- ''We've put a formal business strategy around Ben for the first time in history,'' Mr. Lee said -- anticipates a media company that will work online, and off, to create an omnipresent ''parenting channel.''</p>
        <p>''We're going across media whether it's the Web, magazines, publishing, TV, radio, wireless,'' Mr. Lee said. ''You're going to see Ben everywhere.''</p>
        <p>He said negotiations were under way with several media companies to develop Spock-related projects. ''You will see a flurry of major, major strategic deals that are going to show facets, though not necessarily the scale, of our media strategy,'' he said. He declined to give names.</p>
        <p>For now, the Web site features searchable content that includes ''Baby and Child Care,'' product-safety news and community discussions on topics like toilet training.</p>
        <p>In the near future, the site plans to offer writings from other pediatricians, like Dr. Robert Needlman, a former colleague of Spock and the company's vice president for behavior and general pediatrics. In addition, he is an associate professor of pediatrics at Case Western Reserve University in Cleveland.</p>
        <p>DrSpock.com will also add a commerce element that Mr. Lee said will parallel CNet's handling of product reviews and purchases. The company will offer an overview of products -- baby monitors and strollers, for instance. It will be left to those who participate in the site's community areas to comment on or recommend products, he said. The site will also provide shopping links to retailers, so that they can buy the merchandise they have read about.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee acknowledged the competition but maintained that there were crucial differences. And that last word, he said, will be the defining feature of Dr. Spock, the enterprise. ''Ben's brand is the brand of experts,'' he said, explaining that both vintage Spock material and new pieces written by doctors will speak with a voice that is accessible to consumers and authoritative among pediatricians.</p>
        <p>ALOOK at the competitive landscape, however, shows sites, like BabyCenter and ParentSoup, that prominently feature advice from pediatricians on a wide range of topics, and ages. BabyCenter, through its new ParentCenter channel, addresses topics from prenatal to age 8, and ParentSoup tracks child-rearing through the teens. Parenting.com -- the newly revamped child-rearing portal site for Time Inc.'s Parenting, Baby Talk, Healthy Pregnancy and Family Life print magazines -- has adopted a cross-media strategy with book offerings and three weekly 90-second TV spots distributed through CNN.</p>
        <p>On another point, Mr. Lee said that DrSpock.com's relatively late start matters little. ''The brand gives us time, which will give us a way to catch up,'' he said. ''And the brand will put us ahead.''</p>
        <p>Pat as that game plan may sound, the company has found investors. In addition to $2 million from Broadview Capital early this year, DrSpock.com has received $10 million from Zesiger Capital Group, an institutional investment firm in New York. The money is part of a planned $15 million round that values DrSpock.com at $35 million. Mr. Lee said the cash should last the company through the third quarter of 2001; it intends to expand to 45 employees next year, from the current 18.</p>
        <p>Ms. Singer of Jupiter Research said that despite ''a primary forecast of gloom and doom'' for health-information concerns in general, one can detect glimmers of hope for the company in its brand and in the nature of parenthood itself.</p>
        <p>''Parenting is a chronic condition -- you're a parent forever,'' she observed. ''To the degree that a company can serve up relevant tools that are useful to you over time, there is an opportunity for a relationship, even the possibility that people will pay for what you're offering.''</p>
        <p>HEALTH Dan Brekke is a former deputy editor of Wired magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dan Brekke is a former deputy editor of Wired magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
