<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 7-Year Fight, Homeless Get $816,000 in Back Wages</title>
    <meta content="25SETT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/nyregion/25SETT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241796"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Grand Central Partnership (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">34th Street Partnership</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Nina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minimum Wage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6DA1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 7-Year Fight, Homeless Get $816,000 in Back Wages</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NINA BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Nina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>One hundred and ninety eight men and women who worked for $1 an hour while they were homeless will receive back wages totaling $816,000; money is result of ruling in seven-year-long Federal class action lawsuit against Grand Central Partnership and 34th Street Partnership, two major business improvement districts in midtown Manhattan; case reviewed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They slept on plastic chairs or in makeshift beds in a church, rising to put in long shifts in menial jobs, like security patrols at banks across Manhattan's East Side, or cleaning toilets at a shelter. Instead of being paid minimum wage, they got $1 an hour and promises of a path out of homelessness that never seemed to lead anywhere.</p>
        <p>Tonight, 198 of the men and women who were homeless when they worked on streets and in buildings around Grand Central Terminal during the 1990's will be handed more money than most have ever seen at any one time, all in back wages totaling $816,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They slept on plastic chairs or in makeshift beds in a church, rising to put in long shifts in menial jobs, like security patrols at banks across Manhattan's East Side, or cleaning toilets at a shelter. Instead of being paid minimum wage, they got $1 an hour and promises of a path out of homelessness that never seemed to lead anywhere.</p>
        <p>Tonight, 198 of the men and women who were homeless when they worked on streets and in buildings around Grand Central Terminal during the 1990's will be handed more money than most have ever seen at any one time, all in back wages totaling $816,000.</p>
        <p>The money is the result of a ruling in a seven-year-long federal class-action lawsuit against two major business improvement districts in Midtown Manhattan, the Grand Central Partnership and the 34th Street Partnership. The homeless plaintiffs won in 1998, but received no money because of an appeal, until an unusual settlement this month cleared the way for tonight's payments and celebration.</p>
        <p>Some are already using the promise of the checks to stave off eviction. One man plans to use part of his $10,000 check to pay back his mother and brother for the loans they gave him when he was down and out. A woman plans to spend much of the money to help her son, a scholarship student at U.C.L.A. A disabled man in temporary housing hopes his $6,000 will finally lead to an apartment of his own.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Tommy Washington, 41, who will collect money owed him on more than 1,000 hours on foot patrol, echoed several others when he said of the lawsuit: ''It had nothing to do with the money. It's the principle.'' He added: ''They were dragging this on, because they figured, addicts, people in and out of the prison system, sick people -- how many were going to be around to collect?''</p>
        <p>Officials with the two business improvement districts refused last night to discuss the case or the settlement. Instead, they released a brief statement saying that they were ''gratified that this matter has been brought to an amicable resolution.''</p>
        <p>Now the plaintiffs are not only getting their wages, but also free savings accounts and legal advice on how best to handle the windfall. Some of them receive public benefits that could be jeopardized by a lump sum payment, while others have both jobs and homes. Mr. Washington, for instance, is a full-time drug abuse counselor who lives in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Winning either money or vindication  seemed elusive to many of the plaintiffs even after a trial and a federal judge's ruling in their favor two and a half years ago. The judge, Sonia Sotomayor, then a Federal District Court judge in Manhattan and now on the Federal Court of Appeals, ruled that the business districts had violated minimum wage laws, had used the cheap labor of so-called trainees to undercut competing companies, and had contributed the resulting profits to hefty executive salaries.</p>
        <p>But as the business districts appealed, some of the plaintiffs died or disappeared. Even some of the best workers, like Felicia Hart, who had a long history of office work before she took a position with the Grand Central Partnership as a trainee, were living at the edge of destitution because of problems like domestic violence, illness or addiction.</p>
        <p>''When I left Grand Central Partnership, I left with a lot of anger and a lot of hurt,'' said Ms. Hart, who put in more than 40 hours a week in office administration, dispatching and the distribution of donated clothing, according to the partnership's own time sheets. Since then, Ms. Hart added, ''I've been put through the wringer.''</p>
        <p>Mary Brosnahan, director of the Coalition for the Homeless, agreed, recalling times when Ms. Hart, ''a 4-foot-10 scrap of a woman,'' showed up bruised and swollen from a beating by a former boyfriend who followed her to a series of office jobs, including one as an airline ticket agent.</p>
        <p>''She's been consistently the most stalwart,'' Ms. Brosnahan said, crediting Ms. Hart with helping to keep other plaintiffs from giving up hope as the case dragged on.</p>
        <p>Finally, the corporate lawyers who had joined advocates for the homeless on the case agreed to give up more than $1 million in legal fees in order to reach a settlement that would let their clients collect everything that they were owed.</p>
        <p>The lawyers at Cleary, Gottlieb, Steen &amp; Hamilton, and advocates from the Coalition for the Homeless and the Urban Justice Center, who brought the lawsuit, also reluctantly went along with an unusual demand by lawyers for the business districts.  They agreed that the 1998 decision in the case, though already published,  cannot be used as a legal precedent in another lawsuit by homeless people still pending against the business districts.</p>
        <p>''To be on the side of the angels and then end up getting what people deserve is very, very satisfying,'' said Jennifer Kroman, 30, an associate at Cleary, Gottlieb who has handled the case since just before the trial. ''Reaching the settlement was one of the most joyful moments of my career.''</p>
        <p>But it was almost immediately followed by new difficulties of a kind Ms. Kroman is not used to encountering with her corporate clients. ''Of course a lot of people don't have bank accounts,'' she said. ''It occurred to me, 'Where are these people going to cash the check? Why should they pay high check-cashing fees?' ''</p>
        <p>So Cleary, Gottlieb approached its  Citibank branch, which has agreed to set up free savings accounts for all those receiving checks, she said.</p>
        <p>Another complication was the fear that the one-time windfalls could abruptly throw some people off public benefits like Supplemental Security Income or public assistance, or be seized by the city to repay past aid. So Ms. Kroman enlisted lawyers from the Legal Aid Society to help clients work within the rules to their best advantage.</p>
        <p>''My eyes have been opened to the uphill battle that these people face,'' added Ms. Kroman. ''In the last couple of weeks I've spoken to maybe six or seven landlords,'' she said. ''Clients said: 'I've told my landlord I'm getting money in a lawsuit, but they don't believe me. If you don't call I'm going to get evicted.' ''</p>
        <p>The Grand Central Partnership, headed until 1998 by Daniel A. Biederman, who remains as president of the 34th Street Partnership and executive director of the Bryant Park Restoration Corporation, was formed to clean up the central business district in Midtown and to clear away street people. Beginning in 1989, homeless people were hired to help run a 24-hour drop-in center at the former St. Agnes School on East 44th Street, and to work as outreach workers to others still on the streets.</p>
        <p>But that program had to be overhauled in 1995, after accusations that Mr. Biederman's administration had organized the workers into what were called ''goon squads'' to use force to chase homeless people out of bank lobbies with A.T.M.'s.</p>
        <p>Partnership officials denied the abuses at the time, but City Council hearings and an inquiry by the United State Department of Housing and Urban Development led to the rescinding of a federal grant to the program.</p>
        <p>Doug Lasdon, director of the Urban Justice Center, whose social workers kept track of many of the plaintiffs in the early years said of the settlement: ''This sends a strong message that you can't use the homeless for cheap labor.''</p>
        <p>But for some of the plaintiffs, the victory is bittersweet.</p>
        <p>''You had people who died,'' said Rodney Henderson, who lives in temporary housing and works as a painter or construction worker when his health allows. ''They're a lot of people who needed that money.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Washington, who credits a drug treatment program two years ago with helping him to straighten out his life, spoke of his lingering sense of injustice as though addressing his former employer, Mr. Biederman.</p>
        <p>''You say you're doing so much for the city, but you're making that money off the backs of the homeless,'' Mr. Washington said. ''You donate lampposts, flower beds, Bryant Park. How are you going to represent beautify if you're doing ugly behind that?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
