<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>This Time, Benitez Holds Up</title>
    <meta content="25SHEA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/sports/25SHEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benitez, Armando</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D91231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>This Time, Benitez Holds Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Performance of New York Mets pitcher Armando Benitez in victory over New York Yankees in third game of World Series discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The suggestion to stay aggressive wasn't as important as the quick therapy Edgardo Alfonzo provided. The Yankees' Chuck Knoblauch had just led off the ninth inning with a single up the middle and all of Shea Stadium seemed to groan. The flashbacks to Game 1 were unavoidable. Could the Mets' Armando Benitez possibly lose a two-run lead in Game 3 of the World Series?</p>
        <p>Suddenly, there was Alfonzo by Benitez's side on the mound before the sigh had finished expiring from the crowd. He provided the usual tips for pitchers to not stop attacking, but he also added, ''Don't forget you're the man.'' The message sank in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The suggestion to stay aggressive wasn't as important as the quick therapy Edgardo Alfonzo provided. The Yankees' Chuck Knoblauch had just led off the ninth inning with a single up the middle and all of Shea Stadium seemed to groan. The flashbacks to Game 1 were unavoidable. Could the Mets' Armando Benitez possibly lose a two-run lead in Game 3 of the World Series?</p>
        <p>Suddenly, there was Alfonzo by Benitez's side on the mound before the sigh had finished expiring from the crowd. He provided the usual tips for pitchers to not stop attacking, but he also added, ''Don't forget you're the man.'' The message sank in.</p>
        <p>Benitez retired the next three batters in a row, saving the Mets' 4-2 victory over the Yankees early this morning. The Mets trail the series by two games to one.</p>
        <p>''I read a lot of stories about people who say I pitch good in the season, and in the playoffs I pitch a little bad,'' Benitez said. ''What can I say? We're humans. I pitch a lot. Sometimes, when we're tired or in pain I have to come in the game. I don't have to prove or show anybody nothing. People know what I can do.''</p>
        <p>Benitez sounded eerily like John Franco, the veteran closer, who has become Benitez's setup man and counselor and who made a career out of surviving disasters. Franco waited 17 years to get to the Series. Twice in this Series he has handed leads to Benitez. This time, Benitez gave Franco a victory.</p>
        <p>Benitez blew a 3-2 lead in the ninth inning of Game 1, allowing Paul O'Neill to walk on a 10-pitch at-bat before allowing singles to Scott Brosius and then Jose Vizcaino to load the bases. Knoblauch's sacrifice fly tied the score and gave Benitez his third blown save in five postseason opportunities. And that does not count the ninth-inning lead he failed to hold in Game 6 of last year's National League Championship Series because he was the pitcher of record.</p>
        <p>Benitez has pitched most of the last month with an arthritic right knee that has been drained; he received a cortisone injection two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>''I'm pretty confident,'' Benitez said. ''When all the guys talk to me, that helps a lot. I don't have to think about it.''</p>
        <p>After Benitez allowed a game-tying home run to the Giants' J. T. Snow in the ninth inning of Game 2 of the division series, reliever Turk Wendell told him: ''We're not here without you. We need you. You better believe we need you and understand there's a lot of valuable players on this team but we are not where we are without Armando Benitez.''</p>
        <p>The Mets handed Orlando Hernandez his first postseason loss in 11 outings and they did it with pitching. Hernandez loomed over this game like the bully in grade school, ready to turn this series into a romp. The Mets' cast of unheralded players with checkered playoff resumes out-did him.</p>
        <p>After Rick Reed matched Hernandez for six innings, Wendell entered and retired Hernandez and Vizcaino on strikeouts to start the seventh inning. But Wendell walked Derek Jeter on five pitches, prompting Mets Manager Bobby Valentine to call on the left-hander Dennis Cook to face the left-handed David Justice. But Cook hit Justice on his right knee with his first pitch to push Jeter to second base. Bernie Williams swung through a 78-mile-an-hour pitch on a full count to end the inning.</p>
        <p>Cook's outings are never boring, and he had plenty of excitement left. He walked the left-handed Tino Martinez on four pitches to start the eighth. But as he was leaving the field, Cook began yelling at a fan seated behind the Mets' dugout. He retreated to the dugout before emerging again, this time flanked by two police officers as two other officers walked in front of the spectator on top of the dugout. Cook continued to speak his mind as the fan stood up and laughed. Cook finally retreated up the dugout runway.</p>
        <p>Reed admitted he succumbed to nerves in his last start against the Cardinals, when he allowed five runs, four earned, in three and a third innings. His teammate Al Leiter told Reed he did not look confident on the mound and Reed promised he would enjoy himself last night, in what could be his first and only World Series start.</p>
        <p>Despite the Mets' deficit, Reed said he had fun. He wasn't nervous. ''Believe it or not, I wasn't,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
