<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Series Thrills Lost on Fans Of Also-Rans</title>
    <meta content="25NYC.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/nyregion/25NYC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241833"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7D91231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Series Thrills Lost on Fans Of Also-Rans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clyde Haberman NYC column discusses plight of baseball fans living in New Yorkmetropolitan area who are neither New York Yankees nor New York Mets fans (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PAUL CAMPBELL was born in 1956, a year of almost mythic proportions for sports-minded New Yorkers. By now, even those in a trance for the last week must be aware that 1956 was the last time this city wallowed in the splendors and excesses of a Subway Series.</p>
        <p>Mr. Campbell, an executive at a nonprofit education agency in New York, grew up outside Cleveland. Poor guy. Despite living here for 17 years, he cannot get the Cleveland Indians out of his blood, a compulsion roughly akin to hitting himself on the head with a hammer twice a day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PAUL CAMPBELL was born in 1956, a year of almost mythic proportions for sports-minded New Yorkers. By now, even those in a trance for the last week must be aware that 1956 was the last time this city wallowed in the splendors and excesses of a Subway Series.</p>
        <p>Mr. Campbell, an executive at a nonprofit education agency in New York, grew up outside Cleveland. Poor guy. Despite living here for 17 years, he cannot get the Cleveland Indians out of his blood, a compulsion roughly akin to hitting himself on the head with a hammer twice a day.</p>
        <p>The Indians have not won a World Series in his lifetime, not since 1948. For much of the half-century that followed, they were plain awful. ''They represented mediocrity in their good years,'' Mr. Campbell said.</p>
        <p>So it is understandable that he would be unmoved by fellow New Yorkers, generally the native-born, who think that having not one but two local teams in the World Series is their due, even part of the natural order of the universe. These are people who carried on about the 44-year Subway Series drought as if they were the children of Israel wandering in the desert.</p>
        <p>They don't know from drought, Mr. Campbell said. ''Solipsistic,'' he called them. (We warned you he was an educator, a breed sometimes given to 75-cent words.)</p>
        <p>And what did he feel as he listened to their caterwauling?</p>
        <p>''Disdain,'' he said, though he added: ''It's not as strong as contempt. When I was younger, there might have been contempt. Now I'm more understanding.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone is so charitable.</p>
        <p>New York is filled with people who came here years ago to restart their lives, who are woven into the city's fabric as much as anyone from Pitkin Avenue or Delancey Street, but who cannot shake off the sports passions of their childhood. For them, having to watch this Yankees-Mets Series is like being asked to choose between Saddam Hussein and Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
        <p>''It's the only time I feel estranged from my city,'' said David Margolick, a writer for Vanity Fair and formerly for this newspaper. He held true to his beloved Boston Red Sox after giving up on New England for New York 20 years ago. ''My only consolation in the Subway Series,'' he said, ''is that no matter what happens, half of New York's insufferable baseball fans will be crushed.''</p>
        <p>Ouch!</p>
        <p>There is something to what he says, though. The city's self-absorption these days must be rough on those who migrated from elsewhere and remained faithful to teams that have not captured the big prize in almost anyone's memory.</p>
        <p>The accursed Red Sox have not won a World Series since 1918. The Chicago Cubs are even bigger sad sacks. They have not won since 1908. Those poor devils haven't even made it to the Series since 1945.</p>
        <p>For their fans, ''having to listen to New Yorkers yammer on endlessly about themselves is really awful,'' said Daniel Okrent, an editor at large at Time Inc. He used to root for the Tigers of his native Detroit, but, in an apparent burst of masochism, he switched fealty to the Cubs after arriving in New York years ago.</p>
        <p>O NE thing to be said about cheering for perennial losers is that it can build character.</p>
        <p>''I grew up five blocks from Wrigley Field,'' Michael Posner said, referring to the Cubs' ballpark. Mr. Posner has lived in New York for more than two decades as executive director of the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights. But his heart pines for Waveland Avenue in his hometown.</p>
        <p>''There couldn't be any better preparation for a career in human rights than rooting for the Cubs,'' he said. ''It teaches you to stand up for the weak and vulnerable in the face of more powerful forces.''</p>
        <p>The appeal of supporting habitual losers is not something every New Yorker can understand. But you could say that missed opportunities are the essence of baseball. The best hitters in the game, the very best, fail at the plate two times out of three. Few endeavors in life so generously reward imperfection, which helps explain why many writers over the years have found baseball to be a splendid metaphor for life, for family, for sex, for the federal Farm Credit Administration, whatever.</p>
        <p>Let's not get carried away, though. Losing is not all it's cracked up to be. Just ask Mr. Margolick, who is reluctantly cheering for the Mets in the Subway Series, mainly because he would rather chew on razor blades than stand with Yankee fans.</p>
        <p>''The Mets are really the Red Sox in this Series,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Maybe they can still win it.</p>
        <p>''If they're the Red Sox, they won't,'' he said glumly.</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
