<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Backs Cash Award in Race-Based Transfers</title>
    <meta content="25TRAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/nyregion/25TRAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gootman, Elissa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scheindlin, Shira A (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Louima, Abner</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3DE1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="420" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Backs Cash Award in Race-Based Transfers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISSA GOOTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gootman, Elissa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal District Court, Manhattan, Judge Shira A Scheindlin upholds jury's monetary awards to black police officers who were transferred to Brooklyn precinct after Abner Louima was tortured there in 1997; judge also upholds city's right to make race-based transfers in an emergency (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge has upheld a jury's monetary awards to black police officers who were transferred to a Brooklyn precinct after Abner Louima was tortured there in 1997.</p>
        <p>But the judge also upheld the city's right to make race-based transfers in an emergency, even though she said she could not envision an emergency that would warrant them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge has upheld a jury's monetary awards to black police officers who were transferred to a Brooklyn precinct after Abner Louima was tortured there in 1997.</p>
        <p>But the judge also upheld the city's right to make race-based transfers in an emergency, even though she said she could not envision an emergency that would warrant them.</p>
        <p>''The N.Y.P.D. asserts that in its entire history, this is the only incident of race-based transfers,'' wrote the judge, Shira A. Scheindlin of United States District Court in Manhattan. ''Thus, there is little reason to believe that another such incident will occur.''</p>
        <p>Judge Scheindlin's ruling, issued Wednesday and first reported Monday in The New York Law Journal,  came about four months after a District Court jury awarded $50,000 each to 22 black police officers and 2 black sergeants who were transferred to the 70th Precinct in Brooklyn to increase the number of black officers at the station house where Mr. Louima, who is black, was tortured.</p>
        <p>Three white officers were convicted in the case, which outraged many residents and brought an investigation by federal prosecutors in Brooklyn into the police department's treatment of officers accused of using excessive force.</p>
        <p>The city plans to appeal. James M. Lemonedes, chief counsel for the City Law Department, said the aftermath of the Louima incident absolutely constituted the sort of emergency warranting race-based transfers.</p>
        <p>''It's the city's position that it had both the authority to do it and was compelled to do it under these circumstances,'' Mr. Lemonedes said. ''The department did this to avoid the possibility of a race riot.''</p>
        <p>Judge Scheindlin refused to issue an injunction against such transfers, saying she did not want to tie the department's hands in advance.</p>
        <p>Linda M. Cronin, a lawyer for the  officers, said that while her clients might have preferred a court order preventing race-based transfers except in emergencies, the jury's verdict would deter the transfers in the future.</p>
        <p>''The jury obviously believed that the city was not able to prove that they had no other alternative to maintain peace and order,'' Ms. Cronin said. If the city could not prove the need for the transfers in this case, she said, ''they're never going to be able to prove it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
