<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rose by Another Name: White Merlot</title>
    <meta content="25MERL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/living/25MERL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFDF1531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rose by Another Name: White Merlot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC ASIMOV</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov comments on white merlot, noting more than half dozen white merlots are now on market; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WINEMAKERS struck gold in the 1980's by turning red zinfandel grapes into pink wine and calling it white. Now, 20 years later, they are going for the gold again with the latest bit of wine alchemy, white merlot.</p>
        <p>More than half a dozen white merlots are now on the market. Some are being made by some of the country's biggest producers, like Canandaigua Wine Company, which is selling white merlots through a new label, Nectar Valley, and Beringer Vineyards, which is hoping to sell half a million cases this year under its own label. Sutter Home Winery, the leading producer of white zinfandel, made 300,000 cases of white merlot in 1998, its second vintage. E. &amp; J. Gallo has test-marketed a white merlot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WINEMAKERS struck gold in the 1980's by turning red zinfandel grapes into pink wine and calling it white. Now, 20 years later, they are going for the gold again with the latest bit of wine alchemy, white merlot.</p>
        <p>More than half a dozen white merlots are now on the market. Some are being made by some of the country's biggest producers, like Canandaigua Wine Company, which is selling white merlots through a new label, Nectar Valley, and Beringer Vineyards, which is hoping to sell half a million cases this year under its own label. Sutter Home Winery, the leading producer of white zinfandel, made 300,000 cases of white merlot in 1998, its second vintage. E. &amp; J. Gallo has test-marketed a white merlot.</p>
        <p>And it's not only a California phenomenon. At least two French winemakers are exporting white merlots to the United States, while Abarbanel, a kosher winery in Cedarhurst, N.Y., is producing a white merlot with grapes from France.</p>
        <p>Unlike zinfandel, which has been an American phenomenon partly because the grape is grown almost nowhere else, merlot achieves greatness in Bordeaux, where it is a primary grape in St.-Emilion and Pomerol. Elsewhere it has always been a secondary blending grape, and was almost never used in roses because of its herbaceous quality.</p>
        <p>But in the 1990's, merlot took off in the United States, a craze that caused growers in California and elsewhere to tear out old vines and plant merlot. The producers of white merlot say frankly that they are hoping to capitalize on the American infatuation with merlot and with blush wines.</p>
        <p>''If we can take a hugely popular grape like merlot and make it appealing to the two-thirds of wine drinkers who drink only white and blush wines, that's a good thing,'' said Stan Hock, director of communications for Trinchero Family Estates, the owners of Sutter Home Winery in Napa Valley. ''It enables them to experience merlot in a different package, avoiding the body and tannin that those folks tend to find disagreeable.''</p>
        <p>Even the French are tailoring their product for the American market. About five years ago, Fortant de France, a French producer that was hoping to cash in on the white zinfandel craze, tried to interest Americans in traditional dry French roses.</p>
        <p>The results were dismal, said Stephen Klein, director of sales and marketing in the United States for Les Vins Skalli, owner of Fortant de France. Then the company tried making a merlot rose.</p>
        <p>''We've had amazing success with it,'' Mr. Klein said. ''Americans love merlot, they drink a lot of merlot, and it seems to work.'' This year, he said, the company expects to sell about 12,000 cases.</p>
        <p>The Fortant de France wine is nothing like the typical American white zinfandel, which is sweet, salmon colored and often a little fizzy. Though the Fortant merlot has just a touch of sweetness, it tastes dry and refreshing, an excellent value for $8 a bottle. American versions from Beringer ($8) and Nectar Valley ($5) are good as well, sweeter than the Fortant de France but not nearly as sweet as white zinfandel.</p>
        <p>Other bottles though, like a white merlot from Forest Glen ($8), are unpleasantly vegetal, a characteristic often found in inexpensive merlots.</p>
        <p>The most common method these days of making roses is to remove grape skins, which provide wine with color, tannins and body, from the grape juice shortly after the fruit is crushed. Leave the skins in longer and the wine gets darker. Taking them out sooner makes the wine paler. But even though almost any red grape can be used for roses, merlot roses had been practically unheard of until now.</p>
        <p>Some winemakers have shied away from white merlot. Glen Ellen, which makes white zinfandel, had considered producing a white merlot but rejected the idea.</p>
        <p>''There's an element of tannin that gives the wine bitterness,'' said Joel P. Butler, a spokesman for UDV Wines, which owns Glen Ellen. ''The winemakers felt they came out bitter and tannic, and most people don't buy these wines for the bitterness.''</p>
        <p>Aside from creating a market for a new product, a white merlot boom would give California winemakers something to do with a glut of merlot grapes. With the 1990's boom in merlot sales, the amount of merlot grapes planted in the state rocketed up to 47,638 acres in 1999 from a mere 7,435 in 1990. Many of these grapes are planted in California's Central Valley, the long inland spine stretching from Bakersfield north through Sacramento, where huge amounts of grapes are grown for inexpensive bulk wines and blending.</p>
        <p>In the process, the price of Central Valley merlot grapes has dropped to $200 to $300 a ton from $500 to $600 a ton five years ago, said Joseph W. Ciatti, a California wine broker.</p>
        <p>Not only can white merlot take care of the grape glut, it can also give white zinfandel drinkers something to aspire to, just as Chevrolet drivers used to move up to Buicks.</p>
        <p>''It is a target for the white zin consumer who may be getting bored with white zin but there aren't a lot of alternatives out there,'' said Conness Thompson, a spokeswoman for Canandaigua. ''Merlot has a lot of cachet; the idea is taking advantage of the cachet.''</p>
        <p>Such talk is not likely to appeal to wine snobs who would no sooner drink a white zinfandel than chug a six-pack. But just as dry roses can be found on just about every table in the south of France in the summer,  slightly sweet pink wines have their place in this world.</p>
        <p>And that place is ''next to food with a little bit of sweetness, or on the beach, or in the park waiting for tickets to Shakespeare,'' said Joshua Wesson, a wine consultant who is a partner in Best Cellars, a wine shop with branches in New York, Boston and Washington state. ''Good roses are good roses, whatever the grape.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
