<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Obscure Diversions Well Worth the Detour</title>
    <meta content="25TAST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/living/25TAST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TASTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Asimov, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0D61431F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Obscure Diversions Well Worth the Detour</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Eric Asimov</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Asimov, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Asimov comment on some little-known, hidden charmers of wines from various countries; drawing (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN this information-saturated world, it often feels as if nothing is left to discover, but it's amazing what can be found on the back roads of the world's wine regions.</p>
        <p>Consider the gros manseng, a white grape so obscure that even so noted an authority as Hugh Johnson lists it as a red grape in his ''Pocket Encyclopedia of Wine 2000.'' No matter. Domaine du Tariquet in Gascony produces an excellent fruity white with a touch of sweetness from the grape.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN this information-saturated world, it often feels as if nothing is left to discover, but it's amazing what can be found on the back roads of the world's wine regions.</p>
        <p>Consider the gros manseng, a white grape so obscure that even so noted an authority as Hugh Johnson lists it as a red grape in his ''Pocket Encyclopedia of Wine 2000.'' No matter. Domaine du Tariquet in Gascony produces an excellent fruity white with a touch of sweetness from the grape.</p>
        <p>Or how about the roussette, also called the altesse, a little-known grape from the equally little-known Bugey region in eastern France? Franck Peillot turns it into a delightfully fresh and aromatic white wine.</p>
        <p>France is not the only country with hidden charmers. Umbria, in Italy, is best known for lackluster Orvieto. But occasionally I've run across sagrantino di Montefalco, a rich, dry red wine made from the sagrantino grape, which has the personality Orvietos lack.</p>
        <p>The wines of the Basque region in Spain are as little known as they are hard to pronounce, but remember if you can the word ''txakoli'' (pronounced CHOCK-oh-lee), a synonym for fresh, light white wines that go beautifully with seafood.</p>
        <p>Mendocino County in California is not off the beaten trail, but it's rare that you find wine made from the charbono, an obscure grape with unknown origins. Ca'Vesta, a spinoff of Fife Vineyards, uses it to produce a rustic, gulpable red.</p>
        <p>Finally, while riesling is not an obscure grape, it is only occasionally turned into ice wine, made with grapes that have frozen on the vine, greatly concentrating their sugars. This arduous procedure, identified mostly with Germany, produces nectar of great sweetness and acidity. Inniskillin Wines in Canada makes ice wines that are delicious.</p>
        <p>DOMAINE DU TARIQUET, GROS MANSENG,  VIN DE PAYS DES COTES DE GASCOGNE 1998 $12  Aroma of peaches, slightly sweet yet refreshing, with a minerally finish.</p>
        <p>FRANCK PEILLOT, ALTESSE, ROUSSETTE DU BUGEY,  MONTAGNIEU, FRANCE 1999 $20  Fresh, pear-scented and delicious.</p>
        <p>TERRE DE 'TRINCI, SAGRANTINO DI MONTEFALCO, UMBRIA 1995 $23  Deep fragrant fruit wrapped in smoky tar; sweet and tannic.</p>
        <p>TXOMIN ETXANIZ, GETARIAKO TXAKOLI, SPAIN 1999 $15  Slightly fizzy with delightful apple, pear and citrus flavors.</p>
        <p>CA 'VESTA, CHARBONO, MENDOCINO 1997 $20  Grapey aromas, soft and appealing, but not a lot of backbone.</p>
        <p>INNISKILLIN, RIESLING, ICE WINE, NIAGARA PENINSULA 1998 (half bottle) $65  Thick and sweet, with strong orange and apricot flavors.</p>
        <p>Prices are those paid in various wine shops in the New York area.</p>
        <p>TASTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
