<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Minnesota Penalized by N.C.A.A.</title>
    <meta content="25MINN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/sports/25MINN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Collegiate Athletic Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Minnesota</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0D71531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Minnesota Penalized by N.C.A.A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Collegiate Athletic Association places University of Minnesota men's basketball program on probation for four years, takes away five scholarships and put limits on recruiting contacts for what organization calls serious academic violations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Collegiate Athletic Association placed the University of Minnesota men's basketball program on probation for four years yesterday, took away five scholarships and put limits on recruiting contacts for what the organization called the most serious violations to come before it in 20 years.</p>
        <p>The violations involved the former coach Clem Haskins, an academic adviser and a secretary who did more than 400 pieces of course work for at least 18 student-athletes from 1994 to 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Collegiate Athletic Association placed the University of Minnesota men's basketball program on probation for four years yesterday, took away five scholarships and put limits on recruiting contacts for what the organization called the most serious violations to come before it in 20 years.</p>
        <p>The violations involved the former coach Clem Haskins, an academic adviser and a secretary who did more than 400 pieces of course work for at least 18 student-athletes from 1994 to 1998.</p>
        <p>''The University of Minnesota is and should be deeply ashamed of what happened,'' said Jack Friedenthal, the chairman of the N.C.A.A.'s Division I committee on infractions and a professor of law at George Washington University.</p>
        <p>Still, the committee stopped short of banning Minnesota from participating in future postseason play and from imposing more serious sanctions because university officials had moved swiftly to investigate the scandal and offered comprehensive penalties of their own. For example, Mark Yudof, the university president, kept the Gophers from postseason play last season, took away three scholarships for this academic year and offered to repay 90 percent of the university's share for playing in the 1994, 1995 and 1997 N.C.A.A. basketball tournaments, an estimated $350,000.</p>
        <p>Minnesota Coach Dan Monson said that players and staff were ''ecstatic'' that no postseason ban was imposed. ''The last few days I've been really dreading and getting nervous for the fact of having to face those players like I did last year and tell them that dream is gone,'' Monson said. ''To be able to go to practice every day and have the opportunity to strive for something, to strive for that goal, is a very happy day for us.''</p>
        <p>The report, as well as Friedenthal, placed the blame for the violations on Haskins, his former academic adviser, Alonzo Newby, and a former office manager, Jan Gangelhoff. It was Gangelhoff who prompted the investigation in March 1999 when she told The St. Paul Pioneer Press about schoolwork she had done for Minnesota basketball players.</p>
        <p>''The violations were significant, widespread and intentional,'' the N.C.A.A. report said. ''More than that, their nature -- academic fraud -- undermined the bedrock foundation of a university and the operation of its intercollegiate athletics program.''</p>
        <p>Gangelhoff told The Associated Press that the report was ''thorough and just.''</p>
        <p>''I sighed with relief to see that the issue of lack of institutional control during Coach Haskins's reign was dealt with thoughtfully and seriously,'' Gangelhoff said. ''As I stated months ago, this recognition by the N.C.A.A. would allow them to send a strong message to member institutions about their serious commitment to academics.''</p>
        <p>Friedenthal said the investigation found that Newby went from office to office to get retroactive grading and intimidated instructors to make sure that basketball players received passing grades. It also found that Newby arranged for Gangelhoff to do the players' schoolwork with Haskins's knowledge.</p>
        <p>During the investigation, Friedenthal said Haskins withheld evidence and misled investigators, but ''eventually had to admit he didn't tell the truth.'' Haskins, Gangelhoff and Newby will have to go before the N.C.A.A. if they want to return to college sports. Newby and Gangelhoff must also go before the infractions committee if they want to return to college athletics.</p>
        <p>''He had complete control and everyone was answering to him and him alone,'' Friedenthal said of Haskins, who accepted a $1.5 million buyout months after Gangelhoff came forward. ''It can be a formula for this kind of disaster.''</p>
        <p>The N.C.A.A. also ordered that team records from the N.C.A.A. tournament and National Invitation Tournament -- and the tournament records of players who engaged in academic fraud from 1993-94 through 1998-99 -- be erased.</p>
        <p>In addition, all references to the program's success those years -- including its 1997 Final Four appearance -- must be expunged from everything from recruiting brochures to the banners in the university's field house.</p>
        <p>Friedenthal also admonished university officials. ''A rogue individual can bring a house down by doing things that are inappropriate and hiding them,'' he said. ''You need a vigilant administration that can smell it out.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
