<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Profit Is Strong at Pfizer and Schering-Plough, but Shares Fall</title>
    <meta content="Y25DRU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/business/25DRUG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pfizer Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Schering-Plough Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Petersen, Melody</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D71531F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="650" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Profit Is Strong at Pfizer and Schering-Plough, but Shares Fall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELODY PETERSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Petersen, Melody</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pfizer Inc says third-quarter net income increased to $1.71 billion, about 30 percent more than $1.3 billion it earned a year ago; sales were $7.2 billion, up 7 percent over $6.7 billion in year-earlier quarter; Schering-Plough Corp reports its net income rose 14 percent, to $591 million, up from $518 million last year; sales rose to $2.4 billion from $2.2 billion in 1999 period (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pfizer Inc. and the Schering-Plough Corporation said yesterday that their earnings for the third quarter were very strong as the companies continued to benefit from rising sales of prescription drugs, especially in the United States.</p>
        <p>Pfizer said that its third-quarter net income from operations increased to $1.71 billion, about 30 percent more than the $1.31 billion the company earned in the corresponding period last year. Those earnings amount to 27 cents a share, which surpassed the expectations of Wall Street analysts by 2 cents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pfizer Inc. and the Schering-Plough Corporation said yesterday that their earnings for the third quarter were very strong as the companies continued to benefit from rising sales of prescription drugs, especially in the United States.</p>
        <p>Pfizer said that its third-quarter net income from operations increased to $1.71 billion, about 30 percent more than the $1.31 billion the company earned in the corresponding period last year. Those earnings amount to 27 cents a share, which surpassed the expectations of Wall Street analysts by 2 cents.</p>
        <p>The amounts exclude special charges related to Pfizer's acquisition earlier this year of Warner-Lambert and other unexpected costs, including the company's withdrawal of Rezulin, a diabetes drug that was taken off pharmacy shelves in March amid questions about its safety. When those special items are included, Pfizer's third-quarter net income was $1.4 billion, a 23 percent increase over that last year.</p>
        <p>Despite the strong report, Pfizer's stock price fell $3.75 yesterday, or nearly 8 percent, to $43.25, as some investors were disappointed by the company's total revenue. Pfizer said its sales in the quarter were $7.2 billion, a 7 percent increase over the $6.7 billion in the quarter last year.</p>
        <p>Schering-Plough reported that its net income rose 14 percent to $591 million, or 40 cents a share, which matched the estimates of Wall Street analysts. It earned $518 million, or 35 cents a share, in last year's third quarter.</p>
        <p>Sales in the quarter rose to $2.4 billion from $2.2 billion in the 1999 period. The company's heavily advertised allergy drug Claritin was a top contributor to that increase. Schering-Plough sold $787 million of Claritin in the third quarter, a 10 percent increase over last year.</p>
        <p>Claritin, which will lose its patent protection in 2002, now makes up about a third of the company's sales. To protect its monopoly on the drug, Schering-Plough is lobbying in Congress to extend the patent's expiration date. It is also planning to soon release a new allergy drug that it expects will have fewer side effects than Claritin.</p>
        <p>In trading yesterday, Schering-Plough's stock fell 25 cents, closing at $52.50.</p>
        <p>Some analysts said they were disappointed in Pfizer's total prescription drug sales. ''They are not as robust as they have been for the last three or four years,'' said Hemant K. Shah, an independent drug stock analyst in Warren, N.J. ''Maybe during the Warner-Lambert merger, they took their eyes off the ball.''</p>
        <p>He pointed to sales of the antidepressant Zoloft as an example of the slowing revenue. Zoloft -- which had sales in the third quarter of $555 million, or 7 percent more than in the period last year -- is not selling as well as two competing medicines, SmithKline Beecham's Paxil or American Home Products' Effexor, Mr. Shah said.</p>
        <p>Of Pfizer's share price, he added, ''The real problem is that this is an expensive stock; a slight disappointment can take a significant toll.''</p>
        <p>But yesterday, in a conference call with analysts, Pfizer executives said that their company had never been stronger.</p>
        <p>They said the sales of some drugs -- including Lipitor, the top-selling cholesterol drug -- had been hurt by unusual buying patterns by drug wholesalers and not by a slowdown in prescriptions.</p>
        <p>They noted that other drugs, including Viagra and Zithromax, an antibiotic, had very strong sales. And they said that Pfizer's profit margin, already among the highest in the industry, is getting even better.</p>
        <p>In the third quarter, Pfizer earned almost 19 percent in profit on its sales. The company said its profit margin was improving as it became more efficient at manufacturing, eliminated some costs with the Warner-Lambert merger and paid less in taxes.</p>
        <p>Said William C. Steere Jr., the chairman and chief executive, ''These are indeed exciting times for Pfizer.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
