<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Austin's 'Dellionaires' Aren't Ready for the Ranch Just Yet</title>
    <meta content="25BARR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARKETING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Austin (Tex)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dell Computer Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Courtney</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Austin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DE123FF936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1244" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Austin's 'Dellionaires' Aren't Ready for the Ranch Just Yet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COURTNEY BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Courtney</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article surveys growing boom in electronic commerce in Austin, Texas; boom is fueled and driven by former employees of Dell Computer who became millionaires through stock ownership or options; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY wheel has a hub. In Seattle, Microsoft laid the groundwork for the broader software scene that has grown up there, luring talented young people to the Northwest, then turning them into millionaires able to comfortably jump ship and start their own companies.</p>
        <p>Silicon Valley's more varied endeavors reflected the influence of alumni of Hewlett-Packard, Fairchild Semiconductor, the Xerox Palo Alto Research Center and Stanford University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY wheel has a hub. In Seattle, Microsoft laid the groundwork for the broader software scene that has grown up there, luring talented young people to the Northwest, then turning them into millionaires able to comfortably jump ship and start their own companies.</p>
        <p>Silicon Valley's more varied endeavors reflected the influence of alumni of Hewlett-Packard, Fairchild Semiconductor, the Xerox Palo Alto Research Center and Stanford University.</p>
        <p>Then there are the former employees of Dell Computer, the leading direct seller of personal computers, who became millionaires through stock ownership or options and are driving the growing and increasingly varied e-commerce boom here. By some counts, there are thousands of these former Dell employees.</p>
        <p>Just what do these rich young retirees from a hardware company bring to a scene that is increasingly dominated by software and commerce?</p>
        <p>Cash, for one thing.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of Dellionaires that have to place their money somewhere,'' said Andrew Harris, a former president of Dell International, who runs a start-up company, HandTech.com, which sells computer products and offers personalized technical support.</p>
        <p>For another, they have too much energy to relax and enjoy ''life on the ranch,'' as Mr. Harris described his time between Dell and HandTech.</p>
        <p>Bruce A. Ezell, another Dellionaire, said, ''There was a saying that working at Dell was like jumping out of an airplane with your hair on fire -- there was an extreme sense of urgency to the corporate culture.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ezell, who helped coordinate Dell's move into software and peripherals, is trying to match money from former Dell workers with start-up companies, as the head of a venture capital firm, Techxas Ventures.</p>
        <p>Finally, there was the perception  at Dell that a hardware business was more than just a hardware business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ezell and Mr. Harris both said that Dell had more influence as a fast marketer of good computers than as a technology laboratory. The company is known for ''its ability to package technology into a solution,'' Mr. Ezell said.</p>
        <p>This emphasis trained Dell employees and managers to look beyond the manufacturing of computers and see how technology fit into the new economy. When workers left, they took that knowledge with them and spun permutations that have made Austin a center of e-commerce.</p>
        <p>But it is not just Dell. Austin has companies like the Trilogy Development Group, which provides software to automate sales and other business operations, and Tivoli Systems Inc., which develops software to manage computer systems. Both companies have spawned technology start-ups. Tivoli is now a division of I.B.M.</p>
        <p>Dell's influence, however, may have the greatest reach.</p>
        <p>At HandTech.com, which Mr. Harris founded with Martin Slagter, the former president of Dell Europe, the focus is on the ''need-help majority,'' providing Web systems for computer resellers. That contrasts with the ''don't-need-help minority'' that Mr. Harris said Dell was concentrating on; that is, ''the tech heads, which developed into the business model for the Fortune 500 companies.''</p>
        <p>At Techxas Ventures, Mr. Ezell compared his strategy for capitalizing on technology growth with the early days of the gold rush.</p>
        <p>''Before the railroads were built, you could get gold out of the mine, but you couldn't easily get it to market,'' he said. ''Railroads ultimately led to faster transportation, which led to technology improvement in ways to mine and bring more gold out.</p>
        <p>''The same holds true with the Internet,'' he said. ''We're not investing in the information companies'' or  gold miners. ''We're investing in the infrastructure, the guys that sell the pickaxes and lifting equipment.''</p>
        <p>FOR Mr. Ezell, who left Dell in 1998, the company also underscored the importance of corporate frugality, emphasized by its founder and chairman, Michael Dell.</p>
        <p>''We sat in a management meeting at Dell,'' Mr. Ezell said. ''There were probably about 100 managers, so we all fit into one room. Michael was talking about how we have to continue to lower our costs. And he said: 'Just this morning I was sitting in my office and there was a credenza there, and I said: 'Why do I need this credenza? It's full of all this stuff I don't need. Why are we spending money on credenzas?'</p>
        <p>''There was a pause,'' Mr. Ezell continued, ''and then Joel Kocher, the president of Dell USA at the time, stood up, and said, 'Michael, you can have my credenza today.'</p>
        <p>''The rest of us -- sitting in the audience as managers -- are saying, 'Well, what are we supposed to do?' So all of a sudden another hand went up, and someone said, 'You can have mine,' and then another hand went up, and before Michael knew it we sent around a pad of paper and everybody who had a credenza signed the list and said, 'Come take my credenza.'</p>
        <p>''And for a three-month time period,'' Mr. Ezell said, ''the Dell factory outlet in Austin was the only place in the country where you could get a smoking-hot deal on a wooden Kimball credenza bundled with a used laser printer for $300.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ezell said the emphasis on keeping costs low has led to a strategy in which an e-business does not build a warehouse to hold inventory, but sends the order to a wholesale distributor. He estimated that more than 50 percent of dot-coms use the method pioneered partly by Dell.</p>
        <p>It is a method that Mr. Harris has taken to HandTech.</p>
        <p>''At Dell, you learned that 'inventory is anathema,' '' Mr. Harris said in his office, where he oversees 110 employees on Austin's Loop 360, which, like Sand Hill Road in Silicon Valley, is becoming a corridor for technology developers and venture capitalists.</p>
        <p>Steering clear of inventory is important in the technology reseller industry for the company that is trying to develop a viable business, Mr. Harris added.</p>
        <p>''In the 1980's this was an eye-opening concept'' he said. ''And at Dell there was an emphasis on 'thinking outside the box.' The company wouldn't be hampered by what the history tells you is right or wrong.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ezell, Mr. Harris and others say that Austin's new economy continues to be shaped by Dell's influence. Mr. Ezell says that Austin is now seen as a technology mecca for venture capitalists. There are a lot of future Dellionaires waiting in the wings, he said. ''We say they're 'vesting in peace,' '' he added, laughing.</p>
        <p>Hans Severiens, an investment banker turned venture capitalist who manages Band of Angels Fund, a group of 150 high-technology investors in Silicon Valley, said: ''People always ask me about other parts of the country, and I say, 'Well, you've got to have a certain infrastructure to make these things work; you've got to have money, an intellectual center, like a good university, a decent climate and the stimulation of other companies.' And I generally come up with two or three places. Austin is one of them.''</p>
        <p>But money, courtesy of Dell, may still be the biggest factor in Austin.</p>
        <p>''It's just easier for young businesses to get cash in Austin, and that's definitely had an impact,'' Mr. Harris said. ''An idea is not much good without money.''</p>
        <p>MARKETING Courtney Barry writes about technology and business in Austin, Tex.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Courtney Barry writes about technology and business in Austin, Tex.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
