<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Call It What You Want, It's Gossip and I Love It</title>
    <meta content="25GOSS$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="E-Commerce" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEB CELEBS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gossip</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">miller, lia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gossip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4DE103FF936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Call It What You Want, It's Gossip and I Love It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIA MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">miller, lia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article reveals Web addresses and areas of specialization of Web sites dedicated to gossip and inside information on media industries and famous individuals; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHERE there are stars, there is gossip. And the Web, which was originally made to spread data among military researchers, has turned out to be even better at spreading the dish, especially on those fast connections at work. These days, news about your favorites' flings travels the world faster than you can say ''Rocco Ritchie'' (the name of Madonna's second child -- if you didn't know that, you need to check out a few of these sites). And with interactive forums and chat rooms, news is analyzed and digested more quickly and by more people than ever before, leading to . . . more gossip.</p>
        <p>There is a huge variety of offerings, from those run by the devoted fan to the giant site run by E! Entertainment. Just remember, gossip is only as reliable as its source. The following sites are some that are used by those who make gossip their business. Your boss will never know.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHERE there are stars, there is gossip. And the Web, which was originally made to spread data among military researchers, has turned out to be even better at spreading the dish, especially on those fast connections at work. These days, news about your favorites' flings travels the world faster than you can say ''Rocco Ritchie'' (the name of Madonna's second child -- if you didn't know that, you need to check out a few of these sites). And with interactive forums and chat rooms, news is analyzed and digested more quickly and by more people than ever before, leading to . . . more gossip.</p>
        <p>There is a huge variety of offerings, from those run by the devoted fan to the giant site run by E! Entertainment. Just remember, gossip is only as reliable as its source. The following sites are some that are used by those who make gossip their business. Your boss will never know.</p>
        <p>PAGE6.COM  (www.page6.com) -- Michael Musto, whose popular gossip column La Dolce Musto can be found at www.  villagevoice.com, calls Page6.com ''an amazing compendium of gossip. You find out things even about yourself that you didn't realize you had done yet.''</p>
        <p>THE AWFUL TRUTH  (www.eonline.com) -- All of E! Online is delicious, but the take-no-prisoners attitude of Ted Casablanca's column is especially great for those guilty-pleasure tidbits.</p>
        <p>AIN'T IT COOL NEWS  (www.aint-it-cool.com) -- Self-acknowledged ''head geek'' Harry Knowles (whose nerdy, cinema-obsessed persona has been parodied on the Simpsons) runs the site for the freshest film industry news: casting, insider buzz on coming films and unauthorized previews.</p>
        <p>JIM ROMENESKO'S MEDIA NEWS  (www.poynter.org/medianews/) -- The most popular (and talked about) site for juicy journalism gossip. The site has turned the tables on those who dish it out and has become an institution.</p>
        <p>MISS TRUTH  (www.cdnow.com/allstar/ misstruth) -- A cool site for pop music gossip. This is Liz Smith for Generation Y.</p>
        <p>THE VELVET ROPE  (www.velvetrope.com) -- The site  for music industry insiders.</p>
        <p>INSIDE  (www.inside.com) -- Its debut made a big splash in June. The founders -- Kurt Andersen, Michael Hirschorn et al. -- are devoted to fulfilling your every insider wish with sections on film, music, books, media, TV and digital media.</p>
        <p>PUBLISHERS LUNCH  (www.publisherslunch.com) -- The latest about the book industry. The ''deals page'' gets to the marrow with real numbers and tells who paid how much for what.</p>
        <p>TVSPY.COM  (www.tvspy.com) -- The Water Cooler provides a forum for TV insiders to gossip about their jobs, bosses and co-workers. You won't read about Brad and Jennifer here, but you can pick up a lot of insider news straight from the source.</p>
        <p>THE SMOKING GUN  (www.thesmokinggun.com) -- Though not exactly a gossip site, The Smoking Gun obtains and publishes celebrities' legal and government documents. For example, you can find William H. Gates's mug shot and the wedding certificate of Angelina Jolie and Billy Bob Thornton.</p>
        <p>WEB CELEBS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
