<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3rd Party Lament: Anyone Listening?; It's Not Easy Being Green. Or Libertarian or Socialist.</title>
    <meta content="25THIR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/politics/25THIR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241798"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Dean E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunau, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clifton, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5DA1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3rd Party Lament: Anyone Listening?; It's Not Easy Being Green. Or Libertarian or Socialist.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Dean E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses how third-party candidates for US Senate from New York are being virtually ignored by public and media as most attention focuses on Democrat Hillary Rodham Clinton and Republican Repr Rick Lazio; Mark J Dunau (Green Party), Jeffrey E Graham (Independence Party) and John Clifton (Libertarian Party) comment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a pretty safe bet that Mark J. Dunau is the only New York candidate in the Senate race who has an organic salad at a Manhattan restaurant named in his honor. He is without a doubt the only candidate who lives in a barn where the bathroom has curtains for walls and the guest quarters are known as the Love Shack. And he alone sees political capital in boasting that Click and Clack of public radio's ''Car Talk'' once broadcast a question about his old Suburban.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunau is the Green Party candidate for Senate, one of six people other than Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio who want to represent New York in the Senate. If Mrs. Clinton shared some of Mr. Dunau's peculiarities -- or, for that matter, embraced his 23-page manifesto, which calls for the legalization of marijuana, a cap on credit card interest rates and a ban on spreading sewage sludge on farmlands -- it would be a sensation from Buffalo to Bombay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a pretty safe bet that Mark J. Dunau is the only New York candidate in the Senate race who has an organic salad at a Manhattan restaurant named in his honor. He is without a doubt the only candidate who lives in a barn where the bathroom has curtains for walls and the guest quarters are known as the Love Shack. And he alone sees political capital in boasting that Click and Clack of public radio's ''Car Talk'' once broadcast a question about his old Suburban.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunau is the Green Party candidate for Senate, one of six people other than Hillary Rodham Clinton and Representative Rick A. Lazio who want to represent New York in the Senate. If Mrs. Clinton shared some of Mr. Dunau's peculiarities -- or, for that matter, embraced his 23-page manifesto, which calls for the legalization of marijuana, a cap on credit card interest rates and a ban on spreading sewage sludge on farmlands -- it would be a sensation from Buffalo to Bombay.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Dunau, 48, is a playwright-turned-organic-farmer, not a first-lady-turned-top-dog-political-contender. Like the other so-called third party candidates in the race, Mr. Dunau takes himself seriously and is impatiently waiting for most other New Yorkers to do the same.</p>
        <p>''My issues of sustenance are dead on,'' Mr. Dunau said recently from behind the wheel of his beat-up delivery truck, loaded with 24 coolers of greens, roots and squash grown on his farm in Delaware County and destined for restaurant and catering-service kitchens in Manhattan and Brooklyn. ''But I am dubious about whether I will have enough money for a radio campaign. I've already borrowed $3,000 on a credit card at 9.9 percent interest.''</p>
        <p>The attention deficit in this Senate race extends well beyond Mr. Dunau. Even Mr. Lazio, the Republican nominee, complains of being at a disadvantage because of Mrs. Clinton's blinding celebrity. (Who has not heard of the first lady?)</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lazio (he has nonetheless raised more than $29 million to her $25 million) can expect no sympathy from the cast of larger unknowns on the Nov. 7 ballot, who include the  radio talk show host Jeffrey E. Graham of the Independence Party (the third largest party in the state) and the would-be revolutionary Jacob J. Perasso of the Socialist Workers Party. The party offers no membership numbers. Mr. Perasso says it is not looking for votes, but to overthrow greedy capitalists.</p>
        <p>''One of the reasons we don't get coverage as much is because we sometimes express hostile attitudes toward the media,'' said John Clifton, a social worker from Jamaica, Queens, the Libertarian Party candidate, whose favorite campaign themes are expanding personal liberty and limiting government. ''We think the media, along with the Democratic and Republican Parties, are often representatives of an established order that has a tilt toward the maintenance of the status quo.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clifton, 41, is running his statewide bid for office on a budget of  $10,000. That is more than most of the other third party contenders have, but at last count, it amounted to only one-2,500th of what Mrs. Clinton has raised and one-2,900th of Mr. Lazio's bankroll. In February, Mrs. Clinton  spent more than Mr. Clifton's entire campaign budget on stuffed mushrooms, shrimp, pasta and other Italian specialties for a fund-raiser catered by Joey's, a restaurant in Syracuse.</p>
        <p>Trying to make his dollars last longer, Mr. Clifton has found a cheap Internet-based toll-free telephone service. Mr. Clifton said a toll-free number (his is 877-407-5493) adds heft to a candidacy, but in his case, callers rarely get more than a brief recording proclaiming ''peace and freedom'' and asking them to please leave a message. It is not uncommon for candidate Clifton to take days to get back to the callers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clifton says that he and most of the other Senate contenders cannot afford to skip their day jobs or hire a staff for their campaigns. It is a case of real people versus professional politicians, he and the other challengers assert.</p>
        <p>''I did get a two-week stretch of vacation this month, but it was not feasible to get more time off,'' said Mr. Clifton, who is the communications manager for a nonprofit group, Services for the Underserved, in Bedford-Stuyvesant. ''I am hoping to achieve what I need to through interviews, the Web site and weekend appearances.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunau, the Green Party candidate, can book no appointments on Mondays or Tuesdays because he must harvest his vegetables and haul them to New York City. In the primary, when he beat Al Lewis (better known as Grandpa in ''The Munsters'' television series) and the political writer Ronnie Dugger, he walked the length of Long Island to attract attention. It took him three weeks because he needed to make frequent working trips back to the farm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunau's 12-year-old son, Bera, pitches in when he can, fielding questions from a visiting reporter and joining his father on the picket line (Mr. Dunau seems to protest more than most, especially when he and the others were excluded from the Clinton-Lazio debates).</p>
        <p>But Bera (who is named for the Hindu god of protection) is usually  too busy studying the encyclopedia and other thick books as part of his home schooling at their Hancock farm to become too invested in his father's candidacy.</p>
        <p>''I am a self-employed family farmer, who with his wife supports two children by growing and selling organic vegetables,'' Mr. Dunau says in one of his favorite stump speeches. ''Rick Lazio and and Hillary Clinton are corporate lawyers. New York needs a corporate lawyer as its next U.S. senator like it needs a hole in the head.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham, 45, a former mayor of Watertown who owns two taverns and is host of a daily radio talk show, had to interrupt an interview recently to help out behind the counter when a rush of after-work customers overwhelmed his downtown Watertown establishment.</p>
        <p>Business is business, he explained apologetically, especially in an upstate town still waiting for signs of the Clinton-Gore economic boom. Mr. Graham makes a lot of his upstate credentials -- he and Mr. Dunau are the only candidates not from New York City or its suburbs -- and the inability of either major party to achieve much there.</p>
        <p>But even in upstate New York, it is tough to attract attention from Watertown, or in Mr. Graham's case, the right kind of attention. He recently made the six-hour trip to Westchester County at the invitation of the N.A.A.C.P., only to be turned away at the front door.</p>
        <p>The group had meant to invite Larry O. Graham, a Democratic candidate for Congress from Westchester County, he was told. But Mr. Graham persisted and eventually got two minutes to speak about his main themes of promoting political reform, cutting taxes and protecting individual rights.</p>
        <p>John O. Adefope, 34, the candidate of the Right to Life Party, works as a  telephone company design engineer to support his wife and three children in Brooklyn. He barely finds time to give interviews or do much campaigning, though he expects to take some vacation during the final days of the race to attend candidates forums and travel upstate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adefope is running a ''back to the family'' campaign that calls for an end to abortion, the introduction of prayer in public schools and renewed patriotism. He has also proposed a ballot initiative that would allow a two-thirds majority of states to bypass Congress and pass federal laws.</p>
        <p>''I think the average American has been left out of the political process,''  Mr. Adefope said. ''If you don't vote what you believe, then you won't get what you want.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perasso of the Socialist Workers Party works nights at a print shop for the alternative press in the Bronx, putting him in bed when most other candidates are at least thinking about wooing voters during the daytime.</p>
        <p>But skipping the job is out of the question. Mr. Perasso depends on his weekly salary of $200, and, he says, he is more committed to getting into broader circulation books by Malcolm X, Che Guevara and his other favorite authors at the print shop than he is in scoring campaign points.</p>
        <p>Shortly after graduating from college in Santa Cruz, Calif., in 1998, Mr. Perasso worked 11 months at a slaughterhouse in Chicago so that he could better understand the hardships of assembly line workers. His most ambitious campaign swing to date was to Australia and New Zealand, where he joined workers on picket lines and did radio interviews in support of ''an international revolutionary movement.''</p>
        <p>He sees no contradiction in campaigning half a world away, he says, because the workers' cause knows no borders.</p>
        <p>''We believe the history of the working class movement is so crucial to the building of our movement,'' said Mr. Perasso, 24, who moved last summer to the Bronx from Detroit (more meatpacking jobs there) and who would like to see the United States follow the model of  Fidel Castro's Cuba. ''If there were no books, I don't believe a socialist revolution could happen.''</p>
        <p>Only Louis P. Wein, who is suing New York City over a $300 million development proposal he led in Staten Island that recently went sour, can take to the road full time as the nominee of the Constitution Party.</p>
        <p>A Republican, Mr. Wein is positioning himself as the ''true conservative'' in the race, emphasizing his antiabortion stance, his opposition to gun control and his Republican credentials (his resume says he was a special consultant on antipoverty programs in the Nixon administration). He says Mr. Lazio and Mrs. Clinton are exactly alike: liberals.</p>
        <p>But even Mr. Wein, who ran for governor in 1990 on the Right to Life line, has little money to spend on his candidacy, which he says is really a primer for a run for governor in two years.</p>
        <p>''I lost all of my wealth in this deal with the city,'' said Mr. Wein, 59, of Staten Island. ''I have under $10,000 for the campaign. But I've traveled 2,000 miles in the last weeks around the state giving speeches and press conferences.''</p>
        <p>In the end, with the odds against them, Mr. Wein and the others are counting on the sentiments of people like Brian Begeal, a dairy farmer in Delaware County, to make sure their candidacies are not rendered irrelevant.</p>
        <p>Mr. Begeal lives down the road from Mr. Dunau, the Green candidate, and early one recent morning, while milking his cows, Mr. Begeal said he had not made up his mind about the election but was clear about one thing: He had no intention of voting for Mrs. Clinton or Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>''I'd rather vote against someone than for someone,'' Mr. Begeal said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunau, who is counting on Mr. Begeal's vote, acknowledged that his neighbor's backhanded endorsement was not the stuff that builds campaigns. But with 1,300 pounds of vegetables to deliver, and seven acres needing to be picked for the next week's harvest, he was not about to quibble.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes,'' he said, ''I don't even know if I'm coming or going.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
