<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="25MBRF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/nyregion/25MBRF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DC1231F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>WESTCHESTER: AIRPORT ROAD TRUCE -- Westchester County and Greenwich, Conn., declared a truce yesterday over a small road near the Westchester County Airport. In January, Greenwich closed westbound traffic on Gateway Lane, a popular shortcut to the airport, forcing Greenwich residents to look for alternate routes. Andrew J. Spano, the Westchester County executive, retaliated by erecting signs inviting drivers to complain about Greenwich. After several months of meetings, the two sides agreed to reopen the road as long as weight limits were placed on nearby roads to discourage trucks, and Gateway Lane was narrowed to limit speeding. Westchester agreed to remove its signs.</p>
        <p>David W. Chen (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>WESTCHESTER: AIRPORT ROAD TRUCE -- Westchester County and Greenwich, Conn., declared a truce yesterday over a small road near the Westchester County Airport. In January, Greenwich closed westbound traffic on Gateway Lane, a popular shortcut to the airport, forcing Greenwich residents to look for alternate routes. Andrew J. Spano, the Westchester County executive, retaliated by erecting signs inviting drivers to complain about Greenwich. After several months of meetings, the two sides agreed to reopen the road as long as weight limits were placed on nearby roads to discourage trucks, and Gateway Lane was narrowed to limit speeding. Westchester agreed to remove its signs.</p>
        <p>David W. Chen (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: CHARGES DISMISSED IN PARK ATTACK -- A Manhattan judge dismissed sexual abuse and robbery charges yesterday against two men who were arrested in attacks on women in Central Park after the Puerto Rican Day Parade in June. An assistant district attorney, Maxine Rosenthal, told the judge there was little videotaped evidence against the two men, Tremayne Bain, 24, of Hempstead, N.Y., and David Rowe, 24, of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Katherine E. Finkelstein (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: SUBWAY STATION REPAIRS -- A $26 million renovation is scheduled to begin soon at the East 86th Street and Lexington Avenue subway station, where the lighting is poor and flooding has caused structural damage. State Senator Roy M. Goodman and E. Virgil Conway, the chairman of the Metropolitan Transportation Authority, said yesterday that the four-year project at the station, one of the busiest in the city with 64,000 passengers daily, is the first of 64 station renovations.</p>
        <p>Susan Saulny (NYT)</p>
        <p>QUEENS: MODIFIED FOOD CRITICIZED -- Environmental and consumer groups testified at a public hearing yesterday on a possible statewide ban on genetically modified foods. They cited last month's Taco Bell recall of products with modified corn that had been approved only for animal consumption. ''The Taco Bell scandal shows that the federal regulations aren't working and that's why we need the state to step in,'' Andy Zimmerman, a coordinator for the New York Biotech Action Network, said in an interview. Food companies say modification increases crop yields and poses no danger to humans. The State Assembly is considering a five-year ban on genetically modified crops.</p>
        <p>Tara Bahrampour (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: ALGERIAN TERROR TRIAL -- A judge ruled yesterday that statements to authorities made by an Algerian accused of helping smuggle explosives into the United States could be used at his trial because they had been given voluntarily. The ruling by Judge John F. Keenan of Federal District Court came after a hearing during which the Algerian, Abdel Ghani Meskini, 32, described his interviews with the authorities after he was arrested in Brooklyn on Dec. 30. Mr. Meskini and Mokhtar Haouari, another Algerian, who was arrested in Canada and brought to the United States for trial, are charged with conspiring since 1997 to support a terrorist group.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: CONNECTION TROUBLES -- Silicon Alley companies plan to tell the City Council tomorrow that slow installation of high-speed Internet connections and other infrastructure problems are hurting their ability to do business. Alice O'Rourke, the executive director of New York New Media Association, said technology companies based in New york wait six to eight weeks for the installation of high-speed connections at a time when the troubled Internet economy makes quick installation especially critical.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: CASINO REGULATOR NAMED -- William Sommeling, 64, was named to the state agency that regulates and issues licenses to casinos in Atlantic City. Mr. Sommeling, an undersheriff in Ocean County since 1989, has begun a new five-year term. He fills the vacancy on the five-member commission created in September 1998 when Bradford Smith, the chairman, resigned. Mr. Sommeling has done private surveillance work for the Claridge casino and the former TropWorld, a commission spokesman said yesterday.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: DEPRESSION REMOVED FROM SURVEY -- The Connecticut Bar Examining Committee has eliminated, for now, clinical depression from the list of ''psychotic disorders'' prospective Connecticut lawyers must disclose. The survey is designed to evaluate applicants' ''fitness to practice law,'' Raymond W. Beckwith, chairman of the examining committee, said yesterday. The survey, which must be taken by applicants for the next bar examination in February, asks whether schizophrenia, paranoia or other serious mental illnesses have been diagnosed in the previous five years. The committee wanted to reconsider depression because it is a less-debilitating disorder than others on the list, Mr. Beckwith said.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>STAMFORD: STRIKING JANITORS ARRESTED -- Four striking janitors and a union official were arrested Monday evening after they sat in the street near the train station to bring attention to the janitors' push for higher wages and health insurance. The police accused them of obstructing traffic, which is punishable by up to 90 days in jail. The janitors, among more than 300 Fairfield County janitors who are on strike, say their wages of $6.15 an hour are too low to support a family. The janitors and the official with the Service Employees International Union were released without bail.</p>
        <p>Steven Greenhouse (NYT)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Today</p>
        <p>SEXUAL ASSAULT LAW -- City Council considers urging the New York Legislature to create a new criminal charge of ''gang sexual assault.'' Committee Room, second floor, City Hall, Manhattan, 10 am. Information: 212-788-6850.</p>
        <p>SECURITY GUARDS AT HOSPITALS -- The City Council has scheduled a hearing on the Health and Hospitals Corporation's plan to privatize security guards at the city's hospitals. Council Chambers, City Hall, Manhattan, 1 p.m.. Information: 212-788-6856.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
