<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Twisting the Classics: Italian Goes Nuova</title>
    <meta content="25REST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/25/living/25REST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fernicola Osteria (NYC Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEED61431F936A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Twisting the Classics: Italian Goes Nuova</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes reviews Fernicola Osteria, Italian restaurant in Williamsburg, Brooklyn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FERNICOLA OSTERIA clings to the upper edge of Williamsburg like a climber to a sheer sheet of granite. Two steps to the north, a long, lonely industrial strip extends deep into Greenpoint. Out the front window, across Kent Avenue, a stark wooden fence runs along a scrubby stretch of riverfront park that attracts the braver kind of jogger. The restaurant, a 100-year-old tavern, sheds a warm, hospitable light onto a cold-looking street. It seems a million miles away from the big city across the river, whose pinpoint lights glitter like an artificial galaxy.</p>
        <p>The regulars can still get a beer at the bar up front, where the local sand hogs gathered years ago, and watch sports on an overhead television, although remodeling has given the barroom a swanky lounge feel, with low-slung chairs upholstered in velvet. It's the dining room that holds some real surprises, though. If this is Italian food, it's like nothing Brooklyn is used to.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FERNICOLA OSTERIA clings to the upper edge of Williamsburg like a climber to a sheer sheet of granite. Two steps to the north, a long, lonely industrial strip extends deep into Greenpoint. Out the front window, across Kent Avenue, a stark wooden fence runs along a scrubby stretch of riverfront park that attracts the braver kind of jogger. The restaurant, a 100-year-old tavern, sheds a warm, hospitable light onto a cold-looking street. It seems a million miles away from the big city across the river, whose pinpoint lights glitter like an artificial galaxy.</p>
        <p>The regulars can still get a beer at the bar up front, where the local sand hogs gathered years ago, and watch sports on an overhead television, although remodeling has given the barroom a swanky lounge feel, with low-slung chairs upholstered in velvet. It's the dining room that holds some real surprises, though. If this is Italian food, it's like nothing Brooklyn is used to.</p>
        <p>Barbara Bogart, the chef, comes to Williamsburg from Mesa Grill, Tribeca Grill and a brief stint at AZ. She did not pack her bags to make eggplant Parmesan. Anthony Fernicola, the owner, asked her to come up with something different, something to catch the eye of the younger people moving into the area, and she has responded with an aggressively modernized Italian menu that touches on the most sensitive issues in Italian cuisine. Can there be such a thing as nuova cucina? If so, does the world want it, or need it?</p>
        <p>The answer, based on the evidence of Fernicola Osteria, is a rousing maybe. When Ms. Bogart aims straight, she can hit her targets. But there are more than a few innocent bystanders getting mowed down here.</p>
        <p>Foie gras, cured in grappa and served with arugula and sour cherries, makes a strong argument for Ms. Bogart's approach. Grappa neatly cuts some of the richness of the foie gras, with the bitter arugula lending support and the cherries a piquant sweetness. Square slices of bresaola, looking like expensive leather, trade off earthy, smoky flavors with sauteed mushrooms and melted truffled goat cheese. A crispy pile of deep-fried whitebait finds the right match in a lemony, custard-like aioli that's hard not to eat on its own.</p>
        <p>Soppressata croutons add zing to fried squid heaped on a bed of frisee and sharpened with little grapefruit slices, and Gorgonzola brulee, although it sounds precious, feels right at home with figs and prosciutto.</p>
        <p>On the appetizer side of the ledger, then, Ms. Bogart builds up some impressive scores, and for those who like their Italian food plain, there's always the sideboard antipasto spread, consisting mainly of grilled vegetables, sold in units of one, three or five dishes.</p>
        <p>Things get a little dicier when the pastas arrive. Spaghetti and crab, tossed lightly with a lemon dressing, is fresh, delicately handled and authoritative, but the orecchiette can barely be found under a landslide of oxtail and wild boar ragu, and a black, sticky sage balsamic sauce makes squash ravioli so sweet it could drift over to the dessert menu. The perfectly straightforward, no-fuss rigatoni with a sparely applied soppressata carbonara sauce makes the right antidote.</p>
        <p>Main courses, too, are up and down. Red snapper grilled with lemon thyme and surrounded by fennel, olives and dates goes one ingredient too far. That ingredient is dates. How did they get invited to the party? Tuna loin is manhandled by a spicy tomato sauce, and I found the lobster spaetzle that accompany the absolutely top-notch veal chop to be, shall we say, an acquired taste. A generously proportioned, comely T-bone steak suffered from overcooking and a garnish of tough, chewy rosemary gnocchi.</p>
        <p>Two dishes with funny names made a good showing. Naked Lobster, a fairly large specimen split in half and helpfully divided into bite-size pieces, was sprinkled with finely diced red bell pepper and fitted out with some real scene stealers: cauliflower crespelle that seemed half pancake, half omelet. Three Little Pigs offered a grilled pork chop, a tangy spiced rib and a caramelized onion and bacon tart, brightened up with sliced plums and diced Fuji apple.</p>
        <p>At dessert, grappa gave the panna cotta an unpleasantly bitter edge, which a handful of rather tasteless raspberries did nothing to alleviate. A baked apple, topped with walnuts and dripping with warm bourbon sauce, got back to first principles in a rewarding way, with a scoop of brown-sugar gelato to keep the plate interesting. A rustic chestnut tart with baked grapes and a little ball of Concord grape ice cream also walked the fine line between forward-looking and foolish without wobbling.</p>
        <p>It's a bit of an adventure at Fernicola. The menu bristles with unexpected combinations and novel twists, some of them so novel that eggplant Parmesan suddenly seems like a classic worth hanging on to. But when she's on her game, Ms. Bogart can make Italian sound like a new language.</p>
        <p>Fernicola Osteria  *  [rating: one star]</p>
        <p>119 Kent Avenue (at North Seventh Street), Williamsburg, Brooklyn; (718) 388-9000</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE: New-wave Italian cuisine in an old brick-walled tavern looking out on the Manhattan skyline.  SOUND LEVEL: Quiet  RECOMMENDED DISHES: Grappa-cured foie gras; bresaola with mushrooms and truffled cheese; spaghetti and crab; rigatoni with soppressata carbonara; lobster with cauliflower crespelle; chestnut tart; nutty baked apple.  SERVICE: Casual, friendly, professional.  WINE LIST: A modestly priced list of about 50 wines, mostly Italian and American, with three proseccos by the glass and nine wines sold by the quarter-liter.  PRICE RANGE: Lunch, salads and pastas, $9 to $12; desserts, $5 to $8. Dinner, appetizers, $8 to 12; entrees, $14 to $26; desserts, $5 to $8.  HOURS: Lunch, Monday through Friday, 11:30 a.m. to 3 p.m. Dinner, Monday through Thursday, 5 to 10 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 5 to 11 p.m.; Sunday, 1 to 9 p.m.  CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: Enter on North Seventh Street; restrooms on dining room level.</p>
        <p>What the stars mean:</p>
        <p>(None) Poor to Satisfactory  * Good  ** Very Good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambiance and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>Past restaurant reviews from the New York Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics, are available on New York Today: www.nytoday.com</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
