<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NBC to Allow Local Choice Of Playoff Or Debate</title>
    <meta content="Y30DEB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/politics/30DEBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDF143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NBC to Allow Local Choice Of Playoff Or Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NBC drops plan to broadcast baseball playoff game instead of first presidential debate and says it will instead give its 222 local affiliates option of carrying either debate or game; some groups that monitor television coverage of politics score failure to give debate priority (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A week after declaring it would broadcast a baseball playoff game instead of the first presidential debate, NBC changed its position yesterday, saying it will give its 222 local affiliates the option of carrying either the debate or the game on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Network officials explained that the unusual decision, one of the rare times the network has offered competing broadcasts in a single time slot, was made in an effort ''to accommodate all of our audiences.'' NBC had been criticized for declining to carry the debate, and even some of its own affiliates petitioned the network to reconsider.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A week after declaring it would broadcast a baseball playoff game instead of the first presidential debate, NBC changed its position yesterday, saying it will give its 222 local affiliates the option of carrying either the debate or the game on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Network officials explained that the unusual decision, one of the rare times the network has offered competing broadcasts in a single time slot, was made in an effort ''to accommodate all of our audiences.'' NBC had been criticized for declining to carry the debate, and even some of its own affiliates petitioned the network to reconsider.</p>
        <p>''By offering feeds of the debate and the baseball game, we will leave the decision to our local stations and affiliates, who know their audiences best,'' Randy Falco, president of the NBC network, said in a statement. ''In markets where local interest in the game is strong, the general manager will have the option of carrying the baseball game.''</p>
        <p>While both the Bush and Gore campaigns said they welcomed any decision that increased viewership of the forum, some groups that monitor television coverage of politics said that NBC's making the debate optional was distressing. (The debate was always to be carried on the network's cable outlet, MSNBC.)</p>
        <p>''It's more of a gesture than a response,'' said Paul Taylor, executive director of the Alliance for Better Campaigns, an advocacy group for better campaign coverage on television. ''They apparently chose to write a contract that forces them to treat sports profit-making No. 1, and democracy No. 2.''</p>
        <p>NBC officials made the announcement as members of Congress and others had sought to persuade both the network and Major League Baseball to modify the schedule so that the debate could get maximum television exposure. A spokesman for Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts confirmed that the senator's office had placed calls to NBC and baseball officials.</p>
        <p>The network had said that its contract with Major League Baseball required it to carry the playoff game live at 8 p.m. Eastern time on its main broadcast network; the Boston debate is scheduled to begin at 9 p.m. Kassie Canter, an NBC corporate spokeswoman, said yesterday that the network was contractually required to make a ''good faith'' effort to find an alternative outlet for the ballgame in any market in which an affiliate chose not to carry it.</p>
        <p>Even among the stations owned and operated by NBC, there were differences. While the NBC-owned WRC in Washington announced that it would carry the debate live, the flagship station WNBC in New York said it would run the playoff game. Wayne Whalen, a WNBC spokesman, said the debate would be broadcast on tape at 1:35 a.m. on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Some other independently owned stations said they were opting to carry the debate. WHDH, the Boston affiliate, had announced last week that it would carry the forum on its home turf. And officials of Hearst Argyle Television, which has 11 NBC affiliates, said yesterday that their nine NBC stations in the East, South and Midwest would carry the debate. Two others on the West Coast would broadcast the playoff game at 5 p.m. Pacific time, and immediately afterward run a taped version of the debate.</p>
        <p>''It is a negative financial incentive to do this,'' said Tony Vinciquerra, chief operating officer of Hearst Argyle, which has stations in places including Baltimore, New Orleans, Orlando, Cincinnati and Winston-Salem, N.C., site of the second presidential debate. But he added that his stations were committed to providing debate and political coverage. ''We worked with NBC to get this to happen, and they made the right decision,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tara Connell, a spokeswoman for Gannett Broadcasting, which owns 12 NBC affiliates, said the company was leaving the decision to each station. And NBC officials said that of two NBC affiliates owned by The New York Times Company, one in Des Moines would carry the debate live while one in Oklahoma City would carry the baseball game, and run the taped debate later.</p>
        <p>NBC figured prominently in the debate negotiations earlier this month, when Mr. Bush announced his proposal for a series of forums as an alternative to the debates organized by the bipartisan Commission on Presidential Debates. One of Mr. Bush's proposed debates was to have occurred on NBC's ''Meet the Press,'' but the Bush campaign eventually abandoned the idea.</p>
        <p>With NBC's decision yesterday, Fox is the only one of the four major networks that will not offer the debate Tuesday on its broadcast channel. The network plans instead to carry the debate on its cable outlet, the Fox News Channel.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
