<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Dept. Unfreezes Hundreds of Promotions After Delay for Security Review</title>
    <meta content="Y30SEC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/world/30SECU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001001T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carpenter, David G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grossman, Marc</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3DD143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Dept. Unfreezes Hundreds of Promotions After Delay for Security Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Department says continuing security crackdown led to freezing of promotions for over 200 senior officials, pending review of their security records by Foreign Service director general Marc Grossman; unfreezes promotions of 200 midlevel officials after weeklong delay; says under 10 of senior officials were barred from promotions after review; some in department complain of poisonous atmosphere created, in part, by security officials; resent Sec Madeleine K Albright's plan to promote senior security official David G Carpenter to under secretary, title never before held by security worker (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A continuing security crackdown at the State Department led to the freezing of promotions for more than 200 senior officials, pending a review of their security records, department officials said today.</p>
        <p>The director general of the Foreign Service, Marc Grossman, said he was assessing the promotion files for security violations before sending the promotions to the White House, which then dispatches them to Congress for approval.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A continuing security crackdown at the State Department led to the freezing of promotions for more than 200 senior officials, pending a review of their security records, department officials said today.</p>
        <p>The director general of the Foreign Service, Marc Grossman, said he was assessing the promotion files for security violations before sending the promotions to the White House, which then dispatches them to Congress for approval.</p>
        <p>The release of the list was delayed after the suspension of the security clearance of one of the department's most senior officials, Martin S. Indyk, ambassador to Israel, and a sudden vigilance by Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, who is under pressure from Congress on security problems.</p>
        <p>This evening, the department said that ''under 10'' officials had been barred from promotions after Mr. Grossman's review of 400 candidates. The nearly 400 people included 200 midlevel officials, whose promotions were released today after a weeklong delay.</p>
        <p>As word of the latest action spread through the department, an assistant secretary of state complained at a senior staff meeting this week that management faced ''rage'' in the building and increasingly demoralized employees, according to several accounts of the session.</p>
        <p>Others, as well as diplomats abroad, complained of a poisonous atmosphere in the department created, in part, by security officials who grilled junior Foreign Service officers about their superiors. One senior official said the obsession with security had created a ''monster'' out of the bureau of diplomatic security, which Congress generously finances to the detriment of other areas of the department.</p>
        <p>Resentment was also expressed at Dr. Albright's desire to promote her senior security official, David G. Carpenter, to under secretary, a title never before conferred on a security worker at the department. That move would put Mr. Carpenter in an elite group of six top officials.</p>
        <p>The decision on Sept. 22 to delay the announcements was the first time that the department has delayed promotions solely because of security concerns, a former director general of the Foreign Service, C. E. Quainton, said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright recently agreed with a demand from Congress that security lapses, including actions like not locking an office safe properly, should be integral parts of individual personnel records.</p>
        <p>In reviewing the transgressions of the officials, whose promotions had already been approved by a promotions board, Mr. Grossman has devised what he calls a Department of Motor Vehicles test. That means breaches will be assessed according to a point system that grades the seriousness of offenses and how long ago they were committed.</p>
        <p>If employees have too many transgressions, they will be sent to the equivalent of ''traffic school,'' security school, he said.</p>
        <p>The approach, officials said today, has been met with cynicism in State Department corridors, where the secretary of state was said to be on a ''security jihad.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright answered questions on security on Capitol Hill this week in what is generally expected to be one of her final appearances and where she gave a deferential curtsy to the chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee, Jesse Helms, Republican of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>''I am trying here to find a middle ground in terms of not having witch hunts or being lax,'' she said. ''We cannot have a culture of laxity as far as security issues are concerned.''</p>
        <p>A day after that hearing, the secretary was peppered with questions by Representative Howard L. Berman, Democrat of California, at a hearing of the House International Relations Committee. Mr. Berman asked about the loss of Mr. Indyk to the Middle East peace talks, and Dr. Albright said she valued Mr. Indyk but had no second thoughts about suspending his security clearance a week ago.</p>
        <p>With his second posting as ambassador to Israel, Mr. Indyk had one of the shining diplomatic careers in the Clinton administration, first as senior White House adviser on the Middle East in Mr. Clinton's first term and as envoy to Israel from 1995 to 1997. He then returned here as assistant secretary for Near East affairs, a post that includes defining policy on Iran and Iraq, Arab countries, North Africa and Israel.</p>
        <p>At the request of Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel, who asked for an envoy whom he could personally trust and connect with, Mr. Indyk returned to Israel in December.</p>
        <p>The State Department has said on several occasions since the suspension that Mr. Indyk's case did not involve espionage and that there was no evidence of classified information having been compromised.</p>
        <p>Department officials said the investigation centered on the mishandling of classified material, including the writing of a classified memo on an unclassified laptop computer and the taking home of confidential documents and returning them to the office the next day.</p>
        <p>The Federal Bureau of Investigation is investigating Mr. Indyk for the period starting when he arrived at the embassy in Tel Aviv in December, said a person who has been briefed on the inquiry.</p>
        <p>That person said that the F.B.I. had interviewed Mr. Indyk two times since the Camp David summit meeting in July and that the Diplomatic Security Bureau of the State Department interviewed him in June. At some point after June, the department referred the case to the F.B.I., apparently because of the climate in Washington created by the prosecution of Dr. Wen Ho Lee at the Los Alamos National Laboratory.</p>
        <p>In recounting aspects of Mr. Indyk's case, the person said Mr. Indyk did not attend the traditional two-week ''ambassador's school'' in 1995, when he was sent to Tel Aviv in a hurry. Thus, he did not receive a full security briefing.</p>
        <p>Last November, Mr. Indyk was warned about his security practices in a generalized review of the Bureau of Near East Affairs, and he received a security briefing in December before returning to Tel Aviv, the individual said.</p>
        <p>In the December briefing, Mr. Indyk was told for the first time to use a Tempest laptop, a secure computer shielded to prevent eavesdropping on the faint radio signals that all electronic devices emit. But such laptops needed a security officer to be with the ambassador when he wrote on it, and the Tel Aviv embassy did not have enough security personnel to spare, this person said.</p>
        <p>On occasion, Mr. Indyk put notes from a diplomatic conversation on an insecure laptop and had the disk  taken to the embassy, this person said. That was considered a breach of regulations, even though having the handwritten notes was not a breach.</p>
        <p>The American setup in Israel is unusual, because the embassy is in Tel Aviv but much of the diplomatic work is in Jerusalem, an hour's car ride away. Traditionally, American ambassadors conduct considerable work in their car or making the rounds of the Israeli government in Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>The suspension of Mr. Indyk's security clearance stripped him of his role in the Middle East peace talks as the administration and Mr. Barak search desperately to reach an accord. Mr. Indyk has been barred by security officials at the State Department from talking to his colleagues, including the Middle East peace coordinator, Dennis B. Ross.</p>
        <p>Mr. Indyk's run-in with the security bureau was in part a product of the aggressive and full-time way he pursued his job, colleagues said. An Israeli author and a peace advocate, Amos Oz, described Mr. Indyk as ''very unambassadorial,'' ''a crusader for peace'' and a man who talked ''either books or Middle East peace.''</p>
        <p>As passions rose at the State Department over Mr. Indyk's case and over Congressional pressure that has resulted Dr. Albright's crackdown, some senior officials recalled the tenure of George P. Schultz as secretary of state, when he was seen as a strong defender of th department.</p>
        <p>In 1986, when the Central Intelligence Agency wanted to introduce random polygraph tests for government employees who handled sensitive information, Mr. Schultz said he would resign rather than agree to tests at the department.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 1, 2000, Sunday  A headline yesterday about a security review at the State Department misstated the effect on promotions of some 200 officials. They have been frozen, not unfrozen, while the review is under way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 1, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A headline yesterday about a security review at the State Department misstated the effect on promotions of some 200 officials. They have been frozen, not unfrozen, while the review is under way.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
