<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milosevic Foes Stage Protests To Force Him To Concede</title>
    <meta content="Y30YUG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/world/30YUGO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greece</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgrade (Serbia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erlanger, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kostunica, Vojislav</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia/Belgrade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2D8173DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milosevic Foes Stage Protests To Force Him To Concede</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ERLANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Erlanger, Steven</byline>
      <dateline>BELGRADE, Serbia, Sept. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thousands of people across Serbia rally in protest against Pres Slobodan Milosevic as opposition leaders call on foreign governments, including Russia and Greece, to examine disputed results of presidential vote; opposition plans rolling series of rallies, demonstrations and strikes to force Milosevic to concede that Vojislav Kostunica won majority of vote; street demonstrations get off to slow start, with rally in Belgrade poorly attended; protests in opposition strongholds attract big crowds; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thousands of people across Serbia rallied today in protest against President Slobodan Milosevic as opposition leaders called on foreign governments, including Russia and Greece, to examine the disputed results of the presidential election last Sunday.</p>
        <p>Vojislav Kostunica, the opposition candidate, says he won the election outright, with more than 50 percent of the vote, but Mr. Milosevic's Federal Election Commission says that Mr. Kostunica fell short and that a runoff vote is required on Oct. 8.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thousands of people across Serbia rallied today in protest against President Slobodan Milosevic as opposition leaders called on foreign governments, including Russia and Greece, to examine the disputed results of the presidential election last Sunday.</p>
        <p>Vojislav Kostunica, the opposition candidate, says he won the election outright, with more than 50 percent of the vote, but Mr. Milosevic's Federal Election Commission says that Mr. Kostunica fell short and that a runoff vote is required on Oct. 8.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kostunica has alleged widespread electoral fraud and vowed to boycott the runoff, and the opposition called a rolling series of rallies, demonstrations and strikes, beginning today, to try to force Mr. Milosevic to concede defeat. Opposition leaders say they hope to shut the country down by Monday.</p>
        <p>But the street demonstrations got off to a slow start.</p>
        <p>Here in the capital, an afternoon rally was poorly attended, with no more than 15,000 people, many of them high school students, gathered in the central Square of the Republic -- too small a crowd, opposition leaders conceded, to start a fire, much less a rebellion.</p>
        <p>So they suspended the rally until 8 p.m., but still the turnout was considered disappointing -- perhaps 40,000 people on a chilly night, far fewer than the 200,000 or more who came out on Wednesday night to hail Mr. Kostunica's apparent victory.</p>
        <p>Some who did show up today were puzzled by the postponement. Goran Ledjenovic, a high school student of 17 in a Jugoslavija T-shirt, said: ''Well, we'll stay to protest, but I don't think he'll go that easily. We need total civil disobedience, not this kind of thing today, which is ridiculous. Everyone needs to come out on the street and block the system.''</p>
        <p>The signs were more troubling for Mr. Milosevic out in the provinces, where people tend to be poorer, angrier and less jaded and have much better access to independent news media.</p>
        <p>Protesters in opposition strongholds like Cacak, Nis, Novi Sad, Kraljevo and Valjevo filled town squares and blocked major national roadways. State television and radio stations in Novi Sad and Kragujevac stopped regular programming to protest against state news, while some semiprivate stations allied with the government, like BK Television, have begun to give straight accounts of opposition news conferences and claims, as has the state-owned daily newspaper Politika.</p>
        <p>The change is particularly noticeable on Studio B, the Belgrade station seized by the Serbian government from the opposition-run city hall in February.</p>
        <p>Throughout Serbia, many theaters, companies and schools shut down, and public offices and enterprises in towns like Cacak also shut. Some 7,500 coal miners stopped work in Kolubara, 25 miles south of Belgrade.</p>
        <p>More troubling to the government, officials said, were blocked roads and some attacks on regional administrative buildings and public service managers by angry opposition supporters.</p>
        <p>Some senior officials of Mr. Milosevic's Socialist Party are said to believe that a resounding defeat in the runoff is the only way to persuade Mr. Milosevic to concede.</p>
        <p>There is said to be significant confusion and unrest within the party, which Mr. Milosevic has controlled since 1987, with some senior officials looking beyond him and even urging him, one official said, to consider conceding defeat to Mr. Kostunica.</p>
        <p>Divisions between the Socialist Party and the Yugoslav United Left party, a creation of Mr. Milosevic's wife, Mirjana Markovic, are said to be more severe. Socialists have resented the growing power of the United Left, which controls many businesses and ministries.</p>
        <p>And United Left officials, including Mrs. Markovic, are reliably said to have urged a harder line on Mr. Milosevic, because they see their fate as tied up with his.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to assess the breadth of the dissension, but one official described the atmosphere as ''chaotic, nervous and spreading.'' The director of the Federal Statistical Bureau, Miroslav Zivkovic, told a former employee that he was concerned about electoral fraud and asked for protection.</p>
        <p>The chairman of the Federal Election Commission, Borivoje Vukicevic, and three other permanent members told another official at a party at the Chinese Embassy on Thursday night that none of them had signed the final statement of the commission that showed Mr. Kostunica leading Mr. Milosevic by 10 percentage points, but less than one point below a majority.</p>
        <p>Today the opposition lodged an official complaint with the election commission, providing its own tally showing that Mr. Kostunica beat Mr. Milosevic by 51.34 percent to 36.22 percent. Nebojsa Bakarec, an aide to Mr. Kostunica, said voting returns had been produced from more than 100 polling places in Kosovo that had never opened but that apparently produced 142,000 votes for Mr. Milosevic. Mr. Bakarec said the votes had inflated the turnout, artificially reducing Mr. Kostunica's percentage.</p>
        <p>One Kosovo polling site -- in Prizren, where very few Serbs now live -- showed more than 4,000 votes for Mr. Milosevic. The polling station is now the local headquarters of the Kosovo Protection Corps, the reformed version of the Albanian secessionist Kosovo Liberation Army.</p>
        <p>The chief United Nations administrator in Kosovo, Bernard Kouchner, said today that he agreed with the opposition charges, since no more than 45,000 people had voted in Kosovo.</p>
        <p>In an effort to resolve the election dispute, Mr. Kostunica urged an independent recount of the ballots. He appealed especially to Greece, ''the birthplace of democracy,'' which has close ties to Serbia.</p>
        <p>Greek officials have said they would be willing to help, but there is no indication that Mr. Milosevic would sanction such outside involvement. The Greek, French and Russian governments are exploring how to help mediate the electoral dispute, diplomats said.</p>
        <p>The opposition sent copies of its election results and materials to Moscow, hoping that the Russian government could influence Mr. Milosevic.</p>
        <p>In another sign of sensitivity to reporting seen inside Serbia by owners of satellite dishes, the Yugoslav government demanded today that the resident correspondent of the British Broadcasting Corporation, Jacky Rowland, leave the country within two days. Officials told her that they were unhappy with the general tenor of the BBC's reporting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
