<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Westchester Officials Join Forces to Oppose County Airport's Predawn Flights</title>
    <meta content="30CURF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/nyregion/30CURF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Westchester County Airport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airport Noise and Capacity Act of 1990</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Delta Air Lines Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E0D8173DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Westchester Officials Join Forces to Oppose County Airport's Predawn Flights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS, Sept. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bipartisan group of congressmen introduces legislation that would impose mandatory curfew on Westchester County Airport in White Plains, NY; voluntary curfew has existed for 20 years prohibiting takeoffs or landings between midnight and 6:30 a.m., but Delta Airlines added 5:59 a.m. flight, prompting legislative action; curfews exist at many airports around country, but this may be first attempt to legislate curfew in accordance with 1990 federal aviation law (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saying that their constituents were being deprived of sleep by airplanes taking off before dawn from Westchester County Airport, a bipartisan group of congressmen introduced legislation today that would impose a mandatory curfew on the airport.</p>
        <p>For the last 20 years, airlines have observed a voluntary curfew prohibiting takeoffs or landings there between midnight and 6:30 a.m. But on Sept. 2, a Delta Airlines subsidiary added a new 5:59 a.m. flight to Atlanta. Since then, local officials, egged on by irate residents, have tried unsuccessfully to persuade the subsidiary, Atlantic Southeast Airlines, to change the flight time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Saying that their constituents were being deprived of sleep by airplanes taking off before dawn from Westchester County Airport, a bipartisan group of congressmen introduced legislation today that would impose a mandatory curfew on the airport.</p>
        <p>For the last 20 years, airlines have observed a voluntary curfew prohibiting takeoffs or landings there between midnight and 6:30 a.m. But on Sept. 2, a Delta Airlines subsidiary added a new 5:59 a.m. flight to Atlanta. Since then, local officials, egged on by irate residents, have tried unsuccessfully to persuade the subsidiary, Atlantic Southeast Airlines, to change the flight time.</p>
        <p>Today, local officials escalated their effort and said they wanted to close the door on any other airlines -- some of which occasionally violate the voluntary curfew -- that might be tempted to follow suit.</p>
        <p>''I think we're far less understanding when it comes to air carriers that demonstrate a blatant disregard for the community's wishes for a few hours of quiet during the night,'' said Representative Sue W. Kelly, the bill's main sponsor. ''Today we're drawing a line in the sand and we're saying, 'Enough is enough.' ''</p>
        <p>The legislation may seem counterintuitive at a time when many suburban airports have eagerly expanded their services to cater to a fast-growing market of commercial and business travelers frustrated by increased delays and congestion at major metropolitan airports.</p>
        <p>But Andrew J. Spano, the Westchester County executive, said that the airport here was not interested in expanding its facilities, much less its hours of operation. After all, the airport, which served more than a half-million passengers last year, is already under tremendous scrutiny because of noise complaints and its proximity to the Kensico Reservoir, a conduit for 90 percent of New York City's drinking water.</p>
        <p>Sam Watts, a spokesman for Atlantic Southeast Airlines, said that while the 5:59 a.m. flight had so far been a disappointment, averaging fewer than 12 passengers per flight, ''We would be opposed to a change that would restrict operations.''</p>
        <p>He said his airline had little choice but to schedule the early flight, because there were no other time slots available. And he said the 5:59 a.m. plane -- a 50-seat Canadair regional jet -- was considered very quiet by the industry.</p>
        <p>Airport curfews are not that uncommon around the country. Though there are no curfews at Kennedy or Newark International Airports, there is a voluntary midnight-to-6 a.m. ban at La Guardia, and some restrictions at Teterboro, in New Jersey. And perhaps most notably, a mandatory curfew exists at Reagan National Airport in Washington.</p>
        <p>But Westchester's may be the first attempt to legislate a curfew in accordance with a 1990 federal aviation law, according to the Federal Aviation Administration.</p>
        <p>The proposal, Westchester officials added, has broad bipartisan support, even with the November elections just a month away. Today, Mrs. Kelly, a Republican, and Mr. Spano, a Democrat, were joined at a news conference by Representatives Eliot L. Engel and Nita M. Lowey, both Democrats. That support also cuts across state lines, as shown by the presence today of Lolly H. Prince, the first selectwoman of Greenwich, Conn., which last year was embroiled in a fight with Westchester over a road near the airport.</p>
        <p>Before today's decision, Westchester officials said they had tried to get the airline to change its mind by urging residents to call the airline and ordering county employees to boycott airlines breaking the curfew.</p>
        <p>Atlantic Southeast officials, in turn, implied that they might compromise if Westchester could increase its capacity of four flights per half-hour to six -- a change that is possible, but that Mr. Spano rejected.</p>
        <p>''I told them, 'You just don't get it: this is not a negotiable item,' '' he said. ''I thought it was blackmail.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
