<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hokies Add WWW To Their X's and O's</title>
    <meta content="30COLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/sports/30COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Virginia Polytechnic Institute &amp; State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E6DD143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hokies Add WWW To Their X's and O's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Drape</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses new Internet site aimed at fans of Virginia Tech football team, which is currently undefeated; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Virginia Tech Coach Frank Beamer calls it a sign of the times: an Internet site where, for an annual fee of $39.99, Hokie-soaked football fans can peruse injury and scouting reports prepared by his staff or settle into a chat room with the coach himself. It is called, modestly or not, BeamerBall.com and actually is tempered with a down home sentiment -- part of the revenue will be parceled among his coaches.</p>
        <p>''I know if Virginia Tech is going to stay in the top of the country, I think there are certain ways this country is going and the Internet is one of them,'' Beamer said of the site, which he launched yesterday. ''I think your more prominent programs are certainly going in this direction. What I like is it's another means for me to help these guys financially. I've got the best staff in the country and I want to keep them right here. This will be another means to helping that situation.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Virginia Tech Coach Frank Beamer calls it a sign of the times: an Internet site where, for an annual fee of $39.99, Hokie-soaked football fans can peruse injury and scouting reports prepared by his staff or settle into a chat room with the coach himself. It is called, modestly or not, BeamerBall.com and actually is tempered with a down home sentiment -- part of the revenue will be parceled among his coaches.</p>
        <p>''I know if Virginia Tech is going to stay in the top of the country, I think there are certain ways this country is going and the Internet is one of them,'' Beamer said of the site, which he launched yesterday. ''I think your more prominent programs are certainly going in this direction. What I like is it's another means for me to help these guys financially. I've got the best staff in the country and I want to keep them right here. This will be another means to helping that situation.''</p>
        <p>A year ago, such forward thinking emanating from the hills of Blacksburg, Va., would have been met with eye-rolling and guffaws if it was acknowledged at all. Yes, the Hokies were considered a solid program, albeit from a weak conference, the Big East, and they were consistently in holiday bowl games. But Tech seemed to wind up in the fruit salad bowls, not the prime rib ones like the Orange, Sugar, Rose and Fiesta.</p>
        <p>But what a difference an 11-0 regular season makes, as well as a compelling but losing performance in the national title game and a quick twitching and optically dazzling quarterback. Last year it took Tech seven weeks to creep from No. 13 in the preseason Associated Press poll to No. 4. This year the Hokies (3-0) got to that ranking in barely four weeks.</p>
        <p>At this time last season, Michael Vick was just finding his way onto the highlight reels and was being described as a gifted red-shirt freshman. Now, he is a staple of college football shows; he has been fitted with a sandwich board's worth of superlatives and is a genuine Heisman Trophy candidate. Naturally, he, too, has a Web page, ''MV2K,'' but it is free as part of the Hokies' sports information department's effort to win him the trophy as college's best player. Last year Lane Stadium had 51,000 seats; this year permanent bleachers have been added to accommodate 56,272 rabid fans.</p>
        <p>Still, Beamer is astute enough to know that as you roar into the future it is worth looking to the past. He remembers the threat of being run out of town, almost evicted from his alma mater, after suffering through 2-9, 3-8 and 2-8-1 seasons in his first six years on the Hokie sideline. And when he looks at the Hokies' opponent today, Boston College (2-1), he anticipates a game a lot like the Hokies' visit last year to Morgantown, W.Va.</p>
        <p>The Hokies were 7-0 and heavily favored against West Virginia. But they needed a 44-yard field goal as time ran out to escape the Mountaineers, 22-20. To Beamer, the circumstances feel familiar and the Eagles are indeed dangerous. They have an offensive line that averages better than 300 pounds and a quarterback, Tim Hasselbeck, who has completed 61.5 percent of his passes for 730 yards -- including a career-high 355 in a romp over Navy last week.</p>
        <p>''This game reminds me of West Virginia,'' Beamer said this week. ''It's a scary week because you know Boston College is going to play their best football game of the year. I think they're going to try to hammer us.''</p>
        <p>So far this season, Vick and Virginia Tech have been doing all the hammering. The quarterback has 412 passing yards, 219 rushing yards -- with an average of 8.8 yards a carry -- and he has accounted for seven touchdowns. The Hokies have scored 52, 45 and 49 points in mauling Akron, East Carolina and Rutgers. The one aspect of Virginia Tech football, however, that is not exactly up-to-date is its scheduling.</p>
        <p>Virginia Tech prefers a slate of nonconference opponents like Akron and Central Florida -- read easy. When lightning forced the cancellation of the Hokies' opener with Georgia Tech, they lost what little margin of error they had in the strength of schedule column, which will be vital when the computers that figure the Bowl Championship Series ranking eventually rev up.</p>
        <p>But until the Hokies lose, they are on equal footing with Nebraska, Florida State and Florida atop college football. No more eye rolls or guffaws directed toward the hills of Blacksburg.</p>
        <p>ON COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
