<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Win the East, Thanks to the Red Sox</title>
    <meta content="30YANK$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/sports/30YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Orioles</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DB143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Win the East, Thanks to the Red Sox</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, Sept. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees clinch American League Eastern Division title despite loss to Baltimore Orioles, 13-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees filed sullenly into their clubhouse tonight, champions of the American League East. They didn't know whether to spray Champagne and hug, or to dress quietly and leave, absorbed by their slump.</p>
        <p>Baltimore had just routed them, 13-2, the Yankees' fifth straight loss, their 13th defeat in 16 games. The Orioles scored 10 runs in the second inning, knocking out Andy Pettitte.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees filed sullenly into their clubhouse tonight, champions of the American League East. They didn't know whether to spray Champagne and hug, or to dress quietly and leave, absorbed by their slump.</p>
        <p>Baltimore had just routed them, 13-2, the Yankees' fifth straight loss, their 13th defeat in 16 games. The Orioles scored 10 runs in the second inning, knocking out Andy Pettitte.</p>
        <p>But in the ninth inning, the final score from Boston's game was posted: the Red Sox had lost to Tampa Bay, 8-6, and the Yankees clinched the division. Some Yankee fans shouted joyously in the stands, but the Yankee players were sedate on the bench, silent, and they passed the bin of Champagne on the way to their lockers after the game. No one seemed to know how to act.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre spoke from the middle of the clubhouse. Remember this is about the long haul, he told them. Remember what you have accomplished, and remember that a lot of players go their whole careers without having a chance to celebrate. Enjoy this, Torre said.</p>
        <p>Relieved temporarily of the burden of their late-season collapse, the players relaxed. ''I don't care -- it's over,'' Derek Jeter barked. ''It's a long, hard year.''</p>
        <p>Jeff Nelson grabbed a bottle of Champagne and soon many of them were spraying one another, Scott Brosius chasing after a couple of teammates with a blast of foam, Luis Sojo counter-attacking, laughing. Jeter doused Torre and they hugged. Some players stood on the fringes, wallflowers to the muted celebration that lasted about 15 minutes. ''There is cause to celebrate, but it is a little subdued because we know this is only the first step to our end goal, and that's another World Series ring,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>His words were perfect, David Cone thought. It was a masterful attempt by Torre to find a way to lift his team out of its decline that threatened to become one of the greatest collapses in baseball history: rather than order the players away from the bubbly and insist that it was inappropriate to celebrate after another brutal defeat, Torre made them feel good about themselves, at least for a day.</p>
        <p>But Torre's words will dry up in the Champagne-soaked clubhouse carpet if the Yankees don't extricate themselves from their malaise quickly. Cone pitches against the Orioles' Mike Mussina Saturday, Orlando Hernandez pitches Sunday, and the playoffs are scheduled to start Tuesday. The Yankees must find themselves in the next three days.</p>
        <p>Over the last three days, the Yankees have started Denny Neagle, Roger Clemens and Pettitte, and the three allowed 20 runs in eight and one-third innings. The Yankees were beaten by the journeymen pitchers Cory Lidle, Bryan Rekar and Chuck McElroy, scoring only three runs in 20 innings against them, and the competition promises to get tougher in the week ahead.</p>
        <p>Pettitte came into tonight's game needing one victory to reach 20 for the season, a mark he had achieved once in his career, and he struck out the first two batters he faced, his fastball crackling, moving, fooling. He had never felt so confident as he did for this game, he said later. Pettitte loves pitching here, and came in with a career record of 7-0 with a 3.58 earned run average in Camden Yards.</p>
        <p>When Pettitte came out for the second inning, the scoreboard showed that Boston led Tampa Bay, 2-0. Cal Ripken fouled off a pitch and eventually drew a base on balls. Pettitte walked Melvin Mora. And he walked Chris Richard to load the bases. Pettitte, who hadn't issued more than three walks in any game in about two months, had walked three straight batters.</p>
        <p>Pettitte fidgeted on the rubber, shook off the signs from catcher Jorge Posada, something he rarely does any more. Pettitte usually lowers his cap to block out the crowd, creating tunnel vision, but as the Orioles rallied, he stood upright, glancing around a bit, like a quarterback anticipating a hit from his blind side.</p>
        <p>Brook Fordyce singled through the middle, and two runs scored. Luis Matos grounded to Jeter, who flipped the ball to second baseman Chuck Knoblauch. Knoblauch, moving awkwardly, stepped on the bag and threw to first, and Tino Martinez was forced off the bag to catch the ball; Matos was safe. Baltimore led, 3-0, and everything was going wrong for the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Brady Anderson walked, and the next four batters stroked singles, and the Orioles led, 7-0. Torre stepped from the dugout to replace Pettitte, whose large eyes were wide, his expression vacant. He slapped his bare hand and glove together, handed Torre the ball and jogged off the field to jeers. He had thrown 43 pitches in the inning, only 15 for strikes.</p>
        <p>Dwight Gooden followed, pitching for the second consecutive day; Torre was using his only experienced middle reliever with his team trailing by seven runs, a sign of his desperation to end this losing streak. After Mora struck out, Richard ripped a three-run homer. Ten runs.  Ten runs.</p>
        <p>The rest of the night was excruciating, Jeter said afterward. The game was effectively over, and the Yankees got sloppy. Jeter made an error, there was a balk and a wild pitch. Everybody was watching the scoreboard, watching Tampa Bay come back from a 4-0 deficit to tie the game, to take a 6-4 lead, then 8-4.</p>
        <p>Rob Cucuzza, the Yankees' clubhouse manager, edged into the dugout to ask Torre what to do about the Champagne, and whether to cover the lockers with protective plastic. Cone quietly asked the same thing.</p>
        <p>The yellow lights on the scoreboard indicated the Red Sox were batting in the ninth, and cut the lead to three runs; then, to two runs. Finally, the capital ''F'' was posted next to the abbreviations. BOS 6 on top, TB 8 on the bottom.</p>
        <p>The Yankees owe so much to the Boston Red Sox, for Babe Ruth, for the legend of Bucky Dent, and now the Red Sox must be thanked for rescuing the Yankees from what could have been an incredible disaster. The Yankees' lead in the American League East had been nine games on Sept. 13, and if the Red Sox had won tonight, the pressure on the Yankees would have mounted exponentially.</p>
        <p>The Yankees can exhale a little, knowing for sure that they will be part of the playoffs. But their offense needs a jump-start, their middle relief is battered, three-fourths of their projected playoff rotation got hammered in the last turn through the rotation.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have come back from adversity before to win, in 1996, in the A.L. Championship Series in 1998, from the personal problems that ravaged the team in 1999. But this is different, more fundamental. They are playing horribly. They have got to start playing better. ''I think it's going to be tougher than in years past,'' Pettitte said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
