<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Grimsley's Arm Troubles Add to Torre's Bullpen Frustration</title>
    <meta content="30PINS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/sports/30PINS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimsley, Jason</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torre, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3DB143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Grimsley's Arm Troubles Add to Torre's Bullpen Frustration</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, Sept. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses injury to New York Yankees pitcher Jason Grimsley, adding to manager Joe Torre's bullpen problems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The emotion that Jason Grimsley tried to hide escaped around his eyes as he buckled his belt and finished dressing in street clothes this afternoon. Bernie Williams had been headed to the field for batting practice, but he saw Grimsley, stopped and asked what was wrong.</p>
        <p>''My elbow,'' Grimsley said in a low voice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The emotion that Jason Grimsley tried to hide escaped around his eyes as he buckled his belt and finished dressing in street clothes this afternoon. Bernie Williams had been headed to the field for batting practice, but he saw Grimsley, stopped and asked what was wrong.</p>
        <p>''My elbow,'' Grimsley said in a low voice.</p>
        <p>Grimsley had been the Yankees' best option to fill the void at middle relief created by Ramiro Mendoza's shoulder injury, but he flew back to New York last night to have a magnetic resonance imaging scan on his right elbow. Manager Joe Torre admitted he feared losing the right-hander for the foreseeable future, and that his bullpen would be thin when the Yankees played in the postseason. ''Maybe we can get by without the depth you'd like to have,'' said Torre.</p>
        <p>Grimsley had been pitching very poorly of late, allowing 11 hits, 5 walks and 9 runs in his last seven and a third innings, and his earned run average -- 2.23 on June 14 -- had rocketed to 5.04. Grimsley has had control problems his nine-year professional career and Torre assumed that Grimsley's trouble was based on a lack of comfort. Torre had been trying to get the right-hander work in the last week.</p>
        <p>But Grimsley told trainers today that his elbow has been hurting for an extended period of time, and he had hoped to pitch through the pain, as he did last year. Torre did not know about his elbow problems this year, or even last year. ''He should've told us for his own well-being,'' an upset Torre said.</p>
        <p>Said Grimsley: ''The last few times out, it's really been hurting. I've got to get it looked at and get it taken care of.''</p>
        <p>Grimsley's status is unclear and the Yankees desperately need David Cone to rebound. He will pitch Saturday against Baltimore's Mike Mussina, after being pulled from the rotation for one turn because of lingering effects from the left shoulder dislocation he sustained earlier this month.</p>
        <p>Just a few days ago, it appeared that the Yankees' middle relief would include the left-hander Randy Choate, the right-hander Dwight Gooden and Grimsley.</p>
        <p>But Grimsley is out and Torre has almost no options other than Cone -- the young left-handers Ted Lilly and Randy Keisler, or the rookie right-hander Craig Dingman.</p>
        <p>Bidding for Pitchers</p>
        <p>The All-Star pitcher Mike Mussina could make his last start for the Baltimore Orioles against the Yankees on Saturday. He is eligible for free agency after this year and has rejected a six-year, $72 million offer from the Orioles; $12 million in that proposal would be deferred, without interest.</p>
        <p>Mussina, the Mets' Mike Hampton and the Yankees' Denny Neagle are expected to be the three best free-agent pitchers available during the off-season. Neagle's struggles down the stretch could curtail the Yankees' interest in signing him to a long-term contract. It is conventional wisdom in baseball that Hampton will sign with a National League team.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees could make a hard pitch for Mussina, who would like to play for a team close to his hometown of Montoursville, Pa.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
