<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MANY NOT ELIGIBLE IN STATE PROGRAM TO INSURE CHILDREN</title>
    <meta content="30INSU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/nyregion/30INSU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pediatrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DE143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MANY NOT ELIGIBLE IN STATE PROGRAM TO INSURE CHILDREN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State officials, health insurance executives and advocates for poor say as many as half of all children enrolled in special health care plan intended to insure children from low-income families do not qualify for plan and will be removed from it over next several months; say thousands of those enrolled should be in Medicaid; say many may have to switch doctors and could even end up with no medical coverage, either temporarily or permanently; blame failure of participating insurance plans to steer Medicaid-eligible families to Medicaid; federal government weighs whether NY owes it money because it reimburses states at higher rate for plan than for Medicaid (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As many as half of all New York children who are enrolled in a special government health care plan do not actually qualify for the plan and will be removed from it over the next several months.</p>
        <p>The plan, the Children's Health Insurance Program, was intended to insure children from low-income families whose incomes are too high for Medicaid and too low to afford private insurance. But thousands of the New York children who were enrolled should in fact be in Medicaid, according to state officials, health insurance executives and advocates for the poor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As many as half of all New York children who are enrolled in a special government health care plan do not actually qualify for the plan and will be removed from it over the next several months.</p>
        <p>The plan, the Children's Health Insurance Program, was intended to insure children from low-income families whose incomes are too high for Medicaid and too low to afford private insurance. But thousands of the New York children who were enrolled should in fact be in Medicaid, according to state officials, health insurance executives and advocates for the poor.</p>
        <p>The first wave of those families began receiving confusing notices several weeks ago that their children would be removed from the program and that they must apply for Medicaid. As a result, experts say, many children may have to switch doctors and could even end up with no medical coverage, either temporarily or permanently.</p>
        <p>And the federal government is examining whether the state may owe it money.</p>
        <p>All around the country, states are trying with varying success to enroll children in the insurance program, which was approved by Congress in 1997 and is reimbursed by the federal government at a higher rate than Medicaid. States receive from 65 percent to 84 percent of the costs of their programs. New York gets 65 percent, compared with 50 percent for Medicaid.</p>
        <p>New York's program, known as Child Health Plus, served as a model: it came long before the federal government got involved, and the state is among only 10 that have established a significant program so far. About 538,000 New York children are enrolled, roughly one quarter of all children in the program nationwide.</p>
        <p>Children were wrongly placed in the program in large part because the insurance plans that participate did not steer families into Medicaid even when it was clear they belonged there, insurance company executives and advocates for the families said.</p>
        <p>Federal law required them to do so, but the responsibility for enforcing that law lies with the State Health Department, which the insurance executives said did not instruct them to screen applicants for Medicaid eligibility. Understanding that the goal was to insure as many children as possible, they said, the companies more or less signed up any poor person who came asking.</p>
        <p>''The Department of Health knew exactly what we were doing,'' said Dr. Michael A. Stocker, president and chief executive of Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield, which insures 96,000 of the state's children enrolled in the program. ''There is no secret about this. And there is no question that it is going to create problems.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Stocker said he expected to lose more than half the children enrolled in Empire's plan.</p>
        <p>The state said the problems arose because time was needed to iron out the program. ''Obviously our top priority is to get children the health insurance they need and deserve,'' said John Signor, a spokesman for the Health Department. ''The federal government is now forcing states to move children who are eligible for Medicaid into that program.'' He estimated that about 22 percent of the children would have to be moved, but insurers and others put the figure closer to 50 percent.</p>
        <p>As a result, thousands of families are being taken by surprise. Several weeks ago, they started to receive letters informing them that they were no longer eligible for Child Health Plus and that they would have to go through the rigorous process of applying for Medicaid. Beneficiaries have 45 days to respond; the first group to get letters will be cut off tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Many of the recipients could not understand the letter, or have no idea what to do, said those who assist the poor in enrolling in insurance plans. Many may have to change doctors; plans like Empire do not participate in Medicaid. Further, many will not go into Medicaid, because it is cumbersome and because some believe the program carries a stigma. As such, many children will end up uninsured.</p>
        <p>''We are seeing, every day, kids falling between the cracks,'' said Kate Lawler, director of the health care access program for Children's Aid Society. ''My big fear is that there are families out there who are getting these letters, don't understand them, and the red flag won't go up until they go to the doctor's office and their card is rejected.''</p>
        <p>Part of the problem is that the state had its program in place before the approval in 1997 of the federal matching program, which clearly forbade enrolling children who were eligible for Medicaid. Further, the amount a family could earn and still get Medicaid rose somewhat in 1999, which meant the status of some children changed.</p>
        <p>But it is clear that the state allowed insurance companies to sign people up after less-than-fastidious checks, health care experts agreed. And many families seem not to have  been informed that their benefits would eventually expire.</p>
        <p>''We were not screening kids for Medicaid,'' said Sue Luce, the director of state government programs for BlueCross BlueShield of the Rochester Area, which expects to lose roughly half its 19,500 enrollees.</p>
        <p>Kalkines, Arky, Zall &amp; Bernstein, a law firm in New York that represents provider-sponsored health plans, estimates that as many as 80 percent of the children were improperly enrolled. That figure, however, is most likely inflated because it is based on limited data that does not account for, among other things, immigration status. (In New York, illegal immigrant children are eligible for Child Health Plus, but not Medicaid.)</p>
        <p>State Comptroller H. Carl McCall warned the Health Department several times over the last few years that it was enrolling too many children -- 41 percent by his estimate -- who belonged in Medicaid.</p>
        <p>In a 1998 audit of the department, his office warned, ''If Medicaid-eligible children continue to be enrolled in the Child Health Plus program, the federal funds used to subsidize the insurance premiums could be recovered.'' The department responded by assuring Mr. McCall's office that it was requiring insurance carriers to screen applicants.</p>
        <p>But the carriers said they felt no such onus.</p>
        <p>''The priority was to get kids insured,'' said Anthony Tassi, a senior health policy analysts for Kalkines, Arky, Zall &amp; Bernstein. ''Plans were not under the obligation to follow up.''</p>
        <p>The change has caught many out of the blue. A 34-year-old Chinese immigrant, for instance, signed up for the program just a few months ago, then received a letter she could not read to inform her that she needed to transfer into Medicaid. ''It is confusing,'' said the woman, who has two children and spoke on the condition of anonymity. She said the Empire representative, when enrolling her, told her she probably did not qualify for Medicaid.</p>
        <p>Mr. Signor said that this spring, the state took steps to address the problem. For instance, Gov. George E. Pataki earmarked $10 million to employ 34 community groups to help families enroll for low-income insurance. It also put Medicaid and Child Health Plus applications into a single form. ''We have a structure in place to ensure it is a seamless process,''  Mr. Signor said.</p>
        <p>Cindy Mann, an administrator at the federal Health Care Financing Administration, which oversees Medicaid, said it was not yet clear whether New York owed a refund. She added that the agency would be monitoring the state's program.</p>
        <p>''In many respects,'' she said, ''New York did not have its infrastructure in place.''</p>
        <p>New York is expected to get additional money from the federal governmeent if the 40 states that did not use their allotments for the child health insurance program are forced to forfeit their funds.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
