<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="30DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DF143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>UAL Says It Expects a Loss, And Its Stock Falls Further  UAL, the parent of United Airlines, said it would report a loss for the quarter that ends today, driving its stock price, which had already fallen 43 percent this year, down another $2, to $42 a share.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>UAL Says It Expects a Loss, And Its Stock Falls Further  UAL, the parent of United Airlines, said it would report a loss for the quarter that ends today, driving its stock price, which had already fallen 43 percent this year, down another $2, to $42 a share.</p>
        <p>UAL's chairman, James Goodwin, said operational problems over the summer reduced revenue, and the high cost of jet fuel and a new contract with pilots raised costs. The news came as a surprise to Wall Street analysts, who had been expecting UAL to earn $2.60 to $3.20 a share. [Page C4.]</p>
        <p>Concession by Time Warner and EMI  Time Warner and the EMI Group have offered to sell EMI's Virgin record label, their biggest concession yet, in an 11th-hour attempt to win approval from regulators in Europe for their $20 billion joint venture. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Mattel Sells the Learning Company  Mattel said it was selling the Learning Company, the educational software unit it bought for $3.6 billion in May 1999, to Gores Technology Group, a private equity buyout firm in Los Angeles, for undisclosed terms. Mattel also said it would eliminate 350 jobs and cut its dividend from 9 cents a quarter to 5 cents a year. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Spending Topped Savings in August  The nation's savings rate fell in August to the lowest rate in at least four decades as consumer spending grew 0.6 percent while personal incomes grew by 0.4 percent, the Commerce Department said. But the department also said that prices paid by consumers showed little sign of inflation. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Denmark's Message for Britain  Denmark's rejection of a single European currency could delay or even jeopardize Prime Minister Tony Blair's proposal for a similar vote in Britain, a cornerstone of his plan to persuade reluctant Britons to abandon their cherished pound in favor of the euro. [A3.]</p>
        <p>A Vote in Brazil for a Local Company  When Brazilians go to the polls tomorrow, the voting machines will be a testament to Procomp Industria Eletronica, a local company that has made a name for itself by meeting challenges like developing the machines in less than six months. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Internet Portal for Phones in Europe  The NTT DoCoMo mobile phone company of Japan and KPN Mobile of the Netherlands said they would start an Internet portal for mobile phones next year in Germany, Belgium and the Netherlands. [C2]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
