<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Apple and UAL Lead Market Downward as Quarter Ends</title>
    <meta content="Y30STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/business/30STOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5D7173DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Apple and UAL Lead Market Downward as Quarter Ends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dow Jones industrial average drops 173.14 points, or 1.6 percent, to 10,650.92; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index loses 21.78, or 1.5 percent, to 1,436.51; Nasdaq composite index falls 105.20, or 2.8 percent, to 3,672.82; for third quarter, Nasdaq fell 7.4 percent and S&amp;P 500 was down 1.2 percent, while Dow rose 1.9 percent; graph; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks closed a shaky third quarter shakily yesterday, as negative earnings warnings from Apple Computer and United Airlines pulled down a wide swath of companies.</p>
        <p>The profit warnings from Apple and the UAL Corporation, the parent of United, were merely the latest in a string of red flags hung out over the last two weeks by big high-profile businesses. And since companies are not scheduled to actually start reporting their results for another 10 days to two weeks, market strategists said, the possibility of additional bad surprises has investors on edge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks closed a shaky third quarter shakily yesterday, as negative earnings warnings from Apple Computer and United Airlines pulled down a wide swath of companies.</p>
        <p>The profit warnings from Apple and the UAL Corporation, the parent of United, were merely the latest in a string of red flags hung out over the last two weeks by big high-profile businesses. And since companies are not scheduled to actually start reporting their results for another 10 days to two weeks, market strategists said, the possibility of additional bad surprises has investors on edge.</p>
        <p>''What the market told us in September is that investors are beginning to get concerned that even though the rate of economic expansion is still above trend line, it is decelerating, and may produce more earnings disappointments than analysts expect,'' said Byron R. Wien, United States equity strategist at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter. ''As the quarter developed, that suspicion increased.''</p>
        <p>Major market averages did an about-face yesterday after a sharp rise on Thursday. For the quarter, two of the three declined, and all three are down for the year.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average slumped 173.14, or 1.6 percent, to 10,650.92. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index lost 21.78, or 1.5 percent, to 1,436.51. The Nasdaq composite index fell 105.50, or 2.8 percent, to 3,672.82.</p>
        <p>For the quarter, the Nasdaq fell 7.4 percent and the S.&amp; P. 500 was down 1.2 percent. The Dow, by contrast, rose 1.9 percent.</p>
        <p>But through the first nine months, all three averages are trading below their closing levels on Dec. 31, 1999: the Dow is down 7.4 percent, the S.&amp; P. down 2.2 percent and the Nasdaq down 9.75 percent.</p>
        <p>As it was the previous three years, the summer quarter this year proved difficult for stocks. Concerns about rising energy prices, a weak euro and, ultimately, how the two would affect profits, caused stocks to yo-yo throughout the period.</p>
        <p>''July was down; August was up, and September was down,'' said Douglas R. Cliggott, United States equity strategist at J. P. Morgan Securities. ''In July, the reality of slower earnings started to feed into the market. In August, those earnings concerns were overwhelmed by joy that the Federal Reserve Board was done raising short-term interest rates. And in September, earnings concerns have re-emerged.''</p>
        <p>Investors aggressively sold shares of companies that said they would not meet profit expectations.</p>
        <p>Intel, which a week ago came out with a negative earnings report, has fallen severely. The semiconductor giant closed at $41.56 yesterday, down $2.88. For the quarter, the stock fell 37.8 percent, the biggest percentage drop of any Dow 30 stock.</p>
        <p>Lucent Technologies is another example. Back in July, the telephone equipment manufacturer said that earnings would fall short of expectations. Since then, the stock, one of the most widely held, has declined more than 48 percent.</p>
        <p>Finally, there is Apple. Its warning, which came after the market closed Thursday, generated a torrent of sell orders yesterday.</p>
        <p>By the close, Apple's stock stood at $25.75, down $27.75 on the day. The one-day move made the stock the second-worst performer in the Nasdaq 100 for the quarter.</p>
        <p>In the last two weeks, 23 companies in the S.&amp; P. 500 index have forecast profit or sales shortfalls. Sixty-four percent of the forecasts that companies have made for their third-quarter results have been negative, according to First Call/ Thompson Financial.</p>
        <p>''The third quarter is always the heaviest period for downward earnings revisions,'' said Thomas Galvin, chief investment officer at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette. ''Part of that is that as companies get into August and September, they have to get more realistic and share it with analysts.''</p>
        <p>But there have been bright spots.</p>
        <p>Utility stocks, widely seen as the safest investments, were stars in the third quarter, continuing a yearlong advance.</p>
        <p>In the quarter, the Dow Jones utilities average rose 29.7 percent. For the year, it is up more than 40 percent. Homebuilders, consumer finance companies and property and casualty insurance companies also had a good quarter.</p>
        <p>Boeing was the best-performing Dow stock, its shares rising more than 50 percent. J. P. Morgan was next best. The stock gained more than 48 percent, largely on the strength of its agreement to be bought by Chase Manhattan Bank.</p>
        <p>Among the stocks in the S.&amp; P. 500, Manor Care, the assisted-living company, did the best in the third quarter, gaining 124 percent. Owens Corning did the worst, falling more than 71 percent.</p>
        <p>Attention -- and hope -- now shifts to the fourth quarter. In recent years, the market has performed best in the final three months.</p>
        <p>''Over the last five years, the S.&amp; P. has risen an average of 10 percent in the fourth quarter, and the Nasdaq an average of 15 percent,'' Mr. Galvin said. ''As a percentage of full-year gains, the fourth quarter has represented nearly half of all the annual performance of the market, as measured by the S.&amp; P. 500 and the Nasdaq.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cliggott said history would have a difficult time repeating itself this year, if only because the Federal Reserve is not likely to prove helpful to stock investors.</p>
        <p>Last year, the Fed flooded the banking system with liquidity to ward off potential computer problems associated with the end of the century. At the end of 1998, the Fed eased monetary policy to minimize any damage from Russia's default. And the year before, it did the same because of Asia's financial crisis.</p>
        <p>''That is a huge difference,'' Mr. Cliggott said.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
