<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COLLEGE FOOTBALL REPORT</title>
    <meta content="30COL.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litsky, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE3DA143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COLLEGE FOOTBALL REPORT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Litsky</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matchup of key college football games this week noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Today's KEY GAMES  NO. 6 WASHINGTON 3-0  NO. 20 at OREGON 3-1  Rankings or not, Oregon, which has won 17 straight at home, is a slight favorite. Last week, it held U.C.L.A. to minus-9 yards rushing. But Washington's quarterback, Marques Tuiasosopo, can run and throw and is especially dangerous when the pocket breaks down.</p>
        <p>NO. 17 WISCONSIN 3-1  NO. 9 at MICHIGAN3-1  A big game in the Big Ten title picture. Both teams have punishing runners, and Michigan has quarterback Drew Henson back after a broken foot. As for Wisconsin's surprising loss to Northwestern last week, Coach Barry Alvarez said, ''If we don't live up to other people's expectations, I'm sorry.''TV: CH7, Noon</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Today's KEY GAMES  NO. 6 WASHINGTON 3-0  NO. 20 at OREGON 3-1  Rankings or not, Oregon, which has won 17 straight at home, is a slight favorite. Last week, it held U.C.L.A. to minus-9 yards rushing. But Washington's quarterback, Marques Tuiasosopo, can run and throw and is especially dangerous when the pocket breaks down.</p>
        <p>NO. 17 WISCONSIN 3-1  NO. 9 at MICHIGAN3-1  A big game in the Big Ten title picture. Both teams have punishing runners, and Michigan has quarterback Drew Henson back after a broken foot. As for Wisconsin's surprising loss to Northwestern last week, Coach Barry Alvarez said, ''If we don't live up to other people's expectations, I'm sorry.''TV: CH7, Noon</p>
        <p>NO. 3 FLORIDA 4-0  at MISSISSIPPI STATE 2-1  Florida continues to puzzle Coach Steve Spurrier. Last time out, it allowed Kentucky 504 yards and still won by 28 points. In that game, Jesse Palmer ran for four touchdowns and passed for one. Mississippi State will bedevil Southeastern Conference foes.</p>
        <p>EAST</p>
        <p>No. 4 Virginia Tech (3-0)  at Boston College (2-1)  Boston College, which rolled up 625 yards against Navy, returns to earth.  TV: CH2, 3:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>No. 10 Miami (2-1)  at Rutgers (2-2)  An easy one for Miami, especially since quarterback Mike McMahon of Rutgers won't start because of a strained throwing shoulder.</p>
        <p>No. 16 Texas Christian (3-0)  at Navy (0-3)  Navy's soft pass defense runs into a passing buzzsaw.  TV: MSG, Noon</p>
        <p>No. 22 Purdue (3-1)  at Penn State (1-4)  Another rough day for Penn State, already off to its worst start in Joe Paterno's 35 years as head coach.  TV: CH7, 3:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Brigham Young (2-3)  at Syracuse (1-2)  Syracuse starts a mean four-game stretch that also includes Pitt, Boston College and Virginia Tech.  TV: ESPN2, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>Princeton (0-2)  at Columbia (1-1)  Columbia has the livelier offense of these struggling Ivy teams.</p>
        <p>Holy Cross (3-0)  at Yale (1-1)  This could be easy for Yale, averaging 495 yards a game in offense.</p>
        <p>SOUTH</p>
        <p>No. 11 Tennessee (2-1)  at Louisiana State (2-2)  A tough prelude for Tennessee, which next plays Georgia, Alabama and South Carolina.  TV: ESPN, 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>No. 23 South Carolina (4-0)  at Alabama (1-3)  With quarterback Phil Petty doubtful with a sprained right ankle, South Carolina's odyssey is in danger.</p>
        <p>Vanderbilt (1-3)  at No. 19 Auburn (4-0)  Vanderbilt's big offense runs into a bigger one.</p>
        <p>Memphis (3-1)  at No. 21 So. Mississippi (2-1)  Southern Mississippi, with tight defense, finally plays at home after beating Alabama and Oklahoma State on the road.</p>
        <p>MIDWEST</p>
        <p>Northwestern (3-1)  at No. 18 Michigan State (3-0)  Northwestern played its game of the year in upsetting Wisconsin.  TV: CH9, Noon</p>
        <p>No. 24 Illinois (3-1)  at Minnesota (2-2)  Minnesota, which couldn't handle the passing of Drew Brees of Purdue, must now stop Kurt Kittner of Illinois.  TV: ESPN, Noon</p>
        <p>SOUTHWEST</p>
        <p>Oklahoma State (2-1)  at No. 13 Texas (2-1)  Texas still struggles on offense, but its defense (nine turnovers against Houston) is first rate.</p>
        <p>Kansas (2-1)  at No. 14 Oklahoma (3-0)  Oklahoma (532 yards against Rice) has too much offense.</p>
        <p>No. 25 Georgia (2-1)  at Arkansas (3-0)  Arkansas, whose touchdown pass beat Alabama with 64 seconds left, is a dangerous underdog.</p>
        <p>FAR WEST</p>
        <p>No. 5 Kansas State (4-0)  at Colorado (0-3)  Coach Gary Barnett of Colorado says of Kansas State: ''Because they're so dominant, you can get caught up in how good they've been every week and it can paralyze you a little bit.''</p>
        <p>No. 8 Southern California (3-0)  at Oregon State (3-0)  Southern California needed three touchdowns in the last 8:07 to beat San Jose State.</p>
        <p>Arizona State (3-0)  at No. 15 U.C.L.A. (3-1)  U.C.L.A., after a strong start to the season, is making too many mistakes.  TV: FSNY, 10:15 p.m.</p>
        <p>MISMATCHES</p>
        <p>Missouri (1-2)  at No. 1 Nebraska (3-0)  Against Iowa last week, Nebraska rushed for 331 yards and Eric Crouch threw 5 touchdown passes.  TV: FSNY, 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>No. 7 Clemson (4-0)  at Duke (0-4)  In beating Virginia, Woodrow Dantzler of Clemson ran for 220 yards and passed for 154.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
