<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Lennon, Time, Loss And Parole</title>
    <meta content="30NYC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/nyregion/30NYC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Beatles, the</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chapman, Mark David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lennon, John (1940-80)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ono, Yoko</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EFDE143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="837" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Lennon, Time, Loss And Parole</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses possibility of parole for Mark David Chapman, who killed Beatle John Lennon 20 years ago; Chapman says in interviews that he could not kill again; article notes that only 5.6 percent of murderers making their first parole board appearance are released; Lennon's wife, Yoko Ono, has written to parole board, though content of her letter has not been made public; officially, public opinion should not be consideration, but article maintains it is difficult to ignore, as millions grieved Lennon's death (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was impossible to suppress a gulp when a copy of Modern Maturity crossed the desk a few months ago, and there on the cover was Paul McCartney. Odd enough that he is called Sir Paul these days. But to have the former Beatle turn up as a poster boy for codgers-in-training was a startling reminder of time's relentless passage.</p>
        <p>Here's another bulletin from the Beatles and the running-clock front: it is 20 years, shy a couple of months, since John Lennon was shot to death outside his apartment building on the Upper West Side. Not only that, but his killer, at least in theory, may soon saunter out of Attica state prison. How's that for the march of time?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was impossible to suppress a gulp when a copy of Modern Maturity crossed the desk a few months ago, and there on the cover was Paul McCartney. Odd enough that he is called Sir Paul these days. But to have the former Beatle turn up as a poster boy for codgers-in-training was a startling reminder of time's relentless passage.</p>
        <p>Here's another bulletin from the Beatles and the running-clock front: it is 20 years, shy a couple of months, since John Lennon was shot to death outside his apartment building on the Upper West Side. Not only that, but his killer, at least in theory, may soon saunter out of Attica state prison. How's that for the march of time?</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, members of the New York State Parole Board are scheduled to journey to Attica, where they will interview 52 inmates whose sentences are due for reappraisal. You probably never heard of 51 of them. But you almost surely know about No. 52: Mark David Chapman, a self-described ''nobody'' who decided to become famous in December 1980 by ending the life of the man whose words and music helped shape the sensibilities of a generation.</p>
        <p>Believe it or not, you refugees from the 60's, Mr. Chapman is eligible for parole, for the first time since he was sentenced to a prison term of 20 years to life.</p>
        <p>A jailhouse interview with him appeared this week in The Daily Express of London, and more of his musings are to come on Monday in a Court TV program. Now 45, Mr. Chapman says he is no longer the demon-plagued man who fired four bullets into Lennon outside the Dakota apartment building and then waited there, calmly reading the novel that was his obsession, ''The Catcher in the Rye.''</p>
        <p>He could not kill again, he insists. ''I think the depression is over, the mental illness is over,'' he said in the interviews, all conducted by Jack Jones, a journalist in Rochester, N.Y., who has been chronicling this Nowhere Man for years.</p>
        <p>Still, other things that Mr. Chapman said could give anyone the willies, including a Parole Board member. He mentioned that he had dreamed of visiting the Dakota, at Central Park West and 72nd Street, and being embraced by Yoko Ono, Lennon's widow.</p>
        <p>''I've had that dream several times,'' he said. ''In it, Yoko Ono is friendly to me and I am, you know, accepted in the home and feel loved.'' Though he added that he had not had the dream ''in a long time,'' some people might find themselves humming the ''Twilight Zone'' theme.</p>
        <p>Is it possible that this murderer will go free? Again, in theory, yes. In reality, however, his chances are about as good as those of John Rocker's being invited to address a conference of the New York Immigration Coalition.</p>
        <p>FORGET Mr. Chapman's notoriety, which hardly works in his favor. Any killer going before the Parole Board for the first time faces a deck stacked heavily against him.</p>
        <p>In the last three years, 303 inmates doing time in New York State prisons for murder or attempted murder made their first appearance before the board. A whopping total of 17 were released. That's 5.6 percent. The numbers were not much better for those convicted of manslaughter. Over those three years, 1,065 first-timers went before the board; 69 were freed, or 6.5 percent.</p>
        <p>''My guess is that Chapman will never get parole, so all this is a case of going through the motions,'' said Robert Gangi, executive director of the Correctional Association of New York. His group, which monitors prisons, argues strongly for preserving parole, a position that runs against the present political tide in this state.</p>
        <p>Naturally, parole officials are offering no predictions. Thomas Grant, a spokesman for the state's Division of Parole, said the board members would base their findings on what Mr. Chapman tells them directly, not on press interviews. They also, Mr. Grant said, will consider the likely impact of their decision on those victimized by the killer. He meant the Lennon family. Indeed, Ms. Ono has written to the board, though it is not known what she said.</p>
        <p>You could argue, as Mr. Gangi does, that Mr. Chapman left millions of victims, people around the world who mourned Lennon's death as if he were family. Officially, their opinions do not count. But it is hard to imagine how the parole board can ignore them -- or the outcry it could expect were it to release Mr. Chapman.</p>
        <p>Those millions seem unlikely to be impressed by the killer's assurance that Lennon would have wanted him freed. That is something we will never know, will we? Mark David Chapman took care of that.</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
