<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Seek Insurance With a Second Kicker</title>
    <meta content="30GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/sports/30GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daluiso, Brad</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E3DA173DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Seek Insurance With a Second Kicker</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Sept. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants consider carrying second kicker on roster after Brad Daluiso misses practice because of injury; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The visitor at the Giants' practice field today had a familiar face and he shared laughs on the sideline with the incumbent place-kicker, Brad Daluiso. The presence of Jaret Holmes, a kicker who was on the Giants' practice squad last season, did not seem to bother Daluiso.</p>
        <p>Daluiso returned to the field today after missing practice Thursday with a stiff back. Between stretching moves worthy of a contortionist, he kicked 10 field goals, and if he feels fine after kicking again on Saturday, he should be ready to play Sunday against the Tennessee Titans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The visitor at the Giants' practice field today had a familiar face and he shared laughs on the sideline with the incumbent place-kicker, Brad Daluiso. The presence of Jaret Holmes, a kicker who was on the Giants' practice squad last season, did not seem to bother Daluiso.</p>
        <p>Daluiso returned to the field today after missing practice Thursday with a stiff back. Between stretching moves worthy of a contortionist, he kicked 10 field goals, and if he feels fine after kicking again on Saturday, he should be ready to play Sunday against the Tennessee Titans.</p>
        <p>But the Giants were apparently concerned enough about Daluiso's ability to kick field goals, extra points and kickoffs at Tennessee to look for insurance. Holmes played for Berlin in National Football League Europe last spring and was one of the last cuts by the Bears following training camp. The Giants do not have a second experienced kicker on their current roster, so asked Holmes to try out.</p>
        <p>''I certainly don't blame them,'' Daluiso said.</p>
        <p>After Holmes's workout, Coach Jim Fassel indicated the team could carry two kickers on Sunday, but signing Holmes would necessitate another transaction to create a roster spot. Fassel did not say whether  he would sign Holmes.</p>
        <p>Daluiso, who is coming back from major surgery on his left knee, has struggled for consistency on his kickoffs, but Fassel believes he has been improving.</p>
        <p>Over all, Fassel said he liked what he had seen in practice. He berated players following Thursday's workout and blamed them for showing ''casualness'' following their first loss of the season, to Washington last Sunday.</p>
        <p>Today the Giants appeared enthusiastic, running on and off the field during their field-goal kicking drills. They will need concentration Sunday when they play at Tennessee's Adelphia Coliseum, a deafening place where the Titans have won a record-tying nine straight games since the stadium opened last season.</p>
        <p>''I think they had good focus,'' Fassel said of his players after practice. ''They understand what I said yesterday.''</p>
        <p>Linebacker Jessie Armstead said:  ''Guys came out with a more focused attitude. We just have to cut down on our mistakes. If you make a mistake, you don't want to make it twice.''</p>
        <p>A repeat performance would mean a sure defeat to an elite team. After reaching the Super Bowl last season, the Titans still possess one of the N.F.L.'s most feared defenses and productive special teams. Kick returner Derrick Mason has helped the Titans begin their average drives on kickoffs at the 37.4-yard line, best in the league.</p>
        <p>Yet Tennessee's offensive game plan plays to the Giants' strength. The Giants' secondary was burned repeatedly by Washington last week, and although free safety Shaun Williams and the defensive backs coach Johnnie Lynn expect the Titans to test them again, that would be out of character for Tennessee. The Titans are essentially a running team, especially with wideout Kevin Dyson out for the season with a knee injury. The Giants' defense has been unyielding against the run.</p>
        <p>With Steve McNair expected to start at quarterback, Tennessee is even more likely to feature its ground attack. McNair's average of 5.8 yards per pass attempt is sixth lowest in the league.</p>
        <p>McNair did not start the Titans' game last week against Pittsburgh because of a bruised sternum, but he entered to lead the Titans to a comeback victory. He took the majority of snaps in practice this week and was named the starter today.</p>
        <p>The Titans rely heavily on running back Eddie George, but he has averaged just 2.9 yards a carry. The Giants have the No. 1-ranked rushing defense in the National Football Conference; they are holding opponents to 64.3 yards a game.</p>
        <p>Titans quarterbacks have passed for only two touchdowns in three games. Giants linebacker Mike Barrow said McNair was a quarterback who could scramble for yardage but noted that in the Giants' first three games, they defeated teams with mobile quarterbacks. Washington's quarterback, Brad Johnson, a more traditional passer, beat them with long passes.</p>
        <p>''I guess you kind of see the mettle of your team this week,'' Giants cornerback Jason Sehorn said of playing after a loss.</p>
        <p>Frank Wycheck, a tight end who is a huge part of Tennessee's offense, should return from a concussion. He was cleared to play by doctors, which is especially important because wide receiver Yancey Thigpen was deactivated today with an injured hamstring.</p>
        <p>The Giants' biggest questions are on offense. The Giants' passing game struggled against Washington, and Tennessee has the top-ranked pass defense in its conference. The Giants' offensive line, which allowed four sacks to Washington, will have to stop the Titans' explosive defensive end, Jevon Kearse.</p>
        <p>But the Titans have been less successful defending the run, and the Giants' combination of Tiki Barber and Ron Dayne forms the league's top rushing offense.</p>
        <p>Quarterback Kerry Collins called Sunday's game ''our biggest challenge of the year.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
