<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; From Lithuanians, a Startling Lesson</title>
    <meta content="30ARAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234807"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lithuania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lithuania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Lithuania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD6173DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; From Lithuanians, a Startling Lesson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses close semifinal game in men's Olympic basketball between Lithuania and United States; praises Lithuanian team for valiant effort; contends United States team is not talented enough to be thrown together with one week of practice to perform as 'dream teams' have in past years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE should be no complaining now about the result, the near shocking upset. No whingeing (whining), as they like to say here. We wanted competition, didn't we? We've been crying out for actual basketball contests of shooting and strength and will, and not the dunk-and-pony shows that became so tedious the minute Michael, Magic and Larry departed their grand Olympic stage.</p>
        <p>Instead of moaning about what Our Guys couldn't do on a night the basketball world permanently readjusted its perception of American dominance, how about we begin with what the Lithuanians nearly did? How about that road stop of a country, which in 1992 needed the Grateful Dead to chip in for uniforms so it could hail its exit from Soviet stranglehold on the international sporting stage?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE should be no complaining now about the result, the near shocking upset. No whingeing (whining), as they like to say here. We wanted competition, didn't we? We've been crying out for actual basketball contests of shooting and strength and will, and not the dunk-and-pony shows that became so tedious the minute Michael, Magic and Larry departed their grand Olympic stage.</p>
        <p>Instead of moaning about what Our Guys couldn't do on a night the basketball world permanently readjusted its perception of American dominance, how about we begin with what the Lithuanians nearly did? How about that road stop of a country, which in 1992 needed the Grateful Dead to chip in for uniforms so it could hail its exit from Soviet stranglehold on the international sporting stage?</p>
        <p>How about a population (3.7 million) that is less than Sydney's waking up this morning with the realization that its determined collection of clashing consonants was a couple of heartbeats from sending its opponent home as the Bad Dream Team? How about that 20-4 second-half run, as the Lithuanians sat back in the zone defense, daring the Americans to make the jump shot? Years of declining field-goal percentages in our celebrated professional league was the prophecy that our boys weren't going to convert their jumpers here with any earthshaking regularity.</p>
        <p>For two weeks here, Alonzo Mourning &amp; Co. have been asking people to stop comparing them to past United States teams, one in particular, a most reasonable request. Yet at the same time, Mourning also said that this team's defining trait was its defense, and that Rudy Tomjanovich was coaching ''the greatest defensive team ever.'' Excuse me, but was that a parade of Lithuanians, French and Russians marching down the lane over the last several days and, at times, scoring at will?</p>
        <p>The myth of the original Dream Team was that it was any kind of team at all. In 1992, it was really an assemblage of great individuals representing the 1980's, greatest of all basketball decades. For the most part, those were the supremely talented contemporary players who also had the fundamental skills of the sport's more earthbound past. They stepped onto the court with a pure sense of basketball intuition. They understood the game, its ebb and flow, and when they sensed the time had come, they clamped down defensively and the opponent would go nine minutes without scoring.</p>
        <p>The team staggering into tomorrow afternoon's gold medal game against France after an 85-83 semifinal victory last night was just grateful it wasn't dead after Lithuania's best free-throw shooter clanked two of three late and crucial attempts. These guys play with the least minute-to-minute continuity of any United States team I've ever seen, and that includes the collegians who won the Goodwill Games two years ago against some of these same international outfits.</p>
        <p>If anything, Team 2000 is also a reflection of the decade past. And with the exception of the Bulls, the 1990's were about exciting but flawed players being marketed as the transcendent superstars they were not.</p>
        <p>''We can't sit here and make excuses and say we only won by 2 points because Shaq wasn't here or Tim Duncan wasn't here,'' Vince Carter said, composed again after he and the others on the United States side looked as if they'd seen the Blair Witch in the game's final minutes. ''Who's to say?''</p>
        <p>Sure, we can argue that if Shaquille O'Neal had come to Sydney, Lithuania would not have come this close. Earnest as he is, Mourning has proved the last three playoff springs he is not a dominant center, and in certain respects, is not a center at all. O'Neal would be punishing these fellows but good, but he is also the rarest of the physically gifted.</p>
        <p>So what are we saying? The absence of one, even two, players from the big, bad U.S.A. is enough to level the playing field against little ol' Lithuania?</p>
        <p>Based on last night, the close preliminary round game between the two countries was no fluke. From the looks of things, the 21st Century David Stern All-Stars just aren't complete enough players to be thrown together with a week's worth of practice in the expectation that they will blow away teams that execute, shoot well and -- most significantly -- are no longer in awe, or afraid.</p>
        <p>''Basketball has evolved in eight years,'' Carter said. ''My expectation was just to win games.''</p>
        <p>True or not, what else could he say after running jubilantly off the court with his index finger raised? On this night, he was just happy to survive, win, like all those other appreciative Olympians we love.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
