<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mrs. Clinton Is Riding The Trend, Polls Agree</title>
    <meta content="30POLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/politics/30POLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Dean E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E5DE143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mrs. Clinton Is Riding The Trend, Polls Agree</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Dean E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several independent polls show Hillary Rodham Clinton ahead of Representative Rick A Lazio; pollsters say Lazio's numbers indicate conservative and anti-Clinton support, but little progress in letting other voters know his positions on issues (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Several recent independent polls in the New York Senate race show Hillary Rodham Clinton has secured a modest but solid lead over Representative Rick A. Lazio.</p>
        <p>Although the polls are inconsistent in some respects and the election is still more than five weeks away, the pollsters agree the trend for now is in Mrs. Clinton's favor and that the burden is on Mr. Lazio to reverse it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Several recent independent polls in the New York Senate race show Hillary Rodham Clinton has secured a modest but solid lead over Representative Rick A. Lazio.</p>
        <p>Although the polls are inconsistent in some respects and the election is still more than five weeks away, the pollsters agree the trend for now is in Mrs. Clinton's favor and that the burden is on Mr. Lazio to reverse it.</p>
        <p>''The polls are singing the same tune but with different strengths,'' said Lee M. Miringoff of the Marist College Institute for Public Opinion in Poughkeepsie. ''They are moving in the same direction.''</p>
        <p>Of the half-dozen or so polls conducted since Mr. Lazio and Mrs. Clinton debated in Buffalo on Sept. 13, Mr. Miringoff's is alone in not putting Mrs. Clinton ahead. The Marist poll, released Sept. 21, showed the two candidates tied, with 48 percent each among likely voters. The poll had a margin of error of plus or minus 4 percentage points.</p>
        <p>More significant than the margin between the two candidates, however, Mr. Miringoff and others said, is Mrs. Clinton's consistent showings near 50 percent. With the exception of the Marist poll, Mr. Lazio has not been able to break beyond the low 40's, an indication, some pollsters said, that he has attracted core Republicans and anti-Clinton voters but has not made much progress in letting other voters know who he is or what he stands for.</p>
        <p>''A problem for Lazio is what is going on at the top of the ticket with Vice President Al Gore,'' said Larry Hugick, vice president of Princeton Survey Research Associates in Princeton, N.J. ''If Gore is really as far ahead in New York as he seems, and it stays that way, it is going to be hard for Lazio. He is getting crossover votes now, but he needs a lot more.''</p>
        <p>A new poll by Princeton Survey Research Associates for Newsday and Channel 11 showed Mrs. Clinton ahead of Mr. Lazio, 52 percent to 42 percent, while a Quinnipiac University Polling Institute poll released on Wednesday showed Mrs. Clinton ahead 50 percent to 43 percent. The New York Times/CBS poll on Sept. 21 gave Mrs. Clinton a 9-point lead, 48 percent to 39 percent, and a poll by Blum &amp; Weprin Associates for The Daily News and WCBS released on Sept. 17 put her ahead 48 percent to 43 percent. The margins of error for the four polls ranged from 3 to 4.5 percentage points.</p>
        <p>The two polls this week that placed Mrs. Clinton at 50 percent or above passed an important psychological barrier in the race, the pollsters said.</p>
        <p>''You can't lose at 50, you can only tie,'' said Maurice Carroll, director of the Quinnipiac organization. ''It is the magic number.''</p>
        <p>Mickey Blum, president of Blum &amp; Weprin Associates, said the 50 percent mark is significant also because it requires a trailing candidate to change voters' minds in order to win, not merely attract those who say they are undecided.</p>
        <p>''She needs to hold on to what she has got, but he actually has to take voters away from her, and that is harder to do,'' Ms. Blum said.</p>
        <p>As is the practice when polls lean one way or the other in a close race, Mr. Lazio's campaign is taking exception with most of the polls that show him behind. Aides to the Republican congressman complain that the methodology often favors respondents in New York City, which is more Democratic than most suburban areas and rural upstate counties. They have found other problems with the sampling as well. In the case of the Newsday/Channel 11 poll released yesterday, for example, the percentage of female respondents was higher than the percentage of female voters in recent statewide elections.</p>
        <p>The central message from the pollsters, however, has not been lost on the Lazio campaign, his aides said.</p>
        <p>''We are going to spend a lot of time talking about the issues New Yorkers care about,'' said Mollie Fullington, a Lazio spokeswoman. ''It is our responsibility and challenge to make sure when New Yorkers go to the polling booths on Election Day that they know who Rick Lazio is.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's campaign, also following the expected script in such situations, expressed gratitude for her edge in the polls, but said Mrs. Clinton was not crowing. Her spokeswoman, Cathie Levine, said the first lady expected a close race and, while encouraged by the recent polls, was not taking a victory for granted.</p>
        <p>The back and forth on polls and the expectations they create are likely to become a bigger part of the campaign as Election Day draws nearer. Mrs. Clinton has the momentum today, but by trailing in the polls now, Mr. Lazio enjoys a certain underdog status that can energize supporters and work to his advantage tomorrow. All it takes is for one major poll to show Mr. Lazio closing the gap, and Mrs. Clinton will be seen as slipping rather than surging.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
