<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brand-Name Auctions, Cut-Rate Connoisseurs</title>
    <meta content="30GOOD$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/opinion/30GOOD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234779"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodheart, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1D9173DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brand-Name Auctions, Cut-Rate Connoisseurs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Adam Goodheart</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodheart, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adam Goodheart Op-Ed article holds price-fixing scandal tarnishing Sotheby's and Christie's may be good for art world by eroding auction houses's aura of infallibility and perhaps spurring collectors to apply higher standards of scutiny to both artworks and art auctions; drawing (M)d</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To many both inside and outside the art world, seeing the names Sotheby's and Christie's next to the words ''collusion'' and ''price-fixing'' has come as something of a shock. The auction houses have long maintained an air of white-glove purity, of aristocratic connoisseurship. The fact that the houses are now facing considerable public embarrassment, not to mention a $512 million settlement to the customers they allegedly defrauded, has sent nervous tremors throughout the art market -- many collectors especially are wondering how this will undermine the sanctity of art transactions.</p>
        <p>But the tarnishing of Sotheby's and Christie's ancient escutcheons may turn out to be a good thing for the art world, and even for art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To many both inside and outside the art world, seeing the names Sotheby's and Christie's next to the words ''collusion'' and ''price-fixing'' has come as something of a shock. The auction houses have long maintained an air of white-glove purity, of aristocratic connoisseurship. The fact that the houses are now facing considerable public embarrassment, not to mention a $512 million settlement to the customers they allegedly defrauded, has sent nervous tremors throughout the art market -- many collectors especially are wondering how this will undermine the sanctity of art transactions.</p>
        <p>But the tarnishing of Sotheby's and Christie's ancient escutcheons may turn out to be a good thing for the art world, and even for art.</p>
        <p>Critics of the two houses have long complained that their reputation is based more in hype than in reality. The auction business is in many ways an ugly one, drawing its lifeblood from death, divorce and financial trouble. (Witness Sotheby's recent sale of the fallen financier Saul Steinberg's collection.) And this isn't the first time the two companies have faced accusations of wrongdoing. In the 1990's, for example, the London investigative journalist Peter Watson and others accused Sotheby's of camouflaging the origins of stolen and smuggled artwork. While denying it had knowingly smuggled anything, Sotheby's announced in 1997 that it would tighten its procedures in response to accusations of improprieties.</p>
        <p>Ever since the Renaissance, a mystique has surrounded the process of collecting art. This is partly because it's expensive and partly because it's difficult. The popular image of a suave, pinstriped connoisseur casting a cool eye over a dealer's offerings has little basis in fact, however. Your typical collector, at the moment of decision on a major purchase, can often be a mass of insecurities: Is it authentic? Is the price right? Does it match the sofa?  In the hothouse, bid-or-pass atmosphere of the auction room, such anxieties are magnified tenfold. The auction houses' overburnished prestige gave buyers confidence in the works they purchased, functioning like an Armani label on a jacket.</p>
        <p>Over the past few decades, the art world's reliance on such labels seems to have intensified. Many novice collectors have entered the market; and the art world, like so much of our culture, has increasingly come under the sway of brand names. The collecting boom has been fueled by crazes for one hot label or another: Impressionist, Warhol, Basquiat. (This isn't  true just at the top end of the market, either: on eBay, the label ''Impressionist,'' applied to the worst paint-by-numbers sunset, seems to drive bidders into a frenzy.) Two of the biggest brand names -- and practioners of ''branding'' -- in the art world have been Sotheby's and Christie's themselves.</p>
        <p>But as the two gradually lose an aura of infallibility, perhaps collectors will start applying higher standards of scrutiny to both artworks and art auctions. Art connoisseurship, after all, is all about the hard work of looking at an object, gathering knowledge about it, teasing out its truths and, just as important, its falsehoods. Brand names -- whether Basquiat or Banana Republic -- are all about saving the consumer from having to look, from having to think.</p>
        <p>''The relation between what we see and what we know is never settled,'' the critic John Berger has written. And in the art world, uncertainty has the potential to fuel not just curiosity, but a greater sense of responsibility -- among auction houses and collectors alike.</p>
        <p>Adam Goodheart is a member of the editorial board of The American Scholar.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Adam Goodheart is a member of the editorial board of The American Scholar.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
