<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>United Airlines Parent Says It Will Have Quarterly Loss</title>
    <meta content="Y30AIR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/business/30AIR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pilots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jet Fuel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Airlines</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ual Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zuckerman, Laurence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pilots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E5DB173DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>United Airlines Parent Says It Will Have Quarterly Loss</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURENCE ZUCKERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zuckerman, Laurence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>UAL Corp, parent of United Airlines, says labor disrpution over summer, coupled with higher cost of jet fuel and expensive new pilot contract, will force it to report loss for quarter ended Sept 30 and probably for next quarter (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The UAL Corporation, the parent of United Airlines, said yesterday that labor disruption over the summer, coupled with the higher cost of jet fuel and an expensive new pilot contract, would force it to report a loss for the quarter that ends today and probably for the next quarter.</p>
        <p>The news surprised Wall Street analysts. As recently as last month, United reiterated its third-quarter earnings estimate of a profit in the range of $2.60 to $3.20 a share.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The UAL Corporation, the parent of United Airlines, said yesterday that labor disruption over the summer, coupled with the higher cost of jet fuel and an expensive new pilot contract, would force it to report a loss for the quarter that ends today and probably for the next quarter.</p>
        <p>The news surprised Wall Street analysts. As recently as last month, United reiterated its third-quarter earnings estimate of a profit in the range of $2.60 to $3.20 a share.</p>
        <p>Although most analysts had been cutting their earnings estimates in recent weeks as United's performance declined, UAL had still been expected to earn 97 cents a share for the third quarter and 63 cents in the fourth before yesterday's announcement, according to the average estimates of analysts surveyed by First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>''It's disheartening,'' said Susan M. Donofrio, an airline analyst at Deutsche Banc Alex. Brown in New York. ''You keep thinking all the bad news is out there and it is not.''</p>
        <p>Brian D. Harris, an airline analyst at Salomon Smith Barney in New York, said United's passenger bookings through October had been hurt by its poor reliability this summer. ''United's got to scramble and do all sorts of initiatives to get people to fly on their planes again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>United, the world's largest airline, had to cancel thousands of flights beginning in April when the contract with its 10,000 pilots came up for renewal. Although the pilots own about 25 percent of UAL's stock, they were angry at the company for what they thought was its unwillingness to grant a generous wage increase after years of below-average pay.</p>
        <p>Many pilots began refusing to fly voluntary overtime, stranding many passengers at the terminal when the airline canceled flights on the day of departure. United eventually reduced its flight schedule by more than 2 percent to help avoid last-minute cancellations, but its performance continued to decline. Fewer than 42 percent of United's flights arrived on time in July, the latest statistics available and by far the worst record in the industry.</p>
        <p>Finally, on Aug. 26, the company and the pilots' union agreed on a tentative new contract that is the richest in the industry. If the deal is approved in a union vote next month, as expected, senior pilots would receive an immediate wage increase of 28.5 percent retroactive to April. (The pay of more junior pilots would increase 21.5 percent.) Wages would then increase 4 percent a year for the life of the four-year contract.</p>
        <p>James E. Goodwin, UAL's chairman, said yesterday in a written statement that the summer's operational problems had reduced revenue significantly, while the new labor contract and the high price of oil had increased costs.</p>
        <p>Like many airlines, United buys futures contracts for oil to protect itself against sudden price increases. But UAL's hedging program was pegged to the price of crude oil, not jet fuel, which has risen much faster, Mr. Goodwin said.</p>
        <p>''We are making every effort to improve our operations and restore our customers' confidence in United,'' he said. ''We believe that these efforts will help us return to profitability.''</p>
        <p>Some analysts are skeptical. UAL is negotiating a new contract with its mechanics, who are also large shareholders in the company. They, too, made concessions in the mid-90's and are eager to receive large wage increases. And the mechanics are not willing to settle for less than the pilots received.</p>
        <p>Other employee groups have joined in. United's 25,000 flight attendants signed a 10-year contract in 1996, but they are now demanding that United raise their wages to a level 5 percent higher than the pay of flight attendants at Delta Air Lines, which is the industry leader.</p>
        <p>The flight attendants union said earlier this week that unless United agrees, it will try to block the airline's proposed $4.3 billion takeover of US Airways. Mr. Goodwin said he would open talks with the union.</p>
        <p>''One of the concerns is with this merger looming ahead, how much power is it giving employees?'' Ms. Donofrio asked.</p>
        <p>She had estimated that UAL would earn $1.90 in the third quarter and $1.10 in the fourth quarter. Yesterday, she cut her estimate to a loss of 25 cents for both quarters. She also downgraded her recommendation to ''market perform'' from ''buy.''</p>
        <p>UAL shares closed yesterday at $42, down $2, or 4.5 percent, on the New York Stock Exchange. The prices of other airline stocks also fell, apparently as a result of UAL's announcement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
