<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ebersol Has Few Regrets About Olympic Coverage</title>
    <meta content="30XTELE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ebersol, Dick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0DB143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ebersol Has Few Regrets About Olympic Coverage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses television coverage of Olympics, emphasizing role of Dick Ebersol, chairman of NBC Sports; Ebersol staunchly defends coverage that is being vilified in other media and garnering low ratings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his sanctuary, his Olympic control room, Dick Ebersol hears no critical evil. Inside the nerve center of NBC Sports' 75,000 square-foot compound, the chairman of NBC Sports happily controls the prime-time production. During 20-hour days he has rarely seen his wife and youngest son. He looks as if he needs a vacation.</p>
        <p>But if he is depressed about lower-than-expected ratings or the criticism about his five-hour nightly cavalcade of events and features, Ebersol will not say. Bob Costas, the prime-time host, said there is no evidence of a change in Ebersol from the highly rated Atlanta Summer Games four years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his sanctuary, his Olympic control room, Dick Ebersol hears no critical evil. Inside the nerve center of NBC Sports' 75,000 square-foot compound, the chairman of NBC Sports happily controls the prime-time production. During 20-hour days he has rarely seen his wife and youngest son. He looks as if he needs a vacation.</p>
        <p>But if he is depressed about lower-than-expected ratings or the criticism about his five-hour nightly cavalcade of events and features, Ebersol will not say. Bob Costas, the prime-time host, said there is no evidence of a change in Ebersol from the highly rated Atlanta Summer Games four years ago.</p>
        <p>''He is a very optimistic person with a sure sense of himself,'' he said. ''It's an understanding of what a leader does. There is no flagging of spirits here. That's largely because of Dick.''</p>
        <p>When his work ends Monday at 3 p.m. Sydney time, Ebersol said: ''I'll be sad because it's over. I'd like it to go on for another week.''</p>
        <p>He said he was never frantic to change anything to resuscitate ratings, and he is astonished at criticism that he is carrying the Olympics on tape from 15 to 18 time zones away but will not carry live events at 4 or 5 in the morning.</p>
        <p>He insisted that viewers still need to be hopscotched between events and informed about athletes. He can tick off evidence that he is staying longer at events before switching than he did in Atlanta or Barcelona, Spain. ''The media would love to have us treat the Olympics like a basketball game, just tip it off and assume everyone knows everything about the Olympics,'' he said today.  He said viewers need what he is providing.</p>
        <p>He chuckled at one printed suggestion that he had ruined the Olympics by showing them on tape-delay or that he is in trouble with his bosses at General Electric for not delivering enough on the $705 million Sydney rights fee.</p>
        <p>The Games will produce a profit, he said, then added, ''You can't get any more straightforward support than the chairman of your company saying, 'If you change a thing, I'll punch you in the nose.' ''</p>
        <p>Ebersol is one of the smoothest executives in television, ever cognizant of his public image and as fluent in the language of production as he in the minutiae of Nielsen ratings. Nearly every day here, he has emerged from his control room, fatigued but somehow energetic, eager to fill the notepads of an audience of reporters as small as one.</p>
        <p>Repeatedly he has excoriated ''jealous'' newspaper editors for assigning stories comparing NBC's taped Olympics with the Canadian Broadcasting Company's ''ludicrous'' live ones without reporting on the CBC's minuscule predawn ratings. But if you've missed those numbers, he has them ready for you in a press release.</p>
        <p>He described newspaper bashing of his Olympics production as ''bloodsport,'' a result of being more immediate, even on tape, than newspapers are from Sydney. ''Editors have had a hard time getting used to the dominance of television in the Olympics,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He cannot see how his production is failing viewers -- surveys, he said, show viewer satisfaction of more than 90 percent -- but he pleads guilty to underestimating the depressing impact of an Olympics in September, when young people are returning to school, when adults are less likely to watch until midnight as they would in July or August.</p>
        <p>''We plateau at 11 o'clock, then the local news break hits, and you could have live naked water polo and viewers won't come back for it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He played down the impact of the Internet on viewing habits and insisted that he would not put live video on his Web site until it was possible to wall off countries and sell online rights country by country the way TV rights are sold.</p>
        <p>Although he cannot escape the reality of lower ratings, which will be the headline about NBC's Olympic experience, he wields the disappointing numbers to prove how the Olympics have driven NBC to power prime-time victories.</p>
        <p>He delighted in pointing out that since 1988, Olympic ratings have fallen less than the World Series, the National Basketball Association finals and ''Monday Night Football'' have in the same period.</p>
        <p>Still, the ratings stare him in the face. Through 14 nights, NBC's 14.0 average rating is down 19 percent from the network's performance in 1988 and 1992 and 35 percent from four years ago. A rating point equals 1.01 million television households.</p>
        <p>This should be a time of lavish praise for Ebersol. It is not. He is, for now, the executive who sent a taped Olympics from Australia to America, in the era of instant, Internet-generated information -- even though Olympics have had a significant taped element for more than 30 years. The strategy has been scored from America to Australia.</p>
        <p>The lack of hosannas for Ebersol is why he called his former rival at CBS Sports, Neal Pilson, now an industry consultant, to thank him for praising NBC's production and saying it is not responsible for lower ratings.</p>
        <p>But Ebersol's strategy has been scorned by news media from America to Australia.</p>
        <p>''I'm not letting it bother me much,'' he said. ''If I had any sensitivity about it -- and it's far less than it was in Atlanta -- I don't have any now.''</p>
        <p>But Ebersol is sensitive, or savvy enough, to have called the radio host Don Imus, who had savaged him for telling Newsweek that he had toned down athlete profiles from their mawkishness in 1996 by ''downgrading asthma as a life-threatening disease.''</p>
        <p>He told Imus the threshold should be lowered to ''a hangnail.''</p>
        <p>As he looks ahead, Ebersol said, much of the Salt Lake City Winter Games will be carried live, but the Athens Summer Games in 2004 will be on tape to put the marquee events into prime time.</p>
        <p>''Live doesn't work in Athens with its seven-hour time difference,'' he said. ''Where would a final fit in prime time? Do you wake an athlete up and send him to the stadium at 2 in the morning?''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
