<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Police in Idaho Searching For a Long Island Woman</title>
    <meta content="30MISS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/nyregion/30MISS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234820"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rewards</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boise (Idaho)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henneman, Lynn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Idaho/Boise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0DF143DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Police in Idaho Searching For a Long Island Woman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lynn Henneman, United Airlines flight attendant from Long Island, disappears in Boise, Idaho, where she was on one-night layover; her purse was found near where, police suspect, she may have been out walking; reward is being offered by family and United for information leading to arrest and conviction; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal investigators and the police in Boise, Idaho, are searching for a newly married flight attendant from Long Island who never showed up for a flight on Monday morning. They believe she disappeared on Sunday after taking a walk from her hotel in Boise, where she was on a one-night layover.</p>
        <p>The woman, Lynn Henneman, 38, of Sag Harbor, has been a United Airlines flight attendant for three years, based at Kennedy International Airport, an airline spokesman said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal investigators and the police in Boise, Idaho, are searching for a newly married flight attendant from Long Island who never showed up for a flight on Monday morning. They believe she disappeared on Sunday after taking a walk from her hotel in Boise, where she was on a one-night layover.</p>
        <p>The woman, Lynn Henneman, 38, of Sag Harbor, has been a United Airlines flight attendant for three years, based at Kennedy International Airport, an airline spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Henneman was staying at the Doubletree Hotel Riverside in Garden City, a community within Boise, and went for a walk on the Boise River Greenbelt, the police said. Using credit card records, the police learned that she shopped at a local art museum, had dinner nearby and may have visited a comedy club.</p>
        <p>Lt. Jim Tibbs, a spokesman for the Boise police, said yesterday that 20 officers were working on the investigation and that search dogs had been called out.</p>
        <p>''We don't know if it was a robbery, we don't know if it was foul play, we don't know if it was sexual, we don't know if it was a kidnapping, we don't know if it was a straight homicide,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''We don't know what the motive is at this point, although it's not looking good. Our hopes are dimming.''</p>
        <p>A reward of $20,000 -- half provided by the family and half by United Airlines -- is being offered for information leading to an arrest and conviction in Ms. Henneman's disappearance, he said.</p>
        <p>Her purse was found near a school, and some of her possessions were found in her hotel room, Lieutenant Tibbs said.</p>
        <p>''As far as anything new, they don't have anything since they found her purse,'' Mark Pettet of Idaho Falls, who is married to Ms. Henneman's sister, said of the police.</p>
        <p>He said yesterday that the police had been talking to a few transients in the area and that some of them thought they might have talked to her.</p>
        <p>''They've kind of chased all the avenues they can. They're not sure where to turn next.''</p>
        <p>When a person disappears under mysterious circumstances and kidnapping is a possibility, the Federal Bureau of Investigation becomes involved after 24 hours, because the person may have been taken across state lines.</p>
        <p>''We know she went to the art museum and dinner, and that's kind of the end of the trail,'' said Bill Matthews, a special agent with the bureau who is based in Salt Lake City. He said he did not believe Ms. Henneman had any enemies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pettet said the purse was the only evidence suggesting there was any foul play involved in his sister-in-law's disappearance.</p>
        <p>''Everything else is totally normal -- her actions, her movements, what she ate, where she ate, her demeanor with the flight crew beforehand,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He described Ms. Henneman as a bit of a loner. ''She liked doing things on her own, she knew what she wanted, she made sure she got it,'' he said. ''She was not very much of a socializer.''</p>
        <p>He said he did not think she did much with her flight crew outside work. ''She liked to find unique restaurants, she liked to find different food,'' he said. ''She did a lot of that on her own.''</p>
        <p>After growing up in a small town -- Livingston, Mont. -- Ms. Henneman spent a lot of time in San Francisco and lived in Manhattan for a while. ''She just really enjoyed going out and seeing the city life and wandering around on her own,'' Mr. Pettet said.</p>
        <p>He said the wait for news was weighing heavily on family members. They include Ms. Henneman's parents, who live in Bozeman, Mont.; her sister, who lives in Idaho Falls; her former husband; and her new husband of three weeks, Walter Us.</p>
        <p>''I know her husband is going to refuse to leave until something shows up,'' Mr. Pettet said. It is not likely, he said, that she would have disappeared to start a new life. ''That would be totally out of character,'' Mr. Pettet said. ''She always wanted to be a flight attendant, and she was finally there doing it. She had never even been late for a flight.''</p>
        <p>In Sag Harbor, a neighbor said she did not see Ms. Henneman or her husband much. ''They were quiet people who kept to themselves,'' said the neighbor, Viola Curley. ''She was busy flying.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
