<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Access to RU-486</title>
    <meta content="30SAT2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/30/opinion/30SAT2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ru-486 (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mifepristone (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE0D7173DF933A0575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Access to RU-486</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial hails Food and Drug Administration approval of abortion-inducing drug RU-486 (mifepristone); sees breakthrough for better access to safe, legal abortions, particularly where abortion services are rare or nonexistent; urges Congress not to override FDA's decisionl</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After more than a decade of legal and political roadblocks, RU-486 has at last been approved by the Food and Drug Administration for abortions in early pregnancy. The widespread use of this drug is far from certain since it is to be employed only during the first seven weeks of pregnancy, and requires more visits to a doctor than surgical abortion does. But it nonetheless represents a breakthrough for better access to safe, legal abortions, particularly in areas of the country where abortion services are rare or nonexistent.</p>
        <p>RU-486, also known as mifepristone, when used in combination with misoprostol, an already approved drug, has been proved safe and effective in numerous clinical tests. More than 600,000 European women have used this method, and it now accounts for more than a third of all abortions in France.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After more than a decade of legal and political roadblocks, RU-486 has at last been approved by the Food and Drug Administration for abortions in early pregnancy. The widespread use of this drug is far from certain since it is to be employed only during the first seven weeks of pregnancy, and requires more visits to a doctor than surgical abortion does. But it nonetheless represents a breakthrough for better access to safe, legal abortions, particularly in areas of the country where abortion services are rare or nonexistent.</p>
        <p>RU-486, also known as mifepristone, when used in combination with misoprostol, an already approved drug, has been proved safe and effective in numerous clinical tests. More than 600,000 European women have used this method, and it now accounts for more than a third of all abortions in France.</p>
        <p>Under the F.D.A.-approved regimen, a patient would first be given a dosage of mifepristone to block the action of progesterone, the hormone that is necessary for the implantation of a fertilized egg in the uterine lining. Two days later the patient would return to the doctor's office to receive a dose of misoprostol, a drug that induces contractions to expel the fetal tissue. About two weeks later she would return for a checkup to determine that the pregnancy has been terminated. The regimen's common side effects, cramping and bleeding, are similar to those of a natural miscarriage.</p>
        <p>The F.D.A.'s approval includes some sensible protections. Only doctors able to determine accurately the duration of a pregnancy and detect an ectopic pregnancy would be allowed to distribute the drug. They must also be able to perform a surgical abortion or refer the patient to another doctor for such surgery if the abortion is incomplete.</p>
        <p>A key benefit of this drug is that it will give women in communities with no surgical abortion services an option that their primary care doctors can administer. State restrictions on abortion will apply to the use of mifepristone, as they do to surgical abortions. Even so, this drug will make abortion a more private procedure, and perhaps less subject to the disruptive protests that frequently surround abortion clinics.</p>
        <p>Already, abortion opponents are looking for ways to limit mifepristone use. Gov. George W. Bush has criticized the F.D.A.'s action as ''wrong,'' and his spokesman says he would order a review of the F.D.A.'s decision. Representative Tom Coburn of Oklahoma will introduce legislation to limit the use of the drug to doctors who currently perform surgical abortions, thus depriving women of easier access. He may also include in his bill a requirement for a registry of those dispensing the drug, which could make doctors targets for anti-abortion harassment.</p>
        <p>Congress should not try to override the F.D.A.'s decision. RU-486 has been intensely studied, and the restrictions imposed by the F.D.A. offer a sound balance in protecting patient health without undermining access to the drug. The truth is, mifepristone's opponents are not focused on patient health. They simply want to make it hard for women to exercise constitutionally protected abortion rights by any method of their choosing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
