<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Gay Man's Awakening Captures the Spirit of a Time</title>
    <meta content="14KRAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drake, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Night Larry Kramer Kissed Me, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E1D81F38F937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Gay Man's Awakening Captures the Spirit of a Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews David Drake's one-man film The Night Larry Kramer Kissed Me; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Commanding the stage in a one-person show is a daunting undertaking. Even more daunting is the attempt to command the movie screen with such a show.</p>
        <p>But in ''The Night Larry Kramer Kissed Me,'' David Drake, reprising his roles as writer and performer of this Obie Award-winning monologue, manages that feat to a praiseworthy degree under the intelligent direction of Tim Kirkman, whose credits include ''Dear Jesse.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Commanding the stage in a one-person show is a daunting undertaking. Even more daunting is the attempt to command the movie screen with such a show.</p>
        <p>But in ''The Night Larry Kramer Kissed Me,'' David Drake, reprising his roles as writer and performer of this Obie Award-winning monologue, manages that feat to a praiseworthy degree under the intelligent direction of Tim Kirkman, whose credits include ''Dear Jesse.''</p>
        <p>The translation of a series of monologues about the life and times of a gay American growing up in the era of the Stonewall riots, the first Gay Pride parade and the plague of AIDS poses the challenge of making material based mainly on words at home in a medium normally at its most hospitable to action.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Drake, whose actorly skills include movement, and Mr. Kirkman, who resists any impulse to open the proceedings beyond the bounds of theater while deftly employing restrained lighting and a few props, meet and overcome this challenge.</p>
        <p>The title ''The Night Larry Kramer Kissed Me'' is a reference to the life-changing occasion on which Mr. Drake, on his 22nd birthday, on June 27, 1985, went to see ''The Normal Heart,'' the play by Mr. Kramer, who founded the gay rights organization Act Up and was shaken into an angry awareness of society's indifference to the AIDS epidemic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Drake's performance takes the audience through his early years of gayness in Baltimore and his decision to leave for New York. He recalls a symbolic Christmas gift for his father, and in the most affecting three scenes he recreates the ambience of a gay gymnasium, takes the onlooker through a sex-drenched night in a gay bar, recalls friends who died of AIDS and envisions a future of gay power.</p>
        <p>At his least interesting, in some of the material about Barbie dolls and his childhood neighbor Janice, Mr. Drake can be cloying; and the show's little touches of humor draw only titters of recognition from its unseen audience. But in discussing indifference to AIDS, in recreating the charged, curious atmosphere and mixed motives of the gym, at the gay bar, and in the midst of death, Mr. Drake can be rivetingly angry, intense, frenetic, frank and touching.</p>
        <p>Theater is ephemeral. The film ''The Night Larry Kramer Kissed Me,'' opening today at the Screening Room, serves the valuable function of preserving not just a performance but the spirit of a time.</p>
        <p>THE NIGHT LARRY KRAMER KISSED ME</p>
        <p>Directed by Tim Kirkman; written by David Drake; director of photography, James Carman; edited by Caitlin Dixon; produced by Michael Caplan and Kirkland Tibbels; released by FilmNext/Montrose Pictures. At the Screening Room, 54 Varick Street, at Laight Street, TriBeCa. Running time: 79 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: David Drake.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
