<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Weighs Timing No. 2 Pick to Upset Rival</title>
    <meta content="Y14CONV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONVENTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E1DA163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Weighs Timing No. 2 Pick to Upset Rival</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore is strongly considering plans to announce his running mate the day after the Republican National Convention ends early next month, as a way of siphoning media attention from the Republican candidate, Gov. George W. Bush, Democratic officials said today.</p>
        <p>National conventions have traditionally afforded presidential nominees a triumphal moment in the spotlight. Sometimes the post-convention ''bounce'' has been fleeting, but other times it has provided real momentum going into the fall campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore is strongly considering plans to announce his running mate the day after the Republican National Convention ends early next month, as a way of siphoning media attention from the Republican candidate, Gov. George W. Bush, Democratic officials said today.</p>
        <p>National conventions have traditionally afforded presidential nominees a triumphal moment in the spotlight. Sometimes the post-convention ''bounce'' has been fleeting, but other times it has provided real momentum going into the fall campaign.</p>
        <p>Concerned that the Republicans could use that bounce to expand the marginal lead they already hold in many national polls, the Democrats are assessing whether to try to reduce Mr. Bush's post-convention coverage with the announcement of their vice-presidential pick.</p>
        <p>''As a tactical option, it's attractive and under serious consideration,'' one top adviser to Mr. Gore said of the plan, which was first reported this morning in USA Today.</p>
        <p>But the adviser said that Mr. Gore had not agreed yet, for several reasons. Mr. Gore may want to allow some time to pass after the Republican convention ends to gauge the public's response to the Republican ticket. And he may also need extra time to determine whether he wants to counter the Republican choice in terms of gender or geography.</p>
        <p>Another variable would be the timing of Mr. Bush's announcement of his running mate. If it is well before the Republican convention, Mr. Gore  will be more likely to make his announcement shortly after the end of that convention, the adviser said.</p>
        <p>Regardless of when Mr. Bush announces his pick, Mr. Gore is likely to announce his choice of running mate well before the Democratic National Convention begins on Aug. 14.</p>
        <p>Democratic officials said today that they have tentatively scheduled President Clinton and Hillary Rodham Clinton to address the convention on its first night, a Monday, allowing Mr. Gore to command the spotlight for most of the next three nights.</p>
        <p>There had been some discussion of having Mrs. Clinton, who is running for the Senate from New York, speak on Tuesday, when the Democrats plan to focus on women candidates. But Mr. Gore's advisers wanted both Clintons to speak on the first evening, to ensure that the vice president would dominate subsequent media coverage.</p>
        <p>Democratic officials said Mrs. Clinton might introduce a biographical video of her husband on Monday night. But they said she would also probably give a speech focusing on her own campaign themes.</p>
        <p>Former Senator Bill Bradley, who formally endorsed Mr. Gore today, is scheduled to be among the featured speakers Tuesday, Democratic officials said. On Wednesday, the convention will begin focusing more on Mr. Gore's biography, with testimonials and, possibly, video clips.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore will accept the nomination on Thursday.</p>
        <p>There has been one hitch to having the Clintons speak Monday night: none of the networks are planning to cover the convention live that night. But Democratic officials said they were hoping ABC would broadcast a halftime report during Monday Night Football in which Mr. Clinton would speak live.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CONVENTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
