<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="14MOVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214651"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E1D91E38F937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. Ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on Page 8.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF ROCKY AND BULLWINKLE,'' starring Rene Russo, Jason Alexander and Robert De Niro, with the voices of June Foray and Keith Scott. Directed by Des McAnuff (PG, 88 minutes). Fans of Jay Ward's old ''Rocky and Bullwinkle'' television show will enjoy the first 10 minutes or so of this movie, which employs the show's characteristically flat animation and goofy humor to update the biographies of the beloved flying squirrel, his antlered sidekick and their enemies Boris, Natasha and Fearless Leader. But the antic whimsy of the cartoon original is betrayed as the film turns into a clunky, muddled stew of special effects, lame jokes and labored attempts at satire. Rocky, Bullwinkle and a young F.B.I. agent save the world from Fearless Leader (Mr. De Niro), but who will save it from misguided, overpriced and overhyped movies? (A. O. Scott).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy movies and film series playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film or series. Ratings and running times are in parentheses. An index of reviews of films opening today appears on Page 8.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF ROCKY AND BULLWINKLE,'' starring Rene Russo, Jason Alexander and Robert De Niro, with the voices of June Foray and Keith Scott. Directed by Des McAnuff (PG, 88 minutes). Fans of Jay Ward's old ''Rocky and Bullwinkle'' television show will enjoy the first 10 minutes or so of this movie, which employs the show's characteristically flat animation and goofy humor to update the biographies of the beloved flying squirrel, his antlered sidekick and their enemies Boris, Natasha and Fearless Leader. But the antic whimsy of the cartoon original is betrayed as the film turns into a clunky, muddled stew of special effects, lame jokes and labored attempts at satire. Rocky, Bullwinkle and a young F.B.I. agent save the world from Fearless Leader (Mr. De Niro), but who will save it from misguided, overpriced and overhyped movies? (A. O. Scott).</p>
        <p>''BUTTERFLY,'' starring Fernando Fernan Gomez and Manuel Lozano. Directed by Jose Luis Cuerda (R, 96 minutes). This gentle, devastating new film, based on short stories by the Spanish writer Manuel Rivas, tells the story of Moncho (Mr. Lozano), a sensitive young boy coming of age in the months before the outbreak of the Spanish Civil War. The movie touches on the usual excitements and mysteries of childhood, but Moncho's relationship with his teacher, the proudly Republican Don Gregorio, beautifully played by Mr. Fernan Gomez, gives the story an unusual degree of pathos and political complexity (Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''CHICKEN RUN,'' with the voices of Mel Gibson, Miranda Richardson and Julia Sawalha. Directed by Peter Lord and Nick Park (G, 86 minutes). The first full-length feature from Aardman Animation is immensely satisfying, a divinely relaxed and confident film that credits youngsters' interest in a cartoon more substantial than the standard bland musical. The movie employs modeled latex figures to tell the story of a group of chickens desperate to escape from a chicken farm before they are turned into pies. Nick Park, who also directed the fabulous Wallace and Gromit shorts, transfers all of the deftness and imagination of his shorter films into an artful big-screen realization. And this briskly paced epic uses Mr. Lord's continuing satirical take on British modesty and balmy superiority. ''Chicken Run'' parodies cultural touchstones from ''Stalag 17'' to ''Star Trek'' to the loose-cannon heroics of Mr. Gibson, the voice of Rocky, the matinee-idol flying rooster who is asked to teach the hens to fly. Finally, it shows that the hens can save themselves through the pluck of Ginger (Ms. Sawalha) and doesn't make a big deal of this. It's a great eggscape from banality (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''DISNEY'S 'THE KID,' '' starring Bruce Willis, Lily Tomlin and Jean Smart. Directed by Jon Turteltaub (PG, 101 minutes). In this cloying throwback to Disney's modest live-action comedies of old, Mr. Willis plays a smarmy image consultant humanized by his encounter with his 8-year-old younger self (Spencer Breslin), who arrives in Los Angeles via a toy red prop plane. By rights, the movie should be dreadful, and it is thick with therapeutic cliches, but it occasionally soars to heights of not bad, thanks to strong performances from Mr. Willis, Ms. Tomlin and Ms. Smart, and to Audrey Wells's surprisingly clever script (Scott).</p>
        <p>''GLADIATOR,'' starring Russell Crowe, Joaquin Phoenix, Connie Nielsen, Richard Harris and Oliver Reed. Directed by Ridley Scott (R, 150 minutes). This movie is the answer to a question no one bothered to ask: what would happen if someone decided to film the imminent extreme football league as if it were a Chanel commercial? Mr. Scott subjects action-packed bouts of mayhem and decapitation in the Roman Colosseum to his glossy, inhuman directing style; it is admirable but repellent. As the noble Roman general who ends up fighting for his life, Mr. Crowe gives a performance with ball-of-fire intensity suffused with a movie star's impatience. He holds the movie together, such as it is (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''GONE IN 60 SECONDS,'' starring Nicolas Cage, Giovanni Ribisi, Angelina Jolie and Robert Duvall. Directed by Dominic Sena (PG-13, 119 minutes). A remake of a movie so insubstantial that its title seems to refer to the length of time it would linger in a viewer's memory. Mr. Cage, who has gone prematurely blond, is the world's best car thief. He is dragged out of his apparently lucrative go-cart business and returns to auto theft to save the life of his brother (Mr. Ribisi). With a magnetic cast of crooks and cops, it's mindless hot-rodding entertainment for those who love car chases with vintage autos, a film so glossy and impersonal that you will sympathize more with the cars than the people (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>* ''GROOVE,'' starring Hamish Linklater, Lola Glaudini and Steve Van Wormer. Directed by Greg Harrison (R, 86 minutes). If you're nostalgic for chasing down a rave gig across the city and arriving to find a pair of 16-year-olds discussing the merits of drum and bass versus jungle, then this mostly knowing and funny comedy is just the film for you. Even if you're not, its seductive lack of pretension will win you over. ''Groove'' is a comedy of moments, tracking a crowd through the ups and downs of one night of pleasure at a rave. Mr. Harrison and his team don't try to pretend that raves are anything new or dangerous. Rather, they're an entrenched circuit with specific tribal complications, and this genial picture captures them (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''ME, MYSELF AND IRENE,'' starring Jim Carrey and Renee Zellweger. Directed by Bobby Farrelly and Peter Farrelly (R, 100 minutes). If ''There's Something About Mary'' offended you with its callous mockery of hair and pet care and its whimsical views of stalking and serial killing, then this latest festival of vulgarity from the Farrelly brothers will make you miserable. But ''Me, Myself and Irene'' shares with their earlier movies a kind of dopey, boyish sincerity and a good-natured sympathy for the underdog that may prove capable of winning over even the dourest spirits. Mr. Carrey, in one -- or is it two? -- of his most charming and repellent performances, plays a Rhode Island state trooper with a split personality and a giant crush on Irene, played with winning moxie and plausible bewilderment by Ms. Zellweger (Scott).</p>
        <p>''THE PATRIOT,'' starring Mel Gibson. Directed by Roland Emmerich (R, 158 minutes). A grueling Revolutionary War epic that, at more than two and a half hours, seems to take place in real time. The brutality and sentimentality are effective, though the film will leave you feeling used as you exit the theater. This sort-of prequel to Mr. Emmerich's ''Independence Day'' stars Mr. Gibson as a gentle farmer who leads the Colonies in wresting freedom from the Brits, using counterintuitive methods alarmingly similar to terrorism. His anguished masculinity is brandished like a musket. The film's chief asset is his relationship with the young actors playing his children; it draws on the actor's real-life feeling about his own large brood, and his work with them is stirring (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''THE PERFECT STORM,'' starring George Clooney, Mark Wahlberg and Diane Lane. Directed by Wolfgang Petersen (PG-13, 150 minutes.) Impressive but monotonously redundant special effects smother the human drama in this true story (adapted from Sebastian Junger's best-selling book) of a group of swordfishermen battling ''the storm of the century'' off Massachusetts in 1991. Mr. Clooney is the ship's glowering, enigmatic captain and Mr. Wahlberg and Ms. Lane are the appealing lovebirds who lend the movie its stingy quotient of warmth. The early scenes, which paint a romantic portrait of the fisherman's life in Gloucester, Mass., promise a great deal, but the movie becomes waterlogged once it leaves shore (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>* ''PRAISE,'' starring Peter Fenton and Sacha Horler. Directed by John Curran (unrated, 98 minutes). A stunner about a doomed relationship that's like Tennessee Williams with the ragged heedlessness of post-punk culture. Gordon (Mr. Fenton) is the epitome of slacker, a slender do-nothing whose passivity is part of his wasted charm. He attracts the sexually voracious Cynthia (Ms. Horler), whose soft body is racked with eczema. Though the movie feels aimless, Mr. Curran lets the explicit detail spell out the compulsiveness of the characters and uses jolts of humor to keep the squalor from lapsing into unrelieved unpleasantness. Ms. Horler's tender and fearless performance is just one of the elements that wiil stick with you (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''SCARY MOVIE,'' starring Jon Abrahams, Carmen Electra and Shannon Elizabeth. Directed by Keenen Ivory Wayans (R, 88 minutes). Mr. Wayans's latest genre-film spoof doesn't so much lampoon the ''Scream'' movies as offer the latest remake, this time as gross-out comedy. ''Scary Movie'' abounds in crude, often stale jokes involving male genitals, female pubic hair, flatulence and dismemberment. There are a few hilarious moments, and some that will provoke guilty laughter, but Mr. Wayans hasn't quite figured out how to parody movies -- like the wildly popular ''Scream'' series -- that already parody themselves (Scott).</p>
        <p>''SHAFT,'' starring Samuel L. Jackson, Vanessa Williams, Jeffrey Wright, Christian Bale, Toni Collette and Richard Roundtree. A sequel/remake to the 1971 semiclassic, starring the always dependable Mr. Jackson. He plays the nephew of the original Shaft (Mr. Roundtree, who appears briefly), and this time, Shaft is a cop. He leaves the force to  track down a racist WASP murderer (Mr. Bale), who joins forces with a drug dealer (the flamboyant and skillful Mr. Wright) to eliminate the hero. This may be the least politically correct movie in some time, and though it tries to convert archetype into stereotype, it doesn't succeed. Watching the two villains squabble for center stage is like watching Luciano Pavarotti and Placido Domingo in a death match for the mike. But Mr. Jackson comes out on top of this emptily entertaining hodgepodge of retro and modern cliches (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''SUNSHINE,'' starring Ralph Fiennes, Rachel Weisz, Jennifer Ehle, Rosemary Harris and James Frian. Directed by Istvan Szabo (R, 180 minutes). In Mr. Szabo's tale of 20th-century Hungarian history, Mr. Fiennes plays three members of a wealthy Jewish Budapest family -- grandfather, father and son -- who endure the corruption of the Austro-Hungarian empire, the viciousness of fascism and the brutality of Communism. Mr. Fiennes's performances, and those of Ms. Ehle and Ms. Harris (playing the same character at different stages of life) help save the film from melodramatic excess. Even though much of the story is crudely told, ''Sunshine'' is a serious, humane and thought-provoking attempt to make sense of complicated and painful historical experiences (Scott).</p>
        <p>''TRIXIE.'' Starring Emily Watson and Nick Nolte. Directed by Alan Rudolph (R, 117 minutes). In this self-billed ''screwball film noir,'' Ms. Watson plays an undercover detective at a lakeside casino investigating the murder of a third-rate lounge singer. Mr. Nolte is the alcoholic, womanizing politician she suspects of the murder. The director is wonderful with actors, and the fine supporting cast, which includes Lesley Ann Warren, Will Patton and Nathan Lane, fills in the movie's sleazy atmosphere. But the story neither connects its narrative dots nor generates suspense, and the humor (the title character is given to silly malapropisms) falls flat (Holden).</p>
        <p>Film Series</p>
        <p>''BEHIND THE MIRROR: AMERICAN FILM IN THE 1950's.'' In the midst of post-World War II prosperity, the United States was beset by fears of Communism and the atomic bomb. In this atmosphere, which included the film industry blacklist and the rapid growth of television, Hollywood produced some of its most complex and memorable films. Now the American Museum of the Moving Image in Astoria, Queens, is revisiting the films of the 1950's with a two-month retrospective running through Sept. 3 that includes works by directors like Elia Kazan, Nicholas Ray, Billy Wilder, Orson Welles, Vincente Minnelli, Sidney Lumet, Alfred Hitchcock and Douglas Sirk, among many others. Tomorrow's program consists of films by Mr. Wilder and Alexander Mackendrick. At 2 p.m. the attraction is ''The Big Carnival'' (1951), sometimes known as ''Ace in the Hole,'' Mr. Wilder's portrayal of a media circus, with Kirk Douglas as the cynical reporter. At 4:30 p.m., the feature is Mackendrick's ''Sweet Smell of Success'' (1957), with Burt Lancaster and Tony Curtis, respectively, as a ruthless newspaper columnist and a sycophantic press agent. The 2 p.m. Sunday attraction is Herbert Biberman's ''Salt of the Earth'' (1953), a dramatization of a strike by Mexican-Americans in New Mexico. At 4 p.m., the feature is a courtroom thriller with political overtones, Mark Robson's ''Trial'' (1959), starring Glenn Ford and Dorothy McGuire. Film screenings are included in museum admission, $8.50 for adults, $5.50 for people over 65 and students with ID, $4.50 for children from 5 to 18 and free to children under 4. The museum is at 34-12 36th Street, at 35th Avenue. Information: (718) 784-0077 (Lawrence Van Gelder).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
