<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>$12 Billion For Schools In New Jersey</title>
    <meta content="14JERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D6163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>$12 Billion For Schools In New Jersey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Assembly gives final approval to $12 billion school construction program; measure will provide $6 billion from sale of bonds for projects in 30 of state's neediest districts, where state will cover all rebuilding costs; other communities will receive $2.6 million borrowed by state, on a sliding scale according to their wealth, to be matched by more billions borrowed locally; Assembly also approves $3.75 billion refinancing of state's Transportation Trust Fund (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a surprisingly swift climax to a long-running battle over how to rebuild New Jersey's crumbling and overcrowded schools, the Assembly gave final approval today to the largest construction program in state history, a $12 billion effort with something for everyone, from the poorest cities to the wealthiest suburbs.</p>
        <p>The measure, one of the most ambitious school-construction initiatives by any state, will provide $6 billion from the sale of bonds for projects in 30 of New Jersey's neediest districts, where the state will cover all rebuilding costs. Other communities will receive $2.6 billion borrowed by the state, on a sliding scale according to their wealth, to be matched by more billions borrowed locally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a surprisingly swift climax to a long-running battle over how to rebuild New Jersey's crumbling and overcrowded schools, the Assembly gave final approval today to the largest construction program in state history, a $12 billion effort with something for everyone, from the poorest cities to the wealthiest suburbs.</p>
        <p>The measure, one of the most ambitious school-construction initiatives by any state, will provide $6 billion from the sale of bonds for projects in 30 of New Jersey's neediest districts, where the state will cover all rebuilding costs. Other communities will receive $2.6 billion borrowed by the state, on a sliding scale according to their wealth, to be matched by more billions borrowed locally.</p>
        <p>The Assembly interrupted its summer recess today to vote on revisions made by Gov. Christine Todd Whitman to both the school construction bill and a $3.75 billion refinancing of the state's Transportation Trust Fund. Both items passed easily and now await only the governor's signature.</p>
        <p>The vote on school construction put an end to arduous negotiations over how, or even whether, to comply with a court order in a decades-old lawsuit, Abbott v. Burke. The New Jersey Supreme Court ruled in May 1998 that the state must pay fully for projects in the neediest districts. It set this past spring as the deadline for construction to begin. Officials said today that, realistically, the building program was not likely to get into full swing until early next year, meaning that new classrooms would begin to open, at the earliest, by the fall of 2001.</p>
        <p>The inclusion of even the wealthiest districts, which will be reimbursed for at least 40 percent of their approved construction costs, drew support for the bill from across the political and economic spectrum. But critics warned that borrowing so much to rebuild schools would increase the state's already soaring debt burden from $14 billion to nearly $23 billion in just a few years.</p>
        <p>Still, the vote in the Assembly, 66 to 8 with one abstention, was not nearly as close as had been expected.</p>
        <p>One of those voting no was Assemblyman Leonard Lance, whose father helped draft the State Constitution in 1947. Mr. Lance, a Republican of Flemington, said the Constitution required that bond offerings be approved by the voters in a general election. He added that if they were asked, ''the people might indeed vote yes.''</p>
        <p>''No constitutional purpose can be effected in an unconstitutional manner,'' Mr. Lance said. ''I am concerned that what we are doing today, while we are well-intentioned, is bad public policy.''</p>
        <p>But Democrats from Bayonne, Newark and other cities that stand to receive the most said the need to repair unsafe, obsolescent and overcrowded school buildings outweighed any constitutional concerns.</p>
        <p>''This is the most important bill I've ever voted on,'' Assemblyman Raul Garcia of Union City said. ''Our children can wait no longer.''</p>
        <p>Lawmakers and advocates for inner-city schoolchildren praised the Assembly's vote today but warned that overseeing billions of dollars in contracts would sorely test the Whitman administration, noting that it had stumbled badly in overseeing a much smaller automobile emissions-testing program.</p>
        <p>A small state agency, the Economic Development Authority, will be  responsible for managing hundreds of construction projects on behalf of local districts.</p>
        <p>''This was the easy part,'' said David G. Sciarra, executive director of the Education Law Center, a Newark advocacy group for poor schoolchildren that has challenged all of the state's school-financing plans since 1973. ''Now the hard work begins. The state is about to undertake a program that it has no capacity to implement and no track record for. And we have a lot of concerns about whether the state agencies involved -- the Department of Education, Treasury, and the E.D.A. -- can come together and develop an infrastructure and expertise that will lead to construction projects in the urban communities that actually meet the needs of the children there.''</p>
        <p>The school construction effort, which could cost $15 billion in bond repayments over 30 years, may well exceed that in any other state, officials said.</p>
        <p>Illinois and Virginia, by comparison, are spending about $1 billion each for school buildings, according to the National Conference of State Legislatures.</p>
        <p>In 1998, California voters approved a $9.2 billion bond issue for public schools and community colleges.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey Assembly speaker, Jack Collins, a likely candidate for governor next year, had done more than any other lawmaker to delay a compromise on the school plan, which was introduced in October 1998 by Governor Whitman and had the early support of the Senate president, Donald T. DiFrancesco, Mr. Collins's chief rival for the Republican gubernatorial nomination.</p>
        <p>Mr. Collins had said, for example, that by ordering the Legislature to fully pay for construction in the districts covered by the Abbott v. Burke litigation, the court had infringed upon the separation of powers. ''Till about an hour ago, I didn't think I was going to be able to vote for this,'' Mr. Collins said today in a lengthy speech at the close of debate. ''Why? Because I think the Supreme Court has way overstretched.''</p>
        <p>One of the changes Mrs. Whitman made to the school construction bill in a conditional veto on June 29 was to strip lawmakers of the right to veto individual school projects. But Mr. Collins, who had argued for that power, instead introduced a separate resolution today that would create a special Assembly oversight committee to ensure against waste and fraud in school projects.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
