<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Retirement to Sydney Games: Joyner-Kersee Attempts a Giant Leap</title>
    <meta content="14TRAC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Joyner-Kersee, Jackie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Willye</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Marion</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E1DF173BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Retirement to Sydney Games: Joyner-Kersee Attempts a Giant Leap</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jackie Joyner-Kersee will come out of retirement at age 38 to jump again at Olympic trials July 14 in Sacramento; she is seeking to make her fifth Olympic team, becoming first American woman to do so since Willye White in 1972; Joyner-Kersee's presence could also throw up impediment to Marion Jones's attempt to win five gold medals at 2000 Summer Games in Sydney, Australia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The lasting image is of Jackie Joyner-Kersee standing on the runway at the 1996 Atlanta Olympics, mired in sixth place in the long jump, one attempt remaining, her right upper leg heavily bandaged from a hamstring injury.  At one point, she had even whacked the leg with the small mallet used to set her mark on the runway, as if hammering the dent out of a fender, trying to will the strained muscle into explosive compliance.</p>
        <p>''I know there is more there,'' she told herself on the infield of the filled Olympic Stadium. ''Forget about the leg. This is it, Jackie. You either attack the board or don't jump at all.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The lasting image is of Jackie Joyner-Kersee standing on the runway at the 1996 Atlanta Olympics, mired in sixth place in the long jump, one attempt remaining, her right upper leg heavily bandaged from a hamstring injury.  At one point, she had even whacked the leg with the small mallet used to set her mark on the runway, as if hammering the dent out of a fender, trying to will the strained muscle into explosive compliance.</p>
        <p>''I know there is more there,'' she told herself on the infield of the filled Olympic Stadium. ''Forget about the leg. This is it, Jackie. You either attack the board or don't jump at all.''</p>
        <p>Attack she did, sailing from sixth place to third on what was to be her farewell jump in the Summer Games, her valedictory performance as the greatest athlete of her generation. Later, Joyner-Kersee said the bronze medal was special, nearly as rewarding as the two gold medals she had won in the heptathlon and the gold she had won in 1988 in the long jump.</p>
        <p>''I really had to work for this one,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the summer of 1998, Joyner-Kersee retired, giving professional basketball a short try, becoming a sports marketing agent and running a foundation dedicated to providing sports opportunities for youngsters in her hometown of East St. Louis, Ill.</p>
        <p>But she could not stay away from track and field. Joyner-Kersee will come out of retirement at age 38 to jump again at the Olympic trials Friday night. She is seeking to make her fifth Olympic team, becoming the first American woman to do so since Willye White in 1972. Joyner-Kersee's presence could also throw up an impediment to Marion Jones's attempt to win five gold medals at the 2000 Summer Games in Sydney, Australia.</p>
        <p>''There's not a Jackie-Marion duel,'' said Bob Kersee, who is Joyner-Kersee's coach and husband. ''Competing against Marion, frankly even going after the gold medal, we've been there, done that.</p>
        <p>''What we haven't done is been on five Olympic teams. That's the challenge. That's what we're excited about. The first thing is to make the team, then you start worrying about trying to win a medal.''</p>
        <p>It is difficult to know what to make of this comeback. The qualifying round is Friday night; the final is Sunday. Joyner-Kersee still holds the American record at 24 feet 7 inches. In fact, she has delivered the top seven jumps by an American woman. Yet, she has not jumped in two years, and her last attempt was a mediocre 20-11 3/4.</p>
        <p>She has been training seriously since late March, Kersee said, but has not taken any full jumps, working instead on the speed to her approach and her technique.</p>
        <p>One of two things will most likely happen. Either retirement has healed her injuries and fresh legs will carry her sufficiently to gain one of three spots on the Olympic team, or she will jump poorly and pay for a moment of hubris. In either case, nothing has happened this season to discourage Joyner-Kersee from believing she can make the American team and win another Olympic medal.</p>
        <p>Fiona May of Italy, the 1996 Olympic silver medalist, has the world's top jump this year at 23-3 1/4. Jones is fifth on the world list with a seasonal best of 22-10 1/2, assured now that her unmatched sprinter's speed can overcome the many inadequacies in her form. Her personal best is 23-11 3/4, and on any given attempt Jones is capable of jumping breathtakingly far or frustratingly short.</p>
        <p>''From what I see in the long jump, between 22 and 23 feet is capable of making the team,'' Kersee said. ''I feel a Jackie who is healthy and on the mark still has that ability. I think we couldn't sit home wondering whether we had a chance to make five Olympic teams. As usual, we've got to go out and accept the challenge. From what I see in terms of trajectory, I still think Jackie is a 23-foot jumper. I don't know that for sure. This is a new experience for me as well. But Jackie has always set all the standards.''</p>
        <p>She has jumped once against Jones at the national championships, three years ago in Indianapolis, where Jones prevailed with a leap of 22-9. Jones is the type of athlete who seems to thrive in the cauldron of competition. Friday night, in addition to the long-jump qualifying, she must run her first round of the 100 meters. While Joyner-Kersee's presence could unnerve Jones, it could just as easily propel her. The two are friends, and Jones has consulted Joyner-Kersee for suggestions about smoothing the kinks in her own awkward technique.</p>
        <p>''It will be wonderful if Jackie's going to be in the mix,'' Jones said recently. ''Jackie's going to be ready. She's not going to come out here and jump 18 feet. I think one of the highlights of my career was competing against her in '97. When the competition starts, it'll be a free-for-all. I'm O.K. with it.''</p>
        <p>And so, Joyner-Kersee, whose grandmother named her after Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis in hopes that she would grow up ''to be the first lady of something,'' returns to the event that helped make her the first lady of track and field. She first learned to long jump on her front porch back in East St. Louis. She and her two sisters would leap into a pit fashioned from sand carried from a nearby park in discarded bags of potato chips.</p>
        <p>''It would be great to see if I could do it,'' Joyner-Kersee said of making the Olympic team for a fifth time. ''I've always admired Willye White, knowing that she was able to do it. It would be an honor and would put me in a pretty exclusive class of people.''</p>
        <p>She said she did not consider herself to be a rival of Jones's.</p>
        <p>''I consider her a friend,'' Joyner-Kersee said. ''I'll be out there critiquing her, seeing if there's anyway I can help her out, but she's the best we have.''</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
