<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Many, a Return to Homelessness</title>
    <meta content="14TENA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214807"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demolition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Irreplaceable Artifacts (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Jayson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EFDE173BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Many, a Return to Homelessness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAYSON BLAIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blair, Jayson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many tenants of three buildings evacuated after partial collapse of neighboring building in East Village tell tales of having been out on the streets before, living in shelters and off the kindness of others; will be permitted to return to their apartments only after demolition of the damaged building; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many tenants told tales of having been out on the streets before. They told stories of having lived in shelters and off the kindness of others. Some had lived on the very streets of the East Village neighborhood where they now have apartments.</p>
        <p>For many residents of 16 Second Avenue, the collapse yesterday of an adjacent building, which forced them from their homes, brought back unwelcome memories. Instead of drugs, unemployment or other similar unfortunate circumstances, the tenants of 16 Second Avenue -- and two other apartment buildings, 31 East First Street and 35 East First Street -- were put on the streets this time by a sudden calamity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Many tenants told tales of having been out on the streets before. They told stories of having lived in shelters and off the kindness of others. Some had lived on the very streets of the East Village neighborhood where they now have apartments.</p>
        <p>For many residents of 16 Second Avenue, the collapse yesterday of an adjacent building, which forced them from their homes, brought back unwelcome memories. Instead of drugs, unemployment or other similar unfortunate circumstances, the tenants of 16 Second Avenue -- and two other apartment buildings, 31 East First Street and 35 East First Street -- were put on the streets this time by a sudden calamity.</p>
        <p>Standing on the steps of LaSalle Academy, at Second Avenue and  Second Street, where the American Red Cross set up an aid center, Jen Villa, 20, said the loss of her home had snuffed out a recent ray of hope she had found.</p>
        <p>''We went through so much to get our apartment, and now we are back on the streets,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Red Cross officials said there were 51 apartments in the three buildings that were evacuated. Fire officials estimated that 100 people were displaced. By 11 p.m., 47 adults and 23 children had signed up for assistance from the Red Cross. Most decided to stay with relatives or friends.</p>
        <p>Chief Donald Burns, the Fire Department's operations commander, said the residents would not be allowed back into their buildings until a few hours after the demolition of the four-story building at 14 Second Avenue. That could happen as early as this morning, he said. That did not calm the concerns of those who had left pets and medicine in their apartments.</p>
        <p>For many, the first sign of their displacement came on the way home from work. The F trains that many of them ride were rerouted away from the Second Avenue station. The next sign came as they walked down Second Avenue and saw the orange police cones that lined the blocks from Houston to Fifth Street. The cones were followed by red and white Red Cross trucks, white police cars, fire trucks and a phalanx of emergency workers.</p>
        <p>''I was getting nervous,'' Inocencia Tejada, 32, a resident of 16 Second Avenue, said. ''I don't know what I am going to do. I don't know where I am going to stay.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
