<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>General Mills Is in Talks to Buy Pillsbury Division of Diageo</title>
    <meta content="Y14FOO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Mills Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pillsbury Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Diageo Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1D9163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>General Mills Is in Talks to Buy Pillsbury Division of Diageo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Mills Inc is in talks to acquire Pillsbury division of Diageo PLC; neither side provides details of proposed price; new company would be world's fourth-largest packaged goods company; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a move that could mean the corporate union of Betty Crocker and the Pillsbury Doughboy, General Mills Inc. said yesterday that it was in talks to acquire the Pillsbury division of Diageo P.L.C.</p>
        <p>While confirming the talks, neither side would give details on a proposed price for Pillsbury. Analysts said it could end up at $9 billion to $11 billion, with Diageo retaining a minority stake. They said the deal could be completed by early next week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a move that could mean the corporate union of Betty Crocker and the Pillsbury Doughboy, General Mills Inc. said yesterday that it was in talks to acquire the Pillsbury division of Diageo P.L.C.</p>
        <p>While confirming the talks, neither side would give details on a proposed price for Pillsbury. Analysts said it could end up at $9 billion to $11 billion, with Diageo retaining a minority stake. They said the deal could be completed by early next week.</p>
        <p>General Mills is attracted to Pillsbury's refrigerated-dough business, which includes ready-to-bake cookies and biscuits. Together with the General Mills yogurt business, which consists of Yoplait and Colombo yogurt, it would create a behemoth with $1.7 billion in sales in that crucial corner of the supermarket.</p>
        <p>''They would have a refrigerated division that is second only to Kraft, and maybe the leader in terms of growth potential,'' said John M. McMillin, a food stocks analyst for Prudential Securities.</p>
        <p>Still, another analyst said that while there would be immediate cost savings by combining the two companies, both of which are based in Minneapolis, it was not clear that the merger would increase General Mills' sales in the long run. ''The biggest hurdle for General Mills would be convincing investors that it could accelerate top-line growth,'' said Andrew Lazar of Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>The announcement portends the latest in a series of pairings between food companies, all intended to increase the size and alter the balance of power between the companies and grocery retailers. In recent years, consolidation among supermarket chains has left the industry with a handful of large multinational players, leaving food makers scrambling for position. The prevailing thinking, that larger food companies make better global suppliers, has led to mergers like the $20.3 billion proposed acquisition by Unilever of Bestfoods, which was announced last month, and the $14.9 billion proposed purchase of Nabisco by Philip Morris.</p>
        <p>It also signals further revision of the Diageo corporate structure. Last month, the company said it would spin off 20 percent of its Burger King holdings, with the goal of eventually spinning off the whole enterprise. Paul S. Walsh, Diageo's chief operating officer who formerly led Pillsbury, has said he wants to focus the company on its Guinness beer brand and liquor business.</p>
        <p>Diageo was formed in 1997 when Grand Metropolitan P.L.C. merged with Guinness; the company changed its name the same year. Diageo is the largest global player in liquor, with about 9 percent of the market; without Burger King and Pillsbury, its holdings would consist solely of alcoholic beverages.</p>
        <p>A sale of Pillsbury ''would open up other options,'' said a Diageo spokeswoman, Kathryn B. Partridge, adding that the company was likely to purchase brands ''within the beverage-alcohol category.'' With the sale of Seagram to Vivendi last month, several brands are up for sale, including Chivas Regal and Martell cognac.</p>
        <p>General Mills makes and markets breakfast cereals, including Lucky Charms, Cheerios and Cocoa Puffs. Besides Yoplait and Colombo yogurt, it recently scored a major hit with Go-Gurt, a yogurt aimed at children that is packaged in a slender portable tube that requires no spoon. So successful is Go-Gurt, in fact, that an adult version is being planned as well.</p>
        <p>The company's Betty Crocker line includes cake mixes as well as Hamburger Helper and Suddenly Salad. General Mills also makes Gold Medal Flour and Lloyd's packaged barbecue, as well as snacks like Gushers and Fruit by the Foot.</p>
        <p>Pillsbury's lineup, which includes the Old El Paso line of Mexican food and Green Giant frozen vegetables, overlaps in several areas, particularly flour and cake mixes.</p>
        <p>It was unclear yesterday whether combining with General Mills would raise antitrust issues. A spokesman for the Federal Trade Commission would not comment on the proposed deal. The talks were reported in yesterday's Wall Street Journal.</p>
        <p>In recent years, General Mills has won praise from Wall Street as the company steadily gained market share for its cereals at the expense of Kellogg. Other General Mills products also succeeded, in large part because of strong marketing and close identification with consumer desires.</p>
        <p>''They could bring to bear their innovation and consumer research to bring out very focused products that consumers like,'' said Erika Gritman Long, an analyst for J. P. Morgan. ''They could improve the operating margins of the existing businesses, just by running them well.''</p>
        <p>Pillsbury, on the other hand, has been perceived as an underachiever by the profit-hungry investment community. ''Pillsbury is not as efficient,'' said Jaine Mehring, an analyst for Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>A merger would probably mean job cuts in Minneapolis, where both companies are based. ''As with any merger there will be some consolidation of jobs and things like that, and I assume some executive-level jobs will be lost,'' said Thomas Stinson, the Minnesota state economist. But he predicted that the packaged-food sector would grow as a result. ''In general, it will be beneficial for this state,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some analysts also said they expected General Mills to sell some Pillsbury businesses, including Green Giant frozen vegetables and Progresso soups, that do not fit neatly into the existing lineup.</p>
        <p>The deal, if it goes through, may set up one more. The combination of General Mills and Pillsbury may  make General Mills a more enticing target for another company, Ms. Long said. ''It would reduce their exposure in cereal from 45 percent to about 25 percent,'' she said, noting that cereal is a difficult market lately. ''And Haagen Dazs would make General Mills even more attractive to Nestle than it already is.''</p>
        <p>Other companies that are considered likely merger candidates include H. J. Heinz, the Campbell Soup Company and the Kellogg Company.</p>
        <p>Shares of General Mills rose 25 cents, to $37, while Diageo fell 12.5 pence, to 599 pence, in London. Diageo's American depository receipts fell 56.25 cents, to $36.3125.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
