<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CRITICAL CONDITION: A special report.; Expansive Ambitions Dig Deep Hole for Health Plan</title>
    <meta content="14HIP.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drew, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Petersen, Melody</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watson, Anthony L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1D7163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CRITICAL CONDITION: A special report.; Expansive Ambitions Dig Deep Hole for Health Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER DREW and MELODY PETERSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Petersen, Melody; Drew, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York has fallen into deep financial hole under leadership of Anthony L Watson, and regulators are investigating lavish spending and clubby atmosphere that seems at odds with HIP's special role in caring for New York City government workers and the poor; State Insurance Department and attorney general's office are poring over financial records, and focusing on Watson's spending on fancy cars and apartments even as HIP's finances dwindled far below amount required by law; critics say HIP's troubles also reflect decisions that were too risky, including expansion beyond insurer's local base; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Anthony L. Watson took command of the Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York nearly a decade ago, he vowed to turn the city's oldest and least expensive health maintenance organization into a first-class operation. He had bold plans to keep caring for the nonprofit's traditional New York clientele -- city workers and the poor -- while attracting millions of wealthier corporate employees up and down the East Coast.</p>
        <p>But since then, many of his ambitions have failed, burying HIP in a deep financial hole. Expanding into other states has led to big losses. And regulators in New York are investigating whether Mr. Watson spent too freely in other ways, squandering millions on lavish salaries, executive perquisites and contracts for board members and friends.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Anthony L. Watson took command of the Health Insurance Plan of Greater New York nearly a decade ago, he vowed to turn the city's oldest and least expensive health maintenance organization into a first-class operation. He had bold plans to keep caring for the nonprofit's traditional New York clientele -- city workers and the poor -- while attracting millions of wealthier corporate employees up and down the East Coast.</p>
        <p>But since then, many of his ambitions have failed, burying HIP in a deep financial hole. Expanding into other states has led to big losses. And regulators in New York are investigating whether Mr. Watson spent too freely in other ways, squandering millions on lavish salaries, executive perquisites and contracts for board members and friends.</p>
        <p>Both the State Insurance Department and the attorney general's office are examining HIP's finances, looking into what former executives describe as a clubby atmosphere that often seemed at odds with HIP's special role in the city's health care system. Mayor Fiorello H. La Guardia created the plan in the 1940's to provide affordable coverage for city workers, and it insures many Medicare and Medicaid patients.</p>
        <p>Over the last several months, insurance regulators have dispatched auditors to pore over HIP's books. They have also subpoenaed documents and taken depositions from Mr. Watson and two other executives. Neil D. Levin, the superintendent of insurance, said the inquiry was wide ranging.</p>
        <p>Most of the questions focus on Mr. Watson, 59, a former Olympic long jumper, whose taste for fancy cars and corporate apartments has infuriated the regulators as some of HIP's financial reserves have dwindled far below the amount required by law.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Watson says he did nothing improper, the investigators are exploring whether some of the expenditures were inappropriate for a nonprofit corporation like HIP, which is exempt from most taxes so that it can plow the money back into health care.</p>
        <p>But critics say HIP's troubles also reflect other problems. They say Mr. Watson's expansions beyond HIP's local base were too risky in today's cutthroat health industry. And recent changes to broaden the mix of doctors, stemming in part from a feud between Mr. Watson and a New York medical group, have troubled health regulators trying to minimize disruptions in care.</p>
        <p>Regulators and analysts do not expect HIP to collapse. But they say it is also clear that the city's taxpayers will have to underwrite part of the cost of reviving the plan.</p>
        <p>HIP's biggest losses have come elsewhere. It lost $40 million when its operation in New Jersey collapsed last year. Its operations in Florida have cost $80 million.</p>
        <p>But given its appeal to workers in the city's clerical, sanitation and teachers' unions, the easiest place for HIP to raise money is in New York, where it still counts 200,000 city workers and their relatives among its 796,000 customers.</p>
        <p>On July 1, HIP raised its premiums by 9.9 percent, which will add about $100 million to the city's health care costs. HIP officials say they plan increases of 8 percent to 12 percent in each of the next three years. Such increases are not inconsistent with what other H.M.O.'s have been seeking, and HIP remains a popular option. Other major plans typically charge premiums that are 10 percent to 20 percent higher.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson, a tall, gruff man known for his intimidating style, conceded in an interview that he had made mistakes.</p>
        <p>Besides his $1 million annual pay package, he agreed that the most visible symbols of extravagance were two Jaguars that HIP leased for him -- one each in New York and  Florida. HIP and its Florida subsidiary also rented several apartments for executives, including one for Mr. Watson near Miami that cost $7,000 a month.</p>
        <p>HIP got rid of the cars and apartments last year after The Daily News wrote about some of HIP's expenses. Mr. Watson said that choosing such luxurious perks ''wasn't the greatest decision I ever made.'' He added, ''But it is nothing illegal.''</p>
        <p>Still, some critics caution that at HIP, there are echoes of the kind of financial dangers that almost ruined Empire Blue Cross and Blue Shield, another health provider, in the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>HIP fell below the required level for financial reserves four years ago. It is now $71 million below the $153 million required as a cushion against unexpected claims.</p>
        <p>''They are really short,'' said Martin D. Weiss, chairman of Weiss Ratings, which analyzes the strength of H.M.O.'s. ''They are not broke, but they are heading that way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson and other HIP executives dispute that, saying they believe the worst days are past. They note that while HIP's customer base fell to 727,000 members in 1998 from 906,000 members in 1990, the company began to rebound in 1999, reflecting some success in attracting new corporate clients. And last year, the New York operation made its largest profit ever -- $25 million, though most of it was sent to cover losses in Florida.</p>
        <p>''We are a much better company than we were,'' Mr. Watson said.</p>
        <p>Complaint files at the State Department of Health suggest that HIP's care has improved in some areas, but that its quality of care has remained about the same over all as that at other large H.M.O.'s. But while HIP officials say they are trying to make changes as smoothly as possible, some patients say they have suffered complications in care.</p>
        <p>Sandra Dent of Manhattan said her father, Noel Dent, 63, had faced delays in cancer treatment while having to change doctors in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''I'm afraid, with all this time, it has just spread through him,'' Ms. Dent said.</p>
        <p>An Eye on the Competition  Deciding to Take On The 'Big Boys'</p>
        <p>When Mr. Watson became HIP's chief executive in 1990, the giant profit-making  H.M.O.'s like Oxford Health Plans and U.S. Healthcare were growing rapidly, and HIP's niche in New York no longer looked as secure or satisfying.</p>
        <p>But critics say that Mr. Watson's response -- competing with the ''big boys'' -- started HIP on the free-spending ways that have endangered it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson said he had little choice but to shake things up. At the time, HIP had a ''terrible reputation,'' he recalled, sitting in his Manhattan office in khakis and a shirt emblazoned with the HIP logo. ''It was accused of being a place with foreign doctors, dirty clinics, and just not a place you wanted to get medical care.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson, who had worked in public health for 20 years, spent millions of dollars to renovate HIP's medical centers. Members had to go to these clinics for treatment, an approach that set HIP apart from other H.M.O.'s with a greater choice of doctors. Mr. Watson also decided to expand smaller operations in New Jersey and Florida. HIP had moved into Florida in the late 1980's to serve New York members who retired there, and Mr. Watson wanted to compete for more business there.</p>
        <p>To project a classier image, he moved HIP's headquarters from a rattletrap building with wire-caged windows to elegant offices on West 34th Street, with a marble lobby and leather couches. He also raised salaries to levels that were competitive with large, profitable companies.</p>
        <p>Before long, office meetings were accompanied by catered meals, former executives say. Mr. Watson held management retreats at the Montauk Yacht Club on Long Island and rewarded sales representatives with trips to resorts.</p>
        <p>But his ambitions foundered in the mid-1990's. First, the Giuliani administration, facing budget problems, forced HIP to accept a three-year freeze in premiums. So in 1996, HIP tapped its financial reserves to upgrade an antiquated computer system that was letting claims go unpaid. With membership falling, it also began making plans to create its own broad network of doctors to appeal to more customers.</p>
        <p>Then it became clear how much of a gamble HIP had taken in the other states.</p>
        <p>The biggest problem, business analysts said, was that managed care companies were undercutting one another on premiums. And HIP was ill-equipped for these battles.</p>
        <p>Records show that it failed to keep a tight control on expenses. And as a nonprofit corporation, HIP could not raise capital as easily as its profit-making competitors to absorb the losses.</p>
        <p>Regulators closed HIP's operations in New Jersey last year after a troubled partner, PHP Healthcare Corporation of Reston, Va., raked off most of HIP's cash.</p>
        <p>And now HIP's Florida affiliate is eating up even more money. Last year, HIP sent $18 million -- all raised from premiums paid by New Yorkers -- to Florida. That brought the total of HIP's subsidies there to $80 million,  more than enough to cover the current hole in its reserve in New York.</p>
        <p>Few H.M.O.'s have been able to make money in Florida. And Mr. Watson said, ''I want to be judged with the condition this industry is in.''</p>
        <p>But records show that HIP has spent tens of millions of dollars in Florida on marketing, including expensive sky box rentals at professional sports events. Yet it still has fewer than half the members of each of the three largest H.M.O.'s there.</p>
        <p>In addition, federal prosecutors have been investigating whether a Florida union leader did anything improper to help outside sales brokers hired by HIP. The brokers helped HIP win a contract with the Broward County School District, but Mr. Watson said he did not believe anything improper occurred.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alexander Ellman, who sat on HIP's board for many years, said, ''I've always been against their presence in Florida.'' Dr. Ellman said he had repeatedly urged Mr. Watson and other board members to abandon Florida.</p>
        <p>The Executive Life  A Driving Ambition, And Jaguars as Perks</p>
        <p>As Mr. Watson's ambitions for HIP rose, so did his insistence on enjoying the rewards of running a larger company, former executives say.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson's salary and bonuses soared to $995,000 last year from $395,000 in 1993. Contractually, he is entitled to a company car. He said he chose a BMW, and then a Cadillac, before the Jaguars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson said that the questions about his salary and perks were ''not fair,'' given that executives at other health companies have similar benefits. ''What are you comparing me against?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>But critics say Mr. Watson went beyond the norm for nonprofit organizations. ''When you start to think you're General Motors, that's when errors start to happen,'' said Sonny Hall, the international president of the Transport Workers Union of America and a HIP board member.</p>
        <p>The insurance regulators are looking at whether HIP violated any laws that forbid nonprofit corporations to enrich their officers or to spend in ways that do not further their public mission.</p>
        <p>One set of questions involves the corporate apartments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson acknowledged that he personally selected the $7,000-a-month apartment in Florida. It was on the 17th floor of a condominium in a waterfront development just north of Miami.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson said he used it once a month when he went to Florida on business. HIP's Florida affiliate leased the apartment from early 1994 until last summer -- costing it more than $450,000.</p>
        <p>Ronald Maiorana, the plan's spokesman, said HIP also had rented two apartments in Manhattan in the late 1990's to save on hotel bills for visiting executives. He said the most expensive one, on East 65th Street, cost $4,500 a month.</p>
        <p>State officials are also scrutinizing some of HIP's contracts with suppliers. In particular, they are looking at millions of dollars in building leases and office-cleaning contracts to determine whether HIP paid too much to two men who are friendly with Mr. Watson.</p>
        <p>HIP officials said the inquiry focused on Mr. Watson's relationship with the manager of a building at 320 East 23rd Street, where Mr. Watson lived from 1986 until 1998 and where HIP has a clinic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watson got the apartment shortly after he joined HIP as an executive vice president. The building's owners, led by Martin H. Goodstein, a developer, treated Mr. Watson well, twice letting him combine his apartment with adjacent ones. Mr. Watson said he personally paid the rent on all three apartments.</p>
        <p>But officials from the New York Medical Group, which ran the clinic until recently, asked the regulators to examine whether Mr. Goodstein and an associate, Samuel B. Lewis, benefited from their dealings with HIP.</p>
        <p>One concern is that shortly before Mr. Watson was promoted to HIP's top job in late 1990, HIP agreed to a new lease on the clinic that real estate experts describe as unusually favorable to the owners.</p>
        <p>And in 1991, Mr. Lewis and Mr. Goodstein formed the S.B.L. Cleaning Corporation, which quickly started receiving business from HIP. Eventually, S.B.L. was cleaning 27 of HIP's 53 medical centers, charging $7.5 million last year.</p>
        <p>State officials are looking into whether those charges were excessive -- and drained money from medical care. Documents show that in 1998, the doctors solicited a proposal from another cleaning contractor offering cheaper rates.</p>
        <p>But HIP officials refused to rebid the contract, and this was one issue in the fight between Mr. Watson and the medical group, which had cared for HIP members for decades. Mr. Watson fired the group last month.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Goodstein nor Mr. Lewis returned calls for comment. Mr. Watson said he did not negotiate the leases or cleaning contracts and had not shown any favoritism.</p>
        <p>''To suggest that there's anything improper, that's a perception, not a reality,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A Question About Oversight  Who Was Minding The Financial Store?</p>
        <p>To consumer advocates, one question is: Why didn't HIP's board members -- or political leaders -- better monitor Mr. Watson?</p>
        <p>As a nonprofit organization, HIP depends on civic, union and business leaders to oversee its executives. Critics say that at HIP, one answer may be that influential board members had business ties or other possible conflicts that compromised their independence.</p>
        <p>When an investment adviser, Charles L. Johnston, left HIP's New York board in 1994, shifting over to its boards in New Jersey and Florida, Mr. Watson gave him a $250,000 contract to watch the New York plan's investments.</p>
        <p>And in 1993, when the Rev. Carl E. Flemister, a Baptist minister, suggested sending volunteers to comfort hospitalized HIP members, Mr. Watson gave him a $125,000-a-year contract to start the program. Mr. Flemister is now the chairman of an umbrella board that oversees all of HIP's operations. He still runs the volunteer program and was paid $183,000 last year. As chairman of the umbrella board, he is also Mr. Watson's boss.</p>
        <p>Charles M. Elson, a professor at Stetson University College of Law in St. Petersburg, Fla., and an expert in corporate governance, said such arrangements could cause board members to consider their own interests over the company's.</p>
        <p>''You want these boards,'' Mr. Elson said, ''to be clean even of the suspicion of a lack of independence.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Flemister, Mr. Johnston and Mr. Watson all denied that the deals had clouded their actions.</p>
        <p>''It might be a fair question to anyone who doesn't know me,'' Mr. Flemister said. ''But I would not destroy my reputation of 50 years, having people gossip that Tony controls me. It just doesn't happen.''</p>
        <p>The regulators are also looking at whether HIP officials have done anything improper in encouraging doctors to make political donations.</p>
        <p>As a nonprofit organization, HIP cannot make campaign contributions. So the medical groups that operate its clinics created a political action committee in 1992. Records show that the committee has donated $160,000 to more than four dozen political groups and officials, including Gov. George E. Pataki and his predecessor, Gov. Mario Cuomo, and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and former Mayor David N. Dinkins.</p>
        <p>But here, too, there are questions about whether Mr. Watson or his aides have gone too far. Documents show that in June 1999, for instance, Mr. Watson's chief of staff, Raymond P. Vacca, faxed the committee a list of seven recommended donations totaling $8,750. Mr. Watson and Mr. Vacca said that these were only suggestions, and that they never exerted any improper pressure.</p>
        <p>The Future of HIP  Still Banking Heavily On New Members</p>
        <p>Looking ahead, HIP still faces problems that could be devastating.</p>
        <p>New York regulators could force major changes in how it operates. New Jersey is demanding $83 million to cover medical bills left unpaid there. And while Mr. Watson thinks he can stop the losses in Florida, he said he also could sell or close the operation.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Watson expressed confidence that HIP's fortunes had turned. He estimated that with the recent rate increase, the plan would earn a $40 million profit in New York this year.</p>
        <p>And under an obscure state law, certain H.M.O.'s, including HIP, can keep raising their rates without regulatory approval. This means that HIP could resuscitate its finances through a series of rate increases, unless City Hall balks and decides to shrink its role in covering city workers. The city pays the premium for workers who choose HIP, and it contributes the same amount for workers who select a more expensive plan.</p>
        <p>In the end, HIP is also banking heavily on attracting more members with its expanding network of doctors.</p>
        <p>But last month, state health regulators delayed its plan to transfer the patients cared for by the New York Medical Group to  organizations run by four hospitals. State health officials said they were worried that care for some patients, especially pregnant women and those with cancer, could be disrupted.</p>
        <p>Since then, regulators have agreed to changes only in the Bronx and in Westchester County, where Montefiore Medical Center began caring for patients on July 1. Contracts with hospitals in Manhattan are either still being completed or are awaiting state approval. And while HIP expects most of the same doctors to remain at its clinics, many are now working under temporary arrangements, and some have quit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
