<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AIDS Studies on Infants Appear to Conflict</title>
    <meta content="Y14AID$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Azt (Azidothymidine) (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">3tc (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lamivudine-3tc (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Threetc (Drug)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Unaids</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perriens, Joseph (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6D7163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AIDS Studies on Infants Appear to Conflict</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <dateline>DURBAN, South Africa, July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reseach reported at international AIDS conference suggests that a simple AZT-based drug regimen may help protect babies from HIV infection; study sponsored by National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases in Bethesda, Md, appears to be in conflict with report last week from Dr Joseph Perriens, who led study for Unaids, a joint United Nations agency; that report questioned benefits for babies of drug regimen utilizing AZT and 3TC (lamivudine) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A simple drug regimen may help protect babies from infection by the AIDS virus, research reported today at the international AIDS conference found. In tests, the regimen was given to women during labor and to their newborns in the first three days of life.</p>
        <p>The study appears to be in conflict with a report of last week that questioned the usefulness of another drug regimen, because it found that the rates of infection from breast-feeding offset the benefits of the treatment. In that study, about as many babies were infected after 18 months as were saved from infection in the first weeks of life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A simple drug regimen may help protect babies from infection by the AIDS virus, research reported today at the international AIDS conference found. In tests, the regimen was given to women during labor and to their newborns in the first three days of life.</p>
        <p>The study appears to be in conflict with a report of last week that questioned the usefulness of another drug regimen, because it found that the rates of infection from breast-feeding offset the benefits of the treatment. In that study, about as many babies were infected after 18 months as were saved from infection in the first weeks of life.</p>
        <p>The two studies used different ways of analyzing data, and leaders of the studies said they now need to resolve the apparent conflict. ''There may also be more subtle reasons'' other than methods for the differences in findings, said Dr. Joseph Perriens. He led the study for Unaids, a joint United Nations agency.</p>
        <p>The leaders said it would be September before they could meet with virologists, epidemiologists, obstetricians, pediatricians and other experts to determine what recommendations should be made.</p>
        <p>''It is therefore premature to make policy decisions based on this data,'' Dr. Perriens said.</p>
        <p>Until then, health officials in Africa are in a quandary.</p>
        <p>Resolution of the conflict is critical because health officials have looked to simple drug regimens to prevent infections from H.I.V., the AIDS virus, in Africa where such rates are the highest in the world.</p>
        <p>In many areas of southern Africa, 30 percent of pregnant women are infected; in South Africa itself, the rate exceeds 20 percent.</p>
        <p>If simple drug regimens work and could be widely used in Africa, hundreds of thousands of babies could possibly be saved from infection each year, proponents said at the meeting.</p>
        <p>But if similar numbers of babies get H.I.V. through breast-feeding, such treatment would not be worth the cost and bother.</p>
        <p>Even if further analysis shows that the drug regimens work, experts said it was imperative for researchers to find safer ways for African women to breast-feed, which many do for two years or more.</p>
        <p>The study that dimmed hopes of an overall benefit for Africa was sponsored by the United Nations and involved a short course of two drugs, AZT and 3TC (lamivudine). The drugs were given to the mother for four weeks before her expected delivery and again during labor. Then both mother and infant took the two drugs for one week after delivery.</p>
        <p>That study found that after 18 months, the rate at which infants acquired H.I.V. through breast-feeding completely offset the benefits of treating the mother and newborn.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the study said that finding was a blow to the effort to protect babies in Africa.</p>
        <p>After that paper was delivered at the AIDS conference, the session moderator, Dr. Lynne Mofenson, of the National Institutes of Health, called the findings of the study ''bad news.''</p>
        <p>The separate report confused the picture by showing a clear benefit. It was sponsored by the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases in Bethesda, Md., and conducted in Uganda.</p>
        <p>It called for giving a single dose of the drug, nevirapine, to women during labor and another dose to the newborn within three days of birth.</p>
        <p>The more hopeful report extended findings from last year that the therapy is nearly twice as effective in reducing transmission of H.I.V. from mothers to their newborn than a short course of the drug AZT.</p>
        <p>After six to eight weeks, according to this study, mothers and infants who received nevirapine had a much lower risk of H.I.V. transmission -- 42 percent less -- than those who took AZT.</p>
        <p>The new data on the same infants showed that after 12 months, the reduction was 39 percent, and preliminary results showed after 18 months the reduction was 42 percent.</p>
        <p>But mothers continued to infect their babies through breast-feeding during the follow-up period.</p>
        <p>In the nevirapine group, transmission rates were 11.8 percent at six to eight weeks, and 15.7 percent at 12 months.</p>
        <p>For comparable periods, the figures were 20 percent and 24.1 percent in the group that received AZT.</p>
        <p>Women and infants tolerated both regimens well and will be followed for five years, said the study's leaders, Dr. Brooks Jackson of Johns Hopkins University and Prof. Francis Mmiro of Mulago Hospital and Makerere University in Kampala.</p>
        <p>More than 21,000 women give birth at the hospital each year, and nearly 16 percent of them are H.I.V. infected.</p>
        <p>The sponsoring National Institutes of Health said in a statement that ''these findings further indicate that a short nevirapine regimen is an effective, simple, and extremely low cost-method for preventing transmission of H.I.V. from mother to child in developing countries.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Jackson said South Africa should approve nevirapine for prevention of mother-to-child transmission.</p>
        <p>Nevirapine is not approved for the prevention of H.I.V. transmission from mother to child. If approved, it will offer practical advantages for use in Africa because it can be stored at room temperature and a pediatric formulation was recently introduced by its manufacturer, the German drug company, Boehringer Ingelheim, which sells it as Viramune.</p>
        <p>Last week, the company said it would offer nevirapine free for five years for the prevention of mother-to-child transmission of H.I.V. in developing countries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
