<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stained Glass, With Sinners, Too</title>
    <meta content="14ANTI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stained Glass</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Getty, J Paul, Museum (Los Angeles)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durer, Albrecht (1471-1528)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holbein, Hans (The Younger) (1497?-1543)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonan, Wendy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stained Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2D81F38F937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1280" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stained Glass, With Sinners, Too</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Antiques column on Getty Museum's exhibit of drawings and stained glass in age of Durer and Holbein; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you think you know what 15th-century German stained glass looks like, you may be wrong. It's not what you see in the Chartres Cathedral.</p>
        <p>Most of us have never seen stained glass like the panels in the J. Paul Getty Museum's exhibition ''Painting on Light: Drawings and Stained Glass in the Age of Durer and Holbein,'' which opened on Tuesday and runs through Sept. 24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you think you know what 15th-century German stained glass looks like, you may be wrong. It's not what you see in the Chartres Cathedral.</p>
        <p>Most of us have never seen stained glass like the panels in the J. Paul Getty Museum's exhibition ''Painting on Light: Drawings and Stained Glass in the Age of Durer and Holbein,'' which opened on Tuesday and runs through Sept. 24.</p>
        <p>The show is full of surprises. Along with the ravishing angels and pious saints, there are soldiers in the midst of a massacre, men and women playing roulette, Heracles slaying the Nemean lion and nude women in a bathhouse.</p>
        <p>The show, organized by the Getty, in Los Angeles, and the St. Louis Art Museum, where it opens on Nov. 4, has 80 preparatory drawings that artists made for these commissions. They are shown alongside 60 stained-glass panels that talented glass painters translated into windows. They were ordered for guild headquarters, town halls and private houses, as well as churches and monasteries.</p>
        <p>Stained glass is, of course, a collaborative art. Artists prepare the drawings; then they or their assistants work out the designs in proportion to the size of the glass panels. These second drawings become the cartoons for the glaziers. (Cartone is an Italian word meaning big paper.)</p>
        <p>The glazier blows the glass by hand in various colors. The glass is then painted on both sides. The material is called stained glass because the outer surface is painted with an enamel called silver stain. When fired, the stain turns yellow. If the underlying glass is blue, the stain turns it green. Details are drawn on the inner surface of the glass with vitreous paint, which ranges in color from gray-brown to black. Details can also be  scratched into the paint. The glass pieces are then joined together with lead strips called cames. The process requires close collaboration, to say the least.</p>
        <p>The Getty show is the result of an equally intense collaboration that lasted 15 years. The story behind it is a bit like the Off Broadway play ''A Coupla White Chicks Sitting Around Talking.''</p>
        <p>In 1985 two American art historians, both specialists in Renaissance drawings, met in Vienna  at a seminar on Durer, the great German painter and engraver. Lee Hendrix, the drawings curator at the Getty, was looking for art for her deparment. ''Begun in 1981, our drawings collection is young,'' she said. ''Our greatest strength in our German drawings is stained-glass drawings from 1480 to 1530.'' Barbara Butts had just completed her doctorate at Harvard and was going to the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston as a drawings curator. The two were young and shared a passion for German Renaissance drawings. They became great friends.</p>
        <p>Ms. Butts confided that she hoped to organize a show on Durer, comparing his preparatory drawings with the actual glass panels the drawings inspired. Ms. Hendrix loved the idea.</p>
        <p>''We realized the drawings had never been seen next to the glass panels they were made for,'' she said. ''This material is so overlooked.'' She said the last survey was a two-volume book, published in German in 1913, on the King of Prussia's collection. ''That glass was stored in Berlin,'' she added, ''and 80 percent of it was destroyed in World War II.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Butts said, ''We knew the drawings, but there was a lot of confusion about what glass had survived and where it was.'' The two curators spent the next 13 years matching the drawings to their stained-glass counterparts.</p>
        <p>The art of drawing flourished in Germany and Switzerland from the late 1400's to the 1600's. Artists like Durer (1471-1528) went to Italy to study Renaissance painting and returned home with new ideas. Drawing was no longer simply a process to record nature. It developed into a true art.</p>
        <p>This art is the subject of a companion show of 16th- and 17th-century German and Swiss drawings the Getty has organized from its own collection (through Aug. 20). It includes detailed figure drawings, compositional studies, portraits and designs for woodcuts, stained glass and decorative objects by Durer, Lucas Cranach the Elder (1472-1553) and Hans Holbein the Younger (1497-1543).</p>
        <p>''Painting on Light'' explores technique and artistry, but it also places stained glass in political and religious contexts.</p>
        <p>''Stained glass is an art form that vividly reflects its time,'' Ms. Hendrix said. ''By the Reformation, the commissioning of monumental stained-glass church windows was dying out in Germany. Secular glass came in.'' Soon stained glass became ubiquitous in Southern Germany and Switzerland.</p>
        <p>From 1400 to 1550 it was used to decorate town halls, private houses, inns, universities, even hospitals. Themes included the Old and New Testaments, classical mythology, heraldry, planetary movements and chivalry.</p>
        <p>''It reflects things people liked to do at that time: card-playing, wrestling, wine-drinking, fishing and swimming, even cooking,'' Ms. Hendrix said. ''History is also profoundly reflected in the glass.''</p>
        <p>The Hapsburg emperor Maximilian I, called ''the last knight'' because he was constantly at war, and his courtiers became great patrons of stained glass. They commissioned panels glorifying knighthood, with scenes of jousting and courtly love.</p>
        <p>In Switzerland, by contrast, stained glass was more political, promoting the drive for independence. In 1513, the Swiss Federation began an anti-Hapsburg uprising in the Alps that lasted more than a century. The Swiss cantons eventually won; the secession of the Swiss Confederation was legalized with the Treaty of Westphalia in 1648.</p>
        <p>The Swiss ordered stained glass that glorified their legendary image, the Wild Man of the Alps, the freedom fighter whose body is covered with hair and who carries a tree trunk as his weapon. He is ''a mythical figure from the medieval imagination, depicted in art and literature far into the 16th century,'' Barbara Giesicke and Mylene Ruoss write in a catalog essay: ''The Wild Man's popularity as shield-bearer was essentially based on the symbolism of his strength and drive for freedom.''</p>
        <p>One Holbein drawing shows the Wild Man leaping through a classical portal from the Alps right into the viewer's space. ''He is as tall as a tree, a symbol of strength, virility and invincible power,'' Ms. Hendrix said. ''Behind him are Alps.''</p>
        <p>In organizing the show, she and Ms. Butts went to Europe several times. ''We got Eurorail passes,'' Ms. Butts recalled. ''We crossed and recrossed Germany and Switzerland.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hendrix added: ''In 1998, we did 14 cities in 28 days. It was a journey of discovery.''</p>
        <p>They sought out a thermal bath in a spa in Switzerland. The doctors and nurses did not recall a stained-glass window there. The curators obtained a key to search the chapel but couldn't find the panel. ''On the way out, we noticed that a curtain had been pulled back by the front door,'' Ms. Hendrix said. ''There was our panel.''</p>
        <p>Borrowing the glass for the show was the next nightmare. ''We visited nearly all the lenders because we had to explain why we needed their stained-glass pieces,'' Ms. Hendrix said. ''This show could never happen again because it took four years just to negotiate the loans.''</p>
        <p>Would they try to do it again? ''It was the collaboration of a lifetime,'' Ms. Butts said.</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
