<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revolutionary Production</title>
    <meta content="14FLIC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AT THE MOVIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohmer, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kehr, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weitz, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weitz, Chris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chuck and Buck (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Lady and the Duke, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Croupier (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4D81F38F937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revolutionary Production</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dave Kehr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kehr, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>At the Movies column; Eric Rohmer is recreating French Revolution in converted warehouse in Paris, for his movie The Lady and the Duke; brothers Paul and Chris Weitz take break from directing to star in independent film Chuck and Buck; photo; British thriller Croupier, made by Mike Hodges for Channel Four, is surprise word-of-mouth hit in US, playing in 117 theaters nationwide (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In St.-Ouen, a nondescript industrial suburb on the northern edge of Paris, Eric Rohmer is recreating the French Revolution inside a converted warehouse. His new film, ''The Lady and the Duke,'' promises to be the most expansive reconstruction of the era ever undertaken, a significant change of pace for a filmmaker famous for intimate romantic, philosophical dramas like ''Claire's Knee'' and ''An Autumn Tale.''</p>
        <p>But this set, too, is surprisingly intimate. On a recent day Mr. Rohmer was restaging a triumphant march down a Parisian boulevard, a process that involved no more than 9 or 10 people: Mr. Rohmer (now a spindly 80), his cinematographer, Diane Baratier (who, in her 30's, looks as if she could be a Rohmer heroine herself), a couple of electricians and half a dozen extras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In St.-Ouen, a nondescript industrial suburb on the northern edge of Paris, Eric Rohmer is recreating the French Revolution inside a converted warehouse. His new film, ''The Lady and the Duke,'' promises to be the most expansive reconstruction of the era ever undertaken, a significant change of pace for a filmmaker famous for intimate romantic, philosophical dramas like ''Claire's Knee'' and ''An Autumn Tale.''</p>
        <p>But this set, too, is surprisingly intimate. On a recent day Mr. Rohmer was restaging a triumphant march down a Parisian boulevard, a process that involved no more than 9 or 10 people: Mr. Rohmer (now a spindly 80), his cinematographer, Diane Baratier (who, in her 30's, looks as if she could be a Rohmer heroine herself), a couple of electricians and half a dozen extras.</p>
        <p>That's because Mr. Rohmer is shooting ''The Lady and the Duke'' on digital video and using the new medium's resources electronically to create a Paris that hasn't existed in 200 years.</p>
        <p>There are two cameras on the set, one pointing toward a 3-by-4-foot painting, based on a period engraving, of the wide boulevard, and another aimed at a wooden window frame placed against a bright green backdrop. Mr. Rohmer instructs an extra on how to lean out and wave while Ms. Baratier lines up the image so that it matches a window on the painted street. By repeating this meticulous process several dozen times, Mr. Rohmer will be able to fill his 18th-century street with a crowd composed of distinct individuals, laid in one by one.</p>
        <p>In Hollywood this shot would involve dozens of technicians and weeks of meticulous post-production. But the less affluent French cinema is used to a hands-on, do-it-yourself technique that finds even a figure as august as Mr. Rohmer pitching in with the detail work. Francoise Echegarray, who is producing ''The Lady and the Duke'' for Pathe Images, the specialized division of the French studio Pathe, suggests that the detail work may be what fascinated Mr. Rohmer in the first place.</p>
        <p>''He is obsessed by architecture,'' she said, ''the architecture of the street as well as the architecture of a film.''</p>
        <p>The movie's $6 million budget is high by French standards but extremely low by American. It is based on the memoirs of Grace Elliot, a British aristocrat who during the revolution became the mistress of the Duke of Orleans, the king's brother. The Lady will be played by the English newcomer Lucy Russell, the Duke by the French character actor Jean-Claude Dreyfus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rohmer approaches his job with quiet concentration. He makes it a rule to decline interviews during production, and a hushed atmosphere prevails on his set, with none of the usual chatter among crew members and cast. It feels less like a sound stage than a laboratory where researchers silently go about their work. For all of the torrents of conversation that have passed before Mr. Rohmer's camera, very little is to be heard behind it.</p>
        <p>Brother Act</p>
        <p>The Weitz brothers -- Paul, 34, and Chris, 30 -- share an impressive resume: they wrote the 1998 computer-animated film ''Antz'' and then directed last summer's hit comedy ''American Pie.'' They wrote the script for ''The Klumps,'' Eddie Murphy's sequel to ''The Nutty Professor,'' and they've just completed filming of their own second feature, ''Down to Earth,'' a remake of ''Here Comes Mr. Jordan'' (No. 2, after Warren Beatty's ''Heaven Can Wait'') that stars Chris Rock and is set for release this fall.</p>
        <p>And in the middle of all that they found the time to star in ''Chuck and Buck,'' an independent feature that was a hit at the Sundance Film Festival and opens in New York today. (Review, Page 10.)</p>
        <p>Chris Weitz plays Chuck, a Los Angeles music producer who finds himself being stalked by Buck (Mike White, who also wrote the script), a childhood friend who has preserved an adolescent crush on him. Buck, rejected, writes a play based on his unrequited passion, and hires Sam (Paul Weitz), an unemployed actor who looks strangely like Chuck, to play him onstage.</p>
        <p>''We don't do this normally,'' Chris said over lunch at a restaurant in the East Village. He has known the director, Miguel Arteta, since they were film students together at Wesleyan University.</p>
        <p>''One day Miguel left a message on my machine asking if I'd act for him,'' he said. ''I thought he was making a short, or messing around with a new digital video camera. So I left him a message saying, 'O.K., as a matter of fact you've spotted my hidden vanity.' So then Paul came on board.''</p>
        <p>Paul continued: ''Yeah, first they had the idea of Chris, and then they realized that this other character was supposed to look like that character, and they thought of me to play a grotesque version of Chris. Apart from its humor, the script was so bizarre and essentially unappealing that it had trouble attracting investors. The advantage of casting us was that you didn't have to pay us.''</p>
        <p>Though the Weitzes had never acted before, they did have the genetic material. Their mother is Susan Kohner, whose performance in Douglas Sirk's ''Imitation of Life'' (1959) earned her an Oscar nomination. And their grandmother is Lupita Tovar, a Mexican actress who went to Hollywood to star in Spanish-language versions of early talkies, including ''Dracula.''</p>
        <p>''At the time we certainly had no idea either that it was going to get into Sundance or that anyone would see it, so it seemed like doing something for the heck of it, just for a challenge,'' said Chris.</p>
        <p>In spite of glowing reviews, the brothers have no further acting plans. ''We're going to keep trying to make different kinds of films, as opposed to staying in the 'American Pie' niche and trying to do that better and better,'' said Paul. ''That's what's going to allow us not to be incredibly bored by being a team.''</p>
        <p>Winning Gamble</p>
        <p>The indie hit of the summer is turning out to be the British thriller ''Croupier,'' which opened on April 21 in New York and has now spread to 117 theaters nationwide. ''It's an old-fashioned word-of-mouth picture,'' said Eamonn Bowles, president of Shooting Gallery Films, the company distributing ''Croupier'' in the United States. ''It just keeps getting bigger.''</p>
        <p>Made three years ago for Channel Four television in Britain by the veteran director Mike Hodges (''Get Carter'') and given a very brief theatrical run in London, the film was rescued from obscurity by a sales agent, Mike Kaplan, who brought it to Mr. Bowles's attention. In 13 weeks of release ''Croupier'' has taken in $2.1 million in the United States, not a staggering figure by Hollywood standards but enough to make it a smash in the independent world.</p>
        <p>''It's gone up 20 percent a week,'' said Mr. Bowles. ''I've never seen anything like it.''</p>
        <p>AT THE MOVIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
