<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond 'Electronic,' a Range of Brash, Rich and Raucous Compositions</title>
    <meta content="14ASKO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lincoln Center Festival 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Asko Ensemble (Music Group)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Schonberg Ensemble (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Leeuw, Reinbert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1DF163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2242" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond 'Electronic,' a Range of Brash, Rich and Raucous Compositions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews electronic music as performed by Asko and Schonberg Ensembles from Netherlands, conducted by Reinbert de Leeuw; series is presented at Lincoln Center Festival 2000 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For many people the term ''electronic music'' still conjures images of passive audiences in darkened concert halls listening to tape-recorded collages of electronically altered sounds played through loudspeakers. One aim of the Lincoln Center Festival's ''Electronic Evolution: A Five-Part Series'' is to show that the range of compositions involving electronic techniques and, in recent years, computer software is so wide, rich and jumbled that the generic term ''electronic music'' may have outlived its usefulness.</p>
        <p>The impressive performers for the exciting concert that opened the series on Wednesday night were the Asko and Schonberg Ensembles from the Netherlands, conducted by Reinbert de Leeuw. Interestingly, for a series examining the evolution of a genre, the three works were performed in reverse chronological order. To suggest what electronic music has become, the evening began with the United States premiere of Ron Ford's ''Salome Fast,'' from 1996. Next came a seminal work by Edgard Varese, ''Deserts,'' composed in 1954. The program ended with Olivier Messiaen's 1944 masterpiece ''Trois Petites Liturgies de la Presence Divine.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For many people the term ''electronic music'' still conjures images of passive audiences in darkened concert halls listening to tape-recorded collages of electronically altered sounds played through loudspeakers. One aim of the Lincoln Center Festival's ''Electronic Evolution: A Five-Part Series'' is to show that the range of compositions involving electronic techniques and, in recent years, computer software is so wide, rich and jumbled that the generic term ''electronic music'' may have outlived its usefulness.</p>
        <p>The impressive performers for the exciting concert that opened the series on Wednesday night were the Asko and Schonberg Ensembles from the Netherlands, conducted by Reinbert de Leeuw. Interestingly, for a series examining the evolution of a genre, the three works were performed in reverse chronological order. To suggest what electronic music has become, the evening began with the United States premiere of Ron Ford's ''Salome Fast,'' from 1996. Next came a seminal work by Edgard Varese, ''Deserts,'' composed in 1954. The program ended with Olivier Messiaen's 1944 masterpiece ''Trois Petites Liturgies de la Presence Divine.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford, an American born in 1959, has an interesting background. After studying composition and piano at Duke University, he moved in 1983 to Amsterdam, where he completed his musical education. ''Salome Fast,'' written for the Asko Ensemble, combines qualities of European elegance and American irreverence. The 15-minute work, a dense, compressed and exhilarating telling of the Salome story, is brilliantly scored for 15 musicians playing traditional instruments and a speaker reciting the biblical text in Aramaic, the language of the time. The only electronic element of the piece is the narrator's amplified voice, which is processed electronically.</p>
        <p>The music is brash, raucous and riveting. In what seems a mischievous upending of expectations, the acoustic instruments imitate sound effects associated with electronic techniques: bleeps, slides, every-which-way splatterings of fast notes. A recurring motif of lush descending parallel chords keeps calming down the music when it becomes frenetic. In the piece's most violent stretch, a thick tonal chord keeps slicing through the chaos. Seldom has a consonant harmony sounded so menacing.</p>
        <p>There was an exotic (for American listeners) yet authentic quality to the Aramaic text, compellingly spoken by Naurez Atto. As the work approaches its conclusion the text becomes increasingly distorted and raspy, and the sounds echo upon themselves from opposite speakers. The effect created is as if the narrator cannot bear to relate the outcome of this horrific story.</p>
        <p>Curiously, coming after Mr. Ford's work, Varese's ''Deserts,'' though a historic score, was somewhat disappointing. Sections of music played by a large ensemble of boisterous wind and percussion instruments alternate with interludes of tape-recorded sounds: the composer's electronically altered montages of instrumental sounds and factory noises. In 1954 the recorded segments must have been shocking. On this occasion they seemed dated.</p>
        <p>The Messiaen was a triumph. ''Three Short Liturgies of the Divine Presence,'' the title in English translation, is scored for female chorus, strings, piano, percussion and the ondes-martenot, an electronic instrument from the 1920's that produces oscillating pitches by operating a wire across a keyboard. The work is rapturous, a devout Roman Catholic composer's deeply personal conception of what celestial music must truly sound like. The work is alive with jerky rhythmic riffs, exuberant bird calls, astringent harmonies, pulsating chords and hauntingly angelic melodies for women's voices.</p>
        <p>The ondes-martenot, played by Valerie Hartmann-Claverie, gives the work just a touch of sci-fi-flick playfulness, which prevents the overt spirituality from seeming too precious. Under Mr. de Leeuw, the Asko and Schonberg Ensembles (who are also performing the opera ''Writing to Vermeer'' during the festival) played incomparably. The women of the Vox Vocal Ensemble (George Steel, conductor) sang with enchanting sweetness. And the pianist Peter Serkin played the stunningly difficult piano part with command, unflagging energy, imagination and, where called for, great delicacy.</p>
        <p>In the last sublime moments of the work, when the pianist does not play, Mr. Serkin sat upright, eyes closed, listening with Buddha-like contemplation.</p>
        <p>When the piece was over it almost seemed intrusive to disturb Mr. Serkin's meditation and break the general spell. But applause, cheers and a prolonged standing ovation soon broke out.</p>
        <p>The series continues tonight in the Low Library Rotunda at Columbia University and tomorrow night at the Society for Ethical Culture (2 West 64th Street, Manhattan). On Tuesday night at Avery Fisher Hall, Mr. Serkin, Mr. de Leeuw and the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center present Messiaen's ''From the Canyons to the Stars,'' a repeat of their acclaimed performance last spring. It should not be missed.</p>
        <p>A Festival Guide</p>
        <p>Lincoln Center Festival 2000 runs through July 30 at several Manhattan locations, with most in the Lincoln Center complex. Tickets for individual events range from $15 to $85 and can be purchased at the box office at Avery Fisher Hall, or through CenterCharge (212) 721-6500 and Ticketmaster (212) 307-4100. Festival information: (212) 875-5928; or at the Web site, www.lincolncenter.org. The New York Video Festival, part of the Lincoln Center Festival, runs from July 21 to 27 at the Walter Reade Theater at Lincoln Center; video tickets are $9; $5 for Film Society of Lincoln Center members; $4.50 for the elderly at weekday matinees. Video schedule information: (212) 875-5601. A schedule of Lincoln Center Festival events follows:</p>
        <p>Manhattan Venues</p>
        <p>ALICE TULLY HALL, 1941 Broadway, at 65th Street, Lincoln Center.  AVERY FISHER HALL, Broadway at 65th Street, Lincoln Center.  COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY, Broadway at West 116th Street, Morningside Heights.  DAMROSCH PARK TENT, Lincoln Center.  FORDHAM UNIVERSITY THEATER, Pope Auditorium, Columbus Avenue and 60th Street.  JOHN JAY COLLEGE THEATER, 899 10th Avenue, at 59th Street.  KAPLAN PENTHOUSE, Rose Building, 165 West 65th Street, Lincoln Center.  LA GUARDIA HIGH SCHOOL CONCERT HALL, 100 Amsterdam Avenue, at 64th Street.</p>
        <p>MAKOR, 35 West 67th Street.</p>
        <p>MITZI E. NEWHOUSE THEATER, Lincoln Center.  NEW YORK SOCIETY FOR ETHICAL CULTURE, 2 West 64th Street.  NEW YORK STATE THEATER, Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>Today</p>
        <p>''FIFTY YEARS OF ELECTRONIC MUSIC TECHNIQUES AND EQUIPMENT,'' Columbia University, Low Library Rotunda. An exhibition on view through August. Hours, daily, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.  ''ELECTRONIC MUSIC -- MEET THE MAKERS,'' Kaplan Penthouse. A discussion with  inventors, including Robert Moog (synthesizer); Don Buchla (marimba lumina); Valerie Hartmann-Claviere (ondes martenot); and Lydia Kavina, who plays the theremin; moderated by David Kean, founder of the Audites Foundation, 5:30 to 8 p.m. Free.  ''BROTHERS AND SISTERS,'' John Jay College Theater. Presented by the Maly Theater of St. Petersburg, 7:30 p.m. (Part 2).  ''FILAO,'' Damrosch Park Tent. A one-ring spectacle, with music and circus-style performances by a French troupe, Les Colporteurs, 7 p.m.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater. A play by Rebecca Gilman, 8 p.m.  ''IN SPITE OF WISHING AND WANTING'' LaGuardia High School Concert Hall. Choreographed by Wim Vandekeybus, with music by David Byrne, 8 p.m.  ''WRITING TO VERMEER,'' New York State Theater. Presented by the Netherlands Opera, 8 p.m.  ELECTRONIC EVOLUTION 3: MASTERPIECES OF 20TH-CENTURY MULTICHANNEL TAPE MUSIC, Columbia University, Low Library Rotunda. Chosen by the Columbia University Computer Music Center, 9 p.m. Ticketholders can attend an interactive multimedia installation from 7 to 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow</p>
        <p>''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 2 and 8 p.m  ''BROTHERS AND SISTERS,'' John Jay College Theater. Presented by the Maly Theater of St. Petersburg, 2 p.m. (Part 1); 7 p.m. (Part 2).  ''FILAO,'' Damrosch Park Tent, 7 p.m.  ''WRITING TO VERMEER,'' New York State Theater, 8 p.m.  ''ELECTRONIC EVOLUTION 4: THE TURNTABLE AS AN ENSEMBLE INSTRUMENT,'' New York Society for Ethical Culture. Featuring the X-ecutioners, DJ Frankie, DJ A. Vee and Kuttin' Kandi and Christian Marclay, 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>''BROTHERS AND SISTERS,'' John Jay College Theater, 2 p.m. (Part 1); 7 p.m. (Part 2).  ''FILAO,'' Damrosch Park Tent, 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>Monday</p>
        <p>BILL T. JONES, Kaplan Penthouse. The choreographer will discuss his works, 6 p.m. Free.  ''FILAO,'' Damrosch Park Tent, 7 p.m.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>Tuesday</p>
        <p>''OLIVIER MESSIAEN -- ARTISTS' VIEWS,'' Kaplan Penthouse. A discussion about the composer, featuring the conductors Hans Vonk and Reinbert de Leeuw and Albert Imperato, founding member of 21C Media Group, a marketing and consulting firm, 6 p.m. Free.  ''GISELLE,'' New York State Theater. The Bolshoi Ballet, 8 p.m.  ''MESSIAEN CELEBRATION,'' Avery Fisher Hall. Presented by the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center, 8 p.m.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 8 p.m.  ''MEREDITH MONK: VOICE TRAVEL,'' New York Society for Ethical Culture, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>Wednesday</p>
        <p>MEREDITH MONK, Kaplan Penthouse. A discussion with the artist and Mark Swed, a music critic, 5:30 p.m. Free.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 2 and 8 p.m.  ''FILAO,'' Damrosch Park Tent, 7 p.m.  ''INNOCENT AS CHARGED,'' Fordham University Theater. Presented by the Vakhtangov Theater of Moscow, 7:30 p.m.  MEREDITH MONK ON FILM, Makor. First in a three-part series of screenings featuring ''Book of Days'' and ''Ellis Island,'' 7:30 and 9:30 p.m. Tickets, $8.  BOLSHOI BALLET: PROGRAM B, New York State Theater. A repertory program featuring ''Appian Way'' and Adagio from ''Spartacus''; the Grand Pas from ''Don Quixote''; ''The Kingdom of the Shades'' from ''La Bayadere'' and ''Symphony in C'' with choreography by George Balanchine, 8 p.m.  ''YOU WALK?,'' LaGuardia High School Concert Hall. Featuring the Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company, 8 p.m.  ''ELECTRONIC EVOLUTION 5: MUSIC FROM THE ETHER: A CELEBRATION OF THE THEREMIN,'' New York Society for Ethical Culture. With Ensemble Sospeso, conducted by Jeffrey Milarsky, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>Thursday</p>
        <p>BOLSHOI BALLET, Kaplan Penthouse. A discussion with Aleksei Fadeyechev, artistic director of the Bolshoi Ballet, and Elizabeth Kendall, a dance critic and writer, 6 p.m. Free.  ''FILAO,'' Damrosch Park Tent, 7 p.m.  ''INNOCENT AS CHARGED,'' Fordham University Theater, 7:30 p.m.  MEREDITH MONK ON FILM, Makor. Second in a three-part series of screenings featuring ''Selected Short Films,'' 7:30 and 9:30 p.m. Tickets, $8.  ''THE BREATHING SHOW,'' La Guardia High School Concert Hall. Featuring the Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company, 8 p.m.  BOLSHOI BALLET, PROGRAM B, New York State Theater. Repertory program, 8 p.m.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>July 21</p>
        <p>''FILAO,'' Damrosch Park Tent, 7 p.m.  VAKHTANGOV THEATER: ''INNOCENT AS CHARGED,'' Kaplan Penthouse. A discussion with members of the company including its artistic director, Mikhail Ulianov, 6 p.m. Free.  ''INNOCENT AS CHARGED,'' Fordham University Theater, 7:30 p.m.  ''YOU WALK?,'' La Guardia High School Concert Hall, 8 p.m.  BOLSHOI BALLET: PROGRAM B, New York State Theater, 8 p.m.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 8 p.m.  ''MEREDITH MONK: VOICE TRAVEL,'' Alice Tully Hall, 8 p.m.  ''MESSIAEN CELEBRATION,'' Avery Fisher Hall. Featuring the New York Philharmonic, conducted by Hans Vonk 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>July 22</p>
        <p>''GISELLE,'' Bolshoi Ballet, New York State Theater, 2 and 8 p.m.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 2 and 8 p.m.  ''FILAO,'' Damrosch ParK Tent, 7 p.m.  ''INNOCENT AS CHARGED,'' Fordham University Theater, 7:30 p.m.  ''YOU WALK?,'' La Guardia High School Concert Hall, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>July 23</p>
        <p>''INNOCENT AS CHARGED,'' Fordham University Theater, 3 p.m.  ''GISELLE,'' Bolshoi Ballet, New York State Theater, 3 p.m.  ''CARIBBEAN ROOTS, CARIBBEAN ROUTES: POLITICS AND SPIRIT,'' Kaplan Penthouse. A discussion with performers, scholars and ethnomusicologists, including Samuel Clayton, founding performer of Mystic Revelation of Rastafari, 6 p.m. Free.  MEREDITH MONK ON FILM, Makor. Last in a three-part series of screenings featuring ''Book of Days'' and ''Ellis Island,'' 2:30 and 4:30 p.m. Tickets, $8.  ''MEREDITH MONK: VOICE TRAVEL,'' LaGuardia High School Concert Hall, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>July 24</p>
        <p>''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 8 p.m.  ''CARIBBEAN ROOTS: CARIBBEAN ROUTES,'' with Nyabinghi Spirit and the Heartbeat of Reggae, New York Society for Ethical Culture, 9 p.m .</p>
        <p>July 25</p>
        <p>JAMAICAN DRUMMING WORKSHOP, Franklin H. Williams Caribbean Cultural Center/ African Diaspora Institute, 408 West 58th Street, Manhattan. With performers from  Mystic Revelations of Rastafari, 4 to 7 p.m. Fee, $10.  ALVIN AILEY AMERICAN DANCE THEATER: Program A,'' New York State Theater. Featuring ''Double Exposure'' and ''Revelations,'' 8 p.m  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 8 p.m</p>
        <p>July 26</p>
        <p>''ALVIN AILEY AMERICAN DANCE THEATER, Program B, New York State Theater, 8 p.m. Featuring ''Blues Suite,'' ''Memoria,'' ''Pas de Duke,'' and ''Revelations,'' 8 p.m.  ''POUR ANTIGONE,'' La Guardia High School Concert Hall. A dance/theater piece by the French choreographer Mathilde Monnier and her company, 8:30 p.m.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 2 and 8 p.m.  ''CARIBBEAN ROOTS: CARIBBEAN ROUTES,'' with Mizik Racine and the Rhythm of Vodou, New York Society for Ethical Culture, 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>July 27</p>
        <p>ALVIN AILEY AMERICAN DANCE THEATER, Program B, New York State Theater, 8 p.m.  ''ALVIN AILEY DANCE COMPANY: JUDITH JAMISON,'' Kaplan Penthouse. A discussion with Ms. Jamison, the artistic director, and members of the company, 6 p.m. Free  ''CARIBBEAN ROOTS: CARIBBEAN ROUTES,'' with Griots of the West Indies, Avery Fisher Hall, 8 p.m. A performance of music and poetry with Linton Kwesi Johnson and the Dennis Bovell Dub Band; David Rudder and Charlie's Roots and Composer and the Mighty Power, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>July 28</p>
        <p>ALVIN AILEY AMERICAN DANCE THEATER, Program A, New York State Theater, 8 p.m.  ''POUR ANTIGONE,'' La Guardia High School Concert Hall, 8:30 p.m.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Lincoln Center Theater, 8 p.m.  ''CARIBBEAN ROOTS: CARIBBEAN ROUTES,'' with Tradewinds of Trinidad, New York Society for Ethical Culture. A performance of parang music and jazz with San Jose Serenaders and Mungal Patasar and Pantar, 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>July 29</p>
        <p>ALVIN AILEY AMERICAN DANCE THEATER, Programs A and B, New York State Theater. Program B, 2 p.m.; Program A, 8 p.m.  ''POUR ANTIGONE,'' La Guardia High School Concert Hall, 8:30 p.m.  ''SPINNING INTO BUTTER,'' Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater, 2 and 8 p.m.  ''CARIBBEAN ROOTS: CARIBBEAN ROUTES:  THE FRENCH CONNECTION: RISING STARS OF CREOLE SONG,'' Avery Fisher Hall, 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>July 30</p>
        <p>ALVIN AILEY AMERICAN DANCE THEATER, Program A, New York State Theater, 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
