<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology Shares Lift Nasdaq, but Wave Stops There</title>
    <meta content="Y14STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DA163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology Shares Lift Nasdaq, but Wave Stops There</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nasdaq composite index climbs 75.27 points, or 1.8 percent, to 4,174.86; Dow Jones industrial average edges up 5.30 points, or 0.05 percent, to 10,788.71; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index rises 2.92 points, or 0.2 percent, to 1,495.84; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Strong quarterly reports from several companies touched off fresh buying in technology stocks yesterday, lifting the Nasdaq composite index to a second consecutive solid gain as the rest of the market mostly languished.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq, which climbed 75.27 points, or 1.8 percent, to 4,174.86, moved more solidly into positive territory for the year. With a gain of 2.6 percent, it has now outperformed the broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, which is up 1.8 percent this year. Nasdaq has surged 31.9 percent since May 23, when its springtime plunge -- a drop of 37.3 percent from its March peak -- hit bottom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Strong quarterly reports from several companies touched off fresh buying in technology stocks yesterday, lifting the Nasdaq composite index to a second consecutive solid gain as the rest of the market mostly languished.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq, which climbed 75.27 points, or 1.8 percent, to 4,174.86, moved more solidly into positive territory for the year. With a gain of 2.6 percent, it has now outperformed the broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index, which is up 1.8 percent this year. Nasdaq has surged 31.9 percent since May 23, when its springtime plunge -- a drop of 37.3 percent from its March peak -- hit bottom.</p>
        <p>''The earnings announcements are giving people confidence'' that Internet and other high-technology companies will sustain profit growth, said Michael D. Jamison, managing director at Brandywine Asset Management in Wilmington, Del.</p>
        <p>Ariba, for example, jumped 27 11/16, to 13 13/16, after issuing its quarterly report, and Applied Micro Circuits, which reported late Wednesday, added 28 1/16, to 153 1/2. Motorola, a New York Stock Exchange company that also posted results on Wednesday, gained 3 3/4, to 39 1/4, as the second most actively traded stock of the day, after Cisco Systems, which rose 1 3/8, to 65 1/4.</p>
        <p>But there was little enthusiasm for other than technology shares.</p>
        <p>The S.&amp; P. 500 rose 2.92 points, or 0.2 percent, to 1,495.84. The biggest upward force was WorldCom, which rose 3 7/16, to 47 15/16, after its merger with Sprint was officially ended. Pfizer was the biggest drag, falling 1 7/8, to 46 1/8.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average edged up 5.30 points, or 0.05 percent, to 10,788.71, its fifth consecutive rise, but is still down 6.16 percent for the year.</p>
        <p>Drug stocks were battered again as Washington appeared to move closer to adding prescriptions to Medicare coverage. Investors fear that will bring price limitations.</p>
        <p>Schering-Plough and Merck each lost more than 4 points, and Bristol-Myers Squibb dropped more than 3.</p>
        <p>Investors were also bracing for government reports today on producer prices, retail sales and industrial output for June, and for a reading on consumer sentiment by the University of Michigan. Evidence that the pace of inflation has become more than a creep or that the economy is not slowing markedly would undermine an assumption that the Federal Reserve's yearlong raising of short-term interest is near an end.</p>
        <p>''The conclusion that most people have is that the Fed is finished,'' said Robert Bloom, president of Friends, Ivory &amp; Sime, a money manager. But he said he disagreed, citing, among other things, a still-taut job market in which job growth is slowing because the pool of potential workers is drying up, not because demand for them has slackened.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Treasury Prices Rise</p>
        <p>(By Bloomberg News) -- Bond prices rose yesterday after a report showed an increase in jobless claims and the Federal Reserve bought Treasuries in two rounds of purchases.</p>
        <p>The price of the 10-year Treasury note rose 1 8/32, to 103 21/32. The note's yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, fell to 5.99 percent from 6.07 percent on Wednesday. The 30-year Treasury bond increased 2 9/32, to 106 4/32. The bond's yield fell to 5.82 percent from 5.88 percent on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
