<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Late-Arriving Williams Ties for Early Lead</title>
    <meta content="14LPGA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Japan Airlines Big Apple Classic (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Rosie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finney, Allison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Kim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2DE173BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Late-Arriving Williams Ties for Early Lead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE, N.Y., July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kim Williams shares lead with Rosie Jones and Allison Finney after first round of Japan Airlines Big Apple Classic (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six years later, Kim Williams still cannot avoid the questions. It does not matter if she plays an excellent round of golf, as she did today in the first round of the Japan Airlines Big Apple Classic. She always has to answer questions about being struck in the neck by a stray bullet in July 1994.</p>
        <p>''You get tired of being known just for that,'' said the 37-year-old Williams, who underwent surgery to remove the bullet in 1995. ''I'd rather be known as the girl that won the tournament, rather than the girl that got shot.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Six years later, Kim Williams still cannot avoid the questions. It does not matter if she plays an excellent round of golf, as she did today in the first round of the Japan Airlines Big Apple Classic. She always has to answer questions about being struck in the neck by a stray bullet in July 1994.</p>
        <p>''You get tired of being known just for that,'' said the 37-year-old Williams, who underwent surgery to remove the bullet in 1995. ''I'd rather be known as the girl that won the tournament, rather than the girl that got shot.''</p>
        <p>Williams has never won a tournament in 13 full seasons on the L.P.G.A. Tour, but she shared the lead after the first round of the $900,000 tournament today at Wykagyl Country Club. Williams shot a four-under-par 67 on the 6,161-yard course and is tied with Rosie Jones and Allison Finney. Jones has 10 victories and Finney has one, none this season.</p>
        <p>Being shot was not the only problem for Williams. She underwent surgery for a ruptured disk almost two years ago and still feels the soreness. She has played little golf since the surgery and no longer has a full exemption.</p>
        <p>Williams was the first alternate for this tournament. She arrived late Wednesday night from her mother's home in Maryland and was told this morning that she was in the tournament in place of Wendy Doolan, who injured her hand in Wednesday's pro-am and could not play.</p>
        <p>''I hadn't hit a ball for 10 days last week because my back acts up sometimes since the surgery,'' said Williams, who teed off shortly before 9 o'clock and proceeded to make five birdies and a bogey for her 67. ''But the reason I scored today was because I putted well.''</p>
        <p>Three of the birdies by Williams came from putts longer than 10 feet and the round of 67 was the first time she broke 70 this season. Four of her birdies came in five holes from the fourth through the eighth.</p>
        <p>Jones registered seven birdies and three bogeys. She said the keys to her round were that she followed her bogeys with birdies and that she changed the way she lined up for putts. ''I stumbled into something yesterday and it helped me,'' Jones said of the change in her putting. ''A friend pointed out that I wasn't lined up well.''</p>
        <p>Finney's round included an eagle on the 432-yard 15th, which plays to par 5, four birdies and two bogeys. She missed the cut in her previous four tournaments, but today's round increased her confidence.</p>
        <p>''This is my Open,'' said Finney, who has not qualified for next week's United States Women's Open. ''This course is a good preparation for the Open.''</p>
        <p>Michelle Redman, the winner of the tournament in 1997, Annika Sorenstam, who won in 1998, and Jennifer Feldott, whose best finish in three years on tour is tied for fifth, were next at two-under 69.</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>GRACE PARK felt ill after playing three holes and withdrew, leaving HELEN ALFREDSSON and KRISTAL PARKER to play as a twosome.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
