<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Residential Real Estate; Summer Rental Market Booms for Only Some</title>
    <meta content="14REAL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brozan, Nadine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Vacation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7D7163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Residential Real Estate; Summer Rental Market Booms for Only Some</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NADINE BROZAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brozan, Nadine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brokers in summer resorts say rental market is good, but not uniformly so, contrary to early expectation; suggest that some people who bought resort houses before stock market began to slide have put those houses up for rent for at least part of summer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the coast of Maine to the Jersey Shore, brokers in summer resorts were salivating this year over the prospects of a record-breaking rental season. Prices were soaring and prospective tenants were pleading with them to accept deposit checks. He who hesitated was lost, agents warned clients. A house on the market one minute was sure to be snapped up the next.</p>
        <p>Then came March and April and a slide in the stock market. Would that break the spell, people wondered, or would the clamor continue, immune to financial gyrations? Layered on top of that was concern about escalating gasoline prices and a succession of rainy weekends that kept some house hunters away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the coast of Maine to the Jersey Shore, brokers in summer resorts were salivating this year over the prospects of a record-breaking rental season. Prices were soaring and prospective tenants were pleading with them to accept deposit checks. He who hesitated was lost, agents warned clients. A house on the market one minute was sure to be snapped up the next.</p>
        <p>Then came March and April and a slide in the stock market. Would that break the spell, people wondered, or would the clamor continue, immune to financial gyrations? Layered on top of that was concern about escalating gasoline prices and a succession of rainy weekends that kept some house hunters away.</p>
        <p>With Memorial Day and Independence Day now past, many brokers say that while the rental market was good, it was not uniformly so, and that some early expectations turned out to be unrealistic. There are some houses available that would have been occupied in prior years.</p>
        <p>''I have rented a four-bedroom house with pool and air-conditioning in Roxbury for $40,000 a season for the last four summers, and this year it has not been rented,'' said Seymour Surnow, who owns the Surnow Group at William Raveis Real Estate in Washington Depot, Conn. ''I have a wonderful Washington rental for August for $6,000 that in the last three years has been taken for the whole season.''</p>
        <p>Though waterfront houses were spoken for long ago no matter where they were, the broader picture varies from one neighborhood to another. For example, on Mount Desert Island, Me., Cuthbert Train, owner of Train Properties, said: ''In Northeast Harbor, we have nothing at all left for August. The rest of the island has been solid but not great. Great is a year when we've rented 80 percent of the inventory. This year, we've probably rented 70 percent.''</p>
        <p>He added, however, that the decline was not sharp enough to cause concern. ''This is a place where people have second, third and fourth houses,'' he said. ''No one is relying on the income.''</p>
        <p>The situation is similarly mixed in the Hamptons, where some say that the booming stock market prompted many former renters to buy and then put their new homes up for rent for at least part of the summer.</p>
        <p>''So with one transaction, you've taken one potential tenant out of the pool and added one new house,'' said Frank Newbold, senior vice president and brokerage manager for Sotheby's International Realty in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>In the view of Judi Desiderio, the vice president of Cook Pony Farm Real Estate, which has offices from Westhampton Beach to Amagansett, ''The season started early, started with a bang and lasted long.''</p>
        <p>''We had 7,000 rental listings through our seven offices this year,'' she said, ''and it looks as if 90 percent'' were rented, or in some cases, sold. ''Tenants are now asking, 'Can we re-rent for next year at the same price?' '' she added.</p>
        <p>That was decidedly not the experience of Tina S. Fredericks, who has her own agency in East Hampton.</p>
        <p>''Things have not gone well here,'' she said the other day, ''and I have heard that other offices have been very quiet. We get many calls from owners who were counting on renting and who have not or who have only been able to do so for a few weeks, and that's been disappointing. Prospective renters who do call have sharply scaled down their requests. People keep asking for a weekend,  and we even had a request for a one-day rental. Last year we had close to 80 rentals and so far this year, we've had 40.''</p>
        <p>Asked what had caused the downturn, she said: ''I just don't know. I think maybe the market is scaring people, and the traffic, and the fact that asking prices are very high. Maybe owners priced themselves out of the market.''</p>
        <p>That was the case on Martha's Vineyard, according to Ann Floyd, who owns Sandcastle Realty. ''People were pushing the envelope price-wise,'' she said. ''We have had any number of owners call and say, 'Hey, you're not renting our house.' We told them to back down and reduce their prices, but it was too late.''</p>
        <p>The fact that there are no weekend reservations left for cars on the ferry to the island does not help. ''So we've tried to encourage owners to do Monday-to-Monday or Tuesday-to-Tuesday rentals,'' Ms. Floyd said.</p>
        <p>Arthur Mazzei, a sales associate at Kurfiss Real Estate in New Hope, Pa., tried to persuade denizens of the Hamptons to try his area instead last year by placing ads in newspapers there. ''I said, 'Now that you've rented your house in the Hamptons, why not try Bucks County for the summer?' and I got good responses,'' he said. ''People told me that they're getting $25,000 to $40,000 per month for their homes and turning around and for $5,000 a month, they got a 5,000-square-foot barn on one of the most scenic roads in Bucks County. And they were only an hour and 45 minutes from Manhattan.''</p>
        <p>''I had such a positive response last year, I thought it would be an automatic carryover to this year,'' Mr. Mazzei said. ''But I realize now I have to refresh people's memories about Bucks County on a yearly basis. This year has been disappointing.''</p>
        <p>What is detrimental to one area can provide a boom to another, and that was the case this year in Lake Wallenpaupack in the Poconos.</p>
        <p>Peter Helms, president of Davis R. Chant Realtors in Hawley, Pa., said his agency was getting a lot of customers who for years had gone to Lake George in upstate New York or  to Lake Winnipesaukee, N.H., ''both of which are six-  to seven-hour rides from New York.''</p>
        <p>''Now,'' he added, ''people are saying, 'With gas prices high, we're not going as far as we had planned. And we are within one tank of gas round-trip from New York.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
