<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pennington Signs With Jets Just in Time for Camp</title>
    <meta content="14JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Chad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6DB163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pennington Signs With Jets Just in Time for Camp</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets open training camp; sign quarterback Chad Pennington (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets will have a full house when they open training camp with two practices today. Quarterback Chad Pennington, the 18th overall selection in this year's draft, signed a five-year incentive-laden contract yesterday that could earn him as much as $23 million.</p>
        <p>Pennington was the last member of this year's unprecedented Jets draft class of four first-round picks to agree to a contract. The Jets were hamstrung by dwindling room under the National Football League's salary cap, which is $62.2 million this season, when negotiations with the first-round picks began. But they had signed their later round picks quickly and then got tight end Anthony Becht to sign during the spring. That left Shaun Ellis, the 12th overall pick, John Abraham, 13th over all, and Pennington. Ellis and Abraham took smaller-than-usual signing bonuses in exchange for guaranteed years later in the deal and advances on their first-year salaries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Jets will have a full house when they open training camp with two practices today. Quarterback Chad Pennington, the 18th overall selection in this year's draft, signed a five-year incentive-laden contract yesterday that could earn him as much as $23 million.</p>
        <p>Pennington was the last member of this year's unprecedented Jets draft class of four first-round picks to agree to a contract. The Jets were hamstrung by dwindling room under the National Football League's salary cap, which is $62.2 million this season, when negotiations with the first-round picks began. But they had signed their later round picks quickly and then got tight end Anthony Becht to sign during the spring. That left Shaun Ellis, the 12th overall pick, John Abraham, 13th over all, and Pennington. Ellis and Abraham took smaller-than-usual signing bonuses in exchange for guaranteed years later in the deal and advances on their first-year salaries.</p>
        <p>Ellis, a defensive end, and Abraham, a linebacker, are expected to contribute immediately in third-down situations, and Becht could wrest the starting tight end job  from Fred Baxter.</p>
        <p>But Pennington, whose signing bonus is $4.1 million, and whose base contract is worth just $6.5 million, had the advantage of playing the game's most critical position. His signing bonus is nearly equal to what Ellis and Abraham got in signing bonuses combined.</p>
        <p>Pennington's base salary in 2000 is $193,000, but he could earn a one-time bonus of nearly $2 million in the later years of the contract, one of many incentive features, if he is in on a prescribed percentage of plays in any of the first three years of the deal. Although Pennington enters camp as the third-string quarterback behind the starter Vinny Testaverde and the backup Ray Lucas, he was anointed the quarterback of the future on draft day.</p>
        <p>Testaverde will turn 37 this season and may not play beyond next season. In a reflective mood while discussing the devastating Achilles' tendon tear that ended his season last year, Testaverde would not even commit to playing next season if all does not go well in 2000. Testaverde, after reporting for the Jets' optional day of runs and physicals, said he takes nothing for granted since the injury.</p>
        <p>''You never know what's going to happen,'' Testaverde said. ''Another serious injury, a couple of trades, you just never know what can happen. The organization can decide to rebuild. If things work out, I'll be back next year. I don't even take for granted that I'm the starting quarterback.</p>
        <p>''Getting injured opened my eyes. Here everybody was thinking about winning a championship -- everything was in place, the entire coaching staff was back, Elway had retired so we're the favorites. A quarter and a half, there goes my season. Everything I worked so hard for to reach the point that I had a better than good chance to win a championship was gone in 20 minutes of football.''</p>
        <p>Testaverde said it may take several years for the strength in his left calf to again equal that in his right, but that he only thinks about his injury when asked about it and that he will not have a lighter workload during training camp because of it.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The Jets signed the rookie free agent fullback MIKE STACK and waived the rookie wide receiver BRANDON CAMPBELL yesterday. They confirmed that they would hold an open practice with the Giants at Michie Stadium at the United States Military Academy in West Point, N.Y., on Aug. 8 at 1 p.m.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
