<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Airbus Industrie Is Considering A Very Big Bet; Group Thinks Behemoth Jet Will Take on the Boeing 747</title>
    <meta content="Y14AIR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000726T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">A3xx Airplane</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boeing 747 Airplane</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Airbus Industrie</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boeing Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5D9163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Airbus Industrie Is Considering A Very Big Bet; Group Thinks Behemoth Jet Will Take on the Boeing 747</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>TOULOUSE, France</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European Airbus Industrie group is close to introducing gigantic double-decker jumbo jet, known for now as A3XX, for use on long-distance routes like those between Asia and Europe or US; jet, with capacity of 555 to 800 passengers, would carry at least 140 passengers more than largest Boeing 747; its development cost would exceed $10 billion; Boeing remains skeptical, saying there is very limited market for such a plane; charts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another white elephant like the Concorde? An extravaganza like the English Channel tunnel? Or a bet-the-company gamble that will prove just as successful as the Boeing 747 it hopes to succeed?</p>
        <p>Europe has a couple of gigantic transportation debacles to its record. The supersonic Concorde jetliner sounded promising, yet never got beyond a production run of about 20 airplanes, and has been confined for the last quarter of a century to a single trans-Atlantic route connecting New York with London and Paris. The Channel tunnel, though an operating success since it opened in 1994, cost $15 billion to build, double the original estimate, and accumulated a $14 billion mountain of debt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Another white elephant like the Concorde? An extravaganza like the English Channel tunnel? Or a bet-the-company gamble that will prove just as successful as the Boeing 747 it hopes to succeed?</p>
        <p>Europe has a couple of gigantic transportation debacles to its record. The supersonic Concorde jetliner sounded promising, yet never got beyond a production run of about 20 airplanes, and has been confined for the last quarter of a century to a single trans-Atlantic route connecting New York with London and Paris. The Channel tunnel, though an operating success since it opened in 1994, cost $15 billion to build, double the original estimate, and accumulated a $14 billion mountain of debt.</p>
        <p>Yet now the European Airbus Industrie group is close to introducing another transportation behemoth, a gigantic double-decker jumbo jet, known for now as the A3XX, for use on long- distance routes like those between Asia and Europe or the United States. With a capacity of 555 to 800 passengers, it would carry at least 140 passengers more than the largest Boeing 747. And its development cost would exceed $10 billion.</p>
        <p>Boeing remains skeptical. ''We think there is a market for this kind of aircraft, but a very, very limited market,'' said John Dern, a Boeing spokesman in Seattle. Boeing calculates that demand over the next 20 years for jetliners in the 400-passenger and up category will amount to ''fewer than 400,'' he said. Boeing itself is ''actively discussing'' with potential customers its own alternative -- a stretched version of the 747 -- but a final decision on whether to build it has not been reached, he added.</p>
        <p>Still, Airbus remains adamant that Europe's experience will be different this time. Unlike the Concorde, its proposed A3XX is encountering strong interest among airlines, Airbus officials say. Unlike the Channel tunnel, they insist, it will be financed in a way that would avoid a financial debacle.</p>
        <p>To get ready for the project, Airbus -- a loose consortium of four big European aerospace companies, Aerospatiale of France; DaimlerChrysler Aerospace of Germany; BAE Systems of Britain, formerly known as British Aerospace; and Construcciones Aeronauticas of Spain -- is recasting its corporate structure. Its French, German and Spanish partners are in the process of merging to form the European Aeronautics Defense and Space Company.</p>
        <p>EADS, as the company is known, will be the world's third-largest aerospace group after Boeing and Lockheed Martin, and on July 10 its shares began trading on European stock exchanges, offering a 30 percent stake to investors, to raise about $3.3 billion. [The shares were offered at a price of 23 euros, or $21.56 each; in Paris on Thursday, they closed at 17.98 euros, down 2.55 euros.]</p>
        <p>Airbus itself will become a unified, more easily manageable company owned 80 percent by EADS and 20 percent by BAE Systems. In return, European governments have pledged to make refundable loans as development aid for the A3XX.</p>
        <p>From the European perspective, the motivation for the A3XX is clear. By all estimates, civilian air travel will continue to grow into the new century at a rate of about 5 percent a year. Yet Boeing, with its 747, has a monopoly on the largest aircraft, those over 400 seats, which are expected to account for about one-quarter of all civilian aircraft sales. The A3XX is in fact only part of a broader effort by Airbus to challenge Boeing in every sector above the 100-seat jetliner.</p>
        <p>For Boeing, the consequences are potentially devastating. For years the 747, the uncontested queen of the skies and the flagship of most of the world's major airlines, has been Boeing's cash cow, accounting in good years for roughly half of Boeing's profits. ''It's a huge, huge item for Boeing,'' said Joseph F. Campbell Jr., an analyst who follows Boeing at Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the new Airbus jumbo jet threatens Boeing's dominance in Japan, where the 747 is king, and where Boeing enjoys cozy relations with both carriers and industrial suppliers of parts for its planes. To respond, Boeing is studying the possibility of investing $3 billion to $4 billion in a stretch version of the 747, for 500 passengers, that would compete head-to-head with the A3XX.</p>
        <p>For Airbus, the stakes are perhaps even greater. Airbus jetliners account for 70 percent of the revenue of EADS, its biggest shareholder, and failure of the A3XX would be a serious burden as the new aerospace giant seeks a start. Moreover, as the first project in which Airbus is relying principally on capital markets rather than government aid, a debacle would sour relations with investors.</p>
        <p>By the end of this year, Airbus will have to decide whether sufficient demand for the new aircraft exists to justify starting construction. Assuming it decides to go ahead, as most experts expect it will, the first test flights will be in mid-2004, and the first aircraft will be delivered in the fall of 2005.</p>
        <p>Still, big obstacles remain. For one thing, Washington is eyeing suspiciously the intention of European governments to help finance the A3XX, and the project affords the potential for a major trans-Atlantic trade war. Since Airbus started in the early 1970's, successive White Houses have objected to its financing through government loans. The Europeans counter that Pentagon spending is tantamount to a hidden subsidy to big United States aerospace contractors, including Boeing.</p>
        <p>In 1992, a compromise agreement was reached regulating aid to the industry, but both Boeing and the next president face tough decisions on whether to challenge, or perhaps even discard, the 1992 agreement if the A3XX project proceeds.</p>
        <p>But the biggest question is whether Airbus can get enough orders to make the project ultimately profitable. Airbus executives have told analysts that they must sell about 240 of the planes before turning a profit, though they will not say within what time frame. Mr. Campbell of Lehman Brothers calculates Airbus will have to sell at least 150 A3XX jetliners by 2010 for it to succeed. With Boeing offering a less expensive alternative, that is a tall order to fill.</p>
        <p>Still, many say the project makes good sense. Nine crucial customers have said they are interested, six publicly, including Emirates Airlines, Air France, Singapore Airlines, the International Lease Finance Corporation, Qantas, and Virgin Group's Virgin Atlantic. And the A3XX, while more expensive initially, would be cheaper to operate per-seat than a 747, Airbus officials say.</p>
        <p>As much as Boeing dreads the prospect, airline companies, like car buyers entering a showroom, relish the idea of having more bargaining clout. When airlines go to Boeing headquarters, said Daniel Solon, managing director of Avmark International Ltd., a London airline consultant, ''at every other category you can say, 'The other guy has such and such. What can you do for us?' ''</p>
        <p>Yet Airbus, as much as it looks forward to making itself Boeing's equal up and down the line, cannot make the decision lightly. ''It's a case of betting the company,'' said Chris Partridge, an analyst at Deutsche Bank Securities in London. ''But then, isn't that what Boeing did with the 747?''</p>
        <p>Indeed, such a huge project seems almost a natural to a Continent that brought forth the Concorde and the Channel tunnel. But at a time when governments in Europe are constrained by the fiscal requirements for the euro, the single currency introduced last year, and companies like Airbus and its shareholders rely increasingly on capital markets, it will not be easy.</p>
        <p>Noel Forgeard, the Airbus chief executive, insists the A3XX is not the huge gamble it has been portrayed. ''It's a figurehead, but it's certainly not the only project we have,'' he said in an interview at Airbus headquarters outside this southern French city. Indeed, he added, relative to the size of the company, which last year generated sales of 15.7 billion euros, or $15 billion, it is not even as ambitious as the 1990's project to develop the A320 family of wide-bodied jets.</p>
        <p>Gamble or not, the A3XX is daunting. At 239 feet, it is not much longer than the biggest 747's, but it would boast two full passenger decks, one above the other, plus a windowless third deck below that could be used for cargo or passenger services. Since the plane would be flown mostly on long-haul routes, like London to Australia or Hong Kong to Los Angeles, Airbus officials fancifully describe the possibility of installing fitness rooms, a duty free shop, even a McDonald's.</p>
        <p>They describe first-class amenities that could include sleeping berths, roomy lounges and cocktail bars -- evoking a cruise liner more than a jetliner. Some experts are skeptical, believing the temptation to squeeze in large numbers of passengers will prevail. ''In the end, it could be more steerage,'' said Avmark's Mr. Solon, ''than Queen Mary.''</p>
        <p>Despite its size, the A3XX, Airbus boasts, will not tax airports more than a 747. Though weighing 590 metric tons, 150 tons more than the biggest 747, an innovative design for the wheel carriage would spread the weight over the tarmac. Most airports will disembark passengers from one level, though newer airports like Hong Kong will be able to link passenger gangways at both upper and lower levels. At any rate, Airbus has assured airlines that the turnaround of the A3XX -- the time needed to unload passengers, cargo and baggage, and be refitted for flight -- would be no longer than the scheduled 90 minutes for the 747.</p>
        <p>For financial planners, of course, the monster is the aircraft's costs. Mr. Forgeard estimates total development costs of 10.7 billion euros, about $10.2 billion, though some experts believe the number could run as high as $20 billion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forgeard said about 4 billion euros would be raised by risk-sharing partners who would supply parts in exchange for providing financing. Another 2 billion euros will be raised with government loans, and the rest through the bond and stock markets.</p>
        <p>To convince airlines of its cost effectiveness, Airbus argues that to break even the A3XX must fill 323 of its minimum 555 seats, or only 33 more than the 747 must fill to be profitable. Yet the A3XX offers 232 more seats, compared with the 747's 123.</p>
        <p>In Washington, the Clinton administration or its successor may be tempted to bring Airbus before the World Trade Organization if American officials believe they can make the case that European governments are providing improper subsidies.  But Boeing, worrying about a backlash among its airline customers and suppliers who build for both airline makers, could be reluctant to encourage such an action. And if Washington presses the case, Airbus pledges to fight back.</p>
        <p>American companies stand to profit by supplying parts like engine supports, landing gear, evacuation systems and much of the electronics for the A3XX. If airlines choose engines from a consortium of General Electric and United Technologies' Pratt &amp; Whitney, one of two engine suppliers, American-made equipment could account for roughly one-third the value.</p>
        <p>At the end of this year the EADS board plans to decide whether to begin construction. Mr. Forgeard, a board member, said the decision would hinge as much on the quality of the orders as on their quantity. Some airlines, he said, because of their sway within the industry, ''will have more influence in terms of a domino effect.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Forgeard, clearly hinting he favors a go-ahead, says the biggest risk would be not to gamble.</p>
        <p>''What would be a real bet,'' he said, ''would be to neglect an important part of the market, or address it with programs not compatible with our resources.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 26, 2000, Wednesday  A picture credit was omitted in Business Day on July 14 with an article about Airbus Industrie's development of a double-decker jumbo jet. The picture, showing employees beneath a full-scale mock-up of the plane, was by Alain Ernoult.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 26, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture credit was omitted in Business Day on July 14 with an article about Airbus Industrie's development of a double-decker jumbo jet. The picture, showing employees beneath a full-scale mock-up of the plane, was by Alain Ernoult.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
