<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; A Blast From the Past</title>
    <meta content="14COLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Bob (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7D6163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; A Blast From the Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed column suggests that Bill Bradley went into four-month self-imposed exile before endorsing Vice Pres Al Gore for president because lying low is a way to avoid the kind of mistakes that can scuttle a vice presidential nomination; notes how Energy Sec Bill Richardson, Sen Bob Graham and Gov Christine Todd Whitman have diminished their chances for a spot on the Democratic and Republican tickets</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Gore received an endorsement yesterday from one Bill Bradley, a former basketball player. Mr. Bradley is said to have served in the United States Senate, but he seems to have spent most of this millennium in seclusion, and much about him is unknown, including the identity of his favorite book.</p>
        <p>In a brief joint appearance with Mr. Gore in Wisconsin, Mr. Bradley revealed that he had once spent 15 months running for the presidential nomination himself, in this very country. He then treated the crowd to a brief recapitulation of his old stump speech, followed by the tribute to Mr. Gore, whom he praised as a member of the Democratic Party.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Gore received an endorsement yesterday from one Bill Bradley, a former basketball player. Mr. Bradley is said to have served in the United States Senate, but he seems to have spent most of this millennium in seclusion, and much about him is unknown, including the identity of his favorite book.</p>
        <p>In a brief joint appearance with Mr. Gore in Wisconsin, Mr. Bradley revealed that he had once spent 15 months running for the presidential nomination himself, in this very country. He then treated the crowd to a brief recapitulation of his old stump speech, followed by the tribute to Mr. Gore, whom he praised as a member of the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley provided a real test for Mr. Gore's reputation as a man who can pander to anything, even an inanimate object. But the vice president delivered the goods, describing Mr. Bradley as ''an important part of America's future'' and, far more imaginatively, a ''friend.''</p>
        <p>It took four months for Mr. Bradley to work himself up to this moment. Returning from his self-imposed exile from public life, he seems like a ghost of campaigns past, somebody who once traded shots with Jimmy Carter or Estes Kefauver. Now that he's back, sort of, he'll automatically be mentioned as a potential vice-presidential candidate. It's none too soon, since we've been running through the pool rather quickly. People call this campaign boring, but when you think about it, the carnage has been quite spectacular.</p>
        <p>Remember when Bill Richardson was a favorite for the number two slot? Back in February the secretary of energy was so omnipresent in Mr. Gore's entourage you expected him to start handing out the box lunches. But that was before gasoline passed $2 a gallon and our national defense secrets turned up hidden behind an office copying machine. Now the poor man is such political dog meat, he'll be lucky if the Democrats let him watch the convention on television.</p>
        <p>And it was just a couple of months ago that Senator Bob Graham of Florida was a hot ticket, shepherding Mr. Gore around the state, introducing him at rallies while the vice president stared at Mr. Graham with rapt, Tipper-level attention. The senator had so much influence he helped prod Mr. Gore into his save-Elian-Gonzalez moment, an unprecedented triple-pander-with-splat that politicians will be gasping about for generations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham, apparently searching for a really dramatic coup to put himself back in contention, recently opened his diaries to Time magazine. It turns out that the senator writes down every single thing he does, 24-7, and has an entry to prove that on the evening in 1994 when his daughter gave birth to a son, he spent the moments between 1:30-1:45 p.m. rewinding a video of ''Ace Ventura, Pet Detective.'' He must have presumed that Mr. Gore would be particularly attracted to a potential vice president who has every move recorded in 4,000 notebooks, color-coded by season.</p>
        <p>The Republican field is getting frayed, too. Gov. Christie Todd Whitman of New Jersey crashed and burned this week, when a photo surfaced showing her frisking a black man and grinning wildly. Mrs. Whitman had apparently been riding around with some state troopers a few years back and jumped at an opportunity to play cop. This raises questions not only about Mrs. Whitman's racial sensitivity, but also her I.Q. Even the most dim-witted male politician in the universe would know what to say if he was invited to pat down a woman in the presence of a photographer.</p>
        <p>''It was a question, at that time, of being hands-on,'' said the governor defensively in a TV interview.</p>
        <p>When an elected official pretends to be hanging with the tough guys  you get Michael Dukakis driving that tank, or Rudy Giuliani and Al D'Amato dressed as Hell's Angels. Bill Bradley, whose example should definitely be followed in this matter, is so averse to funny-costume campaigning he refused to put on shorts and pretend to be a basketball player when he had a fund-raiser at Madison Square Garden with his former Knicks teammates.</p>
        <p>That event, believe it or not, took place during the very same presidential race we're having now. And when you think about it, Mr. Bradley's refusal to come out in public since he lost might just be an attempt to dodge the possible-vice-presidential-candidate curse.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
