<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan to Release Notorious Killer Prompts Debate About Insanity</title>
    <meta content="14RELE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sweeney, Dennis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Soloff, Brenda (Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lowenstein, Allard K (1929-80)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EFDF173BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1230" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan to Release Notorious Killer Prompts Debate About Insanity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Debate about treatment of the mentally ill by criminal justice system is renewed as Justice Brenda Soloff orders release of Dennis Sweeney, who was placed in psychiatric center after courts accepted his plea that he was insane when he killed former Congressman Allard Lowenstein of New York in 1980; Soloff cites Sweeney's success in living under ever looser custody and without any medication over the past six years; directs prosecutors and mental health officials to establish conditions for his release, which would include continued therapy; they object to change of status on ground it would make it harder for Sweeney to be returned to custody in the future; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 20 years ago, Dennis Sweeney began to hear the voices that eventually drove him into the Manhattan law offices of former Congressman Allard Lowenstein, where he pulled a pistol from his windbreaker and shot his former friend and mentor seven times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney, who calmly waited for the police to arrive, pleaded not responsible for the murder by reason of insanity. The state did not dispute his insanity, and he was  committed to the custody of the New York State mental health system. The killing of a well-known congressman drew headlines when it happened, but except for a few periodic news stories, Mr. Sweeney has remained in relative obscurity since 1981, a year after the shooting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 20 years ago, Dennis Sweeney began to hear the voices that eventually drove him into the Manhattan law offices of former Congressman Allard Lowenstein, where he pulled a pistol from his windbreaker and shot his former friend and mentor seven times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney, who calmly waited for the police to arrive, pleaded not responsible for the murder by reason of insanity. The state did not dispute his insanity, and he was  committed to the custody of the New York State mental health system. The killing of a well-known congressman drew headlines when it happened, but except for a few periodic news stories, Mr. Sweeney has remained in relative obscurity since 1981, a year after the shooting.</p>
        <p>But this month, Mr. Sweeney is set to be released from state custody, over the objections of both prosecutors and state mental health officials, who argued that he needed continued supervision at a psychiatric center.</p>
        <p>After reviewing a plethora of psychiatric testimony, as well as the history of Mr. Sweeney's treatment,  Justice Brenda Soloff of State Supreme Court ruled on June 30 that Mr. Sweeney, 57, no longer was in need of hospitalization. She has ordered lawyers for him and for the state to submit conditions for his release by July 27.</p>
        <p>''In discussing whether or not Dennis Sweeney currently has a mental illness requiring inpatient care and treatment, we are in large part dealing with a question which has already been answered in the negative,'' Justice Soloff wrote in her decision, which was released late yesterday afternoon.</p>
        <p>''Indeed, every issue raised comes up against that same initial stumbling block: for some six years, without medication, Dennis Sweeney has been building an ever more complex, satisfying and successful life in the community, permitted by mental health officials.''</p>
        <p>To a certain extent, the judge's decision will not cause any drastic changes in Mr. Sweeney's daily life. For the last five years, he has lived under the loose custody of the Office of Mental Health, staying in a hospital one night every two weeks from midnight to 6 a.m. If he is released, it will be under conditions; Judge Soloff said in her decision that she would expect them to include continued therapy and a prohibition on contacting certain people, including members of Mr. Lowenstein's family.</p>
        <p>But in her decision, Justice Soloff noted that prosecutors and mental health officials objected to the change in status because it would make it harder for mental health officials to return Mr. Sweeney to custody in the future.</p>
        <p>As long as he is still considered a hospital patient, Mr. Sweeney can be re-committed for violating the conditions of his confinement. But once he is released, even under conditions, mental health officials must prove that he once again poses a danger to himself or to the community before he can be institutionalized again.</p>
        <p>The treatment of the mentally ill by the criminal justice system has long been a difficult topic. From the case of John Hinckley, who shot President Ronald Reagan in 1981, to the murder of Kendra Webdale, who was pushed under a subway train in 1999 by a man who had shuttled in and out of psychiatric treatment, public outrage often follows crimes in which mental illness drives someone to sudden violence. Periodically, notorious crimes raise questions about the balance between the rights of the mentally ill and the protection of society.</p>
        <p>Experts generally agree that the insanity defense rarely succeeds, and even when it does, mentally ill defendants usually spend as much as or more time in state custody than they would have if convicted of the crime. New York State maintains varying degrees of custody over roughly 900 people confined for psychiatric care after committing criminal offenses. Richard P. Miraglia, director of the Office of Mental Health's Bureau of Forensic Services, said that the average patient spent about six years in a maximum security facility. Mr. Miraglia said that in a comparison of sentences between inmates and psychiatric patients ''for the more serious offenses, it is comparable.''</p>
        <p>The issue of releasing defendants who were once insane is an uncommon one. In a recent study for the Manhattan district attorney's office, Dr. Stuart M. Kirschner of John Jay College found that only a tiny proportion of criminal defendants ever used a psychiatric defense. Of 96,000 indicted felons between 1988 and 1997 in Manhattan, only 96 did so. Of those, only 41 succeeded.</p>
        <p>At the time of the killing, Mr. Sweeney's illness was diagnosed as paranoid schizophrenia. He met Mr. Lowenstein in 1961 as a freshman at Stanford, where Mr. Lowenstein was a dean. Mr. Lowenstein, who served as a member of the House of Representatives from 1968 to 1970, fueled his enthusiasm for social causes, and Mr. Sweeney traveled to the South to take part in civil rights campaigns.</p>
        <p>But because of his illness, in later years he began to believe that Mr. Lowenstein was part of a Jewish cabal that had tormented him by sending messages through his dental work. Mr. Sweeney sought psychiatric treatment, but his illness worsened, leading him to remove his bridgework with a hacksaw, and eventually to shoot Mr. Lowenstein.</p>
        <p>After the shooting, he was committed to the Mid-Hudson Psychiatric Center, the state's maximum security psychiatric hospital. He remained there for eight years.</p>
        <p>As psychiatrists gradually relaxed the conditions of his confinement, Mr. Sweeney was transferred to the Middletown Psychiatric Center, which is not a high-security hospital. He was able to work in the community and was released on furloughs for increasing amounts of time.</p>
        <p>Since 1992, he has held a series of jobs in the area. He has been a cabinetmaker and a woodworker, managed a woodworking store and now works as what the judge described as an employment specialist. According to Justice Soloff's decision, Mr. Sweeney does not take psychiatric medication, but does undergo regular therapy.</p>
        <p>For the last five years, Mr. Sweeney has lived under the most relaxed confinement possible. Although he is still considered a full-time patient, he reports to the hospital for only one night every two weeks.</p>
        <p>In her ruling, Justice Soloff reviewed the conditions of Mr. Sweeney's confinement and found that he ''is an inpatient in name only.'' The judge said that she based her decision on the testimony of psychiatric experts for the state and for Mr. Sweeney, and that the evidence supported his release.</p>
        <p>''My own observation of Mr. Sweeney showed me a very different person from the nearly affectless person of 14 years ago,'' Judge Soloff wrote. ''This Mr. Sweeney was engaged, responsive and, especially given the circumstances of having to listen to days of testimony about himself and to testify and be cross-examined, remarkably poised.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday evening, members of Mr. Lowenstein's family declined an interview, but released a statement though their lawyer, Thomas Engel.</p>
        <p>''We are obviously disappointed with the court's decision in light of the strong case presented by the district attorney and the state commissioner of mental health,'' the family said. ''Whatever the eventual outcome of these proceedings, nothing can or will change what happened 20 years ago.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
