<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Convention Eve, Beating Mars Image of Philadelphia</title>
    <meta content="14PHIL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Timoney, John F (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E3DF173BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Convention Eve, Beating Mars Image of Philadelphia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Philadelphia, which has been preparing itself as showcase venue for Republican National Convention next month, suffers ignominy of seeing its police on nationally televised videotape beating and kicking black man following car chase; taped images are dampening civic pride in city that has been hailing its own renaissance, and reviving old images of a tough city where police behavior had to be federally monitored; Police Commissioner John F Timoney warns against 'rush to judgment'; black leaders, noting that both white and black police were involved in beating, contend incident was one of brutality more than racism toward suspect, Thomas Jones; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All decked out in bunting and civic pride for the forthcoming Republican National Convention, this city today suffered the ignominy of seeing its police on national television beating and kicking a man accused of stealing a police car and shooting at an officer during a running gun battle through the streets.</p>
        <p>''Welcome, America!'' The Philadelphia Daily News proclaimed to the approaching conventioneers on its front page, above a photograph of the man being pummeled by a group of eight or nine police officers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All decked out in bunting and civic pride for the forthcoming Republican National Convention, this city today suffered the ignominy of seeing its police on national television beating and kicking a man accused of stealing a police car and shooting at an officer during a running gun battle through the streets.</p>
        <p>''Welcome, America!'' The Philadelphia Daily News proclaimed to the approaching conventioneers on its front page, above a photograph of the man being pummeled by a group of eight or nine police officers.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for city leaders who have been anxiously preparing a showcase venue for Republican delegates arriving at the end of the month, the arrest and beating was recorded by hovering TV news helicopters. The tapes were replayed across America as an image of this city that threatened to be more definitive than any red, white and blue balloon drop.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, the videotape doesn't look good, any fool will admit that,'' said Police Commissioner John F. Timoney, who resented as ''inflammatory'' any comparison to the videotaped 1991 clubbing of Rodney J. King that traumatized the nation and scandalized the Los Angeles Police Department.</p>
        <p>Mr. Timoney, a former deputy commissioner in the New York Police Department, warned against a ''rush to judgment,'' saying the man had stolen a police officer's gun and shot him and repeatedly resisted being brought to the ground during a mile-long chase.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department announced that it would review videotapes for evidence of excessive police force. The image on the tapes dampened civic pride in a city that has been hailing its own renaissance, and revived old images of a tough city where police behavior had to be federally monitored.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia's vibrant renewal as a convention city has been widely acclaimed as a triumph over some dark history where a past mayor, Frank Rizzo, personally packed a club in his law-and-order photo opportunities and another, W. Wilson Goode, ordered the police bombing of barricaded protesters, with fatal results and disastrous notoriety.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately this incident may be used by some elements of the protest movement to look at our police department as much more brutal than it actually is,'' said Stefan Presser, legal director of the state American Civil Liberties Union, referring to the anticipated thousands of protesters who plan to demonstrate during the Republican convention, which runs from July 31 through Aug. 3.</p>
        <p>''We saw the situation in Seattle where people with legal protest permits had their march hijacked by others intent on violence, and that's where there's a certain edginess growing right now,'' said Mr. Presser, who in the past decade engaged in various legal challenges to the Philadelphia police and said he found their behavior clearly improving.</p>
        <p>Prominent blacks, noting that white and black police were taped in the beating, contended that the incident was one of brutality more than racism toward the arrested man, who is black.</p>
        <p>''This comes out of a history of violence and brutality in this department for 30 years,'' said J. Whyatt Mondesire, president of the Philadelphia chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.</p>
        <p>In a brief comment while campaigning in Pittsburgh, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, who is to be formally nominated at the Philadelphia convention, said, ''Obviously we've got to take these incidents very seriously.'' But he reserved further comment, as did Republican convention officials who had eagerly selected this overwhelmingly Democratic city after seeing firsthand the evidence of its downtown renewal.</p>
        <p>Gov. Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania, who had urged his fellow Republicans to ''go into nontraditional constituencies'' for the Philadelphia convention, said that while a key 20-second tape was ''a pretty horrible sight,'' it was important to study all of the earlier parts of the chase for a full understanding of the police officers' intensity.</p>
        <p>David L. Cohen, the co-chairman of the city's convention host committee, said a full investigation would show that the police were dealing with a shifting, dangerous situation and that the city's chief officials would tolerate ''no whitewash'' of any excesses.</p>
        <p>''Is this something we think is going to put a stain on Philadelphia? No,'' Mr. Cohen said. ''It's not a blight on the city at the dawn of the convention.''</p>
        <p>A bit of preconvention edginess was discernible even before the beating incident. The City Council, prompted by the violent street demonstrations during sessions of the World Trade Organization meeting in Seattle in December, recently passed an ordinance making it illegal for protesters to wear masks and bandanas with the intent of intimidating the public. And, amid media speculation about the potential for mass arrests, the police said that, if necessary for processing detainees, they would consider reopening the notorious Holmesburg prison, a century-old bastion that was closed five years ago as unusable.</p>
        <p>The edginess grew as planners of protest demonstrations complained that law enforcement surveillance agents had been snooping about routine meetings and photographing them on the streets.</p>
        <p>''It's so silly,'' said Jody Dodd, an organizer with the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, who said the group's plans for strictly nonviolent street protest were already public knowledge on the Internet. Ms. Dodd said the tape of the police beating ''can't help but have a lingering effect in the back of people's minds,'' possibly for the better. ''It behooves the police now to act with great restraint and conduct themselves in the best light,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mayor John F. Street emphasized that there was much more to the chase than the final scene. ''As inflammatory as this tape might be,'' Mayor Street said, ''we have to keep in mind that the police were in the process of apprehending a criminal suspect who had resisted a number of attempts to arrest him and who had shot a police officer.''</p>
        <p>The police said the suspect, 30-year-old Thomas Jones, sped off through north Philadelphia after being stopped for driving a stolen car. Mr. Jones crashed the car and fled on foot, witnesses said, before he was tackled by the police. In a scuffle, the 6-foot-tall, 240-pound man grabbed an officer's gun and began shooting, witnesses and the police said. Then, they said, he jumped into a nearby empty patrol car.</p>
        <p>Officer Michael Livewell was shot in the hand, the police said, while trying to stop the man, who was wounded but fled in the patrol car. Dozens of shots were fired in the chase before the man was cornered at 26th and Oxford Streets.</p>
        <p>At this point, the tapes show the car below, its windows blown out. As police warily approach with drawn guns they seize Mr. Jones as he emerges from the car and is surrounded and wrestled down in a flurry of kicks and punches. Mr. Jones was in fair condition today, handcuffed to a hospital bed after being treated for five bullet wounds.</p>
        <p>The police said records showed that Mr. Jones was an ex-convict whose earlier convictions included robbery, assault and an attempt to run over a police officer while fleeing arrest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
