<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Wimbledon, the Lawn Needs Mowing</title>
    <meta content="14PROF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Paul Annacone</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annacone, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sampras, Pete</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E3DA163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Wimbledon, the Lawn Needs Mowing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Annacone relaxes with his children in East Hampton after an exhausting eight-week European tour as coach of Pete Sampras, culminating with Wimbledon title; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sign by the door instructs visitors to Go Away. The sign by the doorbell offers reassurance, in French, that the linebacker-sized Labrador retriever inside this quirky Hamptons household -- in the backyard, a bionic Barbie doll guards the pool in her birthday suit -- is a pushover. Do signs lie?</p>
        <p>There is no sign -- beyond the heap of tennis sneakers by the doormat -- of Paul Annacone. But we know he's home in East Hampton after the exhausting eight-week European road trip that culminated Sunday at Wimbledon. There, Pete Sampras, the player Mr. Annacone has coached and counseled for five years, rearranged the tennis record books yet again and became the first man in his sport's history to capture 13 Grand Slam singles titles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sign by the door instructs visitors to Go Away. The sign by the doorbell offers reassurance, in French, that the linebacker-sized Labrador retriever inside this quirky Hamptons household -- in the backyard, a bionic Barbie doll guards the pool in her birthday suit -- is a pushover. Do signs lie?</p>
        <p>There is no sign -- beyond the heap of tennis sneakers by the doormat -- of Paul Annacone. But we know he's home in East Hampton after the exhausting eight-week European road trip that culminated Sunday at Wimbledon. There, Pete Sampras, the player Mr. Annacone has coached and counseled for five years, rearranged the tennis record books yet again and became the first man in his sport's history to capture 13 Grand Slam singles titles.</p>
        <p>It was, Mr. Annacone will say, 10 days of an injured Mr. Sampras torturing himself and everyone else within scowling distance, opponents included. But here in his backyard is proof that all's well that ends well.</p>
        <p>A smiling (finally!) Mr. Annacone is winding down from Wimbledon with Barbie, who has been strategically placed in a lounge chair by his good-humored wife, Tracy, and who occasionally gets tossed into the pool by his two children: they get a charge out of giving her bad hair days. Mr. Annacone, 37, gets a charge out of whatever they do.</p>
        <p>The time he spends away from them, 26 to 30 weeks a season, is the only downside to his travels and tribulations alongside Mr. Sampras.</p>
        <p>But today the kids are underfoot and Mr. Annacone is in Nike-issued tennis duds, soaking up the sun, with Moby crooning on the outdoor speakers and a cell phone snuggled to his ear. Mr. Sampras is on the line again, relaying the progress of the tendinitis-inflamed ankle that provoked Mr. Annacone, and two London doctors, to implore him to abort at Wimbledon. (The tennis star ignored the advice he pays for and played on. Call it champion's instinct. Or stubbornness. Mr. Annacone calls it both.)</p>
        <p>On Sunday a ''numb'' Mr. Annacone watched Mr. Sampras prevail, then break down and cry with relief, after setting a most-unlikely-to-be-broken record on the most famous patch of grass in the world. They briefly attended Wimbledon's traditional ball, then stayed up most of the night talking and watching television replays. Mr. Annacone had been asleep for 90 minutes when his telephone jingled at 6 a.m.: an insomnia-plagued Mr. Sampras was thinking about walking to the corner to fetch the morning papers.</p>
        <p>''Can you walk?'' asked the coach. ''Uh, not really,'' said his aching player. ''I'll be over in 10 minutes,'' said Mr. Annacone. And he was. With the newspapers. All part of the job description.</p>
        <p>''The whole relationship is an oxymoron,'' Mr. Annacone insists. ''The athlete pays you to tell him he's being lazy, or whatever, but if he doesn't like what he hears, he can fire you. The thing of it is to tell him what you want him to do in a way that he needs to hear it. It's a whole philosophy thing.'' Thank God for those three years of sociology courses at Tennessee (when your father is superintendent of schools in Sag Harbor, education is not optional). And thank God Mr. Sampras isn't the firing type.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes he looks at me like I have three heads,'' Mr. Annacone says, ''but don't think I don't know I've got the best job in tennis. Pete's big cliche is that winning solves everything, and most of the time, he's right.''</p>
        <p>Now, barely 48 hours after the victory flight home -- Mr. Sampras booked the Concorde, of course -- Mr. Annacone is back to a different reality in his hometown: the patch of grass that surrounds him is the one he's expected to mow. O.K., he'll get to it. And right around the corner at the Paul Annacone Tennis Camp (Mr. Annacone left home at 14 to attend Nick Bollettieri's Florida tennis academy) are dozens of eager ball-strikers just waiting for him to turn them into Sampras clones. Impossible.</p>
        <p>Your kids can try to emulate him, Mr. Annacone tells the parents of his little campers, but don't get delusional. The way he views it, Mr. Sampras ''is a freak of nature. He's going to be great whether I'm coaching him or my wife is.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Annacone's decade on the professional tour was ending in ho-hum fashion -- 3 singles titles, 14 doubles titles, $1.6 million in the bank and a ruptured disk in his back -- when fate threw in his lot with that of Mr. Sampras, whose coach received a diagnosis of brain cancer in 1995.</p>
        <p>Mr. Annacone had just lost at the 1995 Australian Open and was packing his bags when his friend Tim Gullikson, Mr. Sampras's ailing coach, asked him to play surrogate and keep an eye on Mr. Sampras while he flew home for medical tests. Mr. Annacone also assumed the role of confidant for the distraught Mr. Sampras: ''I lost one of my best friends to leukemia when I was 19,'' Mr. Annacone recalls. ''It was a big dose of reality, but it helped me convey to Pete what Tim was going through.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gullikson died 16 months later, Mr. Annacone's job as interim coach turned permanent. Or permanent until Mr. Sampras retires, which, if his body holds up, is not supposed to occur for four or five years. Meantime, Mr. Annacone continues to tinker with his serve -- a bullet into the returner's body is his latest trick -- and tinker with his attitude toward the French Open, the only Grand Slam tournament to thwart him. Mr. Annacone is convinced there's a French Open in the Sampras resume.</p>
        <p>But then, Mr. Annacone is a progressive thinker. He's even thought ahead to life after Mr. Sampras. You see, there's this 15-year-old American prospect. . . .</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
