<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Getty Acquires A New Old Master</title>
    <meta content="14INSI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mercer House (Savannah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Getty, J Paul, Museum (Los Angeles)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hirshhorn Museum (Washington, DC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Gallery of Art (Washington, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">El Greco (Domenikos Theotokopoulos) (1541-1614)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cropper, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brougher, Kerry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ross, Katherine</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D61F38F937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1265" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Getty Acquires A New Old Master</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inside Art column; Getty Museum buys El Greco painting Christ on the Cross at Sotheby's London for $5.8 million; photo; contents of Mercer House, Savannah mansion from book and movie Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil, will be auctioned at Sotheby's in October; Elizabeth Cropper becomes dean at Center for Advanced Study in Visual Arts at National Gallery; Kerry Brougher of Modern Museum in Oxford is named chief curator at Hirshhorn Museum; Sotheby's executive Katherine Ross resigns (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The J. Paul Getty Museum in Los Angeles had its eye on several paintings at the old master auctions in London last week. It ended up buying an El Greco.</p>
        <p>Four bidders at Sotheby's on July 6 fought over ''Christ on the Cross,'' a haunting image of Jesus set against a dark background of swirling clouds. The Getty ended up buying it for $5.8 million, a record for the artist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The J. Paul Getty Museum in Los Angeles had its eye on several paintings at the old master auctions in London last week. It ended up buying an El Greco.</p>
        <p>Four bidders at Sotheby's on July 6 fought over ''Christ on the Cross,'' a haunting image of Jesus set against a dark background of swirling clouds. The Getty ended up buying it for $5.8 million, a record for the artist.</p>
        <p>While many experts thought the museum paid too much, Scott Schaefer, the Getty's curator of paintings, said he believed the work was ''the best version of that composition and entirely by the artist.'' The painting is also ''the first important El Greco to enter the collection of a Los Angeles museum,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Few paintings can be attributed to El Greco with certainty, and when Sotheby's had this work cleaned before it went on sale, his signature became clearly visible at the foot of the cross. The painting also relates closely to others by him, especially in the manner in which he painted Jesus' attenuated body hanging from the cross with his head and his eyes looking toward heaven.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schaefer bid by telephone to George Wachter, director of old master paintings for Sotheby's worldwide. For a museum to bid through an auction house executive is rare. Most museums ask a dealer to bid for them and try to keep their interest secret, fearing that if word gets out, collectors will be even more eager to buy the work, increasing not only the competition but also the price.</p>
        <p>''We choose to bid in different ways,'' said Mr. Schaefer, who worked for Mr. Wachter at Sotheby's in New York before joining the Getty. His museum also bid on de Troy's ''Retour de Bal,'' which was up for sale at Phillips on July 4. The painting ended up selling to Konrad O. Bernheimer, a London dealer, for $3.6 million.</p>
        <p>Asked why the Getty did not bid higher for the de Troy, Mr. Schaefer said, ''The problem when a museum buys at auction is that we have to get approval on the price in advance.'' In this case, he added, he did not think the painting was worth the selling price.</p>
        <p>Sale in the Garden of Good . . .</p>
        <p>Those who read ''Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil'' or saw the movie will remember Mercer House, the 19th-century Italianate mansion in the heart of Savannah, Ga. The house, which fills a city block, was built for Hugh Mercer, a Civil War general who settled in Savannah in 1835 and was a great-grandfather of the songwriter Johnny Mercer. It was also the scene of the 1981 shooting of 21-year-old Danny Hansford, the young lover of Jim Williams, who owned the house then. Williams, who died in 1990, was an antiques dealer known for his unusual collection.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 20 Sotheby's is to auction the contents of Mercer House in a sale that will range from English furniture and export porcelain to a marble bust of King Edward VII and a sword said to have been owned by Napoleon II. Sotheby's estimates the sale will total more than $1.5 million.</p>
        <p>The estimate is low, in part because of the objects' decorative nature and in part because the auction house tends to undervalue objects in house sales purposely. But that isn't stopping Sotheby's from treating this as a celebrity sale. As the auction house did for the four-day sale of the Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis estate in 1996 or the 1998 auction of the contents of the Paris villa that once belonged to the Duke and Duchess of Windsor, it will recreate the rooms in Mercer House in its York Avenue galleries.</p>
        <p>''It's a Southern gentleman's view of the Grand Tour,'' said Ronald D. Varney, a senior vice president in Sotheby's trusts and estates department. The Southern gentleman was Williams, who was tried four times in Hansford's murder and ultimately acquitted.</p>
        <p>''His taste was showy, but he had a good eye,'' said John Berendt, author of ''Midnight in the Garden of Good and Evil.'' ''He went for objects with a noble if not royal provenance.''</p>
        <p>Williams left the house and its contents to his mother, who left it to her daughter, Dorothy Williams Kingery. (All Williams had left his sister in his will was $10, his papers and the rights to ''Psycho Dice,'' a game he invented.) But now that Ms. Kingery owns the house and its contents, she has decided to keep some things for herself, including an oil sketch by John Singer Sargent that was estimated at $125,000 to $175,000 when it was was originally listed with the objects Sotheby's was planning to sell. (People in Savannah familiar with the work say they believe it was withdrawn from the sale over a question of authenticity.)</p>
        <p>But there are still many curiosities left for Sotheby's to auction. Among the highlights is the 19th-century Yusupov Dagger, mounted in silver gilt and turquoise, thought to have been worn and used in the assassination of the Russian monk Rasputin. Williams bought the dagger at auction at Sotheby's in 1987 for $15,400, nearly twice its high estimate of $8,000. This time Sotheby's experts have not decided on an estimate. Also for sale is a leather desk folio, mounted on silver gilt and enamel, with the monogram ''N II,'' made for Czar Nicholas II. Mr. Williams bought the folio at Sotheby's in 1979 for $16,500. Today it is estimated at $20,000 to $30,000. An ormolu armorial coach fitting dating from 1810, used for Napoleon's coronation in 1804, will also be auctioned. One of a pair (the other is in the Philadelphia Atheneum), it is expected to fetch $20,000 to $30,000.</p>
        <p>For more than a year Mercer House has been on the market through Sotheby's International Realty and Cora Bett Thomas Realty. The price was $8.95 million, but it has been re</p>
        <p>duced to about $7 million, Mr. Varney said.</p>
        <p>Add Two in Washington</p>
        <p>Two Washington museums announced appointments this week. Elizabeth Cropper will become dean of the Center for Advanced Study in the Visual Arts at the National Gallery of Art. Ms. Cropper, professor of art history at Johns Hopkins University, is replacing Henry A. Millon, who will retire in December.</p>
        <p>Kerry Brougher, director of the Museum of Modern Art in Oxford, England, has been named chief curator of the Hirshhorn Museum and Sculpture Garden at the Smithsonian Institution. He succeeds Neal Benezra, who left the Hirshhorn in January to become deputy director and curator of modern and contemporary art at the Art Institute of Chicago.</p>
        <p>Subtract One at Sotheby's</p>
        <p>The number of veterans leaving Sotheby's keeps growing. The latest is Katherine Ross, who has been at the auction house for 16 years, most recently as a senior vice president and director of museum services in New York. She has been named senior vice president for public relations and communications at Prada, the fashion company, where she will oversee publicity and special events.</p>
        <p>INSIDE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
