<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recalling the Smell of Love and Being Totally Out of Touch</title>
    <meta content="14FIVE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Podeswa, Jeremy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Five Senses, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E6D61F38F937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recalling the Smell of Love and Being Totally Out of Touch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews movie The Five Senses, written and directed by Jeremy Podeswa; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The Five Senses'' engages the sense of sight. The director, Jeremy Podeswa, gives the picture the warm darkness of autumn, with shadows drifting through the scenes like lost thoughts. It's too bad narrative isn't a sense; the attempt to deal with each of the senses here is so schematic that the movie drifts just like those shadows.</p>
        <p>The most enjoyable scenes are those between Rona (Mary-Louise Parker, who, with her suggestive lower lip and brimming, clear eyes, looks like Mary Tyler Moore with all the primness ironed out) and her best friend, Robert (Daniel MacIvor), cattily going over the pitfalls of relationships. Their sense of smell is involved because they think most relationships stink. Robert also thinks he can smell love, which is why he is meeting with his former lovers, male and female, to determine if any have true feelings for him. He wants to meet Rona's current lover, an Italian chef (Marco Leonardi) with whom she had a fling while on vacation in Europe. And although they have no language in common -- no spoken language, anyway -- he is about to move in with her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The Five Senses'' engages the sense of sight. The director, Jeremy Podeswa, gives the picture the warm darkness of autumn, with shadows drifting through the scenes like lost thoughts. It's too bad narrative isn't a sense; the attempt to deal with each of the senses here is so schematic that the movie drifts just like those shadows.</p>
        <p>The most enjoyable scenes are those between Rona (Mary-Louise Parker, who, with her suggestive lower lip and brimming, clear eyes, looks like Mary Tyler Moore with all the primness ironed out) and her best friend, Robert (Daniel MacIvor), cattily going over the pitfalls of relationships. Their sense of smell is involved because they think most relationships stink. Robert also thinks he can smell love, which is why he is meeting with his former lovers, male and female, to determine if any have true feelings for him. He wants to meet Rona's current lover, an Italian chef (Marco Leonardi) with whom she had a fling while on vacation in Europe. And although they have no language in common -- no spoken language, anyway -- he is about to move in with her.</p>
        <p>''The Five Senses'' is centered on a single office building where Rona is a baker. On another floor is an ophthalmologist (Pascale Bussieres), who is going deaf and wants to re-experience the sounds that have brought him comfort before he completely loses his hearing. Down the hall from him is Ruth (Gabrielle Rose), a masseuse who is totally out of touch with her teenage daughter, Rachel (Nadia Litz). When the very young child of one of her clients disappears while in her daughter's care, their rocky relationship is further disrupted.</p>
        <p>The film deals with urban alienation: all its characters are out of touch and having a hard time communicating except on the shallowest levels. Each character is estranged from the world and has a hard time trusting others.</p>
        <p>But by interweaving several stories, the movie suffers from a peculiar multiplier effect: it deepens its shallowness. The vanished-child subplot, a dreary melodrama, almost derails a movie that is too diffuse for its own good anyway. And as a metaphor for loss, this plot element brings added strain to a movie that's almost all metaphor.</p>
        <p>The Rona-and-Robert scenes (the names of all the major characters start with R) have a prickly zest. Ms. Parker's squirminess radiates unsureness; she can often seem like a little girl trying to get comfortable in a grown woman's body, and the shifting translates into a physical manifestation of neurosis. Mr. MacIvor's character is an eager busybody whose discomfort comes from involving himself in his own life. There is more going on with these characters than with the others because they are talking to each other, and their inability to assess themselves is a more satisfying version of the ideas that Mr. Podeswa, who also wrote the script, is pushing to get across elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Yet the film's smaller moments last. Rachel is lured into a park by a boy (Brendan Fletcher), and the charge that these two misfits get from their voyeurism -- watching a couple make out in the park is almost presexual -- is a boon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Podeswa shows some talent with his actors, but there is too much underplayed sobriety, a deliberate quality that may strike some as nuance but is more like politeness filling in for anomie. What he wants to do in ''The Five Senses'' is show residents of a city, members of a community -- as represented by the building -- as being so wrapped up in themselves that they've lost the capacity for simple stimulation. This is overarticulated in a scene in which Mr. Bussieres is instructed in smaller joys by a heart-of-gold hooker with a deaf child. If all compromises were worked out as easily as they are in this movie, there would be no need for drama.</p>
        <p>''The Five Senses'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes strong language, sexual content and child endangerment.</p>
        <p>THE FIVE SENSES</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Jeremy Podeswa; director of photography, Gregory Middleton; edited by Wiebke Von Carolsfeld; music by Alexina Louie and Alex Pauk; production designer, Taavo Soodor; produced by Mr. Podeswa and Camelia Frieberg; released by Fine Line Features. Running time: 105 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Mary-Louise Parker (Rona), Molly Parker (Anna Miller), Daniel MacIvor (Robert), Gabrielle Rose (Ruth), Philippe Volter (Richard), Marco Leonardi (Roberto), Pascale Bussieres (Gail), Nadia Litz (Rachel) and Brendan Fletcher (Rupert).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
