<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese Bankruptcy Stirs Wider Doubts on Economy</title>
    <meta content="Y14SOG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nikkei Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sogo Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DB163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese Bankruptcy Stirs Wider Doubts on Economy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Collapse of Sogo Co, department store operator that owed more than $17 billion, casts dark cloud over business activities in Japan and resurrects anxieties about fragilities in Japan's economy; benchmark Nikkei stock market falls 1.76 percent as investors seek to protect themselves from potential fallout from Sogo's bankruptcy filing; ruling Liberal Democratic Party says Financial Reconstruction Commission, government agency responsible for overhauling debt-ridden financial system, is responsible for bankruptcy; Sogo has been in deep trouble since April; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The collapse of the Sogo Company, a department store operator that owed more than $17 billion, has cast a dark cloud over business activities here and resurrected anxieties about the fragilities in Japan's economy.</p>
        <p>The benchmark Nikkei stock index fell 1.76 percent today, as investors sought to protect themselves from the potential fallout from Sogo's bankruptcy filing on Wednesday. Even the currency and bond markets, typically indifferent to the travails of individual Japanese companies, seemed uneasy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The collapse of the Sogo Company, a department store operator that owed more than $17 billion, has cast a dark cloud over business activities here and resurrected anxieties about the fragilities in Japan's economy.</p>
        <p>The benchmark Nikkei stock index fell 1.76 percent today, as investors sought to protect themselves from the potential fallout from Sogo's bankruptcy filing on Wednesday. Even the currency and bond markets, typically indifferent to the travails of individual Japanese companies, seemed uneasy.</p>
        <p>Politicians and bureaucrats sought to blame one another for the ham-handed way in which Sogo's bankruptcy, one of the biggest in Japan, came about and the uncomfortable financial issues its demise might force them to confront.</p>
        <p>The ruling Liberal Democratic Party laid responsibility for the bankruptcy on the Financial Reconstruction Commission, the government agency responsible for overhauling Japan's debt-ridden financial system. ''Regarding debt relief procedures in the future, the Financial Reconstruction Commission should be more cautious,'' said Hidenao Nakagawa, chief cabinet secretary and ruling-party spokesman.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, the commission announced that 97 billion yen of taxpayer money, or $892 million at today's rates, would be spent as part of a rescue plan to reduce Sogo's debt. This set the retailer back on its feet but incited a rare burst of public fury that forced politicians to call off the deal on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Reconstruction commission officials rejected Mr. Nakagawa's accusation. ''That's easy for him to say,'' a commission official remarked. ''He would be just as upset if we had let Sogo fail right from the start.''</p>
        <p>Sogo, which operates 25 department stores in Japan and employs 10,000 people, has been in deep trouble since April, when it urged its banks to forgive 631.9 billion yen, or nearly $6 billion, in outstanding debt, a legacy of speculative borrowing in Japan's boom years a decade ago.</p>
        <p>But Shinsei Bank, a Sogo creditor with its own history of financial crisis, objected to Sogo's request. Shinsei, which a group of foreign investors led by Ripplewood Holdings of New York bought from the government last year, not only refused to forgive any debt, but also refused to cast itself as the bank responsible for Sogo's demise. Instead, Shinsei's foreign owners exercised a provision in their purchase agreement that forces the government to take responsibility for loans that have soured since they acquired the bank.</p>
        <p>There was some speculation today that the indirect role of Shinsei's owners in the Sogo collapse would arouse resentment. Foreign ownership of Japanese banks is still relatively rare.</p>
        <p>Ronald Bevacqua, senior economist at Commerz Securities here, said, ''I think that in some quarters this is going to reinforce the idea of, well, we shouldn't have sold an important institution to people who won't play the game our way,''</p>
        <p>But the failure of Sogo raises even more painful, pointed issues for a country where hard questions are typically deferred.</p>
        <p>How can politicians allow legions of debt-laden construction companies that are their biggest supporters to suffer the same fate as Sogo? Shinsei is also a major lender to the Hazama Corporation, which has already asked for debt forgiveness, and other general contractors are suffering, too.</p>
        <p>Can the Japanese economy withstand a flood of bankruptcies? Japan is nurturing what it hopes is a fledgling economic recovery, but a big increase in bankruptcies could derail that by increasing unemployment, forcing fire sales of assets, eroding confidence and pushing the banking system toward new crisis.</p>
        <p>''It's scary,'' said Minoru Nakano, an analyst who has been following Sogo at Teikoku Data Bank, a credit research and monitoring company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nakano said he thought the ruling party was trying to position itself to avoid the fallout from more big bankruptcies, not to stop them from happening. He noted that the Liberal Democrats assigned the construction ministry, long the primary source of party power, to a member of a coalition party, Chikage Ogi, after the June elections.</p>
        <p>''This construction minister is not a member of the ruling party, and that says the ruling party does not want to exert its influence over the industry,'' he said. ''The Liberal Democrats do not want to be involved right now.''</p>
        <p>How big an impact a series of bankruptcies might have on the banking system is unclear. Many banks have set aside reserves to cover potential losses.</p>
        <p>The Industrial Bank of Japan was Sogo's biggest creditor, having lent 380 billion yen, or roughly $3.5 billion. But it said today that while it might have to write off 235.6 billion yen of those loans, the bankruptcy would have no impact on its bottom line. Asahi Bank said it might lose 47.8 billion yen, or $440 million, but that this would not affect its profit.</p>
        <p>Analysts worry that the banks may have underestimated the extent of the losses they could be forced to absorb. Many considered the Financial Reconstruction Commission's planned rescue of Sogo as little more than a bank bailout in disguise. ''If they do allow these companies to collapse,'' an economist said, ''it will precipitate a second banking crisis. The public is going to pay for this one way or the other.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
