<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Neagle Is Scheduled To Start on Monday</title>
    <meta content="14PINS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neagle, Denny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E7DD173BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Neagle Is Scheduled To Start on Monday</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Left-hander Denny Neagle will join New York Yankees (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The corner locker that once belonged to Darryl Strawberry and then Jim Leyritz was empty yesterday, other than a uniform draped on a hanger, No. 41. The blue nameplate, with white lettering, read NEAGLE.</p>
        <p>The left-hander Denny Neagle will join the Yankees today and pitch Monday against the Philadelphia Phillies at Yankee Stadium. Between his arrival and the departure of left fielder Shane Spencer, who will have reconstructive surgery on his right knee next Friday, the Yankees' locker assignments, pitching staff and lineup are all going through changes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The corner locker that once belonged to Darryl Strawberry and then Jim Leyritz was empty yesterday, other than a uniform draped on a hanger, No. 41. The blue nameplate, with white lettering, read NEAGLE.</p>
        <p>The left-hander Denny Neagle will join the Yankees today and pitch Monday against the Philadelphia Phillies at Yankee Stadium. Between his arrival and the departure of left fielder Shane Spencer, who will have reconstructive surgery on his right knee next Friday, the Yankees' locker assignments, pitching staff and lineup are all going through changes.</p>
        <p>Dwight Gooden, who pitched five solid innings last Saturday against the Mets, will move to the bullpen and pitch in long relief. The Yankees have an agreement with Gooden that he will return to the minors if they ask, but they have no plans to do that.</p>
        <p>Ryan Thompson, 32, was called up from Class AAA to replace Spencer in left field and went 1 for 4 with two runs batted in in last night's 11-9 loss to Florida. Thompson actually retired at the end of spring training but agreed to play Class AAA in May and slugged 20 home runs in 247 at-bats, including 11 homers after June 20.</p>
        <p>Thompson was once seen as a can't-miss prospect, considered the best of two youngsters the Mets acquired from Toronto for David Cone in 1992; the other was second baseman Jeff Kent. Robert Thompson, the outfielder's father, keeps a collection of clippings from his son's career, and every so often, Ryan Thompson will glance through the articles, read things he said and shake his head.</p>
        <p>One story portrayed the day when Thompson had a good game at the plate and wore a Superman T-shirt afterward. At the time, he said he could fly.</p>
        <p>''I crashed,'' Thompson said yesterday. ''I crashed and burned.''</p>
        <p>Thompson has had only 42 at-bats in the majors since 1995. He will get the first chance to replace Spencer, an opportunity that could last three months or, in effect, three days.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully he can get a couple of hits and be part of the equation,'' said Joe Torre, the Yankees' manager. ''This is audition time here.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees continue to search for potential trade targets for left field.</p>
        <p>Mendoza Throws on the Side</p>
        <p>Ramiro Mendoza, the Yankees' right-hander, threw about 45 pitches in the bullpen yesterday and could be ready to return from the disabled list in about 10 days, after a few more workouts and a rehabilitation assignment in the minors. Torre has not explicitly said that Mendoza is going to be switched from the rotation to the bullpen, in case there are injuries or circumstances that require Mendoza to remain a starter.</p>
        <p>But the math is simple. Neagle gives the Yankees five veteran starters besides Mendoza and Gooden, and Mendoza is most likely headed to the bullpen.</p>
        <p>''I like starting,'' said Mendoza, ''but that's the decision of the manager, and I respect that.''</p>
        <p>Wilcox Is Recalled</p>
        <p>The Yankees promoted outfielder Luke Wilcox from Class AAA Columbus yesterday. Wilcox gives the Yankees 14 position players in addition to their 11 pitchers. Neagle is not on the Yankees' 25-man roster but will be added today. The Yankees sent Craig Dingman to Class AAA Columbus after the game.</p>
        <p>Clay Bellinger, the infielder, can be promoted to the majors again on Sunday after having spent the minimum 10 days in the minors. Wilcox will then be sent back down.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees are expected to begin negotiations in earnest with DENNY NEAGLE next week, talks that could result in a deal similar to the four-year $36 million contract signed by Minnesota's BRAD RADKE. . . . WILY MO PENA, one of the Yankees' top outfield prospects, damaged cartilage in his knee playing a minor league game Wednesday, and is most likely out for the season. Yankees General Manager BRIAN CASHMAN said that infielder GARY WINROW collided with Pena chasing a pop fly. Pena was placed on the 60-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
