<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Bush, Texas Deficit Becomes Issue in Race</title>
    <meta content="Y14TEX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000715T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE STATE BUDGET"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5D8163BF937A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Bush, Texas Deficit Becomes Issue in Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore blames Gov George W Bush for $610 million budget deficit facing Texas, saying Bush puts politically popular tax cuts ahead of paying for Medicaid and other state services; Bush says earlier state surpluses made tax cuts the right thing to do; lawmakers in Texas also disagree on where responsibility for shortfall lies, and there are predictions of future belt-tightening (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the past few years, Texas has enjoyed such a booming economy that any news about the state budget has usually been good. So when state lawmakers this week announced a $610 million shortfall, the bad news came as a surprise and prompted a pregnant political question:</p>
        <p>How much of the blame belongs to Gov. George W. Bush? Needless to say, Mr. Bush and his presidential rival, Vice President Al Gore, offered very different answers today as they campaigned across the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the past few years, Texas has enjoyed such a booming economy that any news about the state budget has usually been good. So when state lawmakers this week announced a $610 million shortfall, the bad news came as a surprise and prompted a pregnant political question:</p>
        <p>How much of the blame belongs to Gov. George W. Bush? Needless to say, Mr. Bush and his presidential rival, Vice President Al Gore, offered very different answers today as they campaigned across the country.</p>
        <p>In Wisconsin, where he appeared with former Senator Bill Bradley of New Jersey, Mr. Gore blamed the Texas governor for putting ''politically popular'' tax cuts ahead of paying for Medicaid and other state services.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' Mr. Gore said, ''Governor Bush wants to do for American what he's done for Texas: go to Washington and spend our surplus and then more for budget-busting tax cuts and hope that somehow it will all add up.''</p>
        <p>In Pennsylvania, with Gov. Tom Ridge at his side, Mr. Bush shot back, pointing out that earlier state budget surpluses had made tax cuts the right thing to do.</p>
        <p>''If Al Gore suggests a state with a surplus shouldn't cut taxes,'' he asked, ''then how can the American people count on Al Gore to cut taxes when our nation has a surplus?''</p>
        <p>There also was no agreement in Texas as to where any blame should lie. Several Democratic lawmakers traced the shortfall to the $1.6 billion in tax cuts pushed by Mr. Bush and his allies. But the governor's supporters countered that such assertions were cheap politics, noting that  many Democrats had voted for the budget package.</p>
        <p>The immediate question in Texas is, what, if anything, the deficit means for the state's fiscal future. In a bad economic year, the news might have meant immediate budget cuts. But the strong economy is expected to generate $1 billion in surplus tax revenues, and key lawmakers said the money would more than cover the shortfall.</p>
        <p>Still, there were predictions of future belt-tightening. On Tuesday, Lt. Gov. Rick Perry, a Republican, agreed that the state did not face any budget cuts, but he said expanding services as part of the next budget package now seemed less likely.</p>
        <p>The basic explanation for the shortfall can be found in Texas' two-year budget cycle. Lawmakers drafted the current budget, which runs through Aug. 31, 2001, during last year's legislative session. The $99 billion budget, which is divided about evenly between federal matching funds and state general revenues, included a $3,000 pay raise for teachers and $1.7 billion in tax cuts -- the latter pushed aggressively by Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>But State Representative Robert Junell, the Democratic chairman of the House Appropriations Committee, said the shortfall occurred because lawmakers had underestimated the cost of some services when they drafted the current budget. In particular, he said, the rising cost of prescription drugs had created Medicaid overruns of $439 million, while a shortage of prison space meant the state had to spend $168 million to pay for local jail space. The remaining overruns were divided between different state agencies.</p>
        <p>''You do the best you can in forecasting these numbers, but you're going to be wrong,'' said Mr. Junell, a legislative ally of the governor's.</p>
        <p>He said such midcycle shortfalls requiring supplemental appropriations were common in Texas. ''Had we not had a governor running for president of the United States, there would be no story, because we do this all the time,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Linda Edwards, a spokeswoman for Mr. Bush, noted that shortfalls also occurred in midstream during other budgets: $182 million in 1997 and $104 million in 1999. In Pennsylvania, Mr. Bush said President Clinton was planning today to sign a $15 billion supplemental appropriation for extra expenses in the current federal budget year.</p>
        <p>''But today my opponent attacked me because we're going to do the same thing in Texas,'' he said. He added: ''That's why Vice President Al Gore has got no credibility on an issue like this. On one hand he wants to launch an attack. On the other hand President Clinton is doing the same thing.''</p>
        <p>Several Democratic Texas lawmakers were critical of Mr. Bush and the emphasis he has placed on tax cuts. Representative Garnet F. Coleman flew to Wisconsin to appear with Mr. Gore and brief reporters about the budget shortfall. He said the size of this year's shortfall was particularly worrisome.</p>
        <p>''A supplemental appropriation is standard,'' said Mr. Coleman. ''A supplemental appropriation between $610 million and $750 million is not.''</p>
        <p>Some Democrats say they worry that the deficit may reach $750 million. Mr. Coleman was particularly critical of the Medicaid overruns, saying that Mr. Bush and lawmakers had known that fewer federal dollars would be available for the program. He said lawmakers intentionally underfinanced Medicaid to free up money for tax cuts.</p>
        <p>He also said that by spending this year's $1 billion surplus to cover the shortfall, future budgets are short-changed. ''Once you've spent that $1 billion, you've got to keep spending it forever,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Pete Gallego, a Democrat state representative expressed concern that the state might return to the problems of the early 1990's, when tough economic times prevented any expansion of services. But he, like other Democrats, did vote in favor of the budget package.</p>
        <p>''It's kind of unfair to Monday morning quarterback, to say what you did didn't work,'' he said. ''We had an opportunity to vote yay or nay, and most of us voted yay. We're in the same boat as Governor Bush on this issue.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE STATE BUDGET  Correction:  July 15, 2000, Saturday  A headline yesterday about the Texas budget referred imprecisely to a $610 million shortfall. As the article reported, state spending will exceed the amount budgeted but will not exceed tax revenues; there is no deficit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 15, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>A headline yesterday about the Texas budget referred imprecisely to a $610 million shortfall. As the article reported, state spending will exceed the amount budgeted but will not exceed tax revenues; there is no deficit.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
