<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unit Chief With Big Stake Resigns at Morgan Stanley</title>
    <meta content="Y31MORG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/business/31MORG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mack, John J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karches, Peter F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E6D81730F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unit Chief With Big Stake Resigns at Morgan Stanley</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter F Karches resigns as head of businesses catering to institutional customers at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Company; John J Mack, president and chief operating officer, will take over his responsibilities (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter F. Karches, a longtime top executive of Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Company and one of its biggest individual shareholders, has resigned as head of its businesses that cater to institutional customers.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley said John J. Mack, the president and chief operating officer, would take on Mr. Karches's responsibilities. Stephan F. Newhouse, who has been deputy to Mr. Karches, will remain in that position, reporting to Mr. Mack, said Ray O'Rourke, a spokesman for the firm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peter F. Karches, a longtime top executive of Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Company and one of its biggest individual shareholders, has resigned as head of its businesses that cater to institutional customers.</p>
        <p>Morgan Stanley said John J. Mack, the president and chief operating officer, would take on Mr. Karches's responsibilities. Stephan F. Newhouse, who has been deputy to Mr. Karches, will remain in that position, reporting to Mr. Mack, said Ray O'Rourke, a spokesman for the firm.</p>
        <p>All of Morgan Stanley's investment banking and stock and bond sales and trading operations report to Mr. Mack, the firm's No. 2 executive under Philip J. Purcell, the chairman and chief executive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karches, 48, a horse racing enthusiast who owns thoroughbreds, is leaving this week to ''focus my attention on some other goals and priorities,'' he said in a statement. He had been taking a less active role in daily operations, people at the firm said.</p>
        <p>He has kept a low public profile in recent years after a regulator found that the industry's rules on political campaign finance were violated when Mr. Karches made a $1,000 contribution to the Senate campaign of William F. Weld, then the governor of Massachusetts. Morgan Stanley was subsequently barred from the municipal finance business in Massachusetts for two years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karches, who was not available for comment, has accumulated a large stake in the firm since he joined it 24 years ago after graduating from Columbia Business School. He was the first person hired directly out of business school by the Morgan Stanley bond sales and trading business, Mr. O'Rourke, the firm's spokesman, said.</p>
        <p>According to the firm's latest proxy statement, filed in January, Mr. Karches owned about 4.5 million shares of the firm's stock. That stake would be worth about $475 million today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
