<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Endorsements for the Legislature</title>
    <meta content="31THU3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/opinion/31THU3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kreuger, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thermos, Kimon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malave-Dilan, Martin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Roger L (Assemblyman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Denis, Nelson Antonio (Assemblyman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5D61730F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Endorsements for the Legislature</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial endorses candidates in five Democratic primary contests for State Legislature: Liz Kreuger in 26th Senate District in Manhattan, Kimon Thermos in 36th Assembly District in Queens, Martin Malave-Dilan in 54th and Roger Green in 57th Assembly Districts in Brooklyn, and Nelson Denis in 68th Assembly District in Manhattan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York's legislators have traditionally enjoyed something close to political tenure. In the last election, every incumbent won re-election. But in the Sept. 12 primary, several veteran legislators face real challenges. Here are our endorsements in five races. As in all our primary endorsements, the choices do not assure our endorsement in the general election.</p>
        <p>SENATE -- 26th District, Manhattan. State Senator Roy Goodman, a progressive Republican, is one of several targets for Democrats trying to gain control of the State Legislature. His opposition this year will be decided in a vigorous primary battle between Liz Krueger, a longtime community activist, and Robert Bellinson, a lawyer who ran against Mr. Goodman two years ago. Ms. Krueger is known for her efforts to relieve hunger and housing problems among low-income New Yorkers and seeks to expand health care. Mr. Bellinson is campaigning to build the Second Avenue subway and an East Side high school, and to stop organized pub-crawling in the area. In the Democratic primary, we endorse Ms. Krueger, a dynamic community leader with a broader political agenda.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York's legislators have traditionally enjoyed something close to political tenure. In the last election, every incumbent won re-election. But in the Sept. 12 primary, several veteran legislators face real challenges. Here are our endorsements in five races. As in all our primary endorsements, the choices do not assure our endorsement in the general election.</p>
        <p>SENATE -- 26th District, Manhattan. State Senator Roy Goodman, a progressive Republican, is one of several targets for Democrats trying to gain control of the State Legislature. His opposition this year will be decided in a vigorous primary battle between Liz Krueger, a longtime community activist, and Robert Bellinson, a lawyer who ran against Mr. Goodman two years ago. Ms. Krueger is known for her efforts to relieve hunger and housing problems among low-income New Yorkers and seeks to expand health care. Mr. Bellinson is campaigning to build the Second Avenue subway and an East Side high school, and to stop organized pub-crawling in the area. In the Democratic primary, we endorse Ms. Krueger, a dynamic community leader with a broader political agenda.</p>
        <p>ASSEMBLY -- 36th District, Queens. This is the fourth time that Kimon Thermos, a lawyer and president of the Democratic Club in Queens, has run for this seat, edging closer each time to defeating Assemblyman Denis Butler. Mr. Butler decided to retire this round and now Michael Gianaris, associate counsel to Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver, has entered the contest with the full backing of Mr. Silver and most of the Democratic establishment. Mr. Gianaris has promised that he will be independent of his Democratic elders. But Mr. Thermos has worked more closely with the community and has a chance to be more independent in Albany. We have recommended Mr. Thermos in earlier tries and we endorse him in the primary this year.</p>
        <p>54th District, Brooklyn. Despite Assemblyman Darryl Towns's eight years in office, his ambitions for his district have steadily dwindled and his connections to the tobacco industry remain troubling. Although we endorsed Mr. Towns in the last election, it is now time for voters to look elsewhere. His primary opponent, Martin Malave-Dilan, a City Council member, promises to focus on health care, education and economic revitalization in the area.  Although he has not organized his campaign finance reports in a timely fashion, apparently because of computer problems, we endorse Mr. Malave-Dilan in the primary and urge him to file timely campaign finance reports in the general election.</p>
        <p>57th District, Brooklyn. Hakeem Jeffries, a lawyer with an army of young volunteers, has mounted a formidable challenge this year against Roger Green, who has been in the Assembly for almost 20 years. Mr. Jeffries makes a straightforward case that the district has not prospered and the district office is not efficient enough for constituents. However, Mr. Green has become a thoughtful and diligent leader in Albany, often tackling difficult issues like children's health and welfare. We endorse Mr. Green in the Democratic primary.</p>
        <p>68th District, Manhattan. In a area where his father is still famous, Adam Clayton Powell 4th is now trying to unseat Assemblyman Nelson Denis. Mr. Denis, an articulate speaker, has made an admirable effort trying to get banks to give more loans in his area. Despite going along with Assembly leaders to repeal the city's commuter tax, Mr. Denis has since shown his independence and worked for a more open process in the Legislature. We endorse Mr. Denis in the primary.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
