<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; The Satch Is Where It's At</title>
    <meta content="31VECS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/sports/31VECS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Tennis Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2D61730F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; The Satch Is Where It's At</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of the Times column on Louis Armstrong Stadium becoming star of United States Open at National Tennis Center in Flushing, Queens, because of recent renovations allowing fans to sit closer to action; contends Arthur Ashe Stadium, with corporate and luxury boxes, is not well designed, with high tiers of seats that often remain empty; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE old stadium is a relic of Jennifer Capriati's vanished youth, the way former schools and teachers seem gigantic from a distance of time.</p>
        <p>''And you know, I still see it as the real stadium sometimes,'' said Capriati, who does not seem to be the type who dwells on apparitions.</p>
        <p>In fact, Louis Armstrong Stadium has gotten smaller. In the recent renovation of the joint, they shaved off the top deck, turning it into the absolute star of the National Tennis Center, the place where people jam and maneuver and wheedle to get a good seat. How New York is that?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE old stadium is a relic of Jennifer Capriati's vanished youth, the way former schools and teachers seem gigantic from a distance of time.</p>
        <p>''And you know, I still see it as the real stadium sometimes,'' said Capriati, who does not seem to be the type who dwells on apparitions.</p>
        <p>In fact, Louis Armstrong Stadium has gotten smaller. In the recent renovation of the joint, they shaved off the top deck, turning it into the absolute star of the National Tennis Center, the place where people jam and maneuver and wheedle to get a good seat. How New York is that?</p>
        <p>''They still crowd in, and they're not quiet until, like, the first few points are over from the change-over,'' said Capriati who, in her relative dotage, would not have it any other way.</p>
        <p>The stadium named for the great jazz musician rocked and swayed for Capriati yesterday, with men and women of a certain age shouting, ''Good girl, Jen,'' and other parental sentiments as Capriati whacked Henrieta Nagyova, 6-2, 6-2. The fans knew of her troubles, an old story by now, and they were glad to see her show vestigial glimpses of that right-handed forehand that once made her a contenduh, as Marlon Brando put it.</p>
        <p>The Satch is an equal opportunity site. The fans love everybody because they can get close enough to express that love. Whoever plays there benefits from the impromptu joy of fans celebrating something going out of style -- immediacy, intimacy, visibility.</p>
        <p>This certainly is not the case in the dreadfully conceived Arthur Ashe Stadium, where nobody has yet performed the Fountainhead thing and pushed the plunger, so they could start all over. At the Art, there are corporate boxes and luxury boxes and then tiers of seats stretching up to the Delta Shuttle. Television hates the sight of the empty seats -- psychologically bad for ratings.</p>
        <p>''I mean, it's unfortunate,'' said Monica Seles, who beat Anne Kremer, 6-3, 6-4, in the Art yesterday. ''I understand, with the whole boxes and corporations and so on and so on.'' Well, yes, the corporate ennui does help pay Monica's prize money. But still.</p>
        <p>They could fix it by letting the ushers scalp the empty seats, but that grand old Open tradition is apparently discouraged, creating a vacuum. Where have all the people gone? To the Satch, more often than not.</p>
        <p>''I went to the main stadium; it was ridiculous,'' said a lady in a sun dress after Marat Safin outlasted Thierry Guardiola at the Satch.</p>
        <p>With Capriati warming up, fans jammed the narrow hatchways and deftly tried to cut the lines and fill in the 8,253 open seats directly behind the 1,436 reserved seats in the lower boxes. ''It's a cozy stadium,'' said Paul Bruehl of Locust Valley, L.I. ''In the big stadium it's like watching it on TV. I buy the cheapest seat in the stadium, and then I move around for the first week.''</p>
        <p>It is difficult to remember how reviled the Satch was as the main stadium. But now it has four handsome towers at the corners, scoreboards at the north and south ends, precious little advertising and a handsome, compact feel. And the fans flow in and out like the tide, sometimes a riptide.</p>
        <p>Only one force is greater than the Satch, and that is the appeal of the Williams Sisters, the hottest draw in the sport no matter how much poor, fried John McEnroe blathers against women's tennis. Yesterday, the sisters were supposed to play doubles in the Satch in the late afternoon, but their match was rescheduled for the Art, with its 23,219 seats.</p>
        <p>Look out! There went thousands of pilgrims racing across the plaza, leaving behind a modest audience for two young Yanks, Jan-Michael Gambill and Mardy Fish. Among the stalwarts was Kathleen Bernard, originally from Montego Bay, Jamaica, and now a tennis pro at the Roosevelt Island Racquet Club.</p>
        <p>''I've lost Guga, I've lost Rafter, and now Jan-Michael is in trouble,'' Bernard said, mourning the losses of Gustavo Kuerten and Patrick Rafter on Tuesday. ''I can see the Williamses anytime, but I've got to cheer for my man Jan-Michael.''</p>
        <p>Bernard was fair. She watched Fish whip forehands into the corners, and she cheered, ''Go, Mr. Fish, you're really swimming now.''</p>
        <p>The Williamses dispatched their opponents, and the hard-core fans surged back to the Satch to watch Gambill defeat Fish in the fifth set. As darkness fell, Martina Hingis and Pete Sampras were on deck at the Art, which does perk up at night. Meanwhile, Capriati was due back at the Satch for doubles, along with her partner, one Anna Kournikova. At the Satch, the hits just keep on coming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
