<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants and Fassel to Go With a 'Two-Headed Monster' in the Backfield</title>
    <meta content="31GIAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/sports/31GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arizona Cardinals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fassel, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barber, Tiki</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dayne, Ron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Arizona Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7DF1430F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants and Fassel to Go With a 'Two-Headed Monster' in the Backfield</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Giants coach Jim Fassel may use Tiki Barber and Ron Dayne in backfield in opening game against Arizona Cardinals; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Monday, Giants Coach Jim Fassel announced that he was going to have his players wear their road uniforms for Sunday's season-opening home game with Arizona. Today, he announced that he has two starting running backs, Tiki Barber and Ron Dayne, and might introduce both before the game as co-starters at the position.</p>
        <p>''That'd be cool,'' Barber said. ''We're a two-headed monster.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Monday, Giants Coach Jim Fassel announced that he was going to have his players wear their road uniforms for Sunday's season-opening home game with Arizona. Today, he announced that he has two starting running backs, Tiki Barber and Ron Dayne, and might introduce both before the game as co-starters at the position.</p>
        <p>''That'd be cool,'' Barber said. ''We're a two-headed monster.''</p>
        <p>The Giants today also signed free safety Omar Stoutmire, whom the Jets released four days ago. Stoutmire's reaction?</p>
        <p>''God bless the Jets,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And finally, the rookie wide receiver and kick returner Ron Dixon was spiked in the back of his right heel early in practice. After the wound was bandaged, Dixon tried to run on it and came to a skittering, limping halt after catching a pass. That was the end of his workout session, although the Giants insisted that the gash would not hamper Dixon for Sunday's game.</p>
        <p>So much action for an otherwise routine day under the sun on the practice field outside Giants Stadium.</p>
        <p>Fassel's designation of Barber and Dayne as co-starters is not a declaration of running back by committee, even if that's exactly how it sounds. The Giants' plan since April has been to use Barber and Dayne to complement each other since Barber is effective as a receiver and a rusher on quick-hitting plays while Dayne is more of a power back in the traditional style. It is a potent combo: different skills for different game conditions.</p>
        <p>What's puzzling is that Fassel felt the need to define the starting running-back situation at all. He has been questioned about whom he plans to start for weeks and been noncommittal. Barber has started every preseason game, though it has seemed mostly ceremonial, a matter of football protocol since Dayne is a rookie. In the last preseason game, Barber started and Dayne came in after the opening play. Both then played almost as interchangeable, if completely different, parts.</p>
        <p>This figured to be the model for the season and there is no change to that strategy. Except that Fassel felt the need to publicly recognize both Barber and Dayne, perhaps worried that one or the other would feel slighted if either were named the starter.</p>
        <p>''I want Tiki and Ron to touch the football 20 to 25 times each,'' Fassel said. ''And it will change week to week on exactly how they're used. It doesn't matter who starts. If you have to write down one name, then it would be Tiki because he's the senior guy.''</p>
        <p>Of course, Barber's 20 touches could include punt returns and 10 pass receptions. Dayne's could be 25 rushing carries. So who's really the starting running back? And does it matter?</p>
        <p>Apparently it does, because Fassel said he was thinking of have both introduced on the public address system before games, even if that meant 12 offensive starters would be announced.</p>
        <p>Dayne said he didn't care if he started. ''So long as I get to play,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Barber seemed to understand the concept of a multifaceted attack.</p>
        <p>''It's perfect because we're so different,'' he said. ''Thunder and lightning.''</p>
        <p>Next up: Barber and Dayne in the same backfield.</p>
        <p>As for Stoutmire, the Giants signed him as insurance should the starting free safety, Shaun Williams, either develop slowly or not stay healthy. Williams, who missed all of the preseason with a sprained toe, will be making his first National Football League start at the position Sunday against the Cardinals. Stoutmire, 26, has started 19 games with Dallas and the Jets in a four-year career.</p>
        <p>The Giants' current backup at free safety is Lyle West, the team's seventh-round draft pick last year, who has also never started an N.F.L. game. Once Stoutmire learns the Giants defense he will most likely supplant West on the depth chart. To make room for Stoutmire, the Giants today released cornerback Ramos McDonald, whom they had claimed off waivers last week. If McDonald is still unsigned by another team next week, he could return to the Giants, who should have another roster spot open by then.</p>
        <p>Stoutmire today politely defied the Jets' assessment of his preseason, saying he felt he had a good preseason.</p>
        <p>Dixon, meanwhile, was uncomfortable and in pain after a teammate stepped on the back of his right foot during a special teams drill. The spike not only tore into Dixon's heel, it ripped a hole in his shoe.</p>
        <p>The Giants said there was no serious damage to Dixon's foot or Achilles' tendon.</p>
        <p>''I was told he should be fine,'' Fassel said.</p>
        <p>Last, with the weekend weather forecast calling for high humidity and a warm, sunny day, Fassel today was feeling better than ever about his decision to dress his Giants in white instead of their dark blue, traditional home jerseys for the Arizona game.</p>
        <p>''The white uniforms will keep everyone cool,'' the coach said.</p>
        <p>Even the two-headed monster.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
