<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Night Spent Achingly Close to Home</title>
    <meta content="31NEIG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/nyregion/31NEIG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Edgewater (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E7D81430F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="583" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Night Spent Achingly Close to Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA K. DEWAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Edgewater, NJ, watch blaze that began in apartment complex under construction spread to their homes; they comment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With helicopters hovering overhead, and columns of smoke billowing in the not-so-far distance, Janice Tibus stood barefoot on the sidewalk, wearing plaid pajamas and holding a pair of black sandals in one hand. As she and her family tried nervously to get the phone number of a relative, a man on a stretcher was carried by. ''Dad,'' Ms. Tibus yelled, ''That's Uncle Dennis!''</p>
        <p>Her uncle, a volunteer in the Edgewater Fire Department, was being carried out of the inferno that began when an apartment complex being built across the street from the Tibuses's house went up in flames. Minutes later, Ms. Tibus's father, Steven, returned with the news that his brother had suffered only exhaustion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With helicopters hovering overhead, and columns of smoke billowing in the not-so-far distance, Janice Tibus stood barefoot on the sidewalk, wearing plaid pajamas and holding a pair of black sandals in one hand. As she and her family tried nervously to get the phone number of a relative, a man on a stretcher was carried by. ''Dad,'' Ms. Tibus yelled, ''That's Uncle Dennis!''</p>
        <p>Her uncle, a volunteer in the Edgewater Fire Department, was being carried out of the inferno that began when an apartment complex being built across the street from the Tibuses's house went up in flames. Minutes later, Ms. Tibus's father, Steven, returned with the news that his brother had suffered only exhaustion.</p>
        <p>But that was the only good news of the night. The Tibuses no longer had a home.</p>
        <p>Just two hours earlier, Ms. Tibus, 26, and her parents had been on the couch in their living room on Undercliff Avenue -- the house they had lived in for so long they had only eight years left on the mortgage, Steven Tibus said -- and were watching ''Big Brother'' on television. They heard fire alarms, and looked out the window to see what Ms. Tibus described as a ''ball of fire'' headed straight for their house.</p>
        <p>The possessions of Janice Tibus's brother -- he was moving his wife and newborn baby to a new residence -- were on the front porch. Minutes after the Tibuses fled through the back door, two households' worth of clothes and photographs, appliances and books, had been destroyed.</p>
        <p>Throughout the night, families who lived in the string of houses and apartments on Undercliff Avenue hovered as close to their block as firefighters would allow. Some searched for neighbors. Others, like Ellena Calabria, who lived in an apartment on the street, tried desperately to find out if their homes had been saved.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Calabria, who runs a medical billing business from home, could not get much information from the teams of emergency workers trying feverishly to contain the fire. She eventually learned that her building had been damaged, not destroyed.</p>
        <p>Another family, two young daughters in tow, returned from church to find that they could not reach the house they had lived in for four years, and no one could tell them whether it still stood.</p>
        <p>Vilma and Wilfredo Arias, 60 and 65, returned from their evening walk to find their house of 30 years in flames. They called their daughter Xiomara Peddilla, 28, who came to pick them up. ''We've all been there for ages,'' Ms. Peddilla said of her family and their neighbors. ''I grew up there.''</p>
        <p>One nearby resident found himself playing firefighter. Roger Buttot, 48, an artist who lived in a row house on Russell Avenue, said he took a garden hose up on his roof when burning embers from the blaze across the street began to fly.</p>
        <p>While he was on the roof, he said, the wind changed direction and carried the fire away to the south. When actual firefighters came and ordered him down, he snuck around to the back of his house and rescued his dog and two cats.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
