<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gap Announces Its Sales Will Decline by 14% in August</title>
    <meta content="Y31GAP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/business/31GAP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gap Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFDE1430F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gap Announces Its Sales Will Decline by 14% in August</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gap Inc stuns investors by announcing that sales in stores open at least a year will decline 14 percent in August; stock falls 12 percent in after-hours trading (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gap Inc. stunned investors yesterday evening by announcing after the stock market closed that sales in stores open at least a year, a well-watched industry measurement, would decline 14 percent in August. The numbers were not only well below what most analysts expected, they seemed to truly surprise the normally efficient company.</p>
        <p>''The results were clearly a disappointment and fell well below our own expectations,'' said Heidi Kunz, executive vice president and chief financial officer, in a recorded message for investors on monthly sales. While August hardly rivals December for retailers, it is nonetheless an important month because of back-to-school sales.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gap Inc. stunned investors yesterday evening by announcing after the stock market closed that sales in stores open at least a year, a well-watched industry measurement, would decline 14 percent in August. The numbers were not only well below what most analysts expected, they seemed to truly surprise the normally efficient company.</p>
        <p>''The results were clearly a disappointment and fell well below our own expectations,'' said Heidi Kunz, executive vice president and chief financial officer, in a recorded message for investors on monthly sales. While August hardly rivals December for retailers, it is nonetheless an important month because of back-to-school sales.</p>
        <p>Sales at each of the Gap's brands were lower than they were last year in stores open at least a year. The Gap's lower-priced chain, Old Navy, which after blazing growth last year had a sharp downturn early this summer, had a sales decline of more than 20 percent. Sales at the namesake Gap stores were down, the company said, ''in the mid-single digits.'' And even Banana Republic, previously a growth stalwart for the company, had similar declines in sales.</p>
        <p>The Gap's miss on sales is more remarkable because it comes after a series of highly atypical stumbles. The company had a rare earnings disappointment in the first quarter, and then announced a more pronounced earnings shortfall in the second quarter and predicted that earnings would be lower than analysts expected for the entire year.</p>
        <p>Investors sent shares of Gap plunging 12 percent, to $22.50, in after-hours trading after the company announced its August sales. The shares are down more than 50 percent from a February high of $53 and are trading at their lowest point since October 1998. And the news could get worse.</p>
        <p>The company acknowledged that because of a ''highly promotional'' environment, with sales earlier and more widespread, gross margins were lower this August than last year, and said the trend could further hurt earnings. ''We continue to see risk and challenge in the third and fourth quarters,'' Ms. Kunz said in the telephone message.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Barbara Miller, an analyst with Goldman, Sachs, thought Gap's earnings a share would be $1.58. Earlier this month, she lowered her forecast to $1.28. Last night she would not say if she planned to lower her estimates again, but did say, ''This certainly gives me pause.''</p>
        <p>Gap said that some problems emerged with all its brands. First, back-to-school sales, which the company said had built consistently through the month previously, failed to expand in August. The company also blamed the cutback in spending by consumers for retail items.</p>
        <p>In addition, the company cited its decision to rely less on television commercials.</p>
        <p>''Gap brand's decision to shift its marketing mix away from TV in favor of in-store marketing and promotion efforts did not succeed as well as we had hoped,'' said Millard S. Drexler, the company's president and chief executive, in a press release. The Gap said it would change course and support its brands with lots of television advertising in the holiday season.</p>
        <p>Many retailers have had a disappointing year. After six interest rate increases by the Federal Reserve, consumer spending on retail is declining. After the second quarter, many of the biggest retailers said they were expecting a consumer slowdown in the third and fourth quarters.</p>
        <p>Still, some retailers managed to do well with teenagers heading back to school. Analysts are expecting American Eagle Outfitters, a fast-growing Gap rivals, to report a sales gain of 9 percent tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Analysts worried that there might be something more amiss with the Gap. ''There are no teenagers going naked back to school,'' said Richard  Jaffe, a retailing analyst at PaineWebber. ''There have to be other issues impacting Gap. It is a cause for concern.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
