<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Swiss Banks Calling Wall St. Home</title>
    <meta content="Y31EUR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/business/31EURO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Switzerland</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ubs Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Paine Webber Group Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Credit Suisse Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Donaldson Lufkin &amp; Jenrette Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4DF1430F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1197" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Swiss Banks Calling Wall St. Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Aug. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Credit Suisse Group's planned acquisition of Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, following hard on the heels of UBS's deal for PaineWebber, is likely to provide further illustration of Swiss banking's flair for penetrating Wall Street and managing the cultural clashes that expansion outide Europe often brings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Credit Suisse Group's planned acquisition of Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, following hard on the heels of the deal for PaineWebber by the Swiss banking giant UBS, is likely to provide further illustration of Swiss banking's flair for penetrating Wall Street and managing the cultural clashes that expansion outside Europe often brings.</p>
        <p>The Swiss early on sensed the need to expand beyond a domestic market of seven million people. And they seem, more than their European neighbors, to have learned from missteps and become better able to balance the need in financial businesses between autonomy and control.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Credit Suisse Group's planned acquisition of Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, following hard on the heels of the deal for PaineWebber by the Swiss banking giant UBS, is likely to provide further illustration of Swiss banking's flair for penetrating Wall Street and managing the cultural clashes that expansion outside Europe often brings.</p>
        <p>The Swiss early on sensed the need to expand beyond a domestic market of seven million people. And they seem, more than their European neighbors, to have learned from missteps and become better able to balance the need in financial businesses between autonomy and control.</p>
        <p>This ability to adapt is increasingly crucial as European banks break out of their traditional national markets. Many, seeking to grow in size and gain expertise in banking skills less developed in Continental Europe, are acquiring banks in Britain and the United States. The pressure to do so has intensified in recent years as European capital markets have unified, spurred by the creation of a single currency.</p>
        <p>Financial service businesses from corporate banking to personal investment are increasingly shedding the tightly cosseted and closely managed rules of old-time European finance to take on more of the freewheeling, creative quality common in Britain and the United States.</p>
        <p>Last year, for example, Deutsche Bank vastly expanded its American presence by acquiring Bankers Trust for $10 billion.</p>
        <p>An earlier effort by Deutsche Bank to establish such a presence, like those of a few Japanese banks before, proved to be expensive failures. Wall Street opinion was that the foreign banks' insistence on imposing controls would keep them from being successful in the United States.</p>
        <p>Philip Zieschang, an analyst at Bank Julius Baer in Zurich, said it was the Swiss who pioneered the penetration of the Anglo-Saxon banking world. In 1995, the old Swiss Bank Corporation, which merged two years later with Union Bank of Switzerland to form UBS, acquired SG Warburg, a British investment bank with a sizable Wall Street presence. It also absorbed two small but valuable firms in Chicago: O'Connor Associates, a derivatives business, and a money management firm, Brinson Asset Management.</p>
        <p>''The Swiss were aware at an earlier stage of the critical importance of growing internationally,'' Mr. Zieschang said.</p>
        <p>Credit Suisse had moved before then. In 1978, it established a curious joint venture with the Bank of Boston called Financiere Credit Suisse First Boston. That was very much a learning experience, said Bryan Crossley, an analyst at ABN Amro in London. In 1988, Credit Suisse First Boston was beleaguered by duplication and friction, not least because of financial fallout from the stock market crash the previous autumn, prompting Credit Suisse in Zurich to take full control. In the process, it acquired a global investment bank and a powerful calling card in New York and London and on the Continent.</p>
        <p>''In that business, it can be pretty ruthless,'' Mr. Crossley said. ''You can spill blood, but can make it a clean cut.''</p>
        <p>It was also the Swiss who moved earliest in consolidating the European banking market, in 1997, when Union Bank and Swiss Bank startled the financial world by announcing the merger to form UBS, then the world's biggest bank by assets.</p>
        <p>Susanne Borer, a financial analyst at Bank Vontobel in Zurich, says that what is driving the Swiss overseas is also the thirst for size. ''They're very big and they want to be very, very big,'' she said, adding that with PaineWebber, UBS ''essentially bought assets under management.'' With Donaldson, Lufkin, Credit Suisse is getting size in investment banking.</p>
        <p>The pattern is familiar, she said, and the Swiss have plenty of competition. In January, Citigroup announced it was acquiring the investment banking business of Schroders of London for about $2.2 billion; several months later, Chase Manhattan agreed to buy Robert Fleming Holdings for $7.7 billion.</p>
        <p>Many analysts point to the considerable experience that Marcel Ospel, the chairman of UBS, has had with American acquisitions. Mr. Ospel played a prime role in Swiss Bank's acquisition of Warburg, a move that some say threw the drive for British and American properties into high gear. Mr. Zieschang of Bank Julius Baer called him a ''front-runner in opening to Anglo-Saxon influence.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ospel and Lukas Muhlemann, chief executive of Credit Suisse Group, are both 50, members of a younger executive generation in Swiss banking and insurance. Like Mr. Ospel, Mr. Muhlemann, a former McKinsey consultant and insurance executive, has understood the value of integration. For instance, he rotated Credit Suisse First Boston's chief financial officer, Richard E. Thornburgh, between Zurich and New York to fortify trans-Atlantic ties.</p>
        <p>The Swiss hand in dealing with outsiders has not always proved infallible, Ms. Borer said. For instance, past efforts by Credit Suisse to impose less lucrative European compensation methods on Credit Suisse First Boston's American bankers failed, she said, and Credit Suisse was forced to backtrack.</p>
        <p>Still, said Vasco Moreno, who follows banking at the London brokerage firm of Fox Pitt Kelton, ''the Swiss appear to be able to make it stick more than other European institutions.'' In part, he said, that may be because the Swiss seem to be more comfortable culturally with the way business is done in London and New York than are some of their Continental European competitors.</p>
        <p>The fact that Swiss bankers, in the course of daily business in their own small country, have to deal in three languages -- German, French and Italian -- may also be a reason they are more adaptable.</p>
        <p>This does not always mean that they are welcome. Mr. Zieschang noted that Josef Ackermann, a former Credit Suisse executive who joined Deutsche Bank's management board in 1997, has been the focus of friction and disputes that some attribute in part to his being an outsider.</p>
        <p>AXA, the French insurance and financial services giant that owns 72 percent of Donaldson, is shedding the unit because it ''was not prepared to spend the capital to be a player in global investment banking,'' Mr. Crossley of ABN Amro said.</p>
        <p>Some analysts expect AXA to use the proceeds from the sale to expand its asset management business through acquisitions, notably in the United States, following in the footsteps of big European competitors. Last year, Aegon of the Netherlands paid almost $10 billion to acquire Transamerica of San Francisco; earlier, the ING Group of the Netherlands spent almost $15 billion snapping up various insurance businesses from Aetna. In June, AXA Financial paid $3.5 billion through an affiliate to buy the Wall Street brokerage house Sanford C. Bernstein.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muhlemann of Credit Suisse has long been an advocate of cross-fertilization of banking and insurance. In 1997, the year he took over as head of Credit Suisse, he bought the Winterthur Insurance Company. Today's cash-and-stock deal makes AXA one of Credit Suisse's biggest shareholders, with a 10 percent stake.</p>
        <p>It also stirred speculation that Credit Suisse might use the 5.5 percent share it holds in another insurer, Swiss Life, as partial payment. Credit Suisse denied that this would happen, but if it did, it would also leave AXA as a major shareholder in Swiss Life, weaving further links in Europe's financial services industries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
