<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Nixon Aides Skeptical About Report That He Took Drug</title>
    <meta content="Y31NIX$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/national/31NIXO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000911T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dilantin (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nixon, Richard Milhous (1913-94)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stout, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, John H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bull, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Summers, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dreyfus, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D61730F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Nixon Aides Skeptical About Report That He Took Drug</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STOUT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stout, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John H Taylor and Steve Bull, former aides to ex-Pres Richard M Nixon, question report in Anthony Summers' new book on Nixon that he medicated himself with anti-seizure drug Dilantin; Jack Dreyfus, who advocated drug for dealing with anxiety and other conditions, has confirmed he supplied drug to Nixon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two aides to President Richard M. Nixon said today that they doubted he ever took the drug Dilantin, an antiseizure medication, despite a new book that says he did.</p>
        <p>The aides, John H. Taylor, the director of the Nixon Library in Yorba Linda, Calif., who knew Mr. Nixon from the mid-1980's until his death in 1994, and Steve Bull, who was Mr. Nixon's personal aide from mid-1969 until late 1974, said they were skeptical of assertions in the book that Mr. Nixon medicated himself with Dilantin given to him by Jack Dreyfus, the founder of the Dreyfus Fund and an avid promoter of the drug.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two aides to President Richard M. Nixon said today that they doubted he ever took the drug Dilantin, an antiseizure medication, despite a new book that says he did.</p>
        <p>The aides, John H. Taylor, the director of the Nixon Library in Yorba Linda, Calif., who knew Mr. Nixon from the mid-1980's until his death in 1994, and Steve Bull, who was Mr. Nixon's personal aide from mid-1969 until late 1974, said they were skeptical of assertions in the book that Mr. Nixon medicated himself with Dilantin given to him by Jack Dreyfus, the founder of the Dreyfus Fund and an avid promoter of the drug.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dreyfus said last week that an account in the book, ''The Arrogance of Power: The Secret World of Richard Nixon,'' that he gave Dilantin to Mr. Nixon in 1968 was correct. Mr. Dreyfus said he gave Mr. Nixon a bottle of 1,000 capsules of 100 milligrams each ''when his mood wasn't too good,'' and later gave him another bottle of 1,000 capsules.</p>
        <p>The book written by Anthony Summers and published by Viking paints an unfavorable portrait of Richard Nixon politically and personally. Its assertion that he freely medicated himself while coping with the burdens of the White House is one of several contentions that have been disputed by Mr. Nixon's relatives and associates. Mr. Taylor and Mr. Bull volunteered their views in reaction to reports about the book.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor said the Richard Nixon he knew ''went to traditional doctors when he was sick, and always did what they said.''</p>
        <p>As for Dilantin, Mr. Bull, who is now director of government relations for the United States Olympic Committee, said: ''I never saw any evidence that he used any medication of that kind. Never.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dreyfus has advocated the drug as being effective in dealing with anxiety, anger, depression and other troubling conditions.</p>
        <p>Dilantin, introduced in the 1930's, is routinely prescribed by neurologists to prevent seizures caused by epilepsy or other conditions, but is rarely used to treat mental disorders. However, other, newer antiseizure drugs -- including Tegritol and Depakote -- are used in the treatment of depression and some other psychiatric illnesses.</p>
        <p>Dr. Frederick Jacobsen, a psychopharmacologist at George Washington University, said Dilantin was not widely used because it had not proved very effective as a treatment for mental disorders, and had more side effects than newer drugs.</p>
        <p>Common side effects of Dilantin, which is chemically related to barbiturates but does not share their addictive properties, can include sedation, mental confusion or fuzziness, physical unsteadiness and slurred speech. According to the Physician's Desk Reference, such side effects occur primarily when patients take too much Dilantin. But Dr. Jacobsen said confusion can also occur ''with doses within the therapeutic range.''</p>
        <p>With long-term use Dilantin can also cause an overgrowth of the gums.</p>
        <p>''I think the majority of psychiatrists do not find much benefit for Dilantin,'' Dr. Jacobsen said. ''It's not in the standard repertoire of the general psychopharmacologist.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Jacobsen said that to describe Dilantin as a ''mind-altering drug'' was not entirely accurate. ''It would be more accurate to characterize it as a 'brain-altering drug,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Self-medicating with Dilantin, as the book contends Mr. Nixon did, would not be a good idea, Dr. Jacobsen added. ''Self-medication in general is not a good idea, and certainly one runs the risk of toxicity,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor produced a summary of White House records from April 1969 through mid-1973 recalling numerous attempts by Mr. Dreyfus to gain government backing for Dilantin through Mr. Nixon. The records state that Mr. Nixon met with Mr. Dreyfus now and then socially, but they portray the president as reluctant to get into lengthy discussions about Dilantin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taylor said that Mr. Nixon might have accepted Dilantin from Mr. Dreyfus so as not to hurt his feelings, but that if he did he threw it out rather than taking it.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 11, 2000, Monday  An article on Aug. 31 about aides to President Richard M. Nixon who expressed skepticism about assertions in a new book that the president took the antiseizure drug Dilantin misstated the tenure of one aide, John H. Taylor. Mr. Taylor, now director of the Nixon Library in Yorba Linda, Calif., worked for President Nixon from 1979 until the former president's death in 1994. Their association did not begin in the mid-1980's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 11, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>An article on Aug. 31 about aides to President Richard M. Nixon who expressed skepticism about assertions in a new book that the president took the antiseizure drug Dilantin misstated the tenure of one aide, John H. Taylor. Mr. Taylor, now director of the Nixon Library in Yorba Linda, Calif., worked for President Nixon from 1979 until the former president's death in 1994. Their association did not begin in the mid-1980's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
