<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="31GARD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0D61630F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GARDEN Q.&amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dora Galitzki</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Calendula Choices</p>
        <p>Q.  When I lived in New Hampshire, I grew calendulas in my herb garden that were to die for. Now, we have moved near Washington and they just aren't performing well. I'm baffled and need your help, please, as these are among my favorite easy-to-grow annuals.</p>
        <p>A.  Welcome to summer heat. Calendula, also called pot marigold, takes little effort to grow other than remembering to put it in full sun. But while it loves cool climates, in warmer areas it quits blooming in midsummer. If the selection you have has grown long and rangy, this is a perfect time to cut them back by a third to a half. As cool weather returns, they'll rebloom. When they start again, continue your religious devotion to deadheading so they will keep flowering cheerfully right until hard frost finally takes them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Calendula Choices</p>
        <p>Q.  When I lived in New Hampshire, I grew calendulas in my herb garden that were to die for. Now, we have moved near Washington and they just aren't performing well. I'm baffled and need your help, please, as these are among my favorite easy-to-grow annuals.</p>
        <p>A.  Welcome to summer heat. Calendula, also called pot marigold, takes little effort to grow other than remembering to put it in full sun. But while it loves cool climates, in warmer areas it quits blooming in midsummer. If the selection you have has grown long and rangy, this is a perfect time to cut them back by a third to a half. As cool weather returns, they'll rebloom. When they start again, continue your religious devotion to deadheading so they will keep flowering cheerfully right until hard frost finally takes them.</p>
        <p>Calendula selections range from under a foot tall to over two. The flowers are usually bright orange or shades of yellow, and are often fully double. Knockout cultivars include Pink Surprise, with soft peach melba petals and a well-behaved habit, and Touch of Red, whose many petals are edged in a mahogany blush.</p>
        <p>Seed sources include Pinetree Garden Seeds, Box 300, New Gloucester, Me. 04260, (207) 926-3400; and Thompson &amp; Morgan, Box 1308, Jackson, N.J. 08527, (800) 274-7333. Both catalogs are free.</p>
        <p>Best and Worst of Crab Apples</p>
        <p>Q.  This is a tale of two crab apples, and I hope you know a happy ending. Both trees were on the property when we bought our house last year, so I don't have any information about them. This summer the backyard tree has lost all its leaves. The front tree looks fine, but I am afraid that it will also succumb. What steps can we take to help the remaining tree?</p>
        <p>A.  Don't cut it down -- it isn't dead. Crab apples, lovely as they are, attract not only humans and birds, but also a whole host of fungi. Your backyard tree has apple scab, which the wet, cool weather has encouraged this summer. But if it hadn't been scab, it might have been cedar-apple rust, fire blight or powdery mildew.</p>
        <p>When buying one of the trees, the previous owner of your house may have fallen in love with a pretty flower and forgot to ask about disease resistance. Considering everything there is to decide when choosing a crab apple -- like size and shape of the tree when mature; size, color and persistence of the fruit; single or double flowers in red, white, or pink; and whether it's an alternate-year bloomer -- she may have just been awestruck in the middle of all those trees in glorious flower at the nursery.</p>
        <p>Scab is a surprising disease. You may not notice the dull, smoky or sooty area on new leaves, or even the irregular olive-green or brown velvety spots. But you sure notice when all the leaves fall off in midsummer. Rake up and destroy all those fallen leaves, because the fungus overwinters on them and can reinfect the tree next year. Spraying an entire tree every 8 to 10 days with fungicides to prevent scab is not just difficult, but also silly when disease-resistant crab apples are available everywhere.</p>
        <p>Resistance does not mean invulnerability, and a summer of perfect fungus weather can overcome the most resistant of trees, so some cultivars are clearly better than others. High on everyone's list are Adams, Adirondack, Donald Wyman, Harvest Gold, Indian Summer, Professor Sprenger, Prairifire, Snowdrift and Sugar Tyme. By the way, all of these have excellent resistance to cedar-apple rust, too.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
