<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Torre Can Find No Fault With Nelson After Slam</title>
    <meta content="31YANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/sports/31BOMB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DC1430F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1014" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Torre Can Find No Fault With Nelson After Slam</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Aug. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seattle Mariners defeat New York Yankees, 5-3, photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jeff Nelson robotically reviewed his role in the disastrous eighth inning after Tuesday night's game, sounding like a court reporter reading from a transcript as he slumped in a chair in front of his locker. His vacant gaze betrayed the fact that this was probably the third or fourth time he had combed through the memory of all the pitches he threw, including the fastball that Seattle's Edgar Martinez crushed for a game-winning grand slam.</p>
        <p>Andy Pettitte, who had carried a no-hitter into the sixth inning and completely befuddled the slumping Mariners for seven innings, had the same hazy look after the 5-3 loss. A handful of position players, Jorge Posada in particular, appeared catatonic; Glenallen Hill muttered sharply in a low voice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jeff Nelson robotically reviewed his role in the disastrous eighth inning after Tuesday night's game, sounding like a court reporter reading from a transcript as he slumped in a chair in front of his locker. His vacant gaze betrayed the fact that this was probably the third or fourth time he had combed through the memory of all the pitches he threw, including the fastball that Seattle's Edgar Martinez crushed for a game-winning grand slam.</p>
        <p>Andy Pettitte, who had carried a no-hitter into the sixth inning and completely befuddled the slumping Mariners for seven innings, had the same hazy look after the 5-3 loss. A handful of position players, Jorge Posada in particular, appeared catatonic; Glenallen Hill muttered sharply in a low voice.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre seemed alone in his perspective on the wrenching  defeat, at peace with everything that happened because, as he explained, the Yankees didn't give away the game; the Mariners took it from them. Seattle also reduced the Yankees' lead in the American League East to four games and increased its lead over Oakland in the A.L. West to two and a half games.</p>
        <p>There were no grievous mistakes, no stupid plays, nothing on which to hang the loss. ''There's not much you can do about it,'' said Torre, twisting his mouth in resignation.</p>
        <p>Owing to the difference in time zones, Boston's Pedro Martinez was just a few outs from pitching a no-hitter against Tampa Bay when the Yankees began their game here. Some of Pettitte's teammates were watching Martinez on television as Pettitte changed his T-shirt for the last time before taking the mound, reacting loudly when the Boston right-hander finally allowed a hit.</p>
        <p>Pettitte barely noticed; to Torre, Pettitte appeared especially focused, relaxed. ''He didn't seem fidgety at all,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Pettitte's fastball usually clocks in at about 88 or 89 miles an hour, but on Tuesday night, catcher Chris Turner would feel the thump of Pettitte's fastball and glance at the radar gun readings posted on the front of the right-field facade and see ''92 m.p.h.'' or ''93 m.p.h.''</p>
        <p>Pettitte's fastball had dramatic late movement, boring inside on right-handed hitters, and he had command of all his pitches. As a sinkerball pitcher who tries to goad hitters into imperfect contact, he tends to allow a lot of hits. When Pettitte held Seattle hitless through the fourth inning, and the fifth, Turner and Torre and others began to wonder if a no-hitter was possible.</p>
        <p>''I knew I had one,'' Pettitte said. ''Everybody in the stands was screaming at me when I was coming in. For me, I know I'm going to give up hits, so the sooner I can get that over and get that out of my head, the better it is for me. I felt good. I felt like I was going to have the game under control the whole way.''</p>
        <p>The Mariners had just three hits in the first seven innings and trailed by 3-0, although the deficit could have been much greater. The Seattle left-hander Jamie Moyer created land mines for himself by walking seven, but managed to retrace his way through jams, always sure not to give in and throw a fastball over the middle of the plate. The Yankees left two runners on in the first inning, two runners on in the second, and left the bases loaded in the fourth.</p>
        <p>Pettitte got the first out in the eighth before his masterpiece began to crumble. David Bell, Carlos Guillen and Rickey Henderson singled, none of the balls hit very hard.</p>
        <p>Seattle's Stan Javier pulled a line drive toward left field, in the direction of Luis Polonia, who had come into the game one inning earlier. David Justice, bothered by a strained groin since joining the Yankees, had asked to come out of the game after drawing a walk, and given the injury to Paul O'Neill, Polonia -- a poor defensive outfielder -- was the only option. Two days from now, the rosters will expand and Ryan Thompson will be recalled from Class AAA to be the badly needed late-inning defensive replacement.</p>
        <p>But it was Polonia playing left field when Javier hit the line drive, and Polonia rushed in, tried to make a sliding catch and failed. Each runner advanced a base on the single. Torre did not blame Polonia; last week, when Torre was asked about a play Polonia failed to make, he said a different outfielder could have produced a different result. In other words, you can't expect Polonia to do what he does not do well.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' lead had been trimmed to 3-1, the All-Star right-handed hitters Alex Rodriguez and Edgar Martinez were coming to bat and Torre called for Nelson, who struck out Rodriguez, throwing fastballs to get ahead in the count until he whiffed the shortstop with a slider. Nelson challenged Martinez with two fastballs, just out of the strike zone, then threw another one low and away. ''I know Nellie and I know he's got a good fastball, and I just wanted to hit it hard someplace,'' Martinez said. He drove it about three rows deep into the stands, igniting an explosive celebration and lifting the Mariners out of a dismal slump.</p>
        <p>Torre has criticized Nelson repeatedly in the past when he has pitched passively, relying on his slider. But this time, Torre felt Nelson had pitched aggressively, just missing on the first two pitches before being trumped by a great hitter. Torre walked over to Nelson in the dugout and patted him on the side and told him that he had done a good job. It was the third time in 11 days the Yankees lost a game in which they had held a lead of three or more runs.</p>
        <p>Nelson watched a videotape of Martinez's at-bat -- evidence of absolution, in a sense. But in the quiet misery of the Yankees' clubhouse, Nelson hardly felt exonerated. ''This is tough,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
