<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Software Being Offered By Microsoft to Catch AOL</title>
    <meta content="Y31ONL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/31/technology/31ONLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">America Online Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Radio Shack</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Best Buy Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DE1430F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Software Being Offered By Microsoft to Catch AOL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markoff, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Microsoft is preparing new marketing push for its Internet service, MSN, including mass-distributed software offering free hours for signing up, promotional deals with Radio Shack and Best Buy, broadband service and special software designed to make it easier to use Microsoft sites like MoneyCentral, Encarta and HomeAdviser; has had trouble gaining ground against America Online (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, it seems, nothing in the software world has been more ubiquitous than the America Online discs offering free online hours.</p>
        <p>Now Microsoft, which has had trouble gaining ground against AOL in the online-service market, is preparing a new marketing push to woo subscribers. And for the first time it will offer its own mass-distributed software for users of its Internet service, MSN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, it seems, nothing in the software world has been more ubiquitous than the America Online discs offering free online hours.</p>
        <p>Now Microsoft, which has had trouble gaining ground against AOL in the online-service market, is preparing a new marketing push to woo subscribers. And for the first time it will offer its own mass-distributed software for users of its Internet service, MSN.</p>
        <p>The campaign, to begin in October, will include more free hours for signing up, promotional deals with Radio Shack and Best Buy, broadband service and special software designed to make it easier to use Microsoft sites like MoneyCentral, Encarta and HomeAdvisor.</p>
        <p>A test version of the program, to be called MSN Explorer, will be available for downloading on Thursday from MSN.com. Once the campaign is officially begun, the software will also be distributed on discs in the fall.</p>
        <p>The new software, which requires about five megabytes of storage, is intended to offer a single point of entry for new users for all Web and Internet activities.</p>
        <p>The idea, according to Yusuf Mehdi, who is in charge of marketing for MSN, is to make it easier to sign up for MSN and for improved features like Internet search, access to specialized content areas and electronic shopping.</p>
        <p>MSN Explorer has a new look-and-feel, or user interface, he said, based on an internal Microsoft effort code-named Mars, which will also guide design of other Microsoft products.</p>
        <p>Still, Microsoft, which now claims three million Internet-access subscribers, faces a daunting task in catching the leader, AOL, which reported a net gain of 750,000 subscribers the last three months compared with 450,000 for Microsoft.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Microsoft executives who have long extolled Microsoft's leadership in software features are trying to turn MSN Explorer's paucity of features into an advantage.</p>
        <p>Version 5.0 of America Online's software has 138 options that make it confusing, a Microsoft executive said. The new MSN Explorer program has far fewer choices.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
