<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="31DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E7DC1430F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gap Says Sales in August To Decline a Surprising 14%  Gap stunned investors by announcing after the stock market closed that sales in stores open at least a year, a key industry measurement, would decline 14 percent in August, well below what most analysts expected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gap Says Sales in August To Decline a Surprising 14%  Gap stunned investors by announcing after the stock market closed that sales in stores open at least a year, a key industry measurement, would decline 14 percent in August, well below what most analysts expected.</p>
        <p>The Gap's announcement is more remarkable because it comes after a series of highly atypical stumbles. The company had a rare earnings disappointment in the first quarter, and then announced a more pronounced earnings shortfall in the second quarter and predicted that earnings would be lower than analysts expected for the entire year. [Page C2.]</p>
        <p>Mexico Ordered to Pay Damages  An international tribunal that worked to arbitrate a cross-border dispute between an American company, Metalclad, and the Mexican government ordered Mexico to pay nearly $17 million in damages. Citing investor protection provisions of the North American Free Trade Agreement, the tribunal found that the government's actions amounted to an expropriation because they prevented Metalclad from enjoying the full use of the hazardous waste treatment and disposal site it constructed. Shares of Metalclad rose 6 cents, to $4.31. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Blue Chips Drop on Profit Concerns  Blue-chip stocks dropped on concern about profits at manufacturing companies. The Dow Jones industrial average dropped 112.09 points, or 1 percent, to 11,103.01, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index lost 7.25 points, to 1,502.59. The Nasdaq composite index rose 21.64 points, to 4,103.81. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Intel Sues Broadcom in Patent Case  Intel filed a lawsuit accusing Broadcom of ''a carefully crafted plan'' to build its business in cable and high-speed networking products by violating Intel patents. [C20.]</p>
        <p>A Robot That Builds a Robot  For the first time, scientists have created a robot that designs and builds other robots, almost entirely without human help. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Judge Rejects MP3.com Argument  A federal judge rejected an argument by MP3.com that the Universal Music Group is improperly pursuing a copyright infringement claim against the company as a means of driving a potential rival out of business. [C20.]</p>
        <p>Frankfurt Exchange Standing Pat  Werner G. Seifert, the head of the Frankfurt stock market, refused to sweeten the terms of a proposed merger with the London Stock Exchange, dismissing a rival bid of $1.2 billion by OM Gruppen of Sweden as ''ridiculous and derisory.'' The unexpected, and hostile, bid has at least temporarily blocked the planned merger with Deutsche Borse. [C4.]</p>
        <p>SBC and BellSouth Deal Approved  SBC Communications and BellSouth won Justice Department approval to create the nation's second-largest mobile-phone company after agreeing to sell overlapping properties in 16 markets with 20 million people. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Leading Indicators Fell 0.1% in July  The index of leading economic indicators fell 0.1 percent in July, the third consecutive monthly drop, an industry group said. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Boom Has Not Made Up Earlier Loss  What is too often ignored in the nation's booming economy is that this remarkable performance has not yet compensated for the persistent erosion of the income of male workers since the early 1970's. Women have had to fill the breach, but while their wages have risen substantially on average, their pay remains about 20 percent below what men earn. Jeff Madrick: Economic Scene. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
