<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shifting Patterns That Flow And Stretch in the Open Air</title>
    <meta content="31ZIG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Downtown Dance Festival (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Battery Dance Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollander, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFDD1730F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shifting Patterns That Flow And Stretch in the Open Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews performance by Jonathan Hollander and Battery Dance Company, at Downtown Dance Festival in Battery Park; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the missions of Jonathan Hollander and his Battery Dance Company is to present companies that might not otherwise be seen in New York City. One such troupe is the Zig Zag Ballet, a year-old group based in Stamford, Conn., that performed on Tuesday afternoon at Mr. Hollander's Downtown Dance Festival in Battery Park. Founded a year ago by Brett Raphael, Zig Zag is an ensemble of stylish dancers who look ready for anything. That was just as well, given the range of the two works they performed.</p>
        <p>Darrell Moultrie's stylish new ''Pulse,'' a witty jazz ballet set to a witty, pounding jazz-flavored rock score by United Future Organization, more than held its own on the open-air stage in the visually busy park setting. In part that was due to the dancers' simple, stylish black trunks, tops and leotards designed by Elena Comendador. But Mr. Moultrie, a promising choreographer, is obviously someone to watch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the missions of Jonathan Hollander and his Battery Dance Company is to present companies that might not otherwise be seen in New York City. One such troupe is the Zig Zag Ballet, a year-old group based in Stamford, Conn., that performed on Tuesday afternoon at Mr. Hollander's Downtown Dance Festival in Battery Park. Founded a year ago by Brett Raphael, Zig Zag is an ensemble of stylish dancers who look ready for anything. That was just as well, given the range of the two works they performed.</p>
        <p>Darrell Moultrie's stylish new ''Pulse,'' a witty jazz ballet set to a witty, pounding jazz-flavored rock score by United Future Organization, more than held its own on the open-air stage in the visually busy park setting. In part that was due to the dancers' simple, stylish black trunks, tops and leotards designed by Elena Comendador. But Mr. Moultrie, a promising choreographer, is obviously someone to watch.</p>
        <p>The group piece opened with a stretching, oozing solo for Chikako Inoue, danced in silence. Slowly the ballet's other nine dancers spilled out from the sides, folding in and out around Ms. Inoue and then flowing off the stage again. That look of flow, ooze and stretch continued throughout ''Pulse,'' with elegantly ordered lines and wedges of dancers forming shifting patterns that moved like strong apposite river currents. Mr. Moultrie seems to know how to make handsome patterns without appearing to strive for neatness.</p>
        <p>The score's second and third sections included bits of what sounded like dialogue transplanted from a gritty 1940's detective film and a science fiction movie. It all made a nutty kind of sense, in part because of Mr. Moultrie's easy choreographic authority and the assured jazz-ballet style of the dancers. The lead cast was completed by Brian Carey Chung and Marcela Figueroa.</p>
        <p>Ann Marie DeAngelo's ''Crisis,'' set to music by Micky Hart and Gandarvic Harmonic Choir, was far too busy and diffuse for this setting. It was also never quite clear what the religious allusions were meant to add up to. William Isaac and James Samson were latter-day Pieta figures Jae Hyong Kwak seemed to be an angel. And too much was going on choreographically to make much impact. The fine company also included Michele Golden, Sunday Jackson, Luciano Lazzarotto, Anna Mikhailenko and Lisa Tachick, a performer of special warmth.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
