<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="31MBRF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DB1430F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: $3 MILLION FOR HARLEM LIBRARY  A Harlem branch of the New York Public Library will get $3.2 million in city money for renovations, according to a plan to be announced today by City Councilman Bill Perkins. The branch, on West 115th Street, will also receive $500,000 from the Helena Rubinstein Foundation. The landmarked three-story library is one of 65 built with funds from the industrialist Andrew Carnegie in 1901. The renovations are to include a new floor plan and an elevator. Construction is scheduled to begin in 2002.</p>
        <p>Tara Bahrampour (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: $3 MILLION FOR HARLEM LIBRARY  A Harlem branch of the New York Public Library will get $3.2 million in city money for renovations, according to a plan to be announced today by City Councilman Bill Perkins. The branch, on West 115th Street, will also receive $500,000 from the Helena Rubinstein Foundation. The landmarked three-story library is one of 65 built with funds from the industrialist Andrew Carnegie in 1901. The renovations are to include a new floor plan and an elevator. Construction is scheduled to begin in 2002.</p>
        <p>Tara Bahrampour (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: FORMER ART DEALER SENTENCED  Andrew Crispo, once a prominent art dealer, was sentenced yesterday to 85 months in federal prison for extortion. After serving three years in prison for tax evasion, Mr. Crispo declared bankruptcy in 1996. Prosecutors said that he became enraged at the handling of the bankruptcy case by Sandra E. Mayerson, a lawyer who advised the court-appointed bankruptcy trustee, and that he threatened to kidnap her daughter. Mr. Crispo was convicted and imprisoned last October. At yesterday's hearing, Judge Alvin K. Hellerstein of United States District Court also ordered Mr. Crispo to pay a $45,000 fine and $45,000 in restitution to Ms. Mayerson.</p>
        <p>John Sullivan (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: DROP IN UNEMPLOYMENT  Among the nation's largest cities, New York and Newark reported the steepest drops in unemployment over the last year, the federal Bureau of Labor Statistics reported yesterday. In both cities, the jobless rate fell 1.2 percentage points, to 4.1 percent in Newark and to 5.4 percent in New York. But New York still has the third-highest unemployment rate among major metropolitan areas, after Los Angeles and Riverside, Calif.</p>
        <p>Leslie Eaton (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: PEDESTRIAN KILLED  A 25-year-old pedestrian was killed in a hit-and-run accident on the Lower East Side early yesterday, the police said. They said the pedestrian, Val M. Kadievitch, a truck driver from Illinois, was returning to his parked truck about 4:30 a.m. after eating breakfast when he was struck by a truck near the intersection of Delancey and Ludlow Streets. He died shortly after he was taken to Beth Israel Medical Center. The driver of the truck that struck him fled, the police said.</p>
        <p>Elissa Gootman (NYT)</p>
        <p>HAVERSTRAW: ROCKLAND-WESTCHESTER FERRY  Gov. George E. Pataki presided yesterday over the opening of a ferry service from Rockland County to Westchester County for Metro North connections to Grand Central Terminal in Manhattan. For $3 each way, commuters can take the ferry from Haverstraw to Ossining, where they can connect to express trains. The trip from Haverstraw to Grand Central, including the 25-minute boat ride across 2.5 miles of the Hudson River, is estimated to take 80 minutes, less time than travel by car or train alone. Regular morning and evening peak service is to begin on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Al Baker (NYT)</p>
        <p>FORT EDWARD: TOWN EVACUATED  About 800 residents were evacuated from their homes Tuesday night and 25 were treated at hospitals, mostly for respiratory problems, after a rail car began leaking ammonia vapor in Fort Edward, a town 43 miles northeast of Albany. Fire officials said some of the injured were children who suffered asthma symptoms triggered by ammonia vapors and stress. None of the injuries were thought to be serious. A 30,000-gallon tank from Canadian Terra International began leaking vapor, possibly because of a defective valve.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>NEWARK: RULING ON RUNWAY INCIDENT  The Federal Aviation Administration has determined that a July 19 incident in which an American TransAir plane crossed a runway on which a Continental aircraft had been cleared to take off was more than likely a pilot error and not the result of faulty directions by air traffic controllers. Arlene Salac, an F.A.A. spokeswoman, said yesterday that the incident would be reviewed by the agency's flight standards division, which has jurisdiction over the certification of pilots.</p>
        <p>Ronald Smothers (NYT)</p>
        <p>MAHWAH: COLLEGE DELAYS OPENING  Ramapo College of New Jersey will delay the start of its fall semester because bacteria were discovered in the school's water supply. The college will pump large amounts of chlorine through its pipes and is advising people not to drink water from the system until the problem is cleared up. Classes originally scheduled to begin next Wednesday will instead begin on Sept. 11. The contamination was discovered after tests were conducted at the newly constructed Maple Hall. The college had no immediate explanation.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>WATERBURY: FUNERAL FOR SLAIN FIREFIGHTER  Hundreds of firefighters paid their last respects yesterday to Jaime Quinones, left, a 38-year-old Waterbury firefighter killed in a weekend shooting rampage. Wearing black bands across their badges, the firefighters lined the street outside the Immaculate Conception Church as Engine 10 carried the coffin of Mr. Quinones beneath crossed aerial ladders. Mr. Quinones was one of three people killed by a gunman, Mark Cote, on Saturday. Mr. Cote then killed himself.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: GOOD MARKS IN GUN SURVEY  Connecticut's gun-control laws are the strictest in the tristate region and among the strictest in the nation, according to a Washington-based advocacy group, Handgun Control Inc. In Connecticut, which got a grade of A-minus from the group, the police can get a warrant to seize guns from people deemed a threat. New York was rated B-plus, up from a B, because of new laws signed by Gov. George E. Pataki requiring trigger locks, new techniques to link fired bullets to the original handguns, and buyer background checks at gun shows. New Jersey received a B, as it did last year. The national average is C-minus.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
