<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLINTON HANDLED MILITARY POORLY, CHENEY CONTENDS</title>
    <meta content="31CHEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5D91430F932A0575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLINTON HANDLED MILITARY POORLY, CHENEY CONTENDS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Aug. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dick Cheney, Republican vice-presidential candidate and former defense secretary, charges that Pres Clinton has run down military built up by past Republican administrations, speech, Atlanta; holds military is stretched over too many foreign theaters and hampered by low morale, low pay, inadequate training and unreliable weapons and equipment; charges Clinton neglects national defense to point where planners are unsure United States can meet stated goals of being ready to fight two medium-size conflicts at same time; defense analysts see some weakening of military, but hold Cheney exaggerates problems and ignores positive trends under Clinton; text; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential candidate and former defense secretary, delivered a harsh assessment today of the condition of the armed forces under President Clinton, accusing him of ''running down'' a military that has succeeded in recent conflicts only because of the military buildup of past Republican administrations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney said the American military was stretched over too many foreign theaters and hampered by low morale, low pay, inadequate training and unreliable weapons and equipment. He accused Mr. Clinton, and by association Vice President Al Gore, of neglecting the national defense to the point where military planners were no longer certain that the United States could meet its stated goals of being prepared to fight two medium-size conflicts at the same time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential candidate and former defense secretary, delivered a harsh assessment today of the condition of the armed forces under President Clinton, accusing him of ''running down'' a military that has succeeded in recent conflicts only because of the military buildup of past Republican administrations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney said the American military was stretched over too many foreign theaters and hampered by low morale, low pay, inadequate training and unreliable weapons and equipment. He accused Mr. Clinton, and by association Vice President Al Gore, of neglecting the national defense to the point where military planners were no longer certain that the United States could meet its stated goals of being prepared to fight two medium-size conflicts at the same time.</p>
        <p>''Decisions made today shape the forces of tomorrow,'' he told several hundred veterans and political supporters in a hotel ballroom here. ''That is why we were able to win the gulf war -- because we were commanding a military that had been rebuilt in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>''And that is why the current administration has been able to conduct its vast deployments, from Baghdad to Belgrade. The ships and planes were ready. The pilots and crewmen were prepared. The missiles, the ammunition, the equipment and the men and women to use them were all there. That is the military they inherited. The question today is what future presidents will inherit.'' [Excerpts, Page A18.]</p>
        <p>Defense analysts acknowledged several of Mr. Cheney's arguments, but cautioned that he exaggerated some of the criticisms and ignored positive trends in the military under the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of valid points in the speech -- things aren't quite as good as they were under Cheney,'' said Michael O'Hanlon, a defense policy specialist at the Brookings Institution in Washington. ''But he greatly overstates the case.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's appearance, which was scheduled only in the last few days, seemed to signal a shift in tactics. Mr. Cheney's aides had said he would spend the week talking about education. But after more than a week in which the Republican campaign found itself defending its policies on tax and health care, Mr. Cheney returned to more familiar ground for the party with an appeal on national security.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney also seemed to be trying to play the role that Republicans had hoped he would take in the campaign -- lending his age, experience and authority as a former defense secretary to the Republican presidential nominee, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas. Indeed, Mr. Cheney not only framed his remarks as the words of the defense secretary who helped defeat Iraq, but portrayed himself as a man who had returned to public life in large part because of his desire to repair the damage he said had been done to the military.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney offered few concrete proposals in his speech today. But in the past the Bush campaign has called for a $20 billion increase in the military budget for research and development from 2002 through 2006, for directing the Defense Department to spend a fifth of its procurement budget on new technologies and for increasing the recently enacted pay raise for members of the armed services by a further $1 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore responded tonight to Mr. Cheney's criticisms. ''We have the strongest military in the world by far, and we reversed the decline that began in the Bush-Quayle years,'' Mr. Gore told reporters. ''And I have advocated additional steps to continue the rebuilding and strengthening to make sure it's always the best and always more than adequate.''</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign has said that the vice president advocates a 10-year, $127 billion increase in spending on military salaries, training and modernization, and that amount may increase when Mr. Gore adjusts his budget proposals to reflect a growing surplus.</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Cheney also sought to counter the Democratic response to the criticism directed by Mr. Bush at President Clinton's military policies. Since those attacks began in recent weeks, Mr. Gore and his running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut, accused Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney of denigrating the American military, which they said sent a bad signal to allies and potential adversaries.</p>
        <p>''To point out that our military has been overextended, taken for granted, and neglected -- that is no criticism of the military,'' Mr. Cheney said today. ''That is a criticism of a president and a vice president, and the record they have built together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney said that Mr. Gore had expressed concerns that criticism about the military would send the wrong message to potential adversaries, and he used it to make another dig at the Clinton administration. ''If our potential adversaries have received any 'wrong messages' recently,'' he said, ''it was not from the newspapers, but from the nuclear lab at Los Alamos. And what lesson do they draw from the fact that this administration has failed to safeguard our nation's most vital national secrets?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney attributed the Clinton administration's military successes, like the NATO bombing that led to the withdrawal of of Serb forces from Kosovo, and the air strikes on Iraq, to the military buildup under Presidents Ronald Reagan and George Bush. And he said that the Republicans in Congress deserved the credit for recent increases in the defense budget.</p>
        <p>While many of the examples Mr. Cheney cited echoed his past remarks -- that fewer units were ready for combat, recruitment was down, aging equipment posed a danger and low pay was damaging morale -- he cast his criticisms in a much more partisan light.</p>
        <p>''It is the record of eight years of stewardship over the American armed forces by President Clinton and Vice President Gore,'' he said. ''Eight years of neglect and misplaced priorities. Eight years of multiplying missions and unclear goals.  Eight years during which the enemies of freedom have not been idle. Eight years is a long time -- and eight years is long enough.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Hanlon, the Brookings Institution analyst,  criticized Mr. Cheney for not proposing a specific alternative for overseas commitments or enlarging the military. ''As much as Cheney says we've overdeployed and overcut, there's been no proposal by the campaign to reverse either of those policies,'' Mr. O'Hanlon said. ''The idea they'll review U.S. commitments and find any big cutbacks is illusory.''</p>
        <p>A former national security budget specialist under Mr. Clinton, Gordon Adams, said many of the problems Mr. Cheney cited, including substandard military housing, was prevalent during the Bush administration.</p>
        <p>''He's selectively culled barnacles of the readiness issue, but many are out of context,'' said Mr. Adams, who now directs the security policy studies program at George Washington University. ''This is not neglect, I'm sorry.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Adams said the former defense secretary was not giving the military enough credit.</p>
        <p>''When called upon, this force has performed spectacularly well,'' Mr. Adams said. ''To the rest of the world, the U.S. military isn't just the toughest kid on the block, it's the toughest by far.''</p>
        <p>Pentagon officials have countered Mr. Cheney's assertion that morale is declining, citing improvements in the number of troops re-enlisting, which they attribute to two years of increases in pay and benefits. They have also pointed to improvements this year in recruiting, although reserve recruiting has declined and there has been a shortage in commissioned officers, with a drastic increase in the number of captains leaving the Army.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney offered few concrete proposals to bolster the nation's military in his speech, although he did say that a Bush-Cheney administration would spend more money researching new technologies and deploying missile defenses, that it would raise pay for the troops and improve their housing and schools.</p>
        <p>To underscore the importance of what aides billed as a major policy speech, Mr. Cheney's aides encouraged reporters to interview another gulf war colleague of Mr. Cheney's --  Colin L Powell, the retired general who led the joint chiefs of staff. ''I share his view,'' General Powell said in a telephone interview. ''We still have a great force, and I don't think anybody would say we don't. But we owe them everything they need to get the jobs done.''</p>
        <p>And Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, released a statement in support of the speech. ''Congress deserves a share of the blame for this problem for annually treating the defense budget as just another pork barrel,'' Mr. McCain said. ''But the lion's share of our failure belongs rightfully to the man honored to serve as commander-in-chief.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps Mr. Cheney's most pointed dig at the opposition came when he quoted an ''observer of the military'' in his speech.</p>
        <p>''One observer of the military,'' he said, ''had this to say last year: 'Our military faces readiness problems,' he cautioned, 'including falling recruitment, and retention in critical skill areas; aging equipment that costs more to keep operating at acceptable levels of reliability; a need for more support services for a force with a high percentage of married personnel; and frequent deployments.' ''</p>
        <p>''That is a fair summary of the problem,'' Mr. Cheney said, ''and it came from Senator Joseph Lieberman.''</p>
        <p>In His Own Words</p>
        <p>DICK CHENEY</p>
        <p>Remarks prepared for delivery yesterday at an Atlanta hotel at an event sponsored by the Southern Center for International Relations:</p>
        <p>''Our military today is overused and underresourced. Defense spending today is lower as a percentage of G.N.P. than at any time since 1940 -- the year before the attack on Pearl Harbor. At the same time, overseas deployments have multiplied, stretching the services to the limit, and causing shortages of spare parts and equipment. All of this has brought on serious problems of readiness, recruiting, retention and morale.</p>
        <p>Let me be specific. Over the last decade, commitments worldwide have gone up 300 percent, while our military forces have been cut by 40 percent.</p>
        <p>As of January 1993, 85 percent of Air Force combat units were fully ready for their mission. Today that number is at 65 percent. Part of the problem, according to the secretary of the Air Force, is that pilots are flying more missions on older aircraft. The average plane is 20 years old. And even with new planes coming online, by the year 2015, the average plane will be 30 years old.</p>
        <p>The Army reports that 40 percent of its helicopter fleet is not up to performing its mission. The main reason is aging rotary-wing aircraft. The Army also reports a 'dramatic decline' in aviator experience. Flight hours of aviation battalion commanders have declined from an average of 2,000 hours 10 years ago to 1,000 today.</p>
        <p>Budget shortfalls have slowed some training missions and brought others to a complete stop, as when the U.S.S. Decatur was forced to return to port a month early this summer -- because there wasn't enough money for fuel. General Zinni, the recently retired commander of U.S. forces in the Persian Gulf, has said that our military has inadequate resources and too many commitments for the size of the force. Not long ago, he said that America would have trouble mounting another major operation like Desert Storm.</p>
        <p>In that conflict, we had no more effective weapons than the cruise missile, which destroyed the main power grid in Baghdad on the first night of the air war. It was among the weapons of choice in Kosovo as well. The Procurement Subcommittee of the House Armed Services Committee found that at the end of that campaign last year, the Navy had only enough cruise missiles to satisfy a little over half of what is required for two major theater wars . . . The Air Force was left with only one-tenth of what it needed. . . .</p>
        <p>For the fifth consecutive year, the Army and Navy will fail to meet their targets for commissioned officers. Both branches are facing a situation where junior officers are increasingly headed for the door. In a recent G.A.O. survey of more than a thousand officers and enlisted men, a majority said they intended to leave rather than stay and pursue a career. Why are they leaving? For many, the question really is, why stay -- when training is inadequate, equipment is lacking, units are undermanned and forces are deployed in more than a hundred places across the globe, often with unclear missions and inadequate support? . . .</p>
        <p>A much easier call is where to place responsibility for all of this. It is the record of eight years of stewardship over the American armed forces by President Clinton and Vice President Gore. Eight years of neglect and misplaced priorities. Eight years of multiplying missions and unclear goals. . . .</p>
        <p>They claim to have turned things around, but the only thing that has kept it from falling further has been Congress, which has added $50 billion to the administration's defense budget requests over the last several years.</p>
        <p>The needs of our nation's defense, and the needs of our defenders, are not merely relevant in a national campaign. They must be front and center. For his part, Governor Bush has been raising these issues for more than a year. He has offered specific proposals to rebuild the strength and morale of the armed forces, and make them fully capable of meeting every challenge the new century will bring.</p>
        <p>Seizing this opportunity will require not just spending more, but spending more wisely. It means giving today's military what it needs. It means beginning to create the military of the future, by capitalizing on new technologies and placing greater emphasis on R &amp; D. It means accelerating research and deployment of missile defenses.</p>
        <p>But the first order of business is to renew the bond of trust between the commander in chief and the military. This includes very practical steps, like higher pay, improved housing, and better schools for their children. It certainly means reviewing our overseas deployments in dozens of countries, and insisting that deployments have well-defined objectives. It means keeping faith with our veterans, by providing first-rate health care and treating them with dignity. Above all, it means respecting the military and earning their trust in return.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
