<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Reviews Draft Report On 1996 T.W.A. Explosion</title>
    <meta content="23TWA.$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trans World Airlines</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Transportation Safety Board</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zuckerman, Laurence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E2DA1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Reviews Draft Report On 1996 T.W.A. Explosion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURENCE ZUCKERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zuckerman, Laurence</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Transportation Safety Board begins two-day meeting to review a draft of its final report on the cause of the crash of Trans World Airlines Flight 800 over Long Island in July 1996; investigators say they have reached 'inescapable conclusion' that airplane was ripped apart in midair when its center wing fuel tank exploded minutes after takeoff; believe a short circuit sent a surge of electricity into the tank through wiring of a fuel gauge (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Opening the final chapter in the longest and most expensive crash investigation in its 33-year history, the National Transportation Safety Board began a two-day meeting today to review a draft of its final report on the cause of the crash of Trans World Airlines Flight 800 over Long Island four years ago.</p>
        <p>Addressing the five-member board, investigators said they had reached what one official called the ''inescapable conclusion'' that the  Boeing 747 was ripped apart in midair when its center wing fuel tank exploded minutes after it departed from Kennedy International Airport bound for Paris on July 17, 1996. All 230 people aboard were killed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Opening the final chapter in the longest and most expensive crash investigation in its 33-year history, the National Transportation Safety Board began a two-day meeting today to review a draft of its final report on the cause of the crash of Trans World Airlines Flight 800 over Long Island four years ago.</p>
        <p>Addressing the five-member board, investigators said they had reached what one official called the ''inescapable conclusion'' that the  Boeing 747 was ripped apart in midair when its center wing fuel tank exploded minutes after it departed from Kennedy International Airport bound for Paris on July 17, 1996. All 230 people aboard were killed.</p>
        <p>In his opening statement, James E. Hall, chairman of the safety board, said there was no evidence of a criminal act, despite initial suspicions and trace amounts of explosive residue found on three of the tens of thousands of pieces of the plane's wreckage. He strongly condemned critics who maintain that the government is hiding the fact that Flight 800 was downed by a missile or a bomb.</p>
        <p>''I take exception to those who consistently distort the record and persist in making unfounded charges of a cover-up,'' he said, addressing spectators who included family members of the victims. ''They do a disservice to us all but most especially to you, the T.W.A. 800 families, who have suffered so much in this tragedy.''</p>
        <p>Summarizing the conclusions of the four-year investigation, Bernard S. Loeb, the director of the board's office of aviation safety, said that the atmosphere in the fuel tank at the time of the accident was easily capable of exploding with enough force to bring down the airplane.</p>
        <p>Yet despite extensive research and testing, investigators could not determine exactly what ignited the fuel vapors in the nearly empty tank, which had been heated to an explosive state while the 25-year-old jet sat baking in the sun for nearly three hours before taking off. After ruling out several possible ignition sources, Mr. Loeb said that investigators now believe that a short circuit sent a surge of electricity into the tank through the wiring of a fuel gauge.</p>
        <p>''We cannot be certain that this in fact occurred, but of all of the ignition scenarios that we considered, this scenario is the most likely,'' Mr. Loeb said.</p>
        <p>The point of the meeting, which was open to the public under a federal sunshine law, was to let board members question investigators about their 684-page draft report and make revisions. The meeting is expected to conclude on Wednesday, when the board is scheduled to vote to approve the final report and its safety recommendations. The board plans to release abstracts of the report immediately on its Web site, www.ntsb.gov. Internet users can monitor the board meeting live on the site. The full report will be made public in a few months.</p>
        <p>Many of the board's safety recommendations, relating to fuel tank flammability, potential sources of ignition and the maintenance of electrical wiring in older jets, were previously proposed to the Federal Aviation Administration, which was closely involved in the crash investigation. Indeed, the F.A.A. said it had already issued 37 directives to operators of a variety of aircraft models in the wake of the crash, the most sweeping actions in its history, according to the agency.</p>
        <p>The agency is now evaluating ways that the center fuel tank can be kept cooler. It is also studying how to formulate a rule that would direct aircraft operators to inject nitrogen into nearly empty fuel tanks to prevent combustion, regardless of the source of ignition.</p>
        <p>Much of the questioning by board members at today's meeting seemed intended to try to dispel suspicions of a conspiracy.</p>
        <p>Investigators said they considered the possibility of a bomb or missile early on but ruled it out because none of the wreckage showed the characteristic damage present after a high-energy explosion. In addition, there were no holes in the fuselage large enough to have been made by the impact of a missile, they said.</p>
        <p>The investigators theorize that the traces of explosives found on the three pieces of wreckage could have been placed on the jet when it was ferrying troops during the Persian Gulf war, during an explosive-detection exercise with bomb-sniffing dogs that occurred about one month before the crash, or after the crash during the salvage operation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
