<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sauvignon Blanc, a Jacques of All Trades</title>
    <meta content="23WINE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WINE TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wine Talk</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EEDE1F3EF930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sauvignon Blanc, a Jacques of All Trades</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prial, Frank J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank J Prial's Wine Talk column on sauvignon blancs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SAUVIGNON BLANC, the most versatile of white wines, comes in many guises. It can be an aperitif, light, sharp and refreshing; it can be a dinner wine with good body and lovely texture. It can be a magnificent, naturally sweet dessert wine, either on its own or, as it is in Sauternes, artfully blended with other grapes, usually semillon and muscadelle.</p>
        <p>A self-effacing grape, it often hides under other names. All Bordeaux white wines, both dry and sweet, use some sauvignon blanc; the rare Pavillon Blanc of Chateau Margaux is 100 percent sauvignon blanc, and the white of Chateau Haut-Brion is usually two-thirds semillon and a third sauvignon blanc.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SAUVIGNON BLANC, the most versatile of white wines, comes in many guises. It can be an aperitif, light, sharp and refreshing; it can be a dinner wine with good body and lovely texture. It can be a magnificent, naturally sweet dessert wine, either on its own or, as it is in Sauternes, artfully blended with other grapes, usually semillon and muscadelle.</p>
        <p>A self-effacing grape, it often hides under other names. All Bordeaux white wines, both dry and sweet, use some sauvignon blanc; the rare Pavillon Blanc of Chateau Margaux is 100 percent sauvignon blanc, and the white of Chateau Haut-Brion is usually two-thirds semillon and a third sauvignon blanc.</p>
        <p>In the Graves region of Bordeaux, sauvignon blanc is the predominant white grape. Once, it was routinely blended with semillon, a grape that makes a softer, honeyed style of wine, a style that was ignored by most of the world's wine markets. In recent years, sauvignon blanc has become more dominant in the Graves; the wines are fresher and more vibrant, and they have restored Bordeaux's reputation for good white wines.</p>
        <p>In the Loire Valley, along with chenin blanc, melon de Bourgogne (which is the grape of Muscadet) and gros plant, sauvignon blanc produces some of the world's best-known white wines. Sancerre is entirely sauvignon blanc, as are Pouilly-Fume and a host of wines from smaller communities like Quincy.</p>
        <p>Beginning with Cloudy Bay in the early 1990's, sauvignon blanc has become New Zealand's best-known wine. South Africa, too, has begun to produce top sauvignon blancs, beginning with Mulderbosch and Neil Ellis's Groenkloof Sauvignon.</p>
        <p>In this country, sauvignon blanc has followed two paths. The most successful American sauvignon blancs are, to me anyway, fashioned in the Bordeaux style -- the older Bordeaux style, which emphasizes softness and fullness and plays down the more acidic, vegetal style of Sancerre and Pouilly-Fume.</p>
        <p>The best-known American sauvignon blanc goes under a different name. Robert Mondavi makes it, and it's called fume blanc. One of Mr. Mondavi's signal achievements was the revival of sauvignon blanc in California. In the mid-1960's, he took what had been a sugary, bland wine with no varietal character, fermented it completely until it was dry, aged it in oak and then gave it its new name. A name, by the way, that he never registered, so that anyone could use it. When he started working with the grape, there were about 700 acres of it in California; now there are well over 10,000.</p>
        <p>The top of the Mondavi sauvignon blanc line is the Reserve Fume Blanc made from grapes from his most famous vineyard, To-Kalon in Oakville, Calif. The wine, which is all sauvignon blanc, except about 6 percent semillon, is barrel-fermented and aged for about a year in French oak. The result is a complex wine with intense flavors and a rich texture, full-bodied for a sauvignon blanc and with a long finish.</p>
        <p>It is a beautiful wine, diametrically opposed to what I like in a sauvignon blanc, which is lightness, no oak and plenty of vibrant acidity. I recently tasted six Mondavi sauvignon blancs, including three from California and three from Chile. Tasted blind, it turned out that my favorite was from the Mondavi ''Coastal'' group because it had at least some of the herbaceous characteristics of the wines from the Loire, New Zealand and South Africa but from hardly anyone in California.</p>
        <p>It is not a question of right and wrong, or of good and bad. Two distinct styles of sauvignon blanc have emerged, and each has its passionate advocates. To me, the lighter, herbaceous style is perfect with broiled fish and oysters, while the fuller California style is best savored as a sipping wine on a warm summer afternoon. But others prefer the more acidic style as an aperitif and the heavier, oakier style with food.</p>
        <p>The oaked versions, like Mondavi's fume blanc, Caymus Vineyards' Conundrum and Dry Creek Vineyards' fume blanc, match well with almost any dish that normally calls for chardonnay. The more acidic versions, like the French and New Zealand wines, will enhance most kinds of seafood and make perfect companions for a variety of cheeses. Red wine and cheese is the traditional combination. But many red wines are overwhelmend by sharp or pungent cheeses. Not so sauvignon blanc, particularly when matched with goat cheese. Loire goat cheeses like crottin de Chavignol seem to have been invented to go with the local white wines.</p>
        <p>Sancerre and Pouilly-Fume are easy to find in the United States, but domestic sauvignon blancs with the same mineral, herbaceous elements are in short supply. Even so, there are sauvignon blancs out there that display good varietal character. Philip Togni, in the Napa Valley, makes a bone-dry version; others to look for include J. Rochioli, in the Russian River area of Sonoma; Matanzas Creek in Sonoma; Brander Vineyard in Los Olivos; St. Supery in the Napa Valley; and Navarro Vineyards, in the Anderson Valley.</p>
        <p>In California, there are as many interpretations of the sauvignon blanc theme as there are wineries producing it. The trick is to find one you like. If nothing suits your fancy, do join me in the Loire Valley.</p>
        <p>WINE TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
