<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Is It Time To Hang Up the Pen?; 'It's My Last Book. Really. No, I Mean Really, Really.'</title>
    <meta content="23RETI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Binchy, Maeve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pilcher, Rosamunde</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3DB1F3EF930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2154" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Is It Time To Hang Up the Pen?; 'It's My Last Book. Really. No, I Mean Really, Really.'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maeve Binchy, 60, declares that she will not attempt another novel, and so does Rosamunde Pilcher, 75; retirement is a delicate issue for writers, so delicate that several writers sounded out on the topic refuse to discuss it; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There comes a moment in the twilight of literary careers when some popular authors feel compelled to reveal plot twists in their own lives that lead to unlikely denouements: pensions and retirement planning.</p>
        <p>As summer beckoned, the self-described airport author Maeve Binchy declared to headlines in London that her 12th book, ''Scarlet Feather,'' was her very last big novel. So millions of loyal readers should expect no more sprawling page-turners from this Irish bard of heartache, humor and transcontinental house-swapping.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There comes a moment in the twilight of literary careers when some popular authors feel compelled to reveal plot twists in their own lives that lead to unlikely denouements: pensions and retirement planning.</p>
        <p>As summer beckoned, the self-described airport author Maeve Binchy declared to headlines in London that her 12th book, ''Scarlet Feather,'' was her very last big novel. So millions of loyal readers should expect no more sprawling page-turners from this Irish bard of heartache, humor and transcontinental house-swapping.</p>
        <p>Ever.</p>
        <p>''I'm not at all a Frank Sinatra person who can be lured back,'' warned Ms. Binchy, 60, a former teacher and journalist whose best sellers, like ''Tara Road,'' have earned her Oprah Book Club celebrity, advances in the $10 million range and sales in her homeland that outstrip those of William Butler Yeats and Oscar Wilde.</p>
        <p>Ms. Binchy was followed by Rosamunde Pilcher, 75, who revealed that she was shaping the final chapter of a 50-year career that has produced several cozy best sellers about English hearth and home. Her latest, ''Winter Solstice,'' with 600,000 copies in print, soared to the top of the fiction best-seller list of The New York Times after St. Martin's Press published it this month.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I could write another,'' Mrs. Pilcher, whose latest book commanded an advance of more than $6 million, said in an interview. ''I hate publicity.''</p>
        <p>Such open declarations raise a delicate issue in the literary world, where there are no standard tribal retirement rituals. It is a long way from the universe of sports, which lavishes attention on its pensioners. Computer keyboards are not retired. Career best-seller records do not lead to teary stadium send-offs. The creative force that drives writing may still burn, but the energy to promote a book fades like the pitching arm of a middle-aged hurler. In some ways, mulling a writerly finale seems a bit morbid; or, as Mrs. Pilcher put it in a polite British accent, ''I don't think I thought about it anymore than my own death.''</p>
        <p>The retiring literary set is a group usually overlooked in favor of writers like Saul Bellow, who this year, at 85, delivered ''Ravelstein,'' his first major novel in more than a decade. '' The very notion of a pension is not suitable publishing-party conversation.</p>
        <p>''I think I've only discussed this with one other author,'' said Sidney Offit, 71, the author of more than a dozen books and the president of the Authors Guild Foundation, the educational arm of the Authors Guild. He added: ''Retirement depends on why people need to write. For some people, writing is the only world they control; it satisfies a therapeutic aim. Other people have a message they want to deliver and when they're done, they're out. Then there are people who write under the Sam Johnson dictum: 'Anyone who writes for anything other than money is a blockhead.' ''</p>
        <p>The issue is so touchy that some writers  refuse to discuss it. Sidney Sheldon, for example, declined to be interviewed for this article. At 83, he is publishing his 17th novel, ''The Sky Is Falling,'' next month.</p>
        <p>Ray Bradbury, who just turned 80, keeps writing despite the effects of a stroke he had months ago.</p>
        <p>''I wrote part of my novel while I was in the hospital, and I wrote a screenplay,'' he said in an interview. ''You want to live, don't you? If you don't give up, you don't die.'' Mr. Bradbury continues to deliver lectures from a wheelchair, and in the fall of 2001 he will publish a novel about a friendly vampire family called the Elliots, a work that he has been laboring on sporadically for about 55 years.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, Kurt Vonnegut, 77, insisted that his 19th book, ''Timequake,'' was the last in his almost 50-year career. Back then, he confessed relief that he had crossed the marathon finish line. But now his retirement is an issue that he declines to address. ''Well, I don't want to talk about that,'' he said from his summer home in Sagaponack,  a Hamptons retreat on the South Fork of Long Island that is the literary parallel to a Florida retirement community.</p>
        <p>Many older writers decide at some point to devote more time to their lives than to their characters. A prosperous Shakespeare is said to have retreated in perfect health to Stratford in his last two years and produced nothing, leaving others to finish his incomplete plays.</p>
        <p>Lately, even some middle-aged authors have felt compelled to seek short forms of semiretirement. At 45, the Scottish author Iain M. Banks, whose first novel was ''The Wasp Factory,'' announced a few months ago that he was taking a year off from a relentless writing schedule that has resulted in an annual novel or science fiction title for the last 16 years.</p>
        <p>''His wife wanted him to spend some time with her,'' explained Mic Cheetham, Mr. Banks's literary agent in London, who called the break a sabbatical. ''I don't know why some writers say they are retiring. Maybe to get people not to phone them? One of the things about writing is that it's such a very private business. But when you become a best-selling writer, it becomes very public, and everyone keeps asking, 'When's the next one?' Then everyone is completely astonished when you say you're taking a year off. It seems to me very normal.''</p>
        <p>The increasing rigors of a public literary life are often the deciding factor.</p>
        <p>Maeve Binchy's epiphany came as she was sitting at a book event beside another successful writer whom she would identify only as ''a very bad-tempered woman.''</p>
        <p>''She was drumming her fingers on the table,'' Ms. Binchy recalled. ''She kept saying: 'This food is terrible. There should be more people. This is too tiring. It's going on too long.' I thought, this discontented lady has written books, which is what we've always wanted to do. She's allowed this to get into her soul. And I said to myself, 'A little voice of warning, Maeve. Leave before you become like that.' I was really afraid that I would become one of the people to whom this was a treadmill.''</p>
        <p>Roaming the world on an international book tour was not easy on Ms. Binchy's  arthritis; the unending airport corridors tested her joints. Her readers seemed to be getting younger as she gazed out at them at book events. She wondered if she could keep up her appeal. And she and her husband, Gordon Snell, an author of children's books, were content with the state of their bank accounts and pensions and with their homes in London and a village outside Dublin.</p>
        <p>''I feel terribly young, and I feel 23 in my heart,'' said Ms. Binchy, who is published in the United States by Delacorte. ''But I have to realize that the world has changed very much, and so have people's dreams and aspirations. I think a sensible woman would realize that it's hard to keep a finger on the pulse of the young today. It's quite a different lifestyle. They're so much more traveled, so much less insular.''</p>
        <p>''Tara Road,'' for example, one of her most popular books in the United States, explores the fates of two young women who change their lives by swapping their homes in Ireland and America for the summer.</p>
        <p>Ms. Binchy added that she would write some short stories, which did not produce the same sort of publishing pressures as her bread-and-butter full-length novels, like ''Circle of Friends,'' which was made into a movie starring Minnie Driver. She has also dropped a column that she had been writing for The Irish Times.</p>
        <p>''I told my publishers very honestly, from the start, that I was going to do this,'' said Ms. Binchy, who has since retreated on an Alaskan cruise. ''I gave them six months'  notice, but they didn't really believe me. I think the thinking is that I could be persuaded to go back. I couldn't go on in this kind of way, and I don't want more money.''</p>
        <p>There is no doubt that publishers and editors prefer to consider retirement announcements as figments of fertile imaginations and to believe that ultimately writers will be unable to resist the muse, and the money.</p>
        <p>''It is hard for a born storyteller like Rosamunde Pilcher or Maeve Binchy not to tell a story,'' said Thomas Dunne, Mrs. Pilcher's editor of more than 20 years. ''At least, that's what the publishers hope, and there are millions of dollars at stake for them, of course. If you ask Ros Pilcher right now, she'll tell you that she doesn't see another book on the horizon. I think that is entirely possible, but I also believe that she will return to writing after a bit, if only because she enjoys the process.''</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Dunne who patiently persuaded Mrs. Pilcher to write another book after she finished ''Coming Home,'' which sold more than 500,000 copies and provoked their first discussions about retirement. Mr. Dunne called the author at her home in Perthshire, Scotland, in 1997 to suggest an idea for a novel set at Christmastime. Eventually, the idea took hold, and Mrs. Pilcher delivered ''Winter Solstice,'' which happens to include a 60-ish character, a former actress who is seeking retirement.</p>
        <p>''Once I started to think about the characters, I had them in my mind and I had to write their story,'' said Mrs. Pilcher, whose daily efforts would take up part of her morning and afternoon, as well as her dog walks, in which she would mull over plot and character. ''Writing is work, but it's also a compulsion, and once you get your characters on paper, you can't abandon them. You have to respond to them.''</p>
        <p>The creative process was stimulating, she said, but she doesn't consider writing a pleasurable pastime. ''It's a job that you have to do,'' she said. ''But it's still demanding and draining, and I'm very tired at the end of a day's work.'' She vowed that with the completion of the book she would retreat into a ''world of domesticity'' populated by her husband, Graham; their four children; their grandchildren; their friends; and their dachshunds, Daisy and Polly.</p>
        <p>She is not touring the United States to promote her latest novel, adding that the task of selling a book is wearing. ''I'm really quite a private person, and I find it intrusive,'' she continued. ''My husband has a new hip, and all of this happened while I'm trying to juggle 24 balls. I never found it this way before. I suppose when I was younger, I had more energy, and I wasn't looking after a sick husband. This time I think the time has come to hang up the hat, but I'm not going to say that definitely.''</p>
        <p>Almost two years ago, Carl H. Klaus, the founding director of the University of Iowa's nonfiction writing program, decided that he also needed a break after a four-year effort on his latest book.</p>
        <p>He treated his literary exhaustion with a regimen of reading, traveling, and tending his prized vegetable garden of cherry belle radishes and Oregon giant snow peas.</p>
        <p>''But the urge to be writing again returned before the year was out,'' said Mr. Klaus, 68, who suspects that retiring authors are more fatigued by publishing pressures than by writing itself. ''It's irrepressible and comes from the same deep well that I drew upon when a student asked if I had any last words at the end of my last course at Iowa -- and without thinking, I told her, 'Just keep writing.' ''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Klaus is back at the keyboard, pounding out the chapters of a book of essays. He is fully recovered from the rigors of writing his last title, a memoir called ''Taking Retirement: A Beginner's Diary.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
