<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That New York Feeling: Squeezed; It's not your imagination. It really is more crowded.</title>
    <meta content="23SQUE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/23/living/23SQUE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4DB1F3EF930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1390" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That New York Feeling: Squeezed; It's not your imagination. It really is more crowded.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amanda Hesser on crowding in New York City restaurants says many have begun to feel like subway cars at rush hour; says cramped space, long signature of New York dining, has become brand of its own being sought after by restaurateurs in other cities; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S that special something that makes dining in New York City unlike dining in any other place.</p>
        <p>Some call it energy. Some call it buzz.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S that special something that makes dining in New York City unlike dining in any other place.</p>
        <p>Some call it energy. Some call it buzz.</p>
        <p>New Yorkers call it crowding.</p>
        <p>And it's not just their imagination. With real estate at a premium and an economy that's enabling more people to eat out more often, many restaurants have begun to feel like subway cars at rush hour.</p>
        <p>A liberal building code hasn't helped. Nor has an army of designers and restaurant managers, who have finessed the art of squeezing more people into their seating plans. And now, strange as it seems, New York City restaurant crowding has become a brand of its own, sought after by restaurateurs in other cities.</p>
        <p>Here, the public spaces in a restaurant must allow 12 square feet per person, including diners and staff. Maximum occupancy is calculated depending on the square footage, the number of fire exits, their location and their width.</p>
        <p>This seems fairly generous until you compare it with cities like San Francisco and Atlanta, where the limit is 15 square feet per person, or even Philadelphia, where it's 13 square feet per person. Bar areas are much tighter. In Philadelphia, a bar must allow 9 square feet per person; in Atlanta, it's 7. In New York, the space is measured by counter length: 18 inches of it per person.</p>
        <p>''We do a lot of restaurants out of state,'' said Warren Ashworth, a partner in Bogdanow Partners Architects, a Manhattan design firm, ''and I never see a place that's packed the way some places are here.''</p>
        <p>Cramped restaurants have long been a signature of New York dining. The ''21'' Club, which opened in 1929, has always had its back wall of banquettes. Lining walls with banquettes increases the number of tables that can fit in a room. What's remarkable about the tables at ''21'', though, is how closely they are arranged. In order for diners against the wall to get up from the table, a waiter must come by and pull the table out into the room. Now, it seems every bistro in town has the same plan.</p>
        <p>''New Yorkers are much more sophisticated, much more tolerant, and docile actually,'' said Jeffrey Beers, a Manhattan architect who designed China Grill and Calle Ocho. ''They don't mind being bumped around a little bit; in fact, they enjoy it.'' That jab to the back of the head when you're taking a bite of your crab cakes might even be a sign of warmth.</p>
        <p>David Rockwell, a partner in the Rockwell Group, whose designs include Nobu, the Monkey Bar and Vong, said: ''There's a reason you're not eating at home, where you have all the privacy you need. You're eating out as much for the social experience as for a dining experience.''</p>
        <p>But New York diners are also sensitive and, as Mr. Rockwell added, designers are constantly struggling to find that elusive place between ''sardines and Siberia.''</p>
        <p>Restaurateurs spend a lot of time searching for it, too. In the process, walkways get narrower, corners are maximized, and breathing room is kept at a premium.</p>
        <p>A dining room laid out too generously can feel dead. If the tables are six or seven feet apart, Mr. Beers said, ''It's difficult to get a buzz going. It yields a quiet sit-up-straight kind of restaurant.''</p>
        <p>Energy in a restaurant has become a kind of commodity. Many New York designers working in other cities have been asked to come up with a ''New York feel.''</p>
        <p>''They associate that with a slightly tighter table spacing than you might get if you were following an industry standard,'' said Paul Bentel, a partner at Bentel &amp; Bentel Architects/Planners in Locust Valley, N.Y. By industry standards, Mr. Bentel said, tables for four may be spaced five or six feet apart. In New York, he would reduce that to as little as 24 inches, ''to get the kind of energy they associate with a New York restaurant.''</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, though, these same designers are not trying to crunch space down to the limit of 12 square feet per person. If a room is too tight, people will feel uncomfortable and won't want to come back, Mr. Rockwell said.</p>
        <p>The Rockwell Group and Bogdanow Partners both said their restaurants average 16 to 18 square feet per person. The industry standard, Mr. Bentel said, is 20 to 22 square feet per person.</p>
        <p>The bar area is more of a wild card -- and a tighter squeeze. The trouble with many new designs is the mingling of bar areas with eating areas. Often, they collide.</p>
        <p>New York City building codes dictate that smoking areas at the bar can be just six feet from dining tables. Which is why in many restaurants, like Bottino and Babbo, you often feel as if you are eating in the bar and getting bumped by all the traffic flowing through it.</p>
        <p>''In New York, you would have to say it's unavoidable in some cases,'' Mr. Ashworth said. But design can play a part. At Verbena, the bar has just five seats and is set into a dark area with a low ceiling. It sends out a clear message that it is just for waiting for your table, not for lingering.</p>
        <p>Glenn Forley, a partner in Fizer Forley, which designed the restaurant, said: ''A bar any larger would have probably affected the restaurant dining experience, because you would have had more of an overlap. Now, the bar is pretty much separate from the tables.'' The same is accomplished at Eleven Madison Park, where the bar is set off to the side in a small dim room with low ceilings.</p>
        <p>To avoid crowds forming in more open restaurants, designers have taken to adding communal tables in the bar area, which break up crowds and form boundaries. ''By definition,'' Mr. Rockwell said, ''it doesn't allow the bar to become too much of a bar.''</p>
        <p>The new Rosa Mexicano immediately attracted a big bar crowd, making it impossible to navigate at times. Mr. Rockwell, whose company designed the restaurant, has recently added bar-height tables. ''It felt just too open,'' Mr. Rockwell said. ''And there's a lot of people, and making them a little more comfortable made sense.''</p>
        <p>It is the long and narrow restaurants with bars up front that have the most difficulty with traffic jams. At Town, a restaurant under construction in Midtown, the bar itself and the equipment behind it are very shallow. A small lounge is positioned at the end of the bar, so people will be drawn through the area rather than encouraged to linger in it. Other designers add features like a carpet or a rail to signal which areas are for circulation.</p>
        <p>But there is only so much that can be done by a designer. The rest is up to the management to control. And if crowds get out of control, as they do in many restaurant bars, it's the neighbors who step in. New York City's Buildings Department does not have a task force out enforcing occupancy compliance. Most complaints are filed by residents to the Fire Department.</p>
        <p>The New York Fire Department will send an officer to take a head count at the restaurant, said Brian Dixon, a department spokesman. (For occupancies over 75 or restaurants with more than 750 square feet, a sign must be posted and there is an annual inspection, including a review of the seating plan.) If the occupancy limit is exceeded, diners will be asked to leave until it is met. The restaurant can be fined a maximum of $2,500. The unlucky, randomly chosen diners go home hungry.</p>
        <p>But in New York, where crowds are more or less praised, this series of events is rare. So rare that when the Fire Department was asked, it couldn't dig up a single case.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
