<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Company Briefly Suspended For Cable-Spool Accident</title>
    <meta content="23SPOO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sheldon Electric</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kippins, Andresa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valentin, Blanca</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0DD1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Company Briefly Suspended For Cable-Spool Accident</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Transit officials temporarily suspends Sheldon Electric because of an accident in subway on Aug 17 in which a 7,500-pound spool of electrical cable barreled down a staircase and injured two women; company was involved in an almost identical accident in subway in March 1999 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Transit officials said yesterday that they had temporarily suspended a Queens electrical company because of an accident in the subway last week in which a 7,500-pound spool of electrical cable barreled down a staircase and injured two women. The company was involved in an almost identical accident in the subway last year, officials said, and was asked at the time to improve its safety procedures.</p>
        <p>The suspension after last week's incident lasted only until yesterday, when the company, Sheldon Electric of Long Island City, submitted a detailed safety plan; company officials said the plan would prevent such an accident from happening again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Transit officials said yesterday that they had temporarily suspended a Queens electrical company because of an accident in the subway last week in which a 7,500-pound spool of electrical cable barreled down a staircase and injured two women. The company was involved in an almost identical accident in the subway last year, officials said, and was asked at the time to improve its safety procedures.</p>
        <p>The suspension after last week's incident lasted only until yesterday, when the company, Sheldon Electric of Long Island City, submitted a detailed safety plan; company officials said the plan would prevent such an accident from happening again.</p>
        <p>Transit officials said the suspension was imposed because of concerns that the company and the general contractor on the job, CAB Associates of College Point, Queens, were not adhering to rules regarding dangerous work.</p>
        <p>In the accident last Thursday, at the 14th Street and Eighth Avenue station, workers for Sheldon Electric left half a stairway open at the 16th Street entrance, allowing passengers to use one side as the workers manually lowered the spool on the other side.</p>
        <p>But the one-inch-thick nylon rope holding the spool snapped, transit officials said, and the spool rolled down the stairs, hitting the two women, Andresa Kippins, 73, of Bedford-Stuyvesant and Blanca Valentin, 40, of the Bronx. Ms. Kippins suffered several broken bones and had to undergo surgery; Ms. Valentin suffered scrapes and bruises.</p>
        <p>Al O'Leary, the chief spokesman for New York City Transit, said that in a review of Sheldon's jobs, officials found that the company's workers also lost control of a spool of cable on March 25, 1999, while installing communications lines at the West Fourth Street subway station.</p>
        <p>In that incident, a rope being used to lower a spool of cable down a staircase also broke and the runaway spool struck a 39-year-old Brooklyn woman, Xiao Leung, according to a lawsuit filed against the company and the transit agency in State Supreme Court in Manhattan. Ms. Leung suffered a head injury and broken bones and had to have a rod surgically implanted in her leg, said her lawyer, Debra Reiser.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reiser said that Ms. Leung, a seamstress, now suffers from double vision and has not been able to return to work.</p>
        <p>Transit officials said Sheldon was not suspended in that case, but was required to change its practices for moving heavy materials into the subway.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Leary said that before the accident last week, other spools in the renovation project at 14th Street had been lowered down an elevator shaft. But one spool was too large. And so, without consulting with the company's safety engineer or a resident engineer from the transit agency, the workers decided to lower the spool down the half-opened staircase.</p>
        <p>''The people delivering the materials should have gone back and conferred with the safety engineer and the resident engineer,'' Mr. O'Leary said. ''Clearly these are internal communications issues.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Leary said that a superintendent and a foreman for Sheldon Electric had been removed from the project.</p>
        <p>But Michael Cahn, the chief executive of Sheldon Electric, said that neither the superintendent nor the foreman at the 14th Street project had been transferred off the job but were on vacation, and that the company had not yet assigned blame to any individual for the accident.</p>
        <p>''We are cooperating with the Transit Authority,'' Mr. Cahn said. ''We all want to make sure that something like this does not happen again.''</p>
        <p>Officials with CAB Associates did not return a telephone call seeking comment yesterday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
