<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Mentally Ill Brooklyn Boys Missing After Swimming in Off-Limits Area of Hudson</title>
    <meta content="23DROW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drownings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Croton Point Park (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Children's Recreation Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5DB1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Mentally Ill Brooklyn Boys Missing After Swimming in Off-Limits Area of Hudson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two mentally ill teenage boys from Brooklyn Children's Psychiatric Center are missing in swirling waters of Hudson River at Croton Point Park after going swimming in a prohibited section of the river during a camping trip; one counselor nearly drowns trying to save boys (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two mentally ill teenage boys from a state psychiatric center in Brooklyn were missing in the swirling waters of the Hudson River near Ossining, N.Y., last night after they went swimming in a prohibited section of the river during a camping trip, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Two counselors on the trip, from the Brooklyn Children's Psychiatric Center, were watching when the boys, ages 15 and 17, went into the water at Croton Point Park, said Sgt. Donald McArthur of the Westchester County police.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two mentally ill teenage boys from a state psychiatric center in Brooklyn were missing in the swirling waters of the Hudson River near Ossining, N.Y., last night after they went swimming in a prohibited section of the river during a camping trip, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>Two counselors on the trip, from the Brooklyn Children's Psychiatric Center, were watching when the boys, ages 15 and 17, went into the water at Croton Point Park, said Sgt. Donald McArthur of the Westchester County police.</p>
        <p>One counselor nearly drowned trying to rescue the boys, Sergeant McArthur said, and was being held for observation at a hospital.</p>
        <p>The counselors had been told by a park employee earlier in the day that swimming was forbidden at the spot, but it was not clear whether the counselors allowed the boys to swim or if the boys disobeyed them, the sergeant said.</p>
        <p>The Coast Guard suspended the search for the teenagers around 8:30 p.m., after five fruitless hours, said Susan Tolchin, a spokeswoman for the Westchester County executive's office.</p>
        <p>The search was to resume this morning, though the police said they doubted that the boys had survived.</p>
        <p>The boys, whose names were not released, live in a state-run residence on the grounds of the psychiatric center, in Bedford-Stuyvesant, the authorities said. They were part of a group of six patients and four counselors who went on an overnight trip to stay in bungalows at the park, a 508-acre county preserve on the east side of the Hudson about 35 miles north of New York City.</p>
        <p>The campers were apparently looking for a place to swim, but even the official park beach is now closed on weekdays because of a shortage of lifeguards, Sergeant McArthur said. ''I believe someone from the group questioned whether swimming was available,'' he said. ''The parks people we spoke to said that this particular group had been instructed that they could not swim just prior to the incident.''</p>
        <p>Around 3 p.m., Sergeant McArthur said, all six of the patients and two counselors hiked down a steep hill and across a field of boulders to Teller's Point, a desolate area where the Croton and Hudson Rivers meet and riptides and crosscurrents twist through the water.</p>
        <p>''No Swimming'' signs are prominently posted at the point, Ms. Tolchin said.</p>
        <p>It was not clear what led up to the boys'  decision to jump into the river, but they soon began struggling in the current, Sergeant McArthur said.</p>
        <p>A counselor, Lenox Gabriel, 47, went into the water to try to rescue them, but he started going under, Sergeant McArthur said.</p>
        <p>Two county police officers responding to a 911 call dived into the water and pulled Mr. Gabriel out, but the boys had disappeared, the sergeant said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gabriel was in stable condition last night at Phelps Memorial Hospital in Sleepy Hollow.</p>
        <p>All afternoon and into the evening, by air, by water and by land, teams searched the area from the Tappan Zee Bridge, five miles south of the park, to Peekskill, five miles to the north. The tide was coming in when the boys went into the water but it had turned by nightfall.</p>
        <p>New York City police divers searched the river while a city police helicopter circled overhead. Dozens of local, county and state police officers and firefighters scanned the banks, and the Coast Guard searched in its boat, Ms. Tolchin said. ''It's just a terrible thing,'' she said.</p>
        <p>As hope and sunlight began to dim and members of the boys' families began to arrive, crisis counselors were called to the park, said Roger Klingman, a spokesman for the State Office of Mental Health, which runs the psychiatric center.</p>
        <p>Sergeant McArthur said he doubted the boys would be found alive.</p>
        <p>''You like to be optimistic,'' he said, ''but if they haven't gotten ashore the chances are pretty slim.''</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Children's Psychiatric Center, a cluster of nondescript institutional buildings on Bergen Street near Ralph Avenue in Bedford-Stuyvesant, serves young people with serious emotional disturbances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klingman said the campers arrived at the camp on Monday planning to spend two days.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
