<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial Real Estate; Law Firm Is No Longer Lonely in Refurbished Tower on Times Square</title>
    <meta content="23REAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Other Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Proskauer Rose</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcdowell, Edwin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E3DC1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial Real Estate; Law Firm Is No Longer Lonely in Refurbished Tower on Times Square</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWIN McDOWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcdowell, Edwin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commercial Real Estate: Law Firm Is No Longer Lonely in Refurbished Tower on Times Square**Law firm of Proskauer Rose refurbishes its 11 floors at 1585 Broadway in Manhattan, creating a concourse in subbasement for its library and high-tech research center (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five years after moving to Times Square in 1990, the law firm of Proskauer Rose was still the only tenant in the 41-story tower at 1585 Broadway, between 47th and 48th Streets. ''We had been in two buildings on Park Avenue, and suddenly we found ourselves virtually alone in the wild West,'' said Alan S. Jaffe, chairman. ''It was very, very lonely here.''</p>
        <p>Lonely, but not uneventful. Soon after moving into 11 floors, the law firm sued the developers and lenders, contending, among other things, that the paving outside the building was unfinished, the facade incomplete and the elevators in need of repair. And when improvements still were not made, the firm withheld its rent for about six months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five years after moving to Times Square in 1990, the law firm of Proskauer Rose was still the only tenant in the 41-story tower at 1585 Broadway, between 47th and 48th Streets. ''We had been in two buildings on Park Avenue, and suddenly we found ourselves virtually alone in the wild West,'' said Alan S. Jaffe, chairman. ''It was very, very lonely here.''</p>
        <p>Lonely, but not uneventful. Soon after moving into 11 floors, the law firm sued the developers and lenders, contending, among other things, that the paving outside the building was unfinished, the facade incomplete and the elevators in need of repair. And when improvements still were not made, the firm withheld its rent for about six months.</p>
        <p>While all that was going on, the recession hit and the bottom rapidly began falling out of the market for office space in New York; the building at 1585 Broadway alone was losing $1.9 million a month. As a result, in December 1991, the development partnership, 1585 Broadway Associates, controlled by David S. Solomon, filed for protection under Chapter 11 of the Federal Bankruptcy Code.</p>
        <p>Things settled down after Morgan Stanley, the financial services company (now Morgan Stanley Dean Witter), bought the building at auction for $176 million in August 1993 and moved in two years later.</p>
        <p>Ten years still remain on Proskauer's original 20-year lease, and the 125-year-old law firm -- even now the building's only tenant other than Morgan Stanley -- has embarked on a top-to-bottom refurbishing. Three months ago, it remodeled the entire 19th floor, and next month it will begin refurbishing the rest.</p>
        <p>The makeover of the 19th floor, which housed the firm's law library, resulted in 7 large conference rooms and 49 offices for lawyers, plus work stations and offices for secretaries, legal assistants and support staff members. All that was accomplished without adding to the 365,000 square feet that the firm already occupied.</p>
        <p>It was able to do so by relocating the library to the firm's existing space in the subbasement, space that had been used by accounting department employees, by a messenger department and for record storage. But Proskauer employees do not refer to the underground space as a subbasement, much less a cellar. ''We refer to it as a concourse,'' Mr. Jaffe, the chairman, said, clearly savoring his choice of euphemism.</p>
        <p>In fact, this is no ordinary sub- -- whoops, concourse. For starters, it is flooded with light: light from lamps, from recessed ceiling lights, from concealed lights within floor-to-ceiling frosted-glass panels built into the walls, and from light reflected from the polished stainless steel in which the three four-foot-square concrete pillars are sheathed. To add to the brightness, light is reflected from the various woods, including oak and anigre, that were chosen partly for that purpose. The concourse also houses separate men's and women's locker rooms for employees who pull all-nighters or want to freshen up after working out in nearby gyms.</p>
        <p>The library has been incorporated into a new high-tech research center, an area that also includes training rooms, conference rooms, the records department and rooms where documents that bear on a particular case can be consolidated for easy access.</p>
        <p>The research center has space enough for 34 lawyers at any one time to be able to plug in their personal computers and surf the Internet. In addition, 14 staff members help with research, on the Internet and among the library's estimated 60,000 books, journals and other periodicals. The researchers serve not just Proskauer's 420 lawyers in New York but also the 130 or so in the firm's other offices, in Newark, Washington, Los Angeles, Boca Raton, Fla., and Paris. ''This is bigger than some college law libraries,'' said Kit Hartnett, director of library services within the research center.</p>
        <p>The concourse was designed by Gensler, the architectural firm. But Hal Plott, director of administration for Proskauer, said it was the firm's idea to relocate the library underground and to change the overall name to research center. ''We wanted a name that better reflected its purposes,'' he said. The remodeled concourse and the 19th-floor makeover cost a total of $4.5 million.</p>
        <p>From his office, Mr. Jaffe said, ''We thought when we moved here that the redevelopment of Times Square would take place back then, but the recession interfered.'' Since then, he added, Times Square has become a corridor for legal, financial and informational services firms. And Proskauer employees no longer feel like pioneer settlers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
