<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; A Look Behind Al Gore's Punchy Language</title>
    <meta content="23WED3$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raines, Howell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0DC1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; A Look Behind Al Gore's Punchy Language</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWELL RAINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raines, Howell</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Howell Raines Editorial Observer says Vice Pres Al Gore's frequent use of word 'fight' in his nomination acceptance speech reflects his need to play the pugnacious populist and to be seen as politician with conviction; says slashing debate is Gore's instinctive response to virtually every competitive political situation; warns that public may grow weary of Gore's continual announcements that it is fight time in America (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In yesterday's Times, Katharine  Seelye documented the use of ''working families'' as a thematic catch phrase in speeches by Vice President Al Gore and his surrogates. This technique of disciplined repetition is similar to that used by Gov. George W. Bush to give brand-name status to ''compassionate conservatism.'' In either party, it is all part of a process that Stuart Stevens, a Bush strategist, calls ''finding a language'' for a candidacy.</p>
        <p>To my ear, an especially striking part of the language of this year's presidential contest has been Mr. Gore's use of the word ''fight.'' It is hard to recall an acceptance speech with more pugilistic imagery than that delivered by Mr. Gore in Los Angeles last Thursday. The indisputably bellicose Richard Nixon had only one ''fight'' in his 1972 acceptance speech. Mr. Gore used ''fight,'' or derivative verb and noun forms, 23 times. Often, of course, the construction was about ''fighting for working families,'' a combination designed, as Ms. Seelye reported, to underscore the message of economic populism that dominated the Democratic convention.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In yesterday's Times, Katharine  Seelye documented the use of ''working families'' as a thematic catch phrase in speeches by Vice President Al Gore and his surrogates. This technique of disciplined repetition is similar to that used by Gov. George W. Bush to give brand-name status to ''compassionate conservatism.'' In either party, it is all part of a process that Stuart Stevens, a Bush strategist, calls ''finding a language'' for a candidacy.</p>
        <p>To my ear, an especially striking part of the language of this year's presidential contest has been Mr. Gore's use of the word ''fight.'' It is hard to recall an acceptance speech with more pugilistic imagery than that delivered by Mr. Gore in Los Angeles last Thursday. The indisputably bellicose Richard Nixon had only one ''fight'' in his 1972 acceptance speech. Mr. Gore used ''fight,'' or derivative verb and noun forms, 23 times. Often, of course, the construction was about ''fighting for working families,'' a combination designed, as Ms. Seelye reported, to underscore the message of economic populism that dominated the Democratic convention.</p>
        <p>But even when it is tactically selected, the language that candidates choose tells us something about their inner lives, personal histories and psychological comfort zones. Mr. Bush, for example, really does come from a three-generation family political tradition that believes that conservatism should be leavened with a paternalistic kind of caring. That is why George Bush the elder had to wriggle so hard to get into Ronald Reagan's ideological suit, and may also provide a clue as to why Governor Bush is always insisting that he will not enter the White House wearing ''borrowed clothes.''</p>
        <p>What, then, does the language of combat tell us about Mr. Gore and others who use it on the stump? I thought first of a very different kind of Southern presidential candidate, the late George C. Wallace of Alabama. ''The fighting judge'' never seemed to feel fully alive unless he had a posture of aggression toward a world of entitled power -- the federal government, the Kennedys, the fraternity boys at the University of Alabama -- that he always suspected of looking down on him. Mr. Gore does not seem burdened by feelings of personal or regional inferiority.</p>
        <p>But he does long to be perceived as a conviction politician. His cleanup chores in the Clinton administration have undermined that image with the public and, one suspects, within Al Gore as well. Fighting words provide a way for Mr. Gore to depict himself as more resolute than President Clinton and more reliable than his attractive but untested opponent. Both thoughts figured in Mr. Gore's observation that ''the presidency is more than a popularity contest. It's a day-by-day fight for people'' in which one must sometimes ''pick the hard right over the easy wrong.''</p>
        <p>A reading of ''The Prince of Tennessee,'' by David Maraniss and Ellen Nakashima, convinced me that fighting words serve some other purposes for Mr. Gore as well. On one level, they link him to a longstanding Democratic oratorical tradition. As Jimmy Carter noted in his 1980 acceptance speech, Democrats like to see themselves as ''the party of a courageous fighter who knew how to give 'em hell -- Harry Truman.''</p>
        <p>Playing the pugnacious populist seems especially important to Mr. Gore, perhaps because it eases an inner anxiety about his privileged background. On a more personal level, verbal warfare connects the vice president to his father, a New Deal Democrat who preferred lunch-pail issues over the austere campaign oriented toward defense policy that Mr. Gore ran in 1988.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maraniss and Ms. Nakashima write that slashing debate is Mr. Gore's instinctive response to virtually every competitive political situation. The record bears them out. In all his campaigns since 1976, Mr. Gore has felt more secure, more grounded -- and been more successful -- when on the attack. His dismantling of Senator Bill Bradley in the Democratic primaries continued the pattern. And in the last few days, Mr. Gore has rocked Mr. Bush, who looked very wobbly on the stump yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Republicans still insist they can turn Mr. Gore's bellicosity against him with accusations of class warfare. But Mr. Gore may face another more subtle danger. Constant feistiness can wear out political audiences, especially in a time when suburban moderates do not feel particularly threatened by the greedy forces conjured by Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Bush's macro bet for the campaign is that voters are sick of what he calls ''bitter arguments.'' At this point, Mr. Gore is drawn by strategy and instinct to the opposite view. His message is not the blurry and Bushian ''I care,'' but an updated version of Harry Truman that could be summed up as ''Let's get ready to rumble.''</p>
        <p>The polls make Mr. Gore's bet on smash-mouth politics look smart at the moment. But it is a close question as to whether he could play another game if later opinion surveys showed a public weariness with his continual announcements that it's fight time in America.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
