<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yankees Squander Their Rally, Resuming the Boston Two-Step</title>
    <meta content="23YANK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224767"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texas Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E3DA1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yankees Squander Their Rally, Resuming the Boston Two-Step</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees lose to Texas Rangers, 5-4, at Yankee Stadium; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like an old married couple, the Yankees and the Boston Red Sox have come to resemble each other deep in their race for the division title. Every time the Yankees lose, it seems, so do the Red Sox. When the Yankees win, so do the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>The Yankees just cannot divorce themselves from the Red Sox in the American League East. Last night, for example,  shortly after the Anaheim Angels trounced Boston at Fenway Park, the Texas Rangers edged the Yankees, 5-4, at Yankee Stadium when Rafael Palmeiro slammed a tie-breaking home run off Denny Neagle to open the eighth inning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like an old married couple, the Yankees and the Boston Red Sox have come to resemble each other deep in their race for the division title. Every time the Yankees lose, it seems, so do the Red Sox. When the Yankees win, so do the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>The Yankees just cannot divorce themselves from the Red Sox in the American League East. Last night, for example,  shortly after the Anaheim Angels trounced Boston at Fenway Park, the Texas Rangers edged the Yankees, 5-4, at Yankee Stadium when Rafael Palmeiro slammed a tie-breaking home run off Denny Neagle to open the eighth inning.</p>
        <p>The Yankees will wake up this morning and see the Red Sox still very close, three games behind. ''It's weird,'' Neagle said. ''It's been really weird.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees won on Aug. 4; Boston did as well. Each team lost on the next three days. The Yankees lost on Aug. 18 and the Red Sox won, but the next day, the Yankees won and Boston lost.</p>
        <p>The Yankees and Red Sox have had the same result on 13 of 18 days since Aug. 4, their records almost identical: Yankees 10-9, Red Sox 10-8.</p>
        <p>''We can't expect the other team to lose,'' Paul O'Neill said. ''It'd be nice to get a margin. We've got a West Coast trip coming up, and those are big. These next two games at home coming up are important games.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees were in position to pad their margin last night, facing the fading Rangers, but fell behind immediately and in a big way.</p>
        <p>Neagle (3-4) struggled with his mechanics in the first inning, fell behind in the count and kept getting the ball up in the strike zone; he felt ''foreign'' on the mound again, he said.</p>
        <p>He could have used some defensive help, but there was none. Texas had runners at first and third with one out, the game scoreless, when Rafael Palmeiro scorched a line drive to center field, where Clay Bellinger has been filling in capably for the injured Bernie Williams.</p>
        <p>This time, Bellinger came in on the ball as if to try to catch it, then stopped to play it on the bounce.</p>
        <p>Some of the Yankees pitchers have noticed that since the field was hit by heavy rain earlier this month, the ball tends to skid in the outfield, like an 8-ball bouncing across a pool table. Palmeiro's liner skipped past Bellinger and rolled almost all the way to the center-field fence. Both runners scored, with Palmeiro reaching third.</p>
        <p>Gabe Kapler then pulled a hit to left-center to drive home Palmeiro, and when left fielder Luis Polonia took a cautious route to the ball, Kapler hustled into second base.</p>
        <p>He subsequently scored when Ricky Ledee grounded a single through the right side of the infield. ''I just couldn't get comfortable in that inning,'' Neagle said.</p>
        <p>That 4-0 lead appeared insurmountable early because the Rangers' Rick Helling dominated the Yankees early, throwing only 40 pitches in the first four innings, retiring 17 consecutive batters after Polonia doubled to lead off the first.</p>
        <p>There were two outs and nobody on base in the Yankees' sixth, nothing happening. But Polonia crushed a homer, Derek Jeter walked and O'Neill smashed a liner over the right-field wall, the ball requiring about 1.1 seconds to reach the screaming fans for the Yankees' 22nd homer in their last 10 games. Three batters, three runs.</p>
        <p>Luis Sojo doubled home Tino Martinez in the seventh, tying the score, and the Yankees loaded the bases when Helling walked Bellinger and Polonia. Jeter was next, and Tim Crabtree was called on to replace Helling, despite the fact that Jeter had 7 hits in 13 career at-bats against Crabtree.</p>
        <p>With the count three balls and two strikes, Jeter swung through a fastball, ending the inning. He turned to Bruce Froemming, the home plate umpire, and asked, ''Was it high?'' Froemming nodded.</p>
        <p>Neagle had thrown 119 pitches to that point, and the bottom of the seventh lasted a long time. Still, with the left-handed-hitting Palmeiro due to open the eighth, Manager Joe Torre sent the left-handed Neagle out to start the eighth inning. Neagle immediately fell behind, two balls and no strikes.</p>
        <p>Neagle would second-guess himself later for his thought process: worried about possibly walking Palmeiro and then being relieved, Neagle opted to challenge Palmeiro, the one major threat in the entire Texas lineup, with a fastball.</p>
        <p>Palmeiro launched a high drive to right. O'Neill backed up against the wall, looked up, only to see Palmeiro's 32nd homer carry into the stands.</p>
        <p>''I was probably thinking a little selfishly there,'' Neagle admitted.</p>
        <p>It is almost September, and the Yankees and the Red Sox are close together, still.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The slugger DAVID JUSTICE is out with a neck strain, and the Yankees are hoping to get him back in time for tomorrow afternoon's game against Texas. Center fielder BERNIE WILLIAMS might return this weekend. . . . The third-base coach WILLIE RANDOLPH, who broke a rib during batting practice last week, was replaced at his spot last night by the hitting coach CHRIS CHAMBLISS.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
