<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Season To End Early For Coach</title>
    <meta content="23PINS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224765"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stottlemyre, Mel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knoblauch, Chuck</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE5DA1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="721" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Season To End Early For Coach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mel Stottlemyre, Yankees' pitching coach being treated for bone marrow cancer, returns to team but says he will probably be unable to finish season; has been preparing for stem cell transplant; second baseman Chuck Knoblauch continues rehabilitation for right elbow at Yankees' minor league complex in Tampa, Fla; could miss rest of season and possible playoffs (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mel Stottlemyre, the Yankees' pitching coach, in the midst of treatment for bone marrow cancer, returned to the team yesterday but said he would probably not be able to finish the season.</p>
        <p>Stottlemyre has been preparing for a stem cell transplant, in which cells cleansed by chemotherapy are re-introduced into his body. Doctors have not told him exactly when that procedure will take place, but whenever it does -- and Stottlemyre wants to have it done as soon as possible -- he will not be able to return to his job for the rest of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mel Stottlemyre, the Yankees' pitching coach, in the midst of treatment for bone marrow cancer, returned to the team yesterday but said he would probably not be able to finish the season.</p>
        <p>Stottlemyre has been preparing for a stem cell transplant, in which cells cleansed by chemotherapy are re-introduced into his body. Doctors have not told him exactly when that procedure will take place, but whenever it does -- and Stottlemyre wants to have it done as soon as possible -- he will not be able to return to his job for the rest of the season.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I'll make it through the season,'' he said. ''Everything they've done so far, I've been on the upper scale, on the plus side. The things that have bothered me have bothered me a lot less than they've bothered other people. The stem cell collection, instead of taking three days, they probably had enough in one day. I've just been lucky; I've reacted very favorably to all the medication.''</p>
        <p>Stottlemyre intends to serve as pitching coach for the next couple of days and to go on the Yankees' coming road trip, assuming that his latest blood tests, scheduled for today, produce the expected results. ''I feel good,'' he said. ''I came here today with the doctors' blessings.''</p>
        <p>Stottlemyre, who last coached Aug. 5, has watched all but one of the Yankees' games on television and has spoken to Manager Joe Torre regularly. ''The game looks easier on TV,'' Stottlemyre said, joking. ''There's been a lot of good things. A couple of negatives, I guess -- the bullpen in a couple of games. The starters have been pitching well.</p>
        <p>''It's tough sitting at home, watching on television. You're used to watching the game from the dugout, and all of a sudden you're confined to watching the TV.''</p>
        <p>Billy Connors, who has been filling in during Stottlemyre's absence and will accompany the Yankees on the coming road trip, has been keeping Stottlemyre's records in the same manner Stottlemyre does; typically, each pitching coach keeps records in a style that suits only him. ''Billy's been pretty much keeping me up to date,'' Stottlemyre said.</p>
        <p>Stottlemyre decided not to talk to anyone who has had a stem cell transplant until he was actually on the verge of having one himself. Now, he said, he's ready to take that step of discussing it with someone like Roger Neilson, the former coach of the Philadelphia Flyers.</p>
        <p>''I'm curious about how some people rebound,'' Stottlemyre said.</p>
        <p>Torre believes that working helps Stottlemyre -- ''He was going stir crazy,'' Torre said -- and that having Stottlemyre around helps the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''Any time you think of griping, you look around and see Mel and all of sudden what you're griping about seems very insignificant,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch's Nagging Injury</p>
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch continues to go through rehabilitation for his right elbow at the Yankees' minor league complex in Tampa, Fla., and could join a minor league team later in the week. But the pain that has bothered him for almost a month continues to nag at him.</p>
        <p>With time running out on the season, there is a chance Knoblauch will not be able to throw pain-free again before the playoffs. The question, then, will be whether Knoblauch, who can hit without a problem, can play second base with the pain.</p>
        <p>It is a question that Joe Torre will most likely ask Knoblauch in the next few days.</p>
        <p>''I think that's probably the next step, to give him a call and try to figure it out,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>If Knoblauch does feel that he can play with the pain, he could be activated within a week. If he feels he needs relief, the Yankees could pursue more substantive medical treatment, like a cortisone shot, before he continues with his rehabilitation. If he feels he cannot play with his current level of pain, then he could be relegated to the role of pinch-hitter, pinch-runner and part-time designated hitter -- sharing time with Glenallen  Hill and Jose Canseco.</p>
        <p>Torre is obviously hoping Knoblauch can play second base, because of his importance as the Yankees' leadoff hitter; Knoblauch would presumably be replaced in the late innings any time the Yankees have a lead.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
