<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Inflation-Wary, Fed Lets Rates Stand</title>
    <meta content="Y23FED$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/23/business/23FED.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discount Rate</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2DB1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1268" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Inflation-Wary, Fed Lets Rates Stand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Reserve, reassured by evidence that wage and price increases remain under control despite robust economic growth, votes to leave interest rates unchanged but warns that it might raise rates later in year if inflation creeps up; decision leaves benchmark federal funds target rate on overnight loans between banks at 6.5 percent; discount rate remains at 6 percent; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reassured by evidence that wage and price increases remain under control despite robust economic growth, the Federal Reserve voted today to leave interest rates unchanged but warned that it might raise them later in the year if inflation creeps up.</p>
        <p>The decision displayed the Fed's confidence that the economy is gradually moving onto a path of slightly more modest, though more sustainable growth, but suggested as well that the central bank is not yet sure that its campaign of rate increases is complete.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reassured by evidence that wage and price increases remain under control despite robust economic growth, the Federal Reserve voted today to leave interest rates unchanged but warned that it might raise them later in the year if inflation creeps up.</p>
        <p>The decision displayed the Fed's confidence that the economy is gradually moving onto a path of slightly more modest, though more sustainable growth, but suggested as well that the central bank is not yet sure that its campaign of rate increases is complete.</p>
        <p>The task of bleeding off any inflationary pressure without ruining a business expansion is a tricky one under any circumstances. It has become especially complicated in this cycle because, many think, some old rules have been rendered obsolete by the changes that technology and globalization have brought to the economy.</p>
        <p>Analysts and policy makers are increasingly certain that the economy is capable of a substantially faster pace of noninflationary growth than it was a few years ago, though there is considerable debate in and outside the Fed about where the new tipping point might be and how close the economy is to it.</p>
        <p>As it often has in recent years under its chairman, Alan Greenspan, the Fed chose today to be patient but at the same time to offer reassurances that it would move quickly at the first sign of a threat from inflation.</p>
        <p>''Recent data have indicated that the expansion of aggregate demand is moderating toward a pace closer to the rate of growth of the economy's potential to produce,'' the Fed's policy-making arm, the Federal Open Market Committee, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the panel said, ''the risks continue to be weighted mainly toward conditions that may generate heightened inflation pressures in the foreseeable future.''</p>
        <p>The decision means that the Fed is likely to remain on the sidelines for the duration of the presidential campaign. The central bank's policy makers are next to meet on Oct. 3. But the bank has, over the years, tried to avoid taking any action on interest rates in the weeks leading up to Election Day -- which falls this year on Nov. 7. The Fed's first meeting after the election is on Nov. 15.</p>
        <p>The outcome of today's meeting had been widely expected by analysts and investors, and there was muted reaction in the financial markets after the announcement at 2:15 p.m. Stocks finished slightly higher, with the Dow Jones industrial average closing at 11,139.15, up 59.34 points. Bonds were little changed.</p>
        <p>Today's decision left the Fed's benchmark federal funds target rate on overnight loans between banks at 6.5 percent, where it has been since May, when the central bank raised the rate by half a percentage point. The Fed held rates steady at its subsequent meeting in June.</p>
        <p>It also left unchanged, at 6 percent, its discount rate -- the interest rate charged on loans to banks from the Federal Reserve system.</p>
        <p>The central bank has pushed the federal funds rate up 1.75 percentage points in six steps since June 1999 in an effort to tamp down inflation pressure without snuffing out what earlier this year became the longest business expansion on record.</p>
        <p>Some analysts said it was now unlikely that the Fed would raise rates again this year. Others said inflation remained a threat and that it would be a mistake to count the Fed out.</p>
        <p>''As intoxicating as a soft-landing scenario is,'' said Carl Tannenbaum, chief economist at LaSalle Bank in Chicago, ''we have to remain sober for at least another couple of quarters before we allow ourselves to imbibe of it.''</p>
        <p>In the second quarter of the year, the economy grew at a 5.2 percent annual rate compared with a 4.8 percent annual rate in the first three months of the year.</p>
        <p>Those figures were well above what many economists think can be sustained over the long run without igniting a spiral in wages and prices. While it remains a moving target, the economy's noninflationary speed limit now seems to be around or just below 4 percent.</p>
        <p>Yet inflation has edged up only slightly from very low levels, in large part because the strong economic growth has been accompanied by a surge in business efficiency, or productivity, which improved at a 5.3 percent annual rate in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>Even as companies find themselves paying more to attract workers in a tight labor market, where unemployment is at 4 percent, and more for raw materials and equipment, they are cutting costs in other areas or improving efficiency by investing in new technology.</p>
        <p>Within the Fed, there is a long-running debate about whether productivity improvements can continue to outrun inflation pressure. In keeping rates unchanged today, the Fed seemed to be deferring the matter rather than trying to settle it.</p>
        <p>In its statement, the Federal Open Market Committee noted that economic indicators were showing ''that more rapid advances in productivity'' had forced economists to revise upward their estimates of how fast the economy could grow without igniting inflation. At the same time, the committee said, productivity improvements have been ''containing costs and holding down underlying price pressures.''</p>
        <p>But the policy panel suggested that productivity improvements were not a panacea and that the combination of low unemployment and strong growth still had to be viewed as inflationary, especially to the degree that strong demand for goods and services outstripped the economy's ability to keep up.</p>
        <p>The committee, the statement said, ''remains concerned about the risk of a continuing gap between the growth of demand and potential supply at a time when the utilization of the pool of available workers remains at an unusually high level.''</p>
        <p>To some degree, the inflation warning in the statement was intended to keep analysts and traders from concluding that the Fed was signaling an end to this series of rate increases.</p>
        <p>In interviews in recent months, several Fed officials said they hoped to keep Wall Street somewhat off balance to prevent another sharp run-up in stock prices. Within the Fed, the wealth generated in the stock market is regarded as a primary driver of consumer spending and overall demand, and another strong rebound on Wall Street, it is feared, could push demand up to a level that would inevitably fuel inflation.</p>
        <p>But Fed officials no doubt have other, more fundamental inflation worries on their minds. Oil prices remain quite high, and although their effect on overall consumer prices so far has been somewhat muted, high oil prices could still feed through the economy and accelerate inflation.</p>
        <p>There is also concern among some Fed officials that the combination of 4 percent annual growth and 4 percent unemployment will inevitably lead to wage increases that will outstrip productivity gains and put upward pressure on prices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan told Congress last month that he did not think the Federal Reserve would have to drive unemployment higher to prevent inflation. But some of his colleagues -- including Laurence H. Meyer, the Fed governor most closely identified with the school of economists who see a tight link between unemployment and inflation -- are not so sure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
