<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Are Still Exploring Trades for Ewing</title>
    <meta content="23KNIC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Supersonics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Pistons</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Glen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Detroit Pistons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Seattle SuperSonics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DA1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1191" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Are Still Exploring Trades for Ewing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers explore further options to trade center Patrick Ewing after demise of four-team, 13-player swap that would have sent him to Seattle SuperSonics; deal collapsed because of refusal of Detroit Pistons to take on contracts of seven marginal role players; Knicks' interest in trading 38-year-old Ewing is tied to acquiring Glen Rice from Los Angeles Lakers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patrick Ewing is not battling only his aching joints anymore. Public opinion is posting him up, telling him to leave town. His own organization even planned a conference call on Monday night to announce the separation.</p>
        <p>For better or worse, Ewing, the Knicks' franchise center, survived yet another coup to his 15-year reign yesterday. How long he remains in New York is unclear, but the four-team, 13-player swap that would have sent the 38-year-old veteran to Seattle is officially dead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Patrick Ewing is not battling only his aching joints anymore. Public opinion is posting him up, telling him to leave town. His own organization even planned a conference call on Monday night to announce the separation.</p>
        <p>For better or worse, Ewing, the Knicks' franchise center, survived yet another coup to his 15-year reign yesterday. How long he remains in New York is unclear, but the four-team, 13-player swap that would have sent the 38-year-old veteran to Seattle is officially dead.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Knicks, the SuperSonics and the Los Angeles Lakers all entertained possibilities of separate deals that could eventually cause Ewing to land in Seattle and Vin Baker and Glen Rice in New York. The Lakers would secure a power forward to help Shaquille O'Neal and Kobe Bryant defend their title.</p>
        <p>But barring late-night negotiations among the clubs, nothing seemed imminent last night. Ewing, moments away from ending his long association with the Knicks on Monday and the subject of a tabloid headline yesterday that blared ''Good Riddance,'' remained a Knick for another evening.</p>
        <p>A club spokeswoman said the organization had nothing to announce late last night.</p>
        <p>The day began with the Knicks trying to salvage a deal with the SuperSonics, who were prepared to send Baker to New York for Ewing in the proposed trade, which would have been the largest in National Basketball Association history.</p>
        <p>But New York's interest in parting ways with Ewing was tied to acquiring Rice from the Lakers, a person familiar with the Knicks' negotiations said yesterday on condition of anonymity. Rice was one of two other prominent players in the deal, along with Detroit's Christian Laettner, whom the Lakers were trying to acquire.</p>
        <p>Several factors led to the demise of the four-team deal, none more important than the Pistons' refusal on Monday night to take on the contracts of seven marginal role players moments after the Knicks, the Lakers and the SuperSonics had begun plans for a conference call to announce the deal.</p>
        <p>Division among Pistons executives over adding at least three contracts that had more than one year remaining on them led to Detroit's pulling out of the deal. According to an Eastern Conference official, who also spoke on condition of anonymity, the Pistons yesterday asked Scott Layden, the Knicks general manager, to include Marcus Camby in a package. But Layden, the conference official said, was willing to offer only draft picks to the Pistons.</p>
        <p>Other obstacles to acquiring Baker and Rice for Ewing also emerged yesterday afternoon.</p>
        <p>The Pistons, who spent much of yesterday completing a trade that would send Lindsey Hunter to Milwaukee for Billy Owens, showed little inclination to get back involved in a four-team swap. Having lost Grant Hill to Orlando and with public criticism growing over the quality of next season's team, General Manager Joe Dumars was said to be wavering over the potential fallout of his first landmark deal. By securing players with one year left on their current deals, the Pistons were hoping to clear salary-cap room to lure an elite free agent to Detroit next summer, with Sacramento's Chris Webber being the biggest prize.</p>
        <p>In Dallas, the Mavericks were eagerly waiting for the Pistons to bow out of the proposed four-team deal in order to use their players to possibly coax Detroit into giving up Laettner by offering John Wallace and Cedric Ceballos. If they were successful, the Mavericks would have foiled the Knicks' plans twice in one week.</p>
        <p>The Mavericks were instrumental in brokering a four-team trade last week that ended the Knicks' pursuit of the free agent forward Danny Fortson, who ended up in Golden State after Dallas secured the rights to Utah Jazz point guard Howard Eisley. Since Laettner is coveted by the Lakers, any deal for the power forward would lessen the chance that Rice could end up with the Knicks via a multiteam trade with Detroit.</p>
        <p>In Seattle, the All-Star point guard Gary Payton voiced displeasure through his agent that the Sonics did not consult him before agreeing to trade Baker. Payton was not against playing with Ewing, the agent, Aaron Goodwin, said in a published report. But he believed Baker would have a monumental season after two lackluster years that diminished his stature as one of the game's top players.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Ewing was beginning to have mixed feelings about ending his association with New York, a person close to him said. The 12-time All-Star waived the no-trade clause in his contract recently, essentially giving the Knicks approval to move him to another team of his liking.</p>
        <p>After all the innuendo and speculation, it is not inconceivable that Ewing will return for a 16th season in New York at age 38. The Eastern Conference official implied that if the Knicks did not receive what they believed was fair value for Ewing, a future Hall of Famer -- and fair value would be more than just Baker, the official said -- the club would most likely enter training camp with Ewing on the roster.</p>
        <p>''It's not impossible,'' the official said. ''Would they welcome Patrick back if things fell through? From what I hear, they would do it with open arms. They're not letting him go for one player who's not going to help them out as much Patrick already does.''</p>
        <p>Either way, with Miami, Orlando and Charlotte having rejuvenated their teams and on paper, at least, making the Eastern Conference more formidable, the Knicks seem intent on reacting to recent trades by their competitors.</p>
        <p>Michael Jordan, the Washington Wizards' president of basketball operations, told The Washington Post that the Knicks had offered Ewing and four others in a package late last week. Ewing and Chris Dudley were said to be involved in a deal that would send Juwan Howard to New York, another official said. But Jordan apparently did not want Dudley's $7 million-a-year salary on the Wizards' cap for the next season.</p>
        <p>The person familiar with the Knicks, however, denied that Ewing was ever included in a prospective deal with the Wizards. It was unclear whether Ewing would want to play for Washington, which has not been to the playoffs since 1997.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the Wizards sent center Ike Austin to Vancouver for Dennis Scott, Cherokee Parks, Obinna Ekezie and Felipe Lopez.</p>
        <p>There was one major wild card yet to be played. David Falk, the agent for Ewing and Rice as well as the free-agent forward Maurice Taylor, desperately wants to place Ewing on a team that would not only be playoff bound, but also thankful enough to reward him with at least a two-year extension after his current contract expires next summer.</p>
        <p>If Ewing was dealt for Baker, the Sonics would then sign Taylor to play alongside Ewing on the Seattle front line. Rice has said in published reports that he wants to play in New York. If Falk could somehow orchestrate a deal that involved the Knicks securing both players, the deal could be consummated.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
