<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peter Cooper Village Owner Accused of Fraud on Wiring</title>
    <meta content="23RENT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224727"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Peter Cooper Village (Manhattan)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rcn Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Life Insurance Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanders, Steven (Assemblyman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelley, Tina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E4DC1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peter Cooper Village Owner Accused of Fraud on Wiring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelley, Tina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Assemblyman Steven Sanders accuses Metropolitan Life Insurance Co of seeking to overcharge residents of Peter Cooper Village for $30 million in new wiring, saying the insurer stands to earn huge amounts from telecommunications companies like RCN for making the improvements; company seeks rent increases that would amount to $135 a month for a one-bedroom apartment and $170 for a two-bedroom apartment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Manhattan assemblyman accused Metropolitan Life Insurance Company yesterday of seeking to overcharge residents of Peter Cooper Village for $30 million in new wiring, saying the insurer stands to earn huge amounts from telecommunications companies for making the improvements.</p>
        <p>The insurance company, which owns the 2,200-unit Peter Cooper Village, on the east side of Manhattan north of 14th Street, has asked the State Division of Housing and Community Renewal for approval for the increased assessments, which, under law, would remain as rent increases after the new electric, cable, phone and Internet wiring is paid for.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Manhattan assemblyman accused Metropolitan Life Insurance Company yesterday of seeking to overcharge residents of Peter Cooper Village for $30 million in new wiring, saying the insurer stands to earn huge amounts from telecommunications companies for making the improvements.</p>
        <p>The insurance company, which owns the 2,200-unit Peter Cooper Village, on the east side of Manhattan north of 14th Street, has asked the State Division of Housing and Community Renewal for approval for the increased assessments, which, under law, would remain as rent increases after the new electric, cable, phone and Internet wiring is paid for.</p>
        <p>The increases would amount to $135 a month for a one-bedroom apartment and $170 for a two-bedroom apartment. The average two-bedroom apartment rents for about $1,000, according to a list of rents for one of the buildings in Peter Cooper Village.</p>
        <p>The tenants association has protested the increases in a letter to the state housing agency, and, with the assemblyman, Steven Sanders, a resident of Peter Cooper Village, suggests that the insurance company's application is fraudulent because it does not mention the money it may get from companies like RCN and other cable companies.</p>
        <p>''The question is, did it really cost them $30 million, or was there an offset from income they incurred from RCN?'' said Jack Lester, the lawyer for the tenants association, who said many of the residents were elderly and living on fixed incomes.</p>
        <p>''This may be enough to force some of them out,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The apartment complex, built after World War II to house returning veterans, was designed to be affordable for middle-income residents, and in recent years the apartments have been highly sought after as rents increased rapidly elsewhere in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanders said that while tenants were being asked to pay for the wiring improvements, Met Life and RCN have a marketing agreement that provides Met Life with what he believed was ''several millions of dollars'' for the actual wiring, plus a percentage of every new contract for a subscriber in Peter Cooper Village. The agreement includes a clause preventing the parties from speaking about it, he said.</p>
        <p>''We are contending they seriously omitted a significant revenue,'' Mr. Sanders said of the insurer. ''We are suggesting that the actual cost to Met Life is substantially less than what they are purporting it to be, because they have failed to indicate on their application what we believe to be millions of dollars of revenue generated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sanders said that a landlord who is untruthful in an application for a rent increase after completing major capital improvements could lose any chance of being reimbursed for the work and could face major damages.</p>
        <p>He learned of the cable installations after a tenant asked him why a box in the front closet had an RCN logo, since the tenant had not subscribed to any RCN services. He said there was no mention of the cable and telecommunications wiring in the insurer's application for the increase.</p>
        <p>Jennie Morgan, a spokeswoman for the insurer, declined to answer questions about the proposed increase.</p>
        <p>''We are a fair landlord, we play by the rules and we have filed a legitimate application'' for an increase based on major capital improvements, she said. ''Other than that, there's nothing I can say.''</p>
        <p>An RCN spokeswoman also did not provide any information on the two companies' arrangement.</p>
        <p>Dan Irizarry, deputy press secretary for the state housing agency, would not comment on the specifics of the application.</p>
        <p>Many of the tenants at Peter Cooper Village have lived there for decades. ''The overwhelming majority didn't want the wiring, and don't want to pay for it,'' said Al Doyle, president of the tenants association.</p>
        <p>''It's very hard on us,'' said Shirley Ehrlickman, who describes herself as an elderly resident of Peter Cooper Village. She pays $907 a month in rent for a one-bedroom apartment, and expects an increase of $140.</p>
        <p>''The rent is going up, the cost of medication is going up, everything in the city is costing more including food, so you can see it's a hardship on the older population,'' she said. ''To be perfectly honest, I've been seeking an apartment with a lower rental, but it's very hard to find a lower rental.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
