<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reprieve of Sorts for Besieged Stiltsville</title>
    <meta content="Y23STI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/23/national/23STIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Biscayne National Park</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Biscayne Bay (Fla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Park Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DE1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reprieve of Sorts for Besieged Stiltsville</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>KEY BISCAYNE, Fla., Aug. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal parks officials at Biscayne National Park in Florida are evicting occupants of Stiltsville, cluster of ramshackle old houses on pilings in Biscayne Bay; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a clear, hot day, with the sunlight glittering off the water, the houses of Stiltsville seem to float on a liquid horizon. A cluster of seven ramshackle houses built on weathered pilings, the structures dot the shallow waters of Biscayne Bay like shipwrecks.</p>
        <p>Cursed by environmental advocates, praised by others as a symbol of a dying, free-spirited way of life, they have endured 70 years of mildew, rot and hurricanes, and assaults by federal parks officials who want them torn down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a clear, hot day, with the sunlight glittering off the water, the houses of Stiltsville seem to float on a liquid horizon. A cluster of seven ramshackle houses built on weathered pilings, the structures dot the shallow waters of Biscayne Bay like shipwrecks.</p>
        <p>Cursed by environmental advocates, praised by others as a symbol of a dying, free-spirited way of life, they have endured 70 years of mildew, rot and hurricanes, and assaults by federal parks officials who want them torn down.</p>
        <p>Now, the beginning of the end of Stiltsville, just inside Biscayne National Park, seems finally here.</p>
        <p>The occupants of the weather-beaten wooden structures, weekend renters who use them mostly for parties and getaways, are being evicted, federal parks officials said on Monday. The renters, some who have been coming to the houses for decades, have until Dec. 1 to move out.</p>
        <p>The structures themselves will not be torn down but will be opened to the public, perhaps as environmental education sites. But it is only a reprieve.</p>
        <p>The houses would not be rebuilt if substantially damaged by weather, said Linda Canzanelli, superintendent of Biscayne National Park.</p>
        <p>That, say the people who want to keep them in the bay, means it is only a matter of time until a storm wipes them from the horizon.</p>
        <p>''It feels awful,'' said Gail Baldwin, an architect who has had a house in Stiltsville since the early 1970's. ''I feel sad for me and very sad for the community.''</p>
        <p>The houses are woven into the skyline and lore of Miami, a romantic symbol of the region's waterfront culture -- and its weirdness -- since the 1930's, when Eddie Walker, a local fisherman, turned a barge grounded in the shallows into a one-story home.</p>
        <p>Other houses followed, and the community became a getaway for the affluent. It has appeared in television shows including the ''Miami Vice'' series of the 1980's. Carl Hiaasen, a novelist and columnist at The Miami Herald, used the house as a backdrop for one of his popular novels, ''Skin Tight.'' In that book, the hero stabs a man to death with the bill of a fish he had mounted on the wall of his Stiltsville house.</p>
        <p>Once, there were as many as 25 houses, but fires (all the houses were wood) and storms whittled their number to the remaining seven.</p>
        <p>Park officials have long regarded the houses as a nuisance. When the section of Biscayne Bay containing Stiltsville became a national park in 1968, homeowners signed long-term leases, some of which have changed hands many times.</p>
        <p>Ms. Canzanelli said the decision to remove the renters but not the houses was a compromise in the dispute between officials and the renters, who wanted no change.</p>
        <p>It is not a case of the federal government running longtime homeowners who have nowhere else to go off the water but an eviction of people who use the structures to tie up their boats, watch the sunsets and lie under the stars.</p>
        <p>Their use of the houses contributes to the fouling of the shallow water, and endangers a fragile ecosystem coral and seagrass, environmental advocates have argued.</p>
        <p>''Their lease is up,'' Ms. Canzanelli said. ''They don't own the structures and they never owned the structures. There was always an intention that, at the end of this lease, these structures would be removed. We've gone an extra step to keep them for public use.''</p>
        <p>But those who lease the houses say it is just a ploy to prevent them from keeping up the structures, which require regular maintenance, and one that dooms the houses to destruction after the first strong wind.</p>
        <p>''They said they eventually see the national park without Stiltsville,'' Mr. Baldwin said. ''My feeling is the whole thing is a ruse to put the houses on hold, and get us out of there. They're just going to let them deteriorate to the point that they're unsafe, and then they'll have to tear them down.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Canzanelli said the park service must maintain the houses to keep them safe for visitors.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't have made the offer if there wasn't serious interest in protecting the structures for public use,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
