<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Softening Chagall's Surrealistic Dreams</title>
    <meta content="23DANS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">O Vertigo (Dance Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laurin, Ginette</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DC1F3EF930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Softening Chagall's Surrealistic Dreams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>BECKET, Mass., Aug. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews O Vertigo, French-Canadian dance company founded by Ginette Laurin, performing several works by Laurin at Jacob's Pillo Dance Festival in Becket, Mass (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ginette Laurin likes to loop and scatter movement round and round itself and the stage at a mostly unhurried pace. The effect is of a Philip Glass score written in a meditative and indulgent mood and played at half speed. The style worked well in excerpts from Ms. Laurin's 1989 ''Chagall,'' performed by O Vertigo, a leading French Canadian modern-dance company, on Sunday afternoon at the Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival in the Ted Shawn Theater. But a great deal of ''En Dedans'' (''Inside''), which completed the program, looked merely decorative.</p>
        <p>Ms. Laurin, the founder, director and choreographer of O Vertigo, is justly celebrated for her integration of dance with otherwise often ancillary elements like lighting, sets and costumes. All of these contribute to the poetic imagery of the ''Chagall'' excerpts, particularly at the start, when the dancers appear to fly over the clusters of small pale-painted wooden buildings on the stage floor. Crossing and recrossing the stage, their bodies caught, lifted and deposited, the dancers evoke the surrealistic dream worlds of some of Chagall's paintings, softened with a touch of ''Our Town'' and ''Oklahoma!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ginette Laurin likes to loop and scatter movement round and round itself and the stage at a mostly unhurried pace. The effect is of a Philip Glass score written in a meditative and indulgent mood and played at half speed. The style worked well in excerpts from Ms. Laurin's 1989 ''Chagall,'' performed by O Vertigo, a leading French Canadian modern-dance company, on Sunday afternoon at the Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival in the Ted Shawn Theater. But a great deal of ''En Dedans'' (''Inside''), which completed the program, looked merely decorative.</p>
        <p>Ms. Laurin, the founder, director and choreographer of O Vertigo, is justly celebrated for her integration of dance with otherwise often ancillary elements like lighting, sets and costumes. All of these contribute to the poetic imagery of the ''Chagall'' excerpts, particularly at the start, when the dancers appear to fly over the clusters of small pale-painted wooden buildings on the stage floor. Crossing and recrossing the stage, their bodies caught, lifted and deposited, the dancers evoke the surrealistic dream worlds of some of Chagall's paintings, softened with a touch of ''Our Town'' and ''Oklahoma!''</p>
        <p>''En Dedans'' appears to take place in a dream state, too, with the passage of time and shifts in place suggested by changes in costuming and lighting. Separated by blackouts, each sequence elaborates slightly on small gestures and other themes and knits them tighter into the fabric of bodies wheeling, circling and swinging, at momentary rest and in lifts whose shapes add to an already handsome stage picture.</p>
        <p>Ms. Laurin uses cliches like blackouts, counting aloud and whispering with a fair amount of freshness. But with the exception of two passages of double duets toward the middle of the piece, ''En Dedans'' has a rather aimless trajectory.</p>
        <p>Ms. Laurin's use of deliberate repetition makes it hard to settle into her choreography and enjoy the movement and design for themselves. And while the hand gestures provide vivid spots of color in a creamily flowing whole, the gestures often look extraneous.</p>
        <p>There is nothing aimless about the dance from moment to moment, however, or about the dancing itself. The performers' clarity and precision illuminate the piece. Anne Barry stands out, embodying the title with her inward yet lyrically expansive dancing, in a fine company that also included Simon Alarie, Melanie Demers, Kenneth Gould, Patrick Lamothe, Chi Long, Anna Riede, Mari-Claude Rodrigue, David Rose and Donald Weikert.</p>
        <p>''En Dedans'' is set to a collage of sounds and music by composers including Arvo Part, Gavin Bryars, Peter Appleton and the Ensemble Bash. The handsome costumes were designed by Carmen Alie and Denis Lavoie. The lighting was by Hans Peter Boden.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
