<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mint Joins the Grown-Ups' Table</title>
    <meta content="23HERB$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Herbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Melissa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Herbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0DD1F3EF930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mint Joins the Grown-Ups' Table</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELISSA CLARK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clark, Melissa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on cooking with mint, one of most common herbs used in preparation of food; recipes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OF all the common herbs used in cooking today, mint seems to have the least cachet. It lacks the versatility of parsley, the accessibility of basil or dill, the trendiness of cilantro and the seductiveness of rosemary. Too often it is seen, but not eaten, as a dessert garnish.</p>
        <p>But thanks to Mediterranean influences on New York restaurants, mint has become more of a chef's favorite. The herb is indigenous to the Mediterranean and is as essential to that region's cuisine as cilantro is to Mexican cooking. Fragrant leaves of mint are tossed into salads, mixed into dips, dressings and marinades and folded into stuffings for meats, vegetables and breads.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OF all the common herbs used in cooking today, mint seems to have the least cachet. It lacks the versatility of parsley, the accessibility of basil or dill, the trendiness of cilantro and the seductiveness of rosemary. Too often it is seen, but not eaten, as a dessert garnish.</p>
        <p>But thanks to Mediterranean influences on New York restaurants, mint has become more of a chef's favorite. The herb is indigenous to the Mediterranean and is as essential to that region's cuisine as cilantro is to Mexican cooking. Fragrant leaves of mint are tossed into salads, mixed into dips, dressings and marinades and folded into stuffings for meats, vegetables and breads.</p>
        <p>Joseph Savino, the chef of Peccavi, on East 26th Street, takes his cue from dishes like those and uses mint in an artichoke and tomato ragout served with halibut. At Tocqueville, near Union Square, Marco Moreira, the chef, enlivens eggplant caviar with anchovies, olives, crushed red pepper flakes and plenty of mint. Rob Miketa at the TriBeCa Grand adds mint to a salad of peppery arugula tossed with a pungent sheep's milk dressing with harissa. And at Dylan Prime, also in TriBeCa, mint is mixed with preserved lemon in a crust patted onto fish before it is grilled.</p>
        <p>Mint spread from the Mediterranean to northern Europe via the Romans, who learned to pickle it in vinegar for a condiment. The English added sugar and paired it with lamb. But mint never caught on in classic French cooking, the inspiration for many high-end American chefs.</p>
        <p>Today, though, American chefs are exploring varieties beyond the common spearmint and peppermint. At Oceana, the pastry chef, David Carmichael, uses six varieties in a mint and strawberry parfait, including chocolate mint, pineapple mint, grapefruit mint and orange mint. (Yes, they taste the way they sound.)</p>
        <p>''The citrus mints go really well with fruits like strawberries,'' Mr. Carmichael said. To mint ice cream he adds what he calls chocolate mint chips, actually chocolate-covered mint leaves, broken into bits.</p>
        <p>Mint has also won a place in the nuevo Latino cuisine of Douglas Rodriguez of Chicama in the Flatiron district, though Latin Americans usually confine it to tea and cocktails. He blends mint with jalapenos into a spicy mojo sauce for lamb.</p>
        <p>Since mint has an intense flavor, it works best with other strong tastes. Marcus Samuelsson, the chef at Aquavit, says, ''You have to be good when using mint because if you overdo it, it's going to taste too perfumed.'' In his mint ravioli, he kneads it into the dough, mixes it into the ricotta filling and uses it oven-dried as a brittle topping. A foamy sweet tomato sauce, caramelized figs and balsamic vinegar with the pasta keep the mint from taking over.</p>
        <p>Mint is related to basil and needs equal care. Use a light hand, and taste the leaves first to see how strong they are. Since mint tends to turn black when cut, chop it at the last minute. You can blanch mint to reduce the menthol flavor and set the color, but it is at its best quickly cut or torn and added to dishes after they have been cooked, or in the last minutes of cooking. Long simmering can bring out a grassy taste.</p>
        <p>Spearmint and peppermint are usually available even in supermarkets. (Peppermint is darker and has a stronger scent.) More esoteric varieties can be found at Greenmarkets in the city in summertime.</p>
        <p>MINT CHOCOLATE CHIP ICE CREAM  Adapted from David Carmichael, Oceana  Time: 1 hour plus chilling and freezing</p>
        <p>1 quart heavy cream  5 cups packed fresh mint leaves (about 4 ounces), coarsely chopped  1 cup sugar  10 large egg yolks  10 ounces bittersweet chocolate, chopped  1 cup whole mint leaves.</p>
        <p>1. In medium saucepan, bring cream and chopped mint to a simmer. Turn off heat, and let steep 5 minutes. Strain out mint, and return cream to saucepan.</p>
        <p>2. Add  3/4 cup sugar to cream, and bring to a simmer. Whisk together egg yolks and remaining sugar. Remove cream from heat, and add a little to egg mixture to warm, stirring constantly to keep yolks from cooking. Pour egg mixture into cream, stirring constantly. Return custard to heat, and cook over low heat, stirring constantly with a wooden spoon, until mixture thickens enough to coat back of spoon. Remove from heat, and pour into bowl. Cool completely.</p>
        <p>3. Strain custard, then chill until thoroughly cold, at least 4 hours.</p>
        <p>4. Meanwhile, prepare mint chips. Melt chocolate in top of double boiler over simmering water. Cool slightly. Lay a 12-by-24-inch sheet of parchment paper on a work surface. Pour melted chocolate onto parchment, spreading evenly to cover entire surface. Lay mint leaves onto chocolate until half the surface is covered, being careful not to overlap. Lift parchment, and lay plain chocolate over mint-covered chocolate to cover. Place in refrigerator for 20 minutes to set.</p>
        <p>5. Remove chocolate from refrigerator, and peel off parchment. Break chocolate into large pieces, and then roughly chop. Refrigerate until needed.</p>
        <p>6. Freeze ice cream mixture in an ice cream maker, following manufacturer's instructions. Using a spatula, fold in chocolate mint chips by hand. Place in freezer for at least 2 hours before serving.</p>
        <p>Yield: About 1 1/2 quarts.</p>
        <p>MINT MOJO  Adapted from Douglas Rodriguez, Chicama  Time: 25 minutes</p>
        <p>1 cup white vinegar  2 tablespoons mint jelly  1 cup tightly packed fresh mint leaves, finely chopped  5 shallots, minced  2 cloves garlic, minced  1 jalapeno, seeded and minced  2 tablespoons vegetable oil  Salt and freshly ground black pepper.</p>
        <p>1. In a saucepan, combine vinegar and mint jelly. Bring to a boil, and simmer until reduced by half, about 10 minutes. Cool.</p>
        <p>2. Add mint, shallots, garlic, jalapeno and vegetable oil. Transfer to a blender, and puree until smooth. Season with salt and pepper. Serve as a condiment for grilled or roasted meats, vegetables or poultry.</p>
        <p>Yield: 1 3/4 cups.</p>
        <p>SICILIAN EGGPLANT CAVIAR  Adapted from Marco Moreira, Tocqueville  Time: 1 1/2 hours</p>
        <p>2 large Italian eggplants  3 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil  4 cloves garlic, sliced thin  1 pinch red pepper flakes  4 high-quality anchovy fillets, chopped  10 Italian olives, pitted and sliced  1 cup cherry tomatoes, halved</p>
        <p>1/2 cup grated Parmigiano-Reggiano</p>
        <p>1/2 cup plain croutons or diced stale bread  Salt and freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>3/4 cup tightly packed fresh mint leaves, coarsely chopped</p>
        <p>1/4 cup tightly packed fresh Italian parsley leaves, coarsely chopped.</p>
        <p>1. Heat oven to 375 degrees. Prick eggplants all over with a fork, then place on a sheet pan. Roast until tender, about 45 minutes. Let cool completely.</p>
        <p>2. Cut eggplants in half lengthwise, and scoop out meat into a saucepan. Simmer until most of the liquid is evaporated and eggplant is dry, about 20 minutes. Set aside.</p>
        <p>3. In a large saute pan, heat olive oil over medium heat. Add garlic and red pepper, and saute one minute. Add anchovies and olives, and saute another minute, stirring continuously. Add tomatoes, and cook a minute more. Add eggplant, and cook two minutes. Add cheese, croutons and salt and pepper to taste. Stir in mint and parsley until well combined. Serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 to 6 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
