<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Longer A War Zone, Hunts Point Gains Status; New Services Arrive As City Improvements Lift Bronx Community</title>
    <meta content="23HUNT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000824T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit Unions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hunts Point (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forero, Juan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04EFDD1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1874" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Longer A War Zone, Hunts Point Gains Status; New Services Arrive As City Improvements Lift Bronx Community</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUAN FORERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Forero, Juan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hunts Point in Bronx, which has long been associated with prostitution, drug dealing and the wholesale food market, is becoming a decent place to live thanks to recent improvements and some on the way--from rehabilitated housing to new park space to arrival of services the Point never had before, like a post office, credit union for banking and recreation center for children; cornerstone of city-sponsored drive to add new housing is current construction of 42 two- and three-family houses; Hunts Point is also selling itself to artists seeking cheap space; array of problems still persist; photo; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Utter the name Hunts Point, residents say, and most people who do not know better think grit and grime and crime. Thoughts turn to a desolate and particularly polluted stretch of the South Bronx long associated with streetwalkers, drug dealers, rumbling trucks and a sprawling wholesale food market that offers little in the way of aesthetics.</p>
        <p>But these days in Hunts Point, real estate agents regularly knock on Jeannette Johnson's door, offering $200,000 for the elegant century-old town house with the rounded facade where she has lived since 1951. Nearby, William Erazo watches from his window as 42 homes are constructed on a lot where junked cars were once dumped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Utter the name Hunts Point, residents say, and most people who do not know better think grit and grime and crime. Thoughts turn to a desolate and particularly polluted stretch of the South Bronx long associated with streetwalkers, drug dealers, rumbling trucks and a sprawling wholesale food market that offers little in the way of aesthetics.</p>
        <p>But these days in Hunts Point, real estate agents regularly knock on Jeannette Johnson's door, offering $200,000 for the elegant century-old town house with the rounded facade where she has lived since 1951. Nearby, William Erazo watches from his window as 42 homes are constructed on a lot where junked cars were once dumped.</p>
        <p>And Hunts Point is where Bob and Teresa Melendez moved with their teenage son after deciding their apartment in Pelham Bay was too small. It was a homecoming, for both had fled Hunts Point in the 1970's when the neighborhood was being transformed into a wasteland of violence and abandoned buildings.</p>
        <p>''You can see the change, the immense change,'' Ms. Melendez said in her newly renovated two-bedroom apartment on Lafayette Street. ''Compared to what it was in the 1970's and 1980's, it's being reborn. We don't see so much graffiti, drugs and stuff, so much garbage. There used to be so much dumping from windows. It's not like that. It's come a long way.''</p>
        <p>Since 1986, 60,000 homes and apartments have been built or rehabilitated in the South Bronx through city-sponsored programs, and fledgling businesses have begun giving once-barren neighborhoods a try.</p>
        <p>These things have come more slowly to Hunts Point, some residents say.</p>
        <p>Zoned for industry and the home of waste transfer stations and warehouses, scrap metal shops and the 1.9-million-square-foot Food Distribution Center, Hunts Point had not always been thought of as a place for a residential renaissance, longtime residents and business people in the area say.</p>
        <p>But little by little, improvements have come to this sliver of a neighborhood cut off from the rest of the Bronx by the Bruckner Expressway and surrounded on three sides by an industrial park with 650 businesses. Hunts Point's 8,200 residents, most of whom live on a peninsula jutting into the East River known as the Point, are experiencing an array of improvements that have begun or been completed in recent months -- from rehabilitated housing to new park space to the arrival of services the Point never had before, like a post office.</p>
        <p>''In the past, the exciting things that would happen in Hunts Point were things like the new Meat Locker coming to the Cooperative Market,'' said Paul Lipson, executive director of the Point Community Development Corporation, a community group and business incubator. ''It was the Fulton Fish Market coming up here. Now there's much more for residents.''</p>
        <p>A credit union, the area's first banking service in 25 years, will open in October, across Lafayette Street from where the peninsula's first post office is being built. Groundbreaking has begun for a youth recreation center. In June, a new park was inaugurated on the Bronx River. A primary care clinic, also a first, opened last year, and a second is expected to open any week now. And the main street, Hunts Point Avenue, has seen storefront vacancies fall from 60 percent three years ago to about 25 percent today.</p>
        <p>The cornerstone of a city-sponsored drive to add new housing is the current construction of 42 two- and three-family homes near Mr. Erazo's front porch on Bryant Street, where he once watched drug deals go down. This was an area once maligned as a war zone, shown as populated by heroin addicts and criminals in the 1981 film ''Fort Apache, the Bronx.''</p>
        <p>''The fact that they're beginning to build homes around here means people are moving in who'll take care of their homes because it's an investment,'' said Mr. Erazo, 71, a retired salesman who has lived with his family in the house he bought in 1969.</p>
        <p>Hunts Point is also selling itself to artists looking for cheap space, with boosters likening the peninsula to the artists' colony in Williamsburg in Brooklyn. The former American Bank Note Company building is offering up to 27,000 of its 365,000 square feet to artists. Seven painters, sculptors and other artisans have rented space since Arthur Aviles and his dance company arrived in 1998. Five others have signed leases and are moving in.</p>
        <p>''If you're looking for ribbon and bows, it's not here; it's an uncut diamond,'' explained Howard T. Cash, a fine arts photographer. ''The area is still basically camouflaged. So you have to seek things out. You have to be a journeyman and an explorer. You have to go and ask. But a lot of things are here.''</p>
        <p>But even its boosters acknowledge that Hunts Point remains a difficult neighborhood in which to raise a family, and wonder how much better a community zoned largely for industry can become.</p>
        <p>''I think we're still in the stages of becoming a real community in terms of the residential area; it's not there yet,'' said Josephine Infante, director of the Hunts Point Economic Development Corporation, which she founded in 1988 when the neighborhood was still at rock bottom. ''We're still talking about a poor community. It's not going to look like Riverdale.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the peninsula is still saddled with an array of serious problems.</p>
        <p>Its residents are among the poorest in the city. In the late 1990's, unemployment remained at 18 percent, and nearly half of all residents draw public assistance. Only 32 percent of children in the local elementary school passed the school board's reading test this year, compared with 40 percent citywide.</p>
        <p>Perhaps because of the truck traffic and waste transfer stations, more than 25 percent of all children suffer from asthma, said Dr. Braulio Flores, staff doctor at Bella Vista Health Clinic on Hunts Point Avenue.</p>
        <p>Francisco Perez, 57, a member of Mothers on the Move, a local group that has battled industry in the peninsula, said that breathing can be hard for her, too. ''I myself have bronchitis and, at times, it becomes so much worse,'' she said. ''We are waiting for a future when we'll have improvements. It's not easy to work in a community that still needs so many changes.''</p>
        <p>Hunts Point has two dozen waste transfer stations, more than in any other part of the city. Some 12,000 trucks move in and out of the peninsula daily. Warehouses and nearly 100 auto parts suppliers and mechanics provide a scrappy backdrop. A Swedish company is proposing to build a natural gas-powered plant there to produce electricity.</p>
        <p>Yet, Mr. Perez and others who have long called for a tighter rein on industry say the Hunts Point of today is far different from the one they knew just a few short years ago. Crime has fallen to the point where there has not been a single homicide in the peninsula this year.</p>
        <p>And the Hunts Point Economic Development Corporation is pushing a far-reaching plan that will spend $2.3 million to build medians and plant trees and flowers in streets considered too wide and foreboding for a residential neighborhood. The plan also calls for limiting truck routes to a select number of streets, with color-coded signs and the threat of fines discouraging truckers from taking shortcuts through residential streets.</p>
        <p>Signs of renewed life are most apparent, residents say, amid the peninsula's eclectic mix of brick row houses and tenements.</p>
        <p>Kristina Hosch, who with her husband, Eddie Torres, owns several Bronx apartment buildings, went into Hunts Point four years ago to inspect city-owned buildings that were being offered to investors. On that first day, Ms. Hosch recalled, she requested a police escort to tour buildings infested with drug dealers. Today, the four buildings they own have been renovated and painted, with well-lighted hallways, working intercom systems and polished tiles. Recent renovations have left apartments with new hardwood floors, windows and appliances. Tenants have flocked to fill the 172 apartments in the buildings.</p>
        <p>''I never thought it would lose the Hunts Point stereotype and that you'd have the eagerness to get into the buildings,'' she said. ''Now, we're seeing the transformation. As soon as people look at the apartments, they want to rent, the same day.''</p>
        <p>Michael Faust, another developer, decided two years ago to buy a 20-unit building that had been gutted. Now, he is to begin $2 million in renovations financed with loans sponsored by the City Department of Housing Preservation and Development. The hope, said Mr. Faust, whose company has rehabilitated buildings in neighborhoods like Fort Greene in Brooklyn that have become chic, is that the peninsula will undergo a similar revival.</p>
        <p>''This has been one of the untainted or untouched communities,'' Mr. Faust said, ''and now people are going there to fix up, and I think it's a good low-income or moderate-income area that's up and coming.''</p>
        <p>It was not always that way, even on the peninsula's most charming street, Manida, with row after row of elegant, brick homes.</p>
        <p>Jeannette Johnson should know, having seen Manida Street at its best in 1951 when she and her husband, the bandleader Buddy Johnson, first moved in. Then came the 1960's and 1970's, when drug dealers took over, the garbage piled up and her neighbors fled.</p>
        <p>These days, though, Ms. Johnson gets unsolicited visits from real estate agents who want her home, a handsome, two-family brick structure with fine moldings and elegant touches. ''They want to buy the homes here now,'' said Ms. Johnson, whose son, Woodrow, a teacher, lives in the second-floor apartment. ''You would never think they would want to buy homes in Hunts Point. But now, they're offering $245,000.''</p>
        <p>Hugh Coley, a real estate broker with Century 21 Future Homes, is among those who have made a point of staking out homes on the peninsula.</p>
        <p>''Five years ago, I mean they were selling for $30,000, $40,000, $50,000,'' he said. ''That was just the way the market was at that point. No one would want those houses down there. But now, there's talk about businesses moving into the area, and people are looking for investments over there.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnson explains that while she may some day move, for now she is happy.</p>
        <p>''Where else can you get a two-family home like this?'' she said. ''You walk out, it's nice out here. You can park your car out front. It's clean. It's quiet. It's good.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 24, 2000, Thursday  Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about new residential and commercial development in Hunts Point in the Bronx referred incorrectly to a member of Mothers on the Move, a group battling industry in the area. The member, Francisco Perez, is a man.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 24, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about new residential and commercial development in Hunts Point in the Bronx referred incorrectly to a member of Mothers on the Move, a group battling industry in the area. The member, Francisco Perez, is a man.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
