<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Looks to Conservatives</title>
    <meta content="Y23ADB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/23/politics/23ADBO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6DD1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Looks to Conservatives</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore begins fall advertising campaign with 60-second biographical commercial in 16 states; ad described and assessed for accuracy (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore began his fall advertising campaign yesterday with a 60-second biographical commercial in 16 states; a 30-second version will run in a 17th state, Iowa. Gov. George W. Bush of Texas began showing his fall campaign commercials on Monday in many of the same states, including major contested ones like Illinois, Michigan, Missouri, Ohio and Pennsylvania, where the Democrats need to win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore began his fall advertising campaign yesterday with a 60-second biographical commercial in 16 states; a 30-second version will run in a 17th state, Iowa. Gov. George W. Bush of Texas began showing his fall campaign commercials on Monday in many of the same states, including major contested ones like Illinois, Michigan, Missouri, Ohio and Pennsylvania, where the Democrats need to win.</p>
        <p>PRODUCER Campaign Company Inc.</p>
        <p>ON THE SCREEN Generic black-and-white film of police officers in helmets using nightsticks to beat demonstrators protesting the Vietnam War in 1969. Several photographs of Mr. Gore in his Army uniform, one with him sitting respectfully at his father's knee. The music swells. A black-and-white picture of Mr. Gore when he first ran for Congress. As the narrator talks of Mr. Gore's support for the war in the Persian Gulf, the film bursts into color and action, with camouflaged soldiers marching.</p>
        <p>THE SCRIPT Narrator: ''1969. America in turmoil. Al Gore graduates college. His father, a U.S. senator, opposes the Vietnam War. Al Gore has his doubts, but enlists in the Army. When he comes home from Vietnam, the last thing he thinks he'll ever do is enter politics. He starts a family with Tipper, becomes an investigative reporter. Then Al Gore decided that to change what was wrong in America, he had to fight for what was right.</p>
        <p>''He ran for Congress. Held some of the first hearings on cleaning up toxic waste. Made the environment his cause. Broke with his own party to support the gulf war. Fought to reform welfare with work requirements and time limits. His fight now is to ensure that prosperity enriches all our families, not just the few. Strengthen Social Security. Take on big drug companies to guarantee prescription drugs for seniors. Hold schools accountable for results. Tax cuts for working families and the middle class. Al Gore. Married 30 years. Father of four. Fighting for us.''</p>
        <p>ACCURACY This is essentially a promotional biography. It casts Mr. Gore's life decisions -- to enlist in the Army, for example -- in the most positive light. One of the few assertions that the Bush campaign challenges is the claim that Mr. Gore ''fought to reform welfare with work requirements and time limits,'' saying he stood on the sidelines. Mr. Gore was not a major player in drafting the plan offered by President Clinton or in the long debate. But when the Republicans sent Mr. Clinton a bill in July 1996, Mr. Clinton held a cabinet meeting, in which some officials voiced opposition. Mr. Gore strongly urged Mr. Clinton to sign the bill, which he did.</p>
        <p>SCORE CARD This feel-good film is an appeal to conservative Democrats in swing states. It emphasizes Mr. Gore's parting with the left wing of his party on important matters, from the Vietnam War to welfare reform, and casts him as a ''fighter.'' Although the narrator states that Mr. Gore had qualms about the war, the numerous pictures of him in uniform and the emphasis on his enlistment send the message that he not only supports the military but was also on active duty in contrast to Mr. Bush's service in the Texas Air National Guard. The commercial shows that Mr. Gore still wants to convey his human side to voters, and as the first commercial of the fall campaign, it sets an important marker for its positive tone.</p>
        <p>KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
