<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="23DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DC1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mitsubishi Acknowledges It Concealed Complaints  Mitsubishi Motors acknowledged that it had systematically concealed customer complaints about tens of thousands of defective automobiles since 1977.</p>
        <p>The admission by Mitsubishi, Japan's fourth-largest automaker, came a month after its top executive had denied accusations that it had covered up repeated problems that included faulty fuel tanks, fuel tank caps, clutches, crankshafts and brakes. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mitsubishi Acknowledges It Concealed Complaints  Mitsubishi Motors acknowledged that it had systematically concealed customer complaints about tens of thousands of defective automobiles since 1977.</p>
        <p>The admission by Mitsubishi, Japan's fourth-largest automaker, came a month after its top executive had denied accusations that it had covered up repeated problems that included faulty fuel tanks, fuel tank caps, clutches, crankshafts and brakes. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Ameritrade Stock Rises on Rumor  Ameritrade, the fifth-largest online brokerage firm, was contending with a deep slump in its stock price when its new chief executive, Thomas Lewis, abruptly resigned two weeks ago. Since then, Ameritrade's stock has been driven up by speculation that the company will be acquired. That rise accelerated yesterday as shares climbed $1.13, to $17.06, fueled by a rumor that American Express might buy Ameritrade. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Management School of Hard Time  Attica prison, home to many of the most violent felons in New York, may seem like a dangerous place to teach lessons about effective management. But each month, a group of executives and inmates share insights and learn about communicating. Management. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Credit Card Antitrust Trial Ends  The two-month trial of the government's landmark antitrust case against Visa and MasterCard limped to the finish line with both sides expressing satisfaction with their arguments and few reluctant to predict the outcome. [C6.]</p>
        <p>N.A.S.D. Fines E*Trade $20,000  The regulatory arm of the National Association of Securities Dealers announced that E*Trade Securities had been fined $20,000 because it failed to file reports adding up the short positions of its customers for 28 months, from June 1996 through September 1998. Floyd Norris: Market Place. [C9.]</p>
        <p>Partial Verizon Walkout Continues  Two days after more than 50,000 employees of Verizon Communications ended a 15-day strike in New York and New England, representatives for thousands of their colleagues continued to haggle with the company over details of a contract proposal, prolonging the walkout in several Eastern states. [C7.]</p>
        <p>An Executive Moves From No to Yo  When Katherine M. Hudson entered the corporate world at Eastman Kodak some 30 years ago, she was determined to open for herself some doors that until that time were tightly shut to women. Now she is the chief executive of the Brady Corporation, where ''yo'' -- not ''no'' -- is the company cheer. The Boss. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Microsoft Makes a Final Plea  Microsoft made a final plea to the Supreme Court to send its antitrust case first to a federal appeals court for the ''onerous task'' of reviewing the record instead of hearing the appeal directly. [C7.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
