<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Irish Singing Star, Hidden in Plain Sight</title>
    <meta content="23PROF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Brian Kennedy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Brian (Singer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Riverdance (Show)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E4D61F3EF930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Irish Singing Star, Hidden in Plain Sight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brian Kennedy, Irish singing star who is often besieged by fans in Europe, relishes his anonymity in New York, where he is performing on Broadway in the show Riverdance and one night a week at Arlene Grocery; says city's influence will be heard on his next album; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK is giving Brian Kennedy a second chance at anonymity. The Irish singing star with the India-rubber tenor, who shows his face to the autograph-seeking mob in Dublin at his peril, is luxuriating in the quiet freedom of street-strolling and restaurant-lingering, absent the frenzy of fans and the bay of paparazzi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy's splendid anonymity is such that he says two boldface neighbors who live in his apartment building in the Village, Monica S. Lewinsky and Bebe Neuwirth, haven't had the slightest clue to his identity when he politely holds the door for them. ''My neighbors in the lift see me with my guitar, and they ask, 'So what do you do?' '' Mr. Kennedy said, laughing, ''and I spin them a story. I say that I repair guitars.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK is giving Brian Kennedy a second chance at anonymity. The Irish singing star with the India-rubber tenor, who shows his face to the autograph-seeking mob in Dublin at his peril, is luxuriating in the quiet freedom of street-strolling and restaurant-lingering, absent the frenzy of fans and the bay of paparazzi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy's splendid anonymity is such that he says two boldface neighbors who live in his apartment building in the Village, Monica S. Lewinsky and Bebe Neuwirth, haven't had the slightest clue to his identity when he politely holds the door for them. ''My neighbors in the lift see me with my guitar, and they ask, 'So what do you do?' '' Mr. Kennedy said, laughing, ''and I spin them a story. I say that I repair guitars.''</p>
        <p>Not that Mr. Kennedy, 33, is exactly out of the spotlight in Manhattan. As a star of ''Riverdance,'' the Broadway musical, he has been singing four songs plus the finale eight times a week since March at the Gershwin Theater. And lately, on Monday nights, he's been offering up his brand of acoustic Irish soul (large ballads and love songs) to roomfuls of Celtoscenti at Arlene Grocery, the music pub on Stanton Street, as he works out the material for a new album.</p>
        <p>Still, the anonymity that can be conferred by the big city is breathtaking, given Mr. Kennedy's European celebrity. His three solo albums have made his a household voice in Ireland and England. He toured the world from 1994 to 1999 with Van Morrison, and Mr. Kennedy is perennially on television (including a Belfast concert duet with Mr. Morrison before President Clinton in 1996 that was beamed to a billion people).</p>
        <p>Certainly there has been the odd sighting. On his first day in Manhattan, Mr. Kennedy stepped from his building to the pavement and was greeted with ''Look, ooh, it's Brian Kennedy!'' Instantly he was embraced by a tourist mom, dad and three offspring from Cork in Ireland. Of course, the Voice himself furnished his autograph and posed for a family picture.</p>
        <p>For three weeks, he was unrecognized away from the Gershwin until he was crossing West 47th Street and he heard ''a woman screaming in the middle of the street.''</p>
        <p>''I thought she'd been hit by a car,'' he added, ''and then I realized she was yelling, in a big Irish voice, 'Look, there's Brian Kennedy!' And the people on the street are looking around for one of the Kennedys.''</p>
        <p>Monday will be his last appearance at Arlene Grocery until October. Though jammed into a scruffy brick-walled room, fans say they are seizing a rare opportunity. ''It's amazing to see him up close where you can practically touch him,'' said Alice McCaughey, 25, a waitress from Belfast who has been in Manhattan for three years.</p>
        <p>She, a friend and 140 Hibernians had paid their $5 covers on a recent night for an hour and 15 minutes of live Kennedy. Just about everyone in the room was mouthing the words to his hits. Such is the mania of the Irish for a sweet voice, Ms. McCaughey said, that Mr. Kennedy has been surrounded on Dublin streets by his adorers ''and held hostage till he gives them a bit of a song.''</p>
        <p>Critics have praised Mr. Kennedy's powerful, rapid shifts of register and his effortless flights into the countertenor range; fans joke that he should head up a new vocal triad, ''The Irish Countertenors.''</p>
        <p>New York is infusing his next album, ''from the rappers on the street to the three barbershop guys who sing every day in the subway, to the music from out of the car windows,'' he said. ''New York is like a performance, there is music spilling out of everything.''</p>
        <p>His Manhattan sojourn has also encouraged him to put his past in perspective. At Arlene Grocery he performed a new song called ''Christopher Street,'' which includes the words ''I'm finally making peace with the past.''</p>
        <p>His fans are well aware of those years, on Clowny Street at the Falls Road in the heart of Catholic Belfast where he was born ''on the front line of a war,'' as he puts it. As a boy he stepped over bodies blocking his front door, saw neighbors being shot, endured police raids in his house and saw buses aflame down the block.</p>
        <p>He remembers walking home with his four brothers and one sister while British soldiers found amusement in training their guns on them and pretending to shoot. ''It was always odd to turn on the television and see your own street in the news,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The salary of his father, a Roman Catholic working for the British postal system, was so appallingly low that the Kennedys lived for a time as squatters in a cottage so infested with cockroaches ''that we had to burn them out.''</p>
        <p>WHAT saved him, he said, was singing in the choir of St. John's on the Falls Road and in the Clonard Monastery, ''so I was singing in a chapel on Sunday night instead of being bored and looking for trouble.''</p>
        <p>In London, where he moved at 17, a choir performance drew attention to his voice and led to his first regular paid solo singing job -- which led to his new life. Before that gig, to keep from, literally, starving, Mr. Kennedy had been working illegally, caring for dying patients in a hospice. He moonlighted for rent money as a busker, a guitar-strumming singer in the London Underground, ''offering up the odd Elvis tune,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Does he bear malice toward the British for the scars of Falls Road? ''It's hard to, now,'' he said. ''It was in London that I found my voice.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
