<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH SAYS GORE ERRED IN CALLING TAX CUT TOO BIG</title>
    <meta content="23BUSH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/23/politics/23BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congressional Budget Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDC1631F930A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1230" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH SAYS GORE ERRED IN CALLING TAX CUT TOO BIG</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Aug. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican presidential nominee George W Bush aggressively defends his sweeping tax-cut proposal as both responsible and easily affordable in light of federal surplus projections; produces assortment of figures to show that plan would not require cuts in government spending; cites Congressional Budget Office projections of $4.6-trillion surplus over next ten years, including Social Security surplus, and says he needs to make that more clear to voters; photo; defiant declaration responds to Vice Pres Al Gore's repeated charge that Bush would coddle the wealthy at expense of fiscal prudence (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas aggressively defended his sweeping tax-cut proposal today, saying it was both responsible and easily affordable in light of federal surplus projections. Mr. Bush produced an assortment of figures to show that the plan would not require cuts in government spending.</p>
        <p>''I've got to do a better job of making it clear,'' Mr. Bush told reporters in a surprising admission aboard his campaign plane.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas aggressively defended his sweeping tax-cut proposal today, saying it was both responsible and easily affordable in light of federal surplus projections. Mr. Bush produced an assortment of figures to show that the plan would not require cuts in government spending.</p>
        <p>''I've got to do a better job of making it clear,'' Mr. Bush told reporters in a surprising admission aboard his campaign plane.</p>
        <p>The remark came just a day after Vice President Al Gore, suddenly resurgent in the polls, held an extensive discussion of his own suggested tax cuts, which are less than half the size of the ones proposed by Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush pointed to projections by the Congressional Budget Office that the federal government would run a surplus of about $4.6 trillion over the next 10 years, a figure that includes the Social Security surplus. He said voters needed to know that the projection represented money left over even after an expected growth in government spending of about $3.3 trillion.</p>
        <p>He also said that after setting aside the Social Security surplus to shore up that program, he would have roughly $2.3 trillion for tax cuts, new spending and debt reduction. Mr. Bush's proposed tax cut would cost $1.3 trillion over 10 years.</p>
        <p>As soon as voters understand that, he said, ''People will buy into the tax-relief package even more.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not changing my opinion on it,'' he added, a defiant declaration that, like his comments to reporters about the surplus and tax cuts, was largely unprompted. ''It's the absolute right thing to do for America.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's uncharacteristic decision to revisit calculations that his campaign had previously outlined seemed to be an acknowledgment of a potentially troubling political reality for him. Many public opinion polls show that American voters, by and large, are not hankering for an enormous tax cut.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Gore, who has proposed only about $500 billion in tax cuts over the next decade, has been hammering the Texas governor on the issue, repeatedly claiming that Mr. Bush's plan unnecessarily coddles wealthy Americans at the expense of fiscal prudence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said on Monday that Mr. Bush's tax cut would plunge the country into deficits, and today, in a speech in Milwaukee, the vice president added that it would ''wreck our good economy and make it impossible to modernize our armed forces and keep them ready for battle.''</p>
        <p>The burden on Mr. Bush to convince voters that his tax cut is affordable was clear not only in his remarks today but also in those of Representative Ray LaHood, Republican of Illinois, who talked with reporters after a Bush rally in Peoria, Ill. Mr. LaHood had introduced Mr. Bush at today's event.</p>
        <p>Mr. LaHood said that while ''there's some appetite'' among voters for Mr. Bush's suggested tax cuts, ''I think he should also be talking about, 'I want to be able to pay down the debt, too.' I think that is problematic for people.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. LaHood was asked if Mr. Bush's proposed tax cut was too large, both politically and practically, he said merely that it was ''an ambitious proposal'' and that ''Congress will have some say about it.''</p>
        <p>''It's very ambitious,'' Mr. LaHood added. ''There's no doubt about it.''</p>
        <p>During 14 months of campaigning, Mr. Bush has repeatedly said that he is committed to paying down the federal debt, but more often, when he talks about tax cuts, he simply tells people that he wants to return their hard-earned dollars to them. It is a pledge that draws roars of approval from his Republican base.</p>
        <p>While some of the numbers that Mr. Bush and his aides used today for surplus and growth projections had been rounded off, they were essentially valid, in line with estimates from the Congressional Budget Office, and some economists and political analysts consider Mr. Bush's tax cut to be reasonable.</p>
        <p>But others note, among other criticisms of his plan, that if he succeeded in enacting the tax cut, it would be extremely difficult to take it back and raise taxes if the projected surpluses did not materialize.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and his advisers, for their part, say Mr. Gore is the candidate who is potentially endangering the economy by outlining significantly more new spending than Mr. Bush has.</p>
        <p>Today, they cited a report released recently by the National Taxpayers Union, a conservative group, that estimated that Mr. Gore's spending programs over the next 10 years would exceed the surplus, at least if Mr. Gore did not touch the part of that surplus generated by Social Security taxes, as both he and Mr. Bush have promised.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign's concern about accusations that the governor's tax cut is too large was evident both today and on Monday in the aggressiveness of its responses to criticism by Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Karen P. Hughes, the communications director for the Bush campaign, said Mr. Gore had gone ''completely overboard'' and grossly distorted the substance and effect of Mr. Bush's proposal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was ''trying to muddy the waters,'' Ms. Hughes said. ''He doesn't want the American people to know how much money's available.''</p>
        <p>She also said that while Mr. Bush was calling for tax cuts for Americans at every income level, Mr. Gore's plan, directed more specifically at less affluent Americans, would leave 50 percent of taxpayers, totaling 50 million people, without any tax relief.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's plan would reduce federal tax rates across the income spectrum, lowering the highest rate to 33 percent from 39.6 percent and the lowest rate to 10 percent from 15 percent.</p>
        <p>The back-and-forth between the Bush and Gore campaigns about tax cuts, spending and fiscal responsibility reflected a larger aim: each candidate wants to be seen as the more prudent steward of the economy, an issue forever at the top of many voters' concerns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's advisers have long reveled in how well Mr. Bush did in polls that asked voters which candidate they trusted more on the issue. But some of the recent surveys that showed Mr. Gore getting an enormous -- and possibly temporary -- bounce out of the Democratic convention also indicated that voters had at least temporarily reassessed his ability to manage the economy.</p>
        <p>In a CNN/USA Today/Gallup poll released on Sunday, 50 percent of adults surveyed said Mr. Gore would better handle the economy, while 40 percent said Mr. Bush would. Before either party's convention, a poll by the same organizations showed Mr. Bush with a 47 percent to 40 percent lead on the issue. The margin of sampling error was four percentage points.</p>
        <p>On the question of which candidate would better handle the federal surplus, Mr. Gore led Mr. Bush by 48 percent to 41 percent in the recent poll. In the one before the conventions, Mr. Gore trailed Mr. Bush, 38 percent to 49 percent.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
