<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A new sampler of slogans, commercials and campaigns beckons: time for 20 questions.</title>
    <meta content="Y05ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E5D91039F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A new sampler of slogans, commercials and campaigns beckons: time for 20 questions.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advertising column asks 20 questions about advertising, marketing and the media (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is time again to ask 20 questions about advertising, marketing and the media.</p>
        <p>*Now that the Kellogg Company is sponsoring a promotion with the E*Trade Group, centered on a $100 bonus account deposit for consumers who buy Smart Start cereal, will their next joint venture be a Special 401(K)?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is time again to ask 20 questions about advertising, marketing and the media.</p>
        <p>*Now that the Kellogg Company is sponsoring a promotion with the E*Trade Group, centered on a $100 bonus account deposit for consumers who buy Smart Start cereal, will their next joint venture be a Special 401(K)?</p>
        <p>*How come a newspaper advertisement from the FleetBoston Financial Corporation to promote its status as a sponsor of Major League Baseball, which reprinted the lyrics of ''Take Me Out to the Ball Game,'' was careful enough to note that the baseball ''trademarks and copyrights are used with permission'' but misrendered the brand name Cracker Jack as ''crackerjacks''?</p>
        <p>*How pleased were the staff members of Talk magazine and its parents, Hearst and Miramax, to see that a recent subscription offer in a Sunday newspaper insert appeared under a coupon for Tidy Cats Disposable Cat Box and Litter in One?</p>
        <p>*Now that Qwest Communications International has merged with U S West, wouldn't it make for a memorable brand if the combined company were named West Qwest or Qwest West?</p>
        <p>*How could CBS have promoted the sitcom ''Grapevine'' with commercials in which the actors said, ''It's like nothing you've ever seen before'' when it was a remake of a series on the same network in 1992?</p>
        <p>*Did the Kraft Foods unit of Philip Morris really believe parents would rush to buy Capri Sun Fruit Punch Drink Mix because a line at the bottom of print ads reassured them that the product ''won't stain most fabrics and surfaces''?</p>
        <p>*Now that Chad and Alisha Blondeel of Newaygo, Mich., have named their son Espen after ESPN, the sports cable television network, will maternity wards someday soon be filled with babies named Emteevee, Cy Fi, Pax and Dubbya Bea?</p>
        <p>*And will executives at another cable network try to entice Espen's parents to nickname him E?</p>
        <p>*Was it some kind of inside joke that in a magazine ad for a promotion sponsored by Miller Lite beer, depicting a living room furnished with seats from Milwaukee County Stadium, there was a book on an end table titled ''The Italian Renaissance''?</p>
        <p>*What could have put copywriters in the morbid mood to create print ads for the Stouffer's Home Style Entrees line of frozen foods sold by Nestle and the Campbell's Cheddar Cheese Soup sold by the Campbell Soup Company that carried the headlines ''Potatoes so good, you'll think you died and went to heaven'' and ''Quick and easy quesadillas so delicious, you'll swear you've died and gone to Acapulco''?</p>
        <p>*Now that the Army has hired Leo Burnett as its agency, will a Madison Avenue version of ''Fail-Safe'' include a scene in which one general frantically shouts to another: ''Call the president! We've gone to B Com3'' ?</p>
        <p>*Will critics of boy bands cite as proof of their blandness a decision by Famous Fixins, a company that produces celebrity licensed products like Britney Spears Bubble Gum, to introduce a flavored lip balm named after Justin Timberlake of the group 'N Sync that comes in vanilla?</p>
        <p>*Would The Economist magazine have run an ad poking fun at the presidential candidacy of Steven Forbes, carrying the headline ''Concise reporting of the naked truth, love handles and all,'' if Mr. Forbes were not president and editor in chief of Forbes magazine, which competes with The Economist?</p>
        <p>*Now that Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company has introduced a brand called Kenmore Elite, will the next innovation in appliances be a brand called Sub-Zero Plebeian?</p>
        <p>*When the Nabisco Biscuit unit of Nabisco Holdings introduced a character named the Honey Maid Bee in ads for Honey Maid Graham Crackers, did anyone recall the 1950's character Buffalo Bee that appeared in ads for two Nabisco cereal brands, Wheat Honeys and Rice Honeys?</p>
        <p>*Will the introduction by the Franklin Mint of a model of Bonnie and Clyde's getaway car -- a 1932 Ford V-8 ''fully authorized by the Ford Motor Company'' -- mean that collectors will one day be offered a Ford Bronco model to commemorate the O. J. Simpson low-speed chase of 1994?</p>
        <p>*Has there been a better example of an ad slogan boomeranging on the company that made it famous than in a recent ad for TheStreet.com, citing a recommendation to sell Dial Corporation stock before the shares fell sharply, that ended: ''Aren't you glad you read TheStreet.com? Don't you wish everybody did?''</p>
        <p>*Was a recent print ad for the Broadway musical ''Saturday Night Fever'' rendered in the orange and yellow colors of Tide detergent because producers hoped the show would clean up at the box office?</p>
        <p>*Are there any consumers who like the Tic Tac breath mints sold by Ferrero enough to buy the 1,500 packages that will earn the points necessary to order a Trek mountain bike offered as part of the Tic Tac Incredible Stuff promotion?</p>
        <p>*If an advertising columnist asked a posse of beer-drinking buddies ''Whassup?,'' would they reply, ''You ask a lot of questions for someone from Brooklyn''?</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
