<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Where Have You Gone, David Cone?</title>
    <meta content="05ANDE$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cone, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DE1139F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Where Have You Gone, David Cone?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column on New York Yankees ace pitcher David Cone's poor season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LESS than a year ago on the Yankee Stadium mound, David Cone, with his pitching hand and his glove hugging his Yankee cap in disbelief, watched a pop-up come down, down, down into third baseman Scott Brosius's glove for the final out of his perfect game. Then he collapsed in celebration.</p>
        <p>His body language is different now. His disbelief is the same.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LESS than a year ago on the Yankee Stadium mound, David Cone, with his pitching hand and his glove hugging his Yankee cap in disbelief, watched a pop-up come down, down, down into third baseman Scott Brosius's glove for the final out of his perfect game. Then he collapsed in celebration.</p>
        <p>His body language is different now. His disbelief is the same.</p>
        <p>After snatching Oriole left fielder B. J. Surhoff's one-hopper to lead off the sixth yesterday, Cone floated the ball high and wide to first baseman Jorge Posada, whose lunge at the bag was too late.</p>
        <p>On the mound, the 37-year-old right-hander looked away, shaking his head in disbelief at his error.</p>
        <p>''I can't remember ever doing that,'' he said later. ''It was just an easy toss to first base.''</p>
        <p>Minutes later, after he watched second baseman Mark Lewis's two-out, three-run homer disappear beyond the right-center-field fence for a sudden 7-2 lead in an eventual 7-6 loss, Cone stood like a statue, his back to home plate, his head down, his hands on his hips in disbelief.</p>
        <p>''First-pitch slider,'' he said, ''for a three-run homer.''</p>
        <p>By, of all people, the Orioles' ninth-place batter, who had not had a home run all season. And now, after Joe Torre arrived at the mound to change pitchers, Cone jogged to the dugout, trying to ignore the mixture of realistic boos for his 1-7 record and sympathetic cheers for old-times' sake when he was the Yankees' ace.</p>
        <p>''I deserved it and I don't blame them,'' he said of the most boos he has ever heard as a Yankee. ''I kept putting us in a hole. We had a nice comeback, but I put us in too big a hole.''</p>
        <p>Looking to the second half of the season, it's understandable to wonder if Cone will be able to help the Yankees dig themselves out of the hole that jeopardizes another first-place finish in the American League East, if not a wild-card berth in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>He has pitched so poorly that it's understandable to wonder if, despite a career 181-109 record in his 15th major league season, he will ever again be the dependable big-game pitcher that the Yankees relied on so often in the playoffs and the World Series.</p>
        <p>He insists his arm is sound, which makes it even more understandable to wonder if he is through.</p>
        <p>''I couldn't keep the ball in the ballpark,'' he said. ''I only gave up six hits, but four were home runs.''</p>
        <p>Cone has allowed 17 homers this season, including four yesterday that were a one-game high for him.</p>
        <p>''I've tried some things,'' he said, alluding to remedies for his poor record. ''I've moved from the right side of the rubber to the left; I've tried different mechanics. I feel good while I'm doing it, but I've just got to keep the ball in the ballpark.''</p>
        <p>His earned run average is a shabby 6.40. He has not won in his last 11 starts, the longest streak without a victory of his career. His only victory this season occurred April 28, when he pitched seven innings in a 6-0 victory over the now first-place Toronto Blue Jays.</p>
        <p>''It's tough to work on your confidence when you haven't won since April,'' Torre said. ''He's got to find a way to win a game.''</p>
        <p>And the Yankees have to find a way to win more games. Over the last several weeks, their record is 18-28 -- not exactly cost-efficient for baseball's first $100 million payroll. With a $12 million one-year contract, Cone has also been anything but cost-efficient.</p>
        <p>''I feel like I'm holding the club back,'' Cone said. ''I still believe I can turn it around, but my numbers are ugly.''</p>
        <p>Those numbers indeed are ugly. Cone is 5-13 over the last 12 months (including his 6-0 perfect game last July 18 against the Montreal Expos). He has a shaky hits-to-innings ratio: 108 in 90.1. He has a weak walks-to-strikeouts ratio: 43 to 64.</p>
        <p>''His stuff and his velocity numbers have been consistent with last year, but his total command isn't there,'' Torre said. ''He's having trouble locating the slider. I don't know what the answer is, but I'm not about to give up on him helping this team.''</p>
        <p>If the Yankees are to start winning, David Cone needs to start winning, beginning Sunday night when the Yankees play the Mets at Shea Stadium. To know how he is doing, you don't need to watch the scoreboard. Just watch his body language.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
