<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Full House In London Feels Empty To Critics</title>
    <meta content="05NUNN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal National Theater (London)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nunn, Trevor</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Royal National Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DC1039F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Full House In London Feels Empty To Critics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Trevor Nunn, director of Royal National Theater for last three years, is criticized in London papers for leaning too heaviy on crowd-pleasing musicals and being too cautious about promoting new work and younger playwrights; attacks come at time when National has had banner year, winning record nine Olivier Awards and enjoying stellar reviews for many of its 43 productions in last season; photos; Nunn himself says that catching flak is part of job description, although he concedes that mounting untested work demands more bravery than it once did, given threat to box office figures (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While some commercial theatrical producers are accusing nonprofit theaters in the United States of abandoning their mandate to take risks and of playing it safe to fill seats, at least one government-subsidized theater is the subject of similar attacks in Britain.</p>
        <p>Recently, Trevor Nunn, whose credits as director include ''Cats,'' ''Les Miserables'' and ''Nicholas Nickleby'' and who headed the Royal Shakespeare Company for 18 years, has come under considerable fire in the London papers for his three-year-old stewardship of the Royal National Theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While some commercial theatrical producers are accusing nonprofit theaters in the United States of abandoning their mandate to take risks and of playing it safe to fill seats, at least one government-subsidized theater is the subject of similar attacks in Britain.</p>
        <p>Recently, Trevor Nunn, whose credits as director include ''Cats,'' ''Les Miserables'' and ''Nicholas Nickleby'' and who headed the Royal Shakespeare Company for 18 years, has come under considerable fire in the London papers for his three-year-old stewardship of the Royal National Theater.</p>
        <p>In general, critics have taken Mr. Nunn to task for what they call cautious programming that they say leans too heavily on crowd-pleasing musicals and not enough on new work and younger playwrights. Writing in The Guardian in April, Michael Billington said: ''What one craves from the National is some alternative to a musical-dominated commercial culture rather than a duplication of it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Billington compared the current National with that of Mr. Nunn's formidable predecessors, Sir Peter Hall and Richard Eyre, suggesting that Mr. Nunn had abandoned the institution's mandate to break new ground and had failed to make a home for up and coming talent. ''The irony is that under Peter Hall and Richard Eyre, new writing was the National's strongest card,'' Mr. Billington argued. ''Under Trevor Nunn it has become its Achilles' heel.''</p>
        <p>Even when Mr. Nunn does showcase new work, some critics say, he misfires. ''Nunn's choice of new work -- Stephen Poliakoff's abysmal 'Remember This' and Nick Stafford's 'Battle Royal,' '' wrote Nicholas De Jongh in The Evening Standard, ''reminded us what a feeble judge of new plays he is.''</p>
        <p>All this is coming while the National, on London's South Bank, has had a banner year by any standards. In February it won won a record nine Olivier Awards, the London equivalent of the Tony Awards, including one for best director for Mr. Nunn. The new musical ''Honk!,'' based on ''The Ugly Duckling,'' beat ''The Lion King'' for best new musical.</p>
        <p>Many of the theater's 43 productions this past season received stellar reviews, including ''The Merchant of Venice'' and ''Summerfolk.'' The National also exported three productions to New York: ''Copenhagen,'' which won the Tony Award for best play; ''Rose,'' a one-woman play with Olympia Dukakis, which had a less successful run; and ''Our Lady of Sligo,'' a critically praised new Irish drama off Broadway.</p>
        <p>Last season Mr. Nunn sent over ''Not About Nightingales,'' a previously unproduced play by Tennessee Williams that was widely praised by critics. And next season Mr. Nunn's acclaimed production of ''Oklahoma!,'' produced by Cameron Mackintosh, is expected on Broadway.</p>
        <p>In The Evening Standard, Mr. Nunn answered his critics with a 1,500-word explanation of his goals for the National and how he is trying to achieve them. In the piece He quoted Laurence Olivier, who once told him, ''Make no mistake, my boy, running a state-subsidized theater will always be a war.''</p>
        <p>s ''In my darker moments at the South Bank, I feel I know just what he meant,'' Mr. Nunn continued, ''but most of the time I recognize the flak for what it is: a necessary and ongoing debate about what a national theater ought to be.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Sir Peter said that catching flak was part of the job description and that what Mr. Nunn had suffered so far was comparatively mild. ''It's a political appointment, and you get a lot of mud thrown at you,'' Sir Peter said. ''I'm sure Trevor would love to take risks in the National's two main houses, but he'd get run out of town if he didn't balance the books.''</p>
        <p>Sitting in his office on a break between rehearsals recently, Mr. Nunn acknowledged that taking the risk to produce untested work demanded more bravery now than it once did. ''The effort to come to new plays is greater than it ever used to be,'' he said. ''You have to these days recognize the consequence that you could be doing considerable damage to your box office figures if you do that. But one's got to be able to dare. This is not a time to be timid.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunn is constantly aware of the financial pressure. He succeeded in getting the government's Arts Council, which distributes treasury money to the arts, to increase its annual grant to the National to about $21 million; the grant had been frozen at $19 million for six years. Still, Mr. Nunn has said. he has to raise $3.5 million more from private sources.</p>
        <p>''It's nonstop," he said. ''It's a sword of Damocles that dangles above us by a thread and you're constantly imagining that the thread is going to break, it's going to slice you in two.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunn suggests that the critics have pigeonholed him as populist because they associate him with ''Cats'' and Andrew Lloyd Webber, who is known for appealing to middlebrow tastes. He also defends his decision to do musicals, having long disputed any distinction between what is artistically worthy and what is commercially popular. Mr. Nunn maintains, for example, that ''Oklahoma!'' is not only a palatable piece of entertainment but also a pivotal work that changed musical theater.</p>
        <p>As for new work, Mr. Nunn said that up and coming playwrights were welcome and that he was committed to producing venturesome material. ''At least 50 percent of the work should be new writing,'' he said. ''We should be commissioning more, we should be developing and encouraging more new writing in all sorts of different ways.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Nunn said, it is not easy to tap into a new generation of Gorkys or Marlowes, writers who changed the form with their plays. ''You can't just bring about such an age because you want it,'' he said. ''It has to be a confluence of people wanting it and talent and interest being present and available. But I sense that is the case.''</p>
        <p>In the midst of the latest slings and arrows, Mr. Nunn clearly takes refuge in the work itself. Perhaps his greatest point of pride is in bringing on an ensemble of 50 actors, each with an unusually diverse series of roles in the company's repertory, from a small part in Shakespeare's ''Troilus and Cressida'' to a lead role in the Leonard Bernstein musical ''Candide.'' The whole group agreed to stay for 18 months, from January 1999 to June 2000. ''I think that alone is evidence that something special is happening here,'' Mr. Nunn said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunn has received considerable praise for this ensemble. Writing in the The Times of London, Benedict Nightingale called Mr. Nunn's troupe ''the most exciting innovation of his two-year reign.''</p>
        <p>Michael Blakemore, who directed ''Copenhagen'' and has known Mr. Nunn for many years, said that getting to know cast members over an entire season adds a layer of loyalty to the theatergoing experience. ''You can follow individual actors like you follow members of the sports team,'' he said. ''It's the first time the National has been a resident company.''</p>
        <p>If there was any advice Mr. Blakemore might have for Mr. Nunn, he said, it would be to enlist some help and attempt less himself. ''I'm a little surprised he hasn't taken on board a small group of associate directors,'' Mr. Blakemore said. ''He may be trying to do too much.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunn, 60. conceded that the job had taken a personal toll, that he had had less time than he would have liked to see his five children -- ages 4, 9, 11, 14 and 19 -- and his wife, the actress Imogen Stubbs. ''You need to feel there are rewards, that you're making some progress,'' he said. ''I've become a bit of an Eeyore these days. There's a looking on the grimmer side.''</p>
        <p>He feels there is much left to accomplish. While he has stepped up the National's touring, he hopes to do still more as well as to showcase the best of Britain's regional theaters. (The National imported the Birmingham Rep's version of ''Baby Doll,'' which subsequently moved to the West End, and West Yorkshire's revival of ''Singin' in the Rain,'' which plays till July 20.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunn also wants to attract younger and more diverse audiences with special offers. ''There is a perception that the National Theater is for affluent middle England,'' he said. ''It's a perception that I'm determined to change.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Nunn's tenure expires in 2002, there is no obvious successor in view. Would he be interested in a second term, as has been rumored? ''Thoughts about leaving are connected to thoughts about succession,'' Mr. Nunn said. ''One has to know the organization is going to go from strength to strength, rather than by certain calendar day. I'm a believer in organizations finding their future from within. That takes nurturing time.''</p>
        <p>While he could fill his time at the National simply dealing with administrative matters like raising money and programming, he continues to direct (he staged three productions last season) and believes the two roles are complementary. ''The only place from which the theater can be led is the rehearsal room,'' he said. ''I say that in as doctrinaire a way as you care to report it. Doing work, creating work in the rehearsal room is where all the energy of a theater organization proceeds from.''</p>
        <p>''Planning a repertoire can only be done by artists,'' he continued. ''Artists with passions, artists with visions, artists with obsessions. Then all of those things have to be rationalized and made possible. They have to be enabled.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
