<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Convalescing, Japan Debates A Rate Rise</title>
    <meta content="Y05YEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5D61039F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Convalescing, Japan Debates A Rate Rise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, July 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japan's central bank could decide later this month to raise interest rates from their near-zero level now that economy appears to be gaining momentum; such move would be first increase in Japanese rates in a decade; bank's closely watched quarterly survey of business sentiment shows that big Japanese manufacturers were more confident of their future business prospects in quarter ending on June 30 than they have been in three years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faced with growing evidence that the Japanese economy is gaining momentum, the country's central bank could decide later this month to raise interest rates from their near-zero level. Such a move would be the first increase in Japanese rates in a decade.</p>
        <p>The latest sign of economic strength came today with the bank's closely watched quarterly survey of business sentiment, known as the tankan, which showed that big Japanese manufacturers were more confident of their future business prospects in the quarter ending on June 30 than they have been in three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Faced with growing evidence that the Japanese economy is gaining momentum, the country's central bank could decide later this month to raise interest rates from their near-zero level. Such a move would be the first increase in Japanese rates in a decade.</p>
        <p>The latest sign of economic strength came today with the bank's closely watched quarterly survey of business sentiment, known as the tankan, which showed that big Japanese manufacturers were more confident of their future business prospects in the quarter ending on June 30 than they have been in three years.</p>
        <p>''The strength of the tankan means the probability is now quite high for a rate hike,'' said Masaaki Kanno, a senior economist at J. P. Morgan in Tokyo and a former official at the central bank. ''But it's hard to say whether that's a good or bad thing at the moment.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the tankan survey was in many ways a tale of two economies, the global and the domestic, making it hard to draw overarching conclusions from the data.</p>
        <p>While executives at Japan's large corporations were feeling more confident, their colleagues at smaller businesses remained gloomy. That difference in sentiment will complicate the central bank's decision on interest rates, which is likely to be the hottest topic of discussion among the nine policy board members at their next meeting on July 17. The central bank governor, Masaru Hayami, has made it clear that he favors raising rates as quickly as possible, and at least two other members of the policy board have supported him.</p>
        <p>The bank lowered short-term interest rates virtually to zero a year and a half ago, when significant parts of Japan's financial system seemed at risk of collapse and the threat of severe deflation loomed large. But in the process, the bank deprived itself of its most valuable tool, the ability to use interest rates to influence the economy.</p>
        <p>While many economists and policy makers agree that bank officials did the right thing, opinions about when and how the bank should go about recreating a more normal interest rate environment diverge widely.</p>
        <p>There is as yet no clear consensus that the budding economic recovery can flourish on its own, and the tankan survey results did little to resolve the debate.</p>
        <p>Big companies reported that they intended to increase their capital investment by 4.6 percent on average in the current fiscal year, ending in March 2001, but smaller companies said they would be cutting their spending -- and even more sharply than they projected in the previous quarter, from January through March.</p>
        <p>Economists say that difference speaks volumes about the strength of the nascent recovery in Japan's economy, the world's second largest.</p>
        <p>Larger corporations have been able to rely on demand in Europe and the United States to increase business. Were they solely reliant on the domestic economy, like smaller companies and service businesses, they too might be less optimistic about the future.</p>
        <p>Big multinationals also have less need than small companies do for the short-term financing that would become more expensive if the central bank raised interest rates. Indeed, a surge in profits has enabled many large companies to go on a spending spree using their own cash, as reflected in a continuing decrease in bank lending in this country.</p>
        <p>''The big guys that rely on export markets are doing great,'' said Jesper Koll, chief economist at Merrill Lynch &amp; Company in Tokyo, ''but the domestic service sector and small and midsized companies that do most if not all of their business domestically are only a little better than stagnant. The question for the bank thus becomes whom do you run the bank for.''</p>
        <p>Higher rates and borrowing costs for companies might curtail their investment activities or even accelerate the pace of bankruptcies. ''My view is that raising rates would kick off a recession,'' said Robert Alan Feldman, chief economist at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter here.</p>
        <p>But others consider such concerns overblown because the central bank is not likely to raise rates above 0.25 percent. ''The increase in borrowing costs should have only a small impact on economic activity,'' Mr. Kanno of J. P. Morgan said. ''Bank lending is declining anyway, and capital expenditures are increasingly financed internally.''</p>
        <p>The central bank has not laid out guidelines, like inflation targets, that would help steer its decision making and increase understanding of its intentions. It has said that the low rates are meant to help stimulate the economy by keeping the cost of borrowing down. But low rates may also be contributing to a deflationary chain of lower prices, wages and profits.</p>
        <p>Consumer prices in Japan are currently falling at the fastest rate in the last decade. Moreover, the prices that manufacturers can charge for their goods are falling much faster than the prices of their raw material and other costs, eroding profit.</p>
        <p>Central bank policy board members argue that much of this is ''good deflation,'' but they have yet to produce convincing evidence.</p>
        <p>The finance ministry is also making things difficult for the bank in setting a clear policy. The ministry, another center of financial power in this country and often a rival, is using its authority on intervention in the currency markets to send a clear message that it does not favor raising interest rates. It has ordered the central bank to intervene to keep the yen from rising more than 10 times this year. Such intervention tells the market that rates are unlikely to rise, since a rate increase would itself put upward pressure on the yen.</p>
        <p>At times, the bank seems confused about its role. Like most central banks, its legal mandate is to maintain price stability. But lately, some policy board members have expressed concern that a ''moral hazard'' is emerging from the exceptionally loose monetary policy. They fear that by holding rates effectively at zero, they have enabled corporate Japan to avoid the painful overhaul it needs.</p>
        <p>''I understand, and in some ways agree with the concern about moral hazard,'' Mr. Feldman said. ''But the bank is not in charge of structural policy, and anyway, using interest rates to influence structural reform is sort of like using a hammer to hit a screw.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
