<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Advantage Williams: It's Venus vs. Serena</title>
    <meta content="05TENN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Venus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hingis, Martina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Serena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raymond, Lisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E6D61039F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Advantage Williams: It's Venus vs. Serena</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England, July 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Venus Williams defeats Martina Hingis and Serena Williams defeats Lisa Raymond at Wimbledon tennis tournament; Williams sisters will face each other in semifinals; table of their results against each other; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the sixth game of the third set when a nervous murmur slipped out of the spellbound witnesses. A desperate Martina Hingis had lunged to send back a shot that fluttered like a harmless butterfly above the net, and they could see what was coming.</p>
        <p>Rushing forward with a furious churn of arms and legs, Venus Williams materialized like a praying mantis to devour Hingis's effort with a swinging forehand volley. On instinct, Hingis guessed right at the angle of the return and stabbed at the blur of yellow, only to flick a lob long. With a deep sigh, Hingis expressed her hopeless state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the sixth game of the third set when a nervous murmur slipped out of the spellbound witnesses. A desperate Martina Hingis had lunged to send back a shot that fluttered like a harmless butterfly above the net, and they could see what was coming.</p>
        <p>Rushing forward with a furious churn of arms and legs, Venus Williams materialized like a praying mantis to devour Hingis's effort with a swinging forehand volley. On instinct, Hingis guessed right at the angle of the return and stabbed at the blur of yellow, only to flick a lob long. With a deep sigh, Hingis expressed her hopeless state.</p>
        <p>Over and over, beneath the ominous clouds suspended above Center Court today, the powerful Williams made Hingis look as vulnerable as a victim in a dunk tank. Hingis kept popping to the surface, steeling herself for more, but she could only endure so much. In the sixth game of the third set, Williams became the first of the two to hold serve over an eight-game span. Once she grabbed the 4-2 lead, she never wavered on serve again.</p>
        <p>On match point, Williams reached back and uncoiled a 118-mile-an-hour ace to end a 6-3, 4-6, 6-4 classic quarterfinal at Wimbledon. As her serve rocketed past Hingis, Williams squealed for joy. Suddenly, the ominous 20-year-old morphed into a child as she skipped to the net with her ponytail bouncing and her smiling eyes fixed on the friends' box.</p>
        <p>There was her giddy father, Richard, and her next opponent, too. Less than an hour into her sister's match, Serena Williams sneaked into the stadium after having razed Lisa Raymond, 6-2, 6-0, in 41 minutes. On Thursday, Venus and Serena Williams will meet in the semifinals.</p>
        <p>Their matchup marks the third time sisters have met in the tournament's history. In the inaugural Wimbledon final, in 1884, Maud Watson defeated her sister, Lillian,  6-8, 6-3, 6-3. In 1966, Gail Sherriff-Chanfreau slipped by her sister Carol, 8-10, 6-3, 6-3.</p>
        <p>''I see it as an opportunity, not an opportunity against Serena,'' said Venus, who was an emotionally detached spectator when Serena won the United States Open last summer to become the first of the two to win a Grand Slam singles title. ''She's been blazing past opponents -- no mercy. I want to go in with that same attitude.''</p>
        <p>That kind of edge was there for Lindsay Davenport today. Persevering through a troublesome start, she outlasted a surprisingly focused Monica Seles, 6-7 (4), 6-4, 6-0, and will play Jelena Dokic in the other semifinal. Typical Davenport, she has made her way through the draw in wallflower fashion. In all likelihood, she will continue to be part of the background when the Williams sisters meet for the fifth time since they arrived on the pro tour.</p>
        <p>First there was Venus, then Serena. At least one of the parents who guided them to this amazing point will not be in attendance on Thursday. The eccentric Richard Williams plans to attend a funeral that day. He does not know the deceased -- it is a friend of an acquaintance he met at Wimbledon this week -- but he said it will be his escape from a match he sees as a tossup.</p>
        <p>''If I was betting, I'd put 50 pounds on Venus and 50 pounds on Serena; then I can't lose because one of them will be in the final,'' Richard Williams said. ''I think they're excited to get this far, but you have to understand human feelings. I don't think they're excited about playing each other, but their family bond is stronger than tennis.''</p>
        <p>If there was anxiety between Venus and Serena Williams -- both of whom dismiss the notion of a sibling rivalry -- they camouflaged it today with giggles and jokes. Serena, 18, flashed her half-moon grin when told of her father's match-day plan.</p>
        <p>''I know I would be heartbroken if my little Jackie had to play my Star . . . those are my two dogs,'' Serena said like a comic delivering a punch line. ''Maybe it's too much pressure on him. It's probably the same reason I wouldn't watch my dogs.''</p>
        <p>There was laughter as Serena finished her monologue. She is the more extroverted of the sisters, but even the more serious Venus could not resist adding to the light-hearted atmosphere by describing the strategy her little sister used when they were children.</p>
        <p>''Serena was a cheater,'' Venus said. ''I just rolled with it. It's tough to argue against Serena because she was so good at arguing, so good at cheating. It was no use. I don't think this time we'll be calling the lines.''</p>
        <p>The level of play in the Hingis-Williams match even surpassed the tension-filled three-set semifinal the two played at the United States Open last summer. Hingis won that day, but that victory only set her up to lose to Serena in the final.</p>
        <p>During the sixth game of the second set today, Hingis was at her clairvoyant best. As Venus Williams lined up an overhead, Hingis paged through her mental scouting report, crept to her right and was in position. As Williams smashed the overhead, Hingis lunged and blocked it back down the line for a winner. The shot helped produce the service break she needed to go on and take the set.</p>
        <p>Usually, Hingis can shake an opponent's confidence by breaking her spirit. But Williams just kept coming, kept taking the ball in the air on swinging volleys and kept pounding her backhand for 14 winners. To keep pace, Hingis went for every line, as well. Both players took risks with drop shots and continued to plant aggressive ground strokes into the grass like drill bits.</p>
        <p>The two were in an attack-and-respond mode that produced endless deuce games and few holds of serve. Hingis won 6 of 16 break chances, while Williams converted 7 of 20. At one overlapping point of the second and third sets, the players went eight games without holding serve. With Williams going for every first serve, she made only 61 percent. Although Hingis was cautiously spinning in her first serve at 81 percent, it sat up in the cross hairs for Williams.</p>
        <p>''I was just trying to put a first serve in,'' Hingis said. ''It's going to be good enough usually, but not enough against Venus today.''</p>
        <p>Finally, in the sixth game of the third set, Williams stopped the trend and never looked back. In the end, Hingis probably did the best she could do, and she still lost. A player whose self-esteem was once impenetrable was left doused in self-doubt. Over her last four Grand Slam events, Hingis has lost to four hard hitters: Serena Williams (United States Open), Davenport (Australian Open), Mary Pierce (French Open) and Venus Williams today at Wimbledon.</p>
        <p>''It used to be enough just with my abilities I had at the time,'' a dispirited Hingis said. ''It has changed so much since the Williamses started playing better. I guess as the No. 1, you're supposed to win a Grand Slam. But now someone else probably deserves to be No. 1.''</p>
        <p>Only one Williams sister can win a Wimbledon singles title this year.</p>
        <p>''What this thing boils down to is Venus and Serena,'' Richard Williams said. ''Everyone else has to step aside.''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
