<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fast Cars Remain, But Life Is Slower</title>
    <meta content="05AGAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Philippoussis, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DE1139F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fast Cars Remain, But Life Is Slower</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England, July 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Philippoussis, competing in Wimbledon tennis tournament, comments on plans to concentrate on tennis, interview (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is still a Ferrari in the garage, but it is a lonely set of wheels since Mark Philippoussis began discarding the artificial fillers in a life once scant on career substance.</p>
        <p>He would spend his days wave running on Miami Beach, his nights surfing for fun and only his spare moments applying his considerable talents to tennis. The serve, the strokes, the range. He had all the skills but fell short in work ethic. He has put a ''For Sale'' sign on his bachelor pad in south Florida.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is still a Ferrari in the garage, but it is a lonely set of wheels since Mark Philippoussis began discarding the artificial fillers in a life once scant on career substance.</p>
        <p>He would spend his days wave running on Miami Beach, his nights surfing for fun and only his spare moments applying his considerable talents to tennis. The serve, the strokes, the range. He had all the skills but fell short in work ethic. He has put a ''For Sale'' sign on his bachelor pad in south Florida.</p>
        <p>Now, Philippoussis is following the lead of his opponent Wednesday in a quaterfinal at Wimbledon. While Pete Sampras tries to fend off the hot Jan-Michael Gambill in one highlighted quarterfinal match, Philippoussis will look across the court and find Andre Agassi in another one.</p>
        <p>Throughout his career, Agassi has searched for deep meaning; Philippoussis is starting the same journey.</p>
        <p>''I've had everything that you could possibly have,'' Philippoussis said. ''Now I'm a little sick of it, which is good. It's a phase I went through. I got it out of my system. Obviously I still like the fast cars, but I've sold almost all of them.</p>
        <p>''Miami was exciting for me as a 22-year-old when I first moved there. Of course, I mean, the night life and the atmosphere is incredible. But I'm actually moving. I'm going to go back to Australia. I want to be with my family and friends. Start concentrating.''</p>
        <p>He has been focused throughout a laborious but uplifting run through Wimbledon, which included a five-hour victory in the third round and another five-set victory in the fourth. Agassi is much fresher.</p>
        <p>Although Todd Martin pushed Agassi to a fifth set in the second round, he has not dropped a set since. But he is wary of Philippoussis, who has served 77 aces in his last two matches.</p>
        <p>''I would like to know what it feels like to be Mark Philippoussis and hit a 128-mile-per-hour serve down a set point,'' Agassi said. ''I'd like to know what that feels like. But I like the fact that my dynamics of play matches up pretty well against baseliners and big power hitters. I think it brings a lot of elements that the game of tennis has to offer.''</p>
        <p>That is why his quarterfinal is so intriguing. If Philippoussis is the biggest server in the game right now, Agassi is the best at returning the blasts. Although Agassi has won three of the four previous matches against Philippoussis, there is a notable change in the Australian's desire.</p>
        <p>Part of this metamorphosis can be credited to Boris Becker, who recently told Philippoussis that he hadn't reached 40 percent of his potential. Mostly, Philippoussis has been influenced by his coach, Mike DePalmer.</p>
        <p>''We've been talking, and obviously we talk every day,'' Philippoussis, who will be 24 in November, said of his coach. ''He sits me down just to tell me what he thinks I need to do. We've definitely talked about that. Pretty much what he said is: 'If you want to be a champion, you have to be a champion 24 hours a day. You've got to live like a champion, think like a champion, talk like a champion in order to become one.' ''</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
