<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BULLETIN BOARD</title>
    <meta content="05BULL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LearnNow</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Victory Schools Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arenson, Karen W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holloway, Lynette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Lionel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education/Columns/Bulletin Board</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Charter Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4DC1139F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BULLETIN BOARD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT, KAREN W. ARENSON, LYNETTE HOLLOWAY and LIONEL ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward; Holloway, Lynette; Arenson, Karen W; Anderson, Lionel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of education news: Bronx charter school set to open in Sept delays opening for year because of change in company that will run school; LearnNow is replacing Victory Schools, which will continue to oversee Harlem school and open two other new New York charter schools (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charter School Delays Opening</p>
        <p>The Harriet Tubman Charter School, which was scheduled to open its doors to 245 Bronx students in kindergarten through third grade this September, has delayed its opening for a year, following a change in the company that is to operate the school. The Board of Regents, which granted the school a charter last fall, has asked the school to file a new operating plan. LearnNow, a for-profit education company based in New York, has been chosen to run the school, said EUGENE V. WADE JR., the company's chief executive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Charter School Delays Opening</p>
        <p>The Harriet Tubman Charter School, which was scheduled to open its doors to 245 Bronx students in kindergarten through third grade this September, has delayed its opening for a year, following a change in the company that is to operate the school. The Board of Regents, which granted the school a charter last fall, has asked the school to file a new operating plan. LearnNow, a for-profit education company based in New York, has been chosen to run the school, said EUGENE V. WADE JR., the company's chief executive.</p>
        <p>Victory Schools, the company that was to have managed Tubman, parted ways with Tubman's directors after a disagreement last spring. But it will continue to oversee the Sisulu Children's Academy in Harlem and is planning to open two new charter schools in New York this fall.</p>
        <p>Students Win Science Awards</p>
        <p>Five New York City high school students won top awards in the Lucent Technologies Bell Labs Science Grant Program, which awards up to $1,000 to minority students from New York and New Jersey. First prize went to LATOY SMITH of Plainfield High School in Plainfield, N.J., for research on bacterial growth at different temperatures. INGRID RABUS of Port Richmond High School in Staten Island, who researched the effects of a hormone on plant growth, shared second prize with CARLENE YOUNG from Plainfield High School, who questioned the validity of horoscopes.</p>
        <p>Four students from Benjamin Cardozo High School in Bayside, Queens,  shared third prize: HUGO GUERRERO studied the effects of water pollution on organisms at a nearby lake; ALAINA SHEPPARD investigated the marsh ecosystem of Long Island Sound; KELLY SILVERA examined polymerize chain reactions that replicate DNA; and ANDRE PLAIR analyzed the way radiation affects the activity of an enzyme.</p>
        <p>Educators Collaborate at Aspen</p>
        <p>As education administrators gathered at the Aspen Institute in Colorado last weekend to discuss how to improve coordination between public schools and universities, the motto on the T-shirts they were given summed up the topic succinctly: ''College Begins at Kindergarten.'' Among the administrators attending the conference were HAROLD O. LEVY, New York City schools chancellor, MATTHEW GOLDSTEIN, chancellor of the City University of New York, RICHARD P. MILLS, the state education commissioner, and PETER D. SALINS, provost of the State University of New York. They traded notes with their counterparts from other states about everything from teacher education to how to win more support from the business community. One thing he learned, Dr. Goldstein said, was that ''New York is really ahead of the rest of the nation'' when it comes to cooperation between universities and public schools.</p>
        <p>Life Lessons for High Schoolers</p>
        <p>Beginning Sunday, 35 underprivileged Bronx high school students will spend two weeks at the State University of New York's Purchase campus learning about graphic design, the Internet and how to test water quality. The program is also aimed at encouraging the students to go to college and educating parents about college admissions and financial aid, said ELIZABETH LONDON, a spokeswoman for Phipps Community Development Corporation, a nonprofit agency in Manhattan that is sponsoring the program with the college and the New York City Board of Education.</p>
        <p>The students were selected by teachers from Theodore Roosevelt High School, Wings Academy and West Farms Career Education Center.</p>
        <p>EDWARD WYATT, KAREN W. ARENSON, LYNETTE HOLLOWAY and LIONEL ANDERSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
