<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tea? Turmeric? The Quest for Safer Barbecue</title>
    <meta content="05WELL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="EATING WELL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Barbecue</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spices</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burros, Marian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Eating Well</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EEDB1039F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1359" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tea? Turmeric? The Quest for Safer Barbecue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marian Burros</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burros, Marian</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marian Burros Eating Well report on techniques for reducing the potential carcinogens released when meat, fish and poultry is grilled over high heat; they include sprinkling meat with tea powder, marinating it with spices like garlic and turmeric, precooking it in oven, removing fat from steaks before cooking and serving green salads; photo; recipes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE height of the barbecue season is not when anyone wants to hear about the hazards of eating meat with a nicely blackened crust hot off the grill. But scientists have long known that substances created when meat and poultry are cooked at high heat can cause cancer in animals and that there is some evidence that they may have the same effect on humans.</p>
        <p>While health professionals still recommend cutting back on overall meat consumption, recent research suggests that there are more appealing ways to make grilled meat less hazardous. Some are common-sensical, like eating it rare (though this is not recommended for chicken or hamburger) or medium instead of well done, or cooking it at lower temperatures for shorter periods. But others are more startling, like sprinkling meat with tea powder, or mixing ground meat with cherries, or just marinating meat before cooking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE height of the barbecue season is not when anyone wants to hear about the hazards of eating meat with a nicely blackened crust hot off the grill. But scientists have long known that substances created when meat and poultry are cooked at high heat can cause cancer in animals and that there is some evidence that they may have the same effect on humans.</p>
        <p>While health professionals still recommend cutting back on overall meat consumption, recent research suggests that there are more appealing ways to make grilled meat less hazardous. Some are common-sensical, like eating it rare (though this is not recommended for chicken or hamburger) or medium instead of well done, or cooking it at lower temperatures for shorter periods. But others are more startling, like sprinkling meat with tea powder, or mixing ground meat with cherries, or just marinating meat before cooking.</p>
        <p>Clearly, scientists are now so aware of the potential risks that they are looking into every corner of the kitchen for solutions. But their research is in its earliest stages, so they are not really sure how or why some of these techniques work.</p>
        <p>''It's hard for scientists to say we don't know,'' said Dr. Mark G. Knize, a member of the Biology and Biotechnology Research Program at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in Livermore, Calif., who is conducting some of the research on the effects of marinades.</p>
        <p>For whatever reason, though, he and other scientists have found that one of the most promising techniques for meat and poultry is marination. Done even briefly, it reduces the cancer-causing compounds called heterocyclic amines, or HCA's, formed when creatine in muscle meats reacts with amino acids at high temperatures. (Fish is much less a problem than meat or poultry.) But marination does nothing to reduce the level of other carcinogens that arise when fat falls on a fire and causes smoke.</p>
        <p>Scientists have not yet deconstructed all their marinade ingredients to pinpoint the anti-cancer agents. They suspect that the antioxidants in certain foods like garlic, onions, chives, turmeric, thyme, rosemary and oregano, as well as vitamins C and E, are responsible.</p>
        <p>In studies last year at the Cancer Research Center of Hawaii in Honolulu, three different sauces were used to marinate steaks overnight. One was a teriyaki sauce, another contained turmeric and garlic powder and the third was a commercial sauce made of honey, high-fructose corn syrup, vinegar, concentrated tomato juice, modified food starch, salt and seasonings. Four-ounce pieces of marinated and unmarinated steak were cooked on a propane gas grill for varying times at varying temperatures. The marinades were not reapplied during cooking.</p>
        <p>The shorter the cooking time and the lower the heat, the lower the levels of the suspect amines in meats marinated in the teriyaki and turmeric sauces, compared with unmarinated meat. Steaks marinated in the commercial sauce and cooked similarly had much higher levels of the amines than the other marinated meats; the researchers said this may have been partly because the corn syrup and honey caused the steaks to burn and char faster and more extensively.</p>
        <p>I conducted taste tests on the teriyaki and turmeric sauces. The turmeric marinade adds flavor to tender but otherwise tasteless steak, while the teriyaki makes meat slightly sweet, although the brown sugar it contains causes the meat to burn faster.</p>
        <p>In a 1997 study at Lawrence Livermore, researchers marinated chicken breasts in a mixture including garlic, salt, citrus juice and olive oil that also contained considerable sugar, and they concluded that the sugar was probably responsible for an increase in one of the amines. Using sweet commercial barbecue sauces may be just the wrong thing.</p>
        <p>Other researchers are looking into other antidotes. Dr. John Weisburger, director emeritus of the nonprofit American Health Foundation in New York, has done studies indicating that sprinkling tea powder, either green or black, on meat before grilling could help reduce the formation of the amines. He surmises that it might even help to drink very strong tea while eating grilled meat. Tea, of course, is a powerful antioxidant. (Powdered tea is available in specialty and Asian markets.)</p>
        <p>And then there is the cherry solution, devised in 1999 in Michigan, a big cherry producer. It substitutes ground fresh cherries for 11.5 percent of the ground beef for hamburgers. J. Ian Gray, a food scientist at Michigan State University in East Lansing who worked on the study, said that there was nothing magical about cherries and that many tree fruits, like plums, would also reduce the amines because they contain similar antioxidants. (I found that adding cherries made hamburger extremely soft, almost mushy.)</p>
        <p>He suggested that mixing 40 milligrams of vitamin E from a gelatin capsule into a pound of ground beef might also do the trick.</p>
        <p>All these findings are still quite preliminary, of course, as is the data linking heterocyclic amines with cancer in humans. Dr. Elizabeth G. Snyderwine, a specialist in chemical carcinogenesis at the National Cancer Institute in Bethesda, Md., said that research on animals certainly supported the notion that the amines ''are potential human carcinogens, and further studies are needed to determine the human risk,'' especially for breast, colon and prostate cancers. But she added that different individuals might react differently to the amines.</p>
        <p>Several recent studies have established a connection between human cancer and meat that has been well cooked, as it is usually done on a grill. Dr. Rashimi Sinha, a researcher at the National Cancer Institute, said, ''We found a twofold risk of breast cancer in women who consumed very-well-done red meat as compared to rare or medium.''</p>
        <p>In another study, at the Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health in Baltimore, researchers found that women who regularly ate flame-broiled (charred) meat also had an increased risk of breast cancer.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Sinha cautioned that ''these are just two studies, and in epidemiological studies you need more than two small studies to make a definitive statement.''</p>
        <p>''In three to five years,'' she added, ''there will be a lot of studies showing whether the association is real or not. At this point there is no consensus.'' She said that eating an occasional well-cooked steak is not harmful but that even though the research is still preliminary, ''eating well-cooked meat four times a week from the grill is a little scary.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Sinha, Dr. Snyderwine and Dr. Knize offered other suggestions to reduce exposure to carcinogens from high-heat cooking like grilling. One is to cook chicken with its skin on and then discard the charred skin. With all meat, avoid eating the charred surfaces.</p>
        <p>Precook meat or chicken in an oven or a microwave oven until it is half done to get rid of some juices that contain the precursors of the carcinogens and to minimize the grilling time.</p>
        <p>Remove fat from steaks before cooking. (As the fat drips onto a fire or coals it causes flare-ups and smoke, which contain other carcinogens.) Keep flames from lapping meat and charring it. And if possible use the indirect method of grilling, with the heat source off to the side instead of directly beneath the food.</p>
        <p>And then there is the more-is-better approach: serve a salad of green leafy vegetables with grilled meat. Certain components of many fruits and vegetables may mitigate the effect of the carcinogens.</p>
        <p>Green salad, marinated steak cooked medium-rare -- that's a summer dinner that may not be a bad prescription.</p>
        <p>TERIYAKI MARINADE  Adapted from the Cancer Research Center  of Hawaii  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>1 clove garlic, crushed  1 piece ginger, minced  2 teaspoons brown sugar</p>
        <p>1/2 cup soy sauce  6 4-ounce pieces of steak.</p>
        <p>Combine garlic, ginger, sugar and soy sauce with  1/2 cup water. Brush on steaks, and marinate overnight in refrigerator.</p>
        <p>Yield: 1 cup.</p>
        <p>TURMERIC GARLIC MARINADE  Adapted from the Cancer Research Center of Hawaii  Time: 5 minutes</p>
        <p>2 teaspoons garlic powder  1 teaspoon ground turmeric  6 4-ounce pieces of steak.</p>
        <p>Stir garlic and turmeric into  1/2 cup water. Brush over steaks, and marinate overnight in refrigerator.</p>
        <p>Yield:  1/2 cup.</p>
        <p>EATING WELL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
