<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Lefty Jones Fails His First Test</title>
    <meta content="05METS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida Marlins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DE1139F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Lefty Jones Fails His First Test</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, July 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florida Marlins defeat New York Mets, 9-8 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Sunday night, facing the Yankees at Shea Stadium on national television in their final game before the All-Star Game break, the Mets are scheduled to start the left-hander Bobby M. Jones. Another option would be to bring back Mike Hampton on three days' rest.</p>
        <p>After Jones failed to hold a five-run lead today and lost to the Florida Marlins, 9-8, Mets Manager Bobby Valentine was asked if Jones would still pitch that showcase game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Sunday night, facing the Yankees at Shea Stadium on national television in their final game before the All-Star Game break, the Mets are scheduled to start the left-hander Bobby M. Jones. Another option would be to bring back Mike Hampton on three days' rest.</p>
        <p>After Jones failed to hold a five-run lead today and lost to the Florida Marlins, 9-8, Mets Manager Bobby Valentine was asked if Jones would still pitch that showcase game.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, probably,'' Valentine said. ''He's in line to, let's put it that way. We'll just see how the whole thing shakes out.''</p>
        <p>It was a lukewarm endorsement, and it was understandable. Making his first Mets start in place of the injured Rick Reed, Jones's command escaped him in the fourth inning. In the fifth, he faced four batters and retired none, then watched as the Marlins took the lead on a double steal that really was not.</p>
        <p>The Mets scored three runs after falling behind by 9-5, and with one on and one out in the ninth, Mike Piazza came off the bench to pinch-hit. Piazza was hit on the left elbow by the backswing of Preston Wilson on Monday, and he did not start because of soreness. X-rays on the elbow showed that nothing was broken, and when Piazza began feeling better today as the game went on, he volunteered to pinch-hit.</p>
        <p>With Jay Payton on first, Piazza hit a grounder to third and Payton beat the throw to second. Though Piazza reached first base safely, the fielder's choice ended his hitting streak at 21 games.</p>
        <p>Worse for the Mets, Antonio Alfonseca then struck out Todd Pratt and Melvin Mora to end the game.</p>
        <p>Jones worked four-plus innings, and gave up seven runs on six hits and three walks. He was starting for the first time since June 10, after pitching only one inning during an eight-game stint with the Mets in mid-June and an inning and a third in a subsequent relief appearance for Class AAA Norfolk.</p>
        <p>Jones worked two bullpen sessions in that time, but there is no substitute for game experience. His fastball was not down as often as he wanted it to be, he said, and his slider was inconsistent. Jones knows the Mets demand better from him, no matter how little he has worked.</p>
        <p>''I think, personally, it's a direct reflection of only pitching two innings in 20 days,'' Jones said. ''But I don't have room to make mistake after mistake. This is a team that's very good with a chance to go a long way. That's not what they're looking for; they're looking for a pitcher to get people out. I think I'm that person, but, hey, I have to show it. I can't just tell them.''</p>
        <p>Jones and Bill Pulsipher arrived at spring training as the favorites to land the fifth starter's spot, but Glendon Rusch passed them both and won the job. Pulsipher, who was traded to Arizona in June, had two starts in May for the Mets and was roughed up, faltering in the fourth inning both times.</p>
        <p>Jones followed the same pattern. He retired eight of the first nine Marlins hitters today, but the more of Jones the Marlins saw, the better they did. Protecting a 5-0 lead in the fourth, Jones issued a pair of two-out walks and was visited on the mound by the pitching coach, Dave Wallace.</p>
        <p>The next hitter was Alex Gonzalez, batting .174, and Jones fell behind, 2-0. His next pitch was a high fastball -- ''He laid one in there,'' Valentine said -- and Gonzalez belted it deep into the left-field seats for a three-run homer.</p>
        <p>''Some pitches that I thought were strikes got called balls today,'' said Pratt, the catcher in place of Piazza, ''and any time the count turns into 1-0 instead of 0-1, or 2-1 instead of 1-2, it doesn't matter who's pitching, the hitter's more confident.''</p>
        <p>Things got worse for Jones in the fifth. The pinch-hitter Mark Smith drew a leadoff walk and Luis Castillo singled. Mark Kotsay ripped an opposite-field double to the warning track in left, scoring two runs to tie the score, 5-5.</p>
        <p>Cliff Floyd then dribbled a grounder about 50 feet toward third base, and it went for an infield single, ending Jones's day.</p>
        <p>Pat Mahomes entered, and with runners at first and third, Floyd broke for second on the first pitch. Pratt's throw bounced off the infield grass and deflected off Floyd's helmet. Mora, the shortstop, raced over to grab the ball, but he could not get it from his glove as Kotsay scampered home with the go-ahead steal of home.</p>
        <p>The play was ruled a double steal, even though Kotsay did not go until the throw bounced and struck Floyd.</p>
        <p>''The triple-clutch -- we had him easy,'' Pratt said. ''The guy didn't break until Melvin had the ball. But that isn't to blame. I'm supposed to be the leader on defense, and I didn't execute well. Our offense gave us enough to win, and the defense didn't play up to our capabilities.''</p>
        <p>After Mahomes walked Wilson, a one-out intentional walk to Derrek Lee loaded the bases. Gonzalez struck out, and Mike Redmond grounded a ball up the middle, giving the Mets a chance to escape the inning with minimal damage.</p>
        <p>But as Mora ranged to his left, he bobbled the ball, and his error sent Floyd home to give Florida a 7-5 lead. Smith singled in two more to increase the lead.</p>
        <p>The Mets got closer on a two-run homer in the sixth by Todd Zeile, who did not start because of a stiff neck,  and a bases-empty shot by Edgardo Alfonzo in the ninth, but the Marlins prevailed, winning their fifth game in a row. The Mets have lost 6 of 11 games to Florida this year, and they will be glad to be done with the upstart Marlins after Wednesday's game.</p>
        <p>''They're going to play havoc with people who have to play them the rest of the year,'' Valentine said. He did not note that the first-place Atlanta Braves have five games left with the Marlins.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>LENNY HARRIS, who had started only once for the Mets, walked three times as the leadoff hitter.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
