<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Creamy Butter, and No Cow</title>
    <meta content="05GOAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Butter</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cookies</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bakeries and Baked Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E4DD1039F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Creamy Butter, and No Cow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amanda Hesser report recommends goat butter imported from France; photos; cookie recipe (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH our allegiances to cow butter, oils and lard, a new butter is bound to be met with suspicion. How will it behave in cooking? Can it be used in a cake? Does it taste as good as cow butter?</p>
        <p>This could be why Fairway on the Upper West Side has carried goat butter on and off for 10 years and it still moves like pig's knuckles. Goat butter doesn't make much of a visual impression, either: it is pure white, like commercial lard.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH our allegiances to cow butter, oils and lard, a new butter is bound to be met with suspicion. How will it behave in cooking? Can it be used in a cake? Does it taste as good as cow butter?</p>
        <p>This could be why Fairway on the Upper West Side has carried goat butter on and off for 10 years and it still moves like pig's knuckles. Goat butter doesn't make much of a visual impression, either: it is pure white, like commercial lard.</p>
        <p>Tasting it, though, is like tasting pinot noir for the first time when all you've ever had is merlot. It's creamy, gentle, lighter than cow butter and, well, goaty. It doesn't have as much tang as goat cheese but it does have a little, and it maintains much of the earthy fragrance of the milk.</p>
        <p>Even with all the new goat-cheese makers in the United States, there is still very little  goat butter available, said Steven Jenkins, the cheese buyer for Fairway, which sells it for $15.15 a pound. He imports it from Celles-sur-Belle, a cheese maker in Poitou-Charentes, in western France. Cooks there treat goat's butter like cow's butter, Mr. Jenkins said, swirling it in hot pans to make beurre noir for skate and sole, and blending it into dough for torte au fromage.</p>
        <p>Goat butter's moisture content is higher than cow butter's, and it is always unsalted. But otherwise the two are interchangeable in most dishes. With sauteed spinach, goat butter coated the leaves and emulsified with the spinach juices at the bottom of the pan. It tasted rich and round and yet, somehow, leaner. I liked it better than cow butter with a minerally green like spinach. Slim carrots glazed with the butter got a thinner coating but were delicious, and you could taste the butter's faint sour tang.</p>
        <p>When I browned some butter in a small pan, it turned the color of a hazelnut and had the same nutty aroma that you get from cow butter. In a recipe for sables, which are delicious with cow butter, it might take a dairy farmer to notice the difference in flavor. The cookies weren't as golden when I used goat butter, but they were just as heavenly.</p>
        <p>The butter's real nuance came through when I spread it on a piece of bread, sprinkled a little sea salt on top and ate it with a glass of Pineau des Charentes, a wine made near where the French goats roam. The wine is honey sweet, and it led me to my next plan for the butter: toast with goat butter and honey.</p>
        <p>SABLES  Adapted from ''Maida Heatter's Best Dessert Book Ever'' (Random House, 1990)  Time: 45 minutes, plus 1 hour's standing time</p>
        <p>2 egg yolks  3 ounces unsalted goat butter  Finely grated rind of 1 large, cold, firm lemon</p>
        <p>1/4 cup granulated sugar  1 cup plus 2 tablespoons sifted unbleached flour</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon salt.</p>
        <p>1. Line two flat or inverted baking sheets with parchment paper. Set aside. Place egg yolks in a small pan, and cover with water. Bring to a simmer, and let cook for 2 minutes; then, remove from heat and let stand for a minute. Remove yolks with a slotted spoon, and let cool.</p>
        <p>2. In a food processor, combine yolks and butter. Process for 10 seconds, scraping sides if necessary, until smooth. Add lemon rind, sugar, flour and salt, and process for 15 to 20 seconds, until ingredients hold together.</p>
        <p>3. Turn dough out onto a floured pastry cloth or lightly floured counter, and with floured hands, form into a firm square shape. Use a floured rolling pin to roll out to a 10-inch square (about  1/8 inch thick). To straighten sides, press a ruler or a long metal spatula against them.</p>
        <p>4. Using a long knife, cut square into four strips, then in the opposite direction into fourths, making 16 squares. Cut each square on an angle, making 32 triangles. Using a thin metal spatula, transfer triangles to  baking sheets, spacing them apart. Dip a fork in flour, and with the underside of  prongs, mark a ridged design on top of each cookie. Let stand for one hour.</p>
        <p>5. Adjust oven racks in upper-third and lower-third positions. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Bake cookies, one sheet on each rack, for about 15 minutes, until only sandy colored. Change racks, and reverse sheets front to back once during baking to ensure even browning.</p>
        <p>6. Remove sheets from oven. Slide parchment off sheets, and let cookies stand until almost cool. With a spatula, turn them over, and let stand until completely cool. Store in an airtight container.</p>
        <p>Yield: 32 cookies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
