<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>VICTOR IN MEXICO PLANS TO OVERHAUL LAW ENFORCEMENT</title>
    <meta content="05FOX.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mexico-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chiapas (Mexico)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Ginger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DEFDD1139F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1195" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>VICTOR IN MEXICO PLANS TO OVERHAUL LAW ENFORCEMENT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINGER THOMPSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thompson, Ginger</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, July 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mexico's president-elect, Vicente Fox Quesada, pledges to rebuild country's federal law enforcement system and wipe out corruption that has crippled nation for decades; is likely to use executive powers to create a Ministry of Security and Justice, similar to Federal Bureal of Investigation, that would be responsible for all federal police, significantly reducing powers of Interior Ministry and attorney general; says he will meet with Pres Clinton and both major presidential candidates to press proposal to open US-Mexico border to less restricted flow of immigrants; expounds on measures his new government will take to deal with range of Mexico's most persistent and complex problems, including fight against poverty, efforts to stem flow of drugs and unresolved conflict in Chiapas; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president-elect of Mexico, Vicente Fox Quesada, announced plans today to rebuild the country's federal law enforcement system, moving it toward an American model of justice as a way to wipe out corruption that has crippled his nation for decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox also said he would travel to the United States soon to meet with President Clinton and both major presidential candidates to press his proposal to open the United States-Mexico border to a less-restricted flow of immigrants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The president-elect of Mexico, Vicente Fox Quesada, announced plans today to rebuild the country's federal law enforcement system, moving it toward an American model of justice as a way to wipe out corruption that has crippled his nation for decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox also said he would travel to the United States soon to meet with President Clinton and both major presidential candidates to press his proposal to open the United States-Mexico border to a less-restricted flow of immigrants.</p>
        <p>The president-elect also explained some of the measures his new government would take to deal with a range of Mexico's most persistent and complex troubles, including the fight against poverty, efforts to stem the flow of drugs through Mexico and the unresolved conflict in Chiapas.</p>
        <p>A two-hour news conference by Mr. Fox, whose election on Sunday ended a 71-year rule of the Institutional Revolutionary Party, turned into a wide-ranging foreign policy address. But his most detailed proposals centered on his fight against corruption, a problem he considers a top priority.</p>
        <p>To accomplish the overhaul, he is likely to use executive powers that allow him to create a federal police agency and to shift law enforcement responsibilities from one agency to another.</p>
        <p>Toward that end, he said, he will  create a Ministry of Security and Justice, similar to the Federal Bureau of Investigation, that will be responsible for all the federal police.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox's plans would also significantly reduce the powers of the Interior Ministry, which currently manages a recently created federal police force. And the attorney general's office would be similarly weakened, not only by the removal of its control over federal law enforcement, but also by Mr. Fox's plans to create a new agency of federal prosecutors to manage investigations.</p>
        <p>Because his ideas have widespread support, Mr. Fox's transformation of the system is also expected to be well received in the Mexican Congress even though it will no longer be dominated by any single political party as a result of the election on Sunday.</p>
        <p>In his wide-ranging comments, Mr. Fox brought up his goal of having greater cooperation between the United States, Mexico and Canada. He suggested the creation of a North American common market that would allow a freer flow of merchandise and workers, with strict standards for the protection of the environment, law enforcement and workers' rights.</p>
        <p>''It appears to me that both of us have lost sight of the goal,'' Mr. Fox said, referring to the United States and Mexico. ''The United States' goal has been to put up walls, police and soldiers to fight immigration. That can't work.''</p>
        <p>''Mexico's goal,'' he added, ''has been to open an escape valve, allowing 350,000 young people to cross the border each year and washing its hands of any responsibility.''</p>
        <p>''If we are serious,'' Mr. Fox concluded, ''the least we can do is sit down and say, 'This is the problem' and the goal is to close the development gap.''</p>
        <p>In his answers to reporters' questions, Mr. Fox also offered specific proposals for improving United States-Mexican relations, including extending the benefits of the North American Free Trade Agreement  more evenly to small businesses on both sides of the border and turning the drug certification program from a unilateral to a multilateral process involving all countries affected by trafficking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox said that in the next two months he would use five international head-hunting concerns to help him select the members of his cabinet so that leading up to his inauguration on Dec. they can work side by side with the ministers they will replace. A team of aides to Mr. Fox have also been assigned to work with the current leaders of the Finance Ministry on setting next year's budget.</p>
        <p>In trying to transform the law enforcement system, Mr. Fox's plans could be upset by a backlash from below, where bureaucrats and officers enjoy strong Civil Service protections.</p>
        <p>President Ernesto Zedillo reorganized and renamed the nation's drug police at least twice, and each time traffickers quickly infiltrated the forces and bought off leading officials.</p>
        <p>And he created a new federal police force to fight a mounting wave of federal crimes, including kidnapping. But so far the new police have done little to make Mexicans, especially those in larger cities, feel any safer.</p>
        <p>Jorge Chabat, an analyst of Mexican law enforcement, praised Mr. Fox's plan to take the federal police out of the hands of politicians, who used the agents for their own agendas. He said he felt some pessimism over whether the new system would be resistant to the corrupting forces of drug traffickers. But, he said, ''someone has to try to fight them.''</p>
        <p>''The truth is whatever the government tries, it will face a problem with the corruption of traffickers.''</p>
        <p>In emphasizing his commitment to fighting corruption, Mr. Fox turned the spotlight not only on the past, but also on his administration and its future. He announced that he would create a ''Commission of Transparency,'' made up of Mexican citizens whose job would be to investigate high-profile scandals of past administrations as well as to serve as a watchdog over his own government.</p>
        <p>But he was careful to make clear that he would not conduct wholesale investigations of government conduct before taking office.</p>
        <p>''We do not want to waste our government looking only at the past and conducting witch hunts that could be misinterpreted,'' Mr. Fox said in the news conference at the presidential residence, Los Pinos. The transparency commission, he added, would be his government's way to ''set its sights forward, to construct a harmonious government and also to make an accounting of the past.''</p>
        <p>In a signal of assurance to the Mexican military, Mr. Fox said he would not consider appointing a civilian as chief of the Ministry of Defense. ''I see no reason to break a tradition that has brought stability to the country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>On other domestic issues, Mr. Fox said he wanted to visit Chiapas as soon as possible and reopen peace talks with the Zapatista rebels. He  said he was willing to consider withdrawing the military from rural areas of conflict in the state, one of the rebels' main demands.</p>
        <p>Fighting poverty was another area that Mr. Fox called a priority and he said that he would not approve budgets or program proposals from members of his cabinet unless they could demonstrate in concrete terms how these would help the poor.</p>
        <p>''This would be our way to pay attention to the groups that have been totally excluded from the development of our country,'' he said. ''It is one of the strong principals that we are going to introduce in the decision-making process of the new government.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
