<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mussina Takes Time To Be a Cordial Visitor</title>
    <meta content="05PINS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212636"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Orioles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mussina, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mendoza, Ramiro</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DE1139F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mussina Takes Time To Be a Cordial Visitor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Yankee Notebook article focuses on possibility that Baltimore Orioles might trade star pitcher Mike Mussina; Yankee Ramiro Mendoza, on disabled list, tests sore shoulder in practice; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a photo opportunity made for baseball's rumor mill: Mike Mussina emerged from the Baltimore Orioles' dugout during the Yankees' batting practice yesterday and shook hands with Derek Jeter and Bernie Williams.</p>
        <p>Mussina, one of the American League's best pitchers over the last decade, is eligible to become a free agent after this season, and already his name is being bantered about as possible trade bait.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a photo opportunity made for baseball's rumor mill: Mike Mussina emerged from the Baltimore Orioles' dugout during the Yankees' batting practice yesterday and shook hands with Derek Jeter and Bernie Williams.</p>
        <p>Mussina, one of the American League's best pitchers over the last decade, is eligible to become a free agent after this season, and already his name is being bantered about as possible trade bait.</p>
        <p>It is unlikely the Orioles would trade him, however. Mussina has the right to veto a trade and may be inclined to do so, and Baltimore is still trying to re-sign the right-hander, who probably is their most important player in their attempt to regain respectability.</p>
        <p>Mussina is seeking a six-year contract from the Orioles for an annual salary close to the $15 million Kevin Brown is being paid by the Dodgers, close to what the Yankees have agreed to pay Roger Clemens in a two-year extension that is expected to go into effect after this year.</p>
        <p>Mussina has never made a secret of the fact that he likes to play for the Orioles, and in Baltimore, which is not far from his home in Montoursville, Pa.</p>
        <p>But if Mussina cannot reach an agreement with the Orioles, there figures to be a robust market for his services. Cleveland is close to his home in Pennsylvania, and so is New York. There may be a time in the fall when Mussina will be greeted -- and wooed -- by Williams and Jeter.</p>
        <p>Mendoza Tests Shoulder</p>
        <p>Ramiro Mendoza, on the 15-day disabled list because of tendinitis in his shoulder, played catch on flat ground yesterday and said he felt a little sore.</p>
        <p>''We'll see how it feels tomorrow,'' the Yankee right-hander said.</p>
        <p>Mendoza could be activated after the All-Star Game break and might move into his old spot in the bullpen.</p>
        <p>Ed Yarnall, the left-hander who will probably be promoted to pitch against Baltimore tomorrow, could win a spot in the rotation if he throws well. The Yankees' preference has been to keep Mendoza in the bullpen and provide a deep corps of relievers.</p>
        <p>Allen Watson, a Yankees' left-hander, received a shot of cortisone in the back of his pitching shoulder, and he will attempt to rehabilitate the joint in the weeks to come. But if Watson's shoulder does not improve and he does not regain velocity on his fastball, he will have arthroscopic surgery that would most likely end his season.</p>
        <p>''My velocity was down 9 to 10 m.p.h.,'' Watson said. ''Hopefully, we're going to try and see if we can rehab and get that back.''</p>
        <p>Watson went on the disabled list last week after separating his right shoulder, and he will need surgery to tighten the shoulder capsule. But he will probably not have that operation until it is determined that he will not pitch any more this year, whether that is in four weeks or four months.</p>
        <p>Spencer Bangs Knee</p>
        <p>Shane Spencer, the Yankees' left fielder, slammed his right knee into the left-field fence while pursuing Mike Bordick's home run in the first inning. The knee quickly swelled.</p>
        <p>''It was this big,'' Spencer said, holding his hands far apart.</p>
        <p>Spencer was examined after the game, but did not feel much pain, and Manager Joe Torre expects him to be available tonight as the designated hitter, with David Justice starting in left field.</p>
        <p>Chris Turner started at catcher in spite of the minor shoulder injury he sustained as he helped to break up last Saturday's fight with Tampa Bay. Turner seemed to be bothered, however, when he made a weak and unsuccessful throw to first base.</p>
        <p>Rotation Duties</p>
        <p>Joe Torre has still not announced some of his starting pitching assignments for this week. He did go so far as to say that Orlando Hernandez will pitch Friday, Roger Clemens on Saturday in the second game of the doubleheader against the Mets (in Yankee Stadium), and David Cone on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Torre would not say who would start tomorrow, mentioning that Ben Ford could be a possibility. But Ford pitched in relief yesterday, and it still appears that Yarnall will be promoted from Class AAA to pitch in that game, and that Jason Grimsley will start the first game of Saturday's doubleheader (at Shea).</p>
        <p>Transportation Schedule</p>
        <p>Any plans to have the Yankees use the subway to travel between games Saturday never really developed. The current plan is for them to be taken by bus from Yankee Stadium to Shea Stadium on Saturday morning while dressed in their street clothes, then change into their road uniforms, which will remain at Shea all weekend.</p>
        <p>After Saturday afternoon's game, set to begin around 1:15, the Yankees will board two buses and be escorted by the police back to Yankee Stadium. If the Mets and the Yankees finish the afternoon game by 4 o'clock, the Yankees could be back by 5 o'clock and have three hours until Game 2 begins.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: YANKEES NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
