<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Assignment for the Courts' Point Man</title>
    <meta content="05PROF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Law</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Jonathan Lippman</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lippman, Jonathan (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4DC1139F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Assignment for the Courts' Point Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column on Judge Jonathan Lippman, New York's chief administrative judge; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE are some of Judge Jonathan Lippman's  responsibilities: hatchet man, water carrier, schmoozer, massager, apologist, defender, memo writer, nastygram writer, rule maker,  breakfast-meeting taker the morning after speaking at a rubber chicken dinner, worrier, worrier, worrier. Smile!</p>
        <p>All this, most days, weekends included, before 9 a.m.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE are some of Judge Jonathan Lippman's  responsibilities: hatchet man, water carrier, schmoozer, massager, apologist, defender, memo writer, nastygram writer, rule maker,  breakfast-meeting taker the morning after speaking at a rubber chicken dinner, worrier, worrier, worrier. Smile!</p>
        <p>All this, most days, weekends included, before 9 a.m.</p>
        <p>In other words, anything associated with riding herd on 1,300 New York State judges and 2,600 town and village justices -- individuals more accustomed to giving orders than receiving them -- plus 15,000 court employees, and, of course, addressing the fears and jeers of the justice consumers, including prosecutors, defense lawyers and the public.</p>
        <p>''The pleasure is in moving mountains!'' Judge Lippman says grandly. Strike that. ''O.K. To budge them a little,'' acknowledges a man who starts his work calls around 5:30 a.m., arriving at his large, airy Lower Manhattan office an hour later.</p>
        <p>Plus, this chief administrative judge must answer to his boss. ''I serve at the pleasure of Judge Kaye,'' says Judge Lippman, the  court system's No. 2 guy, the do-guy, who by his estimate, speaks with Chief Judge Judith S. Kaye seven times a day. (Ten, by her reckoning.)</p>
        <p>''I'll get 10 letters complaining about smoking in the Bronx courthouse and I just send them over to Jonathan,'' Judge Kaye says. ''Then he fixes the problem and I get the credit.''</p>
        <p>Judge Lippman, 55, has spent his entire professional life in the Hydra-headed court system, the last 11 at the near-top or top of the heap. He is said to know more about how the system works than anyone else, having done just about every paper-pushing and executive job in it except one: he's the highest-ranking judge never to have heard a case.</p>
        <p>If he pulled off a minor miracle in transforming New York's jury system, bringing in a million new jurors and making the obligation less frequent and shorter, he is now charged with a major one. Judge Kaye just announced that she intends New York to be the first state to require most nonviolent drug addicts who plead guilty to be offered treatment instead of prison. Facing major obstacles -- reality, among them -- Judge Lippman must make it happen. ''With the jury project, everyone thought the system couldn't get any worse, so 90 percent of the public thought we were on the side of angels,'' says Judge Lippman, a fast-talking, ebullient fellow whose Lower East Side accent renders ''law'' as ''lore.''</p>
        <p>But such consensus does not attach to drugs, crime and punishment. ''There are a lot of political clashes about what to do,'' he adds. Prosecutors who want to be seen as tough on crime will resist him, as will some defense lawyers and judges.</p>
        <p>Judge Lippman is generally respected by Albany legislators -- Sheldon Silver, the Assembly speaker, is a boyhood friend -- and personally liked by many in the system, even when they resent the message du jour from apparatchik central -- more supervision; more accountability, to defuse a recent scandal over patronage; lousy assignments on chambers.</p>
        <p>He learned people-political skills from his father, Ralph Lippman, who started out selling chickens and later managed affordable nonprofit co-op apartments on the Lower East Side, becoming known as the mayor of Grand Street.</p>
        <p>Representing perhaps 10,000 tenants, the Grand Street mayor was always meeting with city dignitaries. ''So many people called him 'Ralphie' that later on, some plaques said 'Ralph E.,' '' Judge Lippman recalls.</p>
        <p>His experiences of the bustling co-op were so positive, he adds, ''that I lived at home till I got married'' (to Amy, a lawyer and mother of their two children).</p>
        <p>''I wasn't always such a grind,'' Judge Lippman asserts. ''At summer camp I was a color war general. But I skipped some grades and entered college at 16, and I wasn't ready, socially, to be a freshman. So I threw myself into work.''</p>
        <p>In a sense, he transferred his affection for Grand Street to the court system, which he entered fresh out of New York University Law School as a lowly law assistant. (Several ranks later, he changed the title to the more dignified ''court attorney.'')</p>
        <p>''It was closer, smaller then, with less back-biting,'' he says. ''Now the system is bigger; there's more cliques. Judges and lawyers were happy to be there then, and that's not so true now.''</p>
        <p>Excepting his immediate family, he says, ''The court system is the only other family I know.'' Sometimes, when trying to calm down veteran court clerks or judges, he'll say, ''Hey! We grew up in the courts together. This is me, little Jonny Lippman, remember?''</p>
        <p>On occasion, the ploy even works.</p>
        <p>In 1995, having been deputy chief administrator for six years, he was appointed a Court of Claims judge as a reward. When Judge Kaye named him to the top job the next year, he could officially say he was a judge bossing judges, though some judges still see him as the quintessential nonjudicial company man.</p>
        <p>Together, with applause and some outrage, he and Judge Kaye have imposed wide-ranging changes on the courts, reining in civil court, opening the family court to the public, and trying to speed the processing of cases.</p>
        <p>''Now we have lawyers complaining that we're moving the cases too fast!'' says Judge Lippman, laughing. ''I never thought I'd hear that.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
