<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lemon Drop Kid Beats Behrens in Suburban</title>
    <meta content="05RACI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburban Handicap</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Durso, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D71039F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lemon Drop Kid Beats Behrens in Suburban</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH DURSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Durso, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lemon Drop Kid wins Suburban Handicap at Belmont Park; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lemon Drop Kid took some fast and serious strides toward racing's year-end honors yesterday when he outran Behrens by two and a half lengths and won the $500,000 Suburban Handicap at Belmont Park in the second-fastest time in the history of the 114-year-old race.</p>
        <p>He not only defeated Behrens, who ran second to the world-class Dubai Millennium in the $5 million Dubai World Cup in March, but also flew the mile and a quarter in 1:584/5 . That time was just three-fifths of a second off the track record, set in the Suburban in 1991 by In Excess. And Lemon Drop Kid also became only the fourth horse to race a mile and a quarter in the Suburban in less than two minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lemon Drop Kid took some fast and serious strides toward racing's year-end honors yesterday when he outran Behrens by two and a half lengths and won the $500,000 Suburban Handicap at Belmont Park in the second-fastest time in the history of the 114-year-old race.</p>
        <p>He not only defeated Behrens, who ran second to the world-class Dubai Millennium in the $5 million Dubai World Cup in March, but also flew the mile and a quarter in 1:584/5 . That time was just three-fifths of a second off the track record, set in the Suburban in 1991 by In Excess. And Lemon Drop Kid also became only the fourth horse to race a mile and a quarter in the Suburban in less than two minutes.</p>
        <p>Edgar Prado, who also rode Lemon Drop Kid to a seven-length score in the Brooklyn Handicap last month, made no secret of the fact that he had kept Behrens blocked on the rail.</p>
        <p>''I knew I had Behrens pinned on the inside, and at the top of the stretch, I wanted to get the jump on him,'' Prado said. ''My horse just took off, and I knew Behrens was chasing me.''</p>
        <p>Scotty Schulhofer, who trains Lemon Drop Kid, conceded that ''the position we were in didn't hurt us.''</p>
        <p>''He just keeps on running,'' Schulhofer said. ''He's finally got focused, and Prado is the big thing as far as the improvements go.''</p>
        <p>And Jeanne Vance, who owns Lemon Drop Kid, said: ''This one is extra special because Behrens was in the race.''</p>
        <p>Both Schulhofer and James Bond, the trainer of Behrens, predicted a return match in the Whitney at Saratoga on Aug. 6. And Bond felt that the four-month layoff and inside post position had compromised Behrens while Wild Imagination set the lead for most of a mile before Lemon Drop Kid made his move and Behrens finally escaped from the rail.</p>
        <p>Lemon Drop Kid ran three-quarters of a mile in 1:094/5  and one mile in 1:341/5 . It was, as predicted, a two-horse race with Lager third and Almutawakel finishing last in the field of six. The winner paid $3.60 for a $2 bet.</p>
        <p>In the day's other stake, the $113,800 Poker Handicap, Affirmed Success made a ringing success of his debut on the grass as he drove home with a length and three-quarters over the Irish horse Rabi, who had half a length on Weatherbird. With Jorge Chavez riding, Affirmed Success ran the mile on the turf in 1:34 flat and paid $4.90 for a $2 bet to win.</p>
        <p>Richie Schosberg, who trains Affirmed Success for Albert Fried Jr., explained the transition in these words: ''After he lost two Breeders' Cup Sprints in a row, we decided that the only alternative was to put him on the turf and see if he could make the Breeders' Cup Mile.''</p>
        <p>In the Poker Handicap, Divide and Conquer broke down on the far turn with a fractured right foreleg and was destroyed by injection. The jockey, John Velazquez, was not injured.</p>
        <p>So, having run seven stakes in seven days through the long Fourth of July weekend, Belmont Park will close for two days and resume racing on Friday at 3 P.M.</p>
        <p>FINISH LINES</p>
        <p>At Monmouth Park on the Jersey Shore, two of BOB BAFFERT's filly stars of last year raced as the favorites in the two features, and came within one neck of sweeping the races with COREY NAKATANI, imported from California, riding. In the $75,000 Regret Stakes, the 1999 juvenile champion Chilukki, who won her first six starts but lost her next three, came back to win by five lengths over Superduper Miss. It was Chilukki's first victory since October, but she was backed down to 1-5 by the bettors and redeemed herself, running the six furlongs in 1:093/5 . In the $300,000 Molly Pitcher Handicap, the 4-year-old Silverbulletday, who lost four of her five previous races, gave it a game effort down the homestretch but missed catching Lu Ravi by a neck. Silverbulletday switched from the rail to the outside as they turned for home, but could not quite overtake the winner, a 5-year-old daughter of A. P. Indy trained by CARL BOWMAN with PAT DAY riding. Lu Ravi ran the mile and a sixteenth in 1:43 and paid $5.60 for upsetting the even-money favorite.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
