<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iran Reformers, Beaten Back, Persist</title>
    <meta content="Y05IRA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E0DE1139F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iran Reformers, Beaten Back, Persist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>TEHRAN, July 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iran's reformers scale back once-defiant agenda for change in face of crackdown by conservative court; are concentrating on regaining public voice through their control of new Parliament; are trying to build bridges with opposition conservatives, who control approximately 30 percent of government, by toning down language on changes they once championed; are focusing instead on reviving once lively national press, streamlining government ministeries, passing national budget and devising legislation to encourage formation of political parties (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With most of their newspapers silenced and many of their activists jailed by conservative courts, Iran's reformers have scaled back their once-defiant agenda for change and are concentrating on regaining a public voice through their control of the new Parliament.</p>
        <p>Inside the vast high-ceilinged chamber where the lawmakers meet, there is a sense of reduced expectations. It is a mood far different from the euphoria that followed their sweeping victory in the first round of parliamentary elections in February.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With most of their newspapers silenced and many of their activists jailed by conservative courts, Iran's reformers have scaled back their once-defiant agenda for change and are concentrating on regaining a public voice through their control of the new Parliament.</p>
        <p>Inside the vast high-ceilinged chamber where the lawmakers meet, there is a sense of reduced expectations. It is a mood far different from the euphoria that followed their sweeping victory in the first round of parliamentary elections in February.</p>
        <p>Then, the reformers pledged that they would soon make good on all the vague promises of democracy and freedom that were made by their hero, President Mohammad Khatami, when he was elected in 1997.</p>
        <p>But their ambitions were visibly trimmed by a conservative backlash -- the press crackdown, the detention of pro-democracy activists, the voiding of more than a dozen races won by pro-Khatami candidates and a three-month delay in certifying the election results for many others.</p>
        <p>''People have huge demands and expectations from this Parliament and government,'' acknowledged Mohammad Reza Tabesh, a newly elected lawmaker from the reform movement and a nephew of Mr. Khatami, in a recent conversation. ''It's almost too much.''</p>
        <p>Then he paraphrased a Persian proverb to describe the Khatami camp's operative strategy: ''The one who moves forward is not the one who moves fast.''</p>
        <p>The new Parliament -- Iran's sixth since the revolution in 1979, which replaced the monarchy with a theocratic leadership -- began work on May 27. It has spent much of the time since then organizing.</p>
        <p>Only 268 members have taken up their posts. The results of elections for the remaining 22 seats in the 290-member body are still being disputed by the conservative Council of Guardians, which approves candidates, certifies elections and can block any legislation that it deems offensive or contradictory to its interpretation of Islam.</p>
        <p>Although the conservative opposition controls only about 30 percent of the Parliament seats already decided, the cautious reform majority has so far tried to postpone their inevitable head-on collision.</p>
        <p>As speaker, they elected a compromise figure, Mehdi Karroubi, a turbaned cleric who ran on a pro-Khatami ticket but is also a former hard-liner and past Parliament leader. Mr. Karroubi has been busy in the last few weeks shuttling from meetings with pro-reform groups to get-togethers with hard-line religious leaders in Qum and in the Council of Guardians.</p>
        <p>''The factions have to learn how to cooperate with each other -- and they will learn,'' said Abbas Salimi Namin, of the conservative Tehran Times daily newspaper. But Iran's politicians, he added, are still new at competing as pragmatic political adversaries and not as arch-enemies.</p>
        <p>''We don't have much experience in this,'' said Mr. Namin. ''The role of parties -- how they should be controlled, how they should work with each other -- it's not very clear to us.''</p>
        <p>As the reformers try to build bridges, they also have toned down their language on changes they once championed, such as lifting the ban on satellite television dishes and limiting the power of quasi-official morals squads and hard-line courts.</p>
        <p>Instead, they have said they will concentrate on reviving the once lively national press, streamlining government ministries, passing a national budget and devising legislation to encourage the formation of political parties.</p>
        <p>Their first and main priority, they said, is to strip the country's press law of restrictive amendments added by hard-liners in the last Parliament, which have been used to close 20 liberal newspapers and magazines since the elections, leaving mostly right-wing publications and the state television channels, which regularly condemn the reform movement as un-Islamic and an agent of American imperialism.</p>
        <p>The muting effect was demonstrated just last week, when a reform member of Parliament rose from his red leather seat and began to denounce the state television operation as the ''mouthpiece'' of only one political faction. A few seconds into his speech, the television screens in the chamber went dark as cameramen from the government broadcasting company shut off their equipment.</p>
        <p>The proposed new press law is energetically backed by Mr. Khatami's government.</p>
        <p>Although the president's aides have spoken of the need to depoliticize the court system and ensure that judges act according to the law, they say he is not likely to offer any sweeping reforms that might provoke a dangerous showdown.</p>
        <p>But their prudence is unlikely to avert clashes with the conservatives. The Council of Guardians, for example, can cancel any new reform legislation it does not like. The Parliament can appeal, but only to another potentially unfriendly body called the Expediency Council.</p>
        <p>A number of hard-liners have already signaled that they will fight the new press law, saying the Parliament should deal with the ailing economy rather than issues of political and press freedom.</p>
        <p>Reform activists, who are badly split among themselves on whether to pursue a state-controlled or free-market economy, said they will try to resist.</p>
        <p>''Of course, economic issues are important and, separately, we have to find solutions to the problems of inflation and unemployment among our youth,'' said Jamileh Kadivar, a reformer elected from Tehran. ''But to solve the economic problems, we must create a stable and secure state in order to attract foreign investment that would in turn create jobs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
