<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lesson in Time Trials From the ONCE Team</title>
    <meta content="05TOUR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abt, Samuel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4D61039F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lesson in Time Trials From the ONCE Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL ABT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abt, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>ST. NAZAIRE, France, July 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tour de France bicycle race continues; Spain's ONCE team wins team time trial; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ONCE team from Spain gave a classic illustration today of how to ride a team time trial, winning by 45 seconds, finishing with all nine of its men together at the same time and placing two of them atop the new standing in the Tour de France.</p>
        <p>But ONCE also offered too obvious a picture of how to illegally shield a rider from the wind. Because the team car blatantly rode beside a rider, Marcos Serrano, offering him protection and a forward draft when the Spaniard began to fall behind on a windy uphill on a long bridge, all its riders were penalized 20 seconds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The ONCE team from Spain gave a classic illustration today of how to ride a team time trial, winning by 45 seconds, finishing with all nine of its men together at the same time and placing two of them atop the new standing in the Tour de France.</p>
        <p>But ONCE also offered too obvious a picture of how to illegally shield a rider from the wind. Because the team car blatantly rode beside a rider, Marcos Serrano, offering him protection and a forward draft when the Spaniard began to fall behind on a windy uphill on a long bridge, all its riders were penalized 20 seconds.</p>
        <p>Otherwise smoothly rotating riders at the head of its single file, ONCE powered to victory over the 70-kilometer (43-mile) flat course from Nantes to St. Nazaire in western France in 1 hour 25 minutes 35 seconds. Second was the United States Postal Service team, 46 seconds behind before the penalty, with Telekom from Germany third, 40 more seconds behind.</p>
        <p>That meant that the new man in the overall leader's yellow jersey is Laurent Jalabert, a Frenchman who long reigned as No. 1 among the world's top 800 professional racers but who has never finished higher than fourth in previous Tours because of his weakness in the highest mountains. Jalabert will most likely continue to wear the jersey at least until the first of those mountains, the Hautacam climb in the Pyrenees.</p>
        <p>Second over all is his teammate David Canada, a Spaniard, 12 seconds behind, with Lance Armstrong, an American and the defending Tour champion, third, 24 seconds behind. Abraham Olano, a Spaniard with ONCE, is fourth, 35 seconds behind, and Slava Yekimov, a Russian with Postal Service, is fifth, 43 seconds behind. Five other ONCE riders rank in the first 11 since the entire team received the time of its fifth man across the line.</p>
        <p>This was the first team time trial in the Tour since 1995. The race against the clock, in which teams set out five minutes apart, was dropped because it penalizes strong riders with weak teams and those teams that have lost riders because of crashes in the early days. There were no such casualties this year.</p>
        <p>The Cofidis team finished seventh among the 20 entries, costing David Millar, a Scot, the yellow jersey he won when the Tour began its three-week journey last Saturday. This morning, Millar was guarded about his chances to remain the leader, especially since his team has worked hard the past two days to chase breakaways and protect his jersey.</p>
        <p>''We rode the course a couple of months ago to check it out,'' Millar said. There's a lot of headwind because of the prevailing wind off the nearby Atlantic, he said.</p>
        <p>''If we've got winds like that all the way, it's going to be fairly harsh.''</p>
        <p>It was. Millar is now in 24th place, 2:27 behind Jalabert, whom he led by 6 seconds when the teams set out. Armstrong also cited the wind as a big factor when he said a few days ago: ''It's point to point, so if there's headwind, it'll be there all the way. If it was start to finish in the same place, at least part of the way you'd have tailwind.''</p>
        <p>Armstrong's Postal Service team finished with only six of its nine starters together, a perilous situation since the time of the fifth man across counts for himself and anybody ahead of him. Johan Bruyneel, the team's directeur sportif, or coach, said Armstrong had gone too hard as the team approached the 4-kilometer-long (2.5-mile-long) St. Nazaire bridge over the Loire River estuary with the gray Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Three riders were unable to keep pace and dropped far behind with a dozen kilometers (7.5 miles) to go. A fourth, Tyler Hamilton, an American, managed to hang on through great courage and willpower.</p>
        <p>A bull throughout the stage, Armstrong remained bullish about at least part of the outcome. ''All is not lost,'' he said. ''The Tour de France won't be decided by the team time trial.''</p>
        <p>''And it's important that I picked up some more time on the climbers and on Ullrich,'' he added, referring to Jan Ullrich, the Telekom leader and the winner of the 1997 Tour.</p>
        <p>When the Tour announced last autumn that it would reinstitute the team time trial, a handful of multiday races in the spring added it too, giving riders a chance to develop their teamwork skills. ONCE, an acronym for a Spanish organization that aids the blind and is also sponsor of the team, won the team time trial in the Etoile de Besseges in France in February and in the Tour of Catalonia in Spain in June. Telekom won in the Tour of Germany and the Tour of Switzerland, both in June.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Vaughters, an American who rode for Postal Service last year, is now with Credit Agricole of France, which finished second in the discipline in Besseges and in the Tour Mediterraneen, also in February. His team finished fourth today, 1:27 behind ONCE.</p>
        <p>Reporting beforehand that ''I did a million team time trials as a junior in the States and I was even junior national champion once,'' Vaughters analyzed the skills needed: ''You can have a lot of strong riders, but if it's not coordinated properly, it'll fall apart. Especially if you've got a little bit of imbalance -- one really strong rider and then some weaker riders.</p>
        <p>''The secret is smoothness, communication and consistent effort within the team.''</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
