<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a U.S. Hospital, Lonely Ex-Soldiers Get No Bands and Few Visitors</title>
    <meta content="05VETS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1212645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SALUTING THE FOURTH: THE VETERANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Independence Day (US) (July 4)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E5DD1139F936A35754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a U.S. Hospital, Lonely Ex-Soldiers Get No Bands and Few Visitors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LeDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lonely former soldiers at veterans hospital, Brooklyn, get no fanfare and few visitors on Independence Day; they comment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A sign in the veterans hospital in Brooklyn reads: ''The Price of Freedom Is Visible Here.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Americans were supposed to remember. Yesterday, hundreds of thousands of people celebrated on the shores of New York Harbor as they watched one of the largest armadas ever assembled. Meanwhile, fewer than two dozen people went to see the men of war and military service who sat silently in the beds and halls and doorways of the Veterans Affairs hospital, unable to see the flotilla from their windows as it passed underneath the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge just a quarter-mile away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A sign in the veterans hospital in Brooklyn reads: ''The Price of Freedom Is Visible Here.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Americans were supposed to remember. Yesterday, hundreds of thousands of people celebrated on the shores of New York Harbor as they watched one of the largest armadas ever assembled. Meanwhile, fewer than two dozen people went to see the men of war and military service who sat silently in the beds and halls and doorways of the Veterans Affairs hospital, unable to see the flotilla from their windows as it passed underneath the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge just a quarter-mile away.</p>
        <p>These men passed the morning inhaling the smell of antiseptic and the stench of bedpans, listening to the mumblings of the dying, lying in bed watching the beautiful boats on their televisions.</p>
        <p>Ward 8 is the cancer precinct, and the men here wait for disease to do what fighting wars could not. To a man, they said they were disappointed that their sacrifices -- some fought, some served, none regretted any of it -- were not appreciated more yesterday, that there was no band playing, that there was no child's hand to hold.</p>
        <p>They said they were lonely.</p>
        <p>''The Star-Spangled Banner'' played on a television and its melody drifted down the hall. The music came from the room of Frank Pardal, 54, who held his eyes closed. He breathed from a tube while his lips mouthed the words. When the music was over, he opened his eyes. He was alone. There were pictures of the boats sailing by on his screen.</p>
        <p>''Holy mackerel, that's big holiday stuff,'' he said. ''They look like a bunch of birds out there, those boats do.''</p>
        <p>He cleared his tube and wiped his fingers on the sheets. ''It don't mean nothing to me though. Independence Day. It don't mean nothing to anyone anymore.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pardal served in the Army from 1965 to 1968 in West Germany. He came home to Staten Island, worked laboring jobs and then was hit by a car. That's when they found the cancer. He has not left the hospital in months. And no one has come to see him.</p>
        <p>''Tell you the truth though, I wish I was out there looking at those long beauties go by, having a cold one and a dog and holding my girl's hand,'' he said. ''Even if I could get out of bed, what could I do? I got a view of an air-conditioning unit.''</p>
        <p>No one likes to hear about self-deception and disappointment and grief, said Eddie Murach, 72, a retired sergeant major who served in World War II, Korea and Vietnam. But, he says, that is precisely what war is, that is precisely what Ward 8 is. Because whatever war it was, Mr. Murach said, however long it lasted, it changed men from scrawny hometown clerks into men who know the fragility of life.</p>
        <p>''I feel sorry for these guys down the hall,'' he said. ''They've got no one.''</p>
        <p>The sergeant is one of the lucky ones. He has his wife, Mary Ellen. He met her at a root beer stand in rural Indiana. He sat in his Buick. She sat in the next car over. That was 47 years, three children and six grandchildren ago.</p>
        <p>She washed him yesterday morning and brought him a pair of binoculars to watch the ships. But the day was hazy and the windows stained with soot. The armada might as well have been in Normandy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murach insisted he was no hero. A 30-year veteran of the Army, Mr. Murach started his career with the Japanese occupation. He was part of the Chosin Reservoir campaign in Korea when the conflict broke out in 1950. He slept in a frozen hole for 60 days. The Army had given its men summer gear for a winter campaign and he watched as men died of exposure. Then the Chinese poured down the ridge, the battalion pulled out, were re-outfitted and pushed back in.</p>
        <p>Then came Vietnam. ''I was 40, and I had to volunteer because they wouldn't send me,'' he said, laying bare-chested in bed. The boats below sailed by. ''I figured it was a career for me and they were taking guys who didn't want to go. I felt it was my duty.''</p>
        <p>He has cancer -- probably caused by  exposure to Agent Orange, he said the doctors told him. He was awarded the Legion of Merit and two Bronze Stars with valor. He spends part of his time in the hospital, part of his time as a high school baseball coach. He loves Buicks and apple pie.</p>
        <p>''I've got more blessings than I'm entitled to,'' Mr. Murach said as he squeezed his wife's hand. ''I do wish that all of us could go outside for just a moment and get a gander of those ships.''</p>
        <p>About 25,000 veterans stayed in the hospitals last year, according to the Veterans Affairs statistics, and 35 million outpatients visited its clinics. Statistics on visitors are not kept. But Sgt. Clifford Newman of the Federal Police Department, who patrolled the empty lobby yesterday morning, said the respect for people in uniform had declined drastically over the last 25 years.</p>
        <p>''The price of freedom is not cheap,'' the sergeant said. ''People could invest a little time. Instead of spending the whole day watching the boats go by and lighting off firecrackers, people should have thought to visit a vet.''</p>
        <p>Carl Passaro sat in a chair in the doorway of his room. ''I'm just going to sit here and watch the floors dry,'' he said. ''It's a cruel, cruel thing to have those boats going by and us locked up in here.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Passaro is 84. He said he saw more action at the horse track than in the Second World War as a supply clerk. And now that he is alone and has no visitors, he wishes he had conducted his life better.</p>
        <p>''I was a crumb, I admit that,'' he said. ''But even a crumb needs company.''</p>
        <p>SALUTING THE FOURTH: THE VETERANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
