<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Enough With the Kompyuta! Let's Makuru!</title>
    <meta content="26TANK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/26/arts/26TANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THINK TANK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Japanese Language</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Correspondence (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passin, Herbert (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Think Tank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E5D71231F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Enough With the Kompyuta! Let's Makuru!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from article by Herbert Passin, professor emiritus of sociology at Columbia University, on the absorption of English vocabulary into Japanese language; article was published in journal Correspondence; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although English is becoming the dominant language around the world, few outside Japan may be aware of how extensively it has transformed Japanese. Herbert Passin, professor emeritus of sociology at Columbia University, reported on this upheaval in ''Japonica: How to Read the Japanese Language if You Know the English Source Code,'' which appeared in the spring-summer issue of Correspondence: An International Review of Culture and Society. Excerpts follow.</p>
        <p>From the Asuka period (A.D. 552-645) through the late Heian (end of the 12th century), the Chinese language completely penetrated Japanese.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although English is becoming the dominant language around the world, few outside Japan may be aware of how extensively it has transformed Japanese. Herbert Passin, professor emeritus of sociology at Columbia University, reported on this upheaval in ''Japonica: How to Read the Japanese Language if You Know the English Source Code,'' which appeared in the spring-summer issue of Correspondence: An International Review of Culture and Society. Excerpts follow.</p>
        <p>From the Asuka period (A.D. 552-645) through the late Heian (end of the 12th century), the Chinese language completely penetrated Japanese.</p>
        <p>The same thing, I would suggest, is happening today with English. English is in the process of being completely absorbed, and its entire vocabulary is becoming available for use in Japanese. Today when new words are made up they will come from English (or to a lesser extent, from some European language), no longer from Chinese.</p>
        <p>It is hard to imagine modern Japan without English. Right now, I am sitting at my desuku (desk), or teburu (table), with the rampu (lamp) on, holding my kompyuta (computer), taipingu (typing), making occasional notes with a boru-pen (ball-pen).</p>
        <p>I sip some kohi (coffee) from a gurasu (glass). When I need a break, I move to the sofua (sofa), lean against the kusshon (cushion) and read the nyusu (news) about the latest sekuhara (sexual harassment) incident. I then turn to the puroguramu (program) on the karar-terebi (color television) and watch a homudorama (home drama).</p>
        <p>There is no ''l'' sound in Japanese so that all foreign words with ''l'' are pronounced with an ''r.'' ''Flight'' becomes ''fright,'' or more exactly, ''furaito.'' A further pronunciation problem is that Japanese syllables all end in vowel sounds, except when there is an ''n.'' ''Book'' becomes ''bukku,'' ''size'' becomes ''saizu,'' ''pencil'' becomes ''penshiru.'' When the syllabic ending is ''n,'' ''pen'' remains ''pen,'' ''downtown'' is ''dauntaun,'' a ''can of beer'' becomes ''kan-biru.''</p>
        <p>Today, because of the enormous increase in the velocity of communications and the diffusion of literacy, the assimilation of foreign languages requires mere decades, or even years, rather than centuries. There are several fairly distinguishable stages in this process. In the first, foreign words are taken in whole and used passively.</p>
        <p>But once these words are domesticated, they immediately open up a new stage in which they take on a life of their own. They are used in ways that may not be instantly understandable to the speakers of the original language. ''Mansion,'' for example (pronounced ''manshon'' in Japanese), which usually suggests to modern Western minds a large, residential estate, like that of the titled aristocracy or the wealthy, is commonly used in Japan to mean a pricey apartment.</p>
        <p>The next step is essential for Japanese: abbreviation.</p>
        <p>There are now thousands of abbreviated English words used by Japanese that without explanation usually cannot be understood by English speakers. A few examples: ''register'' becomes ''reji''; ''negative,'' ''nega''; ''handicap,'' ''hande''; ''reportage,'' ''rupo''; ''permanent wave,'' ''pama.''</p>
        <p>Hundreds, or even thousands, of foreign compounds are taken over with virtually no change (except pronunciation): ''golf bag'' (''gorufu-baggu''), ''software'' (''sofutouea'') and so on. Many, however, even though close to the original meaning, are abbreviated, and once this happens they begin to look a little different and usually cannot be understood by English speakers. A classic example -- by now, hardly used -- is the post-World War I ''moga'' (from ''modan gaaru,'' ''modern girl'').</p>
        <p>At the next stage, foreign words in full or abbreviated form are combined with Japanese words (including completely assimilated Chinese words as well) to make new compounds. An archetypal example is the by now rather old ''tonkatsu'' (''pork cutlet'') made up of the Chinese ''ton'' (''pork''), and ''katsu,'' the abbreviation of ''cutlet.''</p>
        <p>Just as Japanese used to create new words out of Chinese freely and autonomously, so now it is beginning to create a homemade English. When I gave up smoking at my doctor's orders, this was a ''dokutu-sutoppu'' (''doctor-stop''), an example of what I would consider brilliant new English.</p>
        <p>Other examples abound. I like ''bea,'' from ''besu-appu,'' ''base-up,'' that is, a rise in the base wage from which other calculations for the total wage are made.</p>
        <p>The penultimate stage comes when people are no longer aware that the word is not native. ''Pan'' (''bread'') is from 16th- or 17th-century Portuguese. But it is so deeply rooted in Japanese that we now find the baffling compound ''bureddo-pan'' (''bread-pan'').</p>
        <p>In the final stage, the foreign word is completely assimilated to the grammatical form of Japanese. Normally, foreign words (including Chinese) are formed into verbs by adding ''suru'' (''to do'') into adjectives by adding ''na'' and into adverbs by adding ''ni.''</p>
        <p>A good example is the old standby ''saboru.'' Originally, it came from the abbreviated ''sabotage,'' ''sabo,'' but it has become completely Japanified by adding the Japanese verb form ''ru'' and then taken on a somewhat divergent meaning: to play truant, to evade doing something one does not want to do, not to do one's part.</p>
        <p>More recent examples of this creative innovation are: ''makuru'' (to eat at McDonald's), ''saburu'' (to eat while riding a subway car -- from ''sabuuei,'' ''subway'').</p>
        <p>All languages take in foreign loan words. In Japan, Chinese was the first major penetration, and its impact was overwhelming. Fourteen hundred years later, something similar seems to be happening with English. In the centuries in between, Korean, Dutch and Portuguese made significant, though lesser, contributions.</p>
        <p>English itself developed in a similar way. Shaped from Germanic, then invaded by Norman French, its intellectual, legal, scientific and religious vocabularies were also deeply influenced by Latin.</p>
        <p>Today English continues to take in new language from Anglo-Indian, Caribbean, South-African, Irish, Scottish, Australian, Yiddish and countless others.</p>
        <p>Japanese, therefore, is not unique in this process. However we may come to rate the relative penetrability of languages -- and it is debatable, say, whether English, Japanese, Turkish or Uzbek is more open to foreign linguistic influence -- the process of English-absorption that is going on before our eyes in Japan today is awesomely inventive.</p>
        <p>THINK TANK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
