<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Time of Fires, Fatigue, Cash and the U.S.O.</title>
    <meta content="26FIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/26/national/26fire.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Western States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Service Organizations (Uso)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5DA1331F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Time of Fires, Fatigue, Cash and the U.S.O.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>CHALLIS, Idaho, Aug. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Services Organization, known for performing variety shows for troops overseas, is providing similar entertainment for thousands of firefighters across West, where fire commanders liken devastating forest and brush fires of summer to war; old-fashioined stage show in Challis, Idaho, described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They head out before dawn and trudge home after dark, weary and covered in soot, still clutching the shovels and axes that are their weapons out on the battle lines. They sleep as many as 21 to a tent, in makeshift camps pitched beneath smoky, lung-choking skies.</p>
        <p>For thousands of firefighters across the West, these will be the memories of summer 2000, a season so devastating that commanders say they cannot help but see it as a war. And now even the United Services Organization, best known for taking Bob Hope to the troops overseas, has come to this remote corner of Idaho to pay a variety-show tribute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They head out before dawn and trudge home after dark, weary and covered in soot, still clutching the shovels and axes that are their weapons out on the battle lines. They sleep as many as 21 to a tent, in makeshift camps pitched beneath smoky, lung-choking skies.</p>
        <p>For thousands of firefighters across the West, these will be the memories of summer 2000, a season so devastating that commanders say they cannot help but see it as a war. And now even the United Services Organization, best known for taking Bob Hope to the troops overseas, has come to this remote corner of Idaho to pay a variety-show tribute.</p>
        <p>With three former beauty queens in red, white and blue micro-mini-dresses and four-inch heels cooing and flirting from a flatbed truck, the scene along the Salmon River Thursday night brought a taste of the 1950's to an audience that anywhere else would call itself part of the Internet generation. It may have been the most surreal moment in a summer in which fire has drawn people of all stripes from all around the country to the most isolated of places.</p>
        <p>''This is a natural disaster in the United States,'' said Victoria Reed, a former Miss Maine and leader of the U.S.O. troupe, ''and it's important that the U.S.O. is here, because that's been our mission since 1941 -- to entertain the troops.''</p>
        <p>Sgt. Craig Smith, 29, a marine from Birmingham, Ala., last saw a U.S.O. show on a tour that took him to Japan, and he was among those bug-eyed at what fortune had brought to the fire camp.</p>
        <p>''This whole thing is definitely something new,'' said Sergeant Smith, who had never before set foot near Idaho. Even now, he said, ''I've been to more countries than states.''</p>
        <p>Along with paramedics from Tennessee, high-school dropouts from California and federal land managers from all over the United States, Sergeant Smith is among some 1,700 men and a handful of women in eastern Idaho battling what is the largest of dozens of major fires burning across the western United States.</p>
        <p>After working 16-hour days on end, this group found itself gawking on Wednesday and Thursday nights at the performers from the U.S.O., an organization whose past tours have almost always been overseas.</p>
        <p>''Our missions are primarily to remote and isolated places, and there aren't too many places in the United States that qualify,'' said James Pearcy, the director of entertainment at the U.S.O. ''But I guess sleeping on the ground for 30 days in a fire zone in the middle of nowhere would have to count.''</p>
        <p>Led by Ms. Reed, and including Erin Wheatley, Miss Arkansas of 1998, and Stacy Turner of Texas, the New York-based troupe performed a medley of oldies that included everything from ''America the Beautiful'' to ''All My Loving'' and was punctuated, in strutting, pinup-girl style, with the planting of many lipstick-red kisses on the blushing but willing cheeks of young marines and firefighters who had spent too many nights in the cold.</p>
        <p>''What a year!'' John Wallace, 23, a contract worker from Tule Lake, Calif., said in disbelief, not only at the performance but also at his good luck in being part of a year in which record fire damage will also bring record paychecks. ''I'm planning on living through the winter off it.''</p>
        <p>Altogether, well over 25,000 men and women are involved in the firefighting, including what will soon number more than 4,000 military personnel from the Army, Marines and the National Guard, in an operation whose cost is estimated at $15 million a day. But with 1.4 million acres still burning in the West, the current force is not nearly enough, federal officials say, and it cannot prudently be reinforced because of a shortage of trained supervisors.</p>
        <p>As a result, federal officials have said there is little they can do to fight many of the blazes. From fire camps like this one, the main operations have been focused far from the flames, by trying to safeguard houses from danger and to make sure that no new flames break out in areas where the fires have already burned.</p>
        <p>''The resources have just run dry all over the country, and so we've had to back off to wider lines,'' said Bill Cyr, 48, an engineer with the Los Angeles Country Fire Department who since Aug. 5 has bunked down under a yellow tarpaulin every night with a 20-man Marine unit, his charges as a temporary adviser.</p>
        <p>Across the United States, nearly six million acres of land have burned this year, and with hot, dry weather in the West showing no sign of abating, the devastation is on track to become the worst in at least half a century. Fourteen firefighters have been killed during this season, including two prison inmates struck by lightning in Utah on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Some of the worst fires are in the  Bitterroot Valley of western Montana, where a wind-driven flare-up in the last two days has added to a blanket of smoke so thick that on Thursday, midday seemed like deepest dusk. But the Clear Creek fire, burning northwest of here in the Salmon-Challis National Forest, remains the largest single blaze in the country, spanning some 165,000 acres, with only about one-third contained.</p>
        <p>Sixteen helicopters, 66 fire engines and 14 bulldozers, in addition to the 1,755 people, have been assigned to fight the fire. But the area is so vast and so isolated, commanders say, that much of their time and energy is devoted to logistics.</p>
        <p>The nearest substantial airport, in Idaho Falls, is three hours away from this camp, which is set on a highway so that it can be resupplied. It takes the crews an hour each way to reach the fire lines by bus, traveling on narrow Forest Service roads.</p>
        <p>The food served at the camp is far better than standard military fare, and it does not come cheap, said Dale B. Thompson, a Park Service ranger based in Arizona who is managing the food operation here. A Thursday dinner that included halibut and au gratin potatoes dished up by the Big Sky Catering Company of Missoula, Mont., a company that specializes in providing for fire crews, cost taxpayers $16 each , Mr. Thompson said.</p>
        <p>The U.S.O. troupe flew in and out of Boise, Idaho, seven hours away, and was returning to New York for regular weekend performances on the U.S.S. Intrepid, the warship-turned-museum now docked in New York.</p>
        <p>The marines, who arrived here on  Aug. 5, have had only one day off since, and receive no extra pay for their fire service, said Lt. Alison Ake, a spokeswoman. The unit is expected to return to California next Friday.</p>
        <p>By law, the civilian firefighters contracted by the Forest Service and other federal agencies receive more generous treatment.</p>
        <p>They are required to take a day off for every 14 days of work, or 2 days every 21, and most get time-and-a-half for overtime, which adds up quickly over the long days.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wallace, the 23-year-old Californian, figures he will earn $3,000 a month this summer as a member of what is known as a Type II, or second-tier, fire crew. That is more than triple his regular wintertime wage.</p>
        <p>After weeks in the smoke, firefighters say, simple pleasures can feel like enormous rewards. Brian Crawley, a 33-year-old paramedic from southeast Tennessee, was looking forward to a respite from what would be two back-to-back 21-day fire tours.</p>
        <p>''I'm headed to the big metropolis of Challis,'' Mr. Crawley said, ''for two things I can't get here: a bed and a bath.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
