<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accusation of Misconduct Arises at Tailhook Meeting</title>
    <meta content="Y26TAIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/26/national/26TAIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tailhook Association</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, Steven Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DD1331F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accusation of Misconduct Arises at Tailhook Meeting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN LEE MYERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myers, Steven Lee</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Navy is facing new accusation of misconduct at annual convention of Tailhook Assn, nine years after similar accusations led to resignations, fines and changes in military's treatment of women; married couple staying at hotel in Sparks, Nev, where association held convention report being verbally and physically assaulted in hallway on Aug 19 by group of men attending event (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Navy is facing a new accusation of misconduct at the annual convention of the Tailhook Association, officials said today, nine years after drunken debauchery and sexual assaults at another convention led to resignations, fines and changes in the military's treatment of women.</p>
        <p>A man and a woman staying at a hotel in Sparks, Nev., where the association held its convention last weekend, reported being verbally and physically assaulted in a hallway on Aug. 19 by a group of men attending the convention, Navy officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Navy is facing a new accusation of misconduct at the annual convention of the Tailhook Association, officials said today, nine years after drunken debauchery and sexual assaults at another convention led to resignations, fines and changes in the military's treatment of women.</p>
        <p>A man and a woman staying at a hotel in Sparks, Nev., where the association held its convention last weekend, reported being verbally and physically assaulted in a hallway on Aug. 19 by a group of men attending the convention, Navy officials said.</p>
        <p>The Navy did not identify the couple, but said the man reported the accusation to Navy officials on Tuesday, two days after the convention ended, using a telephone hot line set up to handle sexual harassment complaints after the association's raucous convention in 1991.</p>
        <p>The misconduct reported did not appear to be of the same magnitude as the events in 1991, when 83 women, some in the Navy, reported being assaulted or harassed in a hotel in Las Vegas. Nonetheless, the accusation included echoes of the previous scandal, which roiled the Navy.</p>
        <p>Officials said as few as 10 and as many as several dozen Navy and Marine aviators may have been in the hallway of the Nugget Hotel at the time the man and woman say they were assaulted.</p>
        <p>The Navy's inspector general and its criminal service have begun an investigation into the accusation, and investigators have conducted interviews with some of those involved, the officials said.</p>
        <p>The case could prove particularly embarrassing for the Navy because it only restored its official recognition of the association eight months ago.</p>
        <p>At the time, the secretary of the Navy, Richard Danzig, said the association had given its assurances that there would be no repeat of the kinds of incidents that had made Tailhook synonymous with the mistreatment of women in uniform.</p>
        <p>Officials said today that Mr. Danzig would not comment on the incident until the investigation was completed. They said it was premature to say whether the association could once again lose its official status with the Navy.</p>
        <p>On Capitol Hill, Representative Carolyn B. Maloney, Democrat of New York, said it was a disappointment that the convention had produced an accusation so soon after official ties to Tailhook had been restored.</p>
        <p>''It's another sad day for women in the military,'' Ms. Maloney said in a statement. ''When a woman can't walk through a hallway without being groped, there is a serious problem.''</p>
        <p>A statement released by the Pentagon said that the man and woman, who are married, were staying at the hotel, but not as part of the convention. As they returned to their room, they tried to pass through what the man described as a crowded hallway, the officials said.</p>
        <p>The man reported that the crowd in the hallway, all or most of them men, made abusive comments when he asked them to make room for the couple to pass.</p>
        <p>As the couple fought their way through, at least one man in the hallway made ''inappropriate physical contact'' with the woman, a senior Navy officer said, declining to elaborate.</p>
        <p>The Tailhook Association, named for the steel hooks on jets that enable them to land on aircraft carriers, is a private group based in San Diego that acts as a sort of booster club for naval aviation and has long been associated with the Navy and the Marine Corps.</p>
        <p>Although the lack of official recognition never prohibited officers from attending, last weekend's convention was the first since the Navy restored its ties. Attendance was 2,000, with 1,200 to 1,300 active-duty officers taking part, the association's president said.</p>
        <p>Navy officials said several Navy admirals and Marine generals attended this year's convention, but declined to identify them, and it was not clear whether any were aware of the events in the hotel hallway.</p>
        <p>One official said a senior Navy officer apologized to the man, indicating he was at least aware of what had happened.</p>
        <p>The official said it was not clear whether the officer had reported any misconduct to his superiors, as required by Navy policy. The senior officer's role during or after the event would also be investigated, officials said.</p>
        <p>A Navy spokesman, Cmdr. Gregory J. Smith, declined to discuss the senior officer's conduct, citing the investigation, but said the man indicated in his report that he was not satisfied with the apology offered.</p>
        <p>Tailhook's president, Lonny K. McClung, a retired Navy captain and pilot, expressed concern about the accusation, but said he knew few details about what was reported to have happened.</p>
        <p>The convention, which began on Aug. 17 and ended last Sunday, included cocktail parties, dinners, seminars focused on the future of naval aviation and a fly-over of naval jets.</p>
        <p>''I can tell you it was a very successful convention,'' Mr. McClung said in an telephone interview. ''There were only two noise complaints from the hotel.''</p>
        <p>''We left feeling pretty good about the convention,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Lt. Ken Lightfoot, a detective with the Police Department in Sparks, a suburb of Reno, said the police had not received any criminal complaints related to the convention, though they did respond to two medical emergencies at the hotel during the convention, including a man with a head injury at 3 a.m. last Saturday.</p>
        <p>The Tailhook scandal in 1991 had a profound impact on the Navy and the Marine Corps. More than 100 officers were eventually implicated in the assaults or other riotous behavior at the convention.</p>
        <p>The worst of the assaults came when a group of drunken pilots formed a gantlet in a hotel corridor and molested women as they passed.</p>
        <p>The uproar over the assaults led to the resignation of the secretary of the Navy, Lawrence H. Garrett III, and the early retirement of the chief of naval operations, Adm. Frank B. Kelso II, both of whom attended the 1991 convention, though they denied witnessing the worst of the behavior.</p>
        <p>Officials said today that neither Mr. Danzig, nor the current chief of naval operations, Adm. Vern Clark, attended this year's convention.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
