<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congo Leader Hedges on Vow to Allow Access for U.N. Force</title>
    <meta content="Y26CON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225307"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Congo (Formerly Zaire)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kabila, Laurent (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Congo, The Democratic Republic of</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Congo, The Democratic Republic of the</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4DC1331F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congo Leader Hedges on Vow to Allow Access for U.N. Force</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Aug. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congo Pres Laurent Kabila appears to hedge on pledge to allow access for UN peacekeeping force of about 5,500 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A week of conflicting signals from President Laurent Kabila of Congo has left the Security Council no closer to knowing when, if ever, a peacekeeping mission can be sent to the country. The council this week decided that United Nations officials who have been in Congo preparing for the peacekeepers could stay until Oct. 15, giving Secretary General Kofi Annan and the council time to reconsider the operation.</p>
        <p>After announcing on Thursday that the peacekeepers and support forces, totaling about 5,500 people under current plans, could have free access in Congo, Mr. Kabila's government appeared today to be backtracking, officials said here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A week of conflicting signals from President Laurent Kabila of Congo has left the Security Council no closer to knowing when, if ever, a peacekeeping mission can be sent to the country. The council this week decided that United Nations officials who have been in Congo preparing for the peacekeepers could stay until Oct. 15, giving Secretary General Kofi Annan and the council time to reconsider the operation.</p>
        <p>After announcing on Thursday that the peacekeepers and support forces, totaling about 5,500 people under current plans, could have free access in Congo, Mr. Kabila's government appeared today to be backtracking, officials said here.</p>
        <p>In nearly a year of trying to prepare for a peacekeeping operation in a country with inadequate roads, electrical supplies or other basic services in many areas, the United Nations advance team has met repeated obstacles. Because Congo officials always try to control flights and other activities, the Security Council has demanded freedom of movement without the need for permits or advance notice as the United Nations establishes centers of operation.</p>
        <p>In Congo, United Nations officials have faced not only operational hurdles but also orchestrated hostility against international workers, including attacks on United Nations' offices in Kinshasa, the capital. Officials said they fear more violence if the government does not stop encouraging or condoning the anti-United Nations feelings.</p>
        <p>This week, Mr. Annan sent a Nigerian general and former military ruler, Abdulsalami Abubakar, to Congo to tell Mr. Kabila that he must cooperate with the United Nations if the peacekeeping mission is to go ahead. General Abubakar will report to Mr. Annan next week.</p>
        <p>Complicating the picture for a peacekeeping mission, Mr. Kabila said this week that he was freezing a peace accord signed last year in Lusaka, Zambia. That agreement set up a series of steps toward reconciliation in Congo, which has been caught in a prolonged war of shifting alliances for more than five years. Five other countries have been drawn into the conflict, unsettling much of south-central Africa.</p>
        <p>An African diplomat said this week that some regional leaders have concluded that if Mr. Kabila cannot defeat several rebel groups operating in the country, most of them with outside support, he will retreat to his home territory around Lumbumbashi and leave the rest of Congo to the competing groups.</p>
        <p>In one positive move, Mr. Kabila, who refuses to meet with political opponents, has established a human rights panel in Congo and allowed a United Nations monitor to visit the country in recent weeks. The monitor, Roberto Garreton, a lawyer from Chile, had been barred from Congo for several years.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Garreton's final report has not been published, he said this week when he left Congo that there was little good news in either government-controlled or rebel-controlled areas or in border regions where Rwanda and Uganda still have troops.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
