<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peace in Burundi Still Elusive As Africa Readies for Clinton</title>
    <meta content="26BURU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hutu Tribe</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tutsi Tribe</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Burundi</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tanzania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mandela, Nelson R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Burundi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Tanzania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Tanzania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Burundi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hutu Tribe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tribes and Tribalism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E2DB1331F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1323" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peace in Burundi Still Elusive As Africa Readies for Clinton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, Aug. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Failure of warring factions in Burundi to reach peace settlement presents dilemma for Pres Clinton, whose upcoming visit to Tanzania was to witness signing of accord with several dozen African heads of state, including former South African president Nelson Mandela who has been broker in peace talks; observers say it would be unwise to push Burundi too far, since incomplete document signed in hurry to please important foreign guests could push Tutsi hard-liners opposed to accord into more violence with Hutu--both of whom have been massacring each other for past 40 years; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In December, Nelson Mandela took on one of Africa's most frightening problems: the tiny and beautiful country of Burundi, where Hutu and Tutsi have taken turns massacring each other by the thousands for the last 40 years. Rumor was that he accepted the task reluctantly, but he has worked hard and pushed enemies near to a settlement.</p>
        <p>They are not there yet, and that will present a dilemma when President Clinton arrives in Tanzania on Monday to meet with Mr. Mandela and Burundi's leaders. By Mr. Mandela's rigid timetable, the Burundians were to seal their intention to end seven years of civil war in an accord signed in front of Mr. Clinton and several dozen other heads of state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In December, Nelson Mandela took on one of Africa's most frightening problems: the tiny and beautiful country of Burundi, where Hutu and Tutsi have taken turns massacring each other by the thousands for the last 40 years. Rumor was that he accepted the task reluctantly, but he has worked hard and pushed enemies near to a settlement.</p>
        <p>They are not there yet, and that will present a dilemma when President Clinton arrives in Tanzania on Monday to meet with Mr. Mandela and Burundi's leaders. By Mr. Mandela's rigid timetable, the Burundians were to seal their intention to end seven years of civil war in an accord signed in front of Mr. Clinton and several dozen other heads of state.</p>
        <p>Thus Mr. Clinton, eager for some success in Africa, could have stood as midwife of sorts over the birth of one small bit of hope in the ceaseless turmoil of central Africa.</p>
        <p>But a consensus is growing that it would be unwise -- even dangerous -- to push Burundi too far before the meeting. The fear is that an incomplete document, signed in a hurry to please important foreign guests, could push Tutsi hard-liners opposed to the accord into more violence. The threat of further killing in Burundi is all too real.</p>
        <p>''We want all those heads of state to be aware that they are going to be manipulated if they think they are going to assist in a peace accord that all parties agree with,'' said Louis-Marie Nindorera, of the Burundian human rights group Iteka. ''They have to know that most of the people who are there are still deeply divided.''</p>
        <p>A historical precedent haunts the proceedings in the resort town of Arusha, in Tanzania. It was there in August 1993 that the warring parties in Rwanda -- Burundi's northern neighbor -- also signed a peace deal. It was not accepted by many of the Hutu majority in Rwanda. The authority of the Hutu president, Juvenal Habyarimana, dwindled; Hutu militias formed. By April 1994, a genocide against the Tutsi minority exploded, killing in the end at least 500,000 people.</p>
        <p>The situation in Burundi is not directly parallel: It is Tutsi who rule there, in a precarious position because they represent only about 15 percent of the population. But there are similarities. As the signing has grown near, violence has flared. Hutu rebels fighting the Tutsi-controlled government launched several attacks on the capital, Bujumbura, in recent weeks.</p>
        <p>At the same time, hard-line Tutsi groups -- reluctant to give up their long-held power over the majority Hutu -- have been protesting the peace accord on the streets of Bujumbura. Several experts say they are also forming armed militias with no clear accountability.</p>
        <p>The tension is so high that Pierre Buyoya, the nation's president and a Tutsi, felt he had to warn Tutsi hard-liners against staging a coup this weekend when he goes to Tanzania to meet Mr. Mandela and Mr. Clinton. It was an unusual admission of his vulnerability.</p>
        <p>''Those who want to overthrow the government so that the president will not be there to sign the peace agreement should know that their actions will come to no good,'' Mr. Buyoya told civil servants and government administrators on Monday.</p>
        <p>Shoring up his position at home, Mr. Buyoya canceled a trip this week to South Africa to meet with Mr. Mandela for final talks before the planned signing.</p>
        <p>It is not impossible that most of the 19 parties at the negotiating table will end up signing a complete peace accord on Monday. Given the fears of violence -- and the differences that remain over the accord itself -- it is also possible that nothing will be signed. But officials say what is most likely is that some of the parties will sign off only on the points of agreement. They would also, officials say, affirm their commitment to continue talking.</p>
        <p>This would fall short of Mr. Mandela's expectations, and may in fact try his reportedly waning patience. Mr. Clinton would also be forced to preside over a ceremony with less certain importance than he might prefer. But American officials say they are aware of the risks of pushing too hard and are not eager -- with few recent accomplishments toward making peace in Africa -- to stoke the coals of ethnic hatred.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton will travel to Tanzania, at a minimum, to put his stamp of approval on the progress Mr. Mandela has made thus far, the officials say. ''There is no desire to force anybody into anything,'' said one administration official. ''It is our great desire to consolidate the progress that has been made so far and continue to do what we can do to support Mandela's efforts to narrow the differences.''</p>
        <p>Many experts say Mr. Clinton's blessing of a realistic document could be useful in the next phase of talks, though many officials fear a loss of momentum after Mr. Clinton leaves.</p>
        <p>''The fact that there is such an international interest and support for Mandela's efforts and the efforts of Burundians makes people feel they should behave responsibly,'' said Jan van Eck, of the Center for Conflict Resolution in South Africa, who has worked with Burundi's factions since 1995.</p>
        <p>There have been outbreaks of ethnic violence since Burundi, like Rwanda, gained its independence from Belgium in 1962, particularly against the Hutu in 1965 and 1972. The Tutsi have dominated politics, the army and business. This most recent civil war broke out in 1993, when power shifted for a brief time to the Hutu majority. In July 1993, the first Hutu president, Melchior Ndadaye, took office. But three months later, Tutsi paratroopers assassinated him, setting off widespread killings of Tutsi.</p>
        <p>Since then, 200,000 Burundians are estimated to have died.</p>
        <p>The peace accord that Mr. Mandela has been shaping essentially envisions an eventual return of power to the Hutu majority -- who make up nearly 85 percent of the population -- but with rights and protections for the Tutsi.</p>
        <p>Toward that end, the accord calls for a second legislative body, a senate, with broad veto powers that would be split evenly by ethnicity. The army would also be divided evenly for at least 10 years, despite the Tutsi's far fewer numbers.</p>
        <p>But many Tutsi say these measures do not give them enough of a say or protection. Moreover, the Hutu and Tutsi disagree over the terms for a tribunal on genocide and a peace and reconciliation commission. This has caused particular tension among the Tutsi, who want the killings in 1993 recognized as genocide.</p>
        <p>There are other disagreements. The accord envisions a three-year transitional government before general elections, but the sides cannot agree on a leader. They also disagree on whether a cease-fire should be signed before or after the signing of the accord.</p>
        <p>What complicates the issue further is that the two main Hutu rebel groups actually engaged in fighting are not involved directly in the peace talks. So even if a fairly complete document is signed on Monday, it will be, as Mr. Mandela has frequently pointed out, only the beginning of the push toward a final peace.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
