<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Real Confessions</title>
    <meta content="26SAT4" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Court TV (Network)</org>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Confessions (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DD1331F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Real Confessions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial accuses Court TV of engaging in rank appeal to prurience and thrill of violence in order to raise ratings by offering Confessions, program of grisly videotaped confessions of people who have committed violent crimes (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Court TV, which has distinguished itself with live coverage of court proceedings, will offer a new and bizarre program this fall. ''Confessions,'' the new entry, will be a 30-minute show, with each episode presenting three videotaped police confessions of people who have committed murders, rapes and other violent crimes. Broadcasting the tapes is legal because they are part of the public record in cases where the suspects were convicted or were found not guilty by reason of insanity.</p>
        <p>Court TV executives say ''Confessions'' fits in perfectly with their network's mission of exposing the inner workings of the criminal justice system. But culling out the grisliest snippets of selected criminal confessions is little more than a rank appeal to prurience and the thrill of violence, motivated by the network's desire for an audience-grabbing hit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Court TV, which has distinguished itself with live coverage of court proceedings, will offer a new and bizarre program this fall. ''Confessions,'' the new entry, will be a 30-minute show, with each episode presenting three videotaped police confessions of people who have committed murders, rapes and other violent crimes. Broadcasting the tapes is legal because they are part of the public record in cases where the suspects were convicted or were found not guilty by reason of insanity.</p>
        <p>Court TV executives say ''Confessions'' fits in perfectly with their network's mission of exposing the inner workings of the criminal justice system. But culling out the grisliest snippets of selected criminal confessions is little more than a rank appeal to prurience and the thrill of violence, motivated by the network's desire for an audience-grabbing hit.</p>
        <p>Nothing could be cheaper to produce than simply replaying grainy videotapes made by police and prosecutors. Each confession will be edited down to 10 minutes or less. There will be no host or narration, no explanation of the cases, how the suspects were found or how long the interrogation process actually took, because that would detract from the show's ''watchability,'' explains one Court TV executive.</p>
        <p>Since a confession tape is ''just a guy talking,'' says the executive, it may not hold viewers without some added visual texture. So the show's creators will put in split-screen re-enactments of the crime scene and other atmospheric images, alongside the criminal confessor.</p>
        <p>Since its beginning, Court TV has given viewers solid programs focusing on many aspects of criminal justice. The role confessions play is a worthy subject. But a few minutes of isolated tape cannot provide meaningful insight into criminality or even into the minds of these particular offenders. Worse, the utter lack of context can actually misinform  viewers about how interrogations work.</p>
        <p>Court TV made its mark with gavel-to-gavel coverage of trials that showed the entire courtroom process. The network has the legal right to show the confession tapes. But it is regrettable that it is willing to sabotage its reputation for serious legal journalism with a lurid show where tales of murder are offered as a night's entertainment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
