<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: A Dutch Behemoth Invades America; ING Group Makes Its Move in Virtual Banking and Insurance</title>
    <meta content="Y26DUT$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ing Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kist, Ewald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E3DD1331F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: A Dutch Behemoth Invades America; ING Group Makes Its Move in Virtual Banking and Insurance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>ING Group, Dutch insurance and banking giant, is building brand-name empire in US; has already amassed stable of about a dozen insurance companies; it plans to spend about $80 million to unite everything under one umbrella and establish its name across North America; chief executive Ewald Kist comments on his plans to establish many-faceted financial services operation in US; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly a year after Congress cleared the way for insurance companies to own banks and vice versa, most American banks and insurers are still on the sidelines, unable, analysts say, to see how to turn the new opportunity into profit.</p>
        <p>But early in September, a big Dutch company that pioneered banking and insurance combinations in Europe, the ING Group, is planning to break into the American field with a stripped-down virtual bank that will eventually sell insurance. It hopes to become a model for getting the most out of both businesses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly a year after Congress cleared the way for insurance companies to own banks and vice versa, most American banks and insurers are still on the sidelines, unable, analysts say, to see how to turn the new opportunity into profit.</p>
        <p>But early in September, a big Dutch company that pioneered banking and insurance combinations in Europe, the ING Group, is planning to break into the American field with a stripped-down virtual bank that will eventually sell insurance. It hopes to become a model for getting the most out of both businesses.</p>
        <p>The bank is part of a larger plan by ING, a financial services giant with operations in more than 60 countries, to build a brand-name empire in the United States. The company, whose American headquarters are here in Atlanta, has already amassed a stable of about a dozen insurance companies, including two big recent additions bought for nearly $14 billion. It says it plans to spend roughly $80 million -- a huge amount in the insurance world -- to unite everything under one umbrella and establish its name across North America.</p>
        <p>Before Congress scrapped the Depression-era Glass-Steagall Act and other laws that had kept insurance companies and banks separate, two American giants, Travelers Group and Citicorp, joined together as Citigroup in the kind of merger that financial services executives had long argued would better serve customers and add to their fortunes.</p>
        <p>But since the bill became law last November, bankers and insurers have been waiting for signs that customers would rush to do their banking and buy insurance with the same company.</p>
        <p>''Citigroup has had some success,'' said Tom Brown, chief executive of Second Curve Capital, a financial services fund, ''but the jury is still out.''</p>
        <p>For European companies, however, the verdict is in. Banking and insurance combinations have been operating in Europe for more than a decade, some with considerable success. Whether ING can make it work here is far from certain, but it will not be for lack of effort.</p>
        <p>''I think the U.S. financial services will eventually consolidate down to maybe 10 major entities,'' said Colin Devine, an insurance analyst at Salomon Smith Barney. ''ING is obviously serving notice that it intends to be one of the 10.''</p>
        <p>ING's newest addition, an online bank, will feature a savings account paying 6.5 percent interest -- triple the rate at most established banks, but about on par with Internet banks that require minimum deposits of $1,000 or so to open an account. ING Direct will have no minimums, no limits on withdrawals and no fees. The bank also plans to offer consumer loans, mortgages and certificates of deposit. Term life insurance and mutual funds, which ING now sells through its insurance outlets, will later be added to the bank roster.</p>
        <p>To keep costs down, the bank will be run out of a renovated six-story warehouse in Wilmington, Del., where real estate and labor are relatively cheap. The bank will not offer checking accounts, which often are money losers. But it will electronically link checking accounts that customers have at other banks to their accounts at ING Direct, allowing them to transfer money in and out, much as banks now let customers electronically shift funds to and from brokerage houses.</p>
        <p>Instead of branches, the bank will have a scattering of cybercafes where people can drop in to buy pastry and coffee, surf the Web and perhaps check on their digital accounts. Ewald Kist, the chief executive of ING, said ING came up with the idea of the cafes, which it has used with its online banks in Canada, Australia, Spain and France, because ''people like to feel something, see something real.'' The first ING Direct Cafe in the United States is set to open in early October in Manhattan, at 49th Street and Park Avenue.</p>
        <p>''We could have bought a bricks-and-mortar bank, but that would be nothing new for the U.S. market,'' Mr. Kist said. ''We're not in competition with hundreds of thousands of banks. We're doing a new trick.''</p>
        <p>And, somewhat like beaters in a grouse hunt, ING will have 10,500 financial planners with insurance and brokerage licenses around the United States, the largest force of its kind in the country, to point out the virtues of the new bank to their customers.</p>
        <p>Steve Wicker, a banking analyst at the Meta Group, a technology research firm in Stamford, Conn., said he thought the bank would ''definitely make a dent in the market.''</p>
        <p>But other experts are skeptical. James McCormick, president of the First Manhattan Consulting Group, which specializes in financial services and telecommunications, said he sees the bank as a niche player rather than as a challenger to big banks like Wells Fargo and Bank One.</p>
        <p>Customers concerned primarily about high returns from a bank ''are not loyal,'' Mr. McCormick said.</p>
        <p>''And while this segment is not small,'' he added, ''not everybody goes with a bank on that basis. So you have limited growth potential.''</p>
        <p>Still, ING's effort stands out as a bold attempt to capitalize on a new opportunity.</p>
        <p>Since the company's formation through a merger of a bank and an insurer in the Netherlands in 1991, ING has been quietly selling insurance in America through regional companies like Life of Georgia.  ING's insurance predecessor, Nationale-Nederlanden, had owned American insurance companies since the late 1970's. But you had to read the fine print to know that the companies were related or Dutch-owned.</p>
        <p>ING's latest acquistions, ReliaStar Financial Services, a deal announced in May, and the nonhealth insurance units of Aetna Financial Services, announced in July, will make ING one of America's biggest insurers. Now it is planning to shed its cloak of anonymity.</p>
        <p>''There is going to be a lot of noise about ING in the U.S.,'' Mr. Kist said. ''We are a strong company, a world player, and we want to capitalize on that strong name.''</p>
        <p>Under the new strategy, all of ING's American possessions -- including its New York investment banks, ING Barings and Furman Selz -- are being tied together with the parent's name and its orange lion logo. For example, Equitable of Iowa, which the Dutch company bought in 1997, has become ING Equitable Life.</p>
        <p>ING's expansion is the latest foray by European companies into the world's biggest market for financial services. Companies like Aegon, also based in the Netherlands; the Dutch-Belgian Fortis; AXA of France; and Allianz of Germany have been attracted to the United States by favorable economics and regulatory policies. And they are becoming substantial players. Early last year, for example, Aegon bought the Transamerica Corporation, a big American life insurance company. And in June, a unit of AXA, which already was a leader here, bought Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, the New York money management and institutional research firm.</p>
        <p>Though proposed foreign acquisitions in some American industries, notably telecommunications, have stirred nationalistic concerns, there have been no such reverberations yet in the fragmented financial services business.</p>
        <p>To European buyers, American insurance companies, which generally trade at lower price-to-earnings ratios than their European counterparts, seem like bargains.</p>
        <p>Moreover, even with state-by-state regulation of insurance as well as some aspects of banking in the United States, and even with the European Union smoothing out the regulatory differences among its 15 member nations, the Europeans say that doing business in America is easier and less costly than it is in the patchwork of countries and languages that make up Europe.</p>
        <p>Then, of course, companies that want to be truly global feel they must have a significant presence in the United States.</p>
        <p>Another lure is that with more and more Americans responsible for managing their own retirement with 401(k) plans and the like rather than traditional pensions, the personal investment business is booming here far more than in Europe, where pensions are still primarily a governmental obligation. And like their American counterparts, ING and the other European insurers doing business in the United States are focusing more on investing these days than on insurance.</p>
        <p>So the Europeans have been steadily picking off American companies. And many are still on the hunt. But ING, Mr. Kist said, is finished ''with our shopping list for now.''</p>
        <p>The job at hand, he said, is to fit the pieces of the company's empire together to maximize economies of scale and to centralize different lines of business in headquarters around the United States. The old marble and glass Georgia Life building, for example, set on the edge of Atlanta deep in a hardwood forest, has been designated ING's command post not only for the United States operations but for those of Canada and Latin America as well. Des Moines will become the center for fixed annuities.</p>
        <p>The whole idea of expanding ING's American operations, Mr. Kist said, was to be able to become a low-cost provider. ''You need to be well priced and you need to have a presence in all the states,'' he said.</p>
        <p>ING's American competitors have also been consolidating, but so far banks and insurance have largely remained separate. Banks have been reluctant to buy insurance companies, experts say, because they would have to tie up a lot of capital for generally sluggish returns. Most insurers cannot afford a bank big enough to give them a national network of outlets for insurance, and even some that could pony up the money say they regard banking profits as less predictable than those from insurance.</p>
        <p>The industries, however, have been converging to some extent. Many banks have contracted with insurers to sell policies through their branches for a fee. And a handful of insurers have begun experimenting with banking, mostly aimed at their insurance customers.</p>
        <p>The State Farm Mutual Automobile Insurance Company, the biggest American insurer of cars and homes, has started offering a range of financial services online and through its agents. But unlike ING, State Farm is completely new to banking and it concedes it is just getting its feet wet. So is MetLife one of the biggest life insurers. On Aug. 16, MetLife said it was buying a small New Jersey bank, Grand Bank, and that it hoped to start up early next year -- perhaps, analysts say, with an online operation.</p>
        <p>Right now, ING is the company to watch. Mr. Brown, the financial consultant and fund manager, said he expected that many competing bank executives would open accounts at ING Direct to ''see how it's going and to be a fast follower if it succeeds.''</p>
        <p>But he is among those who see long odds. ''In our experience,'' he said, ''pioneers usually end up with arrows in their back.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
