<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Agrees To Free Poet After Protests From Writers</title>
    <meta content="Y26CHI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huang Beiling</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED71331F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Agrees To Free Poet After Protests From Writers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, Aug. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Huang Beiling, Boston-based Chinese poet arrested in Beijing on August 11 in connection with literary journal he edits, will be released and deported to US; is Chinese citizen with permanent-residence status in US; arrest drew protests from literary figures worldwide, as well as from US Embassy in Beijing; police confiscated hundreds of copies of Journal, Tendency, which is published in US, but gve no reason why they detained him; China's State Council Information Office says he was jailed because of illegal business activity (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Boston-based Chinese poet who was arrested two weeks ago in connection with a literary journal he edits will be released and deported to the United States on Saturday, an American Embassy official in Beijing said today.</p>
        <p>The Aug. 11 arrest of Huang Bei ling, who is a Chinese citizen with permanent-residence status in the United States, drew protests from literary figures worldwide as well as from the American Embassy in Beijing. The police also confiscated hundreds of copies of his journal, Tendency, which is published in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Boston-based Chinese poet who was arrested two weeks ago in connection with a literary journal he edits will be released and deported to the United States on Saturday, an American Embassy official in Beijing said today.</p>
        <p>The Aug. 11 arrest of Huang Bei ling, who is a Chinese citizen with permanent-residence status in the United States, drew protests from literary figures worldwide as well as from the American Embassy in Beijing. The police also confiscated hundreds of copies of his journal, Tendency, which is published in the United States.</p>
        <p>The police never said why they had detained Mr. Huang, also known by his literary name Bei Ling, who has lived in the United States for more than a decade and had come back to China for a visit in June. But a spokesman for China's State Council Information Office said on Thursday that he had been ''detained for further review by the Public Security organization'' because of ''illegal business activity.''</p>
        <p>Chinese police can keep suspects in criminal detention for up to 30 days without filing formal charges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huang's release defuses a situation that threatened to become a major political embarrassment for China, at a time when its government is preparing to open a $7 million celebration of Chinese culture this week in the United States.</p>
        <p>Some leading Western writers and scholars had said they would probably boycott the event -- which includes performances, lectures and exhibits in nine American cities -- if  Mr. Huang were still in prison.</p>
        <p>Last week, PEN American Center, the writers group, sent a letter of protest to President Jiang Zemin signed by well-known literary figures including Susan Sontag, Arthur Miller and Seamus Heaney.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Bei's arrest represents an especially alarming escalation of the repressive and inhuman treatment of dissident writers and intellectuals in China during recent months,'' it said.</p>
        <p>Although China's publishing industry and intellectual life generally have become more lively and open in the last few years, the Chinese government has recently attempted to rein in the trend.</p>
        <p>Distributing foreign magazines like Tendency is illegal in China, where the state still officially owns and controls all publications. Although visitors may generally bring in reading matter for personal use without interference, the import of foreign publications requires permits. Still, many are available in intellectual circles and even more widely available on the Internet.</p>
        <p>The Web sites of foreign publications are sometimes blocked by the government, but many educated Chinese know how to circumvent the restrictions and individual articles are often posted in Chinese chat rooms, which are more difficult for the government to monitor.</p>
        <p>Still, the Chinese government clearly regards the burgeoning of information and intellectual discussion as a threat to its control. And it has tried hard to discourage it in a serious, if scattershot, way.</p>
        <p>In the last eight months, it has closed down or warned several publishers whose books were deemed unacceptable. A few private Web sites posting politically sensitive material have been shut and their owners detained. Several prominent academics have been publicly criticized by top government officials, and some have lost their teaching positions.</p>
        <p>But since the government has turned a blind eye to similar activities by many other Chinese intellectuals, Mr. Huang, who had visited China numerous times in the past decade without incident, may not have expected any trouble.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huang had come to conduct a forum on the latest issue of Tendency, which focuses on Mr. Heaney, the Irish poet and Nobel laureate. The Chinese-language journal offers a mix of translations and original works by Chinese writers.</p>
        <p>Although it occasionally publishes work by and about dissident Chinese authors -- and runs a list of underground Chinese literary publications -- Tendency has little overt political content.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huang is to leave on Saturday on a plane for San Francisco. His younger brother, Huang Feng, who lives in Beijing and is also a writer, was detained last week. He was freed late tonight.</p>
        <p>In a statement, the executive director of PEN American Center, Michael Roberts, said his group was ''thrilled'' with Huang Beiling's release, but added, ''The international market in which China seeks full and normal status also includes a marketplace of ideas, and it cannot expect to be welcomed into the one while rejecting the other.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
