<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wrestlers' Dispute Mired in Courts</title>
    <meta content="26OLYM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindland, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sieracki, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1D81331F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wrestlers' Dispute Mired in Courts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matt Lindland's protest over loss to Keith Sieracki at US Olympic trials has held up final roster for US Olympic Greco Roman wrestling team (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Sydney Olympics begin in three weeks, but the roster of the American Greco-Roman wrestling team remains in a legal chokehold.</p>
        <p>A match between Matt Lindland and Keith Sieracki took only minutes at the Olympic trials in June, but two months later, the outcome remains locked in a judicial tug of war between federal arbitrators and federal judges. Sports law experts say the ultimate referee could be the United States Supreme Court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Sydney Olympics begin in three weeks, but the roster of the American Greco-Roman wrestling team remains in a legal chokehold.</p>
        <p>A match between Matt Lindland and Keith Sieracki took only minutes at the Olympic trials in June, but two months later, the outcome remains locked in a judicial tug of war between federal arbitrators and federal judges. Sports law experts say the ultimate referee could be the United States Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>Sieracki, an Army sergeant, defeated Lindland, a four-time national champion in the 167 1/2-pound category, by a score of 2-1 in their deciding bout at the Olympic trials. Lindland filed an immediate protest, saying he had been tripped in violation of Greco-Roman rules, which prohibit the use of the legs to conduct a maneuver.</p>
        <p>The United States wrestling federation, the sport's national governing body, rejected the protest, and the case became as entangled as the two wrestlers on the mat.</p>
        <p>American Olympic athletes have the right to seek binding federal arbitration to resolve disputes, according to the federal Olympic and Amateur Sports Act. All sports federations under the Olympic umbrella also agree to be bound by rulings of the American Arbitration Association. In an attempt to avoid the courts, the United States Olympic Committee has Olympians sign a code of conduct form saying they will settle complaints in arbitration.</p>
        <p>''Now the whole resolution process has been thrown on its ear,'' said Jeff Benz, a lawyer who represented the cyclist Christine Witty in another arbitration case. ''We're back to having courts resolve sports disputes.''</p>
        <p>Lindland first filed for arbitration, and an arbitrator ordered a rematch, which Lindland won, 8-0. Saying he thought the rematch was merely practice, Sieracki then filed his own arbitration case, saying that the first arbitration decision should be invalidated because he had never been invited to the proceeding to defend himself. Thursday, an arbitrator ruled in Sieracki's favor, and it appeared he would be heading to the Olympics.</p>
        <p>However, Lindland took his case to the United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit in Chicago, which ruled later Thursday that the original arbitration should be enforced and that USA Wrestling should submit Lindland's name to the United States Olympic Committee for participation in Sydney.</p>
        <p>The committee now finds itself with a difficult decision: which wrestler does it choose to compete in Sydney, Australia? Both Sieracki and Lindland have arbitration rulings in their favor. The U.S.O.C. is not bound by the Seventh Circuit ruling, although Judge Frank H. Easterbrook wrote in his decision, ''We trust the U.S.O.C. will act responsibly once it receives USA Wrestling's nomination of Lindland.''</p>
        <p>Easterbrook suggested that both wrestlers might have to be named to the Olympic team. International Olympic rules would not allow for that without a waiver from wrestling's world governing body. Short of that, the U.S.O.C. will have to choose either Sieracki or Lindland, or let the case play itself out in the courts, legal experts said. Mike Moran, a U.S.O.C. spokesman, said yesterday that the committee would study the matter over the weekend in an attempt to reach a fair decision.</p>
        <p>Whatever the outcome, this case has pointed out the weakness in the U.S.O.C.'s arbitration process. Ed Williams, a New York lawyer who helped write the athletes' rights section of the Olympic and Amateur Sports Act, said it may be necessary to amend the act to make sure that all parties are brought together at one arbitration hearing so that multiple, conflicting arbitration rulings don't occur. He also said that it may be necessary to state in writing that ''field of play'' decisions made by referees or umpires are off limits to arbitration.</p>
        <p>''Clearly this decision by the first arbitrator may cause other athletes to consider whether they want to arbitrate field-of-play decisions,'' Williams said, which could lead to a chaotic situation in which baseball players take umpires' calls to arbitration and figure skaters challenge judges' subjective rulings. ''It has been generally understood that decisions by referees or umpires are not subject to arbitration, but we haven't written it down in the rules.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Sieracki is exploring his legal options, said his lawyer, Lt. Col. Dan Shaver. One of those options is to seek to have the arbitration ruling in his favor validated by a federal appeals court. That would leave conflicting decisions, which may require the Supreme Court to adjudicate, sports law experts said.</p>
        <p>''Besides my divorce, it's the most frustrating thing I've ever been through, and my divorce was pretty frustrating,'' Sieracki told The Associated Press. He added: ''I've always felt you were supposed to leave it all on the mat, not in the courts.''</p>
        <p>Lindland called the conflicting legal rulings ''insanity,'' but told reporters he felt compelled to appeal what he thought was a ridiculous outcome at the Olympic trials.</p>
        <p>''When you know you're right, it's hard to say, 'Whatever,' and walk away,'' Lindland said. ''My nature is not to quit.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Witty Named to Cycling Team</p>
        <p>COLORADO SPRINGS, Aug. 25, (AP) -- The speedskater Christine Witty's spot on the United States Olympic cycling team was assured today after revelations that a challenger for her roster position tested positive for a high testosterone level.</p>
        <p>Tammy Thomas of Yazoo City, Miss., who narrowly beat Witty in the 500-meter time trial in the Olympic trials in April, had challenged Witty's appointment to the 27-member team, which was announced in July.</p>
        <p>Thomas withdrew her appeal today, the deadline for team officials to submit the final roster for the Sydney Olympics.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
