<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks' Utility Lineup Is Futile Against the A's</title>
    <meta content="26YANK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1225377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E6D61331F935A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks' Utility Lineup Is Futile Against the A's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., Aug. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oakland Athletics defeat New York Yankees, 8-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees are defending their back-to-back World Series championships these days with a whole bunch of folks who had nothing to do with those titles. If you dialed in the Yankees in the fourth inning tonight, this is what you saw: a funky left-hander named Randy Choate pitching, the diminutive Luis Polonia in left field and three other positions manned by utility players.</p>
        <p>The first-place Yankees hold a small but steady three-game lead over Boston in the American League East, an advantage that enables them to nurse their large number of nagging injuries. Bernie Williams, who is expected to return to the lineup Saturday, sat on the bench with Paul O'Neill tonight, and Chuck Knoblauch was in Florida, playing in a minor league game, as the Oakland Athletics trounced David Cone and the Yankees, 8-1. Kevin Appier (12-9) pitched eight innings for Oakland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees are defending their back-to-back World Series championships these days with a whole bunch of folks who had nothing to do with those titles. If you dialed in the Yankees in the fourth inning tonight, this is what you saw: a funky left-hander named Randy Choate pitching, the diminutive Luis Polonia in left field and three other positions manned by utility players.</p>
        <p>The first-place Yankees hold a small but steady three-game lead over Boston in the American League East, an advantage that enables them to nurse their large number of nagging injuries. Bernie Williams, who is expected to return to the lineup Saturday, sat on the bench with Paul O'Neill tonight, and Chuck Knoblauch was in Florida, playing in a minor league game, as the Oakland Athletics trounced David Cone and the Yankees, 8-1. Kevin Appier (12-9) pitched eight innings for Oakland.</p>
        <p>But, as usual, there was no change in the standing: Kansas City whipped the Red Sox, 6-2, and for the 16th time in the last 21 days, Boston had the same result as the Yankees. When the Yankees win, so do the Red Sox, and they seem to lose together as well.</p>
        <p>Cone (3-11) lacked command and good stuff; he almost never threw his slider tonight, and continually worked behind in the ball-strike count. Seven of the 18 batters he faced were able to swing in so-called hitters' counts -- two balls and no strikes, or 3-1. ''I worked myself into some jams, no doubt about it,'' Cone said.</p>
        <p>Said Joe Torre, the Yankees' manager, ''To have a bad game like this, you've got to dismiss it.''</p>
        <p>Matt Stairs ripped a home run on a 3-1 pitch in the second inning. Terrence Long slapped a double leading off the third, and Cone nailed Randy Velarde with a fastball inside and walked Jason Giambi, loading the bases with nobody out.</p>
        <p>Mike Stanley smashed a line drive -- right to third baseman Luis Sojo. But Cone's luck escaped him when Ben Grieve laced a two-run single. Three batters later, Oakland's Eric Chavez ripped a two-run double with an 0-2 count, and even before Chavez's hit landed, the Yankees' bullpen was in motion, preparing for the change. Cone threw 72 pitches in three innings, rarely hitting the target set by catcher Jorge Posada, and Torre decided to save Cone from further abuse and replaced him with Choate.</p>
        <p>Boston's recent failure to capitalize on the Yankees' mediocre play buys healing time for the Yankees. ''This is a scary time of year for me,'' Torre said, ''because if anything major happens, I don't know if we can get it well.''</p>
        <p>About 90 minutes before tonight's game, Williams raised a ball in his right hand and, slowly at first, pulled his arm forward and made a very short throw. Gradually, his throws lengthened, Williams always moving carefully and stiffly, as if he were trying to balance a plate on his head.</p>
        <p>Williams, coming back from a strained muscle in his right side, eventually took batting practice and is ''very much encouraged.'' Torre said it was likely the switch-hitting Williams would start Saturday, as a right-handed hitter, because batting left-handed bothers him. Even if a right-hander comes into the game, Williams's intention is to bat right-handed; it will be the first time he has faced right-handers as a right-hander since he played rookie ball, Williams said, grinning.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch, who has decided to try to play despite the pain he feels in his right elbow, started for Class A Tampa against Kissimmee, and as he led off the fourth inning, he was hit by a pitch on the outside of his left knee. The knee bruise is not considered serious.</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, somehow, I can shake this off and play tomorrow, but don't know if they're going to want me to,'' Knoblauch told The Associated Press. ''I've been thumped a thousand times and I've never been hit in this spot. It was weird.</p>
        <p>''I was just starting to feel in the groove; it was going good. This is how my year has been, exactly right here to a tee. There's nothing I can do but laugh about it. It was going in the right direction.''</p>
        <p>Torre spoke Thursday with Knoblauch, who has tendinitis in his right elbow. Knoblauch told Torre that he was still in pain. Torre told Knoblauch once again how important he is to the team -- Knoblauch is an exceptional leadoff hitter -- and Knoblauch's status seems to have come down to this: Can he play second base with the pain he is feeling? ''We're going to find that out,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Before the game, Knoblauch said that he was ready to play the rest of the season with the pain that has bothered him since he initially hurt the elbow July 24. ''I'm resigned to the fact that it's not going to be healthy,'' he said. ''I'm trying to see if I can play through it. I'll find out throughout these games.''</p>
        <p>If he can't play second base, Knoblauch's role will be far more limited, as a part-time designated hitter, pinch-hitter and pinch-runner, and Torre will probably use Sojo and Jose Vizcaino at second into the postseason.</p>
        <p>O'Neill (hip pointer) lobbied extensively to be in the lineup tonight, telling Torre that he felt well enough to play. ''I almost gave in,'' Torre said. ''But it's probably the safe thing'' to hold him out of the lineup.</p>
        <p>The Yankees remain hopeful that reliever Ramiro Mendoza will have time to recover from his arm trouble, but as Torre looks ahead, he is not counting on Mendoza's presence in his bullpen because of the slow progress of Mendoza's rehabilitation. ''In my mind,'' Torre said, ''it'll be a bonus if we get him back.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
