<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ferreting Out North Korea's Nuclear Secrets: U.S. Intelligence Experts at Odds</title>
    <meta content="Y05KOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Defense Intelligence Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">State Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Risen, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5D7153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ferreting Out North Korea's Nuclear Secrets: U.S. Intelligence Experts at Odds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES RISEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Risen, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Dept and Pentagon are at odds over extent of North Korea's nuclear weapons program, arguing over photos or snippets of intelligence from agents; State Department says Pentagon's Defense Intelligence Agency, known for its hawkish outlook, has been painting far too black a picture, surmising on sketchy evidence that North Korea has up to 10 new installations working on a covert nuclear program; DIA says State Department is too willing to overlook reports of suspicious activity; this dispute lies behind the other debate over whether to build a new national missile defense against countries like North Korea (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Behind the growing debate over whether to build a new national missile defense against countries like North Korea lies an old and bitter dispute over how to interpret the frustratingly limited intelligence data on one of the world's most secretive nations.</p>
        <p>Witness this incident, not previously disclosed: Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright had just completed an upbeat, top-secret briefing for the House leadership in July 1998 on the Clinton administration's dealings with North Korea when one lawmaker posed the question he had been waiting to ask:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Behind the growing debate over whether to build a new national missile defense against countries like North Korea lies an old and bitter dispute over how to interpret the frustratingly limited intelligence data on one of the world's most secretive nations.</p>
        <p>Witness this incident, not previously disclosed: Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright had just completed an upbeat, top-secret briefing for the House leadership in July 1998 on the Clinton administration's dealings with North Korea when one lawmaker posed the question he had been waiting to ask:</p>
        <p>What was Dr. Albright's assessment of a recent intelligence report suggesting that North Korea had built a storage installation that housed components for nuclear warheads? And how long had she known about the report?</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright, according to several people who were present, replied that she had learned of the evidence just two weeks earlier. In a startling departure from the united front that top administration officials usually present to Congress, Lt. Gen. Patrick Hughes, director of the Defense Intelligence Agency, immediately contradicted the secretary of state.</p>
        <p>''Madame Secretary, I have to correct the record,'' said General Hughes, whose agency had produced the report, according to others who were there. ''You were briefed on that intelligence a year ago.''</p>
        <p>That tart exchange offered an unusual glimpse of the depth of the disagreements between the nation's senior diplomats and the Pentagon's top intelligence officials over how to interpret the few hard facts available about North Korea.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers said the dispute had spurred them to demand an independent review of the evidence on North Korea, which the administration eventually acceded to with the appointment of former Defense Secretary William J. Perry as special adviser.</p>
        <p>Much of the debate stems from arcane arguments over photos or snippets of intelligence from agents. State Department officials say the Pentagon intelligence agency, known for its hawkish outlook, has been painting far too black a picture, surmising on sketchy evidence that North Korea has up to 10 new installations working on a covert nuclear program.</p>
        <p>The State Department officials said their skepticism about the quality of the Defense Intelligence Agency's work had been deepened by a 1999 incident in which American diplomats pressed the North Koreans to allow inspections of a site the agency had said was part of a nuclear program. Nothing was found.</p>
        <p>For their part, intelligence analysts at D.I.A. are said to believe that the State Department has been far too willing to overlook reports of suspicious activity. In their view, the failure of a single inspection does not mean the United States should stop pressing the North Koreans about suspect installations, including the building suspected of housing warhead components.</p>
        <p>The crisis over North Korea's nuclear program began in 1993, when analysts reviewing evidence from American spy satellites concluded that a North Korean nuclear reprocessing center at Yongbyon had gone ''hot'' -- had begun to process plutonium.</p>
        <p>American intelligence analysts then watched as the North Koreans dumped radioactive nuclear fuel out of the heavy water reactor into a cooling pool in order to replace it with fresh fuel rods. The spent fuel rods contained enough plutonium for 10 nuclear warheads, officials said.</p>
        <p>The activity at Yongbyon led to a diplomatic showdown, and after months of talks the Clinton administration won a North Korean pledge to freeze plutonium production at the site. In exchange, the United States, South Korea and Japan agreed to give the North oil and technical assistance to build a peaceful nuclear power program. The agreement called for international monitoring of the Yongbyon site, and Energy Department experts were allowed to encase the spent fuel rods at the center to ensure that they could not be used for warheads.</p>
        <p>Before the production freeze, North Korea was able to produce about 26 pounds of weapons-grade plutonium, American intelligence analysts agree. A consensus developed  that North Korea could produce one or two bombs.</p>
        <p>Political problems surfaced when administration officials began to declare that North Korea had agreed to freeze its entire nuclear program. Eventually, however, the lawmakers realized that the agreement covered only Yongbyon and did not preclude nuclear activity at other sites. Suspicions arose that the North Koreans were covertly continuing work on their nuclear program.</p>
        <p>After the administration negotiated the freeze on activity at Yongbyon, the Defense Intelligence Agency began to report that it had detected a series of other secret sites, many of them underground, that analysts suspected were related to an ongoing nuclear program.</p>
        <p>By the late-1990's, the Defense Intelligence Agency, working closely with the National Imagery and Mapping Agency, which processes and analyzes spy satellite photographs, compiled a list of at least 10 such sites.</p>
        <p>None, however, was a ''smoking gun.'' One official termed them ''enigmas'': they raised suspicions, yet the United States did not have enough evidence to prove their ties to a nuclear program.</p>
        <p>Analysts from the Defense Intelligence Agency were most concerned about one installation they suspected of being a storage building for components of nuclear warheads. The identity and exact location of the suspected center, whose existence has not been previously made public, could not be learned.</p>
        <p>Current and former officials say the intelligence on the storage center was obtained at least three years ago, and was based not only on spy satellite photographs and intercepted communications, but also on ''human intelligence'' -- spies -- reporting to the D.I.A.</p>
        <p>The agency also detected another installation, at Kumchangri, that was believed to house an underground nuclear reactor and plutonium reprocessing operation. The existence of that underground facility was publicly disclosed in The New York Times in August 1998.</p>
        <p>In May 1999, the United States pressed North Korea to allow an inspection of the Kumchangri installation. Before that visit, the D.I.A. gave senior officials extensive briefings on Kumchangri, complete with models of what agency analysts believed the installation contained.</p>
        <p>''Kumchangri had all the signatures you would look for if they were putting a reactor underground,'' a former American intelligence official said. ''It had vast water supplies, and the belief was that the reactor would be water-cooled.''</p>
        <p>But when the Americans arrived, they found nothing but a series of narrow, empty tunnels, with no large underground chamber able to hold a nuclear reactor. The inspection was a bust, and an ''embarrassment'' to the United States, one official said.</p>
        <p>The United States sent another inspection team to Kumchangri in May of this year, but again it found nothing to indicate that involvement in a nuclear weapons program.</p>
        <p>''It was really a joke,'' a State Department official said. ''The North Koreans really must have thought we were idiots.''</p>
        <p>Some officials say the United States gave North Korea far too much advance warning of its interest in visiting the Kumchangri site before inspecting it, making it possible for the North Koreans to hide its purpose. They add that the installation was still under construction when it was detected by American intelligence. ''My best guess is that it was something bad on the nuclear side, but no one knows,'' an official said.</p>
        <p>But the inspections of Kumchangri seriously damaged the Defense Intelligence Agency's credibility with administration officials and analysts at the other agencies, particularly the State Department.</p>
        <p>The skepticism deepened after American officials discovered that another installation that had fallen under D.I.A. suspicion turned out to be an underground storage site for the memorabilia of the North Korean leadership.</p>
        <p>As a result, the administration has become very reluctant to pursue leads on other suspected installation identified by D.I.A. The administration has never asked to inspect the secret installation believed to be a warhead storage site, several American officials said.</p>
        <p>''This was a prime example of  policy being driven by intelligence, and at the end of the day it was wrong,'' said a State Department official critical of the D.I.A.'s handling of the Kumchangri case.</p>
        <p>After the failed inspections at Kumchangri, American intelligence officials debated whether to conduct a thorough review of the available intelligence on the North Korean nuclear program and produce what is known as a national intelligence estimate, representing a government-wide consensus on the problem. But there were so many interagency disagreements that no such estimate was commissioned, officials said.</p>
        <p>General Hughes retired in July, 1999, a year after his showdown with Dr. Albright.</p>
        <p>The State Department spokesman, Richard Boucher, said General Hughes eventually apologized to Dr. Albright, who still maintains that she had learned of the secret installation just two weeks before the hearing. But General Hughes said in an interview that while he did apologize to Dr. Albright for ''causing her public embarrassment,'' he stressed that he did not apologize for correcting the record, because her testimony was not accurate.</p>
        <p>''I felt bad that I caused the secretary of state some embarrassment,'' he said. ''But on the other hand, I felt fine about raising the issue, and still do today. I would have hated going away from there with Congress thinking we hadn't properly informed officials about the intelligence.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
