<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chief of Bed-Stuy Economic Group Quits</title>
    <meta content="05BEDF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220112"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Roderick B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6D8153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chief of Bed-Stuy Economic Group Quits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roderick B Mitchell resigns as president of Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corp amid criticism that nation's oldest economic development group is failing in mission of reviving central Brooklyn; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president of the Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation resigned abruptly this week after criticism that his organization -- the nation's oldest economic development corporation -- was failing in its mission of reviving central Brooklyn's economy.</p>
        <p>The resignation of Roderick B. Mitchell, who is 44 and known as Rocky, ended 12 years at the helm of the corporation. He took over the organization when it was on the verge of bankruptcy and oversaw an expansion that included renovating hundreds of homes, creating thousands of jobs and forming a partnership with Pathmark to bring the neighborhood its first large supermarket in many years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The president of the Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation resigned abruptly this week after criticism that his organization -- the nation's oldest economic development corporation -- was failing in its mission of reviving central Brooklyn's economy.</p>
        <p>The resignation of Roderick B. Mitchell, who is 44 and known as Rocky, ended 12 years at the helm of the corporation. He took over the organization when it was on the verge of bankruptcy and oversaw an expansion that included renovating hundreds of homes, creating thousands of jobs and forming a partnership with Pathmark to bring the neighborhood its first large supermarket in many years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mitchell would not say yesterday why he was stepping down. A Restoration spokeswoman, Bev Jafek, said Mr. Mitchell announced Thursday that he was leaving and that yesterday was his last day. ''He isn't being fired,'' she said. ''It's sad. We would like him to stay, and he will not.''</p>
        <p>In a statement issued yesterday by the corporation, Robert F. Kennedy Jr., vice chairman of Restoration, said: ''Rocky guided Bedford-Stuyvesant through the most difficult time in history. Bedford-Stuyvesant will miss his inspired leadership and steady hand.''</p>
        <p>In the early years of Mr. Mitchell's tenure, the corporation, created in 1967 under legislation written by Senators Robert F. Kennedy and Jacob K. Javits and then used as a national model for economic development, was viewed by many as a main player in the neighborhood's revitalization.</p>
        <p>But community leaders say Restoration has been stuck in recent years, bogged down by too much bureaucracy, and has not spurred the economic growth or attracted the kind of businesses that have helped renew other neighborhoods, like Harlem. The corporation, which manages about 900 residential housing units and 300,000 square feet of commercial property, has not expanded its real estate stock in recent years, and it has drawn few new businesses to Fulton Street, the area's main thoroughfare.</p>
        <p>''The perception in the business community is that Restoration was not as invested in the success of small businesses in the surrounding area as it should have been,'' said Errol Louis, a community advocate who heads a local merchants association and who founded the Central Brooklyn Federal Credit Union. ''There was a list that was longer than most people realized of what Restoration was not doing.''</p>
        <p>In the last two years, Restoration, which has an $11 million annual budget, has run a deficit -- $990,000 in the past fiscal year and $1.6 million the year before.</p>
        <p>Ms. Jafek said Restoration had not yet named a successor for Mr. Mitchell.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
