<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raw Deal for Doctors in Poor Areas</title>
    <meta content="05SAT2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Student Loans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rural Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2D8153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="470" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raw Deal for Doctors in Poor Areas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says federal program that pays doctors a bonus to practice in poor rural and urban areas needs a major redesign or millions of dollars to prevent a repeat of this year, when more than 90 percent of debt-laden doctors who joined understaffed clinics were told in midyear, without warning, that the program had run out of money and that they would receive nothing beyond their meager salaries</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal program that pays doctors saddled with huge student loans a bonus to practice in poor rural and urban areas needs a major redesign or millions more dollars. What Congress should not tolerate is a repeat of this year, when more than 90 percent of the doctors who joined understaffed clinics were told in midyear, without warning, that the program had run out of money and that they would receive nothing beyond their meager salaries. The administrative blunder threatens to undermine the worthy program by driving away future applicants.</p>
        <p>Last year 771 doctors took new positions in underserved areas and applied for a federal bonus of up to $50,000 to repay student loans. The program awarded 469 bonuses to new applicants at a cost of about $37 million. But this year the authorities changed the rules and awarded bonuses to only 48 new applicants, less than 10 percent of the 715 new applicants. The decision traps hundreds of doctors who would otherwise have received a bonus in lower-paying jobs they cannot afford to keep. Many of these doctors rejected higher-paying positions in the expectation, based on recent experience, that the government would help them pay off their loans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The federal program that pays doctors saddled with huge student loans a bonus to practice in poor rural and urban areas needs a major redesign or millions more dollars. What Congress should not tolerate is a repeat of this year, when more than 90 percent of the doctors who joined understaffed clinics were told in midyear, without warning, that the program had run out of money and that they would receive nothing beyond their meager salaries. The administrative blunder threatens to undermine the worthy program by driving away future applicants.</p>
        <p>Last year 771 doctors took new positions in underserved areas and applied for a federal bonus of up to $50,000 to repay student loans. The program awarded 469 bonuses to new applicants at a cost of about $37 million. But this year the authorities changed the rules and awarded bonuses to only 48 new applicants, less than 10 percent of the 715 new applicants. The decision traps hundreds of doctors who would otherwise have received a bonus in lower-paying jobs they cannot afford to keep. Many of these doctors rejected higher-paying positions in the expectation, based on recent experience, that the government would help them pay off their loans.</p>
        <p>The administration did not crack down out of malice or callousness. But neither was it adroit in handling the program's financial problems. Without notice, the authorities shifted $7 million out of the bonus program into a program that provides scholarships to medical students who agree to practice in medically underserved areas after they graduate. The shift was made because the administration had allowed spending on the scholarships to fall below Congressionally mandated levels. Then the administration decided to spend the shrunken pool of bonus money in a way that gave priority to doctors who started work at approved clinics last year rather than the doctors who started this year. These two decisions explain the fall from 469 new bonuses to 48 within a year.</p>
        <p>A program that rejects 93 percent of its applicants will not draw many applicants in the future. Congress could address the problem by spending an extra $7 million or more. The money would be well spent because the approved clinics are woefully understaffed. The administration also plans to switch its priority to new applicants, making this year's losers permanent. But the administration might also fix the core problem. It should be possible for doctors to learn before they pick up and move to a clinic whether they will in fact receive a bonus to repay their loans. The certainty would not only make the program fairer to the doctors, but also attract more high-quality applicants.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
