<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Year Out of Bankruptcy, Barneys Is Still Looking for Sure Footing</title>
    <meta content="Y05BAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Editors' Note Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000823T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barney's Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Questrom, Allen L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3D8153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1344" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Year Out of Bankruptcy, Barneys Is Still Looking for Sure Footing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article assesses tenure of Allen L Questrom as chief of Barneys New York; his attempts to bring firm out of bankruptcy have had mixed success; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the troubled retailer J. C. Penney announced last week that Allen L. Questrom would be its new chief executive, Wall Street was euphoric.</p>
        <p>Penney has been dogged by disappointing sales at its department stores, but its stock rose 16.5 percent that day. And Mr. Questrom's credentials led 4 of the 12 analysts that cover the company to upgrade the stock, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the troubled retailer J. C. Penney announced last week that Allen L. Questrom would be its new chief executive, Wall Street was euphoric.</p>
        <p>Penney has been dogged by disappointing sales at its department stores, but its stock rose 16.5 percent that day. And Mr. Questrom's credentials led 4 of the 12 analysts that cover the company to upgrade the stock, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>''He's got to be a huge improvement at J. C. Penney,'' said George Strachan at Goldman Sachs, who raised his rating to ''market outperform'' from ''market perform.''  ''He's got a lot of charisma and is very decisive.''</p>
        <p>Investor enthusiasm stems in large part from the work that Mr. Questrom did while reviving ailing public companies like Federated Department Stores and Macy's, which Federated acquired under his leadership. But in the most recent chapter of his career, as chairman and chief executive of Barneys New York after it emerged from bankruptcy, it is less clear that the turnaround man has spun straw into gold.</p>
        <p>Though Barneys has had robust sales growth, its cash flow and earnings have not been nearly as strong as the company predicted in documents filed with the United States Bankruptcy Court. This weakness, combined with a less-forgiving investor environment, has dashed any chance of a quick return to public ownership. In addition, the glitzy retailer has been hemorrhaging employees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Questrom, 60, a flawlessly groomed executive, arrived in May 1999 at Barneys, which was famous for dressing men in the finest suits and their social X-ray wives in the newest European designs. The company had come out of bankruptcy in January, and he was not responsible for the plan filed with the court in November 1998. That was done by the retailer's majority owners, two vulture funds, Bar Harbour Management and Whipporwill Associates Inc.</p>
        <p>Doug Teitlebaum of Bar Harbour and David A. Strumwasser of Whipporwill Associates say that the numbers in the filing were based on the projections of previous management, under the leadership of the chief executive, Tom Shull. When Mr. Questrom came aboard, the owners and Mr. Questrom formulated a more conservative plan, the owners say, and the company is exceeding its new targets, though they declined to disclose those numbers.</p>
        <p>At the time of his arrival, Mr. Questrom was heralded as an executive who could generate dynamic growth -- growth essential for Barneys to pay off its substantial debts.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Tarkenton, a bankruptcy lawyer at Womble, Carlyle, Sandridge &amp; Rice in Washington, said he had not studied the Barneys situation, but added, ''Like any company that misses projections significantly, it is a sign that reorganization might be failing.''</p>
        <p>The idea that his yearlong tenure at Barneys has been anything less than spectacular makes Mr. Questrom's eyes flash. He says what really matters for a retailer just out of bankruptcy is to earn the trust of vendors, and that there he surpassed expectations. When he took the helm, 80 percent of vendors were asking to be paid on delivery of goods, he says, and today less than 8 percent do -- and those are mostly small suppliers who cannot afford to do otherwise.</p>
        <p>Barneys stores have experienced double-digit sales growth since he arrived. In fact, much of the luxury market, including Saks Fifth Avenue and Neiman Marcus, has benefited from a strong economy. Mr. Questrom, though, takes credit for helping Barneys partake in the boom by training the notoriously snooty sales force to be more friendly.</p>
        <p>Despite these solid accomplishments, there have been troubling signs at the retailer, most notably executive turnover at Barneys flagship Madison Avenue store since Mr. Questrom arrived. In just the last three months, the company has lost six executives at the level of divisional vice president and above, a creative director, a vice president of communications and the Madison Avenue store manager, or roughly 9 out of 16 senior staff members.</p>
        <p>The turnover would not be a concern at a large chain of stores. At a small, high-end operation like Barneys, though, experienced service people and discerning fashion buyers are vital.</p>
        <p>A common theme among departing employees was that they did not like the change to Mr. Questrom's more corporate manner from the family-style management dating back to the Pressman clan that owned Barneys before bankruptcy. The executive was repeatedly described as ''cold.'' He earned ill will, employees said, by demanding that employees pass basic retail math tests -- an exercise one former staff member described as ''degrading.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Questrom's effort could be defended as needed professionalism for a famously highflying, high-spending operation, staff members said they felt his bottom-line emphasis was not in line with Barneys overall luxury shopping experience. For example, he shifted Barneys away from its traditional emphasis on the most cutting-edge designers.</p>
        <p>''He was focused on business volume makers, not on nurturing the young and upcoming designers,'' said Emilia Fabricant, the former senior vice president responsible for the women's co-op and outlet division, who said she left because she was looking for a new creative environment. ''I thought he was maybe losing the future.''</p>
        <p>Another possible reason for staff departures is that Barneys is in no position to make a public offering of stock anytime soon. Since Barneys emerged from bankruptcy with an estimated value of $240 million, the market valuations of public retailers have collapsed. Most now trade at less than their annual sales. The Neiman Marcus Group, a luxury retailer on solid footing, had 1999 sales of $2.6 billion and has a market cap of roughly 60 percent of that amount. Given sales last year of $365 million and its distressed history, Barneys might have a public value of less than $200 million now.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Questrom's decision to move on may relate to the probability of little short-term benefit in his staying. When he joined, his employment agreement called for him to be paid entirely in stock. The company now says that he will get an undisclosed sum of stock as well as a salary for the year he was the top executive. He will remain chairman after joining Penney.</p>
        <p>Barneys' majority owners say they do not pay attention to short-term valuations and that theirs is a long-term investment.</p>
        <p>Back in its 1998 filing with the bankruptcy court, the company projected a net loss of $614,000 for the fiscal year ending January 2000 and net income of $5 million for the year ending in January 2001. Instead, the company posted a $5.3 million loss last year and expects just to break even this year.</p>
        <p>The shortfall is significant because Barneys has two important pools of debt that will start to come due in 2003. A person with knowledge of the balance sheet says the shortfall already endangers the company's ability to meet these obligations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Teitlebaum and Mr. Strumwasser vigorously deny they will have trouble meeting their debts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shull, who saw Barneys through bankruptcy and helped build its cash flow from a loss of $2 million a year to gains of $20 million yearly, and who also knows the company well, says that if it does not start meeting the original recovery plan it will not be able to pay its debts.</p>
        <p>''In order for them to make their financial commitments in two years, the company would have to achieve an EBITDA of over $70 million,'' he said, using the term that refers to earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization. ''At this stage, barring significant additional investment, that would seem to be a difficult challenge.''</p>
        <p>Editors' Note:  August 23, 2000, Wednesday  An article in Business Day on Aug. 5 reported on the performance of Barneys New York since its emergence from bankruptcy in January 1999. Critics of the departing chief executive, Allen L. Questrom, were quoted as saying that he had shifted the company away from its traditional emphasis on the most cutting-edge designers.</p>
        <p>In fairness, The Times should have included a response from the company. In a statement, the company has since said, ''Barneys today is every bit the fashion incubator that it has ever been.''</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, the article also referred imprecisely to the company's prospects for raising money through a stock sale. Concerns about Barneys and the industry's stocks over all rule out a share issue any time soon. They do not rule out ''a quick return to public ownership''; Barneys already has stockholders, although its shares are not traded regularly.</p>
        <p>The article also misspelled the names of the two firms that own a majority share of the company and misstated the number of senior employees who have resigned in the last three months. The firms are Bay Harbour Management, not Bar Harbour, and Whippoorwill Associates, not Whipporwill. Eight senior employees, not nine, have resigned in the last three months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Editors' Note: August 23, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Aug. 5 reported on the performance of Barneys New York since its emergence from bankruptcy in January 1999. Critics of the departing chief executive, Allen L. Questrom, were quoted as saying that he had shifted the company away from its traditional emphasis on the most cutting-edge designers.</p>
        <p>In fairness, The Times should have included a response from the company. In a statement, the company has since said, ''Barneys today is every bit the fashion incubator that it has ever been.''</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, the article also referred imprecisely to the company's prospects for raising money through a stock sale. Concerns about Barneys and the industry's stocks over all rule out a share issue any time soon. They do not rule out ''a quick return to public ownership''; Barneys already has stockholders, although its shares are not traded regularly.</p>
        <p>The article also misspelled the names of the two firms that own a majority share of the company and misstated the number of senior employees who have resigned in the last three months. The firms are Bay Harbour Management, not Bar Harbour, and Whippoorwill Associates, not Whipporwill. Eight senior employees, not nine, have resigned in the last three months.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
