<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tacoma Journal; Its Air Cleaned, Its Tech High, a City Rebounds</title>
    <meta content="Y05TAC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paper and Pulp</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fiber Optics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tacoma (Wash)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seattle (Wash)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Tacoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fiber Optics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paper and Pulp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5D7153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tacoma Journal; Its Air Cleaned, Its Tech High, a City Rebounds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>TACOMA, Wash., Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tacoma, Wash, once a gritty mill town living in the shadow of Seattle, is undergoing a renaissance and attracting high-tech companies; air, once famously foul, is now clean thanks to closing of pulp plants and cleanups; office rents and housing prices are roughly half Seattle's, and the traffic congestion that bedevils Seattle is not yet a problem; city also spent $100 million on fiber-optic network, making city attractive to technology companies; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When EssentialMarkets.com was looking for a place to establish headquarters a year and a half ago, executives at the Internet start-up thought first of the better-known software capitals of the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>''We sat down and the general feeling was, I guess we should look in Seattle, or maybe Bellevue or Redmond,'' recalled David M. Boitano, chief operating officer of the company, which helps businesses sell their products online. ''But the more we talked about Tacoma, the more we thought, Well, why not Tacoma? I mean, we're an Internet company. We can be anywhere.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When EssentialMarkets.com was looking for a place to establish headquarters a year and a half ago, executives at the Internet start-up thought first of the better-known software capitals of the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>''We sat down and the general feeling was, I guess we should look in Seattle, or maybe Bellevue or Redmond,'' recalled David M. Boitano, chief operating officer of the company, which helps businesses sell their products online. ''But the more we talked about Tacoma, the more we thought, Well, why not Tacoma? I mean, we're an Internet company. We can be anywhere.''</p>
        <p>The company's decision to locate here is just one piece in the much larger story of a renaissance for Tacoma, which long suffered from image problems as a gritty mill town living very much in the shadow of Seattle, its more glamorous sister 30 miles to the north. For years the noxious fumes from pulp plants here were so powerful that people in the region spoke of the ''Tacoma aroma.'' The city even seemed a bit of an afterthought in the name of the region's major point of entry, Seattle-Tacoma International Airport.</p>
        <p>But, lured by office rents and housing prices roughly half Seattle's, 100 high-technology companies have started up, relocated or expanded in the downtown area in the last two years, according to the city's Economic Development Department.</p>
        <p>Tacoma's revival is evident not just in the new companies coming here. The Tacoma Art Museum is expanding into a new building, and a  convention center three times the size of the existing one is rising downtown. The infamous smell is gone, a result of mill closings and cleanups, and the air is much cleaner, yielding spectacular views of Mount Rainier, the Olympic Mountains and Puget Sound that rival those in Seattle. And traffic congestion, a major complaint in Seattle and its high-tech suburbs to the east, is not a big problem here in this city of 187,000 people -- not yet, anyway.</p>
        <p>''If you're in Tacoma, you can still choose whether you want to live in an urban, suburban or rural area, and it simply doesn't take long to get around,'' said Eric Cederstrand, a developer here who has built or renovated several downtown buildings that are now home to high-tech companies. ''You can be out in the countryside in half an hour. In Seattle these days, it can take you half an hour to drive three blocks.''</p>
        <p>The revival can be traced in part to municipal officials' decision a few years ago to invest $100 million to stretch fiber-optic lines through much of the city, offering a high-speed data network attractive to technology companies. Tacoma's is one of the largest publicly owned telecommunications infrastructures in the nation, prompting the city to market itself with the theme ''America's No. 1 Wired City.''</p>
        <p>Tacoma also has an impressive stock of turn-of-the-century and Art Deco buildings that were largely in disrepair or even abandoned in recent decades, lending a ghost-town air to parts of downtown. Many of those are being renovated, offering the kind of ''fun, creative space,'' in Mr. Cederstrand's description, that lots of technology companies crave.</p>
        <p>One of his clients, Y3K Inc., a sort of Internet mall that helps small businesses sell products over the World Wide Web, is taking a floor and a half in a 1910 building downtown that has exposed brick walls, high ceilings, sandblasted beams and impressive views.</p>
        <p>Bill Cox, chief operating officer at Y3K, which will move from another Tacoma location to the renovated building this fall, said he discerned no problems in being a bit outside the Seattle-Redmond orbit that is home to giants like the Microsoft Corporation and Amazon.com, and to many lesser-known high-tech companies.</p>
        <p>''I think there are advantages here,'' Mr. Cox said. ''In Seattle, I think, there's a danger that a new company can feel lost in the shuffle. The feeling is, Well, it's just another Internet company. Here, it's a bigger deal. And there's a lot of support from the city.''</p>
        <p>Robert W. Grenley, chief executive of IDmicro, a 25-employee company based here that designs several kinds of wireless tracking devices, also said he saw advantages to being a ''bigger fish in a smaller pond.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grenley, who grew up in the area, said he would have ''laughed out loud'' if he had heard someone predict Tacoma's resurgence 15 years ago.</p>
        <p>''Downtown was decayed, empty, bombed-out,'' he said. ''Parts of it looked like Dresden or something. You were scared to be downtown. And it physically smelled bad. Today it's completely different. It's amazing what's happened here.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boitano, at EssentialMarkets, which is planning to grow to 250 employees from 105 over the next eight months and is leasing new office space downtown, said attracting people to the area was not a problem.</p>
        <p>''You put them in a car and drive them around,'' he said, ''show them the mountains, the water, the quality of housing that's available, the recreation. It's not a hard sell.''</p>
        <p>And Juli Wilkerson, the city's director of economic development, said there was plenty of talent available locally, noting that 22 percent of the work force from Tacoma and surrounding Pierce County still commuted to jobs in the Seattle area.  ''They would love to avoid that commute if they could,'' Ms. Wilkerson said.</p>
        <p>Nathan A. Wright, marketing director at IDmicro, moved from Seattle in February with some trepidation, but was pleasantly surprised.  ''Now I'd say, Why put up with the hassle? Here I've got a seven-minute commute. The views are great, there's a lot going on, but Tacoma's still got a small-town feel to it, too. I'd take this any day of the week.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
