<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bowing to the Middle, Keeping to the Right</title>
    <meta content="Y05REC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D7153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bowing to the Middle, Keeping to the Right</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Aug. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush uses his acceptance speech at Republican National Convention to create a synthesis new to Republican politics: conservative policies described in ways that his campaign believes swing voters will love; must hold conservative base though his policy proposals and then pick up the moderate middle through conciliatory language and willingness to speak about issues that Democrats have long dominated (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his convention speech, Gov. George W. Bush created a synthesis new to Republican politics: conservative policies described in ways that his campaign believes swing voters will love.</p>
        <p>So his $1.3 trillion, 10-year tax cut -- more sweeping than Congressional Republicans ever tried to push through -- became an effort to bring ''common sense and fairness to the tax code.'' His plan to divert some Social Security payroll taxes to private investment accounts amounted to giving ''American workers security and independence that no politician can ever take away.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his convention speech, Gov. George W. Bush created a synthesis new to Republican politics: conservative policies described in ways that his campaign believes swing voters will love.</p>
        <p>So his $1.3 trillion, 10-year tax cut -- more sweeping than Congressional Republicans ever tried to push through -- became an effort to bring ''common sense and fairness to the tax code.'' His plan to divert some Social Security payroll taxes to private investment accounts amounted to giving ''American workers security and independence that no politician can ever take away.''</p>
        <p>The language was positively Clintonian, but as many conservatives were quick to note, Mr. Bush had not actually changed any of the Republican Party's core principles -- from its opposition to abortion, to its support for large tax cuts, to its backing of a vast missile defense system, to its search for conservative Supreme Court justices.</p>
        <p>''He has packaged the traditional conservative positions with completely new covering,'' said Marshall Wittmann, a policy analyst at the Heritage Foundation. ''It's not necessarily a new Republicanism in quite the way that Clinton was a new Democrat.''</p>
        <p>This synthesis is central to Mr. Bush's effort to assemble a winning coalition. The Bush campaign wants to hold its conservative base through its policy proposals, and then pick up the moderate middle through Mr. Bush's conciliatory language and willingness to speak about issues that Democrats long dominated.</p>
        <p>The question for the fall campaign is whether Mr. Bush can convincingly keep up his balancing act as the Democrats try to home in on the details of policy proposals and his record back in Texas.</p>
        <p>Where Mr. Bush describes a tax cut that helps people at the bottom of the economic ladder, the Democrats see a tax cut that helps the rich. While Mr. Bush promises to strengthen Social Security, the Democrats say he could reduce retirement benefits. For all the time Mr. Bush spent delivering policy addresses this spring, a number of his proposals lack specifics.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Bush's record does not always square with his rhetoric. The man who showcased minorities all across his convention is, after all, the same candidate who, when he needed to recover from a defeat in the New Hampshire primaries, began his comeback campaign at a South Carolina university that banned interracial dating.</p>
        <p>''An informed voter is their worst nightmare,'' Douglas Hattaway, a Gore spokesman, said of the Bush campaign. The Democrats have already begun a barrage of ads trying to challenge Mr. Bush's commitment on issues like the environment.</p>
        <p>With the Democrats running against the high cost of prescription drugs, Mr. Bush's aides say they are already debating, for example, whether the Texas governor needs to draw up a plan to show how he would pay for prescription drug coverage. In his nomination speech, Mr. Bush said he would ''make prescription drugs available and affordable for every senior who needs them.''</p>
        <p>But he has never said how he would do that and has never devoted a major address to the issue. All he has done is speak approvingly of one bipartisan plan floated in Congress that would allow Medicare recipients to choose a plan with a prescription drug benefit. And when House Republicans passed their own prescription drug plan, Mr. Bush avoided taking a position on it.</p>
        <p>Or what about Social Security? On Thursday night, Mr. Bush sought credit for his willingness to take a stand on the issue. And he promised that he would strengthen the program ''for the greatest generation and generations to come.''</p>
        <p>But while he has called for some portion of the Social Security payroll tax to be diverted to individual investment accounts for young workers, he has not said what percentage. And he has been silent on a host of related issues, as well.</p>
        <p>He has not said whether he would raise the retirement age. Nor has he specified how much he would reduce the basic Social Security benefit to deal with the diminished payroll tax that would come into the system.</p>
        <p>One group of experts at the New Century Foundation, in a study disputed by the Bush campaign, has said that a plan like Mr. Bush's could result in future retirement incomes 20 percent lower than the levels projected under the current Social Security law.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's tax cut can also be portrayed in different ways. As he always does, Mr. Bush focused on how he would help the people at the bottom of the economic ladder. ''On principle, those in the greatest need should receive the greatest help,'' he said Thursday night. ''So we will lower the bottom rate from 15 percent to 10 percent and double the child tax credit.''</p>
        <p>What he did not say, but the Democrats do, is that like all tax cuts that sweeping, Mr. Bush's plan helps people at the top of the economic ladder the most. The Gore campaign, in a statement, calls Mr. Bush ''compassionate for the rich and conservative for everyone else.''</p>
        <p>In one case on Thursday night, Mr. Bush's language was designed to keep conservatives from becoming alarmed over one area of policy where he is directly breaking with his party's past.</p>
        <p>''One size does not fit all when it comes to educating our children,'' Mr. Bush said, ''so local people should control local schools.'' That was a version of one of his biggest applause lines on the campaign trail -- his insistence that he does not want to be the federal superintendent of education.</p>
        <p>But, in fact, he has proposed using federal funds as a lever to encourage states to give standardized tests in reading and math to all students in grades three through eight. Any state that refused would lose 5 percent of its education money.</p>
        <p>In this period of economic prosperity, the voters may never pay that much attention to the issues and may simply hear Mr. Bush's inclusive rhetoric and make judgments about whether they like the man.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Bush's advisers acknowledge that to some extent he is using issues simply to create the impression that he is a bold leader. The very fact, they say, that he has been willing to take stands that challenge the status quo makes voters think he is up to the job of president.</p>
        <p>''The issues form a composite of the candidate that's bigger than the issues themselves,'' said one senior adviser to Mr. Bush. ''We have and want to be seen as confronting the hard issues, not avoiding them, and doing so in ways that are innovative for a Republican to do.''</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Garin, a Democratic pollster, said that in recent focus groups, ''people did not feel that on the level of issues there is a lot at stake in this election.'' He found -- just as the Republicans are counting on -- that the voters are focusing much more on the character of the candidates and their moral authority.</p>
        <p>For now, at least, the Republicans are confident that Mr. Bush has made conservatism attractive. ''I don't think that Al Gore can win this election,'' said Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin. ''I think George Bush can lose it.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
