<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unilever Announces Plans to Reorganize Into Two Divisions</title>
    <meta content="Y05UNI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Unilever</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E4DA153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unilever Announces Plans to Reorganize Into Two Divisions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Aug. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Global consumer giant Unilever PLC announces major reorganization of top management; company will split into two divisions, one fucused on food products and one on consumer goods (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unilever P.L.C., the global consumer goods giant that has been on a buying spree in the United States, announced a major reorganization of top management today. The move would split the company into two divisions, one focused on food brands like Lipton Tea and Ragu spaghetti sauce and the other on consumer products like Dove soap and Elizabeth Arden cosmetics.</p>
        <p>The announcement revived speculation among analysts that the company, which has this year acquired Bestfoods, Slim-Fast and Ben &amp; Jerry's in the United States in a quest for growth, planned a full split into two companies. But, as it reported a higher-than-expected 7 percent rise in second-quarter profit, the company denied that it was taking its reorganization that far.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unilever P.L.C., the global consumer goods giant that has been on a buying spree in the United States, announced a major reorganization of top management today. The move would split the company into two divisions, one focused on food brands like Lipton Tea and Ragu spaghetti sauce and the other on consumer products like Dove soap and Elizabeth Arden cosmetics.</p>
        <p>The announcement revived speculation among analysts that the company, which has this year acquired Bestfoods, Slim-Fast and Ben &amp; Jerry's in the United States in a quest for growth, planned a full split into two companies. But, as it reported a higher-than-expected 7 percent rise in second-quarter profit, the company denied that it was taking its reorganization that far.</p>
        <p>''This is not a precursor to splitting Unilever, it is a realignment of the business bringing the strategic and operational functions closer,'' Mike Haines, a company spokesman, said.</p>
        <p>The split into two divisions capped a relatively fast-moving series of changes at the sprawling cumbersome giant. Its ability to change course has often been compared to that of a supertanker.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 22, the company announced a $5 billion program to reduce by 10 percent its 250,000 global work force, close 100 factories and winnow its 1,600 brands down to 400 top sellers.</p>
        <p>A few weeks later it began a series of acquisitions in the United States, committing a combined $2.6 billion in a single day in April to acquire Ben &amp; Jerry's Homemade and Slim-Fast Foods, before sealing its $20.3 billion takeover of Bestfoods in June. The Bestfoods deal was its biggest acquisition ever.</p>
        <p>By adding Bestfood brands like Knorr soups and Hellman's mayonnaise, Unilever hoped to strengthen profitability to catch up with rivals such as Danone of France.</p>
        <p>The organizational changes at Unilever, a British-Dutch corporation with headquarters in both Britain and the Netherlands, will not affect the positions of Unilever's two co-chairman, Niall Fitzgerald in London and Anthony Burgmans in Rotterdam, the company and analysts said.</p>
        <p>But, formalizing a de facto division of responsibilities, they will oversee two new divisions run by Patrick Cescau, currently chief financial officer in charge of food, and Keki B. Dadiseth, former head of Hindustan Lever -- a separately traded Indian division -- heading a new home and personal care products division. Mr. Dadiseth transferred to Unilever's management board in May to head a review of its management lineup.</p>
        <p>''They are putting people in charge of these categories with much more clout than ever before,'' said David Lang, an analyst with Investec Henderson Crosthwaite, calling the move a shift away from the power of Unilever's far-flung regional managers in Asia, the United States and Europe. The division between food and the home and personal care products, he said, is a traditional ''fault line'' at Unilever, which has tried several experiments in its management lineup over the last decade.</p>
        <p>While analysts generally welcomed the second-quarter rise in profitability, some expressed reservations about the company's ability to absorb a major management shuffle at the same time it is coping with its cost-saving measures and a string of acquisitions.</p>
        <p>''There is indeed'' a big agenda, said Mr. Haines, the company spokesman. But, he said, the management reorganization would only begin next January ''and will happen progressively in the course of next year.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the extent of Unilever's changes made a full split of the company into two new companies less likely, Mr. Lang at Investec said.</p>
        <p>''They have got such a huge agenda to put together -- the acquisitions and then to sort out their brand portfolio -- that stripping out at this stage seems premature,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The company said the acquisitions of Slim-Fast and Ben &amp; Jerry's had contributed to increased second-quarter profit, while the Bestfoods acquisition had yet to be completed.</p>
        <p>Profit from operations rose to 768 million euros, or $695 million, compared with 715 million euros one year earlier, ahead of analysts' forecasts. Operating margin, with one-time costs, grew to 13 percent from 11.8 percent in Europe and to 9.8 percent from 9 percent in the United States.</p>
        <p>Sales rose 3 percent to 10.9 billion euros, but most significantly, the sales of its top brands -- the 400 on which it wants to build its future -- rose 6 percent, with much of that coming from acquisitions, the company said. Some analysts said the  better-than-expected figures reflected one-time circumstances and would be hard to sustain.</p>
        <p>The higher-than-expected profit gain still trailed Danone, which recently reported a 12.6 percent increase in first-half profit.</p>
        <p>Unilever's share price closed at $:4.31, or about $6.45, on the London Stock Exchange, up 1 percent.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
