<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wave of Illicit Drugs Rolls In, And a Slice of Suburbia Reels</title>
    <meta content="05ECST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ecstasy (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brick Township (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ocean County (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Drug Enforcement Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gregorio, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Juliano, Brian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smuggling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0DE123CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wave of Illicit Drugs Rolls In, And a Slice of Suburbia Reels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>BRICK TOWNSHIP, N.J., Aug. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fast-growing suburb of Brick Township, New Jersey, finds itself hotbed of Ecstasy use; latest incident is arrest of Kenneth S Gregorio and Brian J Juliano for possession of 49,000 tablets of drug; Gregorio, 23-year-old Monmouth University student from Brick who was already on probation for drug arrests, hangs himself in police station; Ecstasy has been well-entrenched in New York City for years, but apparently arrived in Brick only last summer; DEA estimates that 2 million tablets are smuggled into US each week, mostly from Northern Europe, and 750,000 are sold in corridor from New York down to Jersey Shore; photos; map; Gov Christine Whitman last month signed law making Ecstasy possession and distribution crime on level of heroin or cocaine dealing, with long prison terms (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sign, in front of the high school here, is an unavoidable warning to anyone driving through this sprawling township on the Jersey Shore.</p>
        <p>''Deal Drugs in Our Communities and Go to Jail!'' it shouts in 6-foot-tall letters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sign, in front of the high school here, is an unavoidable warning to anyone driving through this sprawling township on the Jersey Shore.</p>
        <p>''Deal Drugs in Our Communities and Go to Jail!'' it shouts in 6-foot-tall letters.</p>
        <p>A graduate of Brick Memorial High School, Kenneth S. Gregorio probably often saw the sign, erected by the local prosecutor, as he drove to his mother's home or to the gym where he regularly worked out. Mr. Gregorio, 23, a Monmouth University junior on probation for two drug arrests, knew the warning was not an idle threat.</p>
        <p>Last Saturday night, shortly after he and his best friend, Brian J. Juliano, were arrested and charged with the possession and intended sale of 49,000 tablets of Ecstasy, Mr. Gregorio removed the drawstring from his sweat pants and hanged himself in a cell in the Neptune police station.</p>
        <p>Mr. Juliano, 23, who, under a newly toughened state law, faces a possible 20-year prison sentence for the intended distribution of Ecstasy, was released Thursday on $240,000 bail. His lawyer, Ray Scotto, said he was so traumatized by his arrest and the death of his friend that he checked into a hospital after his release. ''I don't think he knows what hit him,'' Mr. Scotto said.</p>
        <p>The same could be said for law enforcement officials in this fast-growing swath of New Jersey, which once thought itself far removed from urban trends -- like the dance-club culture that favors techno music and an amphetamine commonly referred to as E.</p>
        <p>''We've become a real hotbed for Ecstasy use,'' said Terrence Farley, director of the Ocean County Narcotics Strike Force. ''It's so pervasive, you can get it anywhere kids gather. I'd say it's the worst drug problem to hit here since the cocaine epidemic'' of the 1980's, he said.</p>
        <p>Those who monitor illegal drugs on the Jersey Shore say Ecstasy, which has been well entrenched in New York City for years,  truly arrived here only last summer. The federal Drug Enforcement Administration estimates that two million tablets are smuggled into the United States each week, largely from Northern Europe, and that 750,000 of those are sold and consumed in the corridor that extends from New York to bustling seaside resort towns like Belmar and Seaside Heights. It is an alluringly profitable drug, costing less than 50 cents per pill to synthesize and selling for about $20.</p>
        <p>Last weekend's haul, with a street value of $1.5 million, was the largest Ecstasy seizure ever made by a municipal police force, the authorities said. They said they think that most of the tablets were headed for the local clubs that flourish in the summer months, some attracting revelers as young as 13 to alcohol-free ''teen nights.''</p>
        <p>''This stuff is being gobbled up like candy,'' Mr. Farley said.</p>
        <p>Investigators are still trying to determine whether the two men operated their business alone or with others, but they said the two most likely distributed the pills to local dealers. Federal drug agents who analyzed the seized cache say they think it originated in the Netherlands or in Belgium.</p>
        <p>Described by friends as easygoing, gregarious and well known for a shared devotion to fitness, Kenneth Gregorio and Brian Juliano did not have reputations as vicious drug traffickers, although Mr. Gregorio had been convicted on drug-related charges before. ''Ken was more than a dime-bag dealer, but he wasn't a big-time dealer,'' said Sgt. James Riccio of the Brick Police Department.</p>
        <p>Classmates at Monmouth University, the two had transferred together from Ocean County Community College and spent much of their free time together. ''They seemed to be the best of friends,'' said Bob Chuva, manager of Work Out World in Tinton Falls, where both men exercised as often as six days a week. ''They rarely came in without the other.''</p>
        <p>After working out, the two men would often stop by Extreme Blendz, a juice bar, to chat and eat. Kevin Smith, who often served the men their protein shakes and chicken parmesan wraps, described them as seriously devoted to fitness.</p>
        <p>''They weren't partyers,'' he said. ''They were working out so hard and so into being healthy -- that's why I can't believe Kenny would do that to himself.''</p>
        <p>But according to prosecutors, Mr. Gregorio, voted ''most unpredictable'' by his high school class, had a self-destructive side. In 1996, a year after graduating from high school, he was arrested and charged with assaulting a Neptune police officer and resisting arrest. In July 1998, the police in Brick caught him with ster oids, a pound of marijuana and scales. Less than a year later, he was arrested again, this time with Ecstasy and $8,000 in cash.</p>
        <p>Greg Sakowicz, a spokesman for the Ocean County prosecutor, said Mr. Gregorio served 45 days in jail on the drug charges, all of it on weekends so the punishment would not interfere with his studies as a communications major. From time to time, he also worked as a construction worker and as an exotic dancer, according to family and friends.</p>
        <p>John J. Novak, a Lakewood lawyer who represented Mr. Gregorio on the drug charges, described him as a studious, well-mannered gentleman. ''He would bring his homework to court and do it in the hallway,'' he said. ''He was very ambitious, the kind of guy who might make it to the Fortune 500 if given a few breaks.''</p>
        <p>Law enforcement authorities have said that Mr. Gregorio's suicide  might have been an effort to avoid a potentially long prison term. Until last month, when Gov. Christine Todd Whitman signed a law making Ecstasy possession and distribution a first-degree crime, tantamount to holding or selling heroin or cocaine, those caught with large amounts of Ecstasy often served little or no jail time. Until 1986, the drug was not even illegal in most states.</p>
        <p>''I think he knew he was going away for a long time,'' said Sergeant Riccio, commander of the Brick Police Department's drug enforcement unit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Juliano, who grew up in nearby Howell, is a criminal justice major and did a brief internship with the West Long Branch Police Department. Last summer, a Neptune police officer stopped him for making an illegal U-turn and found $30,000 in his car. Mr. Novak, who also represented Mr. Juliano in that case, said the money was proceeds from the sale of a used car. The authorities failed to obtain an indictment, and  returned the money to Mr. Juliano.</p>
        <p>A tip led the authorities last week to a Neptune self-storage center, where they found a duffel bag stuffed with 30 pounds of Ecstasy. Mr. Juliano was arrested Saturday night after he came to the storage unit and tried to open the locker. Mr. Gregorio was arrested a short time later at his apartment in Asbury Park.</p>
        <p>The next day, detectives escorted a handcuffed Mr. Juliano to his Tinton Falls town house where, in a combination safe, they found $131,700 in cash, a loaded 9-millimeter gun and hollow-point bullets. A neighbor who saw Mr. Juliano arrive on Sunday said he looked as if he had been crying.</p>
        <p>The woman, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, said his was the only house on the block with an alarm system. ''People would come and go frequently,'' she said. ''Some would stay for a while and others would be gone in minutes.''</p>
        <p>On Thursday, about 80 people came to Mr. Gregorio's funeral at St. Martha's Church in Point Pleasant. In his eulogy, the Rev. Michael Manning told the story of the prodigal son, reminding the mourners that even sinners are loved by God. As he spoke, Mr. Gregorio's girlfriend  clutched his photograph and sobbed.</p>
        <p>As the sun set later that day, groups of teenagers strolled along the boardwalk in Seaside Heights and talked about their clubbing plans for the night. Most everyone had heard of the big Ecstasy raid, although few said it would change their attitude toward the drug or their ability to buy it.</p>
        <p>Outside Hunka Bunka, a club in Sayreville that was holding an event for clubgoers ages 13 to 18, hundreds of teenagers in Lycra and brightly dyed hair waited for their turn to be patted down by the bouncers. Since a recent string of Ecstasy arrests at the club, security has become unforgiving. Baggy jeans are banned and every pack of cigarettes is thoroughly searched.</p>
        <p>Still, many said they had no trouble buying Ecstasy outside and inside the club. Ben Coran, 18, of South Amboy, said he sold the tiny tablets from time to time. ''Like anything in life, if you want it, it can be done,'' he said. ''Deals on the inside are the best, but how the stuff gets in there is a trade secret.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
