<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Glavine Wins 7th Straight</title>
    <meta content="05NL.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NATIONAL LEAGUE: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DD123CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Glavine Wins 7th Straight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atlanta Braves defeat St Louis Cardinals, 6-4; other National League results noted (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Glavine, helped by a season-high four St. Louis errors, won his seventh straight start as Atlanta won, 6-4, last night in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Glavine (14-5), unbeaten since June 27 at Montreal, allowed three runs and six hits in six innings. He improved his record against St. Louis to 13-4, including 8-1 at Busch Stadium, where he is unbeaten in 10 starts since Aug. 20, 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Glavine, helped by a season-high four St. Louis errors, won his seventh straight start as Atlanta won, 6-4, last night in St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Glavine (14-5), unbeaten since June 27 at Montreal, allowed three runs and six hits in six innings. He improved his record against St. Louis to 13-4, including 8-1 at Busch Stadium, where he is unbeaten in 10 starts since Aug. 20, 1990.</p>
        <p>Atlanta, 15-5 since the All-Star Game break, had lost two straight for the first time since July 5-6. The Braves, who got a go-ahead, two-run homer from Andres Galarraga, have the major leagues' best record at 67-42. (AP)</p>
        <p>MARLINS 2, REDS 1: Mike Redmond hit a two-run double and pitcher Ryan Dempster emerged from his month-long slump last night to lead visiting Florida.</p>
        <p>Dempster (10-8) allowed six hits in eight innings for his first victory since July 1. Dempster, chosen for his first All-Star Game last month, had gone 0-4 with a no-decision in his last five starts.</p>
        <p>After Dempster escaped threats in the seventh and eighth, Antonio Alfonseca pitched the ninth for his major league-leading 33rd save in 36 chances.</p>
        <p>Redmond's second-inning double off Pete Harnisch (3-6) sent Cincinnati to its third consecutive loss, another setback to the Reds' hopes of catching St. Louis in the Central Division.</p>
        <p>The Marlins won their third in a row but lost the leadoff hitter Luis Castillo to a leg cramp in the third inning. Castillo, who leads the majors with 46 steals, beat out a grounder for an infield single, then hobbled and sat down holding his right hamstring.</p>
        <p>Harnisch allowed eight hits in eight innings as he got his first loss since July 5. Since rehabilitating a weak shoulder, Harnisch has gone 3-2 with a 2.49 earned run average. (AP)</p>
        <p>ASTROS 7, EXPOS 6: Chris Truby homered twice and Daryle Ward hit a three-run shot for host Houston, which has a franchise-record 83 homers at home this season.</p>
        <p>Truby hit a two-run homer in the third and Ward hit his 15th homer as Houston took a 5-4 lead. Truby added a solo shot, his third, to tie the score at 6 in the sixth inning.</p>
        <p>The Astros, who moved from the spacious Astrodome to homer-friendly Enron Field this season, broke the record of 82 set in 1998 with 32 home games remaining this season.</p>
        <p>Houston starter Chris Holt left in the fourth inning after getting hit in the left cheek by a line drive off the bat of Peter Bergeron.</p>
        <p>Holt left the field under his own power and was taken to a hospital for X-rays, which were negative. He was diagnosed with a bruised cheekbone.</p>
        <p>Holt allowed five runs and seven hits in three and two-thirds innings with three strikeouts. He left leading, 5-4, but Wayne Franklin gave up an R.B.I. single to Wilton Guerrero.</p>
        <p>Jason Green (1-0) pitched one and two-thirds scoreless innings for the victory. Octavio Dotel got four outs for his fifth save.</p>
        <p>The Expos lost for the ninth time in 10 games. (AP)</p>
        <p>ROCKIES 8, PHILLIES 1: Todd Helton went 4 for 4 with two homers and four runs batted in, sending Philadelphia to its fourth straight loss and giving host Colorado just its seventh victory in 29 games.</p>
        <p>Kent Bottenfield (0-1), acquired Sunday from Anaheim for Ron Gant, allowed five runs and 10 hits in six innings in his 100th career start.</p>
        <p>Helton hit a solo homer in the first and a two-run shot in the eighth to raise his National League-leading average to .380.</p>
        <p>Julian Tavarez (7-2) allowed one run and four hits in six innings to get the victory.</p>
        <p>DODGERS 2 BREWERS 1: Eric Karros hit a tie-breaking single in the eighth inning and Kevin Brown matched his career high with 12 strikeouts as the Dodgers won at home for their third straight victory.</p>
        <p>Mark Grudzielanek greeted reliever Juan Acevedo (1-4) with a leadoff single in the eighth and advanced on a groundout before Shawn Green was intentionally walked. Karros followed with a single that went into center field, scoring Grudzielanek.</p>
        <p>Mike Fetters (4-1) relieved with two outs in the eighth and watched catcher Todd Hundley throw out Marquis Grisson at second on his first pitch, then finished for the win.</p>
        <p>Brown was working on a four-hitter and his 18th career shutout until the Brewers tied the score in the eighth on Raul Casanova's double and Marquis Grissom's single.</p>
        <p>RELAFORD IS TRADED: Philadelphia Phillies shortstop Desi Relaford was traded yesterday to the San Diego Padres for a player to be determined, becoming the fourth opening-day starter to leave the team in the past three weeks.</p>
        <p>Relaford, 26, was hitting .221 with 3 home runs and 30 runs batted in over 83 games for the Phillies this season. He also committed a league-leading 24 errors.</p>
        <p>Taking Relaford's spot on the roster is the All-Star catcher Mike Lieberthal, who was activated after spending two weeks on the disabled list with a sprained left ankle. Lieberthal is hitting .300 with 14 home runs and 60 R.B.I. over 82 games this season. (Bloomberg News)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL LEAGUE: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
