<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Cone's Return, Gooden Goes to Bullpen</title>
    <meta content="05CONE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gooden, Dwight</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0D7153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Cone's Return, Gooden Goes to Bullpen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees pitcher Dwight Gooden moves out of starting rotation into bullpen; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the reliever Ramiro Mendoza out indefinitely and David Cone returning to the rotation today, Dwight Gooden will move into the Yankees' bullpen for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>The left-hander Allen Watson was activated from the disabled list last night and assumed Mendoza's spot on the roster after the right-hander was placed on the 15-day disabled list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the reliever Ramiro Mendoza out indefinitely and David Cone returning to the rotation today, Dwight Gooden will move into the Yankees' bullpen for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>The left-hander Allen Watson was activated from the disabled list last night and assumed Mendoza's spot on the roster after the right-hander was placed on the 15-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>Orlando Hernandez will be activated to start against the Seattle Mariners tomorrow, and the left-hander Randy Choate will most likely be sent to Class AAA Columbus to make room for El Duque.</p>
        <p>After Mendoza returned from the disabled list last week, he pitched one-third of an inning against the Minnesota Twins on July 29. Manager Joe Torre noticed that about half of the pitches Mendoza threw were changeups -- a sign that perhaps there was something wrong with the right-hander's arm.</p>
        <p>After playing catch a couple of times with the pitching coach Mel Stottlemyre, Mendoza acknowledged that his shoulder was bothering him.</p>
        <p>Mendoza has asked to be examined next week by James Andrews, a noted surgeon, and Torre acknowledged that he had no idea when Mendoza could be back, or whether the lingering shoulder problem might be something worse than bursitis.</p>
        <p>''It's so tough, because he wants to pitch and he doesn't want to admit that it's bothering him, and he feels he owes it to the team to go out and pitch when he's hurt,'' Torre said. ''It doesn't do him any good to do that.''</p>
        <p>Torre is switching Gooden to the bullpen because the manager has six starters for five spots with the return of Cone, not because of the need for another middle reliever. But the Yankees do need someone to pitch consistently in middle relief. Jason Grimsley has performed that job effectively most of the year, but he has struggled badly lately.</p>
        <p>''Doc is insurance, basically,'' said Torre, who told Gooden of his decision this afternoon, getting agreement from Cone's longtime teammate.</p>
        <p>Cone, skipped in the rotation and sent to Florida to work on his mechanics last Friday, was back in the Yankees' clubhouse yesterday. He indicated that he had made adjustments to his mechanics that enabled him to be in a better position to throw the ball. He compared his tinkering to a hitter trying to shorten a long swing that drags through the strike zone.</p>
        <p>''I feel really good about it,'' Cone said. ''Throughout the year, I've been searching for something that works. It's easy to get lost without your mechanics.''</p>
        <p>Cone said he did not feel good about himself when he first arrived in Florida last week to work with Billy Connors, the team vice president and pitching instructor.</p>
        <p>''Wednesday and Thursday went really well,'' Cone said of his workouts, ''and I feel a heck of a lot better than when I went down there.''</p>
        <p>Cone, who went to lunch and dinner with George Steinbrenner, the team's principal owner, was not aware of Torre's dictum that Gooden will pitch out of the bullpen in the days to come.</p>
        <p>''I'm thinking short term,'' Cone said. ''I'm just trying to win a game tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>Cone has not been credited with a victory since April 28.</p>
        <p>Strawberry to Undergo Tests</p>
        <p>Darryl Strawberry will have surgery next week to determine the extent to which cancer has spread in his body. Recent tests have indicated that some cancer, stemming from the colon cancer he had in 1998, may have moved to his abdomen.</p>
        <p>''You always expect the worst when they take those tests,'' Joe Torre said. ''It's the only way you can deal with it. It's sad. The upside to it is that there are so many ways they can treat that. He's still young, and he's in good shape, aside from the surgery he's going to have to have, and hopefully that weighs in his favor.''</p>
        <p>Strawberry is currently out of baseball, serving a suspension.</p>
        <p>Season Ends for Top Prospect</p>
        <p>The 2000 season is officially over for first baseman Nick Johnson, one of the Yankees' best prospects.</p>
        <p>Johnson, who had a soft tissue injury in his wrist in spring training and has been disabled since, has been sent home in a cast and will not return to Florida until Sept. 6.</p>
        <p>The Yankees are hoping Johnson will recover in time to play in the Arizona Fall League and perhaps in winter ball.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
