<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South African Townships' Poor Brave a Deadly Journey Just to Get to Work</title>
    <meta content="Y05BUS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cape Town (South Africa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cauvin, Henri E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa/Cape Town</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxicabs and Taxicab Drivers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E3DB153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South African Townships' Poor Brave a Deadly Journey Just to Get to Work</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRI E. CAUVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cauvin, Henri E</byline>
      <dateline>KHAYELITSHA, South Africa, Aug. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Buses plying black townships south of Cape Town, South Africa, are regularly shot at and firebombed in a campaign of urban terror apparently orchestrated by criminal elements in the rival minibus taxi industry, who believe their busiess is threatened by the big bus company and the cheaper fares it offers the poor; drivers and passengers have little choice but to run the danger; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every day when Oscar Picane heads off to work, he leaves behind a wife who worries she will never see him again. He is not a police officer or a soldier or a miner, or even a gangster. He is a bus driver here in this sprawling township south of Cape Town, doing a job that has become, for the moment at least, the deadliest occupation in a country with no shortage of dangerous jobs.</p>
        <p>Buses like the one Mr. Picane drives for Golden Arrow Bus Services are under fire here in the Cape Flats, as the townships are collectively known. Stoned, shot at and firebombed, the drivers are the targets of a campaign of urban terror apparently orchestrated by criminal elements in the rival minibus taxi industry, who believe their business is threatened by the big bus company and the cheaper fares it offers the poor here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every day when Oscar Picane heads off to work, he leaves behind a wife who worries she will never see him again. He is not a police officer or a soldier or a miner, or even a gangster. He is a bus driver here in this sprawling township south of Cape Town, doing a job that has become, for the moment at least, the deadliest occupation in a country with no shortage of dangerous jobs.</p>
        <p>Buses like the one Mr. Picane drives for Golden Arrow Bus Services are under fire here in the Cape Flats, as the townships are collectively known. Stoned, shot at and firebombed, the drivers are the targets of a campaign of urban terror apparently orchestrated by criminal elements in the rival minibus taxi industry, who believe their business is threatened by the big bus company and the cheaper fares it offers the poor here.</p>
        <p>The attacks and acts of intimidation, which began five months ago and now number nearly 60, have so far killed four drivers and two passengers, wounded dozens and shaken a community caught between the brazen violence and the limp response of the local and national governments.</p>
        <p>At stake is a share of the scarce resources of a desperate, long-neglected place that, like so many in South Africa, was founded to house black workers as far as possible from the white people they work for.</p>
        <p>Some of the worst violence unfolded late last week with a driver and a passenger dying in a spate of attacks. This week, under increasing pressure, the authorities took the most significant steps so far to curb the violence. More than a dozen suspects were arrested, and hundreds of police officers drawn from elite units around the country were sent in.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Picane, 32, who has been a driver for Golden Arrow for almost four years, has heard all the talk before -- the forceful denunciations of the violence and the promises of swift, decisive action.</p>
        <p>Little changes, and the attacks continue. Indeed, late tonight, a disabled bus was firebombed in Nyanga, a neighboring township. No one was injured, but that is scant comfort to Mr. Picane.</p>
        <p>When he leaves for work each morning shortly before 5, he does so driven by the same economic realities that leave his passengers with little choice but to board his bus, as they begin doing shortly after 5:30 a.m.</p>
        <p>''Of course I am scared,'' he said as he guided his 68-seat bus down the N2 Highway, through the fog-dusted darkness toward Khayelitsha. ''But I am working for my family, so I have to work. My mother and father, they don't know why I'm still working. But I'm the breadwinner. Even my wife, she was crying, 'Why are you still going to work?' ''</p>
        <p>But in a country where millions  are unemployed and the economy is barely growing, work is work, and a job is not easily relinquished, even if risking your life is the only way to keep it. David Tyantsi, a 50-year-old father of five, said that after the latest violence, his family begged him to quit.</p>
        <p>''I told them jobs are scarce,'' he said as he and a few other drivers huddled in the early morning cold during a break at a vacant lot that serves as a terminal in one township neighborhood. ''I haven't got anywhere to go to get a job.''</p>
        <p>Michael Konana, as a passenger, is in the same situation. A factory machinist in Durbanville, north of here, he spends about $5 a week on his bus ticket. Taking a taxi to work would cost him another $3 to $4, a dear premium for someone like Mr. Konana, who makes about $40 a week. ''I'm scared, but I've got no other choice, because the buses are cheaper than the taxis,'' he said a few minutes after boarding Mr. Picane's bus, which was northbound for Bellville.</p>
        <p>A seemingly endless sea of shanties southeast of Cape Town, Khayelitsha lies miles away from the cities and towns where Mr. Konana and most of his neighbors work. Transporting them to Cape Town and the other urban centers has always been a lucrative and competitive enterprise.</p>
        <p>But rarely, if ever, has the fare battle between taxis and buses been so violent -- and part of that could be attributed to a recent national government effort to reshape the bloated, poorly regulated taxi industry.  Tactics common among rival taxi operators are now in some instances being turned on the bus company, a convenient target for taxi drivers' fear and anger with government plans.</p>
        <p>Taxi fleets are to be trimmed by tens of thousands, and an aging collection of vans is to be replaced with larger, more suitable minibuses. A crackdown is also planned on the unlicensed operators who have saturated the market.</p>
        <p>Depending on whom you ask, the response from the authorities has been inadequate, inept or both. The provincial government and the national government have argued about who is ultimately responsible for controlling the situation, even as the violence persists and the perpetrators disappear.</p>
        <p>Negotiations between the bus company and the taxi industry have been fruitless, and hours after the two most recent killings, they broke down altogether. The local minister of security quit last week, saying the national government, which controls the police and army, had given him little power to act.</p>
        <p>The handling of the crisis has left the bus drivers indignant. ''The national government had to intervene long ago,'' said Yaasien Abrahams, the shop steward for the South African Transport and Allied Workers Union.</p>
        <p>A driver for 13 years and shop steward for the last 9, Mr. Abrahams says he is a marked man. He and his family were in hiding for three weeks, he said, after the authorities learned that an attempt was likely to be made on his life. He resurfaced a few days ago and now wears a bulletproof vest.</p>
        <p>''I'm not sure if it's safe for me now, but I don't know how long a man can run,'' he said. ''Unfortunately, these people negotiate through the barrel of a gun.''</p>
        <p>Like most drivers and passengers,  Mr. Abrahams is not white, and he wonders how the crisis might otherwise have been handled here in the only province where whites have retained control of the local political machine.</p>
        <p>''I'm positive that if this had happened in Sea Point or the suburbs,'' he said, referring to the fashionable neighborhood on Cape Town's waterfront, ''it would have been resolved. But it's only black people who are dying.''</p>
        <p>Until something changes, people like Elizabeth Letsie will have to live with fear. ''We were on the bus that was shot last Thursday,'' Ms. Letsie, a domestic worker, said as she sat with her 13-year-old son, Emmanuel, one row from where they were when shots rang out last week. ''We were sitting right there. We were both shaking. We were afraid, but we have no choice.''</p>
        <p>A man of the townships himself, Mr. Picane knows how much his neighbors depend on him and his colleagues, and that, too, brings him back each day. Every so often, he pulls his white-faced wristwatch from his jacket pocket and steals a quick look. Shootings or no shootings, a schedule is a schedule.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
