<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Job Growth Slows, Suggesting Fed May Not Raise Interest Rates</title>
    <meta content="Y05ECO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFD9153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Job Growth Slows, Suggesting Fed May Not Raise Interest Rates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US companies add fewer jobs than economists anticipated during July, reducing chances that Federal Reserve will raise interest rates at its late-August meeting; unemployment rate remains unchanged at 4 percent; private-sector payrolls grow by 138,000, but overall employment falls 108,000; economists welcome possibility of gradual slowing of economy; charts; tables (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American companies added fewer jobs in July than economists had expected, reducing the chances that the Federal Reserve will raise interest rates when it meets later this month, analysts said.</p>
        <p>In a sign that economic growth is slowing, the unemployment rate remained unchanged at 4 percent in July as private-sector payrolls grew by 138,000, about half the number that most analysts had predicted. Over all, employment fell by 108,000 last month because of the large number of temporary government workers who finished collecting census data in June, the Labor Department reported yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American companies added fewer jobs in July than economists had expected, reducing the chances that the Federal Reserve will raise interest rates when it meets later this month, analysts said.</p>
        <p>In a sign that economic growth is slowing, the unemployment rate remained unchanged at 4 percent in July as private-sector payrolls grew by 138,000, about half the number that most analysts had predicted. Over all, employment fell by 108,000 last month because of the large number of temporary government workers who finished collecting census data in June, the Labor Department reported yesterday.</p>
        <p>''This is an economy that has gone from spectacular growth to steady and solid growth,'' the labor secretary, Alexis M. Herman, said.</p>
        <p>Manufacturing companies and restaurants accounted for more than two-thirds of the job growth last month, and other sectors -- like real estate, construction, and insurance -- hired relatively few new workers. In a possible sign that businesses expect sales to slow, the number of people working for temporary-help and job-placement concerns fell, and overall growth in that sector so far this year is now less than half what it was in 1999.</p>
        <p>''The economy is slowly losing altitude,'' said James E. Glassman, a senior economist at Chase Manhattan Bank.</p>
        <p>The employment numbers offered the first broad picture of the economy's performance in July, and economists predicted that the Federal Reserve's policy-making committee would decide on Aug. 22 that it did not need to raise interest rates to slow growth. Last week, Alan Greenspan, the Federal Reserve chairman, told members of Congress that the jobs data, as well as coming reports on inflation and productivity, would have a significant effect upon the action the committee took.</p>
        <p>Since June 1999, the Fed has raised its benchmark short-term interest rate six times, to 6.5 percent, from 4.75 percent, in an attempt to ward off inflation.</p>
        <p>The one sign of inflationary pressures in yesterday's report was a mild one: hourly wages for production employees, who make up about three-fourths of the work force, rose 6 cents, to $13.76, continuing at a pace that is faster than in late 1999. Since the start of the year, wages have risen at an annual rate of 4 percent, up from 3.2 percent in the second half of last year.</p>
        <p>Other labor costs, like those for benefits and bonuses, appear to be growing more quickly, said Ken Matheny, a senior economist at Macroeconomic Advisers, a consulting firm in St. Louis. The government will report official figures on compensation next week.</p>
        <p>But productivity gains still appear to be strong, allowing companies to increase their workers' pay without raising prices to maintain profits, analysts said. That, combined with the moderate job growth in the private sector, has left both economists and investors confident that the Federal Open Market Committee will not raise interest rates later this month, much as it refrained from doing so at its most recent meeting in June.</p>
        <p>''This report was the final nail in the coffin,'' said William Dudley, the chief domestic economist at Goldman, Sachs. The investment bank told clients yesterday that it was changing its forecast and no longer expects a rate increase in August or in the remainder of the year.</p>
        <p>All of the major stock market indexes closed higher yesterday, as investors' confidence about the unlikelihood of an interest-rate increase outweighed tepid profit announcements in the drug and semiconductor industries.</p>
        <p>Some economists think a rate increase is still possible, if not in August then at the following meeting of the committee, in October. Factory orders and consumer confidence have both risen recently, and the gross domestic product grew at a surprisingly fast 5.2 percent annual pace in the second quarter. But most analysts agree the odds of action by the Fed has fallen in recent weeks. Outside of gas prices, inflation remains slight, and recent statistics on consumer spending and home sales have also suggested an economy that is slowing as it has entered its 10th year of expansion.</p>
        <p>At the end of June, almost 90 percent of economists surveyed by Macroeconomic Advisers thought the Fed would raise interest rates in August or October. By last week, the number had fallen just below 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's report depicted a job market that has changed little over the last nine months, as employment growth has slowed. Private-sector payrolls did fall significantly in May, but modest increases during the other months of the year have made up for the decline. The unemployment rate has stood between 3.9 percent and 4.1 percent since October, and the portion of Americans over the age of 16 who are working was the same as it had been in July 1999: 64.2 percent. Over all, 134.7 million people hold jobs.</p>
        <p>The unemployment rate for black Americans fell two-tenths of a percentage point last month, to 7.7 percent, but remains slightly higher than it was earlier in the year. The rates for whites and Hispanics were roughly unchanged.</p>
        <p>Analysts had expected companies to make up for almost all of the drop in employment caused by the end of work for census takers. Instead, job growth in most industries was slight or nonexistent in July. After seasonal adjustments, the number of people working for hotels grew slightly, to 1.93 million, for example. The number of employees at day-care centers (763,000), savings banks (240,000) and coal mines (79,000) all stayed approximately level.</p>
        <p>Even the increase in manufacturing jobs -- one of the largest since the early 1990's -- may be less robust than it seems, said James F. O'Sullivan, an economist at J. P. Morgan.</p>
        <p>Manufacturing payrolls actually fell by about 100,000 in July. However, because of a mathematical formula that the Labor Department uses to smooth seasonal work force fluctuations, the report said that the number rose by 46,000. In other words, only after statisticians had discounted the usual change between June and July did manufacturing employment appear to increase.</p>
        <p>But data from the last few years suggests that manufacturing employment may vary less in the summer than it once did, Mr. O'Sullivan said. If that is the case, the seasonal formula could erase much of the apparent gain in manufacturing in August.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
