<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mexico's Best Drops a Queen To Turn a Declarer's Head</title>
    <meta content="05CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220074"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Contract Bridge League</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DE153CF936A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="456" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mexico's Best Drops a Queen To Turn a Declarer's Head</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott Bridge column on players to be named to American Contract Bridge League Hall of Fame in Anaheim (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some of the greatest players in the history of the game will be named to the American Contract Bridge League's Hall of Fame in Anaheim, Calif., on Thursday. In the living category, Sidney Lazard and Ira Rubin have been elected. Among deceased players, Lou Bluhm, Harry Fishbein and Charles Solomon are being honored. The Von Zedtwitz Award for deceased players will go to Meyer Schleifer, and the Blackwood Award, for various contributions to the game, to George Rosenkranz.</p>
        <p>Rosenkranz, 83, has long been Mexico's leading player, and is the author of 10 books on the game. His 11 national titles include the Vanderbilt Knockout and the Spingold Knockout twice each, and his team reached the Bermuda Bowl semifinal in 1983.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some of the greatest players in the history of the game will be named to the American Contract Bridge League's Hall of Fame in Anaheim, Calif., on Thursday. In the living category, Sidney Lazard and Ira Rubin have been elected. Among deceased players, Lou Bluhm, Harry Fishbein and Charles Solomon are being honored. The Von Zedtwitz Award for deceased players will go to Meyer Schleifer, and the Blackwood Award, for various contributions to the game, to George Rosenkranz.</p>
        <p>Rosenkranz, 83, has long been Mexico's leading player, and is the author of 10 books on the game. His 11 national titles include the Vanderbilt Knockout and the Spingold Knockout twice each, and his team reached the Bermuda Bowl semifinal in 1983.</p>
        <p>His professional work as a research chemist specializing in steroids changed the world. In 1951, he and a colleague synthesized cortisone and, even more important, the active ingredient in what became the birth control pill.</p>
        <p>In the diagramed deal, played in December, Rosenkranz held the East cards. He and his partner were fortunate in one way but unfortunate in another. His opponents could and should have bid to six spades, a much better slam that would have succeeded. South was at fault after his partner had made a fourth-suit bid of three clubs: He should have clarified his distribution by jumping to four spades at his third turn.</p>
        <p>The actual six-heart contract was distinctly inferior. South could expect to lose a club trick and at least one trump trick. However the fates had favored the declarer by giving East a doubleton heart queen. The chance of this, or of the same holding in the West hand, was 27 percent.</p>
        <p>Rosenkranz succeeded in confusing the issue and thwarting the fates. He made his doubleton queen look like a singleton queen. A diamond was led to the ace, and a diamond was returned. When South won and cashed the heart ace, the queen appeared immediately on his right.</p>
        <p>Now South was at the crossroads. Was East trying to deceive him? In general it is right to assume that the opponents are playing normally rather than deceptively. So South swallowed the bait. He finessed the heart eight, going down in a slam that would have made easily against routine defense.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
