<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Holocaust Memoir Is Reissued, No Longer Designated Fiction</title>
    <meta content="12MEMO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Continuum International Publishing Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Littner, Jakob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Journey Through the Night (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E0DB1038F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Holocaust Memoir Is Reissued, No Longer Designated Fiction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Continuum International Publishing Group reissues Jakob Littner memoir, Journey Through the Night, Holocaust novel describing stark tale of his hairbreadth escape from Nazis that was long thought to be work of fiction; book was originally published as Jakob Littner's Notes From a Hole in the Ground; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was, critics said, one of the more harrowing Holocaust novels, a prominent German writer's stark tale of a Jewish stamp dealer's hairbreadth escapes from the Nazis, in the end hiding beneath the cellar of a Ukrainian.</p>
        <p>But to Jakob Littner, that was no novel. That was his life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was, critics said, one of the more harrowing Holocaust novels, a prominent German writer's stark tale of a Jewish stamp dealer's hairbreadth escapes from the Nazis, in the end hiding beneath the cellar of a Ukrainian.</p>
        <p>But to Jakob Littner, that was no novel. That was his life.</p>
        <p>Now a professor's sleuthing has stripped away a veneer of fiction from the work, ''Jakob Littner's Notes from a Hole in the Ground,'' published in 1992 by the German writer Wolfgang Koeppen, and given the book new standing as fact.</p>
        <p>In truth, said the professor, Reinhard Zachau, chairman of the German department at the University of the South in Sewanee, Tenn., Koeppen appropriated Littner's memoir after assisting its first brief publication in Germany in 1948. Littner died in New York in 1950. Koeppen, who had achieved fame in the 1950's with a trilogy of novels about Germany's postwar struggles, died in 1996.</p>
        <p>Now, largely based on Dr. Zachau's research, Littner's original book has been published in English, and once again as nonfiction and as his own work. Under his original title, ''Journey Through the Night,'' it was issued in June by the Continuum International Publishing Group of New York and London.</p>
        <p>''While there have been several Holocaust 'memoirs' that have been unmasked as fictions,'' Continuum said in a statement, ''this is perhaps the first time that a Holocaust 'novel' turns out to be a fabrication based minutely on a genuine Holocaust memoir.''</p>
        <p>In response to complaints from Littner's survivors in 1993, Thomas Sparr, an editor at Koeppen's publisher, Judischer Verlag, a Jewish subsidiary of Suhrkamp Verlag, one of the largest German publishing houses, wrote that the company ''never denied but rather confirmed that the book contains'' Littner's ''Notes.'' Koeppen ''gave the notes an adequate form,'' he said, and acknowledged Littner in the title. But the designation of novel was later dropped.</p>
        <p>Yet scholars and Littner's relatives fault Koeppen's book as misleading. ''There was gross misrepresentation involved in calling the work a novel,'' said Dr. Zachau, who tracked down Littner's original manuscript. ''And then there was something more subtle, the perpetuation of changes Koeppen made 40 years earlier when he took liberties with a straightforward if terrifying narrative to make it into something more literary and mythic, something more aesthetic.''</p>
        <p>A Hungarian-born Polish citizen, Littner was living with his family in Munich when the war sent him fleeing back to Poland and then to Zbaracz in Ukraine, where the SS was killing Jews. His son and daughter-in-law were trapped in the Warsaw ghetto and sent pleas for food until the letters abruptly stopped. His wife and sisters were killed by the Germans. But Littner was secretly aided by Christine Hintermaier, his Christian, partner in the stamp business.</p>
        <p>Littner; the woman who would become his second wife, Janina; and another son, Richard, found refuge in a vault under the cellar of a Ukrainian's house, for which they paid extravagantly, in one case with gold bridgework that Littner tore from his mouth. After nine months all but buried alive, the three  were liberated in March 1944.</p>
        <p>Littner emigrated to New York in 1947, his manuscript in the hands of a Munich publisher. Koeppen later said he was retained to work on the book in exchange for food packages from Littner, although when the book, ''Notes from a Hole in the Ground,'' came out in a small printing in Germany in 1948, only Littner's name was on it as the author.</p>
        <p>But Koeppen had made changes. Where Littner had issued a plea for forgiveness and written, ''It is not for people to judge others,'' Koeppen -- in Littner's voice -- had gone further, calling Nazism's crimes ''beyond human judgment,'' a liberty that one critic called ''Aryan chutzpah.''</p>
        <p>The texts of the 1948 and 1992 books were the same, Dr. Zachau said, but Koeppen had added an introduction claiming authorship. ''I ate American rations and wrote the story about the suffering of a German Jew,'' he wrote. ''In doing so it became my story.''</p>
        <p>Skeptical, Professor Zachau tracked down a relative of Littner's in Maryland, Kurt Nathan Grubler, who had a copy of Littner's original manuscript and authorized its publication. Mr. Grubler's name appears on the cover of the new book; he is credited as its translator and editor.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Koeppen, as a German gentile and literary talent, felt the need to buttress Littner's memoir, said Professor Zachau. But he added, ''Probably the best way to come to grips with Nazism would simply have been to let Jakob Littner speak for himself.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
