<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quick Trips Through The Imagination</title>
    <meta content="MB031237" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Vacation" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD81138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quick Trips Through The Imagination</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin recommends novels and short-story collections that can transport summertime reader to farway places (special section, Vacation) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUMMER makes us think of childhood. It means school is over. It means vacation time, trips to the beach, seersucker and T-shirts and sundresses. It also means, to many of us, novels and short stories -- fiction that offers rapid transport to other places, while allowing us to put down the highlighter and pencil, shrug off facts and figures and theories, and lose ourselves in a writer's imaginative world.</p>
        <p>Here, then, are some novels and short-story collections to pack in the beach bag or the backpack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUMMER makes us think of childhood. It means school is over. It means vacation time, trips to the beach, seersucker and T-shirts and sundresses. It also means, to many of us, novels and short stories -- fiction that offers rapid transport to other places, while allowing us to put down the highlighter and pencil, shrug off facts and figures and theories, and lose ourselves in a writer's imaginative world.</p>
        <p>Here, then, are some novels and short-story collections to pack in the beach bag or the backpack.</p>
        <p>''The Chekhov Omnibus: Selected Stories,'' edited by Donald Rayfield.  Translated by Constance Garnett.  The young Chekhov once observed that writing came as easily to him as eating pancakes, and his astonishing literary production would transform both the modern theater and the writing of modern fiction. Though his earliest tales are little more than quick, offhand sketches seasoned with slapstick humor, his mature stories evince the psychological complexity and atmospheric detail that distinguish his best-known plays.</p>
        <p>''Freedomland,'' by Richard Price. With this novel, Richard Price took the sort of story that usually inspires made-for-TV movies and created a genuine literary thriller -- a novel that holds a dark mirror up to America in the Age of O.J. The book is reminiscent of the much publicized 1994 news story about Susan V. Smith, who made the phony assertion that her two sons, whom she  murdered, had been abducted by a black carjacker. But it quickly opens out into a harrowing examination of  the political and social repercussions that such a story can have on a community. The novel not only captures the nervous arc of a crime investigation, but also makes palpable the media storm that often follows in its wake.</p>
        <p>''Headlong,'' by Michael Frayn.  Published last year and shortlisted for Britain's 1999 Booker Prize, Michael Frayn's ''Headlong'' is, at once, an antic satire of England's chattering classes and a clockwork-perfect farce about the folly of human nature. The folly concerns an impulsive philosophy professor who allows greed, snobbery and simple hubris to lead him astray -- all for the sake of a painting that may or may not be a long-lost masterpiece by Pieter Bruegel.</p>
        <p>''The Stories of Vladimir Nabokov,'' edited by Dmitri Nabokov.  This volume of 65 stories -- which range from ''The Wood-Sprite,'' published in a Russian emigre newspaper in Berlin in 1921, to ''Lance,'' published in The New Yorker in 1952 -- treats the reader to a glittering recapitulation of Nabokov's glorious career. His fascination with the alchemical transactions between life and art, his obsession with memory, his own experience of expatriation and his love of games and puzzles -- all the themes of his best-known novels can be found here, distilled into these lapidary, gemlike tales.</p>
        <p>''White Teeth,'' by Zadie Smith.  Zadie Smith's remarkable debut novel is a big, populous, multicultural production that is part Dickens, part Salman Rushdie, part Martin Amis, and altogether original. Set in a cacophonous contemporary London of curry shops, pool halls and cheap hair salons, ''White Teeth'' recounts the adventures of two World War II veterans and their dysfunctional families with rollicking good humor. At the same time, it unfolds into a  meditation on the varieties of historical experience and the effect that cultural and familial history can have on the shape of someone's life.</p>
        <p>MICHIKO KAKUTANI</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
