<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Short Stories by Writers Who Got Away; Oklahoma City Was O.K.</title>
    <meta content="MB022643" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Vacation" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oklahoma</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solomon, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oklahoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0D81138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Short Stories by Writers Who Got Away; Oklahoma City Was O.K.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Solomon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Solomon, Deborah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deborah Salomon article on a family vacation in Oklahoma; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>My husband grew up in Oklahoma City and he recently persuaded me to accompany him on a trip back home. Oklahoma? Must we, dear? It's one of those states of indeterminate character, officially Southwestern yet possessing neither the mountainous grandeur of the West nor the fabled charms of the South. It does not conjure up any images, except, perhaps, for a long-ago Broadway musical in which the corn was as high as an elephant's eye, lyrics that could lead one to think that elephants were an Oklahoma specialty.</p>
        <p>We made the trip with our two sons and, curiously enough, it turned out to be one of my favorite vacations. I won't pretend that the accommodations were quaint. We stayed at the Waterford Marriott Hotel, a squat, red-brick edifice whose grounds previously belonged to an orphanage, as a sign out front attested. (Couldn't they just say ''Welcome''?) Our room overlooked a cemetery and, when I sat down on the terrace to read, the winds were so fierce my newspaper blew away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>My husband grew up in Oklahoma City and he recently persuaded me to accompany him on a trip back home. Oklahoma? Must we, dear? It's one of those states of indeterminate character, officially Southwestern yet possessing neither the mountainous grandeur of the West nor the fabled charms of the South. It does not conjure up any images, except, perhaps, for a long-ago Broadway musical in which the corn was as high as an elephant's eye, lyrics that could lead one to think that elephants were an Oklahoma specialty.</p>
        <p>We made the trip with our two sons and, curiously enough, it turned out to be one of my favorite vacations. I won't pretend that the accommodations were quaint. We stayed at the Waterford Marriott Hotel, a squat, red-brick edifice whose grounds previously belonged to an orphanage, as a sign out front attested. (Couldn't they just say ''Welcome''?) Our room overlooked a cemetery and, when I sat down on the terrace to read, the winds were so fierce my newspaper blew away.</p>
        <p>So, what, exactly, did I love about this city? For one thing, it was fascinating to be in a place where the word ''cholesterol'' never crosses anyone's lips, despite a local predilection for eating a piece of beef at least once every three hours. One day we had beef sausage at breakfast, burgers for lunch and beef ribs for dinner. Here is a state where either you're driving around looking at cows -- or eating them.</p>
        <p>Our trip had other highlights as well. We visited the National Cowboy Hall of Fame and purchased a souvenir bag of red dirt. Moreover, we browsed in the corner antiques shops, where we did not find Queen Anne chairs, but discovered a brand of Oklahoma-made dishware that is guaranteed not to break even if you drop it from the top of a tall building.</p>
        <p>But mostly I remember the Sonic Drive-In, the sublime coziness of sitting in a rented car on a spring night, savoring our vanilla shakes and (beef time again!) cheeseburgers. I have no idea why this memory should endure while so many others have fallen away, but that's the strange thing about vacations. You can read all the travel brochures in the world and organize your trip down to the last costly detail, but hey, y'all, there's just no way to plan those moments when happiness descends.</p>
        <p>Deborah Solomon, an art critic, is at work on a biography of Norman Rockwell.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Deborah Solomon, an art critic, is at work on a biography of Norman Rockwell.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
