<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Paris, Bistros Still Draw a Full House</title>
    <meta content="12BIST$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000726T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Benoit (Paris Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">L'Ami Louie (Paris Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chez Georges (Paris Restaurant)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">La Grille (Paris Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Apple, R W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA1038F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Paris, Bistros Still Draw a Full House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By R. W. APPLE Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Apple, R W Jr</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>R W Apple Jr article on four of his favorite bistros in Paris--Benoit, Chez George, La Grille and L'Ami Louis--and several others worth visiting; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE word ''bistro'' is used as promiscuously in Paris as the word ''deli'' is used in New York.</p>
        <p>There are Greek bistros, Chinese bistros, Mexican bistros, cafes that call themselves bistros and steak-frites joints that call themselves bistros. Bistros are hot, and every quick-franc artist in town wants to cash in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE word ''bistro'' is used as promiscuously in Paris as the word ''deli'' is used in New York.</p>
        <p>There are Greek bistros, Chinese bistros, Mexican bistros, cafes that call themselves bistros and steak-frites joints that call themselves bistros. Bistros are hot, and every quick-franc artist in town wants to cash in.</p>
        <p>Bistros in the true sense -- the name comes from a Russian word meaning quick -- were riding high when I first ate my merry way around the French capital in the 1960's. Then, you could still find most of the places that A. J. Liebling had haunted 25 years before. But they soon went into decline, and when a revival came in the 1980's, it produced restaurants that were bistros in name only. The decor was right -- lacquered wood storefronts, bare floors, even zinc bars -- but not the food.</p>
        <p>Happily, Paris is a conservative city, slow-changing and resistant to ''progress,'' and quite a few of the genuine articles survive. Lovers of the sturdy, copious, grandmotherly cooking that marks a true bistro pass favorite addresses from hand to hand, like Russians in the Communist era exchanging samizdat manuscripts. The guidebooks may forget, but die-hard bistro owners and clients, Frenchmen and foreigners alike, tend the flame.</p>
        <p>I count myself among the more avid members of that fraternity, and my wife, Betsey, is no less keen. For us, Darroze and Taillevent and Gagnaire are shrines to be visited occasionally, not crammed into a single week's visit to Paris; bistros are for relaxed, restorative, everyday chow.</p>
        <p>Much of it is based on humble ingredients, transformed into culinary gold by the alchemy of slow simmering with wine and herbs. This is the food of artisans, not artists, of guardians of tradition, not trailblazers.</p>
        <p>Pot-au-feu, stuffed cabbage, navarin d'agneau, poulet au vinaigre -- dishes like those have been and still are the mainstays of bistro cooking. So are frogs' legs and snails, tripe and kidneys, and old-school desserts like oeufs a la neige (floating island) and tarte Tatin.</p>
        <p>No proper bistros have designer lighting, none have a maitre d'hotel and none have Muzak. You go to eat and drink, not to impress a client or pitch woo.</p>
        <p>On our last few visits to Paris, Betsey and I have revisited most of the places on my bistro list. Here are up-to-date reports on four of the top spots, with briefer notes on others where we enjoyed ourselves.</p>
        <p>BENOIT  (20 rue St.-Martin, Fourth Arrondissement, 011-33-1-42-72-25-76).</p>
        <p>Like a woman who wears too much makeup, Benoit has an air of slightly suspicious glamour. Is the velvet too red, the brass too shiny? No, it's la vraie chose, genuine down to the last potted palm.  Founded in 1912 by Benoit Martray, it has been faithfully tended for four decades by  Michel Petit, his grandson.</p>
        <p>That's M. Martray in the photo on the back wall, a beret perched jauntily on his head and double chins deployed proudly beneath it. His face is creased by a big smile. Jean, the handsome, cheeky waiter, smiles, too.</p>
        <p>M. Petit is one of the last bistrotiers who buy Beaujolais in casks and bottle it in their own cellars, in bottles identified only by a tiny neck label. It is always a good choice.</p>
        <p>The food follows tradition, up to a point. In small, judicious ways, M. Petit constantly strives for lighter, more contemporary versions of the classics, with no discernible loss of flavor. There is more parsley and less garlic in the snail butter; the hearty, gelatinous veal knuckle is served with a barely thickened tomato sauce; beef cheeks, with a more delicate texture, go into a stew rather than heftier cuts.</p>
        <p>But you need not fear asparagus ice cream or foie gras with rhubarb or some other abomination committed in the name of innovation.</p>
        <p>The cassoulet is ideal winter fare. In hot summer weather, a sumptuous dish of jellied fish -- a kind of cold bouillabaisse -- sometimes appears on the menu. Summer is the season as well for the masterstroke among the restaurant's desserts, a luscious charlotte of raspberries and wild strawberries. It is more than enough, all by itself, to justify the star that the Michelin guide gives Benoit. No other bistro in Paris is so honored.</p>
        <p>CHEZ GEORGES  (1 rue de Mail, Second Arrondissement, 011-33-1-42-60-07-11).</p>
        <p>Bernard Brouillet's menu is still produced on an old Metro liquid duplicator, in the red-purple script that used to be synonymous with bistros, and the long, skinny room is still lined with oversize mirrors.</p>
        <p>This is a busy, happy place, with a fine, rosy glow, where old friends celebrate and new friends are made. Everyone talks to everyone else, glad to be tucking into the seared onglet (hanger steak), a tasty, chewy slab of meat showered with minced shallots, or the excellent offal -- grilled veal kidneys with bearnaise sauce, calf's liver topped with a thick rasher of bacon in the  English style, or veal sweetbreads in a mushroom cream sauce.</p>
        <p>The service is handled by charming women who have been around since some of the bankers on whom they wait at lunch were tellers. One of the many small pleasures of Georges is watching them fillet the sole (a house specialty, served with a white wine sauce) with the deftness of neurosurgeons.</p>
        <p>This is a neighborhood of temptations. Kenzo is two steps away, Dehellerin's cookware store two more. The greatest of all, however, is the bistro's wine list, packed with old Burgundies and Bordeaux at prices half of those you would pay in a two- or three-star gastronomic temple. Not cheap, mind you -- something 10 to 25 years old from Dujac or Comte Armand will set you back $75 to $250 -- but very reasonable for what you get.</p>
        <p>How do they do it? Some of the most famous growers, whose wines are carefully rationed, have been supplying Chez Georges, and eating there, for decades. The Marquis d'Angerville nipped in for lunch just a few days before our most recent visit.</p>
        <p>LA GRILLE  (80 rue du Faubourg-Poissonniere, 10th Arrondissement, 011-33-1-47-70-89-73).</p>
        <p>''The egg is from the country, Monsieur,'' the jolly waiter said, urging me to order the oeuf en gelee as a first course. It was, and it was cooked to perfection, the yellow-gold yolk a little more than soft-boiled. A small scallop of ham and a half-dozen leaves of tarragon also helped to transform something that might have been banal into a work of aspic art.</p>
        <p>That's the way it is at La Grille. Order a frisee salad and the curly lettuce comes to the table with its crown of bacon strips still steaming from the pan, as it should be and seldom is. Skinny little lamb chops are delectable, says Betsey, the lamb expert.  Chocolate mousse, so dark and rich it looks almost black, is exquisitely under sweetened.</p>
        <p>But La Grille's centerpiece is the tawny turbot, with a lattice of dark bars expertly seared into its flesh by la grille under the baleful eye of the chef and owner, Yves Cullerre, he of the silver handlebar mustache. It comes with a tart, ivory-hued beurre blanc. In addition, you should order the little discus of sliced potatoes baked with butter, plus the house Sancerre from Domaine Tabordet.</p>
        <p>There is something profoundly reassuring about the dozens of coats of dark red lacquer on the walls, the circular staircase leading up to the loos, the lace and embroidery at the windows and on the banquettes. Here, you sense, the modern world is held at bay.</p>
        <p>''We are the last dinosaurs,'' the dumpling-shaped Mme. Cullerre told us on our last visit, ''and we want to do things this way to the end of our days.''</p>
        <p>L'AMI LOUIS  (32 rue du Vertbois, Third Arrondissement, 011-33-1-48-87-77-48).</p>
        <p>In all the years I have been visiting this little bistro, on a seedy side street in a banal neighborhood, it has never been listed in the Michelin guide. The flaking dirt-brown paint on the walls, the worn-out floor tiles and the tired tin ceiling evidently fall short of the red book's decor requirements.</p>
        <p>French critics love to trash the place, not least because it has so many American clients and because it charges such high prices; the two things are probably not unrelated.</p>
        <p>When I started going there, more than 25 years ago, L'Ami Louis had very few American clients, and no one spoke any English.  Antoine Magnin, then considered the city's master rotisseur, or roaster, was still at his post, red kerchief tied round his neck, and Louis Gadby, now the patron, was a young  waiter. The wine list was much slimmer (so was I) and cheaper. Nobody dreamed of calling weeks in advance for a table, as they do now.</p>
        <p>It all makes me feel like Methuselah. But every qualm vanishes with the first magnificent mouthful of the juicy roast chicken, the tender leg of baby lamb or the enormous rib of beef. They are unmatched anywhere. The notably garlicky snails, scallops and potato cake can, I admit, wreak havoc on the  digestion, but for me at least, they're worth the heartburn.</p>
        <p>One reason for the high prices, of course, is prime ingredients. All over Paris this spring, restaurateurs told me that French morels were almost unobtainable. They had been forced, several confessed, to substitute inferior Turkish mushrooms. Not M. Gadby: he showed us a big basket full of the fattest morels imaginable, which came from Compiegne, just outside Paris. Cooked with plenty of cream, they tasted even better than they looked. Well they might have; they had cost 800 francs a kilo, or more than $50 a pound.</p>
        <p>Two tips: Order one portion for two, and go not for dinner but for lunch, especially on Sunday, when the clientele are often all French.</p>
        <p>ALLARD  (41 rue St.-Andre-des-Arts, Sixth Arrondissement, 011-33-1-43-26-48-23).</p>
        <p>Some of the soul went out of this most famous of bistros, once the holder of two Michelin stars, when Andre Allard died and his wife, Fernande, retired. But after years in gastronomic purgatory, it is once again full at lunch and dinner (now served until 11:30) almost every day. The resurrection is the work of Claude Leyrac, an experienced bistrotier, who has had the sense to keep many old favorites on the list: the world's best cucumber salad, crunchy and creamy; the famous duckling with olives; the lip-smacking beef and veal and lamb stews; and a baked custard my mother would have envied.</p>
        <p>CARTET  (62 rue de Malte, 11th Arrondissement, 011-33-1-48-05-17-65).</p>
        <p>When Marie-Antoinette Cartet ran this eight-table bistro near the Place de la Republique, it was open only for lunch; in the evenings, she told me, she liked to go to the theater. When Marie-Therese and Raymond Nouaille took over 20 years ago, they started serving dinner and installed a new kitchen.  But the menu is immutable. No one in Paris serves silkier brandade de morue, a blend of salt cod, potatoes, garlic, cream and olive oil. And what could be homier than Cartet's boeuf a la ficelle, a fillet suspended in a pot of boiling stock and simmered gently, or its lemon tart, as warmly golden as the summer sun?</p>
        <p>JOSEPHINE  (117 rue du Cherche-Midi, Sixth Arrondissement, 011-33-1-45-48-52-40).</p>
        <p>Extravagant flower displays provide islands of color in Jean-Christian Dumonet's two sober dining rooms, and luxury abounds on his carte. He makes a specialty of truffles, in nonpareil omelets and ragouts, and he combines perfectly cooked langoustines with a tangle of herbs and lettuces in a rich  man's salad. But most dishes can be ordered in half portions, which helps hold  down costs and calories. At lunch on Wednesdays, the classic leg of lamb with white beans should not be missed; other days I favor the dark, winy boeuf bourguignon. And mon Dieu, the wines! Two large, closely printed pages list red Bordeaux stretching back to 1928 at eminently fair prices.</p>
        <p>CHEZ SAVY  (23 rue Bayard, Eighth Arrondissement, 011-33-1-47-23-46-98).</p>
        <p>Founded in 1923, Savy, an island of culinary modesty amid oceans of gastronomic pretension in one of the city's richest neighborhoods, has roots in the Auvergne, the deeply rural center of France. The varied local clientele, including personalities from nearby television stations, order the petit farcou, a fat, chlorophyll-laden pancake of spinach, chard, leeks and herbs, and the slow-cooked shoulder of lamb, falling off the bone. A jug of Cahors and prime regional cheeses like Cantal and Roquefort will make you purr. Eat in the narrow front room, called le wagon (dining car) by habitues.</p>
        <p>LA TOUR DE MONTLHERY  (5 rue des Prouvaires, First Arrondissement, 011-33-1-42-36-21-82).</p>
        <p>This is a set designer's vision of a bistro, with sausages dangling from the ceiling, red-checked cloths on the tables and customers with Gauloises dangling from their lips. Beaujolais is drawn straight from a barrel at the bar. I don't know which are more Rabelaisian -- the cheerful rabble you'll find at the next table, or the vast portions of mutton with white beans, pigs' feet and profiteroles. A survivor of the old Halles market district, La Tour is open 24 hours every weekday. Pot-au-feu every Thursday; service with just the right touch of impertinence every day.</p>
        <p>CHEZ LA VIEILLE  (1 rue Bailleul, First Arrondissement, 011-33-1-42-60-15-78).</p>
        <p>Adrienne Biasin, the old woman for whom this hole in the wall was named, has retired, but her bistro is bubblier, better and more generous than ever, thanks to the new owner, the chic Marie-Josee Cervoni. A Corsican, she has added tastes of her homeland to the menu, including a raw ham reminiscent of Smithfield. You order a main course (perhaps the beef stew with carrots) and help yourself to the half-dozen starters and half-dozen desserts served family style.  Among the former, a boar terrine, well-seasoned stuffed cabbage and a refreshing mussel and tomato salad stand out; among the latter, prunes in red wine. Drink the peppery St.-Joseph from the Rhone.</p>
        <p>Which is to say nothing of Chardenoux, and Aux Charpentiers, and Chez Rene, and Moissonier. . . .</p>
        <p>RASPBERRY CHARLOTTE  Adapted from Benoit, Paris  Time: 1 1/4 hours, plus draining and chilling</p>
        <p>1 3/4 cups fromage blanc (see note)  8 cups raspberries</p>
        <p>1/2 cup plus 1 tablespoon superfine sugar  1 3/4 teaspoons gelatin  1 3-ounce package soft ladyfingers (about 24).</p>
        <p>1. Place a fine sieve lined with cheesecloth over a bowl, and drain fromage blanc at room temperature for 3 hours, or in refrigerator for 8.</p>
        <p>2. In a blender, food processor or food mill, combine 4 cups of raspberries with 1 tablespoon sugar and 1 tablespoon water. Let sit  about 10 minutes. Puree until smooth.</p>
        <p>3. Transfer puree to a sieve placed over a bowl. Push puree through sieve until it yields 1 cup. Discard solids.</p>
        <p>4. In a dish, combine gelatin with 2 tablespoons water, and let sit for 10 minutes. In a saucepan, heat  1/4 cup raspberry puree until nearly boiling. Add gelatin mixture; stir to dissolve. Remove from heat, and cool.</p>
        <p>5. In a mixing bowl, whisk together drained fromage blanc with remaining raspberry puree and remaining sugar. Whisk in cooled gelatin-raspberry mixture.</p>
        <p>6. Gently fold 2 cups whole raspberries into fromage blanc mixture. Transfer mixture to a 1-quart mold, cover with plastic, and refrigerate overnight or up to 2 days.</p>
        <p>7. To assemble charlotte, invert chilled mold over a plate (dip mold in hot water to help it release). Arrange ladyfingers along sides of the charlotte. Decorate top with remaining 2 cups whole berries.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Note: fromage blanc is available in specialty markets.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 26, 2000, Wednesday  An article on July 12 about Paris bistros misspelled the name of a noted cookware store near the bistro Chez Georges. It is E. Dehillerin, not Dehellerin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 26, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article on July 12 about Paris bistros misspelled the name of a noted cookware store near the bistro Chez Georges. It is E. Dehillerin, not Dehellerin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
