<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Merckx on the Tour: 'It's Over'</title>
    <meta content="12TOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abt, Samuel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1D81038F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Merckx on the Tour: 'It's Over'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL ABT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abt, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>REVEL, France, July 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tour de France bicycle race continues; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The Tour is finished,'' Eddy Merckx decided today. He found no dissenters. Who could disagree with a man who won five Tours de France and 520 other races? Who, furthermore, could disagree after watching Lance Armstrong break a lot of legs, as the riders put it?</p>
        <p>''He did a very strong ride, an exceptional ride,'' Merckx said, referring to Armstrong's facile demonstration of power Monday in the Pyrenees. ''It's over.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The Tour is finished,'' Eddy Merckx decided today. He found no dissenters. Who could disagree with a man who won five Tours de France and 520 other races? Who, furthermore, could disagree after watching Lance Armstrong break a lot of legs, as the riders put it?</p>
        <p>''He did a very strong ride, an exceptional ride,'' Merckx said, referring to Armstrong's facile demonstration of power Monday in the Pyrenees. ''It's over.''</p>
        <p>''He's not only the best rider but the most serious. He races all season, not just one month, like so many others.''</p>
        <p>That statement was a dig at those, unlike the Merckx of old, who care exclusively about victory in the Tour de France. ''Lance has won his second Tour. What he did yesterday nobody has done for years.''</p>
        <p>Armstrong, the Texan, and Merckx, the Belgian champion of the 1970's, long one of Armstrong's heroes, are close friends. That did not appear to influence Merckx's judgment, which is universally shared.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen anybody climb so swiftly,'' Raymond Poulidor, who finished second in the Tour a handful of times in the days of Jacques Anquetil and Merckx, said this morning.</p>
        <p>Only Armstrong is still reserved about the outcome. ''Form is a funny thing -- it comes slowly and goes away quickly,'' he said Monday. Today he said that he had balked at having Champagne served at the team dinner after the Pyrenees stage because he finished second, not first.</p>
        <p>''If we win in Paris, there will be Champagne,'' he said, ''but Paris is a long way off.'' The Tour ends there on July 23.</p>
        <p>Another former champion who raved about Armstrong's performance was Greg LeMond, the other American who won the Tour and who is in France for a reunion of his old Z team, with which he finished first in the world's greatest bicycle race in 1989 and 1990. ''I haven't seen anybody dominate a race like that, ever,'' said LeMond, who also won the Tour in 1986.</p>
        <p>He watched the mountain stage on television. In it, Armstrong, the leader of the United States Postal Service team, built an overall lead of more than four minutes over his rivals. Merckx watched it in person, offering commentary for Belgian television then and his opinions today in Revel as he awaited the finish of the 11th of 21 daily stages.</p>
        <p>With the rivals that Armstrong has buried in the standing awaiting possible revenge on the next big climb on Thursday, two low-ranked riders were given their freedom Tuesday. The two, Santiago Botero, a Colombian with Kelme in 45th place, and Erik Dekker, a Dutchman with Rabobank in 61st place, made the most of it.</p>
        <p>Bolting away at Kilometer 14 of the 218.5-kilometer (135-mile) jaunt, the two riders got as far as 14 minutes 44 seconds ahead.</p>
        <p>That was serious. Although Dekker started the day more than 26 minutes behind Armstrong, Botero was 17:40 behind. With the 14:44 lead, the Colombian was in second place over all on the road, the realm of dreams. In addition, he is a good climber, unlike Dekker, and could be a factor in the four days in the mountains ahead.</p>
        <p>Led by United States Postal Service, the pack began chasing and the lead descended to manageable proportions. At the finish, Dekker was an easy first in the sprint, completing the stage in 5:05:47, a speed of 43 kilometers an hour (27 miles an hour).</p>
        <p>His victory in the second stage of the 87th Tour also increased his lead in the race for the most aggressive rider. Botero collected a bundle of points over six small climbs en route to friendly Revel and rose from fifth to second place in the competition for king of the mountains.</p>
        <p>The vanguard of the pack finished 4:51 behind the two leaders, with a larger group 14 seconds slower.</p>
        <p>Armstrong held his overall lead of 4:14 over Jan Ullrich, a German with Telekom and the 1997 Tour champion, in second place and 5:10 over Christophe Moreau, a Frenchman with Festina, in third place. Botero jumped to 30th place over all and Dekker to 47th.</p>
        <p>The stage began in Bagneres de Bigorre in the foothills of the Pyrenees and wended east through placid countryside, with long vistas of sunflower fields and pastures spotted with horses and cattle. The narrow, curvy road passed through avenues of plane trees and tidy villages.</p>
        <p>In short, the tourist's France. But any tourist coming here should pack earmuffs and an umbrella. The weather was cold -- 14 degrees Celsius (57 Fahrenheit) near noon -- windy and intermittently rainy. Summer seems to have skipped France this year.</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
