<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y12BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EED81038F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: ACQUITTED IN STUDENT ATTACK  A military court acquitted a former Tehran police chief of ordering an attack on a student dormitory that led to a week of pro-reform protests. The verdict brought immediate criticism from students. Farhad Nazari and 17 subordinates were charged with injuring scores of students and killing one in the attack last July. Two defendants were found guilty. ''Such rulings will lead to social insecurity and people will lose their confidence in the judiciary,'' said Ibrahim Sheik, a student leader, a sentiment echoed by other students.</p>
        <p>Nazila Fathi (NYT)</p>
        <p>IRAN: KHATAMI PLEA TO U.S.  President Mohammad Khatami, on a visit to Germany, urged the United States to take the next step toward reviving diplomatic relations with Tehran. ''You can be sure that when the United States has the key in its hand, it will not give it away,'' he said on German public television. He said he recognized a ''new turn'' in Washington, but that the shift did not go far enough.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: ACQUITTED IN STUDENT ATTACK  A military court acquitted a former Tehran police chief of ordering an attack on a student dormitory that led to a week of pro-reform protests. The verdict brought immediate criticism from students. Farhad Nazari and 17 subordinates were charged with injuring scores of students and killing one in the attack last July. Two defendants were found guilty. ''Such rulings will lead to social insecurity and people will lose their confidence in the judiciary,'' said Ibrahim Sheik, a student leader, a sentiment echoed by other students.</p>
        <p>Nazila Fathi (NYT)</p>
        <p>IRAN: KHATAMI PLEA TO U.S.  President Mohammad Khatami, on a visit to Germany, urged the United States to take the next step toward reviving diplomatic relations with Tehran. ''You can be sure that when the United States has the key in its hand, it will not give it away,'' he said on German public television. He said he recognized a ''new turn'' in Washington, but that the shift did not go far enough.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>WEST BANK: CRITIC ORDERED FREED  The Palestinian High Court ordered the release of a professor jailed for criticizing Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian rights group LAW said. The group said the court in Ramallah ordered the release of Abdel-Sattar Qassim, but a LAW activist said he did not know when the order would be carried out. Professor Qassim, a political science lecturer, was among 20 people who signed a petition in November accusing Mr. Arafat of sanctioning corruption in his administration. He was detained, released and jailed again in February.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>AUSTRIA: PANELISTS TO BE NAMED  The European Court of Human Rights will announce today the names of three people who will examine Austria's rights record. They will concentrate on minority rights, refugees and immigrants and the political nature of Jorg Haider's far-right Freedom Party. The review could lead to an end to Austria's political isolation within the European Union. Possible candidates are former President Martti Ahtisaari of Finland; the former European Commission president, Jacques Delors; former Prime Minister Carl Bildt of Sweden and the onetime European Union human rights envoy to Bosnia, Elisabeth Rehn.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>TURKEY: KURDS HELD  The police detained 15 Kurdish activists, the latest in a series of arrests of members of the country's main legal Kurdish party, an official from the party said. Although the People's Democracy Party has campaigned for a negotiated end to the country's 15-year-old Kurdish conflict, Turkish authorities have long suspected it of acting in league with Abdullah Ocalan's armed separatist rebels.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: ROYAL CENTENARY  Britain began a formal celebration of the 100th birthday of the Queen Mother with a full dress service of thanksgiving at St. Paul's Cathedral attended by the British royal family, royalty from other European countries, Prime Minister Tony Blair and other senior politicians and uniformed men and women from military units with which she is associated. The Queen Mother, whose birthday is Aug. 4, took the cheers of thousands of well-wishers from the steps of the church.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>MEXICO: 19 EX-AIDES HELD  Authorities arrested 19 men who served as municipal officials in Mexico City during the 1994 to 1997 tenure of former Mayor Oscar Espinosa Villareal, charging them with crimes ranging from embezzlement to abuse of authority. They were among 75 civil servants sought in a corruption investigation led by the city's top prosecutor, who has asked the Congress to impeach Mr. Espinosa, now the tourism minister, on fraud charges.</p>
        <p>Sam Dillon (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN: CURBS ON SHARIF'S WIFE LIFTED  The police have ended the house arrest in Lahore of the wife of the ousted prime minister, Nawaz Sharif. Kulsoom Sharif was prevented from leaving her house after she staged a nine-hour standoff with the police on Saturday in an attempt to start an antigovernment march. The Lahore police chief said ''Kulsoom is free to go anywhere.''</p>
        <p>(AP, Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>SRI LANKA: MORE KILLINGS  Tamil Tiger rebels killed four civilians in a mortar attack near a Buddhist temple in northeast Sri Lanka hours after the military began an operation in northern Jaffna, the government said. The attack came hours after the military said it had destroyed a Tigers' bunker line at Ariyalai near Jaffna town. The government said 62 rebels had been killed and 118 wounded in that attack.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>PACIFIC</p>
        <p>FIJI: 'BLUE LAGOON' ISLE SEIZED  Supporters of the rebel leader George Speight seized a resort where ''The Blue Lagoon'' was filmed, worsening Fiji's 54-day government crisis with the first attack on a foreign-owned facility. The rebels later released 40 tourists staying at the 500-acre Turtle Island resort owned by an American, Richard Evanson. In Suva, the capital, rebels freed 9 of the 27 government members they took hostage on May 19. The prime minister was not among those freed.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>ETHIOPIA, ERITREA: U.N. ROLE  A group of United Nations liaison officers will arrive in Ethiopia and Eritrea by the end of next week, in the first stage of a peacekeeping operation to enforce the cease-fire that the two nations signed last month, a senior United Nations military official said in Asmara, the Eritrean capital. But the official, Maj. Gen. Timothy Ford, said it would be several months before the full force was deployed.</p>
        <p>Ian Fisher (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
