<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Short Stories by Writers Who Got Away; Lost and Found in July</title>
    <meta content="MB022335" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Vacation" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D81138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Short Stories by Writers Who Got Away; Lost and Found in July</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Ford</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ford, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Ford article relates a memory of childhood travel (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most of my life's travel has been distinctly of the little ''t'' variety. Not the kind you come home and give a speech about at the Explorers Club but, rather, travel viewed as an activity to be borne for its value of connecting (or, if you like, separating) two acts of at least temporary staying.</p>
        <p>From my childhood, travel always meant being on the way to someplace: the Mississippi Delta -- that big, flat cottonfield passing the car window on our Christmas trip from Jackson to Little Rock; the Everglades -- the big, murky watery part out there on the left as we drove to the opening of the Fontainebleu Hotel in Miami Beach in 1955. (''Vacation'' in my family most often meant driving with my father over his sales route.) And if ever we stopped, en route, what I found was my self -- suddenly, profoundly nowhere. Stepping from the interior cool of a roadside cafe out into the dazing south Louisiana sunshine, what awaited was an alien landscape I had no use for, nor it for me. Better to be back in the car.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most of my life's travel has been distinctly of the little ''t'' variety. Not the kind you come home and give a speech about at the Explorers Club but, rather, travel viewed as an activity to be borne for its value of connecting (or, if you like, separating) two acts of at least temporary staying.</p>
        <p>From my childhood, travel always meant being on the way to someplace: the Mississippi Delta -- that big, flat cottonfield passing the car window on our Christmas trip from Jackson to Little Rock; the Everglades -- the big, murky watery part out there on the left as we drove to the opening of the Fontainebleu Hotel in Miami Beach in 1955. (''Vacation'' in my family most often meant driving with my father over his sales route.) And if ever we stopped, en route, what I found was my self -- suddenly, profoundly nowhere. Stepping from the interior cool of a roadside cafe out into the dazing south Louisiana sunshine, what awaited was an alien landscape I had no use for, nor it for me. Better to be back in the car.</p>
        <p>Once, in 1952, our Mercury broke down between Shreveport and Lake Charles. Ville Platte was the place. West of the Atchafalaya. We stayed a week attending a generator. And what we did in Ville Platte was walk the streets in the summer heat, evening upon evening. Nothing has ever seemed so foreign to me: the murmur of French patois spoken by strangers. The great, still live oaks at dusk. The great hovering dragonflies they called ''snake doctors.'' The intensity of waiting long in a place where no one knew you.</p>
        <p>My purest, most lucid memory of travel, however, is almost certainly my first. Our car -- another one now, a brown '47 Ford Tudor with a ballcap visor -- again broken down; but this time on the great arcing silver bridge above the Mississippi at Greenville. It was the 3rd of July. I do not remember the car's peculiar problem, only that my father was out on the hot, windy span above the water seeing to it, while my mother held me in what even then felt like a death's grip -- fearful that I, her only child, age 4, might somehow break loose, escape the car, go springing, cartwheeling off into space. Lost.</p>
        <p>She held me to her on that steaming, air-conditionless day in a way I had never been held before and haven't since. The world outside our busted car -- all that was waiting, the world we were traveling through -- was to be feared and guarded against lest it get you.</p>
        <p>My mother remembered that day very well, years later, during the time of her illness. ''Oh, Richard,'' she said from her hospital bed, ''when you were a little boy I smothered you. I'm so sorry now.''</p>
        <p>I of course did not think she had. To me, it only seemed like love. But in the years since then I have traveled about quite a lot, tempting that ''nowhere'' again and again. Perhaps it has been to prove that the uncertain territory between two known things no longer, finally, frightens me.</p>
        <p>Richard Ford is a novelist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard Ford is a novelist.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
