<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 213 Years, A.M.E. Church Elects First Woman as a Bishop</title>
    <meta content="12BISH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214391"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Methodist Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">African Methodist Episcopal Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodstein, Laurie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McKenzie, Vashti Murphy (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McKenzie, Stan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Methodist Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EED91138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 213 Years, A.M.E. Church Elects First Woman as a Bishop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE GOODSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodstein, Laurie</byline>
      <dateline>CINCINNATI, July 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>African Methodist Episcopal Church, nation's oldest black denomination, elects its first woman bishop, Rev Vashti Murphy McKenzie, pastor of Payne Memorial AME Church in Baltimore; her husband, Stan McKenzie, would normally be expected to serve as episcopal supervisor in Women's Missionary Society; election of McKenzie and three other bishops is delayed a day because of conflict over how many bishops will retire; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 213 years of fighting for the civil rights of blacks, the African Methodist Episcopal Church took a groundbreaking step tonight, electing a woman as bishop of the church for the first time.</p>
        <p>As church members wept and whooped with emotion in the packed convention hall here, the Rev. Vashti Murphy McKenzie, a dynamic preacher and community organizer, was swept up in a mob embrace by her children and husband, supporters and members of her church in Baltimore. Later, she embraced the bishop who had first ordained her, and took the bishops' podium flanked by her family and a corps of women ministers and lay leaders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 213 years of fighting for the civil rights of blacks, the African Methodist Episcopal Church took a groundbreaking step tonight, electing a woman as bishop of the church for the first time.</p>
        <p>As church members wept and whooped with emotion in the packed convention hall here, the Rev. Vashti Murphy McKenzie, a dynamic preacher and community organizer, was swept up in a mob embrace by her children and husband, supporters and members of her church in Baltimore. Later, she embraced the bishop who had first ordained her, and took the bishops' podium flanked by her family and a corps of women ministers and lay leaders.</p>
        <p>''Brothers and sisters, because of God's mercy and grace, we are able to stand here in the sun,'' she said in a firm, clear voice. ''The stained glass ceiling has been pierced.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McKenzie, who is the pastor of Payne Memorial A.M.E. Church in Baltimore, is the first woman to be elected bishop in any of the three predominantly black Methodist denominations. The A.M.E. is the nation's oldest black denomination and has often taken a leading role in civil rights battles and the push for black economic advancement. The post of bishop in the A.M.E. Church is prestigious and can transform a local pastor into a national leader.</p>
        <p>''We need some female leadership,'' said Crissandra Abernathy, a church member from St. Louis, as a wave of McKenzie supporters in red T-shirts swept by. ''She's committed. She knows what she's doing. And she has the charisma for the job. This is a new generation, and you have a whole new set of leaders coming up.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McKenzie was among 42 candidates for four open seats as bishop, and another candidate was a woman, the Rev. Carolyn Tyler Guidry, who as a presiding elder supervises 19 A.M.E. churches in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Ms. McKenzie quickly formed an alliance with the other winners, all men, who prevailed after three rounds of balloting. They are the Rev. Preston Williams of Atlanta, the Rev. Gregory G. M. Ingram of Detroit and the Rev. Richard Norris of Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>The voting in the convention center here was as passionately contested as any presidential race. Overseeing the proceedings were the church's 20 bishops, all of them men, many of them gray with age.</p>
        <p>Once elected, bishops serve until retirement. The job comes with a salary that is usually more than $100,000, and other perquisites include paid housing and travel costs, and a car and driver. But some of the candidates who are pastors at large, influential churches already live with such perks.</p>
        <p>The A.M.E. Church was founded when a group of black worshipers were forced from their knees while praying at a segregated church in Philadelphia in 1787. It is now an international organization, with more than 8,000 congregations and 2.5 million members.</p>
        <p>More than 10,000 church members from the United States, Africa, the Caribbean, Britain and Canada today filled rows of chairs on the floor of the Cincinnati Convention Center, which could hold one and a half football fields, for the vote. Among them were 1,800 voting delegates who registered their choices on electronic keypads, the first time the group has voted without paper ballots at its general conferences, which are held every four years to elect officials and make decisions on everything from budgets to missionary priorities.</p>
        <p>The election was hotly contested and highly political, with candidates making their way through the convention center shaking hands and waving, like members of Congress at a county fair. Supporters dressed in matching T-shirts and caps paraded through the convention center chanting and singing and carrying signs with pictures of their favorites. Candidates hand out pencils and water bottles, hair gel and even tubes of toothpaste imprinted with their names. Ms. McKenzie's campaign set up a television screen just inside the doors of the convention center to play over and over a video promoting her accomplishments.</p>
        <p>According to church tradition, as the spouse of a bishop, Ms. McKenzie's husband, Stan McKenzie, who once played in the National Basketball Association, would be expected to serve as an episcopal superviser in the Women's Missionary Society. As with this election, any other arrangement would be unprecedented.</p>
        <p>The election of bishops was delayed by a day, in part because of a controversy over how many bishops would retire. Bishops in the A.M.E. church are supposed to retire at 75, but lawyers were called in to resolve disputes over the birth dates of several long-serving bishops.</p>
        <p>The conflict came to a head late Monday night when Bishop Hamel Hartford Brookins resisted a vote by the delegates in favor of his retirement. Angry shouting erupted from the convention floor and the bishops on the dais, and there was a brief attempt to evict reporters. Eventually, Bishop Brookins, who in the last decade weathered financial scandal in his post, was allowed to be ''located'' instead of retired. Under that arrangement, he will be able to stay on for four more years and serve at-large, on full salary, but a new bishop will be elected to his seat.</p>
        <p>Ms. McKenzie was tapped for higher leadership in the church by Bishop Brookins when he appointed her to the pulpit of Payne Memorial, a large, influential church, 10 years ago. In that time, the congregation has grown from 300 members to 1,700, and runs several community development programs and ministries from an office building it now owns. Her church was among the first to apply for and receive money from the government to help former welfare recipients make the transition to employment.</p>
        <p>The friction was an indication that many in the church were ready to see new leaders replace the older generation.</p>
        <p>''You get the sense among many of the delegates,'' said Mike McKinney, communications director for the general conference, ''that it is time for new leadership.''</p>
        <p>The A.M.E. Church is the first of the three predominantly black Methodist denominations, which also include the African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church and the Christian Methodist Episcopal Church, to select a woman bishop.</p>
        <p>The United Methodist Church elected a woman as bishop in 1981, and the Episcopal Church consecrated its first woman as bishop in 1989.</p>
        <p>It was 1964, at the church's 37th general conference in Cincinnati, when the first woman ran for bishop in the A.M.E. Church. The pathbreaker was the Rev. Carrie T. Hooper, an evangelist, author and composer from New York, said Bettye Collier-Thomas, a history professor at Temple University and the author of ''Daughters of Thunder: Black Women Preachers and their Sermons, 1850-1979'' (Josie Bass, 1997).</p>
        <p>Only 13 delegates voted for Ms. Hooper, even though women had 230 of the 1,067 votes at the general conference, said Dr. Collier-Thomas.</p>
        <p>''What has happened is, in the last 30 years,'' said Dr. Collier-Thomas, ''you have more women who felt there was an opportunity for them to become ordained and to pastor churches. They went to seminary, they've got degrees, and their numbers have really risen. But the majority of them in terms of African-American women find they can't find a pastorate. Many are assistant ministers, which I call the stained-glass ceiling.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McKenzie addressed those women tonight in her victory speech, saying, ''I stand here tonight on the shoulders of the unordained, women who serve without affirmation or appointment.</p>
        <p>''I don't stand here alone, but there is a cloud of witnesses who sacrificed, died and gave their best,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
