<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SENATE CHAIRMAN OFFERS PROPOSAL ON DRUG BENEFITS</title>
    <meta content="12DRUG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Health Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roth, William V Jr (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DB1138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SENATE CHAIRMAN OFFERS PROPOSAL ON DRUG BENEFITS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senate Finance Committee chairman, William V Roth Jr, will propose a government-administered program to offer drug benefits to all Medicare recipients, breaking with House Republicans, who have passed a bill that would give subsidies to insurance companies to entice them into providing drug benefits to people on Medicare; under Roth's proposal, Medicare beneficiaries would have two options if they want freedom in choosing their doctors: staying in original fee-for-service program, with existing benefits, premiums, deductibles and co-payments, or enrolling in a high-option plan, which would provide drug benefits but would also charge more for certain services, like laboratory tests and home health care; Democrats and White House are surprised and pleased by Roth's move; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the battle over prescription drugs shifting to the Senate, the chairman of the Senate Finance Committee has broken with House Republicans and will propose a government-administered program to offer drug benefits to all Medicare recipients, senators of both parties said today.</p>
        <p>Senate Democrats and White House officials said that they were surprised and pleased by the proposal from the panel's influential chairman, William V. Roth Jr., and that they believed it would increase the chances of adding drug benefits to Medicare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the battle over prescription drugs shifting to the Senate, the chairman of the Senate Finance Committee has broken with House Republicans and will propose a government-administered program to offer drug benefits to all Medicare recipients, senators of both parties said today.</p>
        <p>Senate Democrats and White House officials said that they were surprised and pleased by the proposal from the panel's influential chairman, William V. Roth Jr., and that they believed it would increase the chances of adding drug benefits to Medicare.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth, a Delaware Republican, will go over his proposal at a closed meeting of the Finance Committee on Wednesday. The panel will have an opportunity to amend and vote on it later this month.</p>
        <p>A bill passed last month by the House would give subsidies to insurance companies to entice them into providing drug benefits to people on Medicare -- an approach opposed by President Clinton and by most Democrats in Congress, who say it is unlikely to work.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers said Mr. Roth clearly intended to depart from the House bill, under which private insurers would administer drug benefits and bear much of the financial risk.</p>
        <p>By contrast, a Senate Republican aide said, under Mr. Roth's proposal, ''the government would bear the insurance risk and take responsibility for administering the benefit, as it does with the rest of Medicare.''</p>
        <p>The House bill was passed by a vote of 217 to 214, largely along party lines. Democratic senators said Mr. Roth's proposal was much better than the House bill because drug coverage would be integrated into Medicare, the health insurance program for the elderly and disabled.</p>
        <p>Several Democrats said they could work with Mr. Roth, a conservative Republican who is running for re-election in a tight race against the governor of Delaware, Thomas R. Carper, a Democrat. Mr. Roth's proposal for a government-administered drug program would almost certainly have appeal to older Delaware voters.</p>
        <p>Senate Republican leaders gave no immediate indication of how they would respond to Mr. Roth's proposal. Trent Lott of Mississippi, the Senate Republican leader, neither embraced nor rejected it. John S. Czwartacki, a spokesman for Mr. Lott, said tonight that the majority leader ''has no comment at this time.''</p>
        <p>Democrats see Medicare drug benefits as one of their most potent political issues in this year's elections. Congress is far from passing any bill acceptable to Mr. Clinton, and many lawmakers believe a stalemate is the most likely outcome. But Senate Democrats said Mr. Roth's efforts could help narrow the gap between the parties, increasing the chances that drug benefits might be added to Medicare this year.</p>
        <p>Chris Jennings, the health policy coordinator at the White House, said he did not know all the details of Mr. Roth's proposal. But, he said, if Mr. Roth has rejected the idea of subsidizing insurance companies to provide drug benefits, ''that would represent a very important step forward.''</p>
        <p>Senator Bob Graham, Democrat of Florida, said: ''I am very pleased at what I've heard of Senator Roth's proposal. He accepts the fact that prescription medication is a central part of a modern health care system, not the red-headed third cousin at the family picnic that's shuffled off to the side and treated in a demeaning manner.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Graham added: ''Senator Roth puts drug coverage into the family of Medicare, rather than having it isolated in a private insurance plan. We know in advance that private insurers are very reluctant to offer free-standing drug coverage.''</p>
        <p>Senator Richard H. Bryan, Democrat of Nevada, sounded a similar note, saying: ''The chairman appears to have crossed the Rubicon and is embracing a prescription drug proposal within Medicare. In my view, that is very significant.''</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Roth's proposal, Medicare beneficiaries would have two options if they wanted freedom in choosing their doctors. They could stay in the original fee-for-service program, with the existing benefits, premiums, deductibles and co-payments. Or they could enroll in a high-option plan, which would provide drug benefits but would also charge more for certain services, like laboratory tests and home health care.</p>
        <p>''This is an explicit trade-off,'' said a Republican who helped draft the plan. ''The co-payments, the co-insurance, would save money. The money could be reinvested to provide a richer package of benefits.''</p>
        <p>In April, when asked to describe their strategy for passing drug legislation, White House officials said they pinned their hopes on the Finance Committee, where members of the two parties have a history of working together. Mr. Roth has solicited the views of the 19 other committee members in hopes of sending a bill to the Senate floor with bipartisan support.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth's proposal incorporates many features of a bill devised by moderate Democrats on the committee, including Mr. Graham and Senator Charles S. Robb of Virginia.</p>
        <p>While Republican leaders have not weighed in on Mr. Roth's proposal, their aides said the lawmakers were pleased that Mr. Roth was adhering to the budget blueprint adopted by both houses of Congress in April. That blueprint set aside up to $40 billion over five years for Medicare drug benefits. Mr. Clinton and Congressional Democrats say they never accepted that limit and want to spend more on drug benefits.</p>
        <p>Public response to Mr. Roth's proposal will depend on the answers to two questions: How much will beneficiaries have to pay for drug coverage? And how much will they receive in benefits? Details of the proposal were still being adjusted tonight, to reflect cost estimates from the Congressional Budget Office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth's desire to charge beneficiaries a fee for home health services provoked a predictable outcry from the industry.</p>
        <p>James C. Pyles, a lawyer for the American Association for Home Care, said: ''The idea of a co-payment on home health care is monumentally stupid. It would hit the sickest, most vulnerable patients, who tend to be the highest users of home care.'' Medicare spending on home care dropped 45 percent in the last two years, to $9.7 billion in 1999, from $17.5 billion in 1997.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roth's proposal, as described today by senators and their aides, includes these elements:</p>
        <p>*A new office would be established in the Department of Health and Human Services to administer drug benefits and to negotiate contracts with health maintenance organizations serving Medicare beneficiaries. The office would be separate from the current Medicare agency, the Health Care Financing Administration, but would work closely with it.</p>
        <p>*Medicare would pay a larger share of a person's drug bills as those expenses increased. While the details are still being worked out, the government might pay half of drug costs below a specified level -- perhaps $3,500 or $4,000 a year -- and 80 percent of costs beyond that. By contrast, under many Democratic proposals, the government would pick up 100 percent of drug costs above some level, like $4,000 a year.</p>
        <p>*The government would hire private companies to help manage drug benefits for the elderly, to negotiate discounts from drug manufacturers and to set up networks of drugstores in different parts of the country.</p>
        <p>*In the high-option Medicare plan, the government would establish a single deductible for the two existing parts of Medicare. The program now has separate deductibles, $100 a year for doctors' services and $776 for inpatient hospital care. In addition, there would be a separate deductible for drug insurance.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Clinton's plan and under the bill passed by the House, the government would offer subsidies to employers to encourage them to continue providing drug benefits to retirees. Mr. Roth is not proposing such subsidies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
