<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hollywood Is Asked to Join A Campaign Against Drugs</title>
    <meta content="Y12MES$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Office of National Drug Control Policy</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccaffrey, Barry R (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5DB1138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="392" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hollywood Is Asked to Join A Campaign Against Drugs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White House Office of National Drug Control Policy is encouraging major movie studios, as well as individual directors and writers, to promote antidrug messages in films; Gon Barry R McCaffrey, office's director, says government is using only its power of persuasion, not financial incentives, to influence cinematic themes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The drug wars are gearing up in Hollywood.</p>
        <p>The White House's Office of National Drug Control Policy is increasing its campaign to encourage major movie studios, as well as individual directors and writers, to promote antidrug messages in films.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The drug wars are gearing up in Hollywood.</p>
        <p>The White House's Office of National Drug Control Policy is increasing its campaign to encourage major movie studios, as well as individual directors and writers, to promote antidrug messages in films.</p>
        <p>''We believe there will be opportunities to leverage popular movies and videos that responsibly communicate campaign messages, after they have been released,'' Gen. Barry R. McCaffrey, the office's director, said in testimony prepared for a Congressional hearing today. ''As powerful as television is, some experts believe that movies have an even stronger impact on young people.''</p>
        <p>Under questioning from a panel of the House Government Reform Committee, and reporters afterward, General McCaffrey emphasized that the government was using only its power of persuasion, not financial incentives, to influence cinematic themes. The efforts, which he said could take years to yield results, include briefings, workshops and conversations with industry leaders.</p>
        <p>''There is no money at all, zero, given to any program for including antidrug messages,'' General McCaffrey told reporters. ''These decisions are made by the creative community on their own.''</p>
        <p>The general's sensitivity on the subject was acute because similar programs the drug office has for the television and magazine industries have drawn fire from outside critics as unwarranted government propaganda.</p>
        <p>Until late January, drug office officials were allowed to see in advance more than 100 episodes on all major television networks.  If the government approved a show with an antidrug message, the network received credit that reduced the number of costly public service announcements it was required by law to broadcast.</p>
        <p>In response to criticism, the drug office stopped reviewing scripts and watching episodes in advance. Similarly, it said it did not read magazine articles before publication in deciding whether to grant financial credit.</p>
        <p>Congress authorized General McCaffrey in 1997 to spend up to $1 billion over five years in television, print and other advertising against drug use. For every advertisement bought, the publication or network would run a public service announcement or incorporate an antidrug message into the article or program.</p>
        <p>There is no such financial incentive in the arrangement with the movie industry. The drug office buys antidrug trailer advertisements -- $2.4 million worth last year -- to be shown in theaters before movies. These payments go to the theater owners, not the studios.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
