<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Irvin Makes Retirement Official</title>
    <meta content="12NFL.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="N.F.L.: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Cowboys</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Irvin, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Dallas Cowboys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1D81138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Irvin Makes Retirement Official</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Irvin, who suffers from fragile spine, retires as Dallas Cowboys football player; roundup of other football news (M)0</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than two years after a Sunday in 1997 when he stood on the sideline with tears streaming down his cheeks because he believed his team had quit, Michael Irvin was the one quitting yesterday, nearly in tears again as he described his passion for football, the Cowboys and the city of Dallas.</p>
        <p>''I like to think of myself as a warrior,'' Irvin said yesterday at a news conference. ''I wanted to be dragged off the field, and I was.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than two years after a Sunday in 1997 when he stood on the sideline with tears streaming down his cheeks because he believed his team had quit, Michael Irvin was the one quitting yesterday, nearly in tears again as he described his passion for football, the Cowboys and the city of Dallas.</p>
        <p>''I like to think of myself as a warrior,'' Irvin said yesterday at a news conference. ''I wanted to be dragged off the field, and I was.''</p>
        <p>Irvin's final catch came late in the first quarter of a game last Oct. 10 in Philadelphia. When Irvin was tackled, the back of his head bounced on the hard turf of Veterans Stadium, and he was carted off the field and into an ambulance.</p>
        <p>He was temporarily paralyzed with a herniated disk. Tests revealed a fragile spine that he had been fortunate not to damage earlier in his career.</p>
        <p>A somber Irvin admitted days later that he was considering retirement. He struggled with the decision for months until his wife and mother made him realize that being able to play with his children was more important than trying to win another Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>Irvin, 34, will now work for Fox Sports Net's Sunday pregame show.</p>
        <p>He caught 750 passes for 11,904 yards in his career, ninth over all. Of the players ahead of him, only Jerry Rice has as many as his three Super Bowl rings.</p>
        <p>But Irvin's career was marked by off-field problems, too, and whether that will affect his Hall of Fame candidacy will not be known for five years.</p>
        <p>''He wasn't blessed with the best physical abilities, but he made up for it with desire and work ethic,'' quarterback Troy Aikman said. ''He practiced every day as if he were going up against the 49ers.'' (AP)</p>
        <p>ERIC SWANN RELEASED: The Arizona Cardinals released Eric Swann yesterday, as he had requested. Swann, when healthy one of the most dominant defensive linemen in football, had been sidelined for 21 games over the past three seasons because of an arthritic right knee that has required seven surgeries. He appeared in just nine games last season.</p>
        <p>The release saves the team approximately $3.5 million, reducing pressure on its salary cap.</p>
        <p>Swann, who turns 30 next month, has played nine pro seasons. Although he never played college football, he was the Cardinals' first-round selection in 1991. He has amassed 522 tackles, 44 sacks, 8 fumble recoveries and 2 interceptions. (AP)</p>
        <p>STEELERS TACKLE RETIRES: Pittsburgh Steelers nose tackle Joel Steed retired yesterday because of knee problems and his impending release from the team. Steed said he was fortunate to have been able to play his entire eight-year career in Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>He was taken by the Steelers in the third round of the 1992 draft out of Colorado and was twice selected for the Pro Bowl. But Steed also had a history of injuries, including two knee operations since the end of the 1998 season. He missed the final two games last season with knee soreness.</p>
        <p>Steed, 31, finishes his career with 315 tackles, including 215 solo. (AP)</p>
        <p>AN HONOR FOR MARINO: Miami-Dade County will rename a street after the former Dolphins quarterback Dan Marino.</p>
        <p>Marino retired in March as the most productive passer in National Football League history after spending his 17-year career with the Dolphins. He was a nine-time Pro Bowl selection and passed for a record 61,361 yards and 420 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>The street in front of the Dolphins' Pro Player Stadium, 199th Street, will be renamed Dan Marino Boulevard on Aug. 21. (Bloomberg News)</p>
        <p>N.F.L.: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
