<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former Doctor Charged in Death Of 3 Patients</title>
    <meta content="12DOCT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poisoning and Poisons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northport (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Columbus (Ohio)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sammarco, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siano, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Serini, Aldo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swango, Michael J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio/Columbus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poisoning and Poisons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D91138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former Doctor Charged in Death Of 3 Patients</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., July 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former doctor, Michael J Swango, is charged with 1993 murders of three patients under his care at veterans hospital, Northport, NY, and pattern of fraud dating back to 1984, when he allegedly killed patient in Columbus, Ohio, Federal court; charges come before Swango's scheduled release from federal prison, where he serves sentence for fraudulently obtaining Northport post; follow finding of poison in exhumed bodies of patients Thomas Sammarco, George Siano and Aldo Serini; indictment stuns relatives of dead patients; chronology of events; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everywhere Michael J. Swango went, it seemed, death soon followed. In medical school, as a young intern, as a doctor, many of the patients he saw died. But he always managed to find new posts -- even after he was convicted of trying to poison several co-workers by putting ant killer in their doughnuts.</p>
        <p>Except for the case with the doughnuts, the authorities never charged him with any violent crimes. But today federal investigators here said that they had amassed enough evidence to charge Mr. Swango with the 1993 murders of three patients who were under his care at a Veterans Affairs hospital in Northport, N.Y., and with a pattern of fraud dating back to 1984 when, court papers charge, he killed a patient in Columbus, Ohio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everywhere Michael J. Swango went, it seemed, death soon followed. In medical school, as a young intern, as a doctor, many of the patients he saw died. But he always managed to find new posts -- even after he was convicted of trying to poison several co-workers by putting ant killer in their doughnuts.</p>
        <p>Except for the case with the doughnuts, the authorities never charged him with any violent crimes. But today federal investigators here said that they had amassed enough evidence to charge Mr. Swango with the 1993 murders of three patients who were under his care at a Veterans Affairs hospital in Northport, N.Y., and with a pattern of fraud dating back to 1984 when, court papers charge, he killed a patient in Columbus, Ohio.</p>
        <p>The officials charged Mr. Swango -- who was to have been released this Saturday from a federal prison in Colorado, where he has served a three-and-a-half-year sentence for fraudulently obtaining the Northport post -- after exhuming the three New York patients and finding poisons in their bodies. In some cases, the court papers charge, Mr. Swango falsely claimed that he had obtained ''do not resuscitate'' orders from relatives of his victims to make sure that efforts would not be made to revive them after their attempted murder.</p>
        <p>''Instead of using his medical license to become a healer, Swango embarked upon a career as a killer,'' said Loretta E. Lynch, the United States attorney for the Eastern District of New York. ''Through a web of lies and deception, Swango inveigled his way into the confidence of hospital administrators across the country and the world. Once in their trust and in their employ, he utilized his skills to search for victims and take their lives.''</p>
        <p>If convicted, Mr. Swango, 45, could face the death penalty. His lawyer, Randi Chavis, did not respond to repeated calls for comment. In the past, Mr. Swango has maintained his innocence.</p>
        <p>The three murder charges in the indictment stem from incidents in 1993, when Mr. Swango was hired as a medical resident by the Stony Brook Health Sciences Center after lying to the admissions office, saying that his previous conviction for poisoning stemmed from a ''barroom brawl.'' As a Stony Brook intern, he was assigned to the Veterans Affairs Medical Center in Northport.</p>
        <p>He had worked there for three months when Stony Brook officials learned about his criminal past -- which had been featured in newspapers and on national television -- and fired him. Stony Brook officials said at the time that they had determined that no harm had come to the 147 patients he treated there.</p>
        <p>Federal officials disputed that today. They charged Mr. Swango with killing three patients with lethal injections while at the Northport hospital: Thomas Sammarco, 73; George Siano, 60, and Aldo Serini, all of Long Island. A spokesman for Stony Brook, Patrick Calabria, refused to comment on the case.</p>
        <p>The indictment came as a shock to relatives of the dead patients. Roselinda Conroy said that it had never occurred to her that her stepfather, Mr. Siano, had died of anything but natural causes. ''We must face the horrible fact that he did not die at the hands of cancer, but at the hands of a madman,'' she said today.</p>
        <p>The indictment charges Mr. Swango with assaulting a fourth patient there, Barron Harris, by giving him an injection of a paralyzing medication. Mr. Harris, who was 60, then fell into a coma and later died.</p>
        <p>There may have been many more victims, investigators said. Ms. Lynch said that prosecutors believe that Mr. Swango may have been involved in a number of other murders across the globe, from Ohio to Zimbabwe. But she declined to speculate on how many there might be.</p>
        <p>In the indictment, though, prosecutors paint a portrait of a serial killer who began in his very first job out of medical school. After that, they charge, he lied and misrepresented himself to obtain other medical jobs where he could kill again.</p>
        <p>In ''Blind Eye: The Terrifying Story of a Doctor Who Got Away With Murder'' (Simon &amp; Schuster, 1999), James B. Stewart contends that the Swango case highlights the reluctance of the medical profession to screen or sanction its own. ''The case shows that the medical establishment will blindly trust the word of a fellow doctor over the word of other witnesses, and that the medical profession cannot adequately police itself,'' Mr. Stewart said in an interview today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stewart writes in the book that questions were raised about Mr. Swango when he was a medical student at Southern Illinois University. Classmates called him Double-O Swango, joking that he had a license to kill, because of the large number of his cases that ended in deaths.</p>
        <p>In 1984, as a medical resident at Ohio State University Hospital, Mr. Swango was accused of causing a patient to have a seizure after injecting something into her intravenous tube. The patient, Rena Cooper, survived and told hospital officials about the attack, but they did not believe her. The hospital found no evidence against Mr. Swango, though a subsequent report on its investigation by the dean of the university's law school found that the hospital had not been thorough.</p>
        <p>Today's indictment, which was unsealed in Federal District Court here, mentions the attack on Mrs. Cooper and says that Mr. Swango ''murdered, attempted to murder and assaulted patients'' while at Ohio State University Hospital. It also says that he murdered Cynthia McGee, 19, in 1984 by giving her a potassium injection that caused her heart to stop.</p>
        <p>David P. Ferguson, the associate vice president for university relations, said that Ohio State had done its best to arrive at the truth. ''We could all benefit from the clarity of hindsight,'' he said, ''but we feel what we did was appropriate and diligent at the time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Swango was not allowed to continue his residency there for a second year. When he left, he returned to his native Illinois and found work as an emergency medical technician with the Adams County Ambulance Service. While there he was convicted of lacing his co-workers' doughnuts and coffee with an arsenic-based ant killer. Five people became ill, but no one was killed.</p>
        <p>He was sentenced to five years in prison, but served only two.</p>
        <p>His sentence raised eyebrows in Ohio, where prosecutors took another look at his residency and found ''circumstantial evidence'' but no proof that he had committed crimes. When he got out of prison, officials charged, Mr. Swango used false names and false documents to try to get a number of medical positions. He was rejected from the Ohio Valley Medical Center; hired by a Veterans Hospital in South Dakota, but fired when his past became known, and then hired by Stony Brook.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Swango was dismissed by Stony Brook in 1993, he went to practice medicine in Zimbabwe,  where the authorities have issued a warrant for his arrest on charges that he poisoned seven patients, five of them fatally.</p>
        <p>He was arrested in 1997, while stopping over in Chicago en route to a new job as a doctor in Dhahran, Saudi Arabia. He pleaded guilty to making a false statement to Stony Brook officials, and began serving the three-and-a-half-year sentence.</p>
        <p>The Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Department of Veterans Affairs and prosecutors, meanwhile, began building their case against him.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
