<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Private Business in China: A Tough, Tortuous Road</title>
    <meta content="12PRIV$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7DA1138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Private Business in China: A Tough, Tortuous Road</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>JIAXING, China</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Entrepreneurs have a hard time starting and running their businesses in China, where they are denied credit by banks, discriminated against by regulators and barred from entering many industries, all because of ideological inertia; economy is still dominated by government-owned enterprises despite all the talks about economic reform; China may have to embrace capitalism more fully as it enters World Trade Organization, since foreign companies could then take over a huge part of domestic economy unless private entrepreneurs are unleased to compete with them; map; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yu Xianglin wants to build a blimp.</p>
        <p>He has notebooks filled with drawings of airships that recall his boyhood fantasies of 50 years ago. He has regulatory specifications and a business plan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yu Xianglin wants to build a blimp.</p>
        <p>He has notebooks filled with drawings of airships that recall his boyhood fantasies of 50 years ago. He has regulatory specifications and a business plan.</p>
        <p>But after two years of hard work, Mr. Yu, 60, remains grounded because he is a private businessman, something not quite as scarce as a zeppelin in this officially socialist country, but still rare where ''capitalist'' is a dirty word.</p>
        <p>His most pressing problem is getting a bank loan. The bank requires a guarantor, almost impossible for a private businessman to find in China. Even if a private company has a guarantor, most loans are for only three or four months -- 18 months in exceptional cases.</p>
        <p>''That's not long enough to get a business off the ground,'' said Mr. Yu, a portly man dressed in a black Hugo Boss shirt that matched his jet-black hair.</p>
        <p>''It's really, really tough for private companies in China,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Though this country has been marching famously on the road toward economic change for more than two decades now, it is far from the evolving capitalist society that many people in the West imagine.</p>
        <p>The private sector, concentrated on the country's southeastern coast, remains a small slice of an economy that is still dominated by government-owned enterprises. Even China's 800 million ostensibly independent farmers grow crops on state-owned land and sell grain to state-owned grain companies.</p>
        <p>Private companies, excluding those controlled by foreigners, accounted last year for less than 20 percent of China's economic output, and employed fewer than 50 million people in a country of 1.25 billion. While a sizable gray economy accounts for much hidden private activity, barriers to raising money keep most private businesses from providing more than a handful of jobs.</p>
        <p>There is growing pressure to change that. Allowing private companies to absorb the state's excess workers is an obvious way to improve the Chinese economy, locked in a cycle of bank lending to the money-losing state-owned enterprises that sustain those workers.</p>
        <p>And officials are beginning to realize that they need people like Mr. Yu for an even more pressing reason rooted in Chinese nationalism: with World Trade Organization membership expected to open the domestic market wider to foreign companies in the next five years, foreigners could take over a huge part of the economy unless China unleashes private entrepreneurs soon.</p>
        <p>''If state-owned enterprises can't perform and there isn't a viable domestic private sector, the economy will by default become mostly foreign-owned,'' warned Andy Xie, an economist for Morgan Stanley Dean Witter in Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>Yet entrepreneurs like Mr. Yu are systematically shunned by China's banks, often discriminated against by government regulators and barred from entering many industries.</p>
        <p>In a conference room above the auto repair shop that has already made him relatively wealthy, Mr. Yu said he could sell as many as 90 blimps immediately if he had the money to make them. The expertise would come from a technical institute in Beijing that has already made a blimp. And an aircraft factory in Sichuan province has agreed to build the airframes and engines. Mr. Yu has even leased enough land amid the smokestacks and power lines here, southwest of Shanghai, to assemble two blimps at a time.</p>
        <p>He envisions blimps used for advertising, geological surveys, even heavy lifting in the country's mountainous west, where the government plans to build dozens of dams in the next few years.</p>
        <p>If he does not start soon, foreign blimp makers will take the market once the country joins the W.T.O. Rules barring foreigners from operating aviation maintenance shops have kept them out of the market so far.</p>
        <p>China's president, Jiang Zemin, laid new foundations for privatization nearly three years ago by officially redefining state ownership, the central tenet of China's economy, to include minority stakes in otherwise private enterprises. Private property was given constitutional protection the next year.</p>
        <p>But ideological inertia still stands in the way. Allowing capitalists to accumulate capital is anathema to the country's hard-line Marxists, who fear that a powerful private sector would erode the Communist Party's power.</p>
        <p>''The government doesn't want to develop the private sector; they just want to use it to help the state-owned economy,'' said Chen Rong, one of Shanghai's largest private entrepreneurs, who exudes a seen-it-all air.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chen, 42, obtained his initial capital from the stock market -- not by issuing shares but by trading shares in the stock market. Speculation in the country's volatile markets provides seed capital for many entrepreneurs who have few alternatives.</p>
        <p>Capital markets are otherwise beyond the reach of most entrepreneurs because the government bureaucracy favors state-owned companies. The government holds a majority stake in almost all companies listed on China's two stock exchanges, in Shanghai and Shenzhen. And private companies cannot issue bonds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chen had hoped to create China's first privately owned financial services company, and he bought a whole floor of the Shanghai Stock Exchange building, where he now has a sleek office. But as a private businessman, he was barred from operating a securities company or owning a seat on the exchange.</p>
        <p>Instead, he invested in another of his pastimes -- bowling, which for a while was almost as popular in China as trading shares. He imported a bowling alley from AMF of the United States, dismantled it and copied its design. Today, he is China's only manufacturer of pinspotting machines, which set up bowling pins after they are knocked down.</p>
        <p>At his fanciful factory compound, where spired and crenelated buildings resemble a low-budget theme park, workers polish sherbet-colored bowling balls by hand.</p>
        <p>Inexpensive labor enables Mr. Chen to sell his bowling equipment for about half what foreign companies charge. But that is about the only advantage China has offered him in his remarkably successful competition with multinational giants like Brunswick and AMF.</p>
        <p>Despite its free-market facade, even Shanghai's economy is less than 10 percent private. Many of the city's chrome-and-glass storefronts contain state-owned businesses or joint ventures between state-owned and foreign companies. Collectives, businesses owned by local government organizations, make up much of the rest.</p>
        <p>In fact, China's official media rarely use the term ''private,'' preferring to call such businesses ''people-operated.''</p>
        <p>The Communist Party's ambivalence toward the private sector is evident even in Wenzhou, a coastal city in Zhejiang province that is considered the cradle of the country's private economy. Ninety percent of the people there are supported by private enterprise.</p>
        <p>''When you get rich, remember your origins,'' reads a billboard there bearing the likenesses of Mao Zedong, Deng Xiaoping and Jiang Zemin above the road to the airport. A similar slogan is painted in white Chinese characters on a red banner stretched across one of the bustling thoroughfares in town.</p>
        <p>President Jiang toured Wenzhou's biggest private companies in May and championed the role of business in helping China develop. But he also called for greater Communist Party representation in private companies.</p>
        <p>China's private sector got its start 20 years ago near Wenzhou, in the lush green hills surrounding the glassy Ou River. A small river town called Qiaotou became a trading entrepot between Shanghai button makers and garment factories farther down the coast, after Deng Xiaoping allowed free markets to sprout around the country.</p>
        <p>Soon, many Qiaotou families were making buttons themselves. They pooled their resources to build a button market, now housed in a new, button-like circular building at the center of town.</p>
        <p>Jin Wenwu recalls growing up in a cramped three-story house filled with buttons, which he sealed in plastic bags with heat from a candle.</p>
        <p>By the time he was a teenager, the family had begun punching buttons from plastic sheets and drilling holes in the buttons using crude, hand-operated machines.</p>
        <p>The business grew along with others in town until there were too many button makers, forcing a wave of mergers that created China's first companies with shareholders. Mr. Jin now owns a 25 percent stake in one of the merged companies.</p>
        <p>Above the roar of buttons tumbling in a dozen rotating polishing machines, Mr. Jin says the government offers no help, but has not interfered with his business either -- yet. An official called the other day asking for a list of party members who work in his factory.</p>
        <p>Because relationships with officials are still so crucial, many private business owners are really just opportunists exploiting their party connections. The resulting corruption has not helped improve the private sector's image. One of the most celebrated entrepreneurs, Mou Qizhong, was recently sentenced to life in prison for fraud.</p>
        <p>Other businesses disguise themselves as government-owned entities to survive. Guo Hongnian and four friends pooled $72,000 in 1992 to establish a liquefied cooking gas factory in Shanghai. But as a private company, they could not get the proper license to sell their gas.</p>
        <p>They paid a city-owned cooking gas supplier $30,000 in return for registering them as a collective enterprise, and their business took off. Its assets are worth about $12 million today.</p>
        <p>Much of China's economic growth in the last 20 years has come from such variants of private enterprise. But the fuzzy ownership structure has limited their growth into bigger companies. Banks and outside investors are reluctant to finance the collectives because it is not clear to whom the enterprises belong.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Guo, 52, wanted to cash out of the cooking gas concern, for example, the city ruled that the assets belonged to the collective and that he and his friends were, in effect, nothing more than employees.</p>
        <p>''We'll fight for these assets the rest of our lives,'' insisted Mr. Guo, shuffling a sheaf of dogeared papers that he said proved his case.</p>
        <p>Despite all the problems, there is a growing sense in China that the private sector is an idling dynamo about to shudder to life. All that is needed is a mechanism to give private owners access to capital.</p>
        <p>The government is already talking about expanding the two stock exchanges to make it easier for fledgling companies, including private ones, to raise money. And it is talking about letting foreign-owned companies list shares for buying and selling by Chinese.</p>
        <p>That would encourage foreigners to pump money into young companies because it would give investors an easy way to get their money out later.</p>
        <p>Already, Internet companies are providing the most energetic private business growth because of foreign venture capital pouring into the country.</p>
        <p>Given the current harsh environment, those private companies that do play by the rules and survive end up remarkably healthy, with resilient streams of revenue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yu quit a state-owned machine tool factory to start repairing trucks in 1977. The business grew along with traffic on the roads and he never needed to borrow.</p>
        <p>Having beaten the system once, he is confident his new venture will succeed even though he has never been up in a blimp. ''When we build one, I'll be the first passenger,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
