<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Do Endorsements and Debates Count? A Lot, It Seems</title>
    <meta content="Y12END$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE POLLS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Annenberg Public Policy Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1DB1138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="438" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Do Endorsements and Debates Count? A Lot, It Seems</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Huge polling project conducted by Annenberg Public Policy Center of University of Pennsylvania finds that endorsements and debates have played critical roles in this year's contests for presidential nominations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Endorsements and debates played critical roles in this year's contests for presidential nominations, according to findings of a huge polling project conducted by the Annenberg Public Policy Center of the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Nightly tracking polls of voters in Iowa and New Hampshire, for example, showed that Vice President Al Gore's Jan. 5 debate attack on Bill Bradley over health care and his Jan. 8 blast over a Bradley vote on flood relief had a distinct effect on Democratic voters, and halted the momentum the former New Jersey senator had built.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Endorsements and debates played critical roles in this year's contests for presidential nominations, according to findings of a huge polling project conducted by the Annenberg Public Policy Center of the University of Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Nightly tracking polls of voters in Iowa and New Hampshire, for example, showed that Vice President Al Gore's Jan. 5 debate attack on Bill Bradley over health care and his Jan. 8 blast over a Bradley vote on flood relief had a distinct effect on Democratic voters, and halted the momentum the former New Jersey senator had built.</p>
        <p>''In two debates, Bradley effectively lost the nomination,'' said Kathleen Hall Jamieson, director of the Annenberg center.</p>
        <p>Endorsements cut both ways, Dr. Jamieson said. For example, the endorsement of Gov. George W. Bush by the National Right to Life Committee won him votes from abortion opponents in his race against Senator John McCain,  but cost him votes among Republican supporters of abortion rights. That endorsement, she said, ''may have misled people into thinking McCain was more pro-choice than he actually was.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Jamieson described the value of endorsements as a shortcut for voters ''seeking information about candidate stands.''</p>
        <p>The key to deriving impact from endorsements, she said, was usually to advertise them. In Iowa, for example, only 19 percent of Democrats were aware of the endorsement of Mr. Bradley by Senator Paul Wellstone of neighboring Minnesota, who campaigned frequently with him. But 75 percent knew that Senator Tom Harkin of Iowa had endorsed Mr. Gore. The Harkin support was shown often in Gore advertisements. The Wellstone endorsement was not shown at all. Instead,  Mr. Bradley's campaign used an advertisement showing that he was being backed by Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan of New York.</p>
        <p>Another important finding was that knowing the source of a political advertisement can be critical to its effectiveness. Dr. Jamieson found that a Bush radio advertisement accusing Mr. McCain of opposing spending for cancer research was widely known across the country and had a big impact on female voters, although it was broadcast only in New York. Those who knew that the Bush campaign had sponsored it were 11 percentage points less likely to believe it than those who did not, Dr. Jamieson said. Had it been sponsored by a group calling itself Citizens for Breast Cancer Research, for instance, it might have been even more effective, she said.</p>
        <p>These findings are among the first from a polling effort that began last December and will end only next January, after more than 100,000 interviews on Americans' political opinions, knowledge and use of media.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE POLLS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
