<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Proposes Move To Promote Adoption</title>
    <meta content="Y12BUS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E2DF1138F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Proposes Move To Promote Adoption</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>ROYAL OAK, Mich., July 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush calls for measures to promote adoption, including grants to states and an increase in the adoption tax credit; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush declared today that ''foster care ought to be a bridge to adoption'' and called for measures to promote adoption, including grants to states and an increase in the adoption tax credit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, the presumptive Republican presidential nominee, announced the proposals as he returned to his ''compassionate conservative'' themes and planned several weeks of appearances devoted to social welfare measures for low-income and struggling Americans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush declared today that ''foster care ought to be a bridge to adoption'' and called for measures to promote adoption, including grants to states and an increase in the adoption tax credit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, the presumptive Republican presidential nominee, announced the proposals as he returned to his ''compassionate conservative'' themes and planned several weeks of appearances devoted to social welfare measures for low-income and struggling Americans.</p>
        <p>He illustrated the day's theme by visiting the Judson Center here, which provides support services to families. He listened as a panel of young people, parents and officials told of their experiences with foster care.</p>
        <p>The Texas governor briefly outlined his ideas to change foster care from a permanent situation for many children to a way station toward adoption or toward a child's return to his biological family. He proposed $1 billion in grants over five years to be used by states to try to keep children with their biological families if those homes are considered safe.</p>
        <p>He also proposed increasing the adoption tax credit, which was signed into law by President Clinton in 1996, to $7,500 from $5,000 at a cost of $1 billion over five years.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Bush called for spending $300 million more over the same period to be used for vouchers to assist teenagers who are leaving the foster care system. The vouchers, of up to $5,000 per person, could be used for college tuition or vocational training.</p>
        <p>The governor said he would require states to conduct criminal background checks on prospective foster-care parents and adoptive parents. Federal law currently allows states to opt out of the checks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush pointed to his own state as a leader in improving foster care and the adoption system. The number of children who can be permanently adopted rose to 2,123 in 1999 from 1,033 in 1996 because of procedures developed to keep children from languishing in foster care, an aide to Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign immediately attacked Mr. Bush's credibility by pointing to such findings as a 1999 report that ranked Texas 49th among the 50 states in the number of children living in poverty.</p>
        <p>''The facts speak for themselves, said Kym Spell, a Gore aide. ''Bush's record in Texas is short on compassion and long on broken promises.''</p>
        <p>For most of the 45-minute panel session, Mr. Bush simply questioned the panelists or listened as they told inspirational tales of overcoming difficult family situations. Television cameras filmed the kinds of scenes that have become a Bush campaign staple: the candidate surrounded by minority children.</p>
        <p>''I appreciate the spirit of love that exists inside these walls,'' Mr. Bush said, as he sat under a blue banner proclaiming ''Strong Families, Safe Children.''</p>
        <p>Former Lt. Gov. Connie Binsfeld of Michigan told Mr. Bush that states needed more flexibility in using federal funds. ''I could talk for two days, governor,'' she said, ''because -- ''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush interrupted her, saying, ''I don't know if I could listen for two.''</p>
        <p>At another point Mr. Bush hugged one of the two foster sons that Sierra Craig was adopting as he talked about the adoption tax credit. He tried to draw out her 11-year-old son, Eric. ''What grade are you in?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>''Sixth,'' the boy whispered. Mr. Bush said: ''That's good. I was in sixth grade once, too.''</p>
        <p>The governor spent most of the day in this battleground state at three receptions intended to raise nearly $2 million for the national and state Republican parties.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
