<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Modern Genghis Takes a Diplomatic Tack</title>
    <meta content="12PROF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (Foreign)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mongolia</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Enkhsaikhan Jargalsaikhany</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Enkhsaikhan Jargalsaikhany (Amb)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Mongolia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E1D61038F931A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Modern Genghis Takes a Diplomatic Tack</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>public lives: modern genghis</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIRST, about the name: In three and a half years in New York, as the ambassador to the United Nations from Mongolia, Enkhsaikhan Jargalsai-khany has not yet tired of explaining it (''most people spell it very correctly, because it's so unusual,'' he says). Mongolian names mean nice things. His first name means ''good and peaceful.'' His last name -- his father's name, plus a ''y'' to denote ''son of'' -- means ''happiness is good.''</p>
        <p>Now the pronunciation: enk-SIGH-han jar-gal-SIGH-ha-nee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIRST, about the name: In three and a half years in New York, as the ambassador to the United Nations from Mongolia, Enkhsaikhan Jargalsai-khany has not yet tired of explaining it (''most people spell it very correctly, because it's so unusual,'' he says). Mongolian names mean nice things. His first name means ''good and peaceful.'' His last name -- his father's name, plus a ''y'' to denote ''son of'' -- means ''happiness is good.''</p>
        <p>Now the pronunciation: enk-SIGH-han jar-gal-SIGH-ha-nee.</p>
        <p>Now for what has kept Ambassador Enkhsaikhan, 49, so busy, in and out of the United Nations.</p>
        <p>Last month, he made a success of the Festival of Mongolia, a New York celebration of his homeland that diplomatic types did not expect to draw 25,000 people, as it already has in total.</p>
        <p>And yesterday was Mongolia's traditional national feast day. In every province of the country, costumed revelers celebrated, cheering on feats of wrestling, archery and horsemanship.</p>
        <p>But instead of partying, the ambassador has been busily reassuring Western diplomats and trade partners that, as he put it, ''we are not going back to Communism.''</p>
        <p>He referred to last week's election upheaval in Mongolia, where the 76-seat Parliament was captured by the Mongolian People's Revolutionary Party (formerly the Communist Party). ''The voters were saying they want the government to pay more attention to social issues,'' he said, referring to a severe drought and harsh winter that punished the Mongolian economy. ''There will be no restoration of the socialist system in Mongolia.''</p>
        <p>The ambassador is also reassuring diplomatic peers about his own tenure. A new cabinet will be formed later this month and a new prime minister named. But the ambassador said that since Mongolia's foreign policy has long enjoyed bipartisan support, ''I don't see why the election would affect my role.''</p>
        <p>Shortly after arriving at the United Nations three and a half years ago, Ambassador Enkhsaikhan assumed key posts. He has been vice president of the General Assembly, chairman of its legal committee and chairman of the 30-nation group of Landlocked Developing Countries. He has also been active in the 70-nation Forum of Small States.</p>
        <p>The ambassador's country of 2.4 million has suffered from nearly a millennium of bad spin, thanks to Genghis Khan, who dominated a third of the known world. Undaunted, the ambassador began an image upgrade. The 21-event Festival of Mongolia he organized, mounted for $1 million, continues into September. (The festival Web site lists events at www.un.int /mongolia/festival-form.htm.)</p>
        <p>But perhaps the greatest challenge for this circus lover has been to dance the tightrope between Russia and China. In 1998, he persuaded the General Assembly to adopt a resolution giving Mongolia nuclear-weapon-free status. Now he is pressing the five atomic powers to pledge to make Mongolia a perpetual nuclear-free zone, and will meet with them next month in Geneva.</p>
        <p>These days he lives at Mongolia's diplomatic residence on the Upper East Side with his second wife, Batgerel (she is a hydraulic engineer, and her name means ''strong light''), along with the six children, ages 6 to 23, from his marriages.</p>
        <p>He has been nimble at networking beyond the United Nations. The ambassador is ''extremely able,'' said Schuyler G. Chapin, New York City's cultural affairs commissioner, who helped coordinate the festival, ''and is something of a Renaissance man.'' Ambassador Enkhsaikhan speaks seven languages: Mongolian, English, Russian, French, Spanish, Czech and Arabic.</p>
        <p>His linguistic facility mirrors the diplomatic postings of his father, who, after being orphaned at 4, rose to become Mongolia's first ambassador to China and first ambassador to the United Nations. When the father opened the Mongolian mission to the United Nations in 1962, the 12-year-old son attended the United Nations School and learned English. (He also discovered Tad's Steaks, the chain that offered bargain flame-broiled steak. ''Can that still cost $1.49?'' he asked. Nope: now it's $8.79.)</p>
        <p>AT 19, Mr. Enkhsaikhan was accepted into the Soviet Union's elite diplomat hatchery, the Moscow State Institute for International Relations. Ultimately he received a doctorate in international law.</p>
        <p>After foreign ministry posts in Mongolia, and a six-year stint in New York where he handled legal and diplomatic chores, he was a surprisingly nonsenior choice to be the second in command at the Mongolian Embassy in Moscow in 1988.</p>
        <p>It was there that he played his part in Russian history. On the second day after the 1990 coup, a power struggle in the Foreign Ministry resulted in a dangerous phone call from some of his former institute classmates, Ambassador Enkhsaikhan recalled.</p>
        <p>Boris Yeltsin's allies, denied access to fax machines by the Soviets, ''asked if I could be of help, by faxing out translations of Yeltsin's decrees,'' Mr. Enkhsaikhan said.</p>
        <p>''It was crucial to demonstrate that he was in charge and issuing laws.''</p>
        <p>In truth, Mr. Enkhsaikhan was being asked to commit Mongolia to the outcome of the revolution. He got his ambassador to agree, then faxed the Yeltsin decrees. ''It was really simple,'' he said. ''We had to choose sides.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
