<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Polls Show Virtual Tie in the Crucial Presidential Race in Mexico</title>
    <meta content="Y24MEX$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fox Quesada, Vicente (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labastida Ochoa, Francisco (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dillon, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFDA1730F937A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Polls Show Virtual Tie in the Crucial Presidential Race in Mexico</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM DILLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dillon, Sam</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, June 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public opinion surveys show Francisco Labastida Ochoa, candidate of Mexico's governing Institutional Revolutionary Party, and Vicente Fox Quesada of center right National Action Party in virtual tie in presidential election, with as many as one-fourth of voters undecided (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Public opinion surveys show the two leading presidential candidates in a virtual tie before the election on July 2, with as many as one-fourth of the voters undecided.</p>
        <p>Three polls show the candidate of the governing party, Francisco Labastida Ochoa, leading by a slender margin. A fourth survey showed Vicente Fox Quesada of the center-right National Action Party slightly ahead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Public opinion surveys show the two leading presidential candidates in a virtual tie before the election on July 2, with as many as one-fourth of the voters undecided.</p>
        <p>Three polls show the candidate of the governing party, Francisco Labastida Ochoa, leading by a slender margin. A fourth survey showed Vicente Fox Quesada of the center-right National Action Party slightly ahead.</p>
        <p>The half-dozen polls were issued on Wednesday and Thursday. A law prohibits publishing polling information from midnight tonight until 8 p.m. on Election Day.</p>
        <p>The polls show that the race in which Mr. Labastida enjoyed an overwhelming advantage over Mr. Fox has continued to narrow.</p>
        <p>And they have intensified the extraordinary uncertainty and tension about the outcome of an election that has become a plebiscite on whether the Institutional Revolutionary Party, known as the PRI, should continue to govern after 71 years in power.</p>
        <p>''Either candidate, Labastida or Fox, could win this election,'' Alejandro Moreno, chief pollster at Reforma, a newspaper here, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>In the survey that Reforma published on Thursday, Mr. Labastida was favored by 34 percent, Mr. Fox by 32 and Cuauhtemoc Cardenas, a leftist, by 13. Three percent said they would vote for minor candidates or no candidate, and 19 percent said they were undecided or refused to respond. The margin of sampling error was plus or minus 3 percentage points.</p>
        <p>Another poll, commissioned by Reuters and conducted by Zogby International, a research concern in New York, showed Mr. Labastida supported by 31 percent of voters, Mr. Fox by 29 percent and Mr. Cardenas by 10 percent. The margin of sampling error was plus or minus 3 percentage points.</p>
        <p>About 3 percent of those surveyed said they supported minor candidates, and 27 percent said they were undecided or declined to respond, the president of the business, John Zogby, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>In a third survey, conducted by Grupo de Economistas Asociados, a research concern here, Mr. Fox was supported by 32 percent, Mr. Labastida 31 percent and Mr. Cardenas by 15 percent. Twenty percent were undecided. Two percent supported minor candidates. The margin of sampling error was plus or minus 4 percentage points.</p>
        <p>''It's really a tie,'' said the director of the organization, Mauricio Gonzalez Gomez.</p>
        <p>The polls started a debate about how to interpret the high number of uncommitted voters. Some experts said the undecided and nonresponsive voters, whose numbers ranged from 18 to 27 percent, represented the percentage of eligible voters who were highly unlikely to cast ballots.</p>
        <p>Other experts said the high percentage reflected the high level of fear in the electorate after an extraordinarily bitter campaign.</p>
        <p>Complaints have been heard across Mexico that officials of the government and the PRI have threatened that voters would lose access to welfare and farm programs if Mr. Fox won.</p>
        <p>As a result, some experts said, many people who express indecision are reluctant to acknowledge their intentions to vote for the opposition.</p>
        <p>Most surveys before the last presidential election, in 1994, predicted that the PRI would earn 2 to 3 percentage points more than the party eventually received.</p>
        <p>Several new surveys showed that when voters were asked to leave aside their preferences and to say whom they expected to win, significantly more Mexicans said they believed that Mr. Labastida would win.</p>
        <p>In 1994, the PRI won votes from many Mexicans by portraying itself as the party that could offer stability in a dangerous world.</p>
        <p>This year, as Mr. Fox has campaigned as the candidate of change, Mr. Labastida has again been playing on voters' fears.</p>
        <p>A survey by another group, Consultores y Marketing Politico, suggested that the tactic could be effective. Asked to choose between social peace and having a new party in power, nearly 8 in 10 voters said they preferred stability.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
