<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Unknown Lifts the Yanks, but Rivera Lets Them Down</title>
    <meta content="24YANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDD1430F937A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Unknown Lifts the Yanks, but Rivera Lets Them Down</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago White Sox defeat New York Yankees, 4-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees were pummeled last week by the Chicago White Sox at Yankee Stadium. The two-time defending World Series champions lost four games in their backyard in emphatic fashion and trudged around like shadows of their former selves. They were also ornery about losing two games to the Boston Red Sox this week and splitting a pivotal series they could have swept.</p>
        <p>All of their angst had been building, and the Yankees had to turn to Ben Ford to help them find redemption against the team with the best record in the American League.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Yankees were pummeled last week by the Chicago White Sox at Yankee Stadium. The two-time defending World Series champions lost four games in their backyard in emphatic fashion and trudged around like shadows of their former selves. They were also ornery about losing two games to the Boston Red Sox this week and splitting a pivotal series they could have swept.</p>
        <p>All of their angst had been building, and the Yankees had to turn to Ben Ford to help them find redemption against the team with the best record in the American League.</p>
        <p>Ben Who? Ford is the 24-year-old rookie who has been a reliever for all but two starts in his career. He was rushed to the major leagues because of Orlando Hernandez's sprained right elbow.</p>
        <p>It was not Ford who failed the Yankees as he pitched effectively into the seventh inning. It was Mariano Rivera who failed them. Carlos Lee belted a leadoff homer in the ninth inning and Jose Valentin had a two-out broken-bat single to deliver Herbert Perry with the decisive run as the White Sox rallied for two runs in the ninth to win, 4-3, beating the Yankees for the fifth straight game.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, I was trying to do my job in the ninth,'' Rivera said. ''I couldn't do it.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees (36-32) dropped to third place in the A.L. East, one game behind the first-place Blue Jays (40-34) and a half game behind the Red Sox (37-32). After losing their third straight game, the Yankees are as low as third for the first time since April 18, 1999.</p>
        <p>The White Sox slowly gained more fan support as 38,773 fans came to Comiskey Park on a muggy, rainy night. They came to see if the surging White Sox could stymie the Yankees again. Few came to watch Ford.</p>
        <p>But he lasted into the seventh, Jeff Nelson rescued him by wriggling through a bases-loaded, one-out jam and the Yankees used run-scoring hits by Bernie Williams and Shane Spencer in the eighth to take a 3-2 lead. Rivera stranded a runner in the eighth, but he crumbled in the ninth and botched his third save in 19 chances. The Yankees' closer mishandled four saves in 49 chances all of last season.</p>
        <p>''Mo is human, I guess,'' Manager Joe Torre said. ''We're finding that out. We'll still take our chances with him.''</p>
        <p>Even though the Yankees are pursuing offense and again showed they need it because Paul O'Neill's homer was all they managed off starter Jim Parque, Ford delighted them with his poise.</p>
        <p>Hernandez will toss a ball on Saturday and could be placed on the disabled list if he feels uncomfortable, which would probably keep Ford in the rotation. For one night, Ford, who had the flu, looked as if he belonged. But, for the fifth straight game, the White Sox humbled the Yankees.</p>
        <p>''I'm upset about the loss,'' Ford said. ''It's hard to take, but I'm happy with where I'm at.''</p>
        <p>The first thing Ford had to do when he arrived at Comiskey was locate his locker. He ambled into the clubhouse about two and a half hours before the game and walked right past the locker with ''FORD 31'' above it. It was the third time in seven games that the Yankees started a rookie.</p>
        <p>When Torre was asked why the Yankees selected Ford, a career reliever, to start, the manager answered, ''I have no clue.'' Torre freely admitted that he does not analyze what is happening with Class AAA Columbus and accepts whatever recommendations the organization makes. The organization selected Ford, who had made 282 straight relief appearances before starting twice this month.</p>
        <p>Someone asked Torre if he would recognize Ford and he said, ''Hopefully, I'll recognize him for about six or seven innings.''</p>
        <p>That was Torre's way of asking Ford to keep the Yankees close until the sixth or the seventh in his first major league start, which he did. Ford made eight appearances for Arizona in 1998, but, before June 2, he had not started since high school.</p>
        <p>After Ford walked Ray Durham, the leadoff batter, and Valentin reached on an infield single in the first, Frank Thomas hit a rocket to left field. Ford could have been in deep trouble, but Spencer hustled to the warning track and made a leaping catch. When Magglio Ordonez rapped into a double play, Ford eased off the mound.</p>
        <p>Ford, who is 6 feet 7 inches tall and who throws a sharp fastball, kept the White Sox scoreless and matched Parque until the fourth. But Valentin had another infield single, and Ford walked Thomas and Ordonez to fill the bases.</p>
        <p>After the pitching coach Mel Stottlemyre visited Ford, he produced a double-play groundout that gave the White Sox a 1-0 lead. It was a huge double play because now Ford could see his seat in the dugout. Another out and the damage would be kept to one run. Ford jammed Chris Singleton, but he blooped a single between a plodding Williams and a diving Spencer to make the score 2-0. Though they lost that lead, the White Sox still have the Yankees' number.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>As BERNIE WILLIAMS was discussing how JUAN GONZALEZ or SAMMY SOSA or any high-profile personality would fit on the Yankees, he brought up DAVID WELLS, ROGER CLEMENS and CHAD CURTIS as players who made adjustments when they came to New York. ''This team has a way of doing away with attitudes,'' Williams said. ''Boomer, Roger and Chad Curtis are all guys who came here with attitude problems. We have so many guys who know how to play, they have no choice but to follow.'' . . . CHUCK KNOBLAUCH was the designated hitter for the second time in three games tonight as JOSE VIZCAINO made his first start as a Yankee at second base. . . . The game was delayed 68 minutes by rain in the sixth.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
