<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Player Shakes Up Coca-Cola Bias Case; Some Workers Face a Tough Choice</title>
    <meta content="Y24GAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Law</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Willie E. Gary</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coca-Cola Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gary, Willie E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mehri, Cyrus</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1DC1730F937A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2197" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Player Shakes Up Coca-Cola Bias Case; Some Workers Face a Tough Choice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Attorney Willie E Gary enters federal racial-discrimination lawsuit against Coca-Cola, dividing plaintiffs by promising them larger financial settlement than their current attorney, Cyrus Mehri; tangled web between Coke and Gary described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To his old friend the Rev. Jesse Jackson, Willie E. Gary is ''a bigger-than-life character.'' Indeed, whether the topic is compensation for a client in one of the hundreds of personal-injury cases he has taken on, or the fine points of his private jet, a Gulfstream II soon to be replaced by a Boeing 737, Mr. Gary is a man who thinks in outsized proportions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary, 52, has been practicing law for the last 25 years and presides over his own firm, housed in a baronial waterfront office in Stuart, Fla., half an hour north of Palm Beach. Among his courtroom triumphs was a $500 million award in 1995 for a Mississippi funeral home owner who sued the Loewen Group. It was then the biggest verdict in Mississippi history, and was eventually reduced to $175 million, still a tidy sum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To his old friend the Rev. Jesse Jackson, Willie E. Gary is ''a bigger-than-life character.'' Indeed, whether the topic is compensation for a client in one of the hundreds of personal-injury cases he has taken on, or the fine points of his private jet, a Gulfstream II soon to be replaced by a Boeing 737, Mr. Gary is a man who thinks in outsized proportions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary, 52, has been practicing law for the last 25 years and presides over his own firm, housed in a baronial waterfront office in Stuart, Fla., half an hour north of Palm Beach. Among his courtroom triumphs was a $500 million award in 1995 for a Mississippi funeral home owner who sued the Loewen Group. It was then the biggest verdict in Mississippi history, and was eventually reduced to $175 million, still a tidy sum.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary is well aware of his power, stemming from dozens of similar successes. So his sudden decision this spring to take up the cause of black Coca-Cola employees in their racial-discrimination claims against the company has created no small commotion, dividing the plaintiffs by promising to win them enormous sums of money and threatening the tentative settlement in the federal lawsuit that was announced last week.</p>
        <p>For the Coke employees, some of whom had lost faith in the original legal team, Mr. Gary's leap into the case changes the equation. Now that a settlement is close, they must decide, once details are made available this fall, whether to stay that course or switch to Mr. Gary.</p>
        <p>''We're between a rock and a hard place,'' said Kenneth Phillips, who was laid off in February as a computer engineer in Coke's Atlanta headquarters. He is not a plaintiff, but would be covered by the settlement, which includes current and former employees from 1995 to now. ''They are playing games with people's lives.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary promises more cash for his clients than he says the lead lawyer, Cyrus Mehri, has sought from Coke. Mr. Mehri says he has never discussed specifics with Mr. Gary, whose pledge has helped him attract four of the eight named plaintiffs, along with some of the 2,000 current and former Coke employees who would be included under the settlement.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Gary has begun a fresh offensive against Coke. Teaming up with Johnnie L. Cochran, the lawyer who defended O. J. Simpson, Mr. Gary filed a $1.5 billion lawsuit in Georgia state court contending that a group of black women who worked at Coke were subjected to a hostile work environment, racial harassment and other unfair treatment. One woman, the complaint stated, was told to clear away lunch plates and ''made to feel more like a maid than a paraprofessional.'' Another was supposedly paid $15,000 to $20,000 less than white colleagues in similar jobs.</p>
        <p>A Coke executive, Carl Ware, has called the Gary-Cochran lawsuit ''an 11th-hour act of blatant and disruptive legal maneuvering'' intended to derail the settlement.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Gary is no stranger to the company, and his complicated relationship with Coke is seen by many as a major factor in the legal role he is now playing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson introduced him to the company's former chairman and chief executive, M. Douglas Ivester, in January -- thinking, he recalled, that Mr. Gary could give Coke some advice on how to handle the lawsuit. In March, Coke's marketing department completed a major advertising deal with Mr. Gary's recently formed cable TV channel, MBC Network.</p>
        <p>In April, Mr. Gary was contacted by one of the plaintiffs who was looking for a new lawyer; Mr. Jackson had provided Mr. Gary's name.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary's bid to join the federal lawsuit, on the plaintiffs' side, was rejected by the judge. But his dealings with Coke have provoked questions about his ability to represent Coke employees properly. He says he will file his own lawsuits and not worry about any class-action aspects, where the potential conflicts of interest are particularly potent. The separate settlement from Coke, he says, actually makes his job easier. ''Basically, they will have admitted their wrongdoing,'' he said in an interview at his office in Stuart, ''and that's a hurdle I won't have to cross.''</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, his only experience in a class-action discrimination lawsuit has been defending a Florida sugar company sued by West Indian cane cutters in a case that he won and is being appealed. In 1998, he was fined by the court for being abusive to lawyers on the other side, trial documents show. A spokeswoman for Mr. Gary said the order was later dismissed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary traces his interest in the Coke case to his father, who spent much of his life being underpaid as he picked string beans, cabbage and other crops in sweltering fields across the Southeast. Dividing the Coke plaintiffs was not his preference, he said. ''We wanted unity in this case,'' he said. ''But sometimes, it's just not feasible to do it.''</p>
        <p>He said he had explained the details of the advertising deal between his television channel and Coke to the four plaintiffs who hired him. In March, the company agreed to pay several million dollars over five years to show commercials on the MBC Network, a family-entertainment channel aimed at black audiences in several metropolitan areas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary recalls that he began seeking a role on the plaintiffs' side in the Coke lawsuit in April. Then on May 9, MBC announced the advertising deal. Newspaper reports about it came as a surprise to most of the black employees who had met with Mr. Gary individually and in group meetings in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gary was ready with damage control. ''When he flew his staff of attorneys in and they broke it down, then we understood,'' said a Coke employee involved in the case. ''He is not someone that Coke wants to see.'' Those lawyers pointed to a $5 million settlement he got from a Coke bottler for a toddler injured by one of its delivery vans.</p>
        <p>A Coke spokesman said the company sought the advertising deal because it wanted to reach the channel's target audience. The channel specializes in religious, sports and entertainment programming for black families; Mr. Gary stars on ''Spiritual Impact,'' his own talk show. ''There was no awareness on the part of the lawyers at Coke that we were having negotiations for a media buy with MBC,'' said the spokesman, Rob Baskin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary sees no conflict. ''If my standing up for my principles and what I believe in is going to make them cancel the contract,'' he said, ''then the hell with the contract.''</p>
        <p>He has no trouble, he says, distinguishing between Coke, his opponent in the lawsuit, and Coke, his business partner. ''They allowed this to happen,'' he said, his voice rising. ''They knew it was happening, and they didn't do anything about it. It would be a sad day in America if they got away with it.''</p>
        <p>Others, however, say that Mr. Gary should avoid even the appearance of conflict. ''It's not a matter of which he cares about more,'' said John Coffee, a professor at Columbia University Law School who has kept a close eye on the Coke lawsuit. ''It's that the interests overlap.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mehri, the plaintiffs' lawyer who represented black workers at Texaco in a racial-discrimination case that was settled for $140 million in 1996, said he was put off by Mr. Gary's whirlwind attempt to become co-lead counsel on the federal class-action lawsuit. ''We could not rule out the possibility of a conflict of interest, even though we did not know the full extent of his relationship with the company,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson's relationship with Coke is also complex. The company supports his social-action organization, Operation Rainbow/PUSH, and the organization owns a small stake in the company. For the last two years, Coke has been a major sponsor of the group's annual convention, held in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Coke is also a sponsor of the Wall Street Project, a program led by Mr. Jackson that seeks to improve investment opportunities, including access to capital, for minorities.</p>
        <p>At the Coca-Cola annual meeting this year in Delaware, Mr. Jackson delivered an impassioned oration on the lack of diversity at Coke. But he did not endorse the boycott of Coke products called for by the previous speaker, Larry Jones, a former employee who took a busload of black employees from Atlanta to Wilmington. Mr. Jones and several others took the boycott to Manhattan this week, holding up placards that read ''Coke Discriminates'' as traffic streamed past them in Times Square.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary's connection to Mr. Jackson, and both men's ties to Coke, are sources of concern to some. ''Now Willie Gary comes in, and he has a strong tie with Jesse Jackson, yet Jesse Jackson has a strong tie with Coke,'' Mr. Phillips said. ''It's very chaotic.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Jackson said he originally thought Mr. Gary could serve as Coke's peacemaker. ''I thought Willie could help them resolve the crisis,'' he said. ''They could have no doubt used his services. He could have at least laid out for them what the options were.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary has great rapport with juries, evoking his country roots to stupendous effect. And he works hard at his craft. His personal office, complete with carved stone fireplace and full bar, adjoins a paneled miniature courtroom, in which witnesses and lawyers rehearse their lines.</p>
        <p>Asked whether he was prepared to handle the Coke lawsuit, Mr. Gary said he had handled all kinds of corporate litigation, including breach of contract and discrimination cases.  According to some Coke employees, Mr. Gary has made convincing arguments that he can get them a bigger award than Mr. Mehri's team.</p>
        <p>''The ones who are knowledgeable about this will opt out and go to Willie Gary,'' one employee said. ''Willie Gary has profoundly stated that we are aiming for the sky. If it starts at $1 billion, we'll walk away with $1 million.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mehri said he had never discussed the size of the projected settlement with Mr. Gary. ''It is not our practice to discuss settlement strategy with any attorney who comes barreling in off the street,'' he said. ''We never did, and we never would.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mehri has some detractors as well. Concern about his effectiveness escalated in early April after one of the plaintiffs listened in on a conference call between several lawyers on Mr. Mehri's team, Mr. Phillips said, and concluded that Mr. Mehri was not working in everyone's best interests. The concerns included the amount of cash the plaintiffs were likely to receive. Mr. Mehri's team dropped three of the plaintiffs after deciding that they were not acting in the best interests of the whole class.</p>
        <p>Now the Coke employees worry that the tentative settlement will fall short of what they think they deserve. ''I don't want them to go for a small amount of money for all the discrimination that has occurred,'' said Angela Graham, one of the plaintiffs in the lawsuit Mr. Gary filed.</p>
        <p>While some talk of rejecting the settlement, they also express concern that Coke may see the split between the lawyers as a strategic advantage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gary said that would be a mistake. ''The longer they drag out this case, the worse it's going to get,''  he said. ''It's cheaper to do the right thing than to have to deal with a guy like Willie Gary.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
