<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Inning Gives Jones More Than He Needs</title>
    <meta content="24METS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Pirates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Pittsburgh Pirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DD1430F937A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Inning Gives Jones More Than He Needs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Pittsburgh Pirates, 12-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The choice was obvious but not easy. Bobby J. Jones had seven years in the major leagues and the pride that goes with it. But the Mets' right-hander was pitching poorly, and because of off-days in the schedule, the plan was to skip him for two turns through the rotation. The Mets wanted Jones to go to Class AAA Norfolk for a while, to stay sharp and, just maybe, rediscover something. Jones had enough major league service time to veto the demotion, but he accepted it and is glad he did.</p>
        <p>Building off two starts in the minors in which he tinkered with his delivery and fortified his curveball, Jones returned last night and pitched eight strong innings, leading the Mets to a 12-2 victory over the Pittsburgh Pirates at Shea Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The choice was obvious but not easy. Bobby J. Jones had seven years in the major leagues and the pride that goes with it. But the Mets' right-hander was pitching poorly, and because of off-days in the schedule, the plan was to skip him for two turns through the rotation. The Mets wanted Jones to go to Class AAA Norfolk for a while, to stay sharp and, just maybe, rediscover something. Jones had enough major league service time to veto the demotion, but he accepted it and is glad he did.</p>
        <p>Building off two starts in the minors in which he tinkered with his delivery and fortified his curveball, Jones returned last night and pitched eight strong innings, leading the Mets to a 12-2 victory over the Pittsburgh Pirates at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Mets scored nine runs in the third inning, one shy of the highest single-inning total in franchise history. But Jones hardly needed that much support. He allowed five hits and one run, walking two and striking out eight. Those were better numbers than he posted at Norfolk (10 innings, 15 hits, 7 earned runs), but numbers did not matter there.</p>
        <p>''You have an opportunity to work on things without having that much pressure on you,'' Jones said of his stay in the minors. ''I think that I needed that, to go down there and just be able to work on things.''</p>
        <p>Jones does not throw hard, and his assortment of pitches is considered below average. But he has been able to master that stuff well enough to have made an All-Star team and to have started three times on opening day. At Norfolk, he threw more fastballs than usual, searching to rediscover his command of the pitch.</p>
        <p>He also adjusted his delivery. Jones had altered it in spring training, pumping his hands together in front of his body in an effort to get the ball out of his glove quicker. At Norfolk, he found a way to remove the ball on time while keeping his hands at chest level, and he noticed he was getting better downward movement on his fastball.</p>
        <p>He also worked to improve his curveball, and the combination devastated the Pirates. In his last start for the Mets, a 13-5 loss at Yankee Stadium on June 10, the Yankees swung and missed at only two of Jones's first 47 pitches. Last night, he got better results immediately.</p>
        <p>The Pirates' leadoff hitter, Warren Morris, struck out swinging on a high fastball. Jason Kendall was next, and he swung through an outside fastball -- 87 miles an hour on the Mets' radar gun, which Manager Bobby Valentine believes is probably the slowest in the National League -- for strike three.</p>
        <p>Wil Cordero then swung and missed at two curveballs before popping out on a fastball for the third out.</p>
        <p>''The first batter, every pitch was crisp,'' Valentine said. ''You can't really tell what you're going to get -- things change in a hurry in our game -- but the first inning was the perfect inning. He threw crisp pitch after crisp pitch, right where Mike was sitting.''</p>
        <p>After the Mets' nine-run third put them ahead by 10-1, Jones told catcher Mike Piazza that he wanted to continue using all his pitches, to pitch as if the score was 1-1.</p>
        <p>''I had something to prove tonight,'' Jones said. ''I had to stay with my game plan.''</p>
        <p>He stayed with it, but the first batter of the fourth, Cordero, stroked a double down the left-field line. Jones escaped the inning scoreless, getting two fly outs and fanning Aramis Ramirez, squelching a big inning before it could start.</p>
        <p>Besides his victory over Arizona on May 19 and an abbreviated April start in which he strained a calf muscle, Jones had allowed at least three runs in an inning in all of his starts.</p>
        <p>His focus never wavered, Valentine said. Jones is not expressive when he pitches, and people can mistake that for nonchalance. But Valentine said he observed a ''determined competitor'' last night.</p>
        <p>''Some people may think that he doesn't care,'' Valentine said. ''He cares as much as anybody that there is.''</p>
        <p>The Mets supported Jones (2-3) with a run on a bases-loaded balk in the second, but the Pirates tied the score, 1-1, in the third. That was the last time the game was close.</p>
        <p>With two runners on and one out in the third, the Pirates rookie starter Bronson Arroyo went up and in with a fastball to Piazza, who turned on it and looped it into the left-field bleachers for a three-run homer. The Mets had a 4-1 lead, Piazza had his 21st home run (and third in his last three games), and a rout was on.</p>
        <p>With two men on, Jay Payton's bouncer took a bad hop and ruined the Pirates' chances of an inning-ending double play. One run scored, and three batters later, Melvin Mora drove in three runs with a double.</p>
        <p>The Pirates helped out with two errors in the third, and by the time Piazza struck out to end the inning, the Mets had scored nine runs in an inning for just the fifth time in their history. The Mets have scored more runs in an inning only once, when they posted a 10-run sixth on June 12, 1979, against Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Mets reserve JOE McEWING doubled in the seventh inning last night. McEwing has 17 hits for the Mets, and 11 are doubles. . . . The right-hander GRANT ROBERTS has had only modest success at Class AAA Norfolk this year -- he is 4-4 with a 4.76 E.R.A. -- but he is attracting the interest of other teams as the Mets approach the trading deadline. Scouts from seven teams -- including Minnesota, Los Angeles, Kansas City, Oakland and the Cubs -- attended Roberts's last start.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
