<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dummy Became an Island, And a Slam Sank Helplessly</title>
    <meta content="24CARD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1D61630F937A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dummy Became an Island, And a Slam Sank Helplessly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott bridge column on knockout teams play at Tri-State Regional Championships; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A lead that might be the most devastating of the year contributed to a result that might be the most surprising of the year. It occurred in January at the Tri-State Regional Championships in Port Chester, N.Y., and the event was a bracketed knockout teams, in which the best teams, based on masterpoint holdings, form the top bracket.</p>
        <p>Included in this group, just barely, was a cinderella team: Sheila Cornstein, Susan Mendik, Emily Seiden and Carol Silvera. Mendik and Silvera were on the brink of becoming life masters, and the others had recently acquired that title. Between them they owned some 1,700 master points, and their chances of victory were effectively zero. The field included bunches of world and national champions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A lead that might be the most devastating of the year contributed to a result that might be the most surprising of the year. It occurred in January at the Tri-State Regional Championships in Port Chester, N.Y., and the event was a bracketed knockout teams, in which the best teams, based on masterpoint holdings, form the top bracket.</p>
        <p>Included in this group, just barely, was a cinderella team: Sheila Cornstein, Susan Mendik, Emily Seiden and Carol Silvera. Mendik and Silvera were on the brink of becoming life masters, and the others had recently acquired that title. Between them they owned some 1,700 master points, and their chances of victory were effectively zero. The field included bunches of world and national champions.</p>
        <p>They fought hard to reach the semifinal and were now overmatched: Their opponents owned more than 50,000 points and hundreds of titles. But study the diagramed deal, on which both North-South pairs reached seven no-trump. In the auction shown, the four-club bid is Gerber, asking for aces. When South admits to owning one, North bids seven no-trump, expecting that his partner will be able to claim 13 tricks quickly.</p>
        <p>That was the result when Seiden was declaring for the Cornstein team. The opening lead was a club, and the ace won in dummy. South cashed the ace and king of diamonds, providing for the possibility that the diamond queen would fall singleton or doubleton and that the hearts would break badly. Then she took her five black-suit club winners.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, she had 13 tricks because the hearts split normally. If they had not, there was a good chance that the player with the heart length would have been squeezed in some fashion.</p>
        <p>In the replay against the same contract, Cornstein selected the spade ten as her opening lead. Attacking declarer's long suit is not normally a good move, but here it was devastating.</p>
        <p>South's communications were now shattered and he could no longer score three club tricks. He managed two by throwing the club ace on a spade winner, but had to fall back eventually on a diamond finesse. When this failed, the result was one down and the Cornstein team had won 17 imps, which helped carry them to victory in the match.</p>
        <p>Buoyed by this success, the Cornstein foursome went on to win the final. A remarkable lead had produced a remarkable result.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
