<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israeli Rivals Use Media Leaks In the Fight Over Peace Talks</title>
    <meta content="Y24MIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharon, Ariel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharansky, Natan (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E2DB1730F937A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israeli Rivals Use Media Leaks In the Fight Over Peace Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Campaign of media leaks is under way by political rivals in Israel to expose bargaining positions in peace talks with Palestinians and put pressure on Prime Min Ehud Barak not to make significant concessions; latest leak of US document containing plausible outline of possible peace settlement, which was obtained by rightist Likud leader Ariel Sharon and Interior Min Natan Sharansky, discussed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A campaign of leaks is under way to pre-expose Israel's bargaining positions in its peace negotiations so as to put pressure on Prime Minister Ehud Barak against making significant concessions to the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>The latest leak came today when an Israeli newspaper printed the contents of what it called an American ''nonpaper'' that it said could provide the basis for a three-way, retreat-style summit meeting in the Washington area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A campaign of leaks is under way to pre-expose Israel's bargaining positions in its peace negotiations so as to put pressure on Prime Minister Ehud Barak against making significant concessions to the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>The latest leak came today when an Israeli newspaper printed the contents of what it called an American ''nonpaper'' that it said could provide the basis for a three-way, retreat-style summit meeting in the Washington area.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials dismissed the document as speculative, and Americans officials said it was unofficial, of unknown origin and inaccurate.</p>
        <p>Still, the document, as summed up by the newspaper Yediot Ahronot, does contain the plausible outline of an eventual agreement. The newspaper said Interior Minister Natan Sharansky and Ariel Sharon, leader of the rightist Likud Party, had obtained the document. The office of Mr. Sharanksy said he had provided it to the newspaper.</p>
        <p>The document says Israel would be able to consolidate and annex settlement blocs with Palestinian assent, if it gave up equivalent territory elsewhere. It says some 40,000 settlers would have to be evacuated or, if the Palestinians agreed, remain under Palestinian rule.</p>
        <p>It says that if the Palestinians agreed, the Jordan Valley would be transferred to full Palestinian control, but leased back to Israel.</p>
        <p>It says that the principle of the right of return of Palestinian refugees would be granted, but that very few refugees would actually be allowed to come back. An ''opaque formula'' would expand a family reunification plan that already exists, under a different name.</p>
        <p>It says Mr. Barak is contemplating conceding Arab neighborhoods in Jerusalem to Palestinian control in exchange for a Palestinian declaration that the conflict is over.</p>
        <p>And it says the United States and other Western nations would pledge an aid package of more than $100 billion that would be distributed over 20 years. Most of the money would constitute a compensation package for Palestinian refugees and their host countries.</p>
        <p>A Western diplomat who saw the document said it was handwritten and seemed to contain notes from a briefing by a Jewish-American official. The notes refer to ''our land'' and ''our settlements.''</p>
        <p>Several weeks ago, Mr. Sharansky released what he said was his understanding of Mr. Barak's intended concessions in an anguished letter to the prime minister that he made public. Today, the essence of Mr. Sharansky's letter was reprinted in full-page advertisements here, under the headline: ''Dear Prime Minister Barak: We are seriously concerned.'' It is signed by members and leaders of several American Jewish organizations.</p>
        <p>Late today, Mr. Sharanksy, whose Russian immigrant party remains part of Mr. Barak's fragile coalition, sent the prime minister a letter accusing him of keeping the coalition partners in the dark about the substance of the negotiations. He said Mr. Barak planned to co-opt critics in his cabinet by taking them with him to Washington, but that it would not work: ''We will be left with only one choice -- to agree to an accord to which we are opposed, or to reject it and return home. This may sound simple in theory, but I know and you know that the option to reject an agreement is unrealistic and would lead to the disgrace of Israel before the world.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharanksy urged Mr. Barak to stop his ''race toward a summit'' and to work more closely with his coalition partners to forge a consensus agreement. Mr. Sharanksy said he would ''end the partnership between us'' if Mr. Barak did not agree.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
