<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Davies Feels Cozy And Leads By 2 Shots</title>
    <meta content="24LPGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mcdonald's Lpga Championship</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davies, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4D71730F937A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Davies Feels Cozy And Leads By 2 Shots</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>WILMINGTON, Del., June 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laura Davies leads after second round of McDonald's LPGA Championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shortly after arriving at DuPont Country Club this week, Laura Davies felt good about her chances.</p>
        <p>''When I walked in the locker room, and I hear all the whining about it's long and it's tough, I just love it,'' Davies said. ''They get a tough course, it's a major championship, and there's a lot of whining that goes on. They like the shorter, easier courses. I like the longer, tougher courses.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shortly after arriving at DuPont Country Club this week, Laura Davies felt good about her chances.</p>
        <p>''When I walked in the locker room, and I hear all the whining about it's long and it's tough, I just love it,'' Davies said. ''They get a tough course, it's a major championship, and there's a lot of whining that goes on. They like the shorter, easier courses. I like the longer, tougher courses.''</p>
        <p>And after the second round today, Davies also likes her chances to win another McDonald's Ladies Professional Golf Association Championship. Ending her day with three consecutive birdies and shooting a five-under-par 66, Davies was six under par (136) for the tournament. She held a two-stroke lead over Wendy Ward.</p>
        <p>Ward, who shot a 69, was four under par for the tournament, while Jan Stephenson, who also shot 69, was tied for third place at three under par with Stefania Croce, who shot 67. Karrie Webb, trying to win her third consecutive major, was even par (142), six strokes behind Davies after a second-round 70.</p>
        <p>It is easy to understand why Davies has won three times at DuPont -- in 1993, before the event was a major, and at major championships in 1994 and in 1996. Driving the ball is her strength, and the layout at DuPont, which gives her an opportunity to cut loose off the tee, plays into her hands.</p>
        <p>''Of all the courses we play all year, this is the only one that genuinely makes it a real advantage to the long hitters,'' Davies said. ''That's why I love it so much, because I can get out there and have some fun with the driver.''</p>
        <p>Having fun is rarely a problem for Davies, who at age 36 remains one of the tour's most jovial players. She has won 4 majors and 18 L.P.G.A. tournaments, yet she leaves her game at the course, and admits she does not like to practice.</p>
        <p>''I have always said, 'If I can't see the range, I won't go to the range,' '' Davies said.</p>
        <p>Webb's domination of the L.P.G.A. Tour for the last 18 months has forced Davies to reassess her ways. Davies did not win an L.P.G.A. Tour event last year, and now she spends time at the range.</p>
        <p>''I've never been dedicated to anything, but I'm certainly practicing a bit more,'' Davies said.</p>
        <p>It paid off today. Davies made six birdies and only one bogey, and she nearly made a hole in one at the par-3 No. 17, hitting an 8-iron shot from 156 yards that stopped just inches from the cup for an easy tap-in birdie.</p>
        <p>''I could hear the crowd getting louder and louder, and I really thought it was going in,'' Davies said.</p>
        <p>The three players closest to Davies are facing a difficult challenge, particularly on this course and in a major championship. Ward has never won a major. Croce, a 30-year-old player from Italy, has never won a tournament. And Stephenson, who is 48, has not won a tournament since 1987, when she was one of the tour's best players.</p>
        <p>''This course suits Laura to a tee,'' said Stephenson, who has rebuilt her career and her swing after injuring her hand after being mugged in 1990.</p>
        <p>''If I hit in the rough, I have to chip out. Laura can power her way through.''</p>
        <p>So Davies entered the weekend feeling confident about her game, and comfortable in her surroundings.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't say I come expecting to win,'' she said. ''But I fancy my chances every time we come here.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Four players were tied at two under par -- JANE GEDDES, the first-round leader, who shot 74, MICHELE REDMAN, WENDY DOOLAN and TRACY HANSON. The defending champion, JULI INKSTER, and PAT HURST were one under par; ANNIKA SORENSTAM one over par; DOTTIE PEPPER two over; SHERRI STEINHAUER three over; BETSY KING four over; and NANCY LOPEZ five over. . . . Notables who missed the five-over-par cut included LORIE KANE (seven over), CHARLOTTA SORENSTAM (eight over), and GRACE PARK (nine over). . . . HELEN DOBSON withdrew after injuring herself while hitting the ball out of the rough.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
