<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Charity Wins Its Argument With a Trust, but Is Still Denied the Money</title>
    <meta content="22CHAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/nyregion/22CHAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Big Red Boat II (Cruise Ship)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Primier Cruise Lines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christian, Nichole M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0D7113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Charity Wins Its Argument With a Trust, but Is Still Denied the Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TAMAR LEWIN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>More than 200 crew members of cruise ship Big Red Boat II are stranded without pay in Staten Island; ship is being held in port because of lawsuit brought against Premier Cruise Lines by suppliers, who claim thay have not received payment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a bitter fight between two old-line New York charities, a state appeals court yesterday ruled that a foundation that administers charitable gifts from hundreds of trust funds wrongly redirected money designated for a society that aids the poor -- but the court also said the challenge came so late that the claims were barred.</p>
        <p>The 155-year-old Community Service Society filed claims against the 76-year-old New York Community Trust five years ago, charging that it should not have interfered since 1971 with the wishes of six donors who had specified that the society should receive money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a bitter fight between two old-line New York charities, a state appeals court yesterday ruled that a foundation that administers charitable gifts from hundreds of trust funds wrongly redirected money designated for a society that aids the poor -- but the court also said the challenge came so late that the claims were barred.</p>
        <p>The 155-year-old Community Service Society filed claims against the 76-year-old New York Community Trust five years ago, charging that it should not have interfered since 1971 with the wishes of six donors who had specified that the society should receive money.</p>
        <p>The question before the court was how much discretion community trusts have to reroute a donor's gift from one charity to another -- a murky legal issue that cuts close to the heart of more than 540 community foundations nationwide.</p>
        <p>Such foundations exist in part to make sure that as years go by and donors die, their bequests do not go on flowing to outdated charities. In the early 1900's, when the first community foundations were formed, supporters of the concept cited, for example, an endowment Benjamin Franklin left to aid apprentices -- a group that no longer existed in America.</p>
        <p>But because the opinion by Justice Richard T. Andrias of the Appellate Division of the State Supreme Court in Manhattan dealt so specifically with the facts of the case, delving at length into the particulars of the community trust's long relationship with the society, it was unclear how the opinion would affect the way that community foundations distribute the $25 billion in trust funds they control.</p>
        <p>''We believe the court ruled properly in determining that the events which formed the focus of this lawsuit happened too long ago to have any merit,'' said Lorie A. Slutsky, president of the trust.</p>
        <p>She and others at the trust, however, were disturbed by the ruling's findings on the standards for redirecting money, standards that they said would require community foundations ''to guess the thoughts of a deceased donor.''</p>
        <p>Henry Christensen, the lawyer for the Community Service Society, said that even though his client lost, as a technical matter, the ruling helped to  establish rigorous, and important,  standards for trusts' decisions to redirect money.</p>
        <p>''The reason everyone's been watching this so closely is that this is the first time, in a contested case, that a court has said these decisions are subject to judicial review, and the standard is abuse of discretion, not gross malfeasance,'' he said. ''That's very significant.''</p>
        <p>Both sides said they were considering an appeal.</p>
        <p>Back in 1971, the New York Community Trust redirected money from six trusts that had specifically named the Community Service Society as a recipient, including the bequest of Laura Spelman Rockefeller, made in 1928, which gave 10 percent of its income to the society.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the trust redirected money that had been designated for several other charities, including the American Cancer Society, the American Heart Association, the N.A.A.C.P., the Federation of Jewish Philanthropies, Catholic Charities of the Archdiocese of New York, the Salvation Army, the United Hospital Fund and The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>The New York Community Trust is the nation's largest community foundation, with $2 billion in assets and $131 million in grants last year. The foundation's trust document allows it to redirect funds whenever circumstances change so much as to ''render unnecessary, undesirable, impractical or impossible'' the terms of the original gift.</p>
        <p>In the case of the Community Service Society, the trust decided in a 1971 review that the group was no longer a desirable beneficiary because of a change in its approach to its work with the poor.</p>
        <p>''The whole point of community foundations was to allow for variances, because often, needs change and gifts given in good faith don't pan out,'' said Gregory Diskant, a New York lawyer who represented the Council on Foundations in Washington, which filed a ''friend of the court'' brief supporting the New York Community Trust. ''And community trusts are a huge success for people smart enough to know they can't foresee the future.''</p>
        <p>David R. Jones, the president of the Community Service Society, said that although the society cannot recover all of the money, because of the six-year statute of limitations, it would seek to have the community trust honor the donor's original instructions from now on.</p>
        <p>''The language of the trusts hasn't changed, so we plan to go back, now that the courts have found we were stripped inappropriately, and ask the New York Community Trust to give us the income we are supposed to get, going forward, which we think is about half a million a year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
