<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="22PUBL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/nyregion/22PUBL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berezovsky, Boris A</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Natural Blonde (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Godfather of the Kremlin (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5D7113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column notes parties held for Liz Smith, who has published memoir Natural Blonde, and Paul Klebnikov, who has published book Godfather of the Kremlin: Boris Berezovsky and the Looting of Russia; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just Published  And Getting By</p>
        <p>Oh, to be the type of columnist who has a just-published book. The television appearances! The parties!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just Published  And Getting By</p>
        <p>Oh, to be the type of columnist who has a just-published book. The television appearances! The parties!</p>
        <p>First, though, one has to write such a book.</p>
        <p>If one does so, and if one is the columnist LIZ SMITH -- whose memoir, ''Natural Blonde,'' went on sale on Tuesday -- one then has to endure good-natured ribbing from friends like BARBARA WALTERS at -- yes -- a party at Le Cirque 2000.</p>
        <p>All in the interest of accuracy, Ms. Walters insisted.</p>
        <p>And so, those who had not read ''Natural Blonde'' learned the following about Ms. Smith from Ms. Walters: ''She is not a natural blonde. Do not ask me how I know.''</p>
        <p>Those who had not read ''Natural Blonde'' also learned Ms. Smith's age, in a roundabout way. ''She is not 77,'' Ms. Walters said. ''You do not look like this at 77. What you should know is that she is 55, and for 55, not so great.''</p>
        <p>So what is it like to be a columnist at one's own party? Hasn't Ms. Smith covered a lot of parties? How many, anyway?</p>
        <p>''I'd have to sit down and make an educated guess: 30 years, three parties a week, and that's conservative,'' Ms. Smith had said earlier in the evening. ''I'm not a party person, and I have a theory you never get a real story at a party.''</p>
        <p>So much for scoops.</p>
        <p>But there was a real story at this party: the guest list, which Ms. Smith said was ''100 more than it should be.''</p>
        <p>This was why there was a second room waiting for those who found the room in which Ms. Smith was holding forth too crowded. This was also why there was a lot of people-watching by people who are often watched.</p>
        <p>''It's like a living Vanity Fair,'' said the actress CHRISTINE BARANSKI. ''RENATA ADLER, DOMINICK DUNNE and IVANA TRUMP.''</p>
        <p>Not to mention CONNIE CHUNG; SKITCH HENDERSON and his wife, RUTH; HENRY A. KISSINGER; MARY TYLER MOORE and her husband, DR. S. R. LEVINE; BOBBY SHORT; and some well-known faces that did not recognize other well-known faces.</p>
        <p>''I just said hello to MERYL STREEP, not knowing who she was,'' said the author JAMES BRADY. ''See the woman in the green pantsuit?''</p>
        <p>Worth the Weight</p>
        <p>The invitation began ''Mark Dixon invites you,'' but the drinks and hors d'oeuvres were served at the SoHo apartment of the artist EDWINA SANDYS and her husband, RICHARD KAPLAN, an architect.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dixon, it turns out, is Ms. Sandys's son from a previous marriage. The party was for a friend of Mr. Dixon's, PAUL KLEBNIKOV, whose book, ''Godfather of the Kremlin: Boris Berezovsky and the Looting of Russia,'' was just published by Harcourt. Mr. Berezovsky is Russia's leading financier and media tycoon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klebnikov gave Mr. Dixon credit for help. ''Mark ran a management consulting company in Russia,'' he said. ''He sent me all his rejects, and I wrote about them.''</p>
        <p>Someone asked Mr. Klebnikov about possible retribution (Boris N. Yeltsin, Vladimir V. Putin, the International Monetary Fund and the Russian mafia probably would not like what Mr. Klebnikov says about them in the book).</p>
        <p>''I'm not worried,'' he said. ''They've got a lot more than me to worry about.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Klebnikov may not have realized it, though Mr. Kaplan certainly did, but the guests had an elevator to worry about. As the crowd -- which included RICHARD E. OLDENBERG, a former director of the Museum of Modern Art, and PETER FOGES, a television producer -- began to leave, Mr. Kaplan warned, ''This elevator can't take more than 3,000 pounds.'' With eight people inside, Mr. Foges reassured him: ''I weigh very little. I can't vouch for anyone else, but I weigh very little.''</p>
        <p>A man to his right concurred, ''I don't weigh much either. We don't all weigh 3,000 pounds.''</p>
        <p>Off they went, with the elevator creaking and groaning.</p>
        <p>When the doors parted on the ground floor, the elevator operator said: ''Watch your step. It went down too far!''</p>
        <p>The elevator was a foot below ground level. Mr. Foges and the other man looked at each other, shrugged and said, simultaneously, ''Guess we weigh more than 3,000 pounds.''</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
