<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Testimony, Firestone Puts Onus on Ford</title>
    <meta content="Y22TIR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/business/22TIRE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone/Firestone Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goodyear Tire &amp; Rubber Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tire and Rim Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Petrauskas, Helen O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tauzin, Billy (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lampe, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFD8113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Testimony, Firestone Puts Onus on Ford</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Firestone Tire begins unusually explicit attack on safety of Ford Explorers in testimony before House subcommittee as two companies criticize each other's products and executives from both companies try to explain internal documents that committee members found incriminating; Firestone says operating Ford Explorer with its tires inflated to pressure recommended by automaker, 26 pounds per square inch, provides smaller 'margin of safety' than exists for competing sport utility vehicles; Ford says that Firestone tires on 1996 Explorers were involved in fatal rollover accidents at rate 15 times of Goodyear tires on same vehicle; Ford vice president Helen O Petrauskas tells Repr Billy Tauzin, who is presiding at hearing, that 26 pounds per square inch her company recommends is not only optimum level for handling, ride comfort and tire endurance, but is also well within guidelines of Tire and Rim Association; Bridgestone/Firestone Inc executive vice president John Lampe says '26 is the minimum for a speed-rate tire'; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Firestone began an unusually explicit attack on the safety of Ford Explorers in testimony before a House subcommittee today as the two companies criticized each other's products and executives from both companies tried to explain internal documents that committee members found incriminating.</p>
        <p>Firestone said that operating a Ford Explorer with its tires inflated to the pressure recommended by the automaker, 26 pounds per square inch, provided a smaller ''margin of safety'' than existed for the Chevy Tahoe, Jeep Cherokee and other competing sport utility vehicles. Ford said that Firestone tires on 1996 Explorers were involved in fatal rollover accidents at a rate 15 times that of Goodyear tires on the same vehicle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Firestone began an unusually explicit attack on the safety of Ford Explorers in testimony before a House subcommittee today as the two companies criticized each other's products and executives from both companies tried to explain internal documents that committee members found incriminating.</p>
        <p>Firestone said that operating a Ford Explorer with its tires inflated to the pressure recommended by the automaker, 26 pounds per square inch, provided a smaller ''margin of safety'' than existed for the Chevy Tahoe, Jeep Cherokee and other competing sport utility vehicles. Ford said that Firestone tires on 1996 Explorers were involved in fatal rollover accidents at a rate 15 times that of Goodyear tires on the same vehicle.</p>
        <p>At one point, Helen O. Petrauskas, vice president for environmental and safety engineering at Ford, told Representative Billy Tauzin, Republican of Louisiana, who presided at the hearing, that the 26 pounds per square inch her company recommended was not only the optimum level for handling, ride comfort and tire endurance, but was also well within the guidelines of the Tire and Rim Association, an industry group based in Akron, Ohio.</p>
        <p>She was interrupted by John Lampe, executive vice president of Bridgestone/ Firestone Inc., who said that ''26 is the minimum for a speed-rated tire, Congressman.''</p>
        <p>Most tires sold for vehicles that use highways are speed rated, a measure that gives the maximum speed at which they can operate. Mr. Lampe seemed to be suggesting that tires meant for highway use needed a minimum inflation of 26 pounds per square inch. Some tires sold for off-road use are not speed rated.</p>
        <p>The Tire and Rim Association publishes a table that lists the carrying capacity of tires based on their air pressure, which does, in fact, go down to 20 pounds per square inch, although the significance of extending the table that far is not clear, with most highway vehicles carrying inflation recommendations of 26 pounds or higher.</p>
        <p>''The only reason it does is that's how much room there is on the page,'' said an executive at another tire company, who spoke on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>The carrying capacity of the Explorer is an issue because if the tires are overloaded, they overheat and may fail. Firestone agreed a decade ago with the 26-pound recommendation, but Mr. Lampe pointed out today that at 30 pounds per square inch, a level of inflation that his company has been recommending since August, the Explorer can handle 400 more pounds.</p>
        <p>A table distributed by Firestone shows that the 2000 Explorer, with tires inflated at Ford's recommendation of 26 pounds, would be safe. But if the pressure fell by 7 pounds -- as is common, Firestone said, because many people fail to check their tire pressure -- the four-door, four-wheel- drive model would reach its carrying capacity. And if the pressure fell any further, it would be overloaded even if the weight of the passengers and cargo was within Ford's limits. The comparable ''margin of safety'' figures for models with two doors, or two-wheel drive, run from 8 to 12 pounds per square inch.</p>
        <p>In contrast, according to Firestone, the Chevy Blazer and Tahoe, Dodge Durango and Jeep Grand Cherokee Laredo have margins ranging from 14 to 18 pounds per square inch.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lampe, in his turn to testify, struggled to explain how a 1996 test of scores of tires at the company's Decatur, Ill., plant, where most of the faulty tires were made, managed to show a substantial number of failures in which treads separated from tires, the failure now blamed for about 100 deaths in cases in which Explorers have rolled over.</p>
        <p>A Firestone document turned over to Congressional investigators described the test of 239 tires from the factory, some of them prototypes but 129 of them regular tires from the production run. Of those, investigators say, 15 failed; the company said it was 11; 6 had tread separations.</p>
        <p>''That's more than acceptable, isn't it?'' asked Bart Stupak, a Michigan Democrat, who said he wanted to know why the company did not notify Ford and federal officials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lampe replied that the test used was ''very abusive'' and far more severe than those required by the government. And he added, ''In every case, we retested tires again; we didn't close our eyes; we didn't walk away from a problem.''</p>
        <p>But he did not say in testimony what the company did about the problem, other than test additional tires. He declined to answer the question in a session with reporters after his testimony, conducted in a hallway outside the hearing room.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Petrauskas, in her testimony, tried to convince the members of the committee that it made no difference that the vehicle that Ford had used to test the Firestones at 26 pounds per square inch was not an Explorer, as the company had initially said, but an F-150 pickup truck rigged to mimic an Explorer's weight distribution. The company had previously said it used an Exporer for the tests.</p>
        <p>The committee, struggling to complete its hearing and move on to work on legislation stiffening reporting rules, managed to hold its members' opening statements to 61 minutes, compared with more than two hours at its last hearing. Ideas varied, though, on what the law should say. Rodney Slater, the Secretary of Transportation, showed up late and endorsed criminal penalties for ''egregious violations'' of existing laws.</p>
        <p>Committee members varied on whether instituting criminal penalties would be helpful. Representative John Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, said it would probably encourage corporate executives not to cooperate with investigations, so as not to incriminate themselves. But the Senate Commerce Committee unanimously approved a bill on Wednesday that would provide such penalties.</p>
        <p>Another issue is whether to allow the Transportation Department to establish a measurement of vehicles' tendency to roll over, and publish the data for consumers. The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration would like to do so but has been blocked by Congress; today several committee members said they favored such an index.</p>
        <p>There was still no clarification of why the tires fail. Mr. Lampe of Firestone, who said on Sept. 12 that his company had brought in an outside expert to determine why the tires had failed, said today that the expert had actually started work a couple of days ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
