<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Morgan Stanley Misses Forecast and Its Stock Tumbles</title>
    <meta content="Y22MORG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/business/22MORG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan Stanley Dean Witter</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFDB113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Morgan Stanley Misses Forecast and Its Stock Tumbles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Morgan Stanley Dean Witter misses earnings forecasts in its fiscal third quarter; company earned $1.25 billion on revenue of $6.3 billion for three months ended Aug 31; net income for period rose 28 percent from third quarter a year ago; Dean Witter stock falls $6.50, or 6.8 percent, to $89.44 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, the nation's second-largest securities firm and a darling of the investment industry, stumbled a bit on Wall Street yesterday.</p>
        <p>The firm reported its fiscal third-quarter results, and for the first time in five years they fell short of earnings forecasts. The numbers themselves were far from shabby: Morgan said it earned $1.25 billion, or $1.09 a diluted share, on revenue of $6.3 billion for the three months ended Aug. 31.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, the nation's second-largest securities firm and a darling of the investment industry, stumbled a bit on Wall Street yesterday.</p>
        <p>The firm reported its fiscal third-quarter results, and for the first time in five years they fell short of earnings forecasts. The numbers themselves were far from shabby: Morgan said it earned $1.25 billion, or $1.09 a diluted share, on revenue of $6.3 billion for the three months ended Aug. 31.</p>
        <p>Net income for the period rose 28 percent from the third quarter a year earlier, earnings per share increased 31 percent, and revenue was up 18 percent. And Morgan Stanley's return on equity, a widely used measure of corporate performance, was an annualized 28 percent.</p>
        <p>But Wall Street had been expecting more, forecasting earnings of $1.17 a share, according to data from First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>Analysts cited a sharp slowdown in trading revenue and a drop in investment banking fees from second-quarter levels as the main culprits preventing the firm from meeting earnings estimates. But the analysts also acknowledged that the results were nothing to sneeze at.</p>
        <p>''This quarter was nothing to be embarrassed about,'' said Mark Constant of Lehman Brothers. ''It was a good, solid quarter. And it was a reminder that we shouldn't take the best-case scenario for granted all the time. There is an inherently wide band when you estimate broker earnings.''</p>
        <p>Still, investors were less than thrilled. Shares of Morgan Stanley Dean Witter fell $6.50, or 6.8 percent, to $89.44.</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch, the nation's largest brokerage firm, fell $3.50 a share, to  $62.69; the Goldman Sachs Group dropped $4.75, to $113.25; and Lehman Brothers lost $2.94, closing at $141.50.</p>
        <p>Investor disappointment with Morgan's results was probably accentuated by the strong gains reported earlier in the week by Goldman, Sachs and Lehman Brothers. In addition, the earnings figures may have offered an excuse for some to take profits: through Wednesday, Morgan Stanley Dean Witter's stock had gained 116 percent in the last 12 months.</p>
        <p>The market's reaction ''is a bit of a tempest in a teapot,'' said Guy Moszkowski, an analyst with Salomon Smith Barney. ''I have thought the stock was expensive, and even after today's sell-off it still is. But it is clearly one of the franchise leaders in this business. They made a fantastic return on equity.''</p>
        <p>A sharp decline in stock market volatility during the summer helped stunt Morgan Stanley's results.</p>
        <p>Trading revenue for the quarter totaled $1.63 billion, up 43 percent from a year earlier but down 35 percent from the second quarter, when stock market averages tumbled. In addition to a slowdown in stock market swings, commodities and fixed-income trading results were also down from those in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>''Generally, they got smacked in the equity derivatives area because volatility fell off so much in the quarter,'' said Richard Strauss, a Goldman, Sachs analyst. ''That affects them more than anybody because 60 percent of their trading business is in equities.''</p>
        <p>The trading results prompted concern among analysts that Morgan Stanley had suffered proprietary losses during the quarter.</p>
        <p>Robert G. Scott, chief financial officer at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, said in a teleconference with analysts that the firm had sustained no proprietary trading losses.</p>
        <p>Net income for the securities arm of the business, including trading and commissions, rose 28 percent from the period a year earlier, to $825 million.</p>
        <p>Investment banking revenue, or fees for helping companies sell stock and advising on mergers, fell 3 percent, to $1.15 billion.</p>
        <p>In the teleconference Mr. Scott said that looking forward, the backlogs of announced and unannounced merger-and-acquisition deals were higher now than they were a year ago, and that the firm's backlog of equity offerings was comparable to a year ago.</p>
        <p>''We expect to be busy between now and the end of the year in equity underwriting,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere, the company reported a record quarter for its Discover credit card business. Net income rose 10 percent from a year earlier, to $222 million, driven by increased spending by card holders and the lowest loss reserve in five years.</p>
        <p>Net income from the firm's asset management business rose 62 percent, to $199 million. In the last year, Morgan Stanley said it had increased its assets under management by $90 billion, to $548 billion.</p>
        <p>The firm's investment portfolio, which posted a loss of $242 million in the second fiscal quarter because of a sharp slump in technology stock prices, yielded gains of $55 million in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Those returns fell far short of the $480 million in gains that Goldman, Sachs reported on Tuesday. Goldman had a second-quarter loss of $321 million in its investment portfolio.</p>
        <p>Separately, Mr. Scott said the firm intended to expand its Nasdaq trading capacity by building, not buying a specialist firm, unlike Goldman and Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>He said that Morgan Stanley, which currently makes markets in 700 Nasdaq stocks, plans to increase that to about 1,000 by the end of this year and to 3,000 by the middle of 2001.</p>
        <p>''We think we can build the capability for much less than it costs to buy the capacity,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
