<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Missed Field Goals A Bad Sign For Giants</title>
    <meta content="22GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/sports/22GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Bears</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Chicago Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E2D9113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Missed Field Goals A Bad Sign For Giants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Problems besetting New York Giants special teams unit discussed; team was unable to convert on three field goal chances in last week's game against Chicago Bears (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brad Daluiso, the Giants' place-kicker, doesn't want to dwell on the three field-goal attempts the team botched on Sunday. Those misses turned what should have been an easy victory over the Bears into a last-minute stand by the defense.</p>
        <p>But Daluiso said that the ugly performance -- a missed kick, a bad hold and a blocked kick -- was an unusual series of events that probably won't happen again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brad Daluiso, the Giants' place-kicker, doesn't want to dwell on the three field-goal attempts the team botched on Sunday. Those misses turned what should have been an easy victory over the Bears into a last-minute stand by the defense.</p>
        <p>But Daluiso said that the ugly performance -- a missed kick, a bad hold and a blocked kick -- was an unusual series of events that probably won't happen again.</p>
        <p>Brad Maynard, the punter and holder, said the team was fortunate to come away with the 14-7 victory.</p>
        <p>''We go in there to score points,'' Maynard said today after practice.  ''Three times we were unsuccessful. You'll lose more games than you win with three opportunities that you don't score.''</p>
        <p>The missed field goals underscored mistakes that have plagued the special teams unit during Coach Jim Fassel's tenure. Fassel took over the Giants in 1997, and since then, the team has finished in the bottom half of the National Football League in defending kickoff returns and in the bottom third against punt returns.</p>
        <p>This week, Fassel strongly defended the special teams coach Larry MacDuff, who has been Fassel's assistant through the head coach's four seasons. Fassel said  that the mistakes on the field were made by the players and were not a result of the coaching; he said MacDuff had been told not to use any more first-team players because of the risk of injury.</p>
        <p>At 3-0, the Giants have been carried by a resurgent defense and an expanded and explosive offense. But Maynard warned, understandably, that little mistakes on special teams could still cost the Giants a game. That's the last thing the Giants want on Sunday night against visiting Washington, which Fassel called the ''biggest game we'll play the first half of the season.''</p>
        <p>Daluiso's first field goal attempt last Sunday in Chicago went wide left. His second went straight into the offensive line after Maynard was unable to control the ball; Maynard said he thought the snap was low. The ball fell and Daluiso kicked it on its side. The third attempt was blocked when the offensive line left a Bears defender unblocked.</p>
        <p>''I've done it a million times in a thousand games in college and in the pros,'' Maynard said. ''You see three different kicks, we had three different guys with letdowns. It's the entire unit then that goes down.''</p>
        <p>Daluiso, who converted all four of his attempts at Philadelphia the previous week, is pleased with his field goal kicking. After having surgery last year on his left knee -- not the leg he kicks with -- he is still regaining his strength on kickoffs. One of his eight kicks against Philadelphia in Week 2 went 77 yards into the end zone for a touchback, but one traveled just 40 yards and another went 45.</p>
        <p>Maynard is averaging 40.7 yards on punts, about the same as the 41-yard average he had last season. But 5 of his 12 punts have come from within the opponents' 48-yard line and required more placement than distance. He is pleased with his performance and today in practice was routinely kicking spirals into the end zone.</p>
        <p>Maynard could play a crucial role Sunday. Washington's Deion Sanders let one punt go off his face mask in Monday's loss to Dallas, but is still a dangerous punt returner.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>KERRY COLLINS said the quarterback controversy last season with the Giants is similar to what is going on with the Redskins this season. BRAD JOHNSON, the starter, is under pressure after Washington signed JEFF GEORGE in the off-season. Collins replaced KENT GRAHAM as the Giants' quarterback in the 11th game in 1999. ''I saw the effect it had on Kent,'' Collins said. ''He played tight. In this league, it's a real luxury to have the support of your organization, of the coaching staff, both in words and deeds. It's got to wear on Brad's mind. I know if I was in that situation, it would definitely weigh on my mind. I empathize with him. It makes a big difference, just for your psyche and the way you approach things, knowing you don't have to throw every pass perfectly.''</p>
        <p>Tight end PETE MITCHELL missed his second day of practice with what Coach JIM FASSEL called an ulcer in the colon lining. Fassel was unsure if Mitchell would practice Friday and said he is questionable for Sunday's game. . . . Fassel was pleased with the new sod on the grass field at Giants Stadium and said it was better than what the Giants played on in their opener here on Sept. 3.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
