<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Light Look At Dark Ages</title>
    <meta content="22FAMI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/arts/22FAMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FAMILY FARE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graeber, Laurel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7D8103BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Light Look At Dark Ages</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurel Graeber</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Graeber, Laurel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Family Fare column of events of interest to families in New York; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York is filled with all kinds of people, but one type, if you believe ''Sex and the City,'' is sorely lacking: knights in shining armor.</p>
        <p>That won't be the case on Sunday, however, at least not in Upper Manhattan. Once again, it's time for the Medieval Festival in Fort Tryon Park, which will recall the days when men were men, ladies were fair and the average life span was 30 years or so. But in one day of revelry, why worry about little details?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York is filled with all kinds of people, but one type, if you believe ''Sex and the City,'' is sorely lacking: knights in shining armor.</p>
        <p>That won't be the case on Sunday, however, at least not in Upper Manhattan. Once again, it's time for the Medieval Festival in Fort Tryon Park, which will recall the days when men were men, ladies were fair and the average life span was 30 years or so. But in one day of revelry, why worry about little details?</p>
        <p>The festival focuses on the merry side of medievalism, with jesters, jugglers, magicians and craftsmen. And, of course, jousters. The Grand Joust, at 5:20 p.m., will feature Robin Hood versus the Sheriff of Nottingham, and Will Scarlet (one of Robin Hood's band) versus the villainous Sir Guy de Gisbourne.</p>
        <p>These characters will also be among the playing pieces in the festival's living chess game at 3:30 p.m. ''So we do have a bit of a story line going, which we haven't done in the past,'' said Eileen Merle-Rao, the festival's performance director.</p>
        <p>Young visitors will enjoy storytelling, puppet shows, their own parade at 4:30 p.m. (costumes are encouraged) and a children's area with a 25-foot dragon. ''He has a nice new coat of scales,'' Ms. Merle-Rao said.</p>
        <p>The event will also include music, from folk harp to Scottish pipers, and lots of dancing, all with professional performers, Ms. Merle-Rao said.</p>
        <p>And just how do you find experienced jousters in this day and age?</p>
        <p>''It's easier than you think,'' she said. ''You just go on the Internet.''</p>
        <p>Medieval Festival, Sunday from noon to 6 p.m. in Fort Tryon Park, West 190th Street and the Hudson River, Washington Heights. Free. Rain date: Oct. 1. Information: (212) 795-1600.</p>
        <p>Show Them the Money!</p>
        <p>The financial district is known primarily as a place for grown-ups to work. But this weekend it will be a place for children to play and, if they wish, to step into adults' shoes and learn that trading isn't just something you do with Pokemon cards.</p>
        <p>This mixture of business and funny business was concocted by the Downtown Alliance, whose ''Kid around Downtown: A Weekend of Family Fun'' will include not only ''Children's Day Onstage at the Twin Towers,'' an annual entertainment event that will take place tomorrow, but also historical tours of downtown, lots of outdoor entertainment and a chance to spread a little cheer in the hallowed halls of big money.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time all three downtown exchanges are going to be open at the same time for a Saturday,'' said Valerie Lewis, the alliance's assistant vice president for public affairs and marketing.</p>
        <p>For instance, children 8 and up can take part in ''Amex in Action,'' which includes a guided tour of the American Stock Exchange and an interactive mock trading session (tomorrow at 10 and 11:30 a.m. and Sunday at noon and 1:30 p.m.).</p>
        <p>Tomorrow the New York Stock Exchange will offer ''Kids on Wall Street: An Investment in Our Future,'' with tours, interactive exhibits and a chance to tap into the market database (noon, 1, 2 and 3 p.m.).</p>
        <p>Tomorrow and Sunday, the New York Mercantile Exchange will offer visitors ages 6 to 12 a peek at the commodities market, with simulated trading sessions they can join every hour from noon to 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>And don't forget the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, which will offer demonstrations on ''The Mechanics of Money,'' tomorrow at 11 a.m. and noon, 2 and 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>If your tykes are too little to be amateur tycoons, they will still have plenty of options, ranging from children's theater at the National Museum of the American Indian to demonstrations at the New York City Police Museum to appearances by Theodore Tugboat, a PBS character, at the South Street Seaport Museum.</p>
        <p>Best of all, in this neighborhood of big bucks, you probably won't have to spend even one.</p>
        <p>''Kidaround Downtown,'' tomorrow and Sunday from about 10 a.m. on in Lower Manhattan. Many events have limited space and are open on a first-come, first-served basis. Most are free. Main information booth: Liberty Plaza Park, at Broadway and Liberty Streets. Information: (212) 835-2789 or www.kadnyc.com.</p>
        <p>Have a Blast</p>
        <p>The New Year is here, and it's time to blow your horn.</p>
        <p>Not the New Year celebrated in Times Square with those pathetic little party tooters, but the Jewish New Year, or Rosh Hashana, which begins next Friday at sundown and requires an instrument of slightly more substance: a shofar, or ram's horn.</p>
        <p>Children will be able to explore all its possibilities on Sunday, when the Jewish Museum will hold its Fifth Annual Shofar Festival. They will be invited to decorate, blow and take home plastic shofars, which ''will all be outfited with a little blower device, so even a small child will have success,'' said Carol Zawatsky, the museum's director of education.</p>
        <p>Robin Bady will offer songs and tales, and Ernie Strauss, who might be considered the Satchmo of shofars, will bring about a dozen examples to touch and to try. And since a New Year needs a parade, all the young visitors will join a rousing museumwide march that will include a contest for the longest blast.</p>
        <p>''It's such a great thing to encounter,'' Ms. Zawatsky said. ''Here's a New Year and a new generation.''</p>
        <p>Shofar Festival, Sunday from 1 to 4 p.m. at the Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, (212) 423-3200. Admission: $8; students and the elderly, $5.50; under 12, free. Materials fee: $3.</p>
        <p>FAMILY FARE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
