<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Are in Usual Funk, But Now Yankees, Too?</title>
    <meta content="22BASE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/sports/22BASE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7DE1E3BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Are in Usual Funk, But Now Yankees, Too?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses late season problems besetting New York Yankees and New York Mets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acting on the first item of their off-season agenda, the Mets will petition the commissioner to make two changes in their 2001 schedule: cancel their games with the Braves in Atlanta and eliminate September. Alas, they will not find a sympathetic ear.</p>
        <p>''I think in both cases that will be very difficult for even the commissioner to do,'' Commissioner Bud Selig said. ''While they gave me new sweeping authority, I don't believe it includes either one of those schedule considerations.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acting on the first item of their off-season agenda, the Mets will petition the commissioner to make two changes in their 2001 schedule: cancel their games with the Braves in Atlanta and eliminate September. Alas, they will not find a sympathetic ear.</p>
        <p>''I think in both cases that will be very difficult for even the commissioner to do,'' Commissioner Bud Selig said. ''While they gave me new sweeping authority, I don't believe it includes either one of those schedule considerations.''</p>
        <p>The smile in Selig's voice was clear, but this has not been a laughing matter for the Mets. Certainly they will make the playoffs, because the Arizona Diamondbacks effectively ended their own season a month ago. The highest-scoring team in the National League last season, the Diamondbacks reached the nadir by scoring one whole run in three losses to the Los Angeles Dodgers this week.</p>
        <p>But the Mets are experiencing their third successive dysfunctional September, and their play in no way engenders confidence in their ability to be anything more than a wild-card team by default. The Mets will be the N.L. wild-card team because teams like the Diamondbacks mounted no challenge.</p>
        <p>In the American League, the Yankees are not a wild-card team, but the wild-card race has created an intriguing, if not suspicious, scenario. The Yankees' inability to score against Bartolo Colon, Chuck Finley and Dave Burba last weekend (no runs in 23 innings) could make the Yankees pause in their postseason planning.</p>
        <p>The Yankees had been playing so well until they encountered the Indians that they conceivably could have overtaken the Chicago White Sox as the team with the best record and played the wild-card team in the first round. Even if they did not wind up with the best record, as long as theirs was better than  the West winner's, they would play the Indians if Cleveland were the wild-card winner.</p>
        <p>But their seven losses in eight games, the latest a 3-1 decision to David Wells in Toronto last night, and Seattle's eight-game winning streak before their game with Oakland left the Yankees one-half game behind the Mariners.</p>
        <p>If the Mariners were to finish ahead of the Yankees and the Indians were the wild card, then Seattle would play Cleveland and the Yankees would not have to face the shutout firm of Colon, Finley and Burba. They would instead play the White Sox and their depleted corps of starting pitchers.</p>
        <p>Now no one is suggesting that the Yankees are trying to avoid the Indians, but the playoff format does open the door for opponent-fixing shenanigans. The Mets don't need shenanigans; they need victories.</p>
        <p>When the month began, the Mets had the N.L.'s best record, half a game better than the Braves, two and a half games better than the Giants, four games better than the Cardinals. Three weeks later, they have the fourth-best record, four games behind the Braves and the Cardinals, six behind the Giants following their 6-5 loss in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>The Giants and the Cardinals each won 15 of their first 19 games in September, the Braves 11 of their 18. The Mets? They won 7 of their first 20. The sound of their limp as they approach the playoffs is as audible as the pounding of the heart, real or imagined, in Edgar Allan Poe's ''The Tell-Tale Heart.''</p>
        <p>The Mets' problem is not imagined. At a time when a team preparing for postseason play is supposed to be playing its best, the Mets play their worst. Two Septembers ago, their worst cost them a spot in the playoffs. Last September, it forced them into a playoff for the playoffs. This September, it just leaves their fans, not to mention owners, mystified by the annual turn of events.</p>
        <p>Apparently finding it more and more difficult to remain on his best behavior and keep his thoughts to himself, Bobby Valentine incorrectly anticipated a question from reporters Wednesday and blurted, ''If we don't make the playoffs, I'll gladly take Fred off the hook, if we have to get into that nonsense again.'' Valentine was talking about the co-owner, Fred Wilpon, and the decision he faces about Valentine's future with the team.</p>
        <p>Maybe it is nothing Valentine does that precipitates the September Swoon, but the self-proclaimed world's smartest manager evidently has difficulty fixing it. He chewed out his players in a postgame tirade in Atlanta the other night, and they responded by beating the Braves the next night, only the third time in 23 games they had achieved that feat.</p>
        <p>But last night, facing the last-place Phillies, they reverted to losing. At least in between the two games, they were able to go forward with their ritual of making the rookies travel to the next city on the trip in outrageous costumes. Valentine did not don his own costume, the one with the fake mustache and beard. He had already worn that one this season. For his next trick, he will try to manage the Mets to a few victories. He was unable to execute that trick last night.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
