<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Only Sex (Sanitized), Drugs and Rock 'n' Roll</title>
    <meta content="22TAKI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/arts/22TAKI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TAKING THE CHILDREN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nichols, Peter M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Almost Famous (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bait (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Nurse Betty (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5D9103BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Only Sex (Sanitized), Drugs and Rock 'n' Roll</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nichols, Peter M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter M Nichols Taking the Children review of movies Almost Famous, Nurse Betty and Bait; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Almost Famous  Patrick Fugit, Billy Crudup, Kate Hudson, Frances McDormand, Jason Lee, Zooey Deschanel, Anna Paquin, Philip Seymour Hoffman  Directed by Cameron Crowe  R 120 minutes</p>
        <p>''You're not out there to join the party,'' a Rolling Stone editor tells the journalist William Miller (Mr. Fugit). ''We already have one Hunter Thompson.'' Having never met William face to face, the editor is as yet unaware that on the strength of a few good clips the magazine has assigned a 15-year-old to produce a piece of objective reporting on a fast-rising rock group called Stillwater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Almost Famous  Patrick Fugit, Billy Crudup, Kate Hudson, Frances McDormand, Jason Lee, Zooey Deschanel, Anna Paquin, Philip Seymour Hoffman  Directed by Cameron Crowe  R 120 minutes</p>
        <p>''You're not out there to join the party,'' a Rolling Stone editor tells the journalist William Miller (Mr. Fugit). ''We already have one Hunter Thompson.'' Having never met William face to face, the editor is as yet unaware that on the strength of a few good clips the magazine has assigned a 15-year-old to produce a piece of objective reporting on a fast-rising rock group called Stillwater.</p>
        <p>The year is 1973 as William, modeled after Mr. Crowe during his own days as a teenage reporter, joins the Stillwater tour bus in Tempe, Ariz., and starts to get acquainted with Russell Hammond (Mr. Crudup), the group's guitarist and rising star. He also encounters Stillwater's lead groupie, a warm and wise teenager who calls herself Penny Lane (Ms. Hudson).</p>
        <p>''The enemy: a rock writer,'' somebody warns. But William is a forthright boy who may fool Rolling Stone with a fake baritone on the telephone but works his way into the band's confidence with his boyish charm.</p>
        <p>On the road there are calls and messages from his mother, Elaine (Ms. McDormand), a good-hearted and wonderfully expressive worrywart back in San Diego. William reassures her from pay phones in hotel hallways while Penny's groupie cohorts loudly invite him to sessions of sex, drugs and rock 'n' roll.</p>
        <p>In fact, William does no drugging and takes a good part of the movie to lose his virginity. Stillwater carouses some but generally sets a good example, keeping its substance intake under control and leaving hotel furniture intact. William bonds with Russell, a gentle, sensitive sort, in the face of his rising fame, and Penny, who is making Russell her last project, as she calls it, before she moves on to Morocco.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the tour graduates to plane travel and during a midair emergency the band feels compelled to disgorge all kinds of confessions fit for inclusion in William's article. Rolling Stone will give him 3,000 words and maybe the cover. ''Don't let those swill merchants rewrite you,'' warns the critic Lester Bangs (Mr. Hoffman), William's mentor.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- A few verbal confrontations.  SEX -- This is a rock tour so sex is everywhere. Virtually none of it gets on screen, however, and what does is playful and sanitized.  PROFANITY -- Quite a bit, but natural.  FOOTNOTE -- ''My wife had an accident with some Quaaludes,'' William tells a hotel operator in his telephone baritone. An emergency team pumps out Penny's stomach. Russell drops acid, but while drugs are evident, they are played down.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?  UNDER AGE 10 -- No.  AGES 11-13 -- Parents may veto, but Mr. Crowe depicts his rock experiences in a happy light. William is an appealing role model.  AGES 14 AND UP -- A true rarity: an R-rated film the whole family (excluding the little ones) can enjoy.</p>
        <p>Nurse Betty  Renee Zellweger, Morgan Freeman, Chris Rock, Greg Kinnear, Tia Texada  Directed by Neil LaBute  R 112 minutes</p>
        <p>After witnessing the horrific killing of her no-good husband, a sweet waitress named Betty (Ms. Zellweger) turns ''disassociative'' by blocking out the whole thing and driving off to California, where she plans to unite with the fictional man of her dreams, Dr. David Ravell (Mr. Kinnear), a Los Angeles surgeon in the soap opera ''A Reason to Love.''</p>
        <p>Betty is obsessed with the show and the doctor. This is her first time outside Kansas, which conjures visions of the yellow brick road but for one detail: in the trunk of the Buick she has borrowed from her husband's used-car lot are 10 kilos of drugs.</p>
        <p>Unaware of that, Betty proceeds to Los Angeles trailed by the killers, a couple of enforcers from Detroit: Charlie (Morgan Freeman), a reflective dreamer who will become infatuated with Betty's innocence, and Wesley (Mr. Rock), a sociopathic hothead who plays more to type.</p>
        <p>In Los Angeles Betty lands a job at a hospital and actually meets the actor who plays Dr. Ravell. Totally immersed in the show's fanatsy, or so it would appear, she leads him to believe that she's merely angling for a part. By now Charlie and Wesley have traced Betty's snapshots cross- country and are readying for some scenes straight out of ''The Sopranos.''</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- Horrendous and kind of special, even in an age of extreme movie violence. To be brief, Betty's husband is scalped. Such severity may be necessary to establish Betty's flight from reality, but the act obviously is not a sight for young viewers.  SEX -- Simulated sex is performed at the start of the film.  PROFANITY -- Plenty.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?  UNDER AGE 14 -- ''Nurse Betty'' is a strange case. After the killing it becomes a clever, amusing film that, depending on parental guidelines, is not unsuitable for older children. But the killing rules it out.  AGES 14-17 -- Many teenagers will take the scalping in stride. There are no other problems.</p>
        <p>Bait  Jamie Foxx, David Morse, Doug Hutchison, Kimberly Elise, Robert Pastorelli  Directed by Antoine Fuqua  R 120 minutes</p>
        <p>Caught stealing $2,000 worth of prawns (shrimp on steroids), the impoverished Alvin (Mr. Foxx) ends up in the same jail cell as Jaster (Mr. Pastorelli), who has helped steal $42 million worth of gold bullion from the Federal Government. Jaster tells the Treasury Department, represented by the overbearing Edgar Clenteen (Mr. Morse), that he doesn't know what happened to the gold and that he is not responsible for killing two security people during the robbery. That was the work of his accomplice. Jaster doesn't know much about him either, except that he's a computer genius.</p>
        <p>That would be the diabolical Bristol (Mr. Hutchison doing his John Malkovich imitation), but the film doesn't catch up to him until the final explosion and shootout. To track him down, Clenteen has a transmitter planted in Alvin's jaw in the hopes that Alvin will draw Bristol out of hiding.</p>
        <p>Why should Bristol give a hoot about Alvin? Well, Jaster double-crossed Bristol during the robbery and hid the gold somewhere. Bristol figures that Jaster may have told Alvin where during their incarceration together. So everybody trots around Manhattan tracked by Clenteen's electronics experts, who percolate in their command center as if they are directing a moon landing. (If Alvin is so destitute, where did he get that Rolex?)</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- The film gets bloody.  SEX -- Alvin's lovemaking with his girlfriend (Ms. Elise) rocks the eavesdropping equipment at mission central.  PROFANITY -- None (just kidding).</p>
        <p>For Which Children?  UNDER AGE 11 -- A definite no.  AGES 11-13 -- Standard action fodder, meaning not entirely appropriate and in need of an adult escort.  AGES 14-17 -- Mr. Foxx has drawing power, as does this genre among teenage boys.</p>
        <p>TAKING THE CHILDREN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
