<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talk of a Town Is Mrs. Clinton, And the Votes May Soon Follow</title>
    <meta content="22VOIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/nyregion/22VOIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mamaroneck (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Dean E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E5DF1E3BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1284" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talk of a Town Is Mrs. Clinton, And the Votes May Soon Follow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Dean E</byline>
      <dateline>MAMARONECK, N.Y., Sept. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Mamroneck, NY, are giving new attention to Hillary Rodham Clinton's candidacy as Senate race heats up, and there are some hints that she may be making headway among undecided voters; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Lemon Tree hair salon, clean and efficient but no frills at $12 for a wash and cut, is probably not the kind of place where the first lady of the United States would get her hair done.</p>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton can be grateful for that. Wife of the president or candidate for Senate, Mrs. Clinton is not a favorite among the ladies with the scissors here. Donna Gorman, the salon's owner, who lives in Bethpage, N.Y., says she is a great fan of Representative Rick A. Lazio. Haircuts aside (she says both candidates are ''New York stylish''), Mrs. Gorman likes his Long Island roots (they are natural). Tina Becerra, one of her hairdressers, says Mrs. Clinton needs to do more than buy a house up the highway in Chappaqua to qualify for a permanent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Lemon Tree hair salon, clean and efficient but no frills at $12 for a wash and cut, is probably not the kind of place where the first lady of the United States would get her hair done.</p>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton can be grateful for that. Wife of the president or candidate for Senate, Mrs. Clinton is not a favorite among the ladies with the scissors here. Donna Gorman, the salon's owner, who lives in Bethpage, N.Y., says she is a great fan of Representative Rick A. Lazio. Haircuts aside (she says both candidates are ''New York stylish''), Mrs. Gorman likes his Long Island roots (they are natural). Tina Becerra, one of her hairdressers, says Mrs. Clinton needs to do more than buy a house up the highway in Chappaqua to qualify for a permanent.</p>
        <p>''Let's face it, no matter how hard she tries, she really doesn't know New York and is an outsider,'' Ms. Becerra, 25, said today. ''It is a big step to go from first lady to senator.''</p>
        <p>But below the blast of blow dryers, during hushed moments between rinses and curlers, there were some hints that Mrs. Clinton has been making headway among undecided, independent-minded voters, a shift borne out by the latest New York Times/CBS poll, released today. The survey found that Mrs. Clinton is particularly enjoying a bounce in popularity among suburban and politically moderate women.</p>
        <p>''I don't like Whitewater and all of that, but if she deserves to win, she should get it,'' said Mary Cestone, 80, a Republican, who listened quietly as the discussion in the salon raged against Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''I haven't made up my mind, but why not Mrs. Clinton?'' she asked. ''You can't hold a good woman back.''</p>
        <p>Up and down the main thoroughfare in this Westchester County village, where Republicans control the municipal government but declared Democrats slightly outnumber declared Republicans, voters are beginning to turn their attention to the Senate race. Many first took notice last week when Mrs. Clinton and Mr. Lazio held a televised debate in Buffalo, or, if they missed the debate, got pulled in by the media hoopla about Mr. Lazio's apparent aggressiveness toward Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>The last time many here even thought about the race was when Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani announced in May that he would not run against Mrs. Clinton because of his prostate cancer. After that, the Clinton-Lazio showdown seemed to be a letdown for some Mamaroneck voters, even those who favor Mrs. Clinton, leading to a small but discernable wave of Giuliani nostalgia.</p>
        <p>''Giuliani did her a big favor by backing out,'' said Sharon Sawyer, 43, a Democrat, adding that she would have considered voting for Mr. Giuliani but cannot imagine supporting Mr. Lazio. ''I think it would have been a much more difficult race for Hillary.''</p>
        <p>The mayor of Mamaroneck, Deborah Chapin, a Democrat, said it had taken awhile for many Democrats in town to get excited about Mrs. Clinton's candidacy because they were still smarting over the aborted campaign of Representative Nita M. Lowey. Ms. Lowey, a Democrat who represents the Westchester area, had plans to run for the Senate but dropped them when Mrs. Clinton announced her bid. It was the debate in Buffalo, Ms. Chapin said, that finally buried most bad feelings about an outside woman upstaging a local one.</p>
        <p>''The tide is turning,'' Ms. Chapin said. ''Whatever personal objections there may have been to Hillary's candidacy are being outweighed by people being of the same mind on the issues.''</p>
        <p>Most educated guesses place Mamaroneck as a tossup in November. The village has a reputation for voting Republican, though that has been changing. In 1998 Senator Charles E. Schumer, a Democrat, handily defeated the Republican incumbent, Alfonse M. D'Amato, among village voters. The Clinton years, some longtime residents said, seemed to have tweaked the village of 18,000 closer to the Democratic column.</p>
        <p>Laura Smith, 39, was a Republican for years, but she recently dropped her party affiliation and says she is just as likely to vote for a Republican, Democratic or any other party candidate in local and national elections. (She twice voted for Ross Perot of the Reform Party for president and likes Ralph Nader of the Green Party this time around.) Ms. Smith, a disc jockey who also teaches English as a second language to high school students, said that she had been leaning toward Mr. Lazio but that news reports about his behavior in the debate were giving her pause.</p>
        <p>''It bothers me if it is true that he was a jerk the other night,'' said Ms. Smith, who was organizing her lesson plan over coffee and a muffin at the Cafe Mozart. ''I base a lot of my vote on the debates, because you get to see these people under fire and really be themselves. It is the only time to see them spontaneous. They have to prove their mettle.''</p>
        <p>Connie German, 30, a newcomer to the area from Southern California, is also teaching English as a second language. She said she had not made up her mind about the Senate race, although she found it difficult imagining herself voting for Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Ms. German said she had not been a fan of President Clinton, had been particularly upset about the scandals and viewed Mrs. Clinton as guilty by association. Yet Mr. Lazio cannot count on her vote either. She said she had known he would come out fighting during the debate because he had to make a name for himself. But she shares the general opinion that Mr. Lazio crossed some sort of line.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think he would be that rude,'' Ms. German said. ''It looked like a couple of kids in a sandbox. It wasn't very impressive on either side.''</p>
        <p>At Sal's Pizzeria down the street, Ishmael Montanez, 37, was ordering a lunch of Sicilian and cheese pizza slices. Mr. Montanez lives in Yonkers and works in administration at the Orthonet clinic in Mamaroneck. He also said he had been surprised by Mr. Lazio's tone during the debate. (''He came right at her,'' he said. ''It was unbelievable.'') Mr. Montanez said he had pretty much settled on Mrs. Clinton, though talk among his colleagues at the clinic was still very much undecided, he said.</p>
        <p>That is true to a certain extent at the Lemon Tree salon as well. The stylists and some customers talk up a storm when Mrs. Clinton's candidacy comes up, but Mrs. Gorman, the owner, says there is also a strong undertone of sympathy toward Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Did you see her yesterday, they ask. Wasn't she beautiful? Did you see that outfit? She looked so lovely. The women, their heads wrapped in chemicals or their hair sticking every which way out of tiny holes in a skullcap, rarely say they will vote for Mrs. Clinton. But, as Mrs. Gorman observed, salon talk is often about the unspoken.</p>
        <p>''I never hear anything,'' she said,  ''about Rick Lazio.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
