<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Infighting Leads to Indian Pullout of Its Sierra Leone Forces</title>
    <meta content="Y22LEO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/world/22LEON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EEDB113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Infighting Leads to Indian Pullout of Its Sierra Leone Forces</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>India, in wake of dispute between African leaders and Indian commander of UN peacekeeping forces in Sierra Leone, tells UN that it will withdraw all of its troops from force; India's contingent of 3,059 soldiers was largest in force of 12,477 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the wake of a dispute between African leaders and the Indian commander of the United Nations peacekeeping force in Sierra Leone, India has told the United Nations that it will withdraw all of its troops from the force.</p>
        <p>India's contingent of 3,059 soldiers was the largest in the force of 12,477, the organization's biggest current mission. India told the United Nations of its decision on Wednesday, leaving officials scrambling not only to replace the Indians but also to meet an Oct. 31 deadline to show progress in increasing the overall size of the mission.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the wake of a dispute between African leaders and the Indian commander of the United Nations peacekeeping force in Sierra Leone, India has told the United Nations that it will withdraw all of its troops from the force.</p>
        <p>India's contingent of 3,059 soldiers was the largest in the force of 12,477, the organization's biggest current mission. India told the United Nations of its decision on Wednesday, leaving officials scrambling not only to replace the Indians but also to meet an Oct. 31 deadline to show progress in increasing the overall size of the mission.</p>
        <p>The Security Council wants a force of 20,500 troops, but has delayed authorizing its deployment until qualified soldiers can be found and Congress can pay the American share of costs.</p>
        <p>A new commander is expected to be named before the end of the month, United Nations officials said today. With the withdrawal of Indian troops, the position can no longer be claimed by India.</p>
        <p>The Indian commander, Maj. Gen. Vijay Kumar Jetley, had been criticized in Africa for his treatment of soldiers from other nations under his command. The sharpest attacks have come from Nigeria and Zambia, which have troops in Sierra Leone. The United States is now training more Nigerians for peacekeeping duties there.</p>
        <p>General Jetley, has also been at odds with his deputy, Brig. Gen. Muhammad Garba, and with Secretary General Kofi Annan's political representative in Sierra Leone, Oluyemi Adeniji. Both are Nigerians.</p>
        <p>Diplomats said that General Jetley, who is on leave, was about to be replaced by Mr. Annan, who had faulted him in May for a lack of communication with others in the Sierra Leone mission during a crisis when about 500 peacekeepers had been taken hostage by rebels. This prompted outrage in India, which also has troops or military observers in Lebanon, Congo and on the Iraq-Kuwait border. Indian police forces serve in Bosnia, Kosovo and Western Sahara.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, a statement from the secretary general's office praised the Indian contingent in Sierra Leone. ''The performance of all Indian officers and troops has been outstanding,'' the statement said. India has assured the United Nations that it will continue to take part in other peacekeeping duties.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
