<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Antibiotics Ineffective Against Gonorrhea</title>
    <meta content="Y22GER$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/science/22GERM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Venereal Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gonorrhea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hawaii</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Missouri</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Gonorrhea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Venereal Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gonorrhea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venereal Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7D9113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="596" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Antibiotics Ineffective Against Gonorrhea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Centers for Disease Control reports that new evidence from Hawaii and Missouri indicates that gonorrhea is becoming resistant to wider variety of antibiotics (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New evidence from Hawaii and Missouri indicates that gonorrhea is becoming resistant to a wider variety of antibiotics, federal health officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Because of the findings, the federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta issued new recommendations for doctors in prescribing antibiotics for gonorrhea. The agency also urged patients to discuss recent travels with their doctors when gonorrhea was suspected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New evidence from Hawaii and Missouri indicates that gonorrhea is becoming resistant to a wider variety of antibiotics, federal health officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Because of the findings, the federal Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta issued new recommendations for doctors in prescribing antibiotics for gonorrhea. The agency also urged patients to discuss recent travels with their doctors when gonorrhea was suspected.</p>
        <p>Nearly 10 percent of gonorrhea cases in Hawaii last year were resistant to an antibiotic, ciprofloxacin, that has been a standard in treating the sexually transmitted infection, the agency said in its weekly report. Doctors in Hawaii have been advised to stop prescribing ciprofloxacin, also known as Cipro, for gonorrhea.</p>
        <p>In Kansas City, Mo., health officials have found the first reported cluster of people, 12 heterosexual men, with gonorrhea that is resistant to another antibiotic, azithromycin, also known as Zithromax.</p>
        <p>The new findings continue a long-term trend of increasing difficulty in  treating gonorrhea because of resistance to antibiotics, leaving doctors with a more limited choice of antibiotics to prescribe for the infection.</p>
        <p>Ciprofloxacin belongs to a class of antibiotics known as the fluoroquinolones. Ciprofloxacin and another member of the class, ofloxacin, are recommended for gonorrhea because they are inexpensive pills.</p>
        <p>''But as we lose fluoroquinolones and eventually azithromycin, we will drastically reduce the number of oral antibiotics that we can use to treat gonorrhea,'' said Dr. Susan Wang, an epidemiologist at the centers. Thus, doctors will have to turn to injectable and costlier antibiotics, Dr. Wang said.</p>
        <p>Gonorrhea can cause a burning sensation on urination and a discharge from the urethra or vagina.</p>
        <p>If untreated, gonorrhea can lead to infertility, ectopic pregnancy in women, chronic pelvic pain and it can facilitate the transmission of H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS.</p>
        <p>In 1997, gonorrhea reached an all-time low in the United States, with 326,564 cases reported. At its peak, in the 1970's, more than a million cases were reported a year.</p>
        <p>The United States has a higher rate of sexually transmitted diseases than any other developed country.</p>
        <p>Since 1997, the number of gonorrhea cases has risen to 355,642 in 1998 and 360,076 cases in 1999.</p>
        <p>As one measure of the problem, the centers said the incidence of fluoroquinolone-resistant gonorrhea in Hawaii soared to 9.5 percent of samples tested last year compared with 1.4 percent in 1997. Elsewhere in the United States, only 0.2 percent of gonorrhea cases were resistant to fluoroquinolones.</p>
        <p>To counter the rise and new antibiotic resistance problems, the centers advised doctors to ask patients or their sex partners with suspected gonorrhea if they could have acquired the infection in Hawaii, other Pacific Islands, or Asia, where resistance to fluoroquinolone antibiotics is high.</p>
        <p>If so, the centers advised treatment with antibiotics known as cefixime, also known as Suprax, or ceftriaxone, also known as Rocephin,  because no resistance has been reported to these drugs. For patients unable to tolerate these drugs, the  agency advised injections of spectinomycin.</p>
        <p>It also recommends that if an individual develops gonorrhea that does not respond to therapy, doctors and hospitals send cultures to a regional laboratory specializing in testing for susceptibility to antibiotics.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
