<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Krayzelburg Powers To Second Gold Medal</title>
    <meta content="22LENN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: SWIMMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krayzelburg, Lenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piersol, Aaron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Welsh, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2DF113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Krayzelburg Powers To Second Gold Medal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lenny Krayzelburg (US) wins gold medal in 200 meter backstroke in swimming competition at Sydney Olympics; sets Olympic record (1:56.76); Aaron Piersol (US) wins silver medal and Matthew Welsh (Australia) wins bronze medal; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lenny Krayzelburg's body was tightening up and the pain was gripping him. He was still leading the 200-meter backstroke, but his only goal in the last half of the race today was to fend off his American teammate, Aaron Peirsol, and Matthew Welsh of Australia.</p>
        <p>The pain, just on the edge of cramps, made him feel as if he had lost control of his arms. They were stroking behind him, but he could not sense what they were doing. His stroke rate in the 200 meters is slower than his pace in the 100 meters, but he was stroking faster than he preferred.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lenny Krayzelburg's body was tightening up and the pain was gripping him. He was still leading the 200-meter backstroke, but his only goal in the last half of the race today was to fend off his American teammate, Aaron Peirsol, and Matthew Welsh of Australia.</p>
        <p>The pain, just on the edge of cramps, made him feel as if he had lost control of his arms. They were stroking behind him, but he could not sense what they were doing. His stroke rate in the 200 meters is slower than his pace in the 100 meters, but he was stroking faster than he preferred.</p>
        <p>''I was overswimming, and it was catching up to me,'' he said later.</p>
        <p>Whatever his struggles, Krayzelburg increased his lead over his pursuers in each 50-meter segment of the race to take his second gold medal of the Summer Games, in an Olympic record 1 minute 56.76 seconds. It added to the one he left the Sydney International Aquatic Center with after winning the 100-meter backstroke on Monday. Peirsol won the silver in 1:57.35.</p>
        <p>Welsh, who won the bronze today and the silver in the 100, said, ''To get that close to him is incredible.''</p>
        <p>When it was over, Krayzelburg's legs were wobbly. He lay on a mat for five minutes, not enough time to end the pain, but he was led to the medal ceremony. As it ended, he tripped on a bench as he reached his parents in the stands, who each kissed him.</p>
        <p>And so, Lenny Krayzelburg's immigrant tale got a little bit better.</p>
        <p>His story is familiar, maybe one that could have been told by Isaac Bashevis Singer while typing away in his Speedo. Krayzelburg was born in Odessa, in the Ukraine, when it was a state in the Soviet Union, one week short of 25 years ago. He swam 12 hours a day at a Soviet sports school with 44 other young swimmers, emigrated in 1989 with his parents and sister to West Hollywood, Calif. He knew no English, and at first, he had no pool to swim in.</p>
        <p>He later found one in a Jewish community center that was just 25 yards long, then a longer one at Santa Monica College that required a lengthy bus trip to reach.</p>
        <p>And eventually, he fulfilled the faith of a former coach who saw greatness for him in the backstroke, and set world records in the 50-, 100- and 200-meter races.</p>
        <p>Now, two gold medals may be as good as finding that the streets were paved with gold.</p>
        <p>''You know, growing up, the Olympics were always a big thing, and in the last few years, when I watched the Olympics, I'd get emotional watching the stories of sacrifice,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But when he swims, he said, he tries eliminate emotion. ''I expect myself to win, and although I've had challenges and obstacles coming here, I've always thought, 'This is the situation I'm in and I'll give 100 percent effort.' You make the best out of it.'' Although he expressed himself impassively, he added: ''I can't say much more. I definitely don't realize what I accomplished.''</p>
        <p>His voice and passion elevated only when he discussed the impact of team momentum, especially of Misty Hyman's 200-meter butterfly victory on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''That was the most inspirational swim I've ever seen,'' he said. ''I'm speechless about that swim. It lifted the girls in the 800-meter free relay. That's been the swim of the meet.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: SWIMMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
