<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan to Tap Oil Reserve Strikes Some Experts As Temporary Answer</title>
    <meta content="Y22ENE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/national/22ENER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ENERGY ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strategic Petroleum Reserve</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EED6113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1239" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan to Tap Oil Reserve Strikes Some Experts As Temporary Answer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE and DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David; Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Economists, oil traders, refiners and politicians are divided over whether current high prices and low supplies of petroleum constitute new kind of crisis that should be addressed by tapping Strategic Petroleum Reserve (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Strategic Petroleum Reserve was created in the 1970's, it was seen as a defense against supply disruptions that threatened national security -- not as a political tool to manage price disruptions.</p>
        <p>But now economists, oil traders, refiners and politicians are divided about whether current high prices and low supplies of petroleum constitute a new kind of crisis that should be addressed by tapping the reserve. And beyond the debate about intervening in the market, one big question looms: Would dumping a big supply of oil on the market work to lower prices?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Strategic Petroleum Reserve was created in the 1970's, it was seen as a defense against supply disruptions that threatened national security -- not as a political tool to manage price disruptions.</p>
        <p>But now economists, oil traders, refiners and politicians are divided about whether current high prices and low supplies of petroleum constitute a new kind of crisis that should be addressed by tapping the reserve. And beyond the debate about intervening in the market, one big question looms: Would dumping a big supply of oil on the market work to lower prices?</p>
        <p>In the market for crude oil, where prices are set on the limited quantities of oil sold in so-called spot markets, a decision to tap the reserve is likely to drive down the price of oil in the short term. Crude oil for November delivery closed yesterday at $34 a barrel, down $1.24 from the day before at the end of trading on the New York Mercantile Exchange. Heating oil prices also dipped, but much less, largely on the prospect of a release from the reserve.</p>
        <p>But it is unclear whether a move by the administration would have more than a temporary effect on prices. And it is doubtful whether the new supplies would reach the market soon enough to overcome potential shortages in heating oil that loom if the weather turns cold prematurely.</p>
        <p>At the same time, other experts worry that tapping the oil from the reserve in response to higher prices would merely lessen its impact if a more serious supply disruption occurred.</p>
        <p>''Using the reserve for price manipulation is dangerous business,'' said Ian Shepherdson, chief domestic economist with High Frequency Economics in Valhalla, N.Y. ''If they release enough of it, the price will go down. The problem is that you can't do this forever, and fairly soon you will want to rebuild the reserve.''</p>
        <p>What troubles policy makers and economists this fall are the low supplies of heating oil, as both the cold weather and the presidential vote approach. The Northeast consumes most of the heating oil in the country. But this year, inventories of heating oil in New England total only 6 million barrels, compared with 16.3 million barrels a year ago, according to the American Petroleum Institute.</p>
        <p>Supplies proved inadequate when a cold snap struck in late January, causing heating oil prices to spike. Lower inventories of heating fuel this winter could leave the region even more vulnerable to price volatility and possible shortages. As a result of tight supplies, heating oil prices have jumped 70 percent over the last year.</p>
        <p>Tapping the reserve ''is really a short-term policy targeted at home heating oil,'' said Laura D'Andrea Tyson, a former chief economic adviser in the Clinton White House who is now the dean of the Haas School of Business at the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>''It's not an attempt to change the overall market dynamics,'' said Ms. Tyson, who has been advising the Gore campaign on economic issues. ''That's perfectly consistent with the formulation of the reserve.''</p>
        <p>Since last autumn, Senator Charles Schumer, Democrat of New York, has tried to convince the Clinton administration to use the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, arguing that the reluctance on the part of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries to provide more crude called for the government to step in to halt spiraling prices. Although Mr. Schumer had proposed that 30 million barrels be released, he said he believed the Gore proposal was a fair first step, and more important, a sign that the administration may be closer to unlocking the oil.</p>
        <p>''The administration is clearly concerned about prices,'' Mr. Schumer said. ''So far, it is more of a price issue, but any kind of problem that created a disruption in supply would create real problems. We are definitely on the edge.''</p>
        <p>Stored in salt domes along the Gulf Coast, the 570-million-barrel petroleum reserve was established after the first Arab oil embargo in 1973-74 to shield the country against similarly severe breaks in supply. The only time it has been used was in 1991, during the Persian Gulf war that followed Iraq's invasion of Kuwait. At the time, the government wanted to sell about 30 million barrels but issued 17.3 million instead, because the bids it received from oil traders were too low. Oil prices, which had been climbing after Iraq invaded Kuwait, fell sharply on the news of the release.</p>
        <p>If President Clinton authorized a release, getting more heating oil into the low stocks of the Northeast would take about 40 to 50 days, experts said. The petroleum reserve's office in New Orleans would review bids for the oil and ship it to buyers, all within 15 days. Then the oil would travel another week to two weeks to the Northeast and another 10 days would be required to refine it into heating oil.</p>
        <p>Critics of tapping the reserve point out that a greater supply of crude may not help overcome the potential shortages. And even if prices fall in the spot market, consumers would not necessarily see much of an effect at the retail level.</p>
        <p>Industry experts estimate that the price of as much as half the oil that is delivered responds to those fluctuations from daily trading, or the spot market. The remaining oil is priced based on long-term contracts, which provides a steady supply and protects buyers somewhat from the daily price fluctuations. But even those supplies are determined by formulas based on the spot prices. There is no fixed price contract for oil.</p>
        <p>Heating oil stocks fell to perilously low levels in April, as a series of cuts in crude oil production by OPEC  shrank the supply of oil to refiners. At the same time, demand for petroleum products has been high because of the robust economy.</p>
        <p>Since the spring, refineries in the United States have been playing catch up to produce more heating oil and are now running at about 95 percent of their full capacity. Refineries are actually producing more heating oil now than they did a year ago, but it is not been enough to restore inventories.</p>
        <p>As a result, more oil from the reserve may bolster crude inventories but do little to relieve the bottleneck at refineries.</p>
        <p>''We're like every other refinery,'' said Bill Greehey, chief executive of Valero Energy Corporation, a major refiner in San Antonio. ''We're running at 100 percent and maximizing our output of heating oil. These crude inventories won't do anything to create fuel oil. It just sounds good, sounds like a quick fix.''</p>
        <p>If the Clinton administration moves to issue oil from the reserve, most industry analysts expect it to be after next week's summit in Caracas, Venezuela, of leaders of the OPEC countries. Officials said that Saudi Arabia, the cartel's de facto leader, was aware that the White House might use the reserve and that its leaders approved of the move.</p>
        <p>''The Saudis welcome some help from us,'' said one industry expert close to the Saudis. ''They don't want this oil from their own back and they want some help with the price, because everyone thinks it's too high.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ENERGY ISSUE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
