<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rare Stroll In the Garden</title>
    <meta content="22INSI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/arts/22INSI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Federation of the Arts</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wadsworth Atheneum (Hartford, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Manet, Edouard (1832-83)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rothschild, Batsheva de (Baroness)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rembrandt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watteau, Jean-Antoine (1684-1721)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fragonard, Jean-Honore (1732-1806)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Block, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sellers, Kate M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Julia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFD7103BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="993" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rare Stroll In the Garden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Inside Art column; Sotheby's to offer Manet's Woman in a Garden, luscious Impressionist landscape that was last shown in exhibition in Minnesota 47 years ago; photo; painting, estimated to bring as much as $30 million, was in Manet family until ten years ago; Christie's to auction collection of late Baroness Batsheva de Rothschild, including paintings by Rembrandt, Watteau and Fragonard; Kate M Sellers named director of Wadsworth Atheneum, Julia Brown director of American Federation of the Arts; John Block resigns after nearly 30 years with Sotheby's (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Sotheby's and Christie's are finishing their plans for the annual November evening sales of Impressionist and Modern art, it always adds an air of mystery to have an important painting the public has not seen for decades. That's the case this year for Sotheby's, which will be offering Manet's ''Woman in a Garden,'' a luscious Impressionist landscape that was last shown 47 years ago, in an exhibition in Minnesota.</p>
        <p>The painting carries an estimate of $20 million to $30 million and will be offered in New York on Nov. 9. It is an unusually large canvas -- 60 1/2 by 46 inches -- and depicts an American woman, a friend of the artist known only as Mademoiselle Marguerite, reading in the garden behind a Paris house Manet rented in the summer of 1880.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Sotheby's and Christie's are finishing their plans for the annual November evening sales of Impressionist and Modern art, it always adds an air of mystery to have an important painting the public has not seen for decades. That's the case this year for Sotheby's, which will be offering Manet's ''Woman in a Garden,'' a luscious Impressionist landscape that was last shown 47 years ago, in an exhibition in Minnesota.</p>
        <p>The painting carries an estimate of $20 million to $30 million and will be offered in New York on Nov. 9. It is an unusually large canvas -- 60 1/2 by 46 inches -- and depicts an American woman, a friend of the artist known only as Mademoiselle Marguerite, reading in the garden behind a Paris house Manet rented in the summer of 1880.</p>
        <p>The richly painted canvas is seen as an important example of his plein-air painting and of the style that marked Manet's mature period, during the height of Impressionism. It is the last of several Manet paintings of women posed in his garden.</p>
        <p>''The bravura brushwork, the scale of the painting and the vivid effects of light filtered through the foliage make it particularly rare,'' said David Norman, who runs Sotheby's Impressionist and modern art department in New York.</p>
        <p>The painting's provenance is also a big draw: it was in Manet's family until 10 years ago. The seller is a collector who is maintaining anonymity but who art experts say is not American. There are only a few potential buyers at this price range, but Mr. Norman said that the diminishing availability of works this important, and particularly of paintings by Manet, would make ''Woman in a Garden'' especially desirable.</p>
        <p>''Among the Impressionists Manet is the rarest,'' Mr. Norman said.</p>
        <p>Who are the potential buyers? ''In terms of museums we always think of the Getty and the Kimbell,'' he said. ''But there are also collectors in fields like telecommunications who are big buyers these days. When you get up this high, the air definitely gets thinner.''</p>
        <p>Sotheby's is quietly betting that the painting will set a record for Manet, outselling his 1878 painting ''Rue Mosnier With Flags,'' which sold for $26 million at Christie's in New York in November 1989.</p>
        <p>Fit for a Baroness</p>
        <p>As powerful as the Rothschild name is in the world of banking, it also carries a special cachet in art and antiques circles. The family represents generations of the best kind of collecting, from museum-quality old master paintings and French furniture to more esoteric objects like rare scientific instruments and Islamic glass.</p>
        <p>So when Christie's announced this week that in December it would sell a group of old master paintings, Islamic and Venetian glass, porcelains and jewelry, all belonging to the Baroness Batsheva de Rothschild in London, who died five months ago, the auction house knew they had a ready-made winner.</p>
        <p>''Rothschild taste represents the Golden Age in Holland, the Golden Age in France and the Golden Age in England,'' said Lord Hindlip, chairman of Christie's. ''Their taste reflects the fashions of the very best of a certain period.''</p>
        <p>This isn't Christie's first London sale of Rothschild property. In July 1999 its sale of treasures looted by the Nazis and returned to the Rothschild family by the Austrian government totaled $90 million. December's auction will not be nearly so large:  the total is conservatively estimated to be upward of $22 million.</p>
        <p>Highlights include a group of old master paintings, to be sold on Dec. 13, that include Rembrandt's ''Portrait of a Lady, Aged 62,'' signed and dated 1632. Depicting an anonymous woman, clad in black with a white collar and cap setting off her face, its estimate is $5.6 million to $8.4 million. There are also two Watteaus, the most valuable of which is ''Italian Comedians in a Landscape,'' estimated to bring $2.1 million to $2.8 million. It shows an amorous cavalier on bended knee and a guitar-playing woman. There are two exceptional Fragonards; one, ''A Blond Woman With Two Doves,'' is expected to sell for $2.1 million to $3.5 million.</p>
        <p>On Dec. 14 Christie's will offer the Islamic and Venetian glass, furniture and porcelain. Among the stars in this group is an enameled lamp made for Sultan al-Nasir Muhammad, which is expected to sell for $705,400 to $1.1 million.</p>
        <p>Most of the collection was assembled by Baron Alphonse de Rothschild, Baroness Batsheva's grandfather, in the 19th century. Baroness Batsheva, who lived in Jerusalem until her death, was part of the fifth generation of the French branch of the family.</p>
        <p>Arrivals . . .</p>
        <p>Two museum appointments were announced this week. Kate M. Sellers will become the eighth director of the Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art in Hartford, replacing Peter C. Sutton, who announced that he was not returning from a sabbatical. Ms. Sellers, deputy director of the Cleveland Museum of Art, will arrive on Nov. 1.</p>
        <p>Julia Brown, curator of special exhibitions at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, will become director of the American Federation of the Arts, the country's oldest nonprofit art museum service organization, on Nov. 1. She replaces Serena Rattazzi, who is retiring after 10 years in the post.</p>
        <p>. . . And a Departure</p>
        <p>Another old-timer is leaving Sotheby's. This week, after months of speculation, John Block announced his resignation. A nearly 30-year veteran, Mr. Block has been vice-chairman of Sotheby's North America, co-chairman of Sotheby's jewelry department worldwide and a senior auctioneer. He plans to leave at the end of the year.</p>
        <p>His departure will leave a second big hole in Sotheby's jewelry department. In June Prince Dimitri of Yugoslavia left after 15 years. The two men were the company's top business generators in one of the most profitable areas of the auction business.</p>
        <p>INSIDE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
