<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Icahn Sells Entire General Motors Stake a Month After Purchase</title>
    <meta content="Y22CARL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/business/22CARL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Icahn, Carl C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EED9113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Icahn Sells Entire General Motors Stake a Month After Purchase</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Billionaire investor Carl C Icahn has sold his stake in General Motor Corp just one month after purchase; Icahn refuses to disclose when he sold his shares or size of his stake, but says it was less than $15 million (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just a month after notifying General Motors that he might buy as much as 15 percent of its shares, the billionaire investor Carl C. Icahn has sold his stake in the automaker.</p>
        <p>General Motors shares, which rose in August when G.M. disclosed Mr. Icahn's plans, are likely to fall today when investors learn that he has backed away, said John Casesa, auto analyst at Merrill Lynch. ''The stock will be down on this news,'' Mr. Casesa said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just a month after notifying General Motors that he might buy as much as 15 percent of its shares, the billionaire investor Carl C. Icahn has sold his stake in the automaker.</p>
        <p>General Motors shares, which rose in August when G.M. disclosed Mr. Icahn's plans, are likely to fall today when investors learn that he has backed away, said John Casesa, auto analyst at Merrill Lynch. ''The stock will be down on this news,'' Mr. Casesa said.</p>
        <p>Once derided as little more than a greenmailer, Mr. Icahn has gained a reputation as an aggressive value-oriented investor who presses companies with strong assets but weak stock prices to revamp or sell themselves. He made $600 million earlier this year after buying 10 percent of Nabisco Group Holdings and pressing Nabisco management to split the food and cigarette subsidiaries, a step Nabisco took in June.</p>
        <p>For value investors, General Motors is a tempting target. The company's share of the North American auto market has steadily declined for two decades, and analysts say the company suffers from weak management and unexciting cars. Still, G.M. is among the world's largest companies, with 388,000 employees and $6 billion in profit last year. With a market capitalization of $36 billion, the company trades at less than seven times its expected 2000 earnings, despite hidden assets that include a 32 percent stake in Hughes Electronics, worth a further $16 billion.</p>
        <p>G.M. declined to comment on Mr. Icahn's unexpected reversal. Mr. Icahn would not disclose when he sold his shares or the size of his stake in G.M., but said it was less than $15 million.</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether Mr. Icahn has permanently dropped his plans to invest in the automaker. Even as he bought shares last month, Mr. Icahn never publicly disclosed whether he planned to adopt a passive role in the company or an active one in forcing G.M. to restructure.</p>
        <p>But a person close to the situation said Mr. Icahn was angered that General Motors disclosed his plans to buy its shares, driving up the stock price and the cost of his investment. Shares of G.M. rose $4.56, or 7 percent, to $70 on the day that G.M. announced Mr. Icahn's interest, and rose as high as $75.75 early this month. Since then, they have given back some of those gains on fears that higher oil prices will slow auto sales. They closed yesterday at $68.31, up $1.</p>
        <p>Mr. Icahn maintains that the company was not legally required to disclose his plans and that it did so only to get a short-term boost in its stock price. A G.M. spokeswoman said the company disclosed Mr. Icahn's plans because it was in the midst of a $1.4 billion stock buyback and must make available to investors any information that might materially affect its share price.</p>
        <p>Mr. Icahn's anger was compounded when he learned that a large G.M. institutional shareholder -- which had encouraged Mr. Icahn to take a stake in the automaker -- sold its G.M. shares after they rose on the news of Mr. Icahn's involvement. In the face of the twin affronts, Mr. Icahn apparently decided to demonstrate his power to damage G.M.'s stock price by walking away from the company.</p>
        <p>In addition, he may not have realized when he made his initial investment how difficult G.M. would be to revamp, Mr. Casesa of Merrill Lynch said. In North America and Europe, its two most important markets, the auto business suffers from ''chronic excess capacity, no growth, sticky labor issues,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Joseph Phillippi of PaineWebber said General Motors ''has a tremendous amount of work to do on its auto portfolio'' and ''very little product that appeals to the vast majority of baby boomers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Casesa said investors tended to underestimate G.M. because its market capitalization is smaller than some young technology companies with much less revenue and only a few thousand employees. In reality, G.M. has great power, through its unions and its enormous network of dealers, if it feels threatened.</p>
        <p>''It would be very difficult for even someone as persuasive as Icahn to blast through this wall of granite,'' he said. ''It's very difficult for an outsider to affect the course of the fundamental operations at G.M.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
