<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romania Sweeps as Controversy Swirls</title>
    <meta content="22GYMN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: GYMNASTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Romania</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raducan, Andreea</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Amanar, Simona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olaru, Maria</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gymnastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EEDF113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romania Sweeps as Controversy Swirls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andreea Raducan (Romania) wins gold medal in women's individual all-around Gymnastics competition at Sydney Olympics; Simona Amanar (Romania) wins silver medal and Maria Olaru (Romania) wins bronze; controversy surrounding error made in measurement of vault apparatus discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An inexplicable error made in the measurement of the vault apparatus during the women's Olympic all-around final tonight cast doubt on the validity of the outcome and may have cost the former world champion Svetlana Khorkina a chance to win a medal.</p>
        <p>As controversy about the error roiled backstage at the Super Dome, the dominant Romanians were claiming every space on the medal stand. Unflustered by the situation, Romania became the first country to have its gymnasts take the gold, silver and bronze medals since the former Soviet Union swept the event in 1960.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An inexplicable error made in the measurement of the vault apparatus during the women's Olympic all-around final tonight cast doubt on the validity of the outcome and may have cost the former world champion Svetlana Khorkina a chance to win a medal.</p>
        <p>As controversy about the error roiled backstage at the Super Dome, the dominant Romanians were claiming every space on the medal stand. Unflustered by the situation, Romania became the first country to have its gymnasts take the gold, silver and bronze medals since the former Soviet Union swept the event in 1960.</p>
        <p>But as a joyful Andreea Raducan was accepting her gold medal after her spectacular night, as the silver medalist Simona Amanar waved to the crowd and Maria Olaru gripped her bronze medal tightly, an angry Khorkina told reporters to ''get lost.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps more than anyone, the graceful Russian was affected by the measurement blunder made by the technical personnel from the International Gymnastics Federation, the governing body for the sport.</p>
        <p>Through the first two of the four vault rotations -- during which 18 of the 36 gymnasts competed -- the block was 120 centimeters (just over 47 inches) above the floor instead of the mandatory 125 centimeters (just over 49 inches). The nearly two-inch difference in height threw off the timing and technique of several gymnasts.</p>
        <p>Just before the third rotation, an Australian gymnast, Allana Slater, questioned the height of the apparatus. Officials readjusted it and said they would give competitors in the first two rotations a chance to vault again. But the psychological damage was done, particularly in Khorkina's case.</p>
        <p>The Russian diva of gymnastics led after her floor exercise, but crashed badly on her next event, the vault, landing on her knees and bumping her head into the mat. She scored a dreadful 9.025. By the end of the rotation, she had plunged into 10th place.</p>
        <p>''She is our No. 1 gymnast,'' said Valery Dianov, a Russian team official, speaking through an interpreter. ''We expected her to be an Olympic champion. But that jump, the vault was too low. She was emotionally depressed.''</p>
        <p>Still visibly upset, Khorkina then became unraveled on her signature event, the uneven bars. Two moves on the apparatus are named after her, but with her psyche in tatters, she fell on a daring release move she usually handles easily.</p>
        <p>''It's like she said, 'Welcome to my nightmare,' '' said the former American gold medalist Peter Vidmar, an analyst for NBC. ''When she blew the vault, the tears came. She knew it was all over. When she got on the uneven bars, all the wind was out of her sails.''</p>
        <p>At the end of the night, Khorkina did not choose to vault again. She was in 11th place, and after her fall on the uneven bars, not even a perfect score would have put her on the medal stand. Instead, she sat in a huff, talked on a cell phone, and looked disgusted by the situation. But the American Elise Ray decided to revault, and stood as proof of just how much about two inches can mean.</p>
        <p>She had no chance at a medal, but she knew she was better than the 35th spot she occupied thanks in large part to her 7.618 score after two horrific landings on the vault. With the vault block at standard height, she stuck her landing and replaced her disastrous score in the first rotation with a 9.487. With that, Ray rocketed 21 spots through the standings. Instead of an embarrassingly low finish, the United States national champion ended up in 14th.</p>
        <p>''I didn't know what was wrong,'' Ray said. ''It looked low to me, but I thought it was my nerves. Definitely falling on your first event shoots your confidence way down. That was the toughest part, just to keep going.''</p>
        <p>This was the first time in memory that such an error was made at the Olympics. Although many gymnasts were upset, Slava Corn, a federation official, said the athletes had no recourse.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen anything like this,'' United States Coach Kelli Hill said. ''At the Olympics? It's unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>There is a system of checks and double-checks for the equipment. The technical staff makes the measurements, then there are officials and judges who make visual scans of the apparatus. Somehow, the vault escaped everyone's attention until Slater did the math. ''I know where I stand next to the vault, and I know how high it is on me,'' Slater said. ''You don't think of something like this happening at the Olympics. It could have totally changed everything.''</p>
        <p>There is no way of knowing what, if any, change in the outcome would have occurred. Other gymnasts, like Raducan, were unaffected. She was also in the marred rotation groups, but effortlessly landed her vault with a 9.7.</p>
        <p>Unlike the willowy Khorkina, Raducan is the template for the gymnastic pixie. At 4 feet 10 inches tall, holding at 82 pounds, Raducan is a pillow mint next to Khorkina. With her size, speed and quickness, she can adjust more easily to a low vault. As Vidmar said, ''It was like jumping a lunch box,'' for the 5-4 1/2 Khorkina.</p>
        <p>Controversy aside, the diminutive Raducan was a strong adversary for Khorkina. While the 21-year-old Khorkina was the world champion in 1997 and won the European title earlier this year, the 16-year-old Raducan had risen to the level of the elite.</p>
        <p>She unveiled her talent on the floor exercise. Khorkina had the top score on that event (9.812) this evening until Raducan finished off her competition with a 9.825. A product of Romania's factory-like gymnastics system, Raducan was a vision of precision and consistency. She had only one score below a 9.7, a 9.575 on the uneven bars.</p>
        <p>In the end, Raducan, and her medal-winning teammates, were examples of the vice grip the Romanians have on gymnastics. Once, the Russians ruled. Now, it is the Romanians. Not only did they sweep the all-around, they won the team gold on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''I'm very excited,'' Raducan said through an interpreter. ''I was very happy that I got the gold in the team, and I expected a good result tonight. It was important to do my best. I am very happy that I was able to control my emotions.''</p>
        <p>Nothing rattled Raducan, not even the glaring mistake made by the technical staff.</p>
        <p>''It was a tragedy for all the athletes,'' Vidmar said. ''For the rest of Khorkina's life -- or for any of the gymnasts -- they'll say, 'What if?' This was something they had no control over. That's what's sad.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: GYMNASTICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
