<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Space Race for Satellite Radio Is Picking Up Speed</title>
    <meta content="22CARS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/business/22CARS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moran, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4D6103BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Space Race for Satellite Radio Is Picking Up Speed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM MORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moran, Tim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on potential market for satellite radio services for drivers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OFFICIALS of XM Satellite Radio took a step into the future last week with a small demonstration in a refurbished 100-year-old printing building in Washington. They turned on a radio and received music.</p>
        <p>While that may not seem exciting, the signal was one that XM bounced off a K-band satellite orbiting in space. The satellite and the signal bandwidth were both borrowed, but for North American motorists the brief experiment heralded a future of uninterrupted radio reception nationwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OFFICIALS of XM Satellite Radio took a step into the future last week with a small demonstration in a refurbished 100-year-old printing building in Washington. They turned on a radio and received music.</p>
        <p>While that may not seem exciting, the signal was one that XM bounced off a K-band satellite orbiting in space. The satellite and the signal bandwidth were both borrowed, but for North American motorists the brief experiment heralded a future of uninterrupted radio reception nationwide.</p>
        <p>XM and its competitor, Sirius Satellite Radio of New York City, predict that drivers will be among the most enthusiastic customers for their proposed subscription services. If all goes according to plan, satellite radio could be available early next year. Automakers are planning to install special receivers in some 2001-model luxury vehicles.</p>
        <p>The services are expected to bring to radio what cable television brought to the TV industry: an abundance of channels, each dedicated to slivers of the national audience. There will be channels for sports talk; for reggae and merengue; for gospel, salsa and big-band jazz, among many other formats.</p>
        <p>In the early 1990's, the Federal Communications Commission freed space on the 12.5 megahertz ''S band'' for satellite radio, but seven years of legal challenges and lobbying against the plan by broadcasters delayed what was then known as CD radio.</p>
        <p>Sirius and XM officials say they doubt that other broadcasters will be able to enter the business, because of the high start-up costs and a web of technical and industry alliances that have set a standard for the radio receivers. Together, the two companies have put more than $2 billion in capital behind the idea, lining up strategic investors from automakers and consumer-electronics companies.</p>
        <p>This summer, two radio-broadcasting satellites belonging to Sirius roared into orbit at the tip of Russian Proton rockets launched from the Baikonur Cosmodrome in Kazakhstan, with a third to follow in November. ''You feel a sense of gratitude when it goes up,'' David Margolese, Sirius's chief executive, said of the launchings, which he and Sirius staff members watched on closed-circuit television. ''Unlike most things in this world where you have an illusion of a degree of control over what your endeavor is all about, the rocket launch is something where even that illusion is stripped away.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Margolese said that each satellite, which cost about $100 million to build and $140 million to insure and launch, needed to undergo a monthlong ''burn in'' and testing period 27,000 miles above earth before the network could begin live 24-hour broadcasting. Sirius satellites will have an elliptical orbit to give full North American coverage.</p>
        <p>For XM, the first of its two satellites is to be launched by the end of the year from a converted oil rig near the equator in the Pacific Ocean. XM's satellites will stay in a geostationary orbit over the continent. They will be launched by the Sea Launch Consortium, which has had three successful satellite liftoffs, most recently placing PanAmSat 9 into orbit in late August.</p>
        <p>''It is the most powerful commercial satellite available today, at about 15 kilowatts,'' said Hugh Panero, president and chief executive of XM. ''You need a lot of power in order to make sure you can deliver a strong-enough signal.'' XM calls its Washington operation the largest digital studio in America. Currently, 125 people are developing programming there in 82 fiber optic digital broadcast booths. The staff is expected to swell to 350 by next summer.</p>
        <p>''We believe our service will complement local radio, which obviously has a unique, local hook,'' Mr. Panero said. ''People will still tune in to AM and FM to get the local news and the local traffic.''</p>
        <p>Sirius has 150 employees working in 150,000 square feet of studios in the McGraw-Hill Building in Rockefeller Center. Mr. Margolese says the company will benefit from the proximity of other broadcasters in New York, along with an abundance of performers who can provide content for 100 channels of largely advertisement-free music, talk and other programming. ''In Manhattan, you get all kinds of people who are really specialists in all kinds of niche markets, genres and formats,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Carmakers are lining up behind the services. General Motors and Honda have signed on with XM; Ford, DaimlerChrysler and BMW chose Sirius. The two formats will not be compatible at first, but within several years the radios will be capable of getting either signal; consumers will be able to subscribe to either or both. The monthly charge is estimated at $10.</p>
        <p>''The most important thing is, we think it's something our customers want, and will want more of,'' said Phil Wright, director of business development and finance for telematics at the Ford Motor Company.</p>
        <p>While confirming that the radios will first appear on top-of-the-line cars and light trucks, Mr. Wright said automakers expected the prices for satellite radios to drop rapidly once the computer-chip sets that process the signals reach mass production. Early radios will have a separate ''black box'' of chips with a wholesale cost of $300 or more, but the chips will eventually be incorporated directly into the radios. At that point, automakers expect the wholesale price to fall to $75 or $80.</p>
        <p>''Eventually, you're going to see this thing more as a standard-equipment item, certainly on higher series or packaged with different options,'' Mr. Wright said.</p>
        <p>That may not be for several years, though, and in the meantime satellite radio is expected to be a costly prestige option.</p>
        <p>Only a few items will identify cars with the equipment: a palm-sized roof-mounted antenna and a selector button for satellite radio in addition to AM and FM bands. A large liquid-crystal display on the radio's face would show more information than current AM-FM sets provide, including a readout of a song's title, artist and record label to go along with the fadeout-free, interference-free digital broadcast.</p>
        <p>Holding onto a cohesive national signal will require innovative technology like a ''buffer'' of stored broadcast information kept by the car's radio. Mr. Panero, at XM, says that company's two satellites will broadcast identical signals, but at times they will be several minutes out of sync. The buffer will allow receivers that may have ''missed'' one signal because of interference -- say, being in a tunnel or behind a mountain -- to pick up the second signal, re-synchronize and continue uninterrupted play.</p>
        <p>''If you go under an overpass, you will be able to have consistent delivery of the signal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In urban areas and other places where satellite signals may be blocked or bounced by terrain or tall buildings, local ground-based repeater networks will augment the satellite signals.</p>
        <p>Automakers expect consumers to be delighted by signals that do not cut out after 30 or 40 miles of driving. Automakers are also eager to participate in satellite radio because it answers their desire to continue a relationship with customers after a car is sold.</p>
        <p>While subscribers will initially get satellite radio along with the lease or purchase of a new car, at some point the subscription will need to be renewed, and carmakers expect to share in that revenue. Renewal time could also give them opportunities to sell related services, add-on entertainment, security or maintenance features.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wright, at Ford, says his company may eventually bundle Sirius radio with Wingcast, a menu of in-car electronic services that would include a wireless phone connection, Internet access, emergency assistance and entertainment channels; Ford expects all of its new cars to have Wingcast capability by the end of 2004. G.M. has similar plans for its OnStar communications and emergency services system.</p>
        <p>''They want to maintain and develop a very intimate relationship with the customer,'' Mr. Panero said of automakers. ''In the past, they have foregone participating in the cellular or even the radio business -- and they have been responsible for creating some of the environments where these businesses thrived.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
