<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Intel Expects Its Revenue To Be Below Expectations</title>
    <meta content="Y22CHI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/technology/22CHIP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Intel Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Lawrence M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DE1E3BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Intel Expects Its Revenue To Be Below Expectations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Lawrence M</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Intel Corp warns its third-quarter revenues are likely to be below company's previous expectations, primarily because of weaker demand for company's microprocessing chips in Europe; news sends Intel's shares down 20 percent in after-hours trading; Intel expects revenue for third quarter to be about 3 percent to 5 percent higher than second-quarter revenue of $8.3 billion; analysts had predicted growth of 12 to 15 percent (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Intel Corporation warned today that its third-quarter revenues were likely to be below the company's previous expectations, primarily because of weaker demand for the company's microprocessing chips in Europe.</p>
        <p>The news sent Intel's shares down by 20 percent in after-hours trading.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Intel Corporation warned today that its third-quarter revenues were likely to be below the company's previous expectations, primarily because of weaker demand for the company's microprocessing chips in Europe.</p>
        <p>The news sent Intel's shares down by 20 percent in after-hours trading.</p>
        <p>Intel said it now expected revenue for the third quarter to be about 3 percent to 5 percent higher than second-quarter revenue of $8.3 billion. Analysts had predicted growth of 12 to 15 percent. Intel did not forecast third-quarter earnings.</p>
        <p>Analysts surveyed by First Call/ Thomson Financial had previously expected earnings of 41 cents a diluted share.</p>
        <p>Intel made its announcement after the close of the market. Intel shares closed at $61.48, down $1.58, in Nasdaq trading. Intel's stock fell $12.60 to $48.88 in after-hours trading, with 11.7 million shares changing hands, according to Instinet.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that the shortfall from a bellwether technology company like Intel would probably worsen the recent turmoil among stocks in the sector, and that investors should brace for a big Nasdaq sell-off on Friday.</p>
        <p>Intel shares had already lost almost 25 percent of their value after Ashok Kumar, an analyst with U.S. Bancorp Piper Jaffray, downgraded the stock earlier this month. On Wednesday, Mr. Kumar said Intel shares had fallen far enough to represent a trading buy, although he did not change his rating. Today, he said he believed the weakness extended well beyond Europe.</p>
        <p>''There is weakness across all the geographies,'' Mr. Kumar said. ''With the exception of Japan, demand fell off a cliff. What that does is create significant inventory overhang, which basically destroys the pricing environment,'' he said, noting that Intel's archrival, Advanced Micro Devices Inc., stands to suffer the most. ''A.M.D. basically becomes road kill, but there will be a huge ripple effect all up and down the semiconductor supply chain.''</p>
        <p>Since the introduction of the original I.B.M. PC, Intel had been able to ride computer users' endless desire for more processing power. The spread of the Microsoft Corporation's Windows operating system and the related Office suite of applications drove demand for more powerful processors. Intel could introduce processors at higher prices, and consumers would snap them up.</p>
        <p>But the climate is different now. The big drivers of demand are the Internet and electronic commerce, neither of which is limited so much by microprocessor power as by bandwidth. Intel is in the bandwidth business, with various networking products, but not nearly to the extent that it is in the processing power business. And on most of today's real-world applications, there is little benefit in upgrading from a 500-megahertz Pentium II chip to a 1-gigahertz Pentium III. Windows ME, the new operating system from Microsoft, does not require more processing power than did Windows 98.</p>
        <p>Intel said it expected gross profit margin for the third quarter to be 62 percent, plus or minus a point, down from the company's previous expectations. Profit margin is primarily driven by revenues and the mix of product sold during the quarter.</p>
        <p>However, interest and other income is expected to be about $900 million for the third quarter, up from the company's previous expectations of $800 million. Intel said it expected third-quarter expenses to be up 7 to 9 percent from second-quarter expenses of $2.2 billion, primarily because of higher spending on marketing and research and development in new business areas.</p>
        <p>For its second fiscal quarter, which ended on July 1, Intel had revenue of $8.3 billion, a quarterly record, up 23 percent from the second quarter of 1999 and 4 percent sequentially. Net income excluding acquisition-related costs was $3.5 billion, up 98 percent from the second quarter of 1999 and up 16 percent sequentially. At the time, Craig Barrett, Intel's president and chief executive, said he expected strong demand to continue into the second half of the fiscal year.</p>
        <p>[Asian stock markets sank on Friday as technology shares were hit by the profit warning by Intel. In Japan, stocks tumbled, led by semiconductor issues like the chipmakers NEC and Toshiba. By early afternoon, the benchmark 225-issue Nikkei Stock Average had shed 470.33 points, or 2.88 percent, to 15,840.72. In Hong Kong, the Hang Seng Index fell 2.03 percent just after the opening. And regional markets like Seoul and Taipei dominated by technology issues were down about 4 percent to about 6 percent.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
