<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iranian Court, Citing Its Kindness, Cuts Sentences for 10 Jews</title>
    <meta content="Y22IRA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/world/22IRAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sciolino, Elaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DC113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iranian Court, Citing Its Kindness, Cuts Sentences for 10 Jews</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sciolino, Elaine</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Appeals court in Iran reduces sentences of 10 Iranian Jews who had been convicted of cooperating with Israel in a trial that drew relentless international scrutiny and widespread criticism (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An appeals court in Iran today reduced the sentences of 10 Iranian Jews who had been convicted of cooperating with Israel in a trial that drew relentless international scrutiny and widespread criticism.</p>
        <p>But the ruling -- intended as a gesture of the forgiving nature of the Islamic Republic -- seems to have backfired, as the United States, Jewish groups and even the defendants' lawyer criticized it as insufficient.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An appeals court in Iran today reduced the sentences of 10 Iranian Jews who had been convicted of cooperating with Israel in a trial that drew relentless international scrutiny and widespread criticism.</p>
        <p>But the ruling -- intended as a gesture of the forgiving nature of the Islamic Republic -- seems to have backfired, as the United States, Jewish groups and even the defendants' lawyer criticized it as insufficient.</p>
        <p>The ruling followed a review by a three-judge panel and reduced the terms of all 10 Jews by two to six years. After a closed trial in Shiraz, they were initially sentenced in July to 4 to 13 years. The court has yet to rule on the fate of the two Muslims who were convicted and sentenced to two years each in the case.</p>
        <p>In announcing the decision, the head of the judiciary of Fars Province, Hossein Ali Amiri, said, ''These are the least possible sentences, and we have used the ultimate of Islamic kindness and generosity.''</p>
        <p>He added that the 22-page ruling found that those convicted were guilty of one count of cooperation with a hostile state, striking down related charges that had been used to calculate the stiffer sentences.</p>
        <p>But the lead lawyer for the group, Ismael Nasseri, was quoted by the BBC as saying: ''In our view, Israel is the main winner from this verdict. We are unhappy, above all because the charge of collaborating with the Israeli regime has been maintained.''</p>
        <p>No prisoner was freed, despite the fact that under law prisoners may be released after having served 30 percent of their sentences. Since the defendants were imprisoned 19 months ago, long before their trials, those sentenced to terms of two to five years could have been released.</p>
        <p>The defendants, among them a shoe salesman, a government worker, the owner of a textile store, store clerks and religion teachers, had initially been charged with spying for Israel and the United States in a case that could have brought the death penalty. They were convicted of lesser charges based on evidence gleaned from their confessions, which were given after long periods of detention in which they were allowed little contact with their lawyers or families.</p>
        <p>The ruling was swiftly criticized. ''The United States is disappointed that today's appeals court decision in Iran does not overturn all of the convictions that were imposed on the 10 Iranian Jews,'' a State Department spokesman, Richard A. Boucher, said. ''We're also disappointed that the Iranian government has not released any of the 10 defendants.''</p>
        <p>''This is not what we hoped for,'' said Malcolm Hoenlein, executive vice chairman of the Conference of Presidents of Major American Jewish Organizations, a group that has monitored the case. ''We're calling on Iran's leadership to intervene immediately and grant them clemency, because it is obvious that Iran's judiciary is not prepared to act in a responsible way.''</p>
        <p>This week, Mr. Nasseri said he had received death threats after refusing to admit that his clients were guilty. ''We have sworn that we will not betray our clients and we cannot accept that our clients are spies,'' Mr. Nasseri was quoted as having said.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Vatican Says It Interceded</p>
        <p>(By The New York Times),  ROME, Sept. 21 -- The Vatican said today that it had interceded ''directly and indirectly'' with Iranian authorities on behalf of the Jews convicted of spying for Israel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
