<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="22CLAS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD6103BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="4469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''LUCIA DI LAMMERMOOR.'' Amato Opera's new season opened last weekend, and sadly, for the first time in nearly 50 years, the fans of this family-run opera company were not greeted in the theater lobby by the co-founder Sally Amato, who died last month at 82. But the company, still run by her husband, Anthony, goes on. Its first offering is a revival of its production of Donizetti's ''Lucia di Lammermoor,'' with performances tonight and tomorrow night, and Sunday afternoon. The soprano Alicia Alexander sings the title role, with Vincent Titone, a tenor, as Edgardo, and Justin Ryan, a baritone, as Enrico. Mr. Amato conducts. Amato Opera Theater, 319 Bowery, (212) 228-8200. Today and tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 2:30 p.m. Tickets are $25 ($20 for seniors and children under 12) (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''LUCIA DI LAMMERMOOR.'' Amato Opera's new season opened last weekend, and sadly, for the first time in nearly 50 years, the fans of this family-run opera company were not greeted in the theater lobby by the co-founder Sally Amato, who died last month at 82. But the company, still run by her husband, Anthony, goes on. Its first offering is a revival of its production of Donizetti's ''Lucia di Lammermoor,'' with performances tonight and tomorrow night, and Sunday afternoon. The soprano Alicia Alexander sings the title role, with Vincent Titone, a tenor, as Edgardo, and Justin Ryan, a baritone, as Enrico. Mr. Amato conducts. Amato Opera Theater, 319 Bowery, (212) 228-8200. Today and tomorrow at 7:30 p.m. and Sunday at 2:30 p.m. Tickets are $25 ($20 for seniors and children under 12) (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''MADAMA BUTTERFLY,'' New York City Opera. Mark Lamos's production, introduced at the Glimmerglass Opera in 1997 and at the City Opera the next year, stands up well, offering a clean canvas for the compelling lighting design of Robert Wierzel. The performance mostly does justice to the production, with Andrew Richards as a strong Pinkerton and Jake Gardner a worthy foil as Sharpless. The whole thing may be even better by now if Susan Bullock, effective in her middle range in the title role, has toned down the shrillness of her high notes on opening night, and Jorge Mester, the conductor, has arrived at a considerate balance for the singers. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., New York State Theater, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $25 to $98 (James R. Oestreich).</p>
        <p>''LE NOZZE DI FIGARO.'' This John Copley production has been in the New York City Opera's repertory for about a quarter-century, but it is attractive and compact and does what a ''Figaro'' production should: foster the sense of ensemble and precise comic timing on which the work depends. The company offers a youthful, well-balanced cast that includes Sari Gruber as Susanna, Dean Ely as Figaro, Paula Rasmussen as Cherubino, Pamela Armstrong as the Countess and John Hancock as the Count. Steuart Bedford conducts. Tomorrow at 1:30 p.m., the New York State Theater. Tickets: $25 to $98; (212) 870-5570 (Allan Kozinn).</p>
        <p>''ROBERTO DEVEREUX.'' This riproarer by Donizetti through English history is a vehicle for its Queen Elizabeth. Lauren Flanigan works assiduously to wrap her considerable talents around the part and with mixed success. The cast is otherwise competent, though not always wisely matched to the roles. But ''Roberto Devereux'' is not that often put on. Mark Lamos's production is worth a listen and a look for bel canto fans. New York City Opera. Sunday at 1:30 p.m. New York State Theater, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $25 to $98 (Bernard Holland).</p>
        <p>''LA TRAVIATA.'' The New York City Opera's handsome and effective staging of Verdi's ''Traviata'' returns to the repertory tonight. The production is by the renowned soprano Renata Scotto, who brings a telling sense of detail and fresh nuance to this familiar work. The impressive soprano Mary Dunleavy sings the role of Violetta. The tenor Bruce Fowler is Alfredo, and the baritone Stephen Powell is Germont. Joseph Rescigno conducts. New York State Theater. Tonight at 8. Tickets, $25 to $98; (212) 496-0600 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''WHAT PRICE CONFIDENCE?'' Ernst Krenek's music deserves more attention, and perhaps this season, the centennial of his birth and the 10th anniversary of his death, it will find a few champions. Elysium -- Between Two Continents, a German-American organization that focuses on the work of artists who were forced to flee Germany during the Nazi years, is taking a first step with an evening built around Krenek's chamber opera ''What Price Confidence?'' The work, about the interrelationships between two married couples, was composed in 1945 but did not have its premiere until 1962. This production, directed by Gregorij H. von Leitis and conducted by John W. Simmons, will be sung by Julia Koci, soprano; Anne Duraski, mezzo-soprano; Christopher Pfund, tenor; and Joshua Parrillo, baritone. The program also includes a selection of Krenek's songs. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 p.m., Sunday at 3 p.m., Riverside Church, Riverside Drive at 122nd Street, Morningside Heights. Tickets: $15 and $25; (212) 870-6784 (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>ARTISTS FOR THE CURE. Tonight there will be a special benefit concert at Carnegie Hall to support breast cancer research at New York Weill Cornell Center. ''Artists for the Cure at Carnegie Hall'' was inspired by the violinist Joan Kwuon, whose breast cancer was diagnosed last year when she was 30 and who is being treated successfully at the Weill center. Joining Ms. Kwuon for the concert will be the conductor and pianist Andre Previn, the mezzo-soprano Denyce Graves, the Juilliard String Quartet, the soprano Evelyn Lear and the Prometheus Chamber Orchestra. Mandy Patinkin will be the evening's host. Carnegie Hall, tonight at 7:30; tickets are $100, $60 and $30. Tickets and information: Carnegie Charge, (212) 247-7800 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>BARGEMUSIC. The pianist Anne-Marie McDermott assembled the meaty programs for this weekend's concerts at this floating concert hall on the East River. In both she will be  joined by the cellist Fred Sherry and the violinist Ani Kavafian. Tonight and Sunday afternoon, the program includes a piano trio by Mozart (the C major, K. 548) and a piano quintet by Schumann (Op. 44) with the violinist Kerry McDermott and the violist Paul Neubauer, separated by the Copland Violin Sonata. Tomorrow evening Ms. McDermott will play the Bach Partita in C minor and will be joined afterward by Ms. Kavafian for a Beethoven sonata (Op. 12, No. 3). The concert ends with Dvorak's piano quintet in A . To</p>
        <p>night and tomorrow at 7:30 and Sunday at 4 p.m. Bargemusic, Fulton Ferry Landing, Brooklyn, (718) 624-4061 or (718) 624-2083. Tickets: $27, $25 for the elderly, $15 for students (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>BASICALLY BACH. This little festival, now in its eighth year, has produced memorable performances, none more so than Walter Hilse's reading of Bach's ''Art of Fugue'' on the church's organ in 1995. For the Bach year, the 250th anniversary of the composer's death, the series revives that performance tomorrow afternoon at 4 and adds a reading of the ''Goldberg'' Variations by the fine harpsichordist Kenneth Cooper at 2 and an account of the B minor Mass by St. Peter's choir with the Gregg Smith Singers and the Bach Festival Orchestra, conducted by Ralph C. Schultz, at 8. Felix Hell, a gifted 15-year-old organist, presents a Bach recital on Sunday at 2 p.m., St. Peter's Church, Lexington Avenue at 54th Street, (212) 935-2200. Tickets: festival, $50; individual recitals, $20; Mass, $25; discounts for students and the elderly (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>LEONIDAS KAVAKOS. This young Greek violinist has made some energetic, beautifully nuanced recordings, and here offers a program that combines emotional weight and technical showiness. Included are the Brahms Sonata No. 1 in G, Bartok's Rhapsody No. 2, Zemlinsky's Serenade in A, Kreisler's ''Viennese Rhapsodic Fantasietta'' and Ernst's ''Fantasy on Hungarian Airs.'' Peter Nagy is the pianist. Tomorrow at 8 p.m., the 92nd Street Y, Lexington Ave. at 92nd Street, (212) 996-1100. Tickets: $18 to $25 (Kozinn).</p>
        <p>BRIAN LEERHUBER. Some years ago the mezzo-soprano Marilyn Horne began to worry that the art of the song recital was waning. So she decided to do something about it, and ever since, the Marilyn Horne Foundation has been providing support to help young singers give recitals throughout the United States. There is a yearly series of concerts at the Kosciuszko Foundation in New York, and this season's offerings begin on Sunday afternoon with a recital by a young California-born baritone, Brian Leerhuber, accompanied by the pianist Michael Baitzer. The three-part program, intriguingly titled ''Songs of Gods and Heroes, Serenades and Nocturnes,'' offers works by Schubert, Wolf, Mendelssohn, Debussy, Ives, Cole Porter, Elinor Remick Warren and others. Kosciuszko Foundation, 15 East 65th Street, Manhattan. Tickets are $15; (212) 734-2130 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>MUSIC BEFORE 1800. Happily, it appears that this invaluable series, as it enters its second quarter-century, will not relax its efforts to find the unusual. Here, Al Qantarah, an Italian quintet of singers and instrumentalists named after a river in Sicily, offers a program of Middle Eastern-tinged music from medieval Sicily and Spain. Sunday at 4 p.m., Corpus Christi Church, 529 W. 121st Street, (212) 666-9266. Tickets: $25; $20 for the elderly; $15 for students (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>NEW JUILLIARD ENSEMBLE. The free concerts by the New Juilliard Ensemble, the school's dynamic contemporary music chamber orchestras, conducted by the inspired Joel Sachs, are consistently exciting and stimulating. This season's offerings begin tomorrow night with a typically intriguing program. Jack Beeson's ''Ophelia Sings'' receives its premiere. There will also be United States premieres of works by Deirdre Gribbin, Laszlo Tihany, Suren Zakarian and John Casken, as well as a work by Ushio Torikai. Don't be dissuaded if these names are unfamiliar. Mr. Sacks knows how to pick winners. Juilliard Theater; tomorrow at 8 p.m. The performance is free, but tickets, available from the box office, are required; (212) 769-7406 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC. Kurt Masur produced one of his first seeming miracles with this orchestra already weeks before he officially took over as music director in 1991, achieving a rare lightness and grace in a concert of Mendelssohn at Tilles Center on Long Island, which included the ''Italian'' Symphony. Here, as part of a welcome three-week minifestival of Mendelssohn, Mr. Masur leads the orchestra in the same symphony, two overtures and the Violin Concerto, with Sheryl Staples, the Philharmonic's superb principal associate concertmaster, as soloist. Today at 2 p.m. and tomorrow at 8 p.m., Avery Fisher Hall, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: today, $31 to $63; tomorrow, $50 to $78 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>STEVE REICH AND MUSICIANS. They revisit pieces from Mr. Reich's past in the second of two concerts at the Miller Theater on the Columbia University campus. Perhaps the richest and subtlest practitioner of the so-called Minimalist style, this American composer offers his landmark ''Music for Eighteen Musicians'' (a repeat from Thursday's program) and also ''Music for Pieces of Wood'' and ''Different Trains.'' Miller Theater, tomorrow night at 7:30, Broadway at 116th Street, (212) 854-7799. Tickets: $25. (Holland).</p>
        <p>ISAAC STERN. Before the official opening of its season, Carnegie Hall takes time to salute its president in honor of his 80th birthday. Mr. Stern, who recently underwent heart surgery, was not scheduled to perform in any case. Instead, he leaves the music-making to family and friends. His sons, David and Michael Stern, conduct the Symphony Orchestra of the Curtis Institute of Music in a Sunday concert at 7:30 p.m., with famous soloists too numerous to mention. Events earlier that day include a Carnegie Kids concert in the Kaplan Space at 1 p.m.; family concerts in the main hall (er, Isaac Stern Auditorium) at 2 and 4; and young artists' chamber concerts in Weill Recital Hall at 3 and 5. Tomorrow, there are Stern films in Weill Recital Hall at 2:30, 5 and 8 p.m., and an exhibition in the Rose Museum from 11 a.m. to 5 p.m., all free. Carnegie Hall, tomorrow and Sunday, (212) 247-7800. Tickets: Carnegie Kids, $3; family and chamber concerts, $5; Sunday evening, $18 to $61 (Oestreich).</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>BIRMINGHAM ROYAL BALLET. A lively and sometimes unconventional British company makes its New York debut with David Bintley's startling ''Edward II,'' based on Christopher Marlowe's play about the 14th-century British king unable to reconcile his homosexual desires and his sense of royal duty. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 8 p.m.; Sunday at 3 p.m. City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212. Tickets: $25 to $60 (Jack Anderson).</p>
        <p>CHERNIAK DANCE. ''Autumn Engravings,'' a suite of works by Susan Cherniak, includes dances to Mahler and to new music by Peter Hyde. Tomorrow and Sunday at 8:30 p.m.  Cunningham Studio, 55 Bethune Street, 11th floor, West Village, (212) 924-0077. Tickets: $15; $10 for students and seniors. (Anderson).</p>
        <p>COYOTE DANCERS. Works by Maher Benham range from the mystical ''To the Night Goddess'' and ''Sipapu'' (for a cast of men between the ages of 12 and 70) to ''Invocation: Monk's Dance,'' staged for actors from the Neighborhood Playhouse School of the Theater. Tonight, tomorrow and Sunday at 8. Kaye Playhouse, 68th Street between Park and Lexington Avenues, Manhattan, (212) 772-4448. Tickets: $20 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>DOWNTOWN ARTS FESTIVAL. Compagnie Faim de Siecle, a multi-everything troupe based in New York and Paris, presents ''Shattered Boxes,'' inspired by the Medea myth. Tonight and tomorrow at 10. The Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793. Tickets: $20 (Jennifer Dunning).</p>
        <p>TRAJAL HARRELL DANCE STYLE. Dance fans can come and go as they please as Trajal Harrell shows five different works at various times during the course of a single afternoon and evening. Tomorrow at 4, 4:10, 4:30, 4:45, 5:15, 5:30, 5:45, 5:53, 6:15, 6:38, 6:43, 6:48 and 7 p.m. University Settlement, 184 Eldridge Street, Lower East Side; information, including specific programming: (212) 539-6710. Tickets: $12, $15 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>IN THE COMPANY OF MEN. A program by male choreographers and dancers features works by Andrew Asnes, Robert Battle, Matt Jensen, Nicholas Leichter, Gabriel Masson, Le Minh Tam, Nathan Trice and Charles Wright. Tonight and tomorrow at 8; Sunday at 6 p.m.; also a children's lecture-demonstration tomorrow at 4 p.m. Pace Downtown Theater, Spruce Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 625-8369. Tickets: $20 for performances; $3 and $1 for lecture (Anderson).</p>
        <p>JODI OBERFELDER. Six dancers perform heroic feats in acrobatic physical exchanges in ''Slay the Dragon,'' a full-evening piece. Set to music by John Zorn, it concerns triumphing over adversity. Tonight (and Thursdays through Saturdays through Oct. 7) at 8. Flea Theater, 41 White Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 226-2407. Tickets: $20; rush tickets, students and seniors, $15 (Dunning).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
