<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaign Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y22CAM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/politics/22CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E5D7113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaign Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>A SHOW OF SUBSTANCE -- All year, Vice President Al Gore has campaigned as the candidate of substance and detail (sometimes numbing detail), while portraying Gov. George W. Bush of Texas as fuzzy on substance and detail. Now Mr. Gore's running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, is following suit. Yesterday while visiting a computer chip plant in Florida, a major swing state, he delivered the first in a series of speeches that his aides said were designed to reinforce the image that the Democratic ticket is one of substance and detail. For 45 minutes he spoke on the ''new economy'' and the glories of high-tech training and research, and by the time he finally finished he had also touched on the uses of steam engines in the 18th century, the computing capacity of electronic gadgets like Palm Pilots and the need for the government to pay down debt to keep interest rates low. ''We are literally at what might be called the big bang stage of the information technology universe,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Richard Perez-Pena (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>A SHOW OF SUBSTANCE -- All year, Vice President Al Gore has campaigned as the candidate of substance and detail (sometimes numbing detail), while portraying Gov. George W. Bush of Texas as fuzzy on substance and detail. Now Mr. Gore's running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, is following suit. Yesterday while visiting a computer chip plant in Florida, a major swing state, he delivered the first in a series of speeches that his aides said were designed to reinforce the image that the Democratic ticket is one of substance and detail. For 45 minutes he spoke on the ''new economy'' and the glories of high-tech training and research, and by the time he finally finished he had also touched on the uses of steam engines in the 18th century, the computing capacity of electronic gadgets like Palm Pilots and the need for the government to pay down debt to keep interest rates low. ''We are literally at what might be called the big bang stage of the information technology universe,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Richard Perez-Pena (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
        <p>SWIPE AT DIVERSITY DISAVOWED -- Democrats called it race-baiting this week when a conservative group started broadcasting a television advertisement in Missouri, a swing state, that features a white woman saying that she pulled her son out of public school because there was ''a bit more diversity than he could handle.'' And after taking a look at the ad, the chairman of the Republican National Committee, Jim Nicholson, condemned it, ''forcefully and without equivocation,'' as he put it. At the same time, Mr. Nicholson charged that a pair of Democratic advertisements in 1998 were similarly racist and demanded that the chairman of the Democratic National Committee, Joe Andrew, condemn them. Mr. Andrew did not immediately respond. The latest ad, which shows a multiracial group of teenagers milling around as the woman speaks, concludes with a ''Vote Republican'' plea and is sponsored by a group that calls itself the Republican Ideas Political Committee. Republican officials say the group has no ties to the party.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>THE GREEN PARTY</p>
        <p>NADER'S 'CATCH-22' -- Though he has little chance of participating in the presidential debates, Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate, says he plans to attend the three forums in Boston, St. Louis and Salem, N.C. as a ''commentator,'' if any reporters want his analysis of the give-and-take. He says, too, that ABC and the Fox Network are still considering his proposal for additional debates that would include him and Patrick J. Buchanan, the Reform Party candidate. Asked why he has not won the 15 percent poll ratings needed to qualify for the three debates, Mr. Nader replied: ''It's a Catch-22. If you don't get mass media, you don't go up in the polls. If you don't up in the polls, you can't get mass media.''</p>
        <p>James Dao (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE INTEREST GROUPS</p>
        <p>N.A.A.C.P. WEIGHS IN -- The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People is spending $9 million on political advertisements and door-to-door organizing to increase black voter turnout in a dozen states in which the presidential race or one or more Congressional races are rated tossups. Run through a new organization, the N.A.A.C.P. National Voter Fund, the effort has registered 21,000 new voters and signed up 2,345 volunteers to help get black voters to the polls, said Julian Bond, the association's board chairman. The group will also run advertisements about the candidates' stands on particular topics without urging viewers to vote one way or the other. As a group, black voters have favored Democrats. The targeted states are Arkansas, Georgia, Illinois, Kentucky, Michigan, Missouri, New Jersey, New York, Ohio, Pennsylvania, Virginia and Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE TRAVEL LOG -- Yesterday was the kind of day that saw Gov. George W. Bush don a blue-on-blue Regis Philbin ensemble to go ''Live With Regis,'' where he talked of strengthening Social Security and cutting taxes. It was also the kind of day that led Al Gore to suggest that Mr. Bush must have thought he was on Mr. Philbin's other show, ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire,'' given his views on taxes and retirement money. The stats for the day:</p>
        <p>Length of the Official Day: Gore, 13 hours (6 1/2 debate preparation); Bush, 15 hours  States Visited: Gore 2, Bush 3  Towns and Cities Visited: Gore 3; Bush, 3  Events: Gore, 2; Bush 2  Press Conferences/Interviews: Gore, 0; Bush 5  Diners Visited/Unscheduled Drop-bys: Gore, 0; Bush 1  Miles Jogged: Gore, 0; Bush 3  Main Message: Gore, energy independence; Bush, Social Security</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
