<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sprinkling Stardust and a Dollop of Magic Over a Pair of Lovebirds</title>
    <meta content="22FANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/arts/22FANT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grey, Joel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, Jean Louisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McIntyre, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ritchie, Michael</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Fantasticks, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D8103BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sprinkling Stardust and a Dollop of Magic Over a Pair of Lovebirds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews movie version of The Fantasticks, directed by Michael Ritchie; Joe McIntyre, Jean Louisa Kelly and Joel Grey star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Perhaps 'The Fantasticks' is by nature the sort of thing that loses magic the longer it endures,'' Brooks Atkinson wrote in The New York Times more than 40 years ago. Of course Atkinson meant simply that this two-act musical trifle went on for too long to sustain its air of lighthearted romanticism. But the New York stage production of ''The Fantasticks'' has endured for something like a geologic age; next to it, even the extinct ''Cats'' occupies but a whisker's breadth on the timeline.</p>
        <p>And now, at long last, there is a movie version, directed by Michael Ritchie and released after languishing on dusty studio shelves for five years. As a film ''The Fantasticks,'' which opens today at the AMC Empire 25, wobbles between the timeless and the anachronistic. For all its robust good cheer it's a timid and uncertain creature, a mewing kitten wandering out into the world in search of a big-hearted 11-year-old girl to tie ribbons around its ears and give it a bowl of warm milk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Perhaps 'The Fantasticks' is by nature the sort of thing that loses magic the longer it endures,'' Brooks Atkinson wrote in The New York Times more than 40 years ago. Of course Atkinson meant simply that this two-act musical trifle went on for too long to sustain its air of lighthearted romanticism. But the New York stage production of ''The Fantasticks'' has endured for something like a geologic age; next to it, even the extinct ''Cats'' occupies but a whisker's breadth on the timeline.</p>
        <p>And now, at long last, there is a movie version, directed by Michael Ritchie and released after languishing on dusty studio shelves for five years. As a film ''The Fantasticks,'' which opens today at the AMC Empire 25, wobbles between the timeless and the anachronistic. For all its robust good cheer it's a timid and uncertain creature, a mewing kitten wandering out into the world in search of a big-hearted 11-year-old girl to tie ribbons around its ears and give it a bowl of warm milk.</p>
        <p>The story is woven of thinnest gossamer. Two adorable ingenues, male and female (Joe McIntyre and Jean Louisa Kelly, both of them lovely and hard-working), live side by side in clapboard farmhouses built on the edge of a glorious painted backdrop. Their fathers (Joel Grey and Brad Sullivan) pretend to feud, on the theory that parental opposition is the surest way to bring their youngsters together. To bring their plan to fruition, the dads hire the cast of a traveling carnival, led by a suave magician called El Gallo (Jonathon Morris), to abduct young Louisa so that Matt can rescue her and win her heart. Though the plan works, the lovebirds soon become disillusioned with each other, and the second act (about which Atkinson complained) follows them into temptation, through the loss of innocence that is a necessary condition for real love.</p>
        <p>It's all done in good fun and without pretensions. Nobody would enlist ''The Fantasticks'' in the canon of great musicals. Lyrics like ''what at night seems so scenic, may seem cynic by and by'' are not exactly Gershwin -- they're not exactly English, come to think of it. But the songs have a fresh-faced precocity, a 40-year-old precocity, to be sure, and the closing number, ''Try to Remember,'' has some claim to minor classic status.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, what looks like magic on stage can seem manic by the light of the screen. Live theater can tolerate outsize gestures, rickety sets and willful illusionism more easily than film, which is a stubbornly literal-minded medium. Mr. Grey and Mr. Sullivan, mugging and swinging their arms to reach the cheap seats, look a little foolish in close-up on the big screen, as does Mr. Morris, who has the flowing tresses and rolling diction of a touring-company veteran.</p>
        <p>The musical numbers are bizarrely edited: in her first big song, Ms. Kelly strolls down a rural lane, cavorts under a tree and reveals her longing for a bit of worldliness to a sympathetic cow. The haphazard cutting wrecks the moment with self-consciousness, a problem that persists through the long fantasy sequence in the middle of the movie. It is only overcome in the final duet, during which the camera stands back and lets the lovebirds belt out their feelings against a Technicolor sky.</p>
        <p>''The Fantasticks'' is, at bottom, a tribute to the transformative power of theater, and the theater is where it should have been allowed to remain. The movie version overflows with affection and good intention, but unwittingly turns a bauble of cheerful fakery into something that mostly feels phony.</p>
        <p>''The Fantasticks'' is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It includes a bout of stagy swordplay and some very mild ribaldry.</p>
        <p>THE FANTASTICKS  Directed by Michael Ritchie; written by Tom Jones and Harvey Schmidt, based on their play; director of photography, Fred Murphy; edited by William Scharf; score by Mr. Schmidt, lyrics by Tom Jones; production designer, Douglas W. Schmidt; produced by Mr. Ritchie and Linne Radmin; released by United Artists Films. At the AMC Empire 25, 234 West 42nd Street, Manhattan. Running time: 86 minutes. This film is rated PG.</p>
        <p>WITH: Joe McIntyre (Matt), Jean Louisa Kelly (Luisa), Joel Grey (Bellomy), Barnard Hughes (Henry), Jonathon Morris (El Gallo), Brad Sullivan (Hucklebee) and Teller (Mortimer).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
