<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Passion For Food And Other Delicacies</title>
    <meta content="22WOMA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/arts/22WOMA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruz, Penelope</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torres, Fina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Woman on Top (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFD6103BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Passion For Food And Other Delicacies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews movie Woman on Top, directed by Fina Torres and starring Penelope Cruz; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The soothing lilt of bossa nova floats over the malnourished but sometimes entrancing romantic comedy ''Woman on Top,'' which starts in Bahia, where the delectable Penelope Cruz plays Isabella, a chef. Isabella cooks magnificent meals, and epicures from around the globe fall in love with her culinary talents. In the dining room of the restaurant her husband, Toninho (Murilo Benicio), the restaurant's owner, flirts with female customers and fronts a band whose tempos dance above the diners' heads like aromas from the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Eventually we learn that Toninho's life has not been all congas and sambas. He has had literally to labor under Isabella, whose lifelong and pronounced motion sickness means she has to be in control of everything. (She gets nauseated whenever she isn't driving, for example.) When Isabella catches him on top, so to speak, with another woman, she runs off to San Francisco, suffering on the plane ride, and moves in with her old friend, the wise drag queen Monica (Harold Perrineau Jr.).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The soothing lilt of bossa nova floats over the malnourished but sometimes entrancing romantic comedy ''Woman on Top,'' which starts in Bahia, where the delectable Penelope Cruz plays Isabella, a chef. Isabella cooks magnificent meals, and epicures from around the globe fall in love with her culinary talents. In the dining room of the restaurant her husband, Toninho (Murilo Benicio), the restaurant's owner, flirts with female customers and fronts a band whose tempos dance above the diners' heads like aromas from the kitchen.</p>
        <p>Eventually we learn that Toninho's life has not been all congas and sambas. He has had literally to labor under Isabella, whose lifelong and pronounced motion sickness means she has to be in control of everything. (She gets nauseated whenever she isn't driving, for example.) When Isabella catches him on top, so to speak, with another woman, she runs off to San Francisco, suffering on the plane ride, and moves in with her old friend, the wise drag queen Monica (Harold Perrineau Jr.).</p>
        <p>Isabella becomes the toast of the city as host of a nightly television cooking show, ''Passion Food.'' This happens because she has made an offering to Yemanja, goddess of the sea, to free her from her broken heart over Toninho. Apparently Yemanja's spell works too well because not only does Isabella feel better the next day, but now every man she sees falls in love with her. Using otherworldy conjuring to make Ms. Cruz more attractive to men is as redundant as a spell to give the lethal boxer Roy Jones Jr. a third fist.</p>
        <p>One wishes ''Woman'' had more fun with the food-as-sex metaphors it toys with, but the director Fina Torres -- whose previous ''Celestial Clockwork'' was also about legerdemain, appetites and a Latina heroine experiencing dislocation -- has a spirited light touch. The banter at the television station is quite funny, and not as soft-headed as the rest of the film.</p>
        <p>Isabella loves to use peppers -- she gets lost in a reverie talking about the different types -- but this  would-be spicy film has been made blandly palatable.</p>
        <p>When Isabella becomes more glamorous, Ms. Cruz's makeup is heavier, and the delicacy of her features is lost. When a photographer says, ''I'm gonna need a big Julia Roberts smile from you,'' it's redundant because Isabella has already been smoothed out to look like she's about to star in ''The Pelican Brief.'' Ms. Cruz is rescued from her earlier mopey frowning and tears faster than Sally Field. Like Ms. Roberts, she has an incandescent smile, which she gets to uncork here.</p>
        <p>The movie doesn't stoop to calling Monica a godmother, though he essentially functions in that way, serving as both narrator and adviser to not only Isabella but also Toninho and Cliff (Mark Feuerstein), the television producer who talks Isabella into doing her show and falls for her as well. Toninho follows Isabella to San Francisco in an attempt to win her back, and he sings his way through the high and twisty streets.</p>
        <p>The storybook appeal of Brazil is a big part of ''Woman on Top.'' ''Brazil is a mood, a state of mind,'' Monica tells Cliff, trying to impart the land's secrets so he can court Isabella. But despite its adorable star and likability, this is a fable with little flavor. The best thing you can say about the movie is that it's real vanilla bean instead of ersatz vanilla.</p>
        <p>''Woman on Top'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes strong language, sexual innuendo and brief nudity.</p>
        <p>WOMAN ON TOP  Directed by Fina Torres; written by Vera Blasi; director of photography, Thierry Arbogast; edited by Leslie Jones; music by Luis Bacalov; production designer, Philippe Chiffre; produced by Alan Poul; released by Fox Searchlight Pictures. Running time: 85 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Penelope Cruz (Isabella Oliveira), Murilo Benicio (Toninho Oliveira), Harold Perrineau Jr. (Monica Jones) and Mark Feurerstein (Cliff Lloyd).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
