<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Atlanta Mayor Denounces F.B.I. Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="Y22ATL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/national/22ATLA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Campbell, Bill (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EFDF1E3BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Atlanta Mayor Denounces F.B.I. Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Simmering Federal investigation into possible corruption in Atlanta local government contracts becomes racial issue this week when Mayor Bill Campbell denounces federal law enforcement authorities as 'forces of evil' for looking into his private life (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A simmering federal investigation into possible corruption in local government contracts became a racial issue this week when Mayor Bill Campbell of Atlanta denounced federal law enforcement authorities as ''forces of evil'' for looking into his private life.</p>
        <p>For months, Federal Bureau of Investigation agents and other federal authorities have been looking at city and county records and questioning government contractors. This year, two county officials pleaded guilty to receiving bribes. A friend of the mayor was also indicted on tax fraud charges, but until the last few days, it was unclear how closely Mr. Campbell was being investigated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A simmering federal investigation into possible corruption in local government contracts became a racial issue this week when Mayor Bill Campbell of Atlanta denounced federal law enforcement authorities as ''forces of evil'' for looking into his private life.</p>
        <p>For months, Federal Bureau of Investigation agents and other federal authorities have been looking at city and county records and questioning government contractors. This year, two county officials pleaded guilty to receiving bribes. A friend of the mayor was also indicted on tax fraud charges, but until the last few days, it was unclear how closely Mr. Campbell was being investigated.</p>
        <p>Beginning on Tuesday, in statements to reporters and on black radio stations, Mr. Campbell, who is black, accused the F.B.I. of conducting a racially motivated ''inquisition'' into his personal and official conduct, questioning his friends, examining his gambling trips and leaking information to Atlanta reporters.</p>
        <p>''The F.B.I. has never been a friend of the African-American community, and they're not a friend now,'' Mr. Campbell said on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>''Why is this happening?'' he asked at a news conference on Tuesday. ''Perhaps there is a political motivation? Perhaps there are ideological differences regarding my aggressive stand on affirmative action.''</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the F.B.I. and for Richard H. Deane Jr., the United States attorney for the Northern District of Georgia, would not respond to the criticism and would not confirm that an investigation of the mayor's office was under way. But in June, Mr. Deane's office subpoenaed documents regarding several minority contractors with links to the mayor, and one of Mr. Campbell's close friends, Fred Prewitt, chairman of the Civil Service Review Board,  was indicted in July on federal tax fraud charges.</p>
        <p>Last week, WSB-TV reported that federal investigators were looking into a trip taken by Mr. Campbell to a casino in Tunica, Miss., last year, examining whether he was accompanied by any city contractors. The mayor's office confirmed that he had made the trip along with Willie Herenton, the mayor of Memphis, and Mr. Campbell said on Tuesday that he had no reason to apologize for taking casino gambling trips.</p>
        <p>The investigation apparently grew out of a corruption case that federal authorities had pursued in Fulton County, which includes most of Atlanta. Earlier this year, a county commissioner and a high-ranking county staff member pleaded guilty to accepting bribes from a local businessman. In expanding the inquiry, Mr. Campbell said at the news conference, the government began looking into whether he took bribes from the owner of a strip club seeking a liquor license. The club employed a friend of the mayor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Campbell said that when the F.B.I. could find no evidence of bribes, it began looking into other city departments.</p>
        <p>''My friends, this is not an investigation, but an inquisition,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The mayor, now in the third year of his second four-year term, has become known for discerning racial bias in many of his critics. But the nature of the racial bias in this case is unclear, because both Mr. Deane and Theodore Jackson, the special agent in charge of the F.B.I.'s Atlanta office, are black. The Clinton administration, which would probably have approved any investigation into high-ranking officials, supports affirmative action. Mr. Campbell did not respond to requests for an interview, but several prominent blacks in Atlanta supported the mayor at a news conference today.</p>
        <p>''J. Edgar Hoover may be gone, but there's still a Hoover mentality among the career employees of the F.B.I.,'' said Tyrone Brooks, a state representative from Atlanta. ''Why else would they be leaking information about the mayor without showing any evidence? They're just trying to destroy his reputation.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
