<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</title>
    <meta content="22KIDS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D7103BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES: FOR CHILDREN</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF MAYA THE BEE,'' told through rod and shadow puppets and a jazz score, is about a little bee who rejects toiling in the hive and flies off to pursue tastes more exotic than honey. Saturdays at 11 a.m. at the Salon Theater, 45 Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village.Tickets: $15; $7 for children. Reservations: (212) 539-6644.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF MAYA THE BEE,'' told through rod and shadow puppets and a jazz score, is about a little bee who rejects toiling in the hive and flies off to pursue tastes more exotic than honey. Saturdays at 11 a.m. at the Salon Theater, 45 Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village.Tickets: $15; $7 for children. Reservations: (212) 539-6644.</p>
        <p>''BLOOMER GIRL,'' the Cotton Blossom Musicals' revival of the 1944 musical set during the Civil War about an early feminist who rebels against uncomfortable hoopskirts. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and Sunday at 3 p.m. at the Theater at St. Clement's, 423 West 46th Street, Clinton. Tickets: $25; $15 for the elderly; $10 for students. Reservations: (212) 246-7277, extension 32.</p>
        <p>''HANSEL AND GRETEL,'' presented for the marionette stage by Puppetworks and Nicolas Coppola, artistic director, Saturdays and Sundays at 12:30 and 2:30 p.m. (through Dec. 17) at Puppetworks-Park Slope, 338 Sixth Avenue, at Fourth Street, Brooklyn. For children 4 and older. Tickets: $7; $6 for children; $4.50 for groups of 20 or more. Reservations required. Information: (718) 965-3391.</p>
        <p>''THE HENSON INTERNATIONAL FESTIVAL OF PUPPET THEATER,'' through Sunday. Batoto Yetu, a Harlem-based children's  troupe, in a program featuring drumming and dancing called ''The Mukishi,'' at the New Victory Theater, 330 West 42nd Street, tonight at 7; tomorrow at 2 and 7 p.m.; Sunday at noon and 5 p.m. Tickets: $17 and $20. ''Simple Gifts,'' for ages 8 and older, consists of individual vignettes by hauntingly lifelike figures, by the Cashore Marionettes, from Conshohocken, Pa., at the Joseph Papp Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village, tomorrow and Sunday at 11 a.m. and 1 p.m. Tickets: $12 and $15. Also at the Public Theater, for ages 7 and older, tonight at 7; tomorrow at noon and 5 p.m.; Sunday at noon and 2 p.m., ''The Girl Who Waters Basil and the Nosy Prince,'' a Garcia Lorca tale performed by the Cuban actor Ruben Dario Salazar and presented by the Cuban Teatro de las Estaciones.. The final performance on Sunday will be in Spanish. Tickets: $15 and $20. Information: New Victory Theater, (212) 564-4222; Joseph Papp Public Theater, (212) 260-2400.</p>
        <p>''JACK AND THE BEANSTALK,'' the Swedish Cottage Marionette Theater presents an updated version of the classic fairy tale with music, puppetry and comedy, tomorrow and Sunday at 1 p.m. at the Swedish Cottage Marionette Theater, Central Park, West Drive at 79th Street, enter at 81st Street and Central Park West or 79th Street and Fifth Avenue. Admission: $5; $4 for children. Reservations required: (212) 988-9093.</p>
        <p>PAPAGENO PUPPET THEATER presents two productions with Susan Delery Whedon, a puppeteer and singer: ''Hansel and Gretel,'' the fairy tale, with music by Humperdinck (at 11:30 a.m.) and ''Puff the Magic Dragon,'' with music by Peter, Paul and Mary (2:30 p.m.). Saturdays and Sundays through Oct. 29 at 462 Columbus Avenue, near 82nd Street. Tickets: $6. Reservations: (212) 874-3297.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>''AN AFTERNOON WITH ARTHUR.'' ''Arthur,'' the children's PBS television series based on the children's books of the same name about an animated aardvark with horn-rimmed glasses, will be the subject of a reading, booksigning and discussion, tomorrow from 1 to 2 p.m. at the Museum of Television and Radio, 25 West 52nd Street, Manhattan, with Marc Brown, creator of ''Arthur,'' who will read from his new book, ''Arthur's Teacher Moves In.'' There will also be a screening of ''Arthur's Chickenpox,'' an episode from the series. For children 5 and older and their families. Free with museum admission: $6; students and the elderly, $4; ages 13 and under, $3. Information: (212) 621-6800.</p>
        <p>''BUILDING BLOCKS.'' ''Renewing a Block and the Spirit of Its People,'' a detailed, scale model of 118th Street between Fifth and Lenox Avenues, designed by the architect Pamela Hersch, was created with a group of children in that Carmel Hill neighborhood. Sunday at 2 p.m. at the Museum of the City of New York, Fifth Avenue at 103rd Street, the architect will take youngsters 6 and older on an insider's tour of the model. Free. Suggested admission to the museum (not required for the workshop): $7; the elderly, students and children, $4; families, $12. Registration required. Information: (212) 534-1672, extension 257.</p>
        <p>DONNELL LIBRARY CENTER, Central Children's Room, 20 West 53rd Street, Manhattan. ''Stories of Courage,'' storytelling with Diane Wolkstein, author of ''The Magic Orange Tree,'' tomorrow at 3 p.m. For ages 6 and older. ''Stories for Joining In,'' for children 5 to 12, with the storyteller John Colligan, Sunday at 3 p.m. Free. Information: (212) 621-0618 or (212) 621-0636.</p>
        <p>''MOBILE MADNESS,'' a workshop tomorrow and Sunday from noon to 4 p.m. at the Staten Island Children's Museum, Snug Harbor Cultural Center, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Livingston, where youngsters will make artworks in motion out of clay, strings, pieces of wood and paint. For all ages. $2 plus museum admission: $4; under 2 and members, free. Information: (718) 273-2060.</p>
        <p>''MEET THE ILLUSTRATOR: STEPHEN KRONINGER.'' The illustrator and collage artist will share his picture book, ''Tie Your Socks and Clap Your Feet,'' (featuring poems by Lenny Hort) with youngsters tomorrow at 4 p.m. in the fifth-floor American paintings galleries, Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park. Free with museum admission: $4; students and the elderly, $2; under 12, free. Information: (718) 638-5000.</p>
        <p>''INTRODUCING MAGIC WITH ACE GREENBERG.'' Magic tricks by the magician and financial wizard -- he is chief executive of Bear Stearns -- Sunday from 9:30 to 11 a.m. at the Kaye Playhouse at Hunter College, 695 Park Avenue at 68th Street. Tickets: $25; $10 for children. Information: (212) 580-0099.</p>
        <p>''MATSURI ON 47TH STREET,'' a free Japanese street festival, including taiko drumming, traditional and folk dancing, martial arts demonstrations, storytelling, games, woodblock printmaking demonstrations and Japanese foods like yakisoba (stir-fried noodles) and mochi (rice cakes), Sunday from noon to 4 p.m., outside the Japan Society, 47th Street between First and Second Avenues, Manhattan. Information: (212) 832-1155.</p>
        <p>QUEENS COUNTY FAIR. An annual event with competitions in livestock, produce, home crafts and arts and crafts. Activities include logrolling, ax-throwing demonstrations, pie-eating contests and carnival rides and games. Children can also go on hayrides, play carnival games and visit the petting zoo, tomorrow and Sunday from 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. at the Queens County Farm Museum, 73-50 Little Neck Parkway, Floral Park, Queens. Admission: $4; children 12 and under, $2. Free parking. Information: (718) 347-3276.</p>
        <p>''SUNDAY SCIENCE SPECTACULAR! NORTH BY NORTHWEST -- ORIENTEERING.'' The 92nd Street Y, at Lexington Avenue, will present science programs one Sunday each month. This weekend, from 10 a.m. to noon, the subject is orienteering. Using map and compass, youngsters will discover the route to a designated spot in the Conservatory Gardens of Central Park. Tickets: $35 for one adult and one child; $10 each additional person (includes transportation). Information: (212) 996-1100.</p>
        <p>UNION SQUARE COMMUNITY CHILDREN'S CARNIVAL, Sunday from 1 to 5 p.m. at the 17th Street end of Union Square Park. Activities include firemen demonstrating fire-fighting equipment and a fire engine children can roam on, a balloon magician, along with a clown and stilt-walker, a magic house children can play on (at 3 p.m.) and pony riding (at 4 p.m.). Free.</p>
        <p>Exhibitions</p>
        <p>''FROM TENT TO TEMPLE: LIFE IN THE ANCIENT NEAR EAST,'' an interactive exhibition (through Jan. 14) developed by the Jewish Children's Learning Lab, Center for Jewish History, Yeshiva University Museum, 15 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 294-8330, showing the daily lives of people in Biblical times, featuring 28 interactive learning stations. In more than 30 displays, the exhibition challenges children to solve problems the way their biblical ancestors did, building a miniature plow, grinding grain with stones constructing a hearth or even hunting game -- images of it, that is -- with bows and arrows ending in suction cups. Sunday at 2 p.m., the museum will be the site of a storytelling and metal engraving workshop, where youngsters 7 to 12 can create embossed siddur (prayerbook) covers. Youngsters should bring their siddur or another book they treasure. Free with admission. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Free with admission: $6; the elderly and ages 5 to 12, $4; under 5 and members, free.</p>
        <p>''WILLIAM WEGMAN: CANES ECCLESIORUM,'' (canes is Latin for church dogs), is an exhibiton of the photographer's famous pooches doing amazing humanlike things, created especially for the Cathedral of St. John the Divine, 112th Street and Amsterdam Avenue, Morningside Heights, through Oct. 22. Free. Information: (212) 316-7540.</p>
        <p>Zoos</p>
        <p>CAREERS WITH ANIMALS. Youngsters will discover the range of jobs available at the zoo, including zookeeper, microbiologist and mechanic, Sunday at 2 p.m. at the Staten Island Zoo, 614 Broadway, off Forest Avenue, West Brighton. Preregistration required. Free with admission: $3; children 3 to 11, $2; under 3, free. Free parking. Information: (718) 442-3174 or (718) 442-3101.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
