<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the 7 Train, Living the Multicultural Ideal</title>
    <meta content="22FLUS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Travel; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Flushing (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Queens Council on the Arts (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brawarsky, Sandee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E2DF113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3237" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the 7 Train, Living the Multicultural Ideal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDEE BRAWARSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brawarsky, Sandee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on festival International Expressions, celebrating the many immigrant cultures co-existing in Queens neighborhoods along Flushing subway line in New York City; photos; map; event sponsored by Queens Council on the Arts marks designation of Number 7 line as National Millennium Trail; list of restaurants and night spots along the way (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fringe on Willa Bronce's red silk shawl follows her lead as she twirls, stamps her feet and raises her arms to the flamenco rhythms of Reynaldo Rincon's guitar. ''I asked the wind if he had seen you,'' Mr. Rincon sings intensely in Spanish, ''and I asked myself if you still loved me.'' She replies with vigorous but graceful movements, and her passion fills the dining room and bar of Meson Asturias in Elmhurst, Queens. With artistry, the Romanian-Irish New Yorker dances on a stage narrower than the platform of the nearby No. 7 train.</p>
        <p>Meson Asturias and many other places with live entertainment along the nine-mile route of the dark red train -- known as the International Express -- are less than a half-hour ride from Grand Central Terminal. This weekend, in honor of the designation of the IRT's No. 7 line as a National Millennium Trail by the White House, the Queens Council on the Arts is presenting ''International Expressions,'' a celebration of the continuing cultural festival underneath the elevated tracks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The fringe on Willa Bronce's red silk shawl follows her lead as she twirls, stamps her feet and raises her arms to the flamenco rhythms of Reynaldo Rincon's guitar. ''I asked the wind if he had seen you,'' Mr. Rincon sings intensely in Spanish, ''and I asked myself if you still loved me.'' She replies with vigorous but graceful movements, and her passion fills the dining room and bar of Meson Asturias in Elmhurst, Queens. With artistry, the Romanian-Irish New Yorker dances on a stage narrower than the platform of the nearby No. 7 train.</p>
        <p>Meson Asturias and many other places with live entertainment along the nine-mile route of the dark red train -- known as the International Express -- are less than a half-hour ride from Grand Central Terminal. This weekend, in honor of the designation of the IRT's No. 7 line as a National Millennium Trail by the White House, the Queens Council on the Arts is presenting ''International Expressions,'' a celebration of the continuing cultural festival underneath the elevated tracks.</p>
        <p>There are free music and dance programs, and many ethnic restaurants and shops are offering special promotions. Visitors can hear Irish fiddle music or watch Indian dance, flamenco or a game of boccie as they nosh their way from Sunnyside to Flushing.</p>
        <p>All this is happening not far from the site of the 1939 and 1964 World's Fairs, now Flushing Meadows-Corona Park. Exploring the neighborhoods along the No. 7 line, I get on and off the train as though it were a monorail. Along Queens Boulevard, the tracks rest on a concrete trestle whose arches form an arcade dividing the traffic lanes. When the line veers onto Roosevelt Avenue, the concrete is abruptly replaced by steel, and the train roars directly above traffic, interrupting sidewalk conversations for about 25 seconds at irregular intervals.</p>
        <p>It's not that these neighborhoods have beautiful tree-lined streets -- although some do -- or that the architecture is particularly significant. Rather, it is the signs, window displays, performances, restaurants, street foods, faces and, when they are revealed, newcomers' stories that make for engaging visits. This is the Lower East Side of my immigrant grandparents, updated, magnified, translated into Hindi, Cantonese, Italian, Thai, Spanish, Korean and many other languages. On these streets the perpetual struggle between clinging to the old country and embracing the new is often visible. In a Mexican party store, the best-selling pinata is a Pokemon.</p>
        <p>Among the few constants, block after block, are children on scooters; second-story offices that house legal, immigration and divorce services; storefronts for making international phone calls; and occasional pocket parks formed by intersecting angular streets. In the nightclubs and restaurants, much of the music has a shared theme: love, home, fear of forgetting. I never knew that I liked Romanian music until I went to Casa Romana in Sunnyside. Camelia Danciu's voice is so full of longing that, even with language skills limited to the items translated on the menu, I understand her sense of nostalgia. She strolls about the dining room as she sings, accompanied by a violin and a keyboard. Fans present flowers.</p>
        <p>Nearby, at Transylvania, 43-46 42nd Street, a Romanian group called Amor plays a mix of Romanian and international songs. With a large portrait of Count Dracula looking out over the dance floor, couples do Romanian versions of the fox trot. A group joins in belly dancing, which then turns into a circular folk dance that not only resembles a hora but has the same name as well. Leading it all is the patriarch of a multigenerational family who strikingly resembles Uncle Tonoose on ''The Danny Thomas Show.''</p>
        <p>On the dance floor of Chibcha, a Colombian nightclub in Jackson Heights with live entertainment most nights, I recognize Bonny King as the guy who dances with a doll attached in the subways. Here he has a live partner, and they are masters of cumbia, salsa and merengue. Well after midnight on a Wednesday, the dance floor rises to become a large stage, and a Cuban-Chinese comedian does shtick in Spanish, followed by ''El Charro de Colombia,'' a male vocalist with a throbbing voice singing mostly about love. And at La Fama, 80-04 Roosevelt Avenue, also in Jackson Heights, an Ecuadorean pop singer thrills the weekend crowd of mostly young people from Ecuador, Peru, Mexico and Colombia, along with a few native New Yorkers trying to catch up with the beat.</p>
        <p>There is also amazing body movement down Roosevelt Avenue and up one flight at Champions Table Tennis Center, 78-14 Roosevelt. Opponents play ruggedly, anticipating the ball several feet from the table's edge; their game bears little resemblance to casual Ping-Pong. Players are the usual Queens mix: from China, Korea, Latin America, Nigeria, the Bronx and Flushing. Lily Yip, a national champion who has played on the United States Olympic team, visits occasionally and wins regularly. The owner, Min Shili, who keeps the place open every day and gives lessons, is a former member of the Chinese national team who has coached the United States national team. Nobody seems to hear the occasional rumble of the train.</p>
        <p>Repeatedly, in conversations with Queens residents, someone brings up the word multicultural or alludes to the melting pot. Usually it's done with a knowing smile or a roll of the eyes, as if to say that what others theorize about is daily Queens reality. That an Indian woman buys Mexican tortillas in a Korean grocery store in a Turkish-Romanian-Irish neighborhood isn't unusual.</p>
        <p>When I ask Shane Moynagh how he learned to bake the triangular hamentashen -- displayed along with the brown bread and cranberry, blueberry and whole wheat scones in the Woodside bakery he owns called Shane's, at 39-61 61st Street -- he replies that the credit goes to a baker named Mohammed who began working in this place when it was still Walter's, a German-Jewish bakery. So a Pakistani baker makes Jewish pastries in an Irish bakery. And in Jackson Heights, a Colombian bakery, Aqui Colombia Antojitos (81-08 37th Avenue), sells challah three ways: plain, raisin and with cheese and guava.</p>
        <p>For Ilana Harlow, folk arts program director at the Queens Council on the Arts, who has been documenting traditional life along the No. 7 line since 1994 and is responsible for nominating it as a National Millennium Trail, the mixing of traditions is natural.</p>
        <p>''The history of the world is that when people are exposed to different cultures, they adopt and adapt as their own whatever appeals to them,'' she said. ''Here, the process happens more intensely.'' One of her favorite examples is a sign in an Indian restaurant on Thanksgiving advertising tandoori turkey. (A useful guide to the various neighborhoods is a booklet written by Ms. Harlow and published by the council, ''The International Express.'')</p>
        <p>''Food,'' Ms. Harlow said, ''is a very accessible first step into a culture.'' This stretch of Queens seems to be an outpost of the $1 snack, whether avena, a sweet oatmeal drink from the Andes; paan, a betel leaf layered with lime paste, rose petals, betel nuts, cloves and other spices and folded into a bite-size packet to be chewed slowly; suman malagkit, Filipino banana leaves stuffed with sweet rice; or a bag of 20 Chinese treats called flavorous cakes, gi-dan-kao, a lemony cross between madeleines and tiny pancakes.</p>
        <p>At the Lemon Ice King of Corona (52-02 108th Street), a small cup of peanut butter ice -- the store's second most popular flavor -- costs 75 cents. The shop faces William E. Moore Park, known by locals as Spaghetti Park, where boccie is played almost every day on a court illuminated by a string of tiny paper lanterns in the colors of Italy. Every Labor Day there's a tournament, and afterward the court is covered with boards to become a dance floor. To the sounds of a live band, couples, fathers and daughters, and pairs of women do the tarantella, waltz and hustle, cheered on by the crowd.</p>
        <p>For many immigrants and their children, the neighborhood quickly becomes the old neighborhood, as people move away, returning to shop and visit friends. Most of the merchants along 74th Street in Jackson Heights between Roosevelt and 37th Avenues, an area known as Little India, do not live in the immediate neighborhood. Nor do many of their clients. But the sidewalks are crowded with people in colorful traditional dress, some carrying 20-pound bags of rice or the latest soundtracks of films made in Bombay (or Bollywood), which are often shown at the Eagle Movie Theater, 73-07 37th Road. Little India is a solid block of South Asian restaurants and sweet shops, a Zabar's-like food emporium called Patel Brothers (37-27 74th Street), custom- and ready-made sari shops, music and gift shops, jewelers specializing in 22-karat gold and beauty salons that adorn women's hands and feet with henna designs in a process called mehendi. Here, many food shops announce that they offer ''Indo-Pak-Bangla'' foods; these cultures coexist peaceably in New York, if not at home.</p>
        <p>Much smaller than Little India is the Filipino neighborhood concentrated on two blocks near the 69th Street station in Woodside, with Phil-Am Foodmart (70-02 Roosevelt Avenue) -- which sells purple yam-flavored ice cream -- and a strip of restaurants, cafes and music clubs. The Indonesian community seems to have a center at Warteg Fortuna, which means tiny place, at the foot of a stairway leading to the 52nd Street Station at 51-24 Roosevelt Avenue. Most customers take the Sumatran-spiced food home, but Indonesians often linger at the shop's eight-seat counter. Adjacent is Nunziato, a florist, run by the daughters and grandsons of the Italian immigrant who founded the business -- next to his farm -- in 1910.</p>
        <p>Many shops and restaurants are team efforts. La Fama and its sister restaurant are run by three brothers from Ecuador; a fourth did the carpentry work. Hemsin, an inviting bakery and restaurant in Sunnyside at 39-11 Queens Boulevard, is run by a group of cousins and friends and is named for the Turkish village they come from. Their talk is filled with optimism; their hard work is their passport to success.</p>
        <p>But Queens is no Disneyland of world nationalities. For many newcomers, there is no welcoming committee, and finding work, learning the language and navigating the system can be difficult. In restaurants and bars, it is not uncommon to see men sitting alone. A Jackson Heights music studio has among its guitar students several Latin American men who have left their families behind and ease their loneliness by playing music in their rooms.</p>
        <p>Some turn to religion and spirits for solace. St. Sebastian's, the 106-year-old church in the old Loews Woodside Theater at 58th Street and Roosevelt Avenue, has a large banner outside proclaiming ''Yesterday, Today, Forever'' in English, Spanish, Korean and Tagalog.</p>
        <p>Longevity is also a motto across the street at Donovan's, a 35-year-old pub at 57-24 Roosevelt Avenue, with customers who have been coming since the place opened, many right after church. Lorna Iovine, 30, who was born in Limerick, bridges the two worlds, ever cheerfully: she teaches second grade at St. Sebastian's and works weekends as a waitress at Donovan's.</p>
        <p>''It's great,'' she said. ''I get to know both sides of the community -- people at school and people hanging out here.'' In a place like Woodside, which she heard of back in Ireland, ''you meet people from so many different places; you educate yourself about what's really important and learn to be more open.'' When not working, she is often relaxing at Donovan's with her husband, Frank, a New York police detective. She wears a miniature gold reproduction of his badge around her neck.</p>
        <p>Yoon Sook Park, a dancer and musician, is working hard to teach the generation born here about Korea's cultural traditions, as she explains through an interpreter. With her daughter Yu-Sun Kwang, also known as Grace, she runs the Korean Traditional Music Institute at 137-45 Northern Boulevard. Changing from jeans to long, flowing skirts, the students begin a series of dances, some more than 2,500 years old. They whirl around colorful fans, then dance with various Korean drums, making grand gestures and creating complex sounds. The more advanced groups do public performances. Ms. Park has taught students ages 4 through 70. Until recently she had an African-American student who traveled from Manhattan; that student is now at Harvard.</p>
        <p>When I ask a group of young girls after class what they thought of the lessons, they answer, as though scripted, that learning about Korean culture is interesting and fun. But when I ask whether their grandmothers know the dances, they giggle uncontrollably. I'm puzzled until I remember that if anyone had asked me as a child whether my Yiddish-speaking grandmother did traditional dancing, I would have giggled, too. But most of these girls don't know their grandmothers, who are in Korea.</p>
        <p>I think of my grandmother again on Flushing's Main Street as I pass the Corsetorium, her kind of store. Benjamin Singer, the owner, says that the shop, opened by his parents in 1920 at 36-35 Main Street, is the oldest business on the street. He has shifted his merchandise to meet changing shopping habits -- ''No one buys half-slips anymore'' -- and now sells lacy lingerie along with the structured undergarments my grandmother favored. Most of his competition has gone out of business, and he imagines that in two or three years his store will close, too.</p>
        <p>Still walking, I pause at the recently rebuilt Flushing branch of the Queens Borough Public Library, the busiest branch in New York State. Inside, tables are crowded with people reading and researching; a young girl is copying poetry. On the steps outside, the names of books and characters representing the many different ethnic groups in Queens are carved into the stone, including ''Gulliver's Travels,'' ''The Odyssey,'' ''Juan Bobo'' (Mexican), Tevye the Dairyman, ''Ghalib's Ghazals'' (Urdu) and Pinocchio. They are all books of searching, of journeys taken. These are the stories of the No. 7 train, now part of the great narrative of the immigrant experience in New York City, and America.</p>
        <p>Returning to Manhattan on the train, I'm lucky to hit the right time of day, when the setting sun bounces off the tracks and casts a glow, a reminder that the No. 7 train is not only the spine of Queens but its soul.</p>
        <p>A World Tour</p>
        <p>''International Expressions,'' a National Millennium Trail celebration, will take place all along the No. 7 line in Queens tomorrow and Sunday. (All events on Sunday are free.) Many restaurants and shops near the train are offering discounts to festival participants, who must say the password, ''International Expressions.'' MetroCard Fun Passes will allow festivalgoers to get on and off the train as often as they like, all day, for $4. For a complete schedule and a list of discounts at restaurants and shops, call the Queens Council on the Arts at (718) 647-3377, or visit the council's Web site (www.queenscouncilarts.org). The booklet ''The International Express: A Guide to the Ethnic Communities Along the No. 7 Train'' can be ordered for $1 from the arts council. A sampling of festival events:</p>
        <p>Tomorrow</p>
        <p>CASA ROMANA, Romanian nightclub and restaurant, 39-20 Queens Boulevard, 40th Street Station, Sunnyside, (718) 784-4768. Romanian music, belly dancing and magician; 7:30 p.m., reservations necessary.</p>
        <p>CHIBCHA, Latino nightclub and restaurant, 79-05 Roosevelt Avenue, 74th Street or 82nd Street stations, Jackson Heights, (718) 429-9033; live music begins at 12:30 a.m.; $5 off admission with password. On Sunday, Colombian vallenato music will be performed by Los Macondos, 4 p.m., free; 10 percent off food with password.</p>
        <p>CORK LOUNGE, Irish bar and restaurant, 33-01 Greenpoint Avenue, 33rd Street Station, Sunnyside, (718) 784-9500. Emerald Ceili (Irish dance party), $12 including refreshments; 8 p.m.</p>
        <p>KOREAN HARVEST AND FOLKLORE FESTIVAL. Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Willets Point-Shea Stadium Station. Korean religious ceremony, music, dance and food, sponsored by Korean Produce Association, tomorrow and Sunday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.; (718) 760-6562 (City of New York Parks and Recreation).</p>
        <p>MESON ASTURIAS, Spanish restaurant, 40-12 83rd Street, 82nd Street Station, Elmhurst, (718) 446-9154. Tomorrow, dining to flamenco and Spanish classical guitar music with Romeria Flamenca, starring Willa Bronce and Reynaldo Rincon; shows at 8:30 and 11 p.m.; Sunday, free shows at 1 and 3 p.m.; 25 percent off lunch or dinner (except lunch special) with password.</p>
        <p>Sunday</p>
        <p>THE BREFFNI, Irish bar and restaurant, 43-45 40th Street, 40th Street Station, Sunnyside, (718) 729-9803. Irish music concert with Andy McGann and Brian Conway, fiddle champions, and Felix Dolan, pianist, 5:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>HARMONY DAY, sponsored by Assemblyman Ivan C. Lafayette, Junction Boulevard between 37th and Roosevelt Avenues, Junction Boulevard Station, Jackson Heights. Multicultural arts festival. Nritya Kala Kendra presents an Indian dance performance, 12:30 p.m.; Chinese Theater Workshop presents a Peking opera, 1:45 p.m.; children's activities from noon to 6. For full schedule call (718) 458-3600 (Jackson Heights Development Corporation).</p>
        <p>INDIAN MUSIC AND DANCE, Flushing Branch of the Queens Borough Public Library, 41-17 Main Street, Main Street Station, Flushing (718) 661-1200. Classical and folk traditions performed by the Shikshayatan Cultural Center, 1:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>''MARY LOU WILLIAMS: IN HER OWN RIGHT,'' Flushing Town Hall, 137-35 Northern Boulevard, Main Street Station, Flushing, (718) 463-7700. Symposium on the jazz composer and pianist Mary Lou Williams, with Dan Morgenstern, Billy Taylor, Linda Dahl and Marc Miller, 2 p.m.</p>
        <p>NANCY'S GRILL, Argentine restaurant, 49-07 43rd Avenue, 52nd Street Station, Sunnyside, (718) 651-6802. Argentine dance with members of Ballet Los Pampas. Learn how to dance a traditional Argentine gato, 2:30 p.m.; performance of tango, danzas (folk dances), milonga and malambo, 3:15 p.m.</p>
        <p>TRAIN TRIBUTE, Renaissance Charter School, 35-59 81st Street, 82nd Street Station, Jackson Heights, (718) 426-8555. ''Queens Millennium Trail,'' a student play about the No. 7 train, 1 p.m.; coffeehouse sponsored with the Pinewoods Folk Music Club, 2 to 4 p.m.; bring songs about trains.</p>
        <p>VIDEO SCREENING, ''The International Express: Communities Along the IRT 7 Train,'' Flushing Branch of the Queens Borough Public Library, 41-17 Main Street, Main Street Station, Flushing, (718) 661-1200. A look at South Asian fashion, Mexican food, Italian recreation and Korean art in Jackson Heights, Corona and Flushing. Screenings, 12:30 and 4 p.m. There is also a photo exhibit, ''Festivals of Chinese Western Provinces.'' Library open noon to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>THE WALL, Irish bar, 54-20 Roosevelt Avenue, 52nd Street Station, Woodside, (718) 429-9426. Irish music session, 7 p.m.</p>
        <p>Places to Visit</p>
        <p>HINDU TEMPLE SOCIETY OF NORTH AMERICA, 45-37 Bowne Street, Main Street Station, Flushing, (718) 460-8484. This building, adorned with carvings of Hindu gods, was mostly created in India and reassembled here in the 1970's. Remove shoes before entering. No photography allowed inside the temple. Open daily 8 a.m. to 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM E. MOORE PARK, 108th Street and 51st Avenue, 111th Street Station, Corona. In good weather, the game of boccie is played beginning around 6 or 7 p.m. Across the street, the Lemon Ice King of Corona is offering a 10 percent discount with the password.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
