<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bill Gates's Senator Confronts Upstart Internet Challenger</title>
    <meta content="22SENA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/22/technology/22SENA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1232679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: IN WASHINGTON STATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (State)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gorton, Slade (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cantwell, Maria</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED7113BF931A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1475" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bill Gates's Senator Confronts Upstart Internet Challenger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Review of US Senate race in Washington, where Republican incumbent Sen Slade Gorton finds himself in fierce race against Democrat Maria Cantwell, Internet exec who is more than 30 years his junior; Cantwell is a top exec at RealNetworks, Seattle company that pioneered audio and visual technology on Internet and that in just a few years helped her accumulate personal fortune her campaign estimates at $40 million; several statewide polls show her close to--or in one, dead even with--Gorton; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just as Henry M. Jackson was once known as the Senator from Boeing, Washington State's Slade Gorton is delighted to call himself the Senator from Microsoft, a man whose pit-bull advocacy for the software giant in the nation's capital has earned him the corporation's gratitude and campaign contributions from William H. Gates and other company officials.</p>
        <p>But as he runs for a fourth Senate term this fall, Mr. Gorton finds himself in a fierce race against a Democratic opponent, more than 30 years his junior, who has even closer ties to another large software company in the Northwest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just as Henry M. Jackson was once known as the Senator from Boeing, Washington State's Slade Gorton is delighted to call himself the Senator from Microsoft, a man whose pit-bull advocacy for the software giant in the nation's capital has earned him the corporation's gratitude and campaign contributions from William H. Gates and other company officials.</p>
        <p>But as he runs for a fourth Senate term this fall, Mr. Gorton finds himself in a fierce race against a Democratic opponent, more than 30 years his junior, who has even closer ties to another large software company in the Northwest.</p>
        <p>She is Maria Cantwell, a top executive at RealNetworks, a Seattle company that pioneered audio and visual technology on the Internet and that in just a few years helped her accumulate a personal fortune her campaign estimates at $40 million. Ms. Cantwell, a 41-year-old former congresswoman, vows to spend ''whatever it takes'' to unseat Mr. Gorton.</p>
        <p>That RealNetworks and Microsoft happen to be rivals has only added spice to the Senate race here, and Ms. Cantwell herself is a highly noteworthy candidate in several respects. While other high-tech millionaires have run for the Senate, she is the first from the Internet industry. And, as the Center for American Women and Politics at Rutgers University puts it, no woman in the country's history has spent a greater amount of money earned entirely by herself on a race for major elective office.</p>
        <p>After spending $5 million and decisively winning Tuesday's Democratic primary over the state insurance commissioner, Deborah Senn, Ms. Cantwell is generating huge attention here for one more reason: she might just win in November.</p>
        <p>Several recent statewide polls have shown her close to -- or in one case, dead even with -- Mr. Gorton. And aside from her money and relentless pitch as the candidate of the ''new economy,'' several other factors have helped to tighten a contest that now offers Democrats a solid chance to pick up a Senate seat that had once seemed safe for the incumbent after several better-known Democrats, including Gov. Gary Locke, passed on the race.</p>
        <p>For one thing, at 72 years old and a fixture of public life here for more than 40 years, Mr. Gorton finds himself facing eerie parallels in Ms. Cantwell's themes to those he invoked in 1980, when he ended the 44-year Congressional career of Senator Warren G. Magnuson, then 75.</p>
        <p>For that race 20 years ago, Mr. Gorton pointedly jogged to the state Capitol in Olympia to file papers for his candidacy. And in one TV spot, showing him running through a park in Spokane, an announcer asked viewers to imagine a senator ''who is still in the prime of his life.''</p>
        <p>Now Ms. Cantwell is stressing this time-for-a-new-generation theme. She reminds voters that Mr. Gorton has been in elected office for about as long as she has been alive, and says it is time for a ''vigorous'' senator with ''new ideas.''</p>
        <p>She has also picked up on environmentalists' continuing ire over a legislative maneuver by Mr. Gorton last year. In attaching a rider to a bill providing aid to Kosovo war victims, he assisted a Texas company's bid to open a gold mine in rural Washington which would use a cyanide-leach process that could pollute the area's rivers. Ms. Cantwell accuses Mr. Gorton of advocating ''19th-century solutions to 21st-century problems.''</p>
        <p>In response, Cynthia Bergman, a spokeswoman for Mr. Gorton's campaign, said that Ms. Cantwell has ''got new money, but old-style government solutions.''</p>
        <p>Officials at Microsoft describe Senator Gorton as a leader on high-technology issues. He has been a vehement critic of the Justice Department's antitrust suit against the company, and his ties to Microsoft have been further strengthened by several daylong visits to the corporate campus in Redmond, where he has received detailed briefings on how Microsoft products work.</p>
        <p>To judge by federal election records, there is little question that Mr. Gorton is Microsoft's candidate. The corporate political action committee has given him $10,000, and Mr. Gates, the chairman, as well as Steven A. Ballmer, the chief executive, have each contributed the maximum of $2,000 for this election cycle. All told, Microsoft employees have contributed $97,925 through Aug. 30, according to the nonpartisan Campaign Study Group of Springfield, Va.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cantwell has received just $8,500 from Microsoft workers, none of them top officials. But she has received $47,300 from RealNetworks employees. And the company's billionaire founder, Robert Glaser, has held fund-raisers for her.</p>
        <p>Far more important, Mr. Glaser did the favor of hiring her as one of the company's first employees shortly after she was voted out of Congress in the Republican tide of 1994, a move that ultimately turned her into a multimillionaire. Starting as vice president of marketing, she rose to become senior vice president for the consumer and e-commerce divisions. She is now on leave from the company to pursue the Senate seat.</p>
        <p>Ms. Cantwell was considered a rising star when she was elected to the state legislature at the age of 28 and to Congress six years later, in 1992. But she lost re-election from a suburban Seattle district that happens to include the Microsoft campus.</p>
        <p>Despite her millions, or perhaps because of them, Ms. Cantwell has taken pains in the campaign to portray her life as unassuming. Never married, she lives in a modest suburban home with her mother and their dog, Chuck, a Yorkshire terrier that the campaign describes as diabetic.</p>
        <p>The supporting campaign roles by Seattle's cybertitans are intriguing. Mr. Glaser, who once worked at Microsoft, earned its wrath when he testified in Congress in 1998 that Microsoft had tried to cripple his technology with code written into a competing software program, a charge Microsoft stoutly denied.</p>
        <p>Even so, it is unlikely that Ms. Cantwell, if she wins, will call herself ''the Senator from RealNetworks'' -- or poke her finger in Microsoft's eye.</p>
        <p>She opposes the Justice Department's proposal to break up the corporation. And officials at both companies say that they agree on a wide range of legislative issues, like electronic privacy laws and expanded immigration visas for foreign workers, and that they have been partners on some business projects.</p>
        <p>''Even before RealNetworks existed, Maria was an effective and outspoken advocate in Congress for Microsoft and the technology industry,'' said Alex Alben, RealNetworks' vice president for government affairs.</p>
        <p>If Ms. Cantwell becomes a senator, said Vivek Varma, a Microsoft spokesman, ''we'd work fine with her. We worked well with Maria when she was in Congress. But Slade has been a real leader on all the issues affecting Microsoft, and he's earned our strong support.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorton also says Washington State needs his seniority and influence in Congress -- a point Mr. Magnuson invoked before Mr. Gorton beat him in 1980.</p>
        <p>Still, money is a big issue in this campaign -- both Ms. Cantwell's, and that of several Native American tribes, who have feuded with Mr. Gorton for years and vow to spend $2 million or more to defeat him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorton said he had a ''secret weapon'' of thousands of grass-roots supporters who would help him win re-election, though Democrats, depicting him as a patron of corporate interests, scoff at the claim.</p>
        <p>''When someone like Slade starts talking about his grass-roots appeal, you know he's in real trouble,'' said Cathy Allen, a Democratic political strategist in Seattle.</p>
        <p>Republicans, meanwhile, said they were confident they could use Ms. Cantwell's largely self-financed campaign, and her short career in Congress, against her. Brett Bader, a Republican consultant here who, like Ms. Allen, is not directly involved in the race, said Ms. Cantwell had ''showed up as a starry-eyed freshman and signed onto Clinton's agenda, and the voters in a moderate, swing district dumped her.''</p>
        <p>''There is only one reason she is given such a chance right now,'' he added. ''It's simply her checkbook. And that's not enough to get her across the finish line.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gorton has accused Ms. Cantwell of trying to buy the election, and his campaign offers a pie chart depicting how little money the Democrat is taking in from ''Real People'' as opposed to ''Herself.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cantwell shrugs off such criticism. ''The public,'' she said, ''would rather have me spend my own money than get my money from special interests.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: IN WASHINGTON STATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
