<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="12TRAN$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4DA143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Optioned RHP Ramon Ortiz to Edmonton of the PCL. Recalled RHP Jarrod Washburn from Edmonton.  MINNESOTA TWINS--Activated LHP J.C. Romero from the 15-day disabled list and optioned him to Salt Lake of the PCL.  TEXAS RANGERS--Named Bobby Jones interim outfield instructor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Optioned RHP Ramon Ortiz to Edmonton of the PCL. Recalled RHP Jarrod Washburn from Edmonton.  MINNESOTA TWINS--Activated LHP J.C. Romero from the 15-day disabled list and optioned him to Salt Lake of the PCL.  TEXAS RANGERS--Named Bobby Jones interim outfield instructor.</p>
        <p>National League  MONTREAL EXPOS--Recalled INF Andy Tracy from Ottawa of the International League.  PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES--Claimed C Cesar King off waivers from the Texas Rangers and optioned him to Scranton/Wilkes Barre of the International League.</p>
        <p>Atlantic League  ATLANTIC CITY SURF--Signed OF Juan Rocha.</p>
        <p>Northern League  SIOUX CITY EXPLORERS--Signed LHP Leonardo Patino and RHP Josh Kuecker.</p>
        <p>Western Baseball League  SONOMO COUNTY CRUSHERS--Signed C Miguel Rodriguez. Released INF Rafael Ozuna.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association  CLEVELAND ROCKERS--Waived C Anita Kaplan and F Daunau Lobela.  LOS ANGELES SPARKS--Waived G Kristin Clark.</p>
        <p>United States Basketball League  FLORIDA SEA DRAGONS--Signed F Antonio Reynolds-Dean and G Arthur Davis. Released C Chuck Roberts and F Lathon Nash. Placed G Carl Boyd and G Roberto Herrera on the inactive list.  WASHINGTON CONGRESSIONALS--Released F-C Antric Klaiber.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  CLEVELAND BROWNS--Signed DE Courtney Brown to a six-year contract and WR Zola Davis and DT Ryan Kuehl to one-year contracts.  HOUSTON--Named Tom Throckmorton BLESTO scout.  SEATTLE SEAHAWKS--Named Scott McCloughan director of college scouting.</p>
        <p>Canadian Football League  CALGARY STAMPEDERS--Signed LB Otis Floyd.  WINNIPEG BLUE BOMBERS--Signed S Spencer McLennan.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  MINNESOTA WILD--Signed a two-year full affiliation agreement with Cleveland of the IHL.</p>
        <p>American Hockey League  AHL--Suspended Hershey RW Scott Parker for two games and Hershey D Sami Helenius for one game for receiving game misconduct penalties against Rochester on May 9. Suspended LW Frank Bialowas pending an investigation into an incident for which he was assessed a game misconduct penalty against Rochester.  HARTFORD WOLF PACK--Signed RW Pavel Brendl.</p>
        <p>West Coast Hockey League  BASKERSFIELD CONDORS--Signed F Paul Willett to a three-year contract.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>ALABAMA--Named Brittney Ezell women's assistant basketball coach.  BALL STATE--Named Sally Northcroft assistant field hockey coach.  CAL STATE-FULLERTON--Named Barbara Erhardt women's assistant basketball coach.  ELON--Announced Phoenix as its nickname.  IONA--Named Harry Hart assistant athletic director for operations.  IOWA STATE--Named Robin Becker women's assistant basketball coach.  LAMAR--Named Joel Washington women's assistant basketball coach.  MERRIMACK--Named Rick Edelmann assistant director of athletics.  NORTH TEXAS--Announced the resignation of Steve Brickey, quarterback coach and offensive coordinator, to become quarterback coach at Iowa State.  NORTHERN ARIZONA--Named Steve Shaff director of sports media relations.  SAINT ANSELM--Announced the resignation of Bob Kerrigan, baseball coach.  SOUTH FLORIDA--Named Harry Elifson women's assistant basketball coach.  TEXAS-SAN ANTONIO--Announced the resignation of Mickey Lashley, baseball coach.  XAVIER--Announced the resignation of Mark Gaffney, men's assistant basketball coach. Rescinded the scholarship of basketball junior F Aaron Turner because of academic shortcomings.SAN ANTONIO--Announced the resignation of Mickey Lashley, baseball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
