<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="12POP.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4DD173BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>BARDO POND, LEE RANALDO AND CHRISTIAN MARCLAY, Cooler, 416 West 14th Street, West Village, (212) 229-0785. Bardo Pond's songs glide and swirl and pound, moving from digression to digression and floating into glimmering jams that carry psychedelia into the 1990's. When Lee Ranaldo isn't playing with Sonic Youth, he is fond of using tape loops and other devices that repeat, reflect and sustain his guitar tones. He is performing as a duo with Christian Marclay, a turntable improviser who uses all the sounds he finds on vinyl, including scratches and pops. Sunday at 9 p.m., with Pelt and Poem Rocket; call the club for admission price (Jon Pareles).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>BARDO POND, LEE RANALDO AND CHRISTIAN MARCLAY, Cooler, 416 West 14th Street, West Village, (212) 229-0785. Bardo Pond's songs glide and swirl and pound, moving from digression to digression and floating into glimmering jams that carry psychedelia into the 1990's. When Lee Ranaldo isn't playing with Sonic Youth, he is fond of using tape loops and other devices that repeat, reflect and sustain his guitar tones. He is performing as a duo with Christian Marclay, a turntable improviser who uses all the sounds he finds on vinyl, including scratches and pops. Sunday at 9 p.m., with Pelt and Poem Rocket; call the club for admission price (Jon Pareles).</p>
        <p>JOHN BUTCHER, JOELLE LEANDRE, RON DE JONG, DEREK BAILEY, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7501. Mr. Butcher, an English saxophonist, comes from the school of full-on European abstract improvisation, in which the musical languages normally associated with the instrument -- jazz, blues, whatever -- are vigorously erased and replaced with carefully deployed sounds and textures. He'll be improvising with the French bassist Joelle Leandre, a strong, talented musician who tends to warm up cold contexts, as well as the percussionist Ron de Jong and the guitarist Derek Bailey, a father figure of European abstract improv. Tonight at 8 and 10; admission is $10 (Ben Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* KARAN CASEY, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3055. Karan Casey first caught the ears of New Yorkers as the singer for Solas, the brashest and best Celtic band on that bustling circuit. She's on her own now, reaching back into the songbook of her native County Waterford to record her second solo album, which will surely show evidence of the thoroughly modern attitude. Sunday at 8 p.m.; admission is $10 (Ann Powers).</p>
        <p>* VIC CHESNUTT AND KRISTIN HERSH, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700. Two legendarily idiosyncratic singer-songwriters find out what they have in common in this tag-team performance. Kristin Hersh, whose work, both solo and with Throwing Muses, delves more deeply into feminine flesh and psyche than most performers could even imagine, shares songs and conversation with her pal Vic Chesnutt, whose insights into damaged hearts and healing souls make the darkest stories bright. Tonight at 8; admission is $15 (Powers).</p>
        <p>DEEP BANANA BLACKOUT, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Manhattan, (212) 777-6800. Working the neo-psychedelic jam band circuit, Deep Banana Blackout sets out to fuse Janis Joplin's blues-rock with the funk of the Meters. It pumps out wah-wah vamps while its singer, Jen Durkin, insists she's ready to ''Bump and Sway''; so are the fans. Tomorrow, doors open at 8 p.m., with Electric Hill opening; tickets are $18 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* LIZ CARROLL, Blarney Star, 43 Murray Street, TriBeCa, (212) 732-2873. Liz Carroll, one of the finest Celtic fiddlers in the United States, isn't afraid to let a little of the Celtic diaspora into her Irish fiddle tunes; touches of bluegrass technique put an American twinkle into the old jigs and reels. Tonight at 9 and 10:30; admission is $10 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>RAMBLIN' JACK ELLIOTT, Bottom Line, 15 West Fourth Street, at Mercer Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 228-7880. The patron saint of folk-music hobos returns to spin some tales about roping cattle, sailing boats and riding rails, all things Ramblin' Jack has not just dreamed about but done. Nearly 70 years of wandering the planet hasn't slowed this balladeer down; he is the living link between the Americas of Woody Guthrie and Ani DiFranco. Tonight at 7:30 and 10:30; admission is $17.50 (Powers).</p>
        <p>ESSENTIALLY ELLINGTON HIGH SCHOOL JAZZ BAND COMPETITION AND FESTIVAL, Avery Fisher Hall, Broadway at 65th Street, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5299. The fifth of these annual festivals -- a large and effective project in the name of nationwide jazz education -- will start with 15 high school bands and end with one winner. If you're into Ellington, come listen to surprisingly tight and well-driven bands play a selection of his compositions and arrangements: tunes like ''Anitra's Dance,'' ''Perdido'' and ''Concerto for Cootie.'' (You may see new trumpet virtuosos come to light in this last selection.) If you're into the sport of it, come cheer on the local team: La Guardia High School for Music, Art and the Performing Arts, led by Bob Stewart, has been a repeat winner in the past. The competition, which is free and open to the public, starts on Sunday from 4 to 7 p.m. and continues on Monday afternoon and evening (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* ANDREW HILL SEXTET, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232. It's coronation time for Mr. Hill, the pianist who represents an oblique genius of 1960's jazz history. The rest of the music has finally caught up with his odd, episodic structures, as the proliferation of young players surrounding him on this engagement and on his strong new album, ''Dusk'' (Palmetto), should make clear. Sets today and tomorrow are at 8 and 10:30 p.m. and midnight, with a cover of $20 or $25; on Sunday night, sets are at 7 and 9, and the cover charge is $15 or $20; $10 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* ETTA JONES, HOUSTON PERSON, Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037. An evergreen act on the New York jazz scene, but one that shouldn't be ignored because of its very availability. Ms. Jones, whose professional history goes back to the 1940's, bands led by Buddy Johnson and Earl Hines, is a gem; she makes you admire the melodies of the standards she sings, and yet she disguises them with bewitching, pitch-bending blues technique. Mr. Person, a tenor saxophonist, is a sweet, cool player. Their interaction has all the encoded language of decades spent working together. Sets through Sunday are at 9:30 and 11:30 p.m., with a 1 a.m. set tonight and tomorrow; cover charge is $20, or $15 on Sunday; $10 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* KRISHNA DAS, WELELA, VIEUX DIOP, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400. This 10th-anniversary celebration for Triloka Records shows the breadth of that world-fusion music label. Vieux Diop is a Senegalese griot; Welela features Rita Coolidge in a vocal trio that explores American Indian song. Krishna Das is the man you hear chanting ''Om Navah Shivaya'' on that haunting compact disc your yoga teacher plays during class. Come prepared to join in and sing the songs of three continents. Tonight at 8; tickets are $18 (Powers).</p>
        <p>TONY LEVIN, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. In a busy and wide-ranging career as a sideman, Tony Levin has been the bass player of choice for art-rock bands including, since the 1980's, King Crimson. They give him a chance to play the Chapman stick (tapping notes on strings with both hands) and to play his bass with drumsticks attached to his fingers. He has been coaxed to make solo albums, and this engagement is to feature music from his new one. He is performing with Jerry Marotta on drums and Larry Fast on synthesizers, with whom he once backed up Peter Gabriel, along with Jesse Green on guitar. Tomorrow at 8 and 10:30 p.m.; tickets are $15 in advance, $17 at the door (Pareles).</p>
        <p>''HANK MOBLEY'S MESSAGE,'' Birdland, 315 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 581-3080. Periodically the young historians of jazz raise a toast to Hank Mobley, one of the definers of the Blue Note sound of the 1960's, a brilliant, often overlooked player with a smoky sound and great rhythm, and a prolific writer of tunes. Supplicants to the Mobley altar in this three-night stand, ending tomorrow, include the saxophonists Craig Handy, Eric Alexander and Bob Berg; the gifted, swinging pianist Benny Green; and a rhythm section of Dwayne Burno on bass and Joe Farnsworth on drums. Sets are tonight and tomorrow at 9 and 11 p.m.; cover charge is $30; $10 minimum at table; $30 at the bar also includes minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>OGANS, S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940. Ogans is a Bahia-style group of nearly a dozen drummers generating a parade beat that swings and struts. The booming rhythm carries old and new hits that will have Brazilians in the crowd singing along. Tomorrow at 8 and 10 p.m. and midnight; admission is $20. (Pareles).</p>
        <p>''THE SONGS OF JIMMY RUSHING,'' TriBeCa Performing Arts Center, Borough of Manhattan Community College, 199 Chambers Street, (212) 346-8510. The singer Allan Harris headlines this tribute to Rushing, the great Basie-band vocalist and one of the best blues singers in history. The backing band includes the pianist Eric Reed, the trombonist Wycliffe Gordon and the drummer Carl Allen. The concert is tomorrow night at 7:30, and admission is  $35; $25 for students and the elderly. At 4:30 in the same location, the jazz film archivist Michael Chertok will present movies of Rushing, free and open to the public (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>SPIRITUALS TO SWING, Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824. This band of young hopefuls who first appeared in the late 80's -- with slightly shifting membership over the last few years -- has ably been making the jazz-gospel connection for new audiences. In the band now are the pianist Eric Reed, the guitarist Mark Whitfield, the saxophonist Craig Handy, the drummer Carl Allen and the bassist Reuben Rogers; the singer/pianist Mose Allison will also be on hand. Tonight at 8; tickets are $30 and $35 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* PAUL VAN DYK, Twilo, 530 West 27th Street, Chelsea, (212) 268-1600. The disc jockey and producer Paul van Dyk emerged from East Berlin to become one of the leading figures in trance, the steady-pulsing, eternally upbeat dance music that fills club floors around the world. It doesn't sound better anywhere than through the stellar sound system at Twilo. Tonight at 1 a.m.; admission is $25 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>YOSUKE YAMASHITA TRIO, Sweet Basil, 88 Seventh Avenue South, above Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 242-1785. Mr. Yamashita, a Japanese pianist, has visited New York a few times a year for quite a while now, and he has been happily plying a combination of raw energy and mainstream technique with a repertory that usually includes well-known ballads along with his own high-impact, quirky tunes. Sets through Sunday are at 9 and 11 p.m., with a 12:30 a.m. show tonight and tomorrow; cover charge is $20 weekends; $17.50 weekdays; $10 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
