<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ducking Questions About Past Relationship and Future Campaign</title>
    <meta content="12MAYO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MAYOR'S SEPARATION: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lategano-Nicholas, Cristyne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanover, Donna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE0DE143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ducking Questions About Past Relationship and Future Campaign</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Giuliani holds news conference, at which he deals with questions about his health, marital problems and possible withdrawal from Senate race; brushes aside questions about whether he had had an affair with Cristyne F Lategano-Nicholas, as mayor's wife has suggested last week; Lategano-Nicholas, who married in February, says she had never had sexual relationship with Giuliani; Giuliani photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joking that ''rumors of my demise are greatly exaggerated,'' Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that he had not yet decided if he would stay in the race for United States Senate. But he brushed aside repeated questions about whether he had had an affair with his former communications director, Cristyne F. Lategano-Nicholas, as the mayor's wife suggested this week.</p>
        <p>''I've said everything I was going to say about that a long time ago,'' Mr. Giuliani said during a packed, raucous news conference in which he frequently said ''shhhhhh!'' to yelling, shoving reporters. ''Cristyne Lategano was an excellent communications director; she did a great job for the city of New York. I've definitively answered all those questions, and I'm not going to drag somebody else's reputation into this.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joking that ''rumors of my demise are greatly exaggerated,'' Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said yesterday that he had not yet decided if he would stay in the race for United States Senate. But he brushed aside repeated questions about whether he had had an affair with his former communications director, Cristyne F. Lategano-Nicholas, as the mayor's wife suggested this week.</p>
        <p>''I've said everything I was going to say about that a long time ago,'' Mr. Giuliani said during a packed, raucous news conference in which he frequently said ''shhhhhh!'' to yelling, shoving reporters. ''Cristyne Lategano was an excellent communications director; she did a great job for the city of New York. I've definitively answered all those questions, and I'm not going to drag somebody else's reputation into this.''</p>
        <p>He added that ''what's going on right now has to do with Donna and me, and what you're trying to do is a back-door way of trying to dredge this all up so you can write more salacious stuff.''</p>
        <p>In August 1997, Mr. Giuliani said that a Vanity Fair article asserting that he had had an ''intimate'' relationship with Ms. Lategano was ''scurrilous'' and ''untrue'' and that the best thing to be done with the article ''is that it can be thrown in the trash.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday Mr. Giuliani added that Ms. Lategano-Nicholas was doing an ''excellent job'' as president of NYC and Company, the city's tourism bureau.</p>
        <p>The mayor's news conference, at a public school on the Lower East Side, was the latest public spectacle in the life of a man who in the last two weeks announced that he has prostate cancer, has a ''very good'' woman friend, is separating from his wife of 16 years and is still running for Senate against Hillary Rodham Clinton. But unlike Mr. Giuliani's emotional display of sadness and regret on Wednesday, when he abruptly announced that he and his wife were separating, the mayor returned yesterday to his more combative, and familiar, public persona.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani frequently berated reporters for their unruly behavior -- ''Do you realize that you embarrass yourselves doing this in the eyes of just about everybody?'' he said at one point -- and snapped at others. When one reporter asked if there might be ''criminality'' involved with giving Ms. Lategano the job at the tourist bureau, Mr. Giuliani shot back: ''Oh, get out of here. Get lost. Get lost. That's a sneaky way of trying to invade somebody's personal life.''</p>
        <p>But the mayor also displayed his new willingness to answer a variety of questions about his personal life, and was at times light-hearted. When one reporter asked if the mayor was ''politically dead,'' Mr. Giuliani laughed and responded: ''I'm sensitive to that word, you know, that last word you used, in any respect. Dead? No, I'm not dead. Rumors of my demise are greatly exaggerated.''</p>
        <p>While many Republicans across the state continued to express doubts that the mayor would stay in the race, others said they believed his performance at his news conference had stanched the political hemorrhaging, for now. In either case, most said publicly only that they felt sadness about the mayor's situation. Mr. Giuliani even received words of sympathy from his opponent's husband, President Clinton, whose relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky resulted in his impeachment.</p>
        <p>''I wish him and his wife and their children well on the health front and on the domestic front,'' Mr. Clinton said in response to a question in the Rose Garden of the White House. ''I think that's all there is -- all anybody would want.'' The president added: ''I've always had a good personal relationship with Mayor Giuliani. It's not been affected by the fact that I think my wife would be a better senator. And on this, I think everybody in New York and everybody in America ought to be rooting for the human side of this to work out.''</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki, speaking to reporters in Rockland County yesterday, said: ''My hope is he will still run.'' Pressed on what contingency plans the party had in place if Mr. Giuliani were to withdraw, Mr. Pataki replied: ''We're still letting the mayor with his family work through the decisions. And I think people should respect that this is a difficult time for Rudy and his family.'' A senior aide to Mr. Pataki told reporters not even to ask Mr. Pataki if he himself would step in to campaign for the Senate seat. ''He's not running,'' the aide decreed.</p>
        <p>Campaign advisers to the mayor, who said they had no idea on Wednesday that Mr. Giuliani was going to announce his separation, presented a cheerier picture yesterday, and said the mayor had told them in the morning to proceed ahead with all campaign plans.</p>
        <p>But longtime critics of Mr. Giuliani criticized the mayor for his friendship with Ms. Lategano-Nicholas and the mayor's involvement in helping her get a $150,000-a-year post  at the tourism bureau.</p>
        <p>''This story has legs,'' said former Mayor Edward I. Koch, a frequent critic of Mr. Giuliani. ''I think it's an abuse of power. It may not be a technical abuse, but in the court of opinion, it's an abuse.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Lategano-Nicholas said she took the day off yesterday to celebrate the 40th birthday of her husband, Nicholas Nicholas, whom she married in February. She said in an interview yesterday that she had never had a sexual relationship with Mr. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hanover's press secretary, Joannie Danielides, said Ms. Hanover spent yesterday making breakfast for her two children, taking them to school, handling correspondence at her office and then recording voice-overs at a New York City studio for her ''House Beautiful'' show on the A &amp; E network.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani said he spent his day working in his office at City Hall, holding his press conference and meeting with two doctors to talk about his treatment for cancer. He said at his news conference that he had no timetable for announcing his decision on treatment or whether he would stay in the race. But aides said yesterday that they expected him to think about his options over the weekend and perhaps make an announcement next week.</p>
        <p>The mayor said he would continue to cut his campaign schedule in half as he meets with doctors, making it unclear whether he would attend four fund-raisers scheduled next Tuesday and Wednesday in California. Aides said that for the time being all four events -- in Los Angeles, San Diego, Santa Barbara and Orange County -- were still on the schedule.</p>
        <p>Republicans said yesterday that the mayor would make the decision on the race based almost solely on his health, but also said that they would not be surprised if he took a poll in the next few days to determine how his personal life had affected his standing with voters.</p>
        <p>Republicans also said that while there was enormous sympathy for Mr. Giuliani, there was also bewilderment among party members over why he had announced his separation without first informing his wife -- a decision, they said, that may have caused Ms. Hanover's angry announcement on Wednesday about Ms. Lategano-Nicholas.</p>
        <p>''He essentially asked for her to go nuclear by behaving that way,'' one top state Republican official said.</p>
        <p>THE MAYOR'S SEPARATION: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
