<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Love Hopes to Finish as He Started</title>
    <meta content="12GOLF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gte Byron Nelson Classic</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Love, Davis 3d</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McCallister, Blaine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6DE143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Love Hopes to Finish as He Started</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>IRVING, Tex., May 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Davis Love III is tied for first place with Blaine McCallister after opening round of GTE Byron Nelson Classic, Irving, Texas; Love has five top 10 finishes this year, but no victories; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been more than two years since Davis Love III last won a golf tournament. That is a long time for a player of Love's caliber, long enough for confidence to slip, for frustration to become overwhelming.</p>
        <p>So after a sorely needed two-week break from competition, Love returned today with a fresher outlook, hoping his new attitude would help him break the mental barriers that have kept him from winning. Perhaps Love is on the right track. Overcoming extremely blustery conditions that featured 35 mile-an-hour wind gusts, Love shot a four-under-par 66, and was tied for first place with Blaine McCallister after today's opening round of the GTE Byron Nelson Classic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been more than two years since Davis Love III last won a golf tournament. That is a long time for a player of Love's caliber, long enough for confidence to slip, for frustration to become overwhelming.</p>
        <p>So after a sorely needed two-week break from competition, Love returned today with a fresher outlook, hoping his new attitude would help him break the mental barriers that have kept him from winning. Perhaps Love is on the right track. Overcoming extremely blustery conditions that featured 35 mile-an-hour wind gusts, Love shot a four-under-par 66, and was tied for first place with Blaine McCallister after today's opening round of the GTE Byron Nelson Classic.</p>
        <p>Six players were tied for third place at 68 -- Lee Janzen, Billy Andrade, Sergio Garcia, John Huston, Jerry Smith and Kevin Sutherland.</p>
        <p>But the strong wind that howled consistently made it a miserable day for many. Ask Tiger Woods, who struggled to a 75, including a 40 on the back nine. After reaching three under par through 10 holes, Woods bogeyed No. 11, double-bogeyed No. 14 and finished with consecutive bogeys on the last three holes.</p>
        <p>''I just didn't have the feel of my swing,'' said Woods, playing his first tournament since the Masters. ''I couldn't hit shots the way I wanted to.''</p>
        <p>But hitting good shots in the wind was not a problem for Love, who played at the TPC of Las Colinas, the more difficult of the tournament's two courses. McCallister, Andrade, Huston, Garcia, Smith and Sutherland all played at Cottonwood Valley today, but they will switch to Las Colinas on Friday, while Love, Janzen and Woods will play at Cottonwood.</p>
        <p>Love was five under par through 17 holes, and he would have finished alone in first place if he had not made a three-putt bogey at No. 18. Yet, it remained to be seen if Love would finish what he has started. Since winning the 1998 MCI Classic, Love has been in position to win many times, only to fall short. This year alone, Love already has five top 10 finishes, but he has stumbled in key situations, failing to break 70 on Sunday during his last five tournaments.</p>
        <p>After winning his first major at the 1997 P.G.A. Championship, Love expected even bigger and better things, but the last two years have been disappointing. He is still ranked No. 6 in the world, he is ninth on this year's PGA Tour money list and he is still only 36 years old. But as the months have passed without victories to show for his efforts, Love admitted he has become frustrated.</p>
        <p>''I've been trying too hard to win,'' said Love, who has 13 career victories on tour. ''It became more than a goal. It was becoming an obsession.</p>
        <p>''I've been at the top of the money list, the top of the world rankings, and I haven't won. Something is getting in the way. Sure, I've got to play to win, but not get obsessed with it, not get obsessed with beating Tiger and obsessed with beating David Duval. Just play golf and have fun.''</p>
        <p>While Love laments not having won in two years, McCallister has not won since 1993. He let a great opportunity slip away last weekend, when he finished second at the Compaq Classic of New Orleans, losing to Carlos Franco on the second hole of sudden death. McCallister bogeyed the final hole of regulation in New Orleans, then missed a four-foot putt for par on the first playoff hole. Yet, instead of sulking about the loss, McCallister responded with a solid round today; growing up in Fort Stockton, Tex., gave McCallister experience in playing with a strong wind.</p>
        <p>''I've seen wind,'' said McCallister. ''I've hit driver from 130 yards on a par-3. That's windy.</p>
        <p>''I had a chance to win that golf tournament last week, and that hurt. But last week is gone and I was very pleased about what I did today. I came here to play well and I'm off to a good start.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>The recent slump by JUSTIN LEONARD continued, as he opened with an 80. The 1997 British Open champion does not have a top 10 finish this year. . . . TIGER WOODS, tied for 76th place, will start Friday in danger of missing the cut. Woods has made 47 consecutive cuts, the longest streak on tour.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
