<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A First Release Meets a Big Boy</title>
    <meta content="12FLIC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AT THE MOVIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dey, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ullman, Tracey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Allen, Woody</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MacLachlan, Kyle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hawke, Ethan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Almereyda, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Shanghai Noon (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Small-Time Crooks (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hamlet (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/At the Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1D6163BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A First Release Meets a Big Boy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rick Lyman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>HOLLYWOOD, May 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>At the Movies column; Tom Dey comments on Disney's unexpected decision to release Shanghai Noon, his first directorial effort, as big Memorial Day movie; Tracey Ullman praises Woody Allen's directing and acting in new movie Small Time Crooks, in which she plays Allen's wife; photo; Kyle MacLachlan comments on playing Claudius opposite Ethan Hawke in Michael Almereyda's modern-day translation of Hamlet (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Dey thought the preview screening of ''Shanghai Noon,'' his first effort as a feature film director, was going pretty well, but he was unprepared for the phone call from Disney distribution executives. ''They said they were so excited about it that they wanted to make it their big Memorial Day release,'' Mr. Dey said. ''Never did I imagine anything like that. We were just a relatively small production shooting in Calgary. We were never considered a summer heavyweight. It was a dream come true.''</p>
        <p>But now Mr. Dey and his comical western, starring Jackie Chan and Owen Wilson, is up against Tom Cruise and ''Mission: Impossible 2,'' the only two national releases on the summer's premier movie weekend. Mr. Cruise opens on May 24, Mr. Chan two days later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Dey thought the preview screening of ''Shanghai Noon,'' his first effort as a feature film director, was going pretty well, but he was unprepared for the phone call from Disney distribution executives. ''They said they were so excited about it that they wanted to make it their big Memorial Day release,'' Mr. Dey said. ''Never did I imagine anything like that. We were just a relatively small production shooting in Calgary. We were never considered a summer heavyweight. It was a dream come true.''</p>
        <p>But now Mr. Dey and his comical western, starring Jackie Chan and Owen Wilson, is up against Tom Cruise and ''Mission: Impossible 2,'' the only two national releases on the summer's premier movie weekend. Mr. Cruise opens on May 24, Mr. Chan two days later.</p>
        <p>''I'm trying to work this angle: we're the underdogs, feel sorry for us,'' Mr. Dey said.</p>
        <p>The summer movie season is already here. ''Gladiator'' opened to $34 million last weekend. John Travolta's ''Battlefield Earth'' opens on Friday (review, Page 10), Disney's computer-animated ''Dinosaur'' on May 19. And then comes Memorial Day.</p>
        <p>The films considered likeliest to be box-office champions -- which include ''The Patriot'' with Mel Gibson, ''The Perfect Storm'' with George Clooney and ''Nutty Professor 2: The Klumps'' with Eddie Murphy -- will roll out with weekly predictability through Labor Day weekend. But which films, if any, will emerge as the summer's sleepers? Some think ''Shanghai Noon'' is a contender.</p>
        <p>The film is a gentle-hearted western about a Chinese Imperial Guard (Mr. Chan) who comes to America in the 1880's to rescue a kidnapped princess (Lucy Liu) and hooks up with a hapless train robber (Mr. Wilson).</p>
        <p>Mr. Dey, working his way through a slice of gooseberry pie at the Farmer's Market this week, said he had not really wanted to make the film when he walked into a meeting with executives at Spyglass Entertainment, which produced the film (as it did last summer's ''Sixth Sense'') with Disney. ''But there I was, in the room with them, and I suddenly started pitching and talking about how I'd make the film, and they said they really liked what they heard,'' Mr. Dey recalled. ''I thought, 'Oh, what have I done?' ''</p>
        <p>He flew to Hong Kong to meet with Mr. Chan, star of the 1998 sleeper hit ''Rush Hour,'' and then to Beijing, where some of the opening scenes were eventually shot in the Forbidden City, after much difficulty.</p>
        <p>Since 1994, after studying at the American Film Institute, Mr. Dey had been making television commercials at Ridley Scott Associates.</p>
        <p>After ''Shanghai Noon'' opens, though, he plans to take some time off before tackling another project. ''I don't know if I have a directorial style,'' he said. ''I mean, this is just my first movie. But I think that, basically, I'd rather be felt than heard.''</p>
        <p>That is to say, he would rather go for the emotion in a scene than go for the funny line. And he learned something else, too, he said. Not until ''Shanghai Noon'' was well into shooting did he realize what it was really about: the friendship between Mr. Chan's and Mr. Wilson's characters. ''It's not about an Imperial Guard coming to America to rescue a princess,'' he said. ''It's about friendship. It's about a very simple thing. That's maybe the most important thing this movie taught me. I learned how to look into a script and find that simple thing.''</p>
        <p>Tracey Loves Woody</p>
        <p>Tracey Ullman's office, from which she plots her career and runs her critically acclaimed HBO comedy series, is on a residential side street in central Santa Monica, within exhaust reach of the freeway.</p>
        <p>''I got a call from Woody Allen saying he had a new script and wanted me to play a part in it,'' Ms. Ullman said. ''I asked if I could see the script, and they had someone bring it over. The man sat out there on the sofa while I sat in here and read it. It was a wonderful part. Could I keep the script? I called up and asked. And they said yes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen has been known to refuse to allow his actors to see, much less keep, an entire script, so Ms. Ullman was happily surprised. It was necessary, though, because of the size of her part. In ''Small Time Crooks,'' the first film Mr. Allen will release through DreamWorks, Mr. Allen plays a hapless hoodlum who has a loving but bombastic relationship with his long-suffering wife, played by Ms. Ullman. Opening on May 19, it co-stars Hugh Grant, Michael Rapaport and Elaine May.</p>
        <p>''Did you see Woody in the movie?'' she asked. ''I thought he looked so cute in his stone-washed denim shorts. It was great seeing him play somebody again who wasn't rich and sophisticated.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ullman said that Mr. Allen always knew what he wanted in a scene but that he was also willing to let some of the actors try lines or movements or wardrobe of their own. Mr. Grant, who plays an uncharacteristically unsympathetic role, was able to ad-lib a revealingly acid twist on his exit line in one scene, she said.</p>
        <p>''All in all,'' she said. ''I would be happy if I were to do nothing for the rest of my life but my television series and Woody Allen movies.''</p>
        <p>A Modern Claudius</p>
        <p>Claudius is normally played by an actor appreciably older than the one playing Hamlet. ''I thought that they had the name of the part wrong when they called to ask me to play the role,'' said Kyle MacLachlan, who appears opposite Ethan Hawke's Danish prince in Michael Almereyda's modern-day translation of the Shakespeare tragedy, opening on Friday (review, Page 1 of Weekend).</p>
        <p>It had been many years since Mr. MacLachlan had played Shakespeare. Before landing his career-starting role in the lead of David Lynch's ''Dune,'' he had studied and performed Shakespeare in regional theater, playing Romeo twice, the boy in ''Henry V'' and Octavius in ''Julius Caesar.'' But between ''Dune'' and now, no Shakespeare.</p>
        <p>Mr. MacLachlan said he was particularly taken with Mr. Almereyda's decision to pitch the tragedy in a very naturalistic, American style of acting and speaking. ''I've always maintained that the best way to speak Shakespeare is to make it as accessible as possible,'' he said. ''If that means you ruin the structure of the poetry, so be it.''</p>
        <p>He can also be seen in Mike Figgis's experimental ''Time Code,''  and will be spending the next few months in New York filming a role -- as the first substantial romantic interest for Charlotte (Kristin Davis)  -- in ''Sex and the City'' on HBO. At the same time, he said, he hopes to renew his contacts with the New York theater world and possibly land a stage role. ''I'd love for it to be Shakespeare,'' he said.</p>
        <p>AT THE MOVIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
