<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SPARE TIMES</title>
    <meta content="12SPAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EEDE173BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="5500" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SPARE TIMES</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 34-12 36th Street, at 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. ''Women Film Pioneers,'' begins tomorrow and runs through May 14; with music by Donald Sosin at most screenings. Tonight and tomorrow night at 6:30, Pedro Almodovar's ''All About My Mother.'' Evening screenings $8; $4 for members and the elderly. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. All activities are free with museum admission unless otherwise indicated. Admission: $8.50; the elderly and students, $5.50; ages 5 to 18, $4.50; 4 and under, free. Information: (718) 784-0077.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATTRACTIONS</p>
        <p>Museums and Sites</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 34-12 36th Street, at 35th Avenue, Astoria, Queens. ''Women Film Pioneers,'' begins tomorrow and runs through May 14; with music by Donald Sosin at most screenings. Tonight and tomorrow night at 6:30, Pedro Almodovar's ''All About My Mother.'' Evening screenings $8; $4 for members and the elderly. Museum hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. All activities are free with museum admission unless otherwise indicated. Admission: $8.50; the elderly and students, $5.50; ages 5 to 18, $4.50; 4 and under, free. Information: (718) 784-0077.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West and 79th Street. ''The Butterfly Conservatory: Tropical Butterflies Alive in Winter,'' through May 29. Admission is by timed entry only. Tickets, which can be reserved and include museum admission, are $15 for adults, $11 for students and the elderly, $9 for children 12 and under. ''Body Art: Marks of Identity,'' on view through May 29. Admission is by timed entry. ''Asian-Pacific American Heritage Month,'' with lectures, films, performances and workshops on weekends in May. Tomorrow and Sunday at 1 and 4 p.m., traditional Korean music and dance. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Passing Through'' (1998), a film about a Korean adoptee who grew up in Minnesota. Tomorrow at 3, a talk on Korean adoptees with Peter Savasta, vice president of the adoption organization Also-Known-As. Sunday: at 1 and 4 p.m., music teachers from Thailand perform Thai regional and classical music; at 2 p.m., ''Regret to Inform,'' a film about the Vietnam War; at 3:15 p.m., a talk on the pressures immigrant families face, with Jessica Lee, executive director of the Coalition of Asian-American Children and Families. Free with museum admission. Imax films are ''Epic Journeys: The Great Migrations'' and ''Dolphins.'' In the Imax Theater tonight and tomorrow night at 9, ''Laser Aerosmith in 3-D''; at 10, ''Led Zeppelin.'' Laser show tickets: $12. Museum hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 8:45 p.m. Admission (suggested donation): $10 for adults; $7.50 for students and the elderly; $6 for children. Combination tickets are available. Information: (212) 769-5100; advance tickets: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY'S ROSE CENTER FOR EARTH AND SPACE, Central Park West at 81st Street. This 333,500-square-foot, seven-floor, 120-foot-high exhibition and research center includes the new Hayden Planetarium, the Cullman Hall of the Universe and the Gottesman Hall of Planet Earth. The Hayden Planetarium contains the Space Theater, presenting ''Passport to the Universe,'' and the Big Bang Theater, featuring narrated visual and audio effects simulating the beginning of the universe. ''Starry Nights: Fridays Under the Sphere,'' from 6 to 8 p.m., music with the Claudio Roditi Quintet. Free with admission; food and cash bar. ''Full Moon: Apollo Mission Photographs of the Lunar Landscape,'' from NASA's Apollo missions to the moon; through Sept. 23. Hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays to 8:45 p.m. Space shows run throughout the day. Admission (suggested donation) to the American Museum of Natural History, which includes the Rose Center: $10; for students and the elderly, $7.50; children 12 and under, $6; under 2, free. Admission to the museum, the Rose Center and the Hayden Planetarium space show: $19; students and the elderly, $14; children 12 and under, $11.50; under 2, free. Information: (212) 769-5100. Reservations: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF TELEVISION AND RADIO, 25 West 52nd Street, Manhattan. Television Documentary Festival, featuring documentaries produced for television in the United States in the past year, following each screening with a panel discussion involving the audience, filmmaker and production team; through May 21. Tonight at 6, ''The American Experience: Abraham and Mary Lincoln: A House Divided,'' with the filmmaker David Grubin. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., ''Something for Everyone: Sondheim Tonight,'' a retrospective commemorating the composer's 70th birthday. Daily screenings at 2; additional screenings on Thursdays at 5:30 p.m. and Fridays at 6:30 p.m.; through June 25. Tonight at 6:30, a David Frost show devoted to the original Broadway production of ''Follies.'' Museum hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 6 p.m.; Thursdays until 8 p.m. On Fridays the theater is open until 9. Admission: $6; students and the elderly, $4; 13 and under, $3. Information: (212) 621-6800.</p>
        <p>NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, 170 Central Park West, near 77th Street. ''Stork Club,'' including an environmental installation that mimics the floor plan of the club, photographs and memorabilia through Oct. 1; the exhibition coincides with the publication of a book by a New York Times culture reporter, Ralph Blumenthal, ''Stork Club: America's Most Famous Nightspot and the Lost World of Cafe Society.'' Tomorrow at 2 p.m., a talk with the editor of the New York Times City section, Constance Rosenblum, author of ''Gold Digger,'' about the life of Peggy Hopkins Joyce.  Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; students and the elderly, $3; 12 and under, free. Information: (212) 873-3400.</p>
        <p>SOUTH STREET SEAPORT MUSEUM AND MARKETPLACE, South and Fulton Streets, Lower Manhattan. In a 19th-century port district with restaurants, shops and bars, the museum has three galleries, a children's crafts center and a boat-building center. Tomorrow and Sunday from 1 to 4 p.m., National Historic Preservation Week is celebrated with tours and activities in the Children's Center, 165 John Street. Free with museum admission. $2 materials fee. Museum hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; closed Tuesdays. Stores in the marketplace: Mondays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 9 p.m.; Sundays, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Museum admission: $6; the elderly, $5; students, $4; children 12 and under, $3. Information: (212) 748-8600; reservations for special events: (212) 748-8786; the marketplace, (212) 732-7678.</p>
        <p>Cruises</p>
        <p>CIRCLE LINE CRUISES, leaving from Pier 83, 42nd Street at the Hudson River, Clinton. A two-hour 24-mile cruise around southern Manhattan, passing landmarks like Ellis Island and the United Nations, daily at 11 a.m. and 3:30 p.m. Tickets: $18; children 12 and under, $10; the elderly, $16. A three-hour, 35-mile cruise around all of Manhattan, today at 10 a.m., noon, 1:30 and 2:30 p.m.; beginning tomorrow, daily at 9:30 and 10:30 a.m., 12:30, 1:30, 2:30 and 4:30 p.m. Tickets: $22; children 12 and under, $12; the elderly, $19. ''Harbor Lights,'' Fridays through Sundays, 7 p.m. Tickets: $18; children 12 and under, $10; the elderly, $16. Information: (212) 563-3200.</p>
        <p>WORLD YACHT, leaving from Pier 81, 41st Street at the Hudson River, Clinton. Daily dinner cruises along the West Side of Manhattan and around New York Harbor, from 7 to 10 p.m., boarding at 6 p.m. Prices: Fridays, $75; Saturdays, $79; Sundays $67 (does not include beverages, taxes or gratuities). Brunch cruises sail on Sundays from 12:30 to 2:30 p.m., with boarding at 11:30 a.m. Price: $39.95. Information: (212) 630-8100.</p>
        <p>N.Y. WATERWAY, leaving from Pier 78, West 38th Street and 12th Avenue, Manhattan. Daily, beginning tomorrow, two-hour full Manhattan cruise, at 10:30 a.m. and 1:30 p.m., through Nov. 12. Tickets: $24; $19 for the elderly; $12 for children. Daily, a 90-minute cruise of New York Harbor; at 10 a.m., noon, 2 and 4 p.m.; through May 26. Tickets: $19; the elderly, $16; ages 3 to 12, $9; 2 and younger, free. Fridays at 10:15 p.m., Disco cruise. Price: $19; $9 for children. A 70-minute twilight tour leaves daily, except Tuesday, at 8:45 p.m.; additional tours on Saturdays at 7:15 and 10:15 p.m. and on Sundays at 7:15. Tickets: $19; the elderly, $16; children, $9. Information: (800) 533-3779.</p>
        <p>Gardens</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN, 900 Washington Avenue, Prospect Heights. ''Lilac Weekend,'' tomorrow and Sunday from 10 a.m. to 6 p.m., including a free tour beginning at 1 p.m. Gallery hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission: $3; $1.50 for students and the elderly; free for children 15 and under; free on Tuesdays, except holidays; and free from 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. Hours: Tuesdays through Fridays, 8 a.m. to 6 p.m.; Saturdays, Sundays and holidays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. The conservatory closes 30 minutes before the grounds close. Information: (718) 623-7200.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN, 200th Street and Kazimiroff Boulevard, Fordham, the Bronx. The grounds include 27 specialty gardens and plant collections and a 40-acre forest. The azaleas, dogwoods and lilacs are at peak bloom. The Rock Garden, home to thousands of alpine plants from six continents, is in bloom through mid-June. ''Peony Festival,'' through Sunday, featuring storytellers with Chinese folk tales (tomorrow at 2 p.m. in the Everett Children's Adventure Garden); Sunday at 2 p.m., Chinese Lion Dance. The festival coincides with the Chinese Peony Show through June 4 in the Haupt Conservatory, with the tree peonies in bloom. Mother's Day weekend, with a plant sale (today through Sunday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m.) and workshop (tomorrow from 1 to 3 p.m.). Tomorrow, afternoon tea with tea sandwiches, scones and shortbread; reservations required, $24.50 and $18 for children. Reservations: (718) 220-8398. Saturdays and Sundays at 12:30 p.m., 90-minute bird walks. Garden hours: Tuesdays through Sundays and Monday holidays, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Conservatory admission: $3.50; students and the elderly, $2.50; children 2 to 12, $2; under 2, free. Grounds admission free for all on Wednesdays and from 10 a.m. to noon on Saturdays. There are also combination packages. Parking: $5. Information: (718) 817-8700.</p>
        <p>WAVE HILL, West 249th Street and Independence Avenue, Riverdale, the Bronx. Gardens, greenhouses and woodlands are part of the 28-acre garden and cultural institution. Landscape paintings of China by Manshen Wang will be exhibited through May 21. Tomorrow at 2 p.m., a woodland walk to observe the wildflowers. Sunday at 2 p.m., a workshop to construct a dried flower topiary; register at extension 213. Materials fee: $10. Grounds hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 9 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission: $4; students and the elderly, $2; Saturdays, free until noon. Information: (718) 549-3200; reservations: extension 213.</p>
        <p>Zoos</p>
        <p>BRONX ZOO, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Fordham. Some 265 wooded acres are devoted to naturalistic habitats, including Jungle World, African Plains, the Baboon Reserve, the World of Birds, the Aitken Sea Bird Colony (with daily penguin feedings at 3:30 p.m., weather permitting), Big Birds and the Congo Gorilla Forest. Hours: Mondays through Fridays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Saturdays and Sundays, 10 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Admission $9; $5 for children 2 to 12 and the elderly; free for everyone on Wednesdays. Parking: $6. Information: (718) 367-1010.</p>
        <p>EVENTS</p>
        <p>''LAW, LITERATURE AND CULTURE,'' Graduate Center of the City University of New York, 365 Fifth Avenue, at 34th Street. A symposium featuring lawyers, writers and professors. Today, 9:15 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. Free. Information: (212) 817-2005.</p>
        <p>''POETS AND PEACEMAKERS,'' Fifth Avenue Presbyterian Church, Fifth Avenue at 55th Street. A free reading of works by Nobel Prize-winning writers by a group of actors and others in the arts, including Rosemary Harris, David Suchet, Adolph Green, Cherry Jones and Frances Sternhagen. Today at 12:30 p.m. Sponsored by the Tipa (Theater to Promote International Peace) Project. Information: (212) 874-2225.</p>
        <p>HOUSE AND GARDEN TOUR, Brooklyn Heights. A self-guided tour of five historic homes. Tomorrow, 1 to 5 p.m. Tickets, $25, will be available at 122 Pierrepont Street, between Clinton and Henry Streets. Sponsored by the Brooklyn Heights Association. Information: (718) 858-9193.</p>
        <p>SPRING FAIR AND FOOD FESTIVAL, Grand Central Terminal, Vanderbilt Hall, 42nd Street and Park Avenue. Cooking demonstrations, musical entertainment and specialty gift merchants. Tomorrow, 10 a.m. to 8 p.m.; Sunday, noon to 6 p.m. Free. Information: (212) 340-2210.</p>
        <p>PAWS WALK 2000, Prospect Park, Bartell-Pritchard Circle, Brooklyn. A walk through the park to promote responsible pet ownership and care. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. Registration begins at 9:45 a.m. Fee: $15 (two-dog maximum). Sponsored by Friends of Van Cortlandt Park and the City of New York Parks and Recreation Department. Information: (718) 601-1460.</p>
        <p>RECREATION</p>
        <p>WOMEN'S SPORTS AND FITNESS HALF-MARATHON AND 5K, Central Park. Two races for women only, Sunday, beginning on the East Drive at 70th Street, with the half-marathon at 8 a.m., followed at 8:05 by the five-kilometer race. Sponsored by the New York Road Runners Club. Advance registration fee, $17; $12 for club members; $10 for junior and senior club members. Race day registration, $22, $15 for members; $12 for junior and senior members. While the adults are running, there will be a play party for children 2 to 8 years old from 7:30 to 10:30 a.m.; admission, $5 in advance, $7 on Sunday. Information: (212) 860-4555.</p>
        <p>ON THE STREET</p>
        <p>NEW YORK CITY BUSINESS EXPO, Fulton Street, from Broadway to Gold Streets, Lower Manhattan. With crafts, food and antiques. Today, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>BLEECKER STREET COUNTRY FAIR, Greenwich Village. Bleecker Street, from Avenue of the Americas to Seventh Avenue. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the Downtown Independent Republican Club.</p>
        <p>THIRD AVENUE MOTHER'S DAY STREET FESTIVAL, from 42nd to 57th Streets, Manhattan. Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by 17th Police Precinct Community Council.</p>
        <p>CRAFTS ON COLUMBUS, Columbus Avenue from 77th to 81st Streets, Manhattan. Tomorrow and Sunday, 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. Sponsored by the American Arts and Crafts Alliance.</p>
        <p>WEST SIDE MONTESSORI SCHOOL SPRING FAIR, West 92nd Street, between West End Avenue and Riverside Drive, Manhattan. Rides, entertainment, crafts and food. Free admission. Tomorrow, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>WALKING TOURS</p>
        <p>''MOTHER'S DAY IN CENTRAL PARK.'' Hidden places in the park, as well as floral displays in Strawberry Fields, the Literary Walk and the Arsenal. Tomorrow at 2:30 p.m. and Sunday at noon and 2:30 p.m. Fee, $12. Sponsored by NYC Discovery Tours. Reservations and meeting place: (212) 465-3331.</p>
        <p>''THE UKRAINIANS AND THEIR NEIGHBORS IN THE EAST VILLAGE.'' A look at the Ukrainian heritage of the area. Meets tomorrow at 2 p.m. outside the Second Avenue Deli, 156 Second Avenue, at 10th Street. Fee, $12. Sponsored by Dr. Phil: New York Talks and Walks. Information and meeting place: (888) 377-4455.</p>
        <p>''JAZZ NIGHTS IN HARLEM.'' A tour of the area, followed by dinner and a stop at a jazz club. Meets tonight and tomorrow at 8 on the northeast corner of Lenox Avenue and 125th Street. Fee: $45. Sponsored by Harlem Heritage Tours. Reservations: (212) 280-7888.</p>
        <p>''URBAN FOREST WALKING TOURS: PELHAM BAY PARK,'' the Bronx. Participants can discover what flowers and vegetation thrive in a saltwater environment. Bronx. Tomorrow at 10 a.m. Fee: $12. Sponsored by the American Museum of Natural History. Registration and meeting place: (212) 769-5200.</p>
        <p>''CARIBBEAN FOOD AND CULTURE OF FLATBUSH,'' Brooklyn. A historical and gastronomic tour led by Alice Baldwin-Jones, an anthropologist. Meets tomorrow at 1 p.m. at the corner of Flatbush and Ocean Avenues. Sponsored by the Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment. Fee, $8; $6 for Center members; $5 for students and the elderly. Information: (718) 788-8500, extension 401.</p>
        <p>FOREST PARK: ''ANNUAL DOGGIE HIKE,'' Queens. Walkers, with or without dogs, are welcome on this four-mile walk through the forest. Meets tomorrow at 11:30 a.m. at Kew Gardens Road and Queens Boulevard. Fee, $3. Sponsored by the Outdoors Club. Information: (516) 671-2095.</p>
        <p>''DANDIES, DUDES AND SHADY LADIES,'' Lower Manhattan. A look back at old New York and the seamier sides of SoHo and the Bowery. Meets on Sunday at 2 p.m. at the subway kiosk at Astor Place. Fee, $10. Sponsored by Street Smarts New York. Information: (212) 969-8262.</p>
        <p>''PARK HOPPING: UNION SQUARE TO MADISON SQUARE,'' Manhattan. Sunday at 1 p.m. Fee, $18. Sponsored by the 92nd Street Y. Information and meeting place: (212) 996-1100.</p>
        <p>''THE PARK IN SPRING,'' Central Park. A tour that incorporates a discussion of the park's landscape design, architecture and restoration with a look at the seasonal foliage. Meets on Sunday at 11 a.m. at the General Sherman statue at 59th Street and Fifth Avenue. Sponsored by the Municipal Art Society. Fee, $15; $12 for Society members. Information: (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>HARLEM GOSPEL TOUR. A tour that includes stops at a church and several cultural institutions. Meets Sundays at 10 a.m. on the southwest corner of Lenox Avenue and 116th Street. Fee: $20. Sponsored by Harlem Heritage Tours. Information: (212) 280-7888.</p>
        <p>''ANNUAL MOTHER'S DAY MULTIETHNIC EATING TOUR,'' a walking and eating tour of the Jewish East Side, Chinatown and Little Italy, featuring history and culinary  samples of these traditional immigrant neighborhoods. Meets on Sunday at 1 p.m. at the southeast corner of Delancey and Essex Streets. Sponsored by Big Onion Walking Tours. Fee: $13; $11 for students and the elderly. Reservations: (212) 439-1090.</p>
        <p>''HELL AIN'T HOT: THIS HERE'S HELL'S KITCHEN,'' Manhattan. A historical look at the gritty area before its transformation into present-day Clinton. Meets on Sunday at 1 p.m. at the northwest corner of 42nd Street and 10th Avenue. Fee, $12. Sponsored by Joyce Gold History Tours of New York. Information: (212) 242-5762.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
