<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Computer Model on Auto Pollution Is Flawed, Study Says</title>
    <meta content="12POLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198826"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7DE143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Computer Model on Auto Pollution Is Flawed, Study Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Academy of Sciences report says Environmental Protection Agency's computer model for predicting how much air pollution comes from cars and trucks underestimates emissions and may overestimate benefits of some pollution-control strategies; EPA spokesman says study is 'constructive' and made good recommendations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency's computer model for predicting how much air pollution comes from cars and trucks underestimates emissions and may overestimate the benefits of some pollution-control strategies, the National Academy of Sciences said in a report today.</p>
        <p>The report did not say how far off the model is, but it said the model ''substantially'' underestimates emissions of unburned fuel from cars and nitrogen oxides from trucks, both major ingredients of smog. And the model may overestimate the value of dashboard lights to warn of pollution control problems and of the value of ethanol and gasoline additives intended to reduce emissions, the study said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency's computer model for predicting how much air pollution comes from cars and trucks underestimates emissions and may overestimate the benefits of some pollution-control strategies, the National Academy of Sciences said in a report today.</p>
        <p>The report did not say how far off the model is, but it said the model ''substantially'' underestimates emissions of unburned fuel from cars and nitrogen oxides from trucks, both major ingredients of smog. And the model may overestimate the value of dashboard lights to warn of pollution control problems and of the value of ethanol and gasoline additives intended to reduce emissions, the study said.</p>
        <p>''The decisions that rely on the results of this model are of tremendous importance to human health, the environment and the economy,'' the report said in explaining the value of accurate computer predictions.</p>
        <p>One member of the committee that wrote the report, Dr. Laurence S. Caretto, dean of the College of Engineering and Computer Science at California State University at Northridge, said the investigators questioned whether the Environmental Protection Agency was ''looking at the right things'' in creating a model. A more accurate model would indicate which pollution-control strategies to pursue, he said.</p>
        <p>The agency developed the program, the Mobile Source Emissions Factor Model, known as Mobile, in 1978 and has revised it intermittently since then. The study said it was ''the central tool used by environmental and transportation agencies to estimate on-road mobile-emissions and to assess national, state and local air-quality programs for controlling such emissions.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the agency, David Cohen, said the study was ''constructive, fair and balanced,'' and made good recommendations. Agency officials noted that they were sometimes accused of setting emissions rules that were too stringent, but that the study seemed to say they might be too lax.</p>
        <p>The committee said the environmental agency was in the dark on some crucial issues, like the reaction of drivers to what is colloquially known as the ''idiot light,'' the federally required warning light on the dashboard that illuminates when a car's computer senses a problem.</p>
        <p>''The committee is unaware of any studies conducted to assess the motorist response to illuminated malfunction indicator lights, although this response rate is one of the most important factors for determining the effectiveness of on-board diagnostic systems in reducing emissions,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>The agency, the report said, also needs to know more about ''high-emitting vehicles'' -- cars and trucks with smoking tailpipes -- that are believed to be the source of a large portion of pollution.</p>
        <p>Pollution regulators should also pay more attention to off-road sources of emissions, the report said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
