<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New England Journal of Medicine Names Third Editor in a Year</title>
    <meta content="Y12JOU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Journal of Medicine</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drazen, Jeffrey M (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EFD9173BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New England Journal of Medicine Names Third Editor in a Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <dateline>WALTHAM, Mass., May 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Jeffrey M Drazen, leading asthma researcher at Harvard with strong ties to drug industry, is named editor of The New England Journal of Medicine; journal's tough conflict-of-interest rules will prevent him from writing certain articles and editorials for at least two years; Drazen pledges to protect integrity of The Journal's information; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dr.Jeffrey M. Drazen, a leading asthma researcher at Harvard with strong ties to the drug industry, was named the editor of The New England Journal of Medicine here today.</p>
        <p>But the journal's tough conflict-of-interest rules will prevent Dr. Drazen from writing certain articles and editorials for at least two years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dr.Jeffrey M. Drazen, a leading asthma researcher at Harvard with strong ties to the drug industry, was named the editor of The New England Journal of Medicine here today.</p>
        <p>But the journal's tough conflict-of-interest rules will prevent Dr. Drazen from writing certain articles and editorials for at least two years.</p>
        <p>Pledging to protect the integrity of The Journal's information, Dr. Drazen, a professor of medicine at Harvard, said he would recuse himself from the editorial process for any papers submitted that relate to asthma or to nine major companies from which he has received research grants or consultation fees.</p>
        <p>Dr. Drazen, 53, helped pioneer asthma drugs now taken by four million asthmatics worldwide. In today's news conference, he strongly defended the need for doctors to work closely and carefully with the drug industry. He called the industry a powerful force without which basic research findings made through taxpayer grants from the National Institutes of Health could not be converted into new therapies to improve patient care and public health.</p>
        <p>Last February, after an internal investigation prompted by articles in The Los Angeles Times, The Journal found that it had violated its own rules in publishing 19 articles by Dr. Drazen and other authors with industry ties. The Journal said the articles should have been written by scientists without such connections, but its editors blamed themselves and said Dr. Drazen had disclosed his industry support.</p>
        <p>Asked today at the news conference about that episode, Dr. Drazen said that as The Journal's new editor in chief he would hand over all manuscripts dealing with his specialty or products made by the nine companies to deputies ''and make sure that they are on the agenda at a time when I do not come to the editorial meeting.''</p>
        <p>In such cases, Dr. Drazen said he wanted ''The Journal to be able to judge the science that comes in, if it is good or bad, without me having anything to do with it.''</p>
        <p>''I do not want to influence things in either a positive or a negative way,'' he said. ''We want the good science and good information to get out there'' in The Journal, which is one of the most influential in the world.</p>
        <p>Dr. Drazen, who will leave his Harvard post, will be the Journal's third editor in chief in less than a year. His selection follows several years of turmoil between the editors of The Journal and its owner, the Massachusetts Medical Society, concerning the society's increasing business ventures.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jerome P. Kassirer was fired as the top editor last summer because of conflicts with society officials over proposals to promote Web sites and create new specialty journals using The New England Journal of Medicine logo. In recent years, The Journal has become a huge source of revenue for the medical society, largely through increased drug company advertising. And the society has become heavily dependent on the Journal's profits to maintain its new $50 million headquarters here.</p>
        <p>Until 1979, The Journal published its profits, which then were $386,540 a year. The Journal no longer discloses its profits, which are estimated to be at least $20 million a year, making its owner the wealthiest medical society in the country. The Journal's profits help keep the society's dues low and membership high, giving the society a degree of political and lobbying clout it would not otherwise have.</p>
        <p>Speaking of Dr. Drazen's selection, Dr. Kassirer said, ''I wish him luck; he'll need it.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Marcia Angell succeeded Dr. Kassirer as editor in chief pending a search committee's choice of a new editor. Dr. Angell, who was a finalist, withdrew recently as a candidate and said she was retiring to write a book on alternative medicine.</p>
        <p>Dr. Steven A. Schroeder, president of the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation in Princeton, N.J., said he did not recall that the search committee, of which he was a member, had discussed Dr. Drazen's ties to the drug industry.</p>
        <p>Medical society officials said they were vesting Dr. Drazen with the same editorial independence and authority to hire the Journal's editors and staff as his predecessors. The society also said Dr. Drazen ''will also have complete authority over the brand of The Journal, including the use of the name, logo, look and feel, in both the print and electronic versions of The Journal.</p>
        <p>One unresolved issue is whether the society will move the Journal's offices from a library in the Harvard Medical School complex to the society's headquarters here in a suburb of Boston, a site that some editors see as too far removed from a hospital setting. The library is within a few dozen yards of the Brigham and Women's Hospital, a Harvard teaching hospital where Dr. Drazen is chief pulmonary physician.</p>
        <p>Speaking of his contract and critics of his ties to the drug industry, Dr. Drazen said: ''I have got what it takes, and you are just going to have to wait and see whether you believe it. There is no way to judge it up front.''</p>
        <p>The search committee's first choice, Dr. Edward J. Benz Jr., physician in chief at Johns Hopkins Hospital in Baltimore, said he had been offered the position but had withdrawn for personal reasons.</p>
        <p>In a letter to Dr. Harry L. Greene II, the executive vice president of the society, Dr. Benz said he wanted to remain a full-time medical school faculty member and continue his research for at least a few more years.</p>
        <p>Dr. Benz denied in the letter that he was turning down the editorship because of any dispute with the society about editorial integrity, use of the Journal's logo, or location of its editorial offices.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
