<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Surprised 'Wild Party'</title>
    <meta content="12BROA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON STAGE AND OFF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Papp, Joseph, Public Theater/new York Shakespeare Festival</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Daniel (Actor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hirson, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, August</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinbruner, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartmann, Eve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wild Party, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cats (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wrong Mountain (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Jitney (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">How to Be a Red Hot Shakespearean Love (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Joseph Papp Public Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/August Wilson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7DB173BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Surprised 'Wild Party'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jesse McKinley</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Stage and Off column; unexpectedly strong showing of Public Theater's production of The Wild Party in Tony nominations encourages producers to run at least through awards ceremony; Cats extends run in response to renewed ticket demand; Daniel Davis reacts to winning Tony nomination for short-lived David Hirson play Wrong Mountain, which closed in February; photo; revival of August Wilson's Jitney extended at Second Stage; Greg Steinbruner, male half of two-person show How to Be a Red Hot Shakespearean Love, proposes to female half, Eve Hartmann (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The unexpectedly strong showing of the Public Theater's production of ''The Wild Party'' in the Tony Award nominations -- the show landed seven -- has apparently lifted the fortunes of that struggling musical enough to persuade its producers to run at least through the Tonys.</p>
        <p>The show, which opened to mixed reviews at the Virginia Theater on April 13, received nominations for best musical, score, book and lighting, as well as for the acting of its three leads: Mandy Patinkin, Toni Collette and Eartha Kitt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The unexpectedly strong showing of the Public Theater's production of ''The Wild Party'' in the Tony Award nominations -- the show landed seven -- has apparently lifted the fortunes of that struggling musical enough to persuade its producers to run at least through the Tonys.</p>
        <p>The show, which opened to mixed reviews at the Virginia Theater on April 13, received nominations for best musical, score, book and lighting, as well as for the acting of its three leads: Mandy Patinkin, Toni Collette and Eartha Kitt.</p>
        <p>And while the nominations provided a much-needed morale lift, they did not provide a huge lift in sales; the show did about $40,000 in business on Tuesday and Wednesday. Still, it has shown stronger sales since its early days -- perhaps because of heavy advertising -- and the producers believe it may be building momentum.</p>
        <p>So now, the producers have decided to stick with the show through the awards on June 4. They hope the national television exposure and some winners generate sales.</p>
        <p>''Things are looking up,'' said Kenneth Lerer, chairman of the Public Theater's board. ''We are moving forward.''</p>
        <p>The decision to keep ''Wild Party'' alive probably means ''Macbeth,'' starring Kelsey Grammer and due on Broadway on June 8, will end up at a Shubert theater. Recent advertisements for that show have been cagey about its eventual home, saying it would play at ''a Jujamcyn theater,'' but it is an open secret that the production has been eyeing the Virginia. But with ''The Wild Party'' staying open, Jujamcyn doesn't appear to have a theater available.</p>
        <p>''Macbeth'' producers aren't commenting on their plans, but because of advertising deadlines and technical questions, they will soon need to know where they're playing. The closing of ''Amadeus'' on Sunday means the Music Box, owned by the Shubert Organization, would be available. The production has been designed for the Virginia but could fit in the smaller Music Box. The production could be lucrative for the Shuberts; it has sold well in its pre-Broadway run in Boston, and Mr. Grammer is expected to be a major draw in New York, too.</p>
        <p>Rocco Landesman, the president of Jujamcyn, and Mr. Wolfe have a long working relationship, which has included Mr. Wolfe's productions of ''Angels in America'' and ''Jelly's Last Jam.''</p>
        <p>Box-office figures for ''The Wild Party'' have been at about 50 percent of capacity.</p>
        <p>Besides the small financial bump, the number of nominations is seen by members of the production team as a vindication for a show that has had its share of detractors. Oddly enough, the other ''Wild Party,'' produced by the Manhattan Theater Club, also found a degree of redemption in the 13 nominations it received for Drama Desk awards.</p>
        <p>Another Life for 'Cats'</p>
        <p>You knew it was going happen.</p>
        <p>The producers of ''Cats,'' scheduled to close on June 25, announced yesterday that the show would extend 11 more weeks in response to extraordinary demand for tickets.</p>
        <p>Sales for ''Cats,'' the longest-running musical in Broadway history, have been hot since word came in February that the show, which has played at the Winter Garden Theater since 1982, would finally meow for the last time. The announcement made front pages coast to coast, and the race for tickets was on. Last week ''Cats'' had the sixth highest grosses on Broadway, with sales of $635,639.</p>
        <p>'I'm a What?'</p>
        <p>It was 6:30 a.m., Pacific Daylight Time, on Monday when Daniel Davis's phone rang. He awoke, and some woman started screaming at him manically, telling him that he had just won a Tony, or was a Tony, or could buy a Tony, or something.</p>
        <p>''I didn't even realize what was happening,'' Mr. Davis said. ''I thought, 'Who is this insane woman?' ''</p>
        <p>The woman, it turned out, was a press agent from Boneau/Bryan-Brown, the agency that had handled ''Wrong Mountain,'' the short-lived David Hirson play in which Mr. Davis had played a grandiose theater director. (The play, which was not loved by critics, closed on Feb. 5 after 28 performances.) The press agent was screaming about Mr. Davis's unlikely, but wildly applauded, Tony nomination for best featured performance in a play. It is his first nomination.</p>
        <p>How did Mr. Davis, who is currently between jobs, react to the news?</p>
        <p>''I was just stunned beyond belief,'' he said. ''I ran up about a $2,000 phone bill.''</p>
        <p>Since then, says Mr. Davis, who played Niles the butler on the sitcom ''The Nanny'' for six years, he has had several calls from directors wondering about his availability. He also said the nomination was something of a vindication for a play he felt was unfairly dismissed.</p>
        <p>''It's such a joy because this feels like it comes from other actors and people who do the work,'' he said. ''It just feels so wonderful.''</p>
        <p>Along the Way</p>
        <p>*The critically acclaimed revival of ''Jitney,'' by August Wilson, has been extended until July 16 at Second Stage, and there is talk of a further extension. The play won the New York Drama Critics award for best play this week. Other winners included the musical ''James Joyce's 'The Dead,' '' which opens in Los Angeles in July, and ''Copenhagen,'' named best foreign play.</p>
        <p>*The creators of ''How to Be a Red Hot Shakespearean Lover,'' a lighthearted look at classic romancing techniques, must be on to something. Recently the male half of the two-person cast, Greg Steinbruner, proposed to the female half, Eve Hartmann. The show finishes a run this weekend at the St. Marks Theater, 94 St. Marks Place in the East Village; a wedding is planned for next year.</p>
        <p>* Bronson Pinchot, Keith David and Randy Danson head the cast of Shakespeare's ''Winter's Tale,'' beginning at the Delacorte Theater in Central Park on June 21.</p>
        <p>*''Enter the Guardsman,'' now in previews at the Vineyard Theater, has pushed its opening from May 18 to May 21. The reason? ''The Laramie Project,'' Moises Kaufman's docudrama, is scheduled to open on May 18 at the Union Square Theater, around the corner from the Vineyard.</p>
        <p>ON STAGE AND OFF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
