<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Third-Ranked Auction House Dips Toe Into Competitive Water</title>
    <meta content="12AUCT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198915"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Phillips (Auction House)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Foundation for Aids Research</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stone, Sharon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6DA143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Third-Ranked Auction House Dips Toe Into Competitive Water</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phillips, world's third-largest auction house, holds its first big evening auction, American Craft Museum; auction is not only Phillips's first time selling multimillion-dollar Impressionist and modern art in a big evening sale, but also its first sale since LVMH Moet Hennessy Louis Vuitton bought company in October; about 40 percent of works go unsold; auction starts with announcement that 3 percent of hammer prices would go to American Foundation for AIDS Research; actress Sharon Stone, charity's campaign chairwoman, tries to stir up interest in auction (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the main gallery of the American Craft Museum, an airless space with room for just 300 seats, the art world waited to see how the first major evening auction by Phillips, the world's third-largest auction house, would fare. And waited. And waited.</p>
        <p>The auction began nearly an hour late, and then it started with an announcement that 3 percent of the hammer prices would go to the American Foundation for AIDS Research. Dressed in a bright orange dress with matching lipstick, the movie star Sharon Stone, campaign chairwoman for the charity, made a speech about AIDS. Throughout the evening, she wandered up and down the aisles trying to drum up excitement in the otherwise dead room.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the main gallery of the American Craft Museum, an airless space with room for just 300 seats, the art world waited to see how the first major evening auction by Phillips, the world's third-largest auction house, would fare. And waited. And waited.</p>
        <p>The auction began nearly an hour late, and then it started with an announcement that 3 percent of the hammer prices would go to the American Foundation for AIDS Research. Dressed in a bright orange dress with matching lipstick, the movie star Sharon Stone, campaign chairwoman for the charity, made a speech about AIDS. Throughout the evening, she wandered up and down the aisles trying to drum up excitement in the otherwise dead room.</p>
        <p>Was this a charity auction or a sale of serious art? several people in the audience asked. It quickly became apparent that even limitless pots of money can't buy a respected place in the art world.</p>
        <p>The auction was not only Phillips's first time selling multimillion-dollar Impressionist and modern art in a big evening sale, but also its first sale since LVMH Moet Hennessy Louis Vuitton bought the company in October. LVMH's chairman, Bernard Arnault, had spent million of dollars trying to make Phillips a major player in an unforgiving art world.</p>
        <p>About 40 percent of the works went unsold. Of the 31 offered, only 18 sold, and of those only 4 were within or above their estimates. The sale totaled $43.9 million. Officials at Phillips said they had raised $1.1 million for the AIDS charity.</p>
        <p>Afterward Mr. Arnault was upbeat about the results. ''It's the largest sale ever for Phillips,'' he said. ''This is a good first step. We are here for the long term, and we will make this work.''</p>
        <p>To compete with Sotheby's and Christie's, LVMH had given sellers financing for 30 of the 31 works offered last night, reportedly an investment of $100 million. In some cases Phillips gave sellers a straight guarantee (an undisclosed minimum price given to the seller regardless of a sale's outcome), an advance, a loan or a combination of the three. Often, experts from competing auction houses said, Mr. Arnault had paid more for the works than their estimates reflected.</p>
        <p>He also spent well over $1 million renting and renovating the American Craft Museum on West 53rd Street, just four blocks from Christie's and across the street from the Museum of Modern Art, for the sale. Phillips's New York headquarters on East 79th Street was too small to accommodate the crowd.</p>
        <p>Ever since the catalog was circulated to collectors last month, the sale had been the talk of the art world. The estimates were too high, experts said. All the negative talk affected the reaction last night. With only a few exceptions, bidding was thin and most often by unidentified telephone bidders.</p>
        <p>The final work in the sale was the most important: Malevich's ''Suprematist Composition,'' an austere abstract painting that hung in the Museum of Modern Art until recently. Before the sale, the painting was placed on an easel in the front of the room shrouded by a black velvet cloth, which Ms. Stone dramatically unveiled when the bidding began. But even that didn't generate excitement. Only two telephone bidders went for the painting, which sold for $17 million. Phillips had refused to estimate the selling price, but LVMH had reportedly bought it for $15 million.</p>
        <p>Malevich's 31 heirs won a claim to have the painting, which had been smuggled out of the Soviet Union in the 1930's, returned last year, and they consigned it to Phillips to sell. While the auction house says the painting dates from 1919, curators at the museum say it was painted later, from 1923 to 1925. The difference in dating is important, experts say: if it was made in 1919, it is far more valuable.</p>
        <p>The other 30 works in the sale were a mixed bag, dominated by a group of paintings that an unidentified Japanese collector bought for high prices during the 1980's art market boom. The Wildenstein Gallery represented the Japanese seller. Both Sotheby's and Christie's made a play for the works, but no one was willing to pay the $27 million that Phillips reportedly spent. The group included works by Monet, Cezanne and Pissarro. One of the few populuar works last night, part of the collection from Japan, was Sisley's ''Garden at Louveciennes (Path to l'Etarche),'' a lush landscape from 1873. It finally sold to an unidentified telephone bidder for $3.5 million, double its high estimate of $1.5 million.</p>
        <p>But a majority of works that sold went for far less than Phillips had estimated. Cezanne's ''View of Gardanne,'' a landscape from 1886-90, was expected to bring $6 million to $8 million. Only one bidder wanted it, and it sold for $5 million.</p>
        <p>(Final prices include Phillips's commission, 15 percent of the first $50,000 and 10 percent of the rest. Estimates do not reflect commissions.)</p>
        <p>After the sale, dealers and collectors milled outside the museum, gossiping about the evening's outcome. ''I felt sorry for them, but it was the worst combination,'' said Alexander Apsis, a partner of C&amp;M Arts, a Manhattan gallery. ''When you have not-great paintings and estimates that are too high, you can't help but get killed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
