<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sierra Leone Rebels Halted Near Capital but Active Elsewhere</title>
    <meta content="Y12LEON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Freetown (Sierra Leone)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Waterloo (Sierra Leone)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onishi, Norimitsu</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E3DA173BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sierra Leone Rebels Halted Near Capital but Active Elsewhere</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onishi, Norimitsu</byline>
      <dateline>FREETOWN, Sierra Leone, May 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Forces loyal to government of Sierra Leone appear to push back rebels attacking capital of Freetown, but fighting intensifies and spreads to other areas; coalition of United Nations peacekeepers, Sierra Leone soldiers and militia known as Kamajors secures road leading to Waterloo, 18 miles from Freetown, but heavy fighting breaks out east of there; in Freetown, pro-government forces tighten security, mindful that infiltrators played critical role last year in rebel attacks that nearly overran capital; photo of refugees fleeing Freetown; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forces loyal to the government appeared to push back rebels attacking the capital today but fighting intensified and spread to other areas.</p>
        <p>A coalition of United Nations peacekeepers, Sierra Leone soldiers and a militia known as Kamajors secured the road leading to Waterloo, about 18 miles southeast of Freetown, but heavy fighting broke out about 10 miles east of Waterloo, said David Wimhurst, the spokesman of the United Nations force.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Forces loyal to the government appeared to push back rebels attacking the capital today but fighting intensified and spread to other areas.</p>
        <p>A coalition of United Nations peacekeepers, Sierra Leone soldiers and a militia known as Kamajors secured the road leading to Waterloo, about 18 miles southeast of Freetown, but heavy fighting broke out about 10 miles east of Waterloo, said David Wimhurst, the spokesman of the United Nations force.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, fighting around Waterloo drove thousands of civilians to gather at Jui Junction, 10 miles from Freetown, as they fled toward the capital. Today, many left Jui Junction for their homes.</p>
        <p>In the capital, pro-government forces tightened security, mindful that infiltrators played a critical role last year in rebel attacks that nearly overran Freetown.</p>
        <p>British paratroopers limited access to the western part of the city, the site of the United Nations headquarters, even setting up barbed wire along the beach.</p>
        <p>United Nations peacekeepers operated checkpoints alongside Sierra Leone soldiers, militiamen and rifle-toting men of unknown affiliation who were dressed mostly in T-shirts and flip-flops.</p>
        <p>''Every minute that goes by strengthens our resolve to bring lasting peace in this country,'' said Prince Nicol, the spokesman for Lt. Col. Johnny Paul Koroma. In alliances that have shifted rapidly since last week, Colonel Koroma is now supporting the government against his former ally, Foday Sankoh, the leader of the Revolutionary United Front. Colonel Koroma led a short-lived junta that toppled President Ahmed Tejan Kabbah in 1997; Mr. Kabbah is now president again.</p>
        <p>Shadowing today's fighting was the continuing search by the United Nations for 500 peacekeepers whose capture by the rebels set off the newest crisis.</p>
        <p>The whereabouts of Mr. Sankoh are still unclear, Mr. Wimhurst said. But talks with the Revolutionary United Front are being held through intermediaries, including President Charles Taylor of Liberia, a former guerrilla who has long supported Mr. Sankoh.</p>
        <p>Securing Freetown has become the priority of the United Nations force. But thousands of peacekeepers remain deployed across the country, some in rebel territory.</p>
        <p>In Makeni, in the center of the country, hundreds of Kenyan peacekeepers who had been surrounded by rebels broke through the cordon and made it to friendly territory. But six were wounded, three seriously, when they came under fire by Sierra Leone soldiers who mistook them for rebels disguised in United Nations uniforms.</p>
        <p>Some rebels have apparently begun wearing uniforms that they stripped from the 500 United Nations hostages. Others have been using the hostages' equipment, including 13 armored cars belonging to Zambian troops. In Port Loko, about 65 miles from Freetown, United Nations peacekeepers were attacked overnight by rebels using armored cars, Mr. Wimhurst said. No casualties were reported.</p>
        <p>The heaviest battles broke out east of Waterloo, despite the heavy presence of Jordanian and Nigerian peacekeepers, and three Land Rovers filled with elite SAS British troops were seen heading east of Waterloo. The 850 British soldiers in Sierra Leone, who came to evacuate European citizens, have been under intense pressure to play a more active role in peacekeeping.</p>
        <p>The 8,700 peacekeepers here include Nigerians, Indians, Kenyans, Jordanians, Zambians, Guineans and Ghanaians.</p>
        <p>The Sierra Leone Army, which is said to number 5,000, was far larger before the junta took power in 1997. At the time most soldiers reportedly sided with Colonel Koroma against the government. In the anarchy of Sierra Leone, many who were soldiers during the day became rebels at night, and came to be known as sobels.</p>
        <p>According to the peace accord that briefly halted the earlier battles, rebellious soldiers fit to be rehabilitated were to be reintegrated into a new government army. But in the desperation that gripped the government in recent days, the government effectively permitted Colonel Koroma to rally his men against Mr. Sankoh's group without any pretence of official rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>''The government has not stopped them from doing what they are doing,'' Septimus Kaikai, President Kabbah's spokesman, said in an interview today.</p>
        <p>The Revolutionary United Front and the Kamajor militia, which is made up of traditional hunters who often provide security in West Africa, are each thought to total more than 15,000 members.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
