<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dismal Dandy Surrounded by Dull Chatterers</title>
    <meta content="12REUN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Shakespeare Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Noble, Adrian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eliot, Thomas Stearns (1888-1965)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boxer, Sarah</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Family Reunion, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2DC173BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dismal Dandy Surrounded by Dull Chatterers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH BOXER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boxer, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sarah Boxer reviews Royal Shakespeare Company's revival of T S Eliot's 1939 play The Family Reunion, directed by Adrian Noble; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>T. S. Eliot scorned his 1939 play ''The Family Reunion'' 11 years after he wrote it. He found Harry, Lord Monchensey, the tortured man at its center, an ''insufferable prig.'' And who can blame him?</p>
        <p>Here is a prodigal son who comes home to the family estate, Wishwood, after eight years' absence, to celebrate his dying mother's birthday. His gift is to tell all her assembled guests -- his aunts and uncles -- that his poor departed wife, whom they think drowned when she fell drunkenly or suicidally over the rails of an ocean liner, was actually pushed, by him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>T. S. Eliot scorned his 1939 play ''The Family Reunion'' 11 years after he wrote it. He found Harry, Lord Monchensey, the tortured man at its center, an ''insufferable prig.'' And who can blame him?</p>
        <p>Here is a prodigal son who comes home to the family estate, Wishwood, after eight years' absence, to celebrate his dying mother's birthday. His gift is to tell all her assembled guests -- his aunts and uncles -- that his poor departed wife, whom they think drowned when she fell drunkenly or suicidally over the rails of an ocean liner, was actually pushed, by him.</p>
        <p>''You would never imagine anyone could sink so quickly,'' he says. To make matters worse, he is being hunted (or thinks he is) by avenging furies. So he has no time to think about anybody but himself. He is on the lam, morally speaking.</p>
        <p>Some think that Eliot came to hate his own bizarre blend of Greek tragedy and English drawing-room comedy because the prig is a thinly veiled T. S. Eliot, and because the poor, drowned woman is a stand-in for Eliot's hysterical, paranoid wife, Vivien, whom he left in 1932 and who was committed to a mental institution four years later, where she died in 1947. If the play is Eliot's attempt to expiate his sin, it is no wonder he later renounced it. But should we?</p>
        <p>In the Royal Shakespeare Company's cool, clean production at the Brooklyn Academy of Music, directed by Adrian Noble, Harry (Greg Hicks) inhabits his own priggishness  so completely that you have to wonder whether the company has assumed Eliot's critical stance and distanced itself from the self-absorbed heart of the play.</p>
        <p>Harry's brooding has an air of dandyism. He strikes poses with his cigarette like a model and talks in the halting cadences of Captain Kirk in ''Star Trek'': ''You do not know what hope is until you have lost it.'' Thank goodness for his plain-spoken aunts and uncles, who can't, and don't want to, understand their cold, rude and fancy nephew. Invariably, they walk in and snuff out his miserable ruminations with some insipid remarks.</p>
        <p>Has the Royal Shakespeare Company discovered that Eliot is much better at depicting dimwittedness than deep torment? Did this company find an Eliot who could parody the selfish excesses of his own guilty soul?</p>
        <p>The production, which is in New York for four days, is as cold and remote as it could be. The actors rarely look at one another, and when they do it seems unnatural. The play opens with ocean sounds and wind. At the back of the stage is a long vertical slab of reflective glass that appears to be a giant digital clock with rows of unreadable red dots. It ticks. Before the arrival of Harry, all the actors have their backs turned to face it, as if they were waiting not so much for Harry as for time itself. The first words of the play, which come from the imperious mouth of Harry's mother -- ''Not yet!'' -- stop the ticking. Is she shouting at the servant or at time itself?</p>
        <p>This play is certainly about time. The domineering mother, Amy, played with icy restraint by Margaret Tyzack, wants Harry to take over her estate before she dies. She is keenly aware of time running out. The aunts and uncles constantly chatter to forget time passing. Aunt Ivy (Cherry Morris) fantasizes about going south. The homey Aunt Violet (Bridget Turner) is against going south. Thick Uncle Gerald (Nicholas Jones) wants to go east. Cozy Uncle Charles (Christopher Good) says he'd rather stay and have a few drinks at his club. To these aunts and uncles, as mindless as the four winds, Amy promises, ''Death will come to you as a mild surprise.'' They are simple folk. When Harry arrives, they are, of course, looking in the wrong direction.</p>
        <p>''The Family Reunion'' revolves not around the mindless chatterers, though, but around the watchers and waiters, those intense souls who see the past in the future and the future in the past. These seers -- Harry's cousin Mary (Zoe Waites), Harry's Aunt Agatha (Lynn Farleigh) and Harry himself -- are all timeless creatures. Mary says, ''I don't belong to any generation.'' Agatha is ''liberated from the human wheel.'' And Harry says things like ''Time and time and time, and change, no change!'' They are the only ones who can see the furies, the black-clad, white-faced, white-gloved creatures who climb up the vertical, temporal slab as if they were geckos.</p>
        <p>But the seers in this production are frightfully earnest schoolmarms and prigs. Surprisingly, the most appealing voices here are the dimwitted aunts and uncles who double as a Greek chorus. When Harry's Cassandra of an aunt, Agatha, drones on about ''the loop in time'' and ''the specters,'' it's good to hear dear Uncle Charles pipe up, ''This isn't cheerful.''</p>
        <p>Usually, the silly chatterers are busy with their daily repressions -- they talk of the weather, the news, the driving habits of their nephews -- but occasionally they huddle together and utter their fears: ''We do not like to look out of the same window, and see quite a different landscape. We do not like to climb a stair, and find that it takes us down.'' Dispersed, they are the four gentle winds whispering cozily. Together, they are a cold dread wind.</p>
        <p>At the end of the play, the aunts and uncles are still confused about the trouble with Harry. But the audience learns the truth, or part of it.  Agatha tells Harry that before he was born his father tried to murder his mother. Agatha saved the unborn child by ordering the father to leave the house. When Harry discovers the crime at the core of the house of Monchensey, the vengeful furies that have haunted him turn into gentle Eumenides, kindly spirits, who lead him away from his hell house. His mother dies. And that's that.</p>
        <p>The play is, for Eliot, surprisingly Freudian. When Harry asks Agatha the Oedipal question, ''Who were my parents?,'' her flip reply, ''Your father and your mother,'' is funny for what it leaves out. When Harry tells his mother, ''I shall make you lie down,'' it is solicitous, sexual and murderous at the same time. When the aunt tells Harry, ''You are the consciousness of your unhappy family,'' she seems to pacify him with the Freudian balm, the idea that not all guilt is deserved.</p>
        <p>In the end, it's unclear whether Harry pushed his wife overboard or whether he was just suffering from a wish fulfilled. It doesn't matter. The birthday candles have been blown out and the chairs have scattered.</p>
        <p>THE FAMILY REUNION</p>
        <p>By T. S. Eliot; directed by Adrian Noble; sets by Rob Howell; lighting by Mark Henderson; sound by Matt McKenzie for Autograph; tour re-creation, Richard Power; assistant director, Helen Raynor; company voice work, Andrew Wade, Cicely Berry and Lyn Darnley; production manager, Patrick Frazer; costume supervisor, Lynette Mauro; company stage manager, Eric Lumsden. The Royal Shakespeare Company presented by the Brooklyn Academy of Music, Bruce C. Ratner, chairman of the board; Karen Brooks Hopkins, president; Joseph V. Melillo, executive producer. At the Harvey Theater, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>WITH: Margaret Tyzack (Amy), Greg Hicks (Harry), Lynn Farleigh (Agatha), Cherry Morris (Ivy), Bridget Turner (Violet), Christopher Good (Charles), Nicholas Jones (Gerald), Zoe Waites (Mary), Alison Reid (Denman), Derek Hutchinson (Downing), Richard Cordery (Dr. Warburton), Rod Arthur (Sergeant Winchell) and James Auden, Mary Duddy, Susan Dury, Graeme Eton and Jennifer McEvoy (Eumenides).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
