<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pace of 'Sleeping Beauty' Is Anything But Sleepy</title>
    <meta content="12BEAU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martins, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tracey, Margaret</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hubbe, Nikolaj</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7DD173BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pace of 'Sleeping Beauty' Is Anything But Sleepy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews New York City Ballet's performance of Sleeping Beauty as staged by Peter Martins; photo of Margaret Tracey and Nikolaj Hubbe (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Ballet's ''Sleeping Beauty'' returned in all its streamlined splendor to the New York State Theater on Wednesday night. And the company is offering performances of this great 19th-century classic, with various changes of cast, through May 21.</p>
        <p>Peter Martins's staging retains much of the traditional choreography by Marius Petipa. There is also additional new choreography by Mr. Martins. But what makes this production unusual is its pace. Mr. Martins has trimmed a few scenes, there is only one intermission, and the pauses between dance numbers within an act are extremely brief. As a result the action speeds by. Therefore it was appropriate that Hugo Fiorato, the evening's conductor, made Tchaikovsky's score seem to surge forward with great excitement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York City Ballet's ''Sleeping Beauty'' returned in all its streamlined splendor to the New York State Theater on Wednesday night. And the company is offering performances of this great 19th-century classic, with various changes of cast, through May 21.</p>
        <p>Peter Martins's staging retains much of the traditional choreography by Marius Petipa. There is also additional new choreography by Mr. Martins. But what makes this production unusual is its pace. Mr. Martins has trimmed a few scenes, there is only one intermission, and the pauses between dance numbers within an act are extremely brief. As a result the action speeds by. Therefore it was appropriate that Hugo Fiorato, the evening's conductor, made Tchaikovsky's score seem to surge forward with great excitement.</p>
        <p>Although the company does have dramatic ballets in its repertory, it is best known for its plotless pieces. Curiously enough, Mr. Martins's ''Beauty,'' though crammed with dances, is also highly dramatic, for with only one great interruption in the action the story line becomes extremely taut. And a fairy tale atmosphere is created by David Mitchell's scenery, which includes some magical projections to indicate the passage of time.</p>
        <p>Over the years Margaret Tracey has gradually been gaining authority in the role of Princess Aurora, the ballet's heroine. She made an eager entrance in her birthday-party scene, then seemed radiant as she sustained the difficult balances in the Rose Adagio. She was fleet in the Vision scene and, with Nikolaj Hubbe as her Prince Desire, she danced the final pas de deux with unruffled dignity. Looking always courteous, sensitive and caring, Mr. Hubbe was an admirable storybook hero.</p>
        <p>Making her debut as the Lilac Fairy, Maria Kowroski danced serenely. But since this character is the personification of goodness, her movements could have been more grandly scaled. In contrast Merrill Ashley was imposing as Carabosse, the evil fairy, moving through the ballet with cold implacable fury.</p>
        <p>Yvonne Borree and Benjamin Millepied danced a lucid Bluebird pas de deux, yet some of their steps could have been more buoyant. This bubbly, carefree duet became unduly careful.</p>
        <p>There were debuts in several solo roles. In the wedding scene variations for jewels and precious metals, Robert Tewsley, a guest artist from the Stuttgart Ballet, looked at ease as Gold, while Jennie Somogyi, as Diamond, made all her movements crystalline. In the christening scene, Carrie Lee Riggins was a playful Fairy of Vivacity, and Amanda Edge fluttered charmingly as the Fairy of Eloquence. As King Florestan, the ruler of this fairy-tale kingdom, Robert Lyon was obviously a benevolent monarch.</p>
        <p>Soloists returning to roles they had danced on other occasions and giving capable performances in them included Rachel Rutherford, Jennifer Tinsley and Michele Gifford, as fairies at the christening, and Kathleen Tracey and Samantha Allen, as jewels.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
