<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Objective Conciliator at Complaint Board</title>
    <meta content="12PROF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Frank Wohl</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Civilian Complaint Review Board (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wohl, Frank H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2D6173BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Objective Conciliator at Complaint Board</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Frank Wohl, chairman of beleaguered New York City Civilian Complaint Review Board, which investigates accusations of police misconduct and sends disciplinary recommendations to Police Department; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SURVIVAL in the city's most thankless public service job might well require an extreme New Yorker: sally forth in that leather hide, brandish that sword! For how else to stave off Norman Siegel of the New York Civil Liberties Union, who calls your agency weak, and Police Commissioner Howard Safir, who says it's too aggressive?</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, you're just trying to hack away at the dense public skepticism about the agency, the Civilian Complaint Review Board, which investigates accusations of police misconduct and sends disciplinary recommendations to the Police Department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SURVIVAL in the city's most thankless public service job might well require an extreme New Yorker: sally forth in that leather hide, brandish that sword! For how else to stave off Norman Siegel of the New York Civil Liberties Union, who calls your agency weak, and Police Commissioner Howard Safir, who says it's too aggressive?</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, you're just trying to hack away at the dense public skepticism about the agency, the Civilian Complaint Review Board, which investigates accusations of police misconduct and sends disciplinary recommendations to the Police Department.</p>
        <p>And so to Frank H. Wohl,  chairman of the beleaguered complaint board, whose manner couldn't be less like a New Yorker's. A courteous, scholarly gentleman whose Midtown law office at Lankler, Siffert &amp; Wohl is decorated with faded 19th-century Western railroad photographs, Mr. Wohl, who hails from Ogden, Utah, is a lapsed Mormon whose notion of rebelliousness is to drink caffeinated coffee.</p>
        <p>During a leisurely visit, he is restrained, occasionally halting in a kindly way (colleagues compare him to Jimmy Stewart, Gary Cooper, Dudley Do-Right), but not dull.</p>
        <p>He speaks of the intellectual allure of the law, a response atypical of most litigators (he's a $500-an-hour man, specializing in white-collar criminal defense, commercial lawsuits and legal ethics) and his love of Shakespeare (''my favorite is 'King Lear' -- I guess because he's a father with daughters and he's an old guy,'' says Mr. Wohl, who has two daughters, is married to their mother, Lisa, a writer, and is an old guy of 57). He also talks about the photographs he took of an Indian cobra milker, travels in Iran and Afghanistan and experiences as a Navy lawyer in Vietnam, memories of which bring fresh, startled tears to a man who, years later, was tough enough for a federal judge to appoint him to clean up the mob-ruled Fulton Fish Market.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wohl has bobbled into the news, however reluctantly, because staff members have prepared a draft of a report that is believed to criticize the police's stop-and-frisk documentation. And in response to Commissioner Safir and city lawyers who said the board should stop recommending discipline for officers who lie, Mr. Wohl voted with his board to continue referring such cases to the Police Department and also to local and federal prosecutors.</p>
        <p>Dudley rules!</p>
        <p>Since taking on the unpaid role of chairman in August 1998, Mr. Wohl says, ''My first priority has been to improve the credibility of the board.'' That's an almost laughingly daunting goal. The agency has had four chairmen in the seven years since it became independent of the police, over the objections of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>Mr. Siegel and others have scorched it for the molasses-slow pace at which its 115 investigators cull through 5,000 complaints a year. Its effectiveness has always been questionable: the Police Department used to re-investigate board cases, dismissing many. Mr. Safir did allow that during Mr. Wohl's tenure the quality of board investigations had improved, vitiating the need for additional Police Department investigation.</p>
        <p>And with the mayor and the police commissioner together appointing 8  of 13 seats on the board, its objectivity has also been challenged.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wohl is a mayoral appointee. Before going into private practice, he  spent seven years as an assistant United States attorney for the Southern District of New York, the federal prosecutor's office that during the  Giuliani administration became a veritable feeder school to City Hall.</p>
        <p>MINDFUL that he is shadowed by that association, Mr. Wohl, who as a federal prosecutor rose to deputy chief of the criminal division and then chief of the civil division, says he knew Mr. Giuliani only casually during those years, although he formed friendships with Giuliani aides during that era. He says he has assiduously avoided speaking with the mayor since becoming board chairman.</p>
        <p>In fact, while opinions of Mr. Wohl's effectiveness are in some respects mixed, with critics saying he lacks the strident forcefulness the role demands and fans placing greater value on his meticulousness, long hours of dedication and tone of quiet diplomacy, rarely is there dispute about his objectivity.</p>
        <p>Indeed, an embrace of neutrality courses through Mr. Wohl's conversation: in what he learned to value as a law student at the University of Chicago, and in a career during which he has been prosecutor, court-appointed administrator, defense lawyer and now a sort of civilian judge, weighing disputes between the public and the police -- at a time of vitriolic distrust of law enforcement.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the ability to see different perspectives springs from his upbringing: ''My parents were divorced when I was 10,'' says Mr. Wohl, an only child. ''So I grew up with my mother and my grandmother. Maybe I got my male role models from cowboy movies, but I didn't feel you had to be male to be strong. That's just as well since I'm still living in a household with lots of women.''</p>
        <p>His mother taught him the value of getting along with others. ''It's important for our board and the Police Department to have a relationship that gets past disagreements, to see if we can get to our common objectives,'' Mr. Wohl says, in his most un-New Yorker-like fashion.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
