<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Aim to Avoid the Discomforts of Home</title>
    <meta content="12KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E4DC143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Aim to Avoid the Discomforts of Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>PURCHASE, N.Y., May 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Preview of Game 3 of playoff series between New York Knicks and Miami Heat, Madison Square Garden (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One after another, a stream of undaunted players in road uniforms have filed through the doors at Madison Square Garden to take part in the open audition for scene stealer.</p>
        <p>It has become a plum playoff part in recent years. In 1998, Indiana's Reggie Miller took his mark on the left wing, just a short dribble from Spike Lee, and pulled a 3-pointer out of his black hat in the final seconds of Game 4 to devastate the Knicks in the Eastern Conference semifinals. In 1997, the Heat's Tim Hardaway ruined the drama of the Knicks' ''Nine Men, One Mission,'' theme when he poured two fourth-quarter 3-pointers over the spirits of a raucous crowd in Game 6 of the second-round series.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One after another, a stream of undaunted players in road uniforms have filed through the doors at Madison Square Garden to take part in the open audition for scene stealer.</p>
        <p>It has become a plum playoff part in recent years. In 1998, Indiana's Reggie Miller took his mark on the left wing, just a short dribble from Spike Lee, and pulled a 3-pointer out of his black hat in the final seconds of Game 4 to devastate the Knicks in the Eastern Conference semifinals. In 1997, the Heat's Tim Hardaway ruined the drama of the Knicks' ''Nine Men, One Mission,'' theme when he poured two fourth-quarter 3-pointers over the spirits of a raucous crowd in Game 6 of the second-round series.</p>
        <p>Too often, playoff opponents have traveled to the Garden, hooked themselves up to the hostility like an I.V. drip and lived for another day. Last year, when the Knicks went on their trip fantastic to the finals, their 6-4 road record was identical to their 6-4 home record. And it took a 4-point play by Larry Johnson to put his team over that .500 mark.</p>
        <p>In the Knicks' three previous playoff brushes with the Heat, Coach Pat Riley's team has bounced back from splitting games in Miami by taking one of their next two games in New York. On Friday night, the Heat will try to turn the Knicks' home into their own castle once again when the two teams play Game 3 in a four-of-seven-game, second-round series that is even at one game apiece.</p>
        <p>''We're excited about getting back here, but just because we're home, it doesn't guarantee a win,'' Latrell Sprewell said today after the Knicks' practiced. ''The Garden is special. But the Heat have been here before, and they understand what they are getting into.''</p>
        <p>It can also be inspirational. In the past, Miller has reveled in his villainous role. And although they aren't as theatrical, Hardaway and Mourning have lifted their games at the Garden as well.</p>
        <p>''We're going in there prepared,'' Riley said today. ''And we're going in there to win. That's the only way we're looking at it.</p>
        <p>''We know they feel good about having the edge. But there will be moments in the game there when they'll go through the same things we went through Tuesday. And we'll have to take advantage of it like they took advantage of us.''</p>
        <p>In Game 2, the Knicks seized upon the Heat's dreadful free-throw shooting; they baited Mourning into shooting jumpers when the short and boxy Johnson guarded him late; and they got away with shooting only 28 percent in the first half.</p>
        <p>As preparation for Game 3, Sprewell, who is shooting an abysmal 24 percent for the series, spent an extra 20 minutes on his jump shot. Across the court, Johnson went one-on-one with Kurt Thomas, who was mimicking Mourning's moves, long after the rest of the Knicks had exited the floor. The Knicks realize they cannot rely on Miami's free-throw malaise to continue, so there was extra work to be done.</p>
        <p>''I thought we took away home-court advantage by winning a game down there, but  they can do the same when they come in here,'' Johnson said. ''It's going to be a critical two games. Big games for them, big games for us. This thing is still up in the air.</p>
        <p>''It depends on the execution, and who's more focused and who goes after the ball. It's a lot of things. Even though we're here at home, home-court advantage doesn't have anything to do with whether you win or lose. It's how you come out and play.''</p>
        <p>There will be adjustments by both teams. But the Knicks' main focus over the last two days has been better ball movement to take the offensive burden off the harassed Allan Houston and Sprewell; crisper decision-making in the final minutes and an intensified effort to keep Mourning out of the paint.</p>
        <p>In a way, it's all six degrees of Johnson. With all the chaos caused by the Heat's attention on Sprewell and Houston, Johnson has been the model of efficiency in the series. He is 8 of 16 from the field, has just one turnover and is often responsible for swift ball movement when he is doubled in the post. More than Sprewell, Houston and Patrick Ewing, Johnson's overall performance could allow the Knicks' to maintain their home-court advantage for once.</p>
        <p>''When Larry has the ball, he's solid,'' the Knicks' assistant coach, Don Chaney, said today. ''Everyone on the floor knows that when Larry has the ball, we're going to get a shot or something positive will happen. I can't say the same thing for everyone else in crunch time. Sometimes, you lose the ball. And Patrick, Sprewell and Allan are known for that. They've done it from time to time. You know Larry will make a good decision in crunch time.''</p>
        <p>Down the stretch in Game 2, Johnson also had a major impact on Mourning's low production in the fourth quarter. Using his low center of gravity, Johnson forced Mourning out of the paint. Seeing an opponent 4 inches shorter, Mourning couldn't resist shooting his jumper and finished only 5 of 18.</p>
        <p>''I can't contest a 6-foot-10 guy; I mean I can jump but I'm not going to block the shot,'' Johnson said. ''I can't let him catch it where he wants it. If he turns and shoots, I can't really do anything about that, but I can make it difficult by keeping him outside.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks can make it easy on themselves by taking care of the home games.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of mystique at the Garden,'' Marcus Camby said. ''But teams have shown they can come in here and win in the playoffs. They get fired up to play here. I know I used to. We can't let it slip away. We have to use the crowd to our advantage and we can't get sidetracked.''  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
