<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Senator Will Challenge Congressman</title>
    <meta content="12SEAB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seabrook, Lawrence B (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Engel, Eliot L (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3DE143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Senator Will Challenge Congressman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Senator Larry B Seabrook announces that he would challenge US Repr Eliot L Engel, who represents parts of Bronx and Westchester County, for Democratic nomination for that seat in Congress; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State Senator Larry B. Seabrook announced yesterday that he would challenge United States Representative Eliot L. Engel, who represents parts of the Bronx and Westchester County, for the Democratic nomination for that seat in Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seabrook, whose State Senate district includes many of the neighborhoods in the 17th Congressional District, announced his candidacy on the steps of City Hall with nearly 200 supporters standing behind him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State Senator Larry B. Seabrook announced yesterday that he would challenge United States Representative Eliot L. Engel, who represents parts of the Bronx and Westchester County, for the Democratic nomination for that seat in Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seabrook, whose State Senate district includes many of the neighborhoods in the 17th Congressional District, announced his candidacy on the steps of City Hall with nearly 200 supporters standing behind him.</p>
        <p>''Our community needs real leadership on the pressing, urgent issues of education and job training and affordable housing and affordable health care,'' Mr. Seabrook said. ''The incumbent believes himself to be associated with our community. I think a representative should be a part of a community. But he is not.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seabrook, 48, made clear what he would emphasize in the campaign: He repeatedly suggested that Mr. Engel's decision to live in a Maryland suburb of Washington instead of in the district has kept him out of touch with the concerns of Bronx and Westchester County residents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seabrook has long said he would run against Mr. Engel, but his candidacy was far from a forgone conclusion among Bronx politicians. He has twice before talked about running for Congress against Mr. Engel, only to decide against it. At his side yesterday was City Councilman Lawrence A. Warden, who is a longtime ally who intends to run for the State Senate seat that Mr. Seabrook must give up to run for Congress.</p>
        <p>Unseating an incumbent is a difficult business, particularly in the Bronx. And Mr. Seabrook is not likely to get much assistance in his quest from the borough's Democratic Party chairman, Assemblyman Roberto Ramirez. Mr. Ramirez has long made clear his commitment to re-electing incumbent Democrats and is said by party officials to view Mr. Seabrook's candidacy as a major annoyance.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Engel, 53, has already raised about $200,000 and is expected to raise much more. In contrast, Mr. Seabrook said yesterday that he had raised about $150,000. But the shifting demographics of the district, whose population is largely and increasingly black and Hispanic, will factor into the race.  Mr. Seabrook is black; Mr. Engel is white.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
