<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heady Throw by Ventura Protects Leiter's Victory</title>
    <meta content="12METS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Pirates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Pittsburgh Pirates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2DB143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heady Throw by Ventura Protects Leiter's Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>PITTSBURGH, May 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Pittsburgh Pirates, 3-2, Three Rivers Stadium, Pittsburgh; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Leiter bounced off the mound, a bundle of energy and nerves, as Bruce Aven's soft chopper floated toward third base. If the Pittsburgh Pirates were going to tie the game, you could almost hear Leiter saying, it was not going to be on a hit like this.</p>
        <p>There were runners on second and third and two out in the sixth inning when Aven buried his hit into the Three Rivers Stadium artificial turf. Third baseman Robin Ventura was playing back because of the turf, and he charged in but had no chance to make the conventional play, a throw to first.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Leiter bounced off the mound, a bundle of energy and nerves, as Bruce Aven's soft chopper floated toward third base. If the Pittsburgh Pirates were going to tie the game, you could almost hear Leiter saying, it was not going to be on a hit like this.</p>
        <p>There were runners on second and third and two out in the sixth inning when Aven buried his hit into the Three Rivers Stadium artificial turf. Third baseman Robin Ventura was playing back because of the turf, and he charged in but had no chance to make the conventional play, a throw to first.</p>
        <p>''Not only did I jam him, but the spin was funny,'' Leiter said. ''It looked like it was going to go foul, but it didn't. Robin didn't panic and he made the right choice.''</p>
        <p>Ventura's choice was to make the shortest throw, to home, where catcher Mike Piazza tagged out Wil Cordero, who was running on contact. The Mets' infield defense has been unsteady at times, but that was a heady play, and Leiter knew it -- he pointed his glove at Ventura, and hugged him after bounding into the dugout.</p>
        <p>''Al hugs a lot,'' Ventura said, dryly. ''It was a warm embrace.''</p>
        <p>The lead was safe, and Leiter protected it the rest of the way in a 3-2 Mets victory that concluded the club's longest road trip in five years. The Mets won only 5 of the 13 games on their four-city trip, and will return home with a 19-17 record.</p>
        <p>The Mets have won all seven games started by Leiter, who improved to 4-0 and lowered his earned run average to 3.40. He says he has been throwing just enough curveballs and changeups to offset his best pitch, the slider, and his confidence is much higher than it was when he struggled early last year.</p>
        <p>''As frustrating as it gets, sometimes you downright dislike the game because of how frustrating it can be,'' Leiter said. ''It's still fun, and I try to think of it as fun.''</p>
        <p>The second inning was no fun for Leiter, but it was fascinating to watch.</p>
        <p>Kevin Young reached on an infield single leading off the second, and Cordero followed with a bloop single. Then Pat Meares popped up, and the Mets' infielders let the ball drop. The runners held their bases, and Edgardo Alfonzo touched second to force Cordero, and then tagged Young, who was holding the base. But Young was safe. Alfonzo said the umpire told him he would have had a double play if he had tagged Young first, then touched the base.</p>
        <p>It was not the only unusual play that inning. Young and Meares tried a double steal, but Leiter picked it up, firing to Ventura. The Pirates survived when Todd Zeile's throw hit Young in the back during a rundown. Luis Sojo's single scored Young.</p>
        <p>Leiter's counterpart was the rookie Jimmy Anderson, who threw eight scoreless innings in a 2-0 victory over the Mets last month. After that game, some Mets grumbled that the 24-year-old left-hander would not be able to duplicate the performance the next time.</p>
        <p>Before tonight's game, they told one another not to try to pull Anderson's fastball, which has late movement away from right-handers. The Mets had only one hit to the opposite field when Anderson beat them; this time, they repeatedly took him the opposite way, and their first five hits were by right-handed hitters to right field.</p>
        <p>''This is a game of adjustments, and we made adjustments and started shooting him to right field,'' said right fielder Derek Bell, who doubled in the first and scored the Mets' first run.</p>
        <p>Anderson was wild in the first inning. His first seven pitches were balls, and the Mets applied what they had learned. After Bell's double, Alfonzo flied to right, but Brian Giles missed it and Alfonzo took two bases as Bell scored. A two-out single by Zeile -- again to right field -- brought in Alfonzo and gave the Mets a 2-0 lead.</p>
        <p>Anderson allowed only one more run, on an opposite-field homer by Zeile, but that was all Leiter needed to give the Mets their second victory in three days.</p>
        <p>''It certainly doesn't make everything that's happened on this road trip disappear,'' Zeile said, ''but it helps us have more momentum than we had coming in.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>REY ORDONEZ is expected to miss three to seven games with inflammation in his right shoulder. ''Yesterday I said, 'Please, no ground balls to me,' '' said Ordonez, who will meet with the Mets' team doctor, DAVID ALTCHEK, on Friday. The Mets are not planning a magnetic resonance imaging test. . . . The Mets considered promoting GRANT ROBERTS to start on Saturday, but when he experienced stiffness in his pitching shoulder after his last start at Class AAA Norfolk, the Mets dropped him from their plans. Roberts is healthy enough to make his next Norfolk start, but BILL PULSIPHER or PAT MAHOMES will start on Saturday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
