<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women in Military Say Silence On Harassment Protects Careers</title>
    <meta content="12HARA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Becker, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Claudia J (Lt Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DB143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women in Military Say Silence On Harassment Protects Careers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH BECKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Becker, Elizabeth</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Women in military say they are reluctant to file sexual harassment complaints, because they fear opening their personal lives to examination and being blamed for inviting sexual advance; 13 of 16 female senior officers interviewed say that they have been target of single instance of sexual harassment in military and that to protect their careers they never reported it; they marvel that Lt Gen Claudia J Kennedy, so close to retirement, would have subjected herself to backlash and tarnished reputation that would inevitably come from making sexual harassment charge; they predict that instead of being remembered for her formidable accomplishments in Army, she will be remembered as woman with sex complaint (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Out of the blue, when they were cooling down after their regular morning jog, a colonel was groped by her male running partner, another colonel who forcefully tried to embrace her, she said.</p>
        <p>''We were back at my house and he just sort of pushed himself on me,'' the woman said. ''I pushed him back and said 'no' and that was it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Out of the blue, when they were cooling down after their regular morning jog, a colonel was groped by her male running partner, another colonel who forcefully tried to embrace her, she said.</p>
        <p>''We were back at my house and he just sort of pushed himself on me,'' the woman said. ''I pushed him back and said 'no' and that was it.''</p>
        <p>The woman, who is now one of the military's senior officers and insists that her name not be revealed, said she did not report this unwanted sexual advance when it happened a few years ago. She said she feared that her reputation and her career could have been ruined if she filed an official complaint.</p>
        <p>Even with the news this week that the Army inspector general, acting on a formal sexual harassment complaint, found that Lt. Gen. Claudia J. Kennedy had been the victim of inappropriate sexual advances from another Army general, the senior officer who said she was accosted after jogging said she still believed she did the right thing.</p>
        <p>''No one's career was hurt, not mine and not his,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The case of General Kennedy, the Army's highest-ranking woman, has revived the question of how pervasive sexual harassment remains in the military and how such cases should be handled. Women in the military are reluctant to file harassment complaints, many female officers said, because they fear opening their personal lives to examination and being blamed for inviting a sexual advance.</p>
        <p>''Now, instead of being remembered as the first woman to earn three stars in the Army, she is going to be remembered as that woman with the sex complaint,'' said the senior officer who, like most of the other 15 senior officers interviewed for this article, spoke only on the condition that she not be identified.</p>
        <p>Of those officers, all but three said that they had been the target of sexual harassment in the military. In interviews, these 13 women all said that to protect their careers they never reported a one-time case of sexual harassment. They marveled that General Kennedy, so close to retirement, would have subjected herself to the backlash and tarnished reputation that would inevitably come from making a sexual harassment charge.</p>
        <p>''She could have ignored this,'' said another officer. ''I suspect right now some companies that might have considered her for employment may not now because of the high visibility of this issue.''</p>
        <p>The women said they generally accepted General Kennedy's account that she made the complaint against Maj. Gen. Larry G. Smith four years after the incident only upon learning that he had been appointed deputy inspector general of the Army, a position that included investigating sexual harassment.</p>
        <p>There could be no other reason, they said, to willingly open oneself to the personal scrutiny that would come with reporting an incident.</p>
        <p>Under military guidelines, a victim of a one-time incident is advised to handle the problem herself, unless it is a flagrant assault. If the harasser makes a second attempt, that is cause for a complaint. Most of those cases are handled with counseling or letters of reprimand.</p>
        <p>In more serious cases, the charge is rarely sexual harassment; it is more likely to be maltreatment of a subordinate or assault and battery.</p>
        <p>Women who are senior officers today -- lieutenant colonel or higher in the Army and Air Force, commander or higher in the Navy, and command sergeant majors in the enlisted ranks -- were among the first to integrate their services. They watched as the parade of public sexual scandals in the military mirrored their private stories.</p>
        <p>They said that during the 1980's, when they were junior officers, they put up with wolf whistles and cat-calls as well as outright sexual assaults, waiting for the services to change. As they rose in rank and the military began cracking down on inappropriate behavior, the harassment became more subtle, ''stealth-like'' in the words of more than one woman, like getting nuzzled on the dance floor or having legs massaged under a dinner table.</p>
        <p>''It takes so much courage for a woman to come forward with a complaint,'' said Lt. Col. Elspeth Cameron Ritchie, a forensic psychiatrist in the Army who works with women who bring charges of sexual assault, the description that General Kennedy has told friends she believes best describes her encounter.</p>
        <p>''What is most likely to happen is a negative effect on your career,''Colonel Ritchie said. The women who bring charges of sexual assault against a man that lead to a trial generally resign from the Army within a year, she said, whether the man was found guilty or innocent.</p>
        <p>Often, Colonel Ritchie said, the victims of harassment in the military have the same reaction: ''Shame, humiliation and wanting to get out of the service -- they leave within one year.''</p>
        <p>In recent polls, surveys and reports, incidents of sexual harassment are down in the military. Even the female senior officers said they believed all branches of the military have made progress in combating sexual harassment.</p>
        <p>But the legal and medical experts who supervise these cases say the figures are low, because most cases go unreported.</p>
        <p>The latest figures from the Department of Defense show a dramatic decrease from 1,599 in 1993 to 558 in 1998. But a top military legal expert in the department said ''those numbers are on the low end'' because so many incidents are not reported.</p>
        <p>''You want to be pretty skeptical of those figures -- they are not going to capture the vast majority of sexual harassment cases,'' said the senior officer, who spoke on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>In a blizzard of e-mail messages and private conversations over the last month, enlisted women as well as junior and senior officers are questioning the reporting policies of the military and searching for a middle ground that would allow women to make complaints without risking their careers in unwanted publicity.</p>
        <p>''I'm angry and getting angrier by the day,'' wrote one senior officer, who also spoke on the condition of anonymity. ''What message does this send to young women?''</p>
        <p>Without knowing how many cases go unreported, the women said, they are wondering how different the military is from civilian life.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, charges of sexual harassment in the civilian workplace have risen by 150 percent, from 6,127 cases in 1990 to 15,222 cases last year, according to figures compiled by the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission.</p>
        <p>The Kennedy case has prompted female senior officers to tell each other and their male colleagues their own stories of sexual harassment to underscore that General Kennedy was not the only senior officer who resisted reporting a sexual advance.</p>
        <p>One woman who is now a higher-ranking officer said that over five years ago, when she was still a lieutenant colonel, she asked her boss for advice about advanced training schools. In response, he requested oral sex.</p>
        <p>''I went in to talk to my commanding officer, a colonel, about which officer training school I would attend and he said he could get me in anywhere I wanted to go if I would do it for him,'' she said.</p>
        <p>She turned around, walked out of the office without saying a word and spent the next three days asking herself what she had done wrong. She said that she seriously thought about retiring from the military.</p>
        <p>''It changed my life,'' she said. ''I feel it just as deeply today as I did then. I was personally and professionally cut to the core.''</p>
        <p>Air Force Maj. Gen. Susan L. Pamerleau, one of the few officers who agreed to be named, said she had wrestled with the question of reporting sexual harassment and the complicated messages coming out of the Kennedy case. She said that she had done exactly what General Kennedy did four years ago.</p>
        <p>''In the past, I've experienced inappropriate behavior and I have personally dealt with it,'' she said. But, echoing the sentiments of most of the other officers, she said, ''the fact that General Kennedy raised the issue and that the military gave it such importance does say we are serious about creating an environment free of harassment and discrimination.''</p>
        <p>The initial Army inquiry substantiated the accusation of General Kennedy that General Smith grabbed her and tried to kiss her in her office at the Pentagon in 1996, Pentagon officials said. The vice-chief of the Army will now review the case and make his finding. Then General Smith has the right to rebut the finding, which could lead to further investigations, before the vice-chief makes a final judgment.</p>
        <p>The inspector general of the Pentagon will then review the case to ensure that there are no procedural problems.</p>
        <p>Following the Tailhook scandal in 1991, the Pentagon and the individual services created anti-harassment policies and took steps to crack down on the problem, including special training on sexual harassment for personnel at all ranks.</p>
        <p>But in the circumscribed world of the military, where it is hard to tell when the professional day ends and private life begins, women and men are together from early morning exercise to the last beer at the officer's club or barracks. And despite the new policies, sexual harassment remains a problem, particularly for women in the junior ranks.</p>
        <p>One woman tapped the work of the military strategist Karl von Clausewitz to describe what it is like to have spent the last 20 to 30 years integrating the military. She pointed to his theory of friction, how the countless small things on a battlefield that a commander cannot control may come together and have a cumulative effect that is devastating.</p>
        <p>''It's the same when you are a woman in the military and you put up with the little slights -- the hesitation to salute, soldiers calling you mom instead of ma'am, hearing the old debate about whether we belong in the military and then some event happens to you, real sexual harassment, and that puts you over the top and you are out of here,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
