<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dell's Quarterly Earnings Are Better Than Expected</title>
    <meta content="Y12DEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dell Computer Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Lawrence M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E1D8173BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dell's Quarterly Earnings Are Better Than Expected</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Lawrence M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dell Computer Corp posts better-than-expected earnings in first quarter ended April 28; profit rose 21 percent, to $525 million, compared with $434 million in year-earlier period; revenue rose 31 percent, to $7.28 billion, from $5.54 billion; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Dell Computer Corporation posted better-than-expected first-quarter earnings yesterday, benefiting from a richer mix of products, with particular strength in sales of servers and storage devices for Internet use.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended April 28, Dell's profit rose 21 percent, to $525 million, or 19 cents a diluted share,  compared with $434 million, or 16 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose 31 percent, to $7.28 billion from $5.54 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Dell Computer Corporation posted better-than-expected first-quarter earnings yesterday, benefiting from a richer mix of products, with particular strength in sales of servers and storage devices for Internet use.</p>
        <p>For the quarter ended April 28, Dell's profit rose 21 percent, to $525 million, or 19 cents a diluted share,  compared with $434 million, or 16 cents a share, in the period a year earlier. Revenue rose 31 percent, to $7.28 billion from $5.54 billion.</p>
        <p>Analysts had expected Dell to earn 16 cents a share, according to First Call/Thomson Financial, which tracks company earnings.</p>
        <p>Before Dell reported its results, its shares closed down 25 cents at $44.6875. In after-hours trading, Dell rose as high as $47.625.</p>
        <p>Dell's relative strength could help reassure technology investors coming after a quarter when Microsoft reported slower-than-expected revenue. Many analysts have suggested that companies are embracing Windows 2000 more slowly than expected, which has also slowed PC sales. Dell itself said in February that its historic growth rates were unsustainable and it projected revenue growth in the low-30-percent range.</p>
        <p>Daniel Kunstler, an analyst at J. P. Morgan, said that revenue only modestly exceeded his estimate but that in the current climate, that was positive. ''Given that everyone is really nervous about PC sales, it's good that they beat it even by a little,'' he said. ''Dell had guided down expectations ahead of Microsoft, so it's not like one company's results are in conflict with the other.''</p>
        <p>Dell said the portion of its business coming from more profitable products continued to increase, with revenue from servers, storage products, workstations and notebook PC's at 48 percent of sales, up from 39 percent in the quarter a year earlier. At the same time, the cost of components declined, particularly for memory chips, which had been in short supply until recently.</p>
        <p>''We had some better-than-expected component pricing, and a better-than-expected product mix,'' Kevin Rollins, Dell's vice chairman, said in a telephone interview. ''That contributed to about 2 cents of the uptick, relative to First Call. The other penny came from tapping into our investments.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rollins said Dell remained comfortable with revenue-growth forecasts in the low-30-percent range for the rest of the year. ''This is really a function of the buildout of the Internet that continues to go on,'' he said. ''There may be some challenges in the second half of the year concerning components, but that will be offset by this continuing infrastructure build for the Internet.''</p>
        <p>In a statement, Michael S. Dell, the company's chairman and chief executive, said, ''The fundamental competitive advantages of our customer-focused direct-business model are widening.''</p>
        <p>Last month, Dell announced a strategy to sell new products and services to Web-based businesses. Dell said sales to the largest dot-com companies and Internet-service providers had grown nearly 260 percent over the last two quarters.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
