<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Universities Choose Recipients for Journalism Fellowships</title>
    <meta content="12FELL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harvard University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stanford University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Michigan</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Scholarships and Fellowships</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E0DE143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Universities Choose Recipients for Journalism Fellowships</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Four universities name recipients of journalism fellowships for 2000-01 academic year; fellowships involve range of study options; schools are Columbia University, University of Michigan, Stanford University and Harvard University (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four universities have named the recipients of journalism fellowships for the 2000-01 academic year. The fellowships involve a range of study options.</p>
        <p>Columbia University</p>
        <p>Thirteen journalists specializing in arts and culture have been selected for the National Arts Journalism Program at Columbia University's Graduate School of Journalism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four universities have named the recipients of journalism fellowships for the 2000-01 academic year. The fellowships involve a range of study options.</p>
        <p>Columbia University</p>
        <p>Thirteen journalists specializing in arts and culture have been selected for the National Arts Journalism Program at Columbia University's Graduate School of Journalism.</p>
        <p>Senior fellows:</p>
        <p>Patricia Bosworth, contributing editor, Vanity Fair magazine, and author of several biographies</p>
        <p>Joseph Horowitz, author, journalist and artistic consultant on classical music</p>
        <p>Wendy Lesser, editor and publisher, The Threepenny Review, Berkeley, Calif.</p>
        <p>Fellows:</p>
        <p>Charles Aaron, senior editor, Spin magazine</p>
        <p>Alicia Anstead, arts and features writer, Bangor (Me.) Daily News</p>
        <p>Holly Bass, contributor, Washington City Paper</p>
        <p>Thomas Conner, pop music critic, Tulsa (Okla.) World</p>
        <p>Eric Fredericksen, senior writer, The Stranger, Seattle</p>
        <p>Minal Hajratwala, ''Perspective'' editor, San Jose (Calif.) Mercury News</p>
        <p>Cynthia Joyce, contributor, Salon.com</p>
        <p>Adam Langer, associate editor, Book Magazine, Chicago, and features writer, Chicago Reader</p>
        <p>Naomi Person, producer, ''Fresh Air With Terry Gross,'' WHYY-FM, Philadelphia</p>
        <p>Ray Rinaldi, arts and entertainment editor, St. Louis Post-Dispatch</p>
        <p>Ten Knight-Bagehot Fellows in Economics and Business Journalism have been named by the Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism. Fellows will take graduate courses at Columbia's Schools of Business, Law, and International and Public Affairs.</p>
        <p>Khawaja Haris Anwar, business writer, Dawn Newspaper, Pakistan</p>
        <p>Rachel Beck, national retail/Internet reporter, Associated Press</p>
        <p>Tim Gray, business writer, Business North Carolina magazine</p>
        <p>Barry Henderson, staff writer, Barron's</p>
        <p>Ward V. B. Lassoe, segment producer, ''Business Center,'' CNBC</p>
        <p>Grainne McCarthy, Jakarta bureau chief, Dow Jones Newswires</p>
        <p>Leslie Moore, Mexico correspondent, Dow Jones's America Economia</p>
        <p>Brian J. O'Connor, managing editor, Bankrate.com</p>
        <p>Jeff Sommer, assistant business editor, New York Times</p>
        <p>Teresa Tritch, senior editor, Money magazine</p>
        <p>Harvard University</p>
        <p>Twenty-four journalists have been named Nieman Fellows and awarded an academic year of study in any part of the university. International fellows will be announced later this month, but following are the American recipients:</p>
        <p>Ken Armstrong, legal affairs writer, Chicago Tribune</p>
        <p>Don Aucoin, television critic, Boston Globe</p>
        <p>Kirstin Downey Grimsley, staff writer, Washington Post</p>
        <p>Anne Fitzgerald, agribusiness writer, Des Moines Register</p>
        <p>Kelli S. Hewett, City Hall/special projects writer, Dothan (Ala.) Eagle</p>
        <p>J. R. Moehringer, Atlanta bureau chief, Los Angeles Times</p>
        <p>Mark Pothier, executive editor, MPG Newspapers, Plymouth, Mass.</p>
        <p>Linda Robinson, Latin America bureau chief, U.S. News &amp; World Report</p>
        <p>Ron Stodghill II, Midwest bureau chief, Time</p>
        <p>Andrew Sussman, senior program producer, ''The World,'' a co-production of the BBC World Service, Public Radio International and WGBH, Boston</p>
        <p>Peter Turnley, photojournalist based in Paris, Newsweek</p>
        <p>Nuri Vallbona, photojournalist, Miami Herald</p>
        <p>University of Michigan</p>
        <p>Thirteen journalists have been named University of Michigan Journalism Fellows.</p>
        <p>Richard L. Colvin, education writer, Los Angeles Times</p>
        <p>Andrea Guthman, associate producer, WTTW-TV, Chicago</p>
        <p>Susan M. Hooper, staff writer, Honolulu Advertiser</p>
        <p>Debbie A. Howlett, Midwest reporter, USA Today</p>
        <p>Douglas Johnson, producer/on-air host, C-Span Networks</p>
        <p>Jason E. Kaufman, freelance writer, Cambridge, Mass.</p>
        <p>Kathleen L. Kerwin, Detroit bureau chief, Business Week magazine</p>
        <p>Richard Leiby, staff writer, Washington Post</p>
        <p>Jon Morgan, sports-business writer, Baltimore Sun</p>
        <p>Milton D. Priggee, editorial cartoonist, Spokesman Review, Spokane, Wash.</p>
        <p>Bruce R. Strong, staff photographer, Orange County (Calif.) Register</p>
        <p>Patricia A. Vila, producer/bureau manager, Havana, CNN</p>
        <p>Yumi L. Wilson, City Hall reporter, San Francisco Chronicle.</p>
        <p>Stanford University</p>
        <p>Twelve American journalists and eight international journalists have been awarded John S. Knight Fellowships at Stanford University.</p>
        <p>Jane Armstrong, national correspondent, Globe and Mail, Vancouver, British Columbia</p>
        <p>Tom Arviso Jr., editor, Navajo Times, Window Rock, Ariz.</p>
        <p>Solaade Ayo-Aderele, assistant chief subeditor, Punch, Lagos, Nigeria (Reuters Foundation Fellow)</p>
        <p>Ray Choto, chief writer, The Standard, Harare, Zimbabwe</p>
        <p>Bonnie DeSimone, sports staff writer, Chicago Tribune</p>
        <p>Tim Johnson, Bogota bureau chief, Miami Herald</p>
        <p>Jerry Large, columnist, Seattle Times</p>
        <p>Bong-Soo Lim, reporter, JoongAng Ilbo, Seoul, South Korea (Shinyoung Journalism Fund Fellow)</p>
        <p>Cheuk-fei Man, assistant chief editor, Hong Kong Economic Journal</p>
        <p>Martha Mendoza, national investigative reporter, San Jose bureau, Associated Press</p>
        <p>Bob Moser, editor, Independent Weekly, Durham, N.C.</p>
        <p>Annie Nakao, staff writer, San Francisco Examiner</p>
        <p>Corina-Rodica Negrea, science news producer, Radio Romania, Bucharest (Lyle and Corrine Nelson International Journalism Fellow)</p>
        <p>Judith Nichols, team leader, breaking news and online, Arizona Republic</p>
        <p>Clara Ins Rueda, managing editor, Gerente, Bogota, Colombia (Knight Foundation Latin American Fellow)</p>
        <p>Sonia Seoane, ''Careers'' editor, El Cronista, Buenos Aires(Reuters Foundation Fellow)</p>
        <p>Lawrence Sheets, bureau chief, Caucacus region, Reuters</p>
        <p>Gini Sikes, producer, MTV News, New York</p>
        <p>David Stabler, classical music critic, Portland Oregonian</p>
        <p>Brian Willoughby, social issues reporter, Vancouver (Wash.) Columbianr</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
