<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Florio Puts Corzine on the Defensive in Their First Debate</title>
    <meta content="12DEBA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Florio, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1DB143BF931A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Florio Puts Corzine on the Defensive in Their First Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, May 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former New Jersey Gov Jim Florio and Jon S Corzine, his opponent in Democratic primary for US Senate, meet for their first debate, Trenton; Florio, after enduring eight-week barrage of costly television commercials by Corzine, seizes control of debate, forcing Corzine on defensive for a full hour; Florio ridicules Corzine's proposals, likening his views to those of Republican politicians and repeatedly attacking his main qualification for Senate: former co-chairman of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After enduring an eight-week barrage of costly television commercials by Jon S. Corzine, his opponent in the Democratic primary, former Gov. Jim Florio, seized control of their first debate today, forcing Mr. Corzine on the defensive for a full hour as the two men showed why theirs is perhaps the most captivating Senate race outside New York.</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio, who had to wait nearly a year for the chance to debate his rival, made the most of the opportunity, ridiculing Mr. Corzine's proposals, likening his views to those of Republican politicians and repeatedly attacking his main qualification for the United States Senate: his record as the former co-chairman of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After enduring an eight-week barrage of costly television commercials by Jon S. Corzine, his opponent in the Democratic primary, former Gov. Jim Florio, seized control of their first debate today, forcing Mr. Corzine on the defensive for a full hour as the two men showed why theirs is perhaps the most captivating Senate race outside New York.</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio, who had to wait nearly a year for the chance to debate his rival, made the most of the opportunity, ridiculing Mr. Corzine's proposals, likening his views to those of Republican politicians and repeatedly attacking his main qualification for the United States Senate: his record as the former co-chairman of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Corzine, an unpolished speaker who had seemed reluctant to attack Mr. Florio personally, criticized the former governor for raising taxes by $2.8 billion during the 1990 recession, a move that cost Mr. Florio his job and led to a Republican takeover of the State Legislature. ''I think we took a problem and made it a crisis,'' Mr. Corzine said.</p>
        <p>In his prepared opening statement, Mr. Corzine sought to cast Mr. Florio as a bad memory best forgotten. ''People can embrace the past without embracing its failures,'' he said. ''The voters of New Jersey are looking to the future, and the Democratic Party should as well.''</p>
        <p>But when their exchanges were extemporaneous, Mr. Florio was far more effective. When Mr. Corzine tried to talk about the specifics of what he calls his ''bold ideas,'' for example, Mr. Florio delivered a withering retort: ''Words,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Bold is about taking on the gun lobby,'' Mr. Florio said. ''Bold is raising the money to finance education for our children. Bold is going out and making sure that we have a clean environment by taking on corporate polluters.</p>
        <p>''Rhetoric is rhetoric, words are words,'' he added. ''This is not bold; this is baloney.''</p>
        <p>The debate today was the first chance for most New Jerseyans to see the two Democratic candidates side by side, and it gave Mr. Florio, who has not yet been able to afford his own television ads, a coveted chance to address a broad audience.</p>
        <p>The debate was taped in Trenton for broadcast tonight on the New Jersey Network, a state-owned group of public television and radio stations that sponsored the event with The New York Times. It will be shown again on Sunday at 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio held a wide lead in the polls against Mr. Corzine, a newcomer to politics, until Mr. Corzine began his ad campaign in mid-March and steadily eroded that gap. Officials in both campaigns say the former governor holds an edge of only about six percentage points among likely Democratic voters, and they expect the race to be exceedingly close right up until the primary on June 6 .</p>
        <p>Throughout today's encounter, Mr. Corzine tried several times to outline his ideas for universal health care, long-term care for the elderly and  disabled, and education, and Mr. Florio belittled them as unrealistic and too expensive. But the two men focused far more on their backgrounds in business and politics than on their proposals.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Corzine spoke in favor of gun control, for example, Mr. Florio zeroed in on Goldman, Sachs's links to gun companies, saying the firm had advised the makers of Smith &amp; Wesson, Remington and Ruger firearms in various transactions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine first denied that he had led Goldman, Sachs while it was advising those companies, then said the stocks of companies that make guns occasionally ''flow through our portfolios provided for the investors.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio responded: ''Jon is getting very good at the political art of squirming off the hook. We're not talking about trading stocks, we're talking about raising capital to go into gun manufacturing companies. And through this whole last decade, Jon was either the C.E.O. or he was a member of the nine-member management commission.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio's attacks were so persistent that Mr. Corzine at one point felt compelled to defend his former employer. ''I'm proud of my record at Goldman, Sachs; I'm proud of Goldman, Sachs,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine offered his most extended rebuke of Mr. Florio for raising taxes in 1990, after promising as a candidate the year before that he would not. Had he been in Mr. Florio's shoes, Mr. Corzine said, he would never have made such a promise. And he would not have raised the sales tax, the ''most regressive'' kind of tax, in any case, he said.</p>
        <p>''Governor, you told the New Jersey public that you would look at the $12.6 billion state budget and find savings,'' Mr. Corzine said, adding that Mr. Florio's actions evinced ''a 'ready, fire, aim' attitude.''</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. Florio called Mr. Corzine's recollection ''an Orwellian rewriting of history,'' and questioned how Mr. Corzine would have replaced the sales tax revenue. ''Jon just took $700 million out of the equation,'' he said. ''That's fine, but I'm still waiting for him to say what he would have done.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio again defended the tax increases as necessary to pay for more aid to needy urban school districts. ''This sounds very much like the Republicans the other night,'' he said of Mr. Corzine's objections. ''It's fine for Republicans to walk away from a commitment to finance education for all of our children.</p>
        <p>''Those kind of know-nothing views about not standing up for our children don't belong in our party. They belong in the other party.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio also attacked his rival on campaign finance reform, repeating his claim that Mr. Corzine was trying to buy the election. Mr. Corzine is bankrolling his candidacy using his $400 million fortune. When Mr. Corzine said, ''Elections are about a contest of ideas, they're not about money,'' Mr. Florio replied: ''Jon's being a bit disingenuous. Even one of his supporters in the audience said he wouldn't be talking to him if it weren't for his money.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, whose aides said his poor debating skills made him seem more human than the composed but sharp-edged Mr. Florio, made no major gaffes and slowly grew more comfortable on the podium. But he appeared nervous at first, his syntax frequently derailed, and some of his points were lost on even the most informed people in the audience. Attempting a riposte to Mr. Florio's attack on his Wall Street record, for example, Mr. Corzine was inarticulate in trying to raise similar questions about Mr. Florio's years in private legal practice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio, by contrast, was as pointed and focused as he has ever been, although it remains to be seen whether his familiar, jabbing cadences and aggressive style will still appeal to voters. Mr. Corzine's supporters believe that many have grown weary of Mr. Florio -- a condition they call ''Florio fatigue.''</p>
        <p>''It's the same old Jim Florio, the same rhetoric, the same old attacking, critical style,'' said State Senator John A. Lynch, a supporter of Mr. Corzine. ''I saw the past, and I saw the future in Jon Corzine. I like the future.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
