<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reshuffling And Heroics Follow Injuries</title>
    <meta content="15DEBU$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Ballet Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E6D6133BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reshuffling And Heroics Follow Injuries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews American Ballet Theater performance, with dancers from other companies filling in for injured Ballet Theater stars (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Damian Woetzel, normally seen with New York City Ballet, where he is that company's male star, unexpectedly led George Balanchine's ''Theme and Variations'' at American Ballet Theater. On the same program a ballerina role normally danced by one person in Twyla Tharp's new ''Variations on a Theme by Haydn'' was divided up and danced by three women.</p>
        <p>Strange things happen at the ballet. But these surprises on Wednesday night at the Metropolitan Opera House testified to a valiant and cooperative effort to deal with numerous injuries and illnesses at Ballet Theater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Damian Woetzel, normally seen with New York City Ballet, where he is that company's male star, unexpectedly led George Balanchine's ''Theme and Variations'' at American Ballet Theater. On the same program a ballerina role normally danced by one person in Twyla Tharp's new ''Variations on a Theme by Haydn'' was divided up and danced by three women.</p>
        <p>Strange things happen at the ballet. But these surprises on Wednesday night at the Metropolitan Opera House testified to a valiant and cooperative effort to deal with numerous injuries and illnesses at Ballet Theater.</p>
        <p>Other substitutions had affected the same bill on Wednesday afternoon. Angel Corella, previously reviewed, stepped in for the injured Jose Manuel Carreno in ''Theme and Variations,'' and Julio Bocca replaced him in Jerome Robbins's ''Other Dances.'' He appeared with Julie Kent and in the evening with Alessandra Ferri.</p>
        <p>Without all this reshuffling, attention would have been focused on this season's revival of Antony Tudor's exquisite ''Jardin aux Lilas.'' At both performances, Ekaterina Shelkanova was the new heroine Caroline.</p>
        <p>Unlike many others in the role, this was a young woman entering into an arranged marriage who would not fight back in the future, making all the more poignant the fugitive encounters with Maxim Belotserkovsky as Her Lover. Both knew how to make drama part of dancing and did not impose acting upon movement.</p>
        <p>Ms. Shelkanova was a bit more of a Chekhov heroine (resigned like one of three sisters) than in tune with Tudor's Proustian inspiration. In the central scene time stands still as all freeze onstage until Caroline, moving toward her lover, acts out her inner desires.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless Ms. Shelkanova's refined style and precise dancing caught the emotional essence of Tudor's expressiveness, its combination of classical footwork and free-form arms. The contrast between Caroline and others in the cast varied in the two performances. As The Man She Must Marry, Robert Hill was unusually enraged. In the evening Ethan Brown was more complex, showing both sympathy to his unwilling bride and a residue of feeling toward his former mistress (An Episode in His Past), passionately danced by Sandra Brown.</p>
        <p>By Wednesday night, when the Tharp ballet built up to the tremendous climax that was missing on opening night, Ms. Brown deserved a medal. At both performances on Wednesday, the injured Susan Jaffe danced only in the beginning and the end of the work. Oksana Konobeyeva danced one of her variations, and Ms. Brown filled in the rest while also darting in and out in her own role.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woetzel's guest appearance in ''Theme and Variations'' found him thoroughly at ease in a role he knows well at City Ballet. That company's loan was Ballet Theater's gain. Mr. Woetzel's unforced virtuosity and gallantry complemented Ms. Kent's elegance. At the matinee Ms. Kent was nonetheless a bland foil to Mr. Bocca's verve in ''Other Dances'' in which he had more rapport with a playful Ms. Ferri in the evening.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
