<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thomas Uses Mourning's Advice to Foil Him in 13 Key Minutes</title>
    <meta content="Y15BOOK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Kurt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mourning, Alonzo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4DD103BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thomas Uses Mourning's Advice to Foil Him in 13 Key Minutes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Play of New York Knickerbockers forward Kurt Thomas in playoff series against Miami Heat and Alonzo Mourning discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kurt Thomas winced as he recalled his rookie days with the Miami Heat when Alonzo Mourning would beat him to the block in practice, then blow by him. ''I didn't know anything,'' Thomas said yesterday, laughing.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Mourning would tutor his pupil. ''Play hard, always play hard,'' was his best advice, Thomas remembered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kurt Thomas winced as he recalled his rookie days with the Miami Heat when Alonzo Mourning would beat him to the block in practice, then blow by him. ''I didn't know anything,'' Thomas said yesterday, laughing.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Mourning would tutor his pupil. ''Play hard, always play hard,'' was his best advice, Thomas remembered.</p>
        <p>But Thomas, now a Knicks reserve, remembered more than that, and he pulled out the mental notes he made on Mourning's game four years ago in Miami.</p>
        <p>Thomas played only 13 minutes in the Knicks' 91-83 victory over the Heat yesterday, but in a five-minute stretch in the fourth quarter, the  6-foot-9-inch center scored 4 points off driving layups, pulled down 3 offensive rebounds and rifled a perfect pass under the basket to Charlie Ward, who gave the Knicks a 9-point lead with 4 minutes 4 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>Thomas also caused Mourning to commit two offensive fouls in the game.</p>
        <p>''I learned so much from him when I was a rookie; he took me under his wing and he taught me a lot of things, how to attack the basket,'' Thomas said. ''I saw how he moves his feet, how he turns his shoulder.''</p>
        <p>Because of that, Thomas knew exactly where Mourning was going. ''I just tried to stay in front of him, try to cut him off, try to take away his jump shot as much as possible,'' Thomas said.</p>
        <p>Thomas's contribution was a significant factor in the Knicks' returning to Miami with the series tied at two games apiece.</p>
        <p>''I thought his effort was terrific and really needed,'' Coach Jeff Van Gundy said. ''One thing you know when Kurt plays is that he is going to play extremely hard. He is going to defend to the best of his ability, which I think he does very well. And the variable is how many offensive rebounds he can get. He was on the offensive glass today. Even some that he didn't get, he kept alive.''</p>
        <p>Thomas was fiery again, no more so than when he soared in for a dunk against Mourning in the fourth quarter. As Mourning went up to block the shot, the two toppled to the court. Thomas appeared agitated and pushed his former mentor while getting up.</p>
        <p>''He was just telling me, 'Don't do that,' '' Thomas said. ''He knows I'm getting back to my old ways -- playing hard. I was just trying to protect myself by pushing him away so I don't come down on him and twist my ankle. That's just how I play.''</p>
        <p>Thomas fractured his ankle his second year with Miami and played only 18 games with the Heat before he was traded to Dallas for Jamal Mashburn. The next season, Thomas played only five games because of the ankle injury, and the Knicks picked Thomas up after the lockout ended last season.</p>
        <p>He averaged 8 points and 6.3 rebounds a game this season, and has averaged 13 minutes and 3.3 points this postseason.</p>
        <p>''He picked up a couple charges on Alonzo, got him frustrated,'' Marcus Camby said. ''He's more mobile than Patrick, so he made sure Zo wouldn't get any baseline dunks. He played inspired basketball.''</p>
        <p>Back to the Boards</p>
        <p>For the fourth straight game, the Heat outrebounded the Knicks, this time by 48-37. But after being outrebounded by 27-13 by halftime, the Knicks responded to Jeff Van Gundy's orders to do better.</p>
        <p>''He got on us a lot,''' Marcus Camby said. ''We still probably got outrebounded, but we tried to make a conscious effort. L. J. got us on a roll in the third quarter.'' Larry Johnson finished with six rebounds.</p>
        <p>The Knicks made the biggest improvement in the fourth quarter, with six offensive and six defensive rebounds. Miami only had nine total in the quarter.</p>
        <p>The Heat's P. J. Brown said:  ''That's been the difference in the series. Whoever wins that battle usually has the chance to win the game. We had a lot of rebounds, but they had the crucial ones. They were making the bigger plays down the stretch, that was the big difference.''</p>
        <p>Noting that the Knicks were dominated on the boards again, Van Gundy said, ''If they are going to continue to do that, it is going to be very, very difficult to find a way to manufacture enough points.''</p>
        <p>The Injury Report</p>
        <p>Miami's Jamal Mashburn, frustrated when no foul was called against Latrell Sprewell on the final play of the first half, kicked a courtside table where reporters were sitting, injuring the right shoulder of Selena Roberts of The New York Times, who was leaning on the table. She was examined by the Knicks' physician, Norman Scott, at halftime and returned to report on the game. After the game, Mashburn apologized to Roberts.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
