<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A flood of trademark applications clearly shows that the Internet is a place businesses want to be.</title>
    <meta content="15PATE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PATENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Patent and Trademark Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE6D7133BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A flood of trademark applications clearly shows that the Internet is a place businesses want to be.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States Patent and Trademark Office received 33,731 applications for trademarks that covered Internet-related products or services in 1999; in 1994, number of such applications was 307; study was done by law firm specializing in Internet law (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR Glenn Gundersen, a law partner at Dechert Price &amp; Rhoads in Philadelphia who specializes in trademark, copyright and Internet law, the numbers are particularly striking: ''This is wild, something I've never seen in my 20 years in this field.''</p>
        <p>He was marveling over a study that his office had just released on trademark applications that gives unique evidence of the trends driving the current economic boom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR Glenn Gundersen, a law partner at Dechert Price &amp; Rhoads in Philadelphia who specializes in trademark, copyright and Internet law, the numbers are particularly striking: ''This is wild, something I've never seen in my 20 years in this field.''</p>
        <p>He was marveling over a study that his office had just released on trademark applications that gives unique evidence of the trends driving the current economic boom.</p>
        <p>The study found that in 1999, the United States Patent and Trademark Office received 33,731 applications for trademarks that covered an Internet-related product or service. Five years earlier, in 1994, it received only 307.</p>
        <p>The report also revealed that once businesses decided the Internet was the place to be, many wanted the same kind of brand or logo: in 1999, 12,000 trademark applications included the ''.com'' suffix. In 1994, a mere four had it.</p>
        <p>Since most applications are for products and services that have yet to hit the market, trademark requests can tell tales about continuing expectations for the digital economy.</p>
        <p>In the last year, trademark applications have also tested the boundaries of what types of products and material the government views as eligible for protection. Those challenges have come, not surprisingly, from applications seeking trademarks that include ''.com,'' ''i'' for Internet or ''e'' for electronic.</p>
        <p>The explosion of interest in those trademarks appears to have contributed to the largest annual increase in total applications -- a 32 percent jump last year, to 265,341.</p>
        <p>''What is so fascinating about this huge jump,'' Mr. Gundersen said, ''is it shows, boy, are we optimistic. And that helps quantify what you're feeling and seeing around you about the economy, and puts it in numbers and percentages that give a feeling for how much of a boom there is in new companies and new businesses launching new ventures.''</p>
        <p>Dechert has made such reports annually for the last 10 years, analyzing the number and type of trademarks and trade names that businesses and manufacturers want to protect. The report is usually for internal purposes, but Mr. Gundersen said he was so struck by this year's results that he decided to publicize them.</p>
        <p>The number and type of trademark applications serve as a barometer for the economy because they reflect confidence in starting new businesses and introducing new products and services, as well as willingness and ability to spend money on brand names, logos and other trademarks. At the same time, the applications raise questions about the value of trademarks compared with Internet address -- or domain name -- registrations, and about the use of descriptive or generic terms, which in the past have been ineligible for trademarks.</p>
        <p>Applications sagged in 1991, when the economy was in a recession. They have increased steadily every year since, in parallel to the economy's growth throughout the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Dechert's report also found that:</p>
        <p>*In 1994, just 89 applications included the word ''Internet'' and only 60 used ''Web''; in 1999, 1,041 included Internet and 1,808 used Web.</p>
        <p>*Between 1998 and 1999, applications for ''e'' trademarks increased 325 percent, while applications for ''i'' trademarks jumped 175 percent, as companies looked for succinct alternatives to Internet, Web and .com.</p>
        <p>*In 1998, 12,235 trademark applications described Internet-related products or services; in 1999, that number more than doubled, to 33,731.</p>
        <p>*New Internet domain names were registered last year at a rate of one every two seconds, while new trademark applications were filed at a rate of one every two minutes.</p>
        <p>(Domain name registration is done through private companies under the supervision of the nonprofit Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers, or Icann.)</p>
        <p>The escalation last year in requests for the .com suffix, and for i-marks and e-brands, forced the Patent and Trademark Office to restate its definition of what terms are eligible for trademark status. As a result, some of the most valuable Internet domain names may not qualify for trademark protection.</p>
        <p>Names like business.com, drugstore.com or airplane.com are crafted out of the kind of generic terms that have long been ineligible for trademarks. At first, the Patent and Trademark Office awarded some of those trademarks, but after some confusion over its policy, it decided to ignore the .com suffix in the same way it ignores terms like ''Inc.''</p>
        <p>''Generally, .com doesn't have any trademark significance,'' explained  Sharon Marsh, an administrator at the trademark office. The agency has posted the policy on its Web site at www.uspto.gov. ''If a mark is descriptive or generic, with .com added, it doesn't change that.''</p>
        <p>But some .com requests are approved, she said. And the overall increase in applications is continuing.</p>
        <p>''Our total filings are up 40 percent for 2000,'' Ms. Marsh said. ''They're not all .com marks, but it's still a huge increase. It's a great economy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gundersen says that Internet branding and trademark law may be on a collision course. Applicants whose requests are denied under the agency's new .com policy have a right to appeal to the Trademark Trial and Appeal Board.</p>
        <p>And yet, such a conflict may lose its significance. After all, trademarks are valuable because they provide exclusivity. But in the Internet world, the same exclusivity can be assured with a domain name; a company that has registered a generic domain name like bank.com is the only one using it. So the domain name -- especially if it becomes a brand in the minds of consumers -- is valuable even if it cannot win a trademark.</p>
        <p>''Before, you looked to trademark law to give exclusivity under a trademarked name or phrase,'' Mr. Gundersen said. ''Now there's a new form of exclusivity to a string of characters. Some people are saying, if the trademark office takes a position that it won't register a trademark, maybe I can live with that because I have an exclusivity that they can't confer.''</p>
        <p>He predicts that principle will be tested when companies register domain names that are similar.</p>
        <p>''There are similar trademarks pending with garden.com, pets.com and others of that ilk,'' he said. ''The real question will be what happens when you have a generic.com and someone else comes real close. What happens when you stick on an i, or an e, or make it a plural?''</p>
        <p>PATENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
