<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off With Pomp and Circumstance</title>
    <meta content="15QUIX$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199722"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oestreich, James R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kopperud, Jean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E5D6133BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="519" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off With Pomp and Circumstance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES R. OESTREICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oestreich, James R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James R Oestreich reviews New York premiere performance of Don Quixote: A Theater Piece for Musicians, at Miller Theater; Jean Kopperud, clarinetist, is in leading role; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Making a steady round of classical-music events, a listener can wonder at times whatever happened to humor? Oh, the knowing smile comes easily and often enough, in response to once-ingenious musical jests or outrageous social satire grown toothless with age. And now with titles there is laughter in the opera house, as often mistimed as it is forced. But what contemporary composer besides Peter Schickele can fill an evening with belly laughs?</p>
        <p>Well, it was a short and modest evening, but John Eaton did it on Tuesday with his delightful ''Don Quixote,'' in its New York premiere performance at the Miller Theater. The official description was ''a theater piece for musicians'': namely, the New York New Music Ensemble, for which it was written. But Mr. Eaton, who teaches composition at the University of Chicago, amended the description from the stage, calling it ''a romp for instrumentalists.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Making a steady round of classical-music events, a listener can wonder at times whatever happened to humor? Oh, the knowing smile comes easily and often enough, in response to once-ingenious musical jests or outrageous social satire grown toothless with age. And now with titles there is laughter in the opera house, as often mistimed as it is forced. But what contemporary composer besides Peter Schickele can fill an evening with belly laughs?</p>
        <p>Well, it was a short and modest evening, but John Eaton did it on Tuesday with his delightful ''Don Quixote,'' in its New York premiere performance at the Miller Theater. The official description was ''a theater piece for musicians'': namely, the New York New Music Ensemble, for which it was written. But Mr. Eaton, who teaches composition at the University of Chicago, amended the description from the stage, calling it ''a romp for instrumentalists.''</p>
        <p>That it is. The hourlong piece, in a modernist idiom expertly bent to descriptive purposes, depicts events from Cervantes's tale, with the instrumentalists ''acting'' and even, on occasion, ''singing.'' (The quotation marks are used advisedly.)</p>
        <p>Jean Kopperud, a clarinetist outfitted with oversize beard and mustache, offered a tour de force as Don Quixote. The knight errant takes repeated physical batterings, as may be recalled, and Ms. Kopperud was sent tumbling several times while continuing to play her instrument. It's a wonder she didn't swallow it.</p>
        <p>The other performers, too, were woven into the flow of the action in Mike Phillips's clever direction. Even the cellist, Theodore Mook, made his lumbering way around the stage in no fewer than four roles: Dulcinea, a muleteer, Altisidora and a country girl. His falsetto singing, while entertaining in the extreme, cannot be said to have posed any serious threat to the current wave of countertenors. The conductor, James Baker, also entered the action at one point, knighting the antihero with his baton.</p>
        <p>Stephen Gosling, the fine pianist, doubled as percussionist, playing the lion's roar, a hybrid instrument that though rarely used, was prominently heard just recently in the Cleveland Orchestra's performance of Varese's ''Ameriques'' at Carnegie Hall. The other performers, all deft and gamely spirited, were Jayn Rosenfeld, a flutist, as Sancho Panza; Linda Quan, a violinist; and Pablo Rieppi, a proper percussionist.</p>
        <p>Peter Nigrini's arty projections greatly enhanced the staging, lending context and continuity. Stephen Quandt's lighting was apt.</p>
        <p>Still, the ultimate credit must go to Mr. Eaton, who summoned this jape from an ebullient musical imagination. The only question is how many other groups will have the ability and the pluck, if not outright courage, needed to perform it as well as the New York New Music Ensemble. All comers are welcome.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
