<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Seance in 4 Parts, With Narration</title>
    <meta content="15SECR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199697"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertheimer, Ron</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Secrets of the Dead (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EED8133BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Seance in 4 Parts, With Narration</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON WERTHEIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wertheimer, Ron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ron Wertheimer reviews PBS's 4-part series, Secrets of the Dead; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Secrets of the Dead'' sounds like the title for some hyperventilating documentary from the Fox network or from one of those pseudo-educational cable channels. Alas, it is the umbrella title of four hyperventilating documentaries that PBS is offering this week.</p>
        <p>The series begins tonight with ''Catastrophe!'' (What is it with these titles?) This two-hour program examines, in tiring detail, the theory of David Keys, a British writer, that some sort of cataclysm in the middle of the sixth century played havoc with the world's weather, leading to major reroutings of the course of history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Secrets of the Dead'' sounds like the title for some hyperventilating documentary from the Fox network or from one of those pseudo-educational cable channels. Alas, it is the umbrella title of four hyperventilating documentaries that PBS is offering this week.</p>
        <p>The series begins tonight with ''Catastrophe!'' (What is it with these titles?) This two-hour program examines, in tiring detail, the theory of David Keys, a British writer, that some sort of cataclysm in the middle of the sixth century played havoc with the world's weather, leading to major reroutings of the course of history.</p>
        <p>''The sun began to go dark,'' proclaims the narrator for the series, Roy Scheider. ''Rain poured red, as if tinted by blood.'' Such melodramatics, augmented by ''X-Files'' graphics plus music and sound effects that could have been lifted from a 1950's horror flick, only undermine the credibility of Mr. Keys and the 18 scientists on view, all from respected institutions, who seem to believe he's onto something.</p>
        <p>One thing is sure: the 530's were a tough time to be a tree, as the thin growth rings attest. ''We can interrogate for any calendar year in the last thousands of years what trees thought of their growth conditions,'' says a paleoecologist. (O.K., oak, you have the right to remain silent.)</p>
        <p>So what did happen? Did an asteroid or comet hit Earth? Nobody thinks so, but this red herring allows Mr. Scheider to intone the words ''extraterrestrial explanation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Keys says he believes that a huge volcanic explosion, say at Krakatoa in Indonesia, was the culprit. Mr. Scheider adds helpfully that such a ''gigantic eruption could have occurred.'' Could have? Why, Mr. Keys credits his explosion with the demise of the Roman Empire, the conquest of Britain, the creation of France and Spain, the founding of Islam and political upheaval in Mongolia that proved the superiority of the cow's digestive system over the horse's. (Dung samples are provided for your inspection.)</p>
        <p>A simulation of Mr. Keys's big bang is played over and over. Ka-bloom. Ka-bloom. Ka-bloom. Still, you're told, ''some scientists remain skeptical.'' Odds are you won't care one way or the other.</p>
        <p>You may be similarly unmoved by tomorrow night's entry, which asks why the Vikings vanished from Greenland around 1500 after thriving there for a half-century. ''These stones are all that remain of a lost Viking civilization,'' Mr. Scheider says. This film, only an hour and a bit calmer, has a dozen experts, none of whom can offer more than an educated guess about the elusive Norsemen. The camera keeps lingering tightly on the Vikings' skulls, as if hoping that they will solve the riddle. They don't.</p>
        <p>''Secrets of the Dead'' concludes on Wednesday with two programs. The first examines what really caused the explosion of the Hindenburg zeppelin, the second puzzles over the abrupt end of an idyllic ancient civilization in what is now the American Southwest. (Hint: That one is called ''Cannibalism in the Canyon.'')</p>
        <p>In the end, of course, the dead keep their secrets. And PBS keeps its dignity, just barely. Coming on Fox: ''When Good Program Ideas Go Bad!''</p>
        <p>SECRETS OF THE DEAD  PBS, tonight through Wednesday night  (Channel 13, New York, at 8)</p>
        <p>A production of WNET/New York and Channel 4 (Britain). Beth C. Hoppe and Dan Chambers, executive producers; William R. Grant, executive in charge. ''Catastrophe!'' is a production of 3BM Television. Simon Berthon, executive producer; Michael Chrisman, producer; Gary Johnstone, producer/director. ''The Lost Vikings'' is a production of Granite Productions. Simon Welfare, executive producer; David Wright, producer/director. ''What Happened to the Hindenburg?'' is a production of Twenty Twenty Television. Claudia Milne, executive producer; Russell England, producer; Dan Clifton, director. ''Cannibalism in the Canyon'' is a production of Engel Brothers Media. Steven Engel, executive producer; Larry Engel and Whitney Wood, producers; Larry Engel, director.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
