<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Knicks Need Houston to Take Flight, So They Can Soar as Well</title>
    <meta content="Y15RHO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Houston, Allan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DA103BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Knicks Need Houston to Take Flight, So They Can Soar as Well</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rhoden, William C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times column contends that New York Knickerbockers must have more scoring from Alan Houston if they are to defeat Miami Heat in playoffs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALLAN HOUSTON sat next to Charlie Ward yesterday, smiling, enjoying  the scene as his much-maligned teammate basked in the glow of a great Mother's Day game.</p>
        <p>Ward scored 20 points and helped the Knicks beat Miami, 91-83, to even their four-of-seven-game playoff series at 2-2. Houston laughed with everyone else when Ward joked that, for a day at least, he knew what it was like to be Latrell Sprewell or Houston, the Knicks' go-to guys whom they have not gone to in the first four games of this Eastern Conference semifinal series. Houston shot 6 for 16 yesterday and scored 17 points; Sprewell was 6 for 15 with 16 points.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALLAN HOUSTON sat next to Charlie Ward yesterday, smiling, enjoying  the scene as his much-maligned teammate basked in the glow of a great Mother's Day game.</p>
        <p>Ward scored 20 points and helped the Knicks beat Miami, 91-83, to even their four-of-seven-game playoff series at 2-2. Houston laughed with everyone else when Ward joked that, for a day at least, he knew what it was like to be Latrell Sprewell or Houston, the Knicks' go-to guys whom they have not gone to in the first four games of this Eastern Conference semifinal series. Houston shot 6 for 16 yesterday and scored 17 points; Sprewell was 6 for 15 with 16 points.</p>
        <p>This was a good day for Ward, a good day for the reserves. Ward's performance was a  tribute as much to fortitude and perseverance as it was to the Knicks' depth.</p>
        <p>The Knicks proved, as they did in Game 2, that they can win games when their main offensive threats are neutralized. But as happy as the story was yesterday, there is something the Knicks know and Miami may know even better: the Knicks need Houston to break free of Dan Majerle's defensive headlock.</p>
        <p>Charlie Ward is tough and solid, but Ward is not the bottomless well the Knicks can go to many more times.</p>
        <p>How can the 34-year-old Majerle hold the  29-year-old Houston in check? Majerle is a great athlete, but he has lost several steps in a 12-year career. He is not as quick as Houston and now simply plays the angles that the Knicks' shooter gives him.</p>
        <p>Houston doesn't bang, Houston doesn't snarl. He's a product of a gentler National Basketball Association. ''A lot of the  2-guards are like Allan,'' Majerle said. ''There are not a lot of physical players in the league anymore since the rules changed.''</p>
        <p>Houston said his strategy was pretty simple: ''When they play me tight, I drive. When they play off me, I shoot.''</p>
        <p>The Heat has not played off Houston since the spring of 1997, when he destroyed Miami by scoring 27 points in Game 1 of the Eastern Conference semifinals. After that game, Heat Coach Pat Riley said, ''When you're not close on him, he can hurt you.''</p>
        <p>Houston has had an odd but game-determining relationship with Miami. After his Game 1 heroics in 1997, he was among the Knicks who left the bench after Game 5 and were suspended for Game 6 or Game 7. Back for Game 7, Houston finished with 25 points but was 1 for 9 in the first half while Miami was building a 17-point lead en route to a 101-90 victory. He cried after that game.</p>
        <p>In the deciding Game 5 in 1998, Houston scored 30 points to lead the Knicks. Of course last year, he eliminated the Heat with his last-second, rim-dancing shot.</p>
        <p>In the four games of this series, Majerle and Bruce Bowen have challenged Houston to demand the ball and take over the game. He has not had to do that, instead being content to let the ball go elsewhere. The Knicks have been fortunate in Games 2 and 4 that  ''elsewhere'' produced. But the Knicks need Houston to be their ''elsewhere'' man.</p>
        <p>Yesterday Houston scored 3 points in the third quarter. In the crucial fourth he hit a 3-pointer with 10 minutes 19 seconds left to put the Knicks up by 7 and another 3 with 8:03 to put the Knicks up by 8.</p>
        <p>''I tried something a little different,'' Majerle said later. ''He burned me a couple times and I went back to doing what I'd been doing.'' Namely, clobbering Houston.</p>
        <p>In a way, this Heat series reopens last season's debate over the Knicks' so-called evolving style of play -- moving from Riley's strong-arming to a more streamlined, fast-paced game that seems to fit Houston, Sprewell and Marcus Camby.</p>
        <p>Up tempo has been better for the Van Gundy Knicks. In the 19 regular-season games the Knicks scored 100 points or more, they were 17-2.</p>
        <p>In 55 playoff games under Jeff Van Gundy, the Knicks are 13-20 when they score fewer than 90 points but 18-4 when scoring more than 90.</p>
        <p>Van Gundy interprets these numbers to  mean the opposition is playing horrible defense, not that the Knicks are simply doing what they do best.</p>
        <p>Last week Van Gundy spoke admiringly of the good old days when Oakley and Mason and Anthony Bonner and Greg Anthony  were part of the Knicks' mauling squad.  Truth is, the Knicks are better in transition and more lethal in transition.</p>
        <p>In transition, Houston leaves Majerle behind. When Van Gundy reverts to that wretched Rileyball, as he did in Games 1 and 3, his team loses. The Knicks go into these Heat games and forget they have jets. That they can fly. Allan Houston is critical to the flight pattern.</p>
        <p>Sooner or later, the Knicks are going to need Houston to reach the Eastern Conference finals. He cannot be quiet if the Knicks are going to advance.</p>
        <p>Things are going to get rougher. The Heat will be getting desperate. The question is, will the Knicks get down-and-dirty desperate with them, or will they take the expeditious route?</p>
        <p>I believe they can fly. They better.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
