<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rebel Group in Sierra Leone Frees 18 U.N. Peacekeepers</title>
    <meta content="Y15LEO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DD103BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rebel Group in Sierra Leone Frees 18 U.N. Peacekeepers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <dateline>FREETOWN, Sierra Leone, May 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>18 UN peacekeepers among more than 500 held hostage by rebel forces in Sierra Leone since beginning of May are released; heavy fighting reported between pro-government forces in Masiaka, 35 miles east of capital of Freetown (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eighteen United Nations peacekeepers among more than 500 held hostage by rebel forces since the beginning of the month were released over the weekend, United Nations officials said today.</p>
        <p>The Revolutionary United Front permitted the peacekeepers, including 11 Indian soldiers and 7 military observers of various nationalities, to rejoin troops stationed in the eastern town of Kailahun, said David Wimhurst, the spokesman for the United Nations force here. The 18, who were in good health, were freed after negotiations between Indian peacekeepers in Kailahun and local rebels, Mr. Wimhurst said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eighteen United Nations peacekeepers among more than 500 held hostage by rebel forces since the beginning of the month were released over the weekend, United Nations officials said today.</p>
        <p>The Revolutionary United Front permitted the peacekeepers, including 11 Indian soldiers and 7 military observers of various nationalities, to rejoin troops stationed in the eastern town of Kailahun, said David Wimhurst, the spokesman for the United Nations force here. The 18, who were in good health, were freed after negotiations between Indian peacekeepers in Kailahun and local rebels, Mr. Wimhurst said.</p>
        <p>The release brought the number of hostages still being held to 486, most of whom are from Zambia.</p>
        <p>The president of neighboring Liberia, Charles Taylor, said tonight that 139 more peacekeepers were being released into Liberian custody, according to The Associated Press.  But the United Nations could not confirm these reports. ''It's a surprise to us,'' said Phil Winslow, a spokesman for the United Nations force in Freetown. Mr. Taylor has backed the Revolutionary United Front in the past and has been asked by Western nations to negotiate for the release of the hostages.</p>
        <p>The Indian troops remain armed in Kailahun, a town near the Liberian border, but are surrounded by followers of the rebel leader, Foday Sankoh. Kailahun, which long served as a base for Mr. Sankoh's forces, was one of the last areas where United Nations peacekeepers had been allowed to deploy before a rebel uprising early this month.</p>
        <p>Despite the release, reports reached the capital today of heavy fighting between rebels and pro-government forces in Masiaka, an important junction town about 35 miles east of here. Soldiers and militiamen loyal to the government, backed by peacekeepers and British soldiers, have pushed the rebels into the hinterland in recent days, since they came as near as Waterloo, about 18 miles from the capital.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, 1,000 British marines arrived aboard ships that remained anchored off the shore of Freetown. The fleet, which carries jet fighters and attack helicopters, reinforced the 700 British paratroopers already here. British officials here and in London have said that Britain's presence in Sierra Leone is only to offer assistance to the United Nations, even as British newspapers have speculated about the real extent of their involvement and suggested that they are now leading the peacekeeping operation.</p>
        <p>Gen. Sir Charles Guthrie, the chief of defense staff and Britain's top soldier, visited Freetown today, meeting with President Ahmed Tejan Kabbah and Maj. Gen. Vijay K. Jetley, the commander of the multinational peacekeeping troops. At a news conference with General Jetley, General Guthrie reiterated his government's message. ''We are not involved in combat,'' he said. ''And we've said we will not be.''</p>
        <p>General Jetley, an Indian, defended his command of the 9,000-member force, which many have criticized as disorganized and unprepared. The peacekeeping mission changed suddenly from a neutral force to one engaged in combat, he said.</p>
        <p>General Jetley said establishing contact with Mr. Sankoh, who vanished after a violent demonstration at his house last Monday, was crucial to obtaining the release of the remaining hostages. ''He's the cult figure of the R.U.F.,'' he said. ''I think we have to negotiate with him. He's the one who's still calling the shots.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
