<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Casinos Put Money in Race In New Jersey</title>
    <meta content="15FUND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic City (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Clifford J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wynn, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trump, Donald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gormley, William L (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Atlantic City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDB103BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Casinos Put Money in Race In New Jersey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Levy, Clifford J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>State Senator William L. Gormley, leading contender for Republican nomination for United States Senate from New Jersey, received $40,000 for his campaign in early March at fund raiser in Las Vegas hosted by Steve Wynn; Donald Trump held similar event for Gormley that raised $55,000; Gormerly has championed effort by New Jersey in recent years to spend more than $200 million to subsidize opening of Wynn casino in Atlantic City (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State Senator William L. Gormley, a leading contender for the Republican nomination for United States Senate from New Jersey, slipped away from the campaign trail one day in early March for an unpublicized visit to Las Vegas. He was not treated like a typical tourist.</p>
        <p>There to greet Mr. Gormley at Le Cirque restaurant in the Bellagio Hotel, Steve Wynn's sumptuous new fun house, was the gambling magnate himself. Mr. Wynn had gathered casino executives for a fund-raiser that drew about $40,000 in donations for Mr. Gormley, who in recent years has championed an effort by New Jersey to spend more than $200 million to subsidize the opening of a Wynn casino in Atlantic City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State Senator William L. Gormley, a leading contender for the Republican nomination for United States Senate from New Jersey, slipped away from the campaign trail one day in early March for an unpublicized visit to Las Vegas. He was not treated like a typical tourist.</p>
        <p>There to greet Mr. Gormley at Le Cirque restaurant in the Bellagio Hotel, Steve Wynn's sumptuous new fun house, was the gambling magnate himself. Mr. Wynn had gathered casino executives for a fund-raiser that drew about $40,000 in donations for Mr. Gormley, who in recent years has championed an effort by New Jersey to spend more than $200 million to subsidize the opening of a Wynn casino in Atlantic City.</p>
        <p>Later in the month, another casino impresario, Donald J. Trump, held a similar event for Mr. Gormley at Trump Tower in Manhattan. The proceeds: $55,000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gormley has amassed far more money than his three Republican opponents, in large part by attracting support from casinos and others tied to the gambling industry -- donors over whom he wields considerable authority as Atlantic City's state senator and chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee, which handles most casino legislation.</p>
        <p>Under New Jersey law, Mr. Gormley and other state officials are usually barred from accepting donations from casino executives and employees. The law is intended to prevent corruption, or at a minimum the appearance of a conflict of interest, when state officials render decisions that affect millions of dollars in Atlantic City casino profits.</p>
        <p>But the law applies to state and local elections in New Jersey, not to federal ones. And Mr. Gormley has declined to abide by it voluntarily in the Senate race to succeed Frank R. Lautenberg, a Democrat who is retiring.</p>
        <p>In a Republican race between little-known candidates relying on advertising to break through to voters, Mr. Gormley's casino ties and stockpile of contributions, now about $1.9 million after expenditures, could prove a critical asset in the final days before the June 6 primary.</p>
        <p>When it comes to gambling in New Jersey, it would be difficult to overstate the influence of Mr. Gormley. He spearheaded measures that allowed companies to expand their casino holdings, permitted casinos to stay open around the clock and let gamblers use credit cards to pay for chips. He wrote a plan to channel a state tax on casino revenues back into subsidies for new casino properties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gormley said the donations from the casino industry were legal and did not affect how he carried out his job in Trenton.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that it's an issue,'' he said in an interview. ''I have represented my district well, and I have represented the state with integrity. This is an industry that is a vital part of the state and has a right on the federal level to participate.''</p>
        <p>But his casino ties could turn into a major issue if he becomes the Republican nominee. Pamela Garfield, a spokeswoman for Common Cause New Jersey, an advocacy group that seeks tighter campaign finance laws, criticized Mr. Gormley, saying he was following the letter, not the spirit, of the law.</p>
        <p>Ms. Garfield said Mr. Gormley's decision to raise casino money underscored flaws in the system. ''As candidates are feeling more and more pressure to raise money, they are going to be forced to press their ethical boundaries,'' she said. ''His acceptance of casino money is a symptom of a broader problem.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gormley is not the only candidate in the primary to reap money from people with an interest in official action. One rival, United States Representative Robert D. Franks of Union County, has been a favorite of political action committees based in Washington. Another, James W. Treffinger, the Essex County executive, has raised money from county employees and from law firms and others with county contracts.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Gormley's connection to the casinos has provided him with an edge. He has taken in more than $200,000 from casino executives and their spouses, out of $2.1 million in total contributions. He has raised about $68,000 from Nevada alone, nearly as much as he has raised from New York State, the records show.</p>
        <p>Park Place Entertainment, Mirage Resorts, Boyd Gaming, Mandalay Resort Group, Showboat, Trump Taj Mahal, Trump Plaza, Trump Marina, Resorts, Treasure Island, Harrah's, Golden Nugget, Bally's Park Place, Caesars, Tropicana, Sands, Atlantic City Hilton -- executives from most of the major casinos in Atlantic City and in Las Vegas and their corporate parents have given, mindful that even if Mr. Gormley loses, he will remain a state senator. (He is up for re-election for his state term in 2001). He has even received contributions from executives in the Mississippi riverboat gambling industry.</p>
        <p>In interviews, the casino executives asserted that they were not looking for something in return from Mr. Gormley, though they acknowledged that it was not a good idea to offend him.</p>
        <p>''I would say he is somebody with a great deal of power in Atlantic City, a great deal of respect in Atlantic City,'' said Mr. Trump, who has feuded with Mr. Gormley in the past over the state's effort to court Mr. Wynn. ''And certainly it is a lot easier if he is on your side.''</p>
        <p>Alan Feldman, a spokesman for Mr. Wynn, whose company, Mirage Resorts, is being bought by MGM Grand, said Mr. Gormley ''has shown leadership that stands out from the pack.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trump said he opposed the ban on casino donations to state candidates in New Jersey, adding that no such rule existed in Nevada. He contended that the New Jersey ban infringed on the industry's right to take part in the political process. That view was echoed to some extent by Mr. Gormley himself, who said he would support weakening the ban, though he would not push to change it because he did not think that a majority of lawmakers would approve such a move.</p>
        <p>In defending the donations, Mr. Gormley said they formed a relatively small percentage of his total treasury. But he acknowledged that he had also received hundreds of thousands of dollars more from donors who were tied to the industry and cared about his decisions, including lawyers and real estate developers, but would not be barred from giving under the state law because they were not casino employees.</p>
        <p>For instance, Mr. Gormley attracts money from people whose firms and companies have contracts with the Casino Reinvestment Development Authority, a state agency that collects taxes from casinos and spends the revenues on projects in Atlantic City and elsewhere in the state. In Trenton, Mr. Gormley is considered to possess virtual veto power over the development authority's activities.</p>
        <p>Lawyers at Connell, Foley, a law firm that received $1.3 million in fees from the authority last year, donated about $28,000 to the Gormley campaign. Lawyers at another firm that has worked for the authority, St. John &amp; Wayne, gave $20,000, while lawyers at a third firm with authority contracts, Riker, Danzig, Scherer, Hyland &amp; Perretti, gave roughly $20,000.</p>
        <p>Executives at Frederic R. Harris, an engineering company that is helping to construct a $330 million tunnel intended to help Mr. Wynn build a new property in the marina area, contributed $17,000.</p>
        <p>Asked about those donations, Mr. Gormley said: ''What I have tried to do over the years is to create an environment of economic growth. People who have participated in that in one form or another think that I have done a pretty good job. Even my critics would say that.''</p>
        <p>To parry questions about casino money, Mr. Gormley's aides have sought to draw attention to fund-raising by Representative Franks and by Mr. Treffinger, the Essex County executive, both of whom have not collected as much money as Mr. Gormley has but have raised significant amounts from people with business before their offices. (A fourth candidate, Murray Sabrin, a college professor, has raised $300,000).</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks has collected 25 percent of the $1.35 million he has raised from political action committees, particularly those interested in legislation before two committees he serves on, the Budget Committee and the Transportation and Infrastructure Committee. He has received money from PAC's representing the American Pilots Association, the American Road and Transportation Builders Association, the American Short Line and Regional Railroad Association and the United Transportation Union.</p>
        <p>Charlie Smith, an adviser to Mr. Franks, dismissed suggestions that those contributions were related to Mr. Franks's votes in Congress.</p>
        <p>''Political action committee contributions,'' Mr. Smith said, ''are nothing more than the aggregated contributions of an industry or group of people who wish to compete in the political process, alongside special interests such as the casinos.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Treffinger, who took office as the county executive in 1995, has raised more than $100,000 from people who work for the county and another $100,000 from lawyers at firms with contracts with county agencies, out of his total of $1.1 million. He is not accepting PAC money.</p>
        <p>Matthew J. Kirnan, Mr. Treffinger's treasurer, said the campaign had not focused fund-raising appeals on county workers.</p>
        <p>''With respect to Essex County employees, most of them are residents of Essex County and really respect the fact that Jim has changed things,'' Mr. Kirnan said.</p>
        <p>Of the law firms, the biggest contributor was DeCotiis, Fitzpatrick, Gluck, Hayden &amp; Cole, whose partners have close ties to both major political parties. Its lawyers donated $55,000 to the Treffinger campaign. Another significant benefactor was McCarter &amp; English, whose lawyers gave about $10,000.</p>
        <p>Decotiis, Fitzpatrick represents the Essex County Improvement Authority, which paid the firm $514,000 last year, officials said. McCarter &amp; English handles the authority's bond work, receiving $380,000 last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirnan said, ''Both firms were doing work for the county long before Jim got here, and they will be doing work afterward.''</p>
        <p>Eric D. Wisler, a partner at Decotiis, Fitzpatrick, said his firm was retained by county agencies because of its skills, not its donations.</p>
        <p>''I'm not naive to say that if you don't contribute and support your friends in their endeavors, that others won't step in behind you and try to take your place,'' Mr. Wisler said. ''But certainly Jim has never exhibited to me the kind of vindictiveness that people associate with politicians -- that if you don't contribute to politicians, you're gone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
