<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Artists' Retreat Reaches Out; Yaddo Celebrates an Anniversary by Shedding a Bit of Its Mystery</title>
    <meta content="15YADD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000518T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yaddo Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yaddo (Artists' Community)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dobrzynski, Judith H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD7133BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Artists' Retreat Reaches Out; Yaddo Celebrates an Anniversary by Shedding a Bit of Its Mystery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH H. DOBRZYNSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dobrzynski, Judith H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Festival of concerts, readings, exhibitions, screenings and open studios and symposiums is being scheduled to honor 100th anniversary of decision to turn 55-room mansion in Saratoga Springs, NY, into artists' retreat known as Yaddo; more than 5,500 writers, composers and visual artists have stayed there for periods of two weeks to two months over the years; festival will begin Apr 15 and run until October; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The ''Private Property'' sign posted just inside Yaddo, the renowned artists' colony in Saratoga Springs, N.Y., has always seemed apt literally and metaphorically. Just as visitors are allowed in the rose garden but not near the 19th-century mansion where artists work, Yaddo has been willing to bask in the glory of the luminaries like Truman Capote and Virgil Thompson who blossomed there, but it has discouraged most publicity about itself.</p>
        <p>Yaddo has never even published a complete list of the more than 5,500 writers, composers and visual artists who have stayed there for periods of two weeks to two months over the years. ''There was always the sense that publicity was bad,'' said Michael G. Sundell, Yaddo's president. ''It was tied to the idea of Yaddo being a retreat and not wanting to pollute that.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The ''Private Property'' sign posted just inside Yaddo, the renowned artists' colony in Saratoga Springs, N.Y., has always seemed apt literally and metaphorically. Just as visitors are allowed in the rose garden but not near the 19th-century mansion where artists work, Yaddo has been willing to bask in the glory of the luminaries like Truman Capote and Virgil Thompson who blossomed there, but it has discouraged most publicity about itself.</p>
        <p>Yaddo has never even published a complete list of the more than 5,500 writers, composers and visual artists who have stayed there for periods of two weeks to two months over the years. ''There was always the sense that publicity was bad,'' said Michael G. Sundell, Yaddo's president. ''It was tied to the idea of Yaddo being a retreat and not wanting to pollute that.''</p>
        <p>But this year is different. In celebration of its 100th anniversary, Yaddo is sponsoring a very public birthday party: a festival of concerts, readings, exhibitions, screenings, open studios and symposiums in New York and Saratoga Springs that began on April 15 and runs through October.</p>
        <p>Something else is unusual, too. In the past, on the rare occasions that Yaddo people spoke about the retreat they usually dwelled on the colony's vaunted history: on Sylvia Plath, Clyfford Still, Katherine Anne Porter, William Carlos Williams and Leonard Bernstein (who went to Yaddo just once but whose antics have always been good for an anecdote or three).</p>
        <p>For the festival, though, the spotlight is more on the artists of the 1980's and 90's. ''The artists involved were insistent on it,'' Mr. Sundell said. ''They wanted to focus on work being done now or recently, because they think highly of a lot of the people they met there.''</p>
        <p>And so the festival includes world premieres of musical pieces by David Del Tredici, Richard Danielpour, Steven Burke and Dan Coleman. It offers readings by Oscar Hijuelos, A. M. Holmes and Robert Stone. It has exhibits of work by Martin Puryear, Joyce Kosloff and Kristen Jones, and performance pieces by John Kelly and William Pope.L. For ''Friendships in Arcadia: Writers and Artists at Yaddo in the 90's,'' on view through Saturday at Art in General in TriBeCa, Yaddo enlisted 25 alums to write wall texts for work by artists. (The complete schedule is listed on www.yaddo.org or www.artandculture.com.)</p>
        <p>In addition to celebrating its centurylong support of creativity, Yaddo has another reason for its newfound willingness to trade some mystique for visibility. A few years ago Yaddo started a fund-raising campaign to assure its future, seeking resources to keep the property in shape and add the occasional upgrade. The goal -- $8.5 million by the end of this year -- is nearly realized, but Yaddo's trustees say they need to attract more donors.</p>
        <p>''If we were going to ask people for money, they had to have heard of Yaddo,'' Mr. Sundell said.</p>
        <p>That meant raising its profile, specifically in New York. ''We do not have the capacity to do something nationally,'' Mr. Sundell said. ''But we could do something in the arts capital of the world, the media capital of the world.''</p>
        <p>So the festival is an investment of sorts. The only money-making part is the annual benefit gala, a silent auction and dinner that takes place tomorrow. Ticket prices for the other events, Mr. Sundell said, were purposely kept low to help spread word of Yaddo; some are free.</p>
        <p>The story of Yaddo (an invented word meant to rhyme with shadow) begins in 1881 when Spencer Trask, a New York financier, and his wife, a poet named Katrina, bought a piney 400-acre estate in the Hudson Valley, land that once held a tavern frequented by Edgar Allan Poe and other literati of the 1830's and 40's.</p>
        <p>A fire destroyed their first home there, but in 1893 the Trasks build a Victorian mansion, a dark-wood and heavy-furniture kind of place that became the scene of famous house parties to which the Trasks invited artists, authors, composers, statesmen and industrialists.</p>
        <p>But there was tragedy as well: the Trasks' four children died young. Lacking heirs, the couple decided in 1900 to create a trust establishing an artists' retreat after their deaths. They imagined a place where artists of all kinds, selected by peer-review panels, could live for two weeks to two months, able to work in peace without daily obligations or interruptions (or, in the last half-century, television).</p>
        <p>Trask died in 1909, his wife in 1922, and Yaddo welcomed its first crop of artists in the summer of 1926.</p>
        <p>Thus Yaddo is cheating a little, celebrating the anniversary of the idea of Yaddo rather than its 100th year of operation. (This isn't the first 100th anniversary, either. In 1993 Yaddo marked the 100th anniversary of its 55-room mansion by opening the doors to public tours for the first time, at $12 a head.)</p>
        <p>''This is the most important date,'' Mr. Sundell argued, ''because this is when they made the decision to create Yaddo, when they signed the papers.'' But he conceded that the colony will undoubtedly have another centennial in 2026.</p>
        <p>In any case the formula has not changed. In the mid-90's, when writing or re-evaluating mission statements was in vogue at corporations and nonprofit institutions, Yaddo's board re-examined the Trasks' vision but decided against changes.</p>
        <p>''I find it fascinating that a 19th-century idea seems to work now,'' Mr. Sundell said. ''That's more interesting than when it worked for John Cheever or Aaron Copland.''</p>
        <p>Plenty of artists still want to make the trip to Saratoga. Each year about 2,000 apply for about 200 spaces. They send resumes, work samples and references, all considered by established artists as they choose the best and the most promising.</p>
        <p>Once there, artists live in somewhat faded Victorian quarters and gather for communal breakfasts and dinners. Quiet time -- reserved for working, or at least not disturbing those who are working -- lasts from 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. and starts again after 10 p.m. What happens in the evening hours depends on who is there and who is willing to plan piano recitals or sing-alongs or readings.</p>
        <p>But the real bonus comes in Yaddo's effect on the work. Most artists, though not all, who have spent time there speak in glowing terms of the surge in creativity and productivity fostered by the supportive environment, the lack of everyday cares and the presence of other artists.</p>
        <p>Many who have spent time at Yaddo keep in touch, and each year about a third of the donations Yaddo receives come directly from alumni, many of whom also actively solicit other gifts. Recently, the sculptor George Rickey and the novelist Rick Moody and his family endowed residencies.</p>
        <p>One of Yaddo's largest contributions came when the author Patricia Highsmith showed her gratitude. Upon her death in 1995 she left her entire estate, worth about $3 million, to Yaddo, even though she only went there once, for two months in 1948. While there she completed ''Strangers on a Train,'' which Alfred Hitchcock adapted into a film in 1951.</p>
        <p>The festival itself is another testament to the loyalty of the artists: so many are contributing work. Several composers wrote pro bono pieces despite a tight deadline.</p>
        <p>''I started working on this about a year and a half ago,'' said George Tsontakis, the composer who organized the musical offerings. ''We brainstormed what we could do -- Michael had grandiose ideas -- and most of the composers squeezed it in.''</p>
        <p>Writers also complied. Several are giving readings. Allan Gurganus, Aileen Ward and Mr. Moody wrote new chapters for Yaddo's old booklet ''Six Decades at Yaddo,'' which is being reissued as ''A Century at Yaddo'' in hardcover, aimed for the first time at the public.</p>
        <p>Anne Carson, Sapphire and Alfred Corn are among those who composed wall texts for the art exhibition, which was organized by Barbara Toll. After its run in Manhattan it will go on view at the Hyde Collection in Glens Falls, N.Y., from May 28 through Sept. 4.</p>
        <p>Several visual artists are opening their studios in the Bronx, Brooklyn, Manhattan and Queens to visitors on June 17 and 18.</p>
        <p>And other organizations, like the Orpheus Chamber Orchestra, Symphony Space and the New York Philharmonic, have joined in for the festival, raising the possibility of future joint events with Yaddo.</p>
        <p>Despite all the hoopla, the public still is not getting close to Yaddo. None of the events are taking place there. ''You could not destroy the place in order to celebrate it,'' Mr. Sundell said.</p>
        <p>The estate has seen a few changes, though. With computers and other electronic devices so much in use by artists, new phone lines for modems are being installed, and a new viewing area for videos is being set up on the estate.</p>
        <p>There is still no television, but there is more contact with the outside world because many artists are now bringing cell phones rather than relying on the communal public phone in the mansion.</p>
        <p>And Yaddo's population is evolving. ''Skin tones are more varied, we're more international, there's a lot more film work and some performing artists and the occasional choreographer,'' said Mr. Sundell, who will retire in September.</p>
        <p>His replacement, Elaina Richardson, the editor in chief of Elle magazine, is expected to do more fund-raising, more publicly.</p>
        <p>But both insist that some things at Yaddo -- the tried-and-true conventions meant to nurture creativity -- will never change.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 18, 2000, Thursday  An article on Monday about events surrounding the 100th anniversary of Yaddo, the artists' colony in Saratoga Springs, N.Y., misspelled the surname of one composer who worked there. He was Virgil Thomson, not Thompson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 18, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Monday about events surrounding the 100th anniversary of Yaddo, the artists' colony in Saratoga Springs, N.Y., misspelled the surname of one composer who worked there. He was Virgil Thomson, not Thompson.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
