<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Decision Is Imminent on Knight's Future</title>
    <meta content="15BOBB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knight, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brand, Myles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DC103BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Decision Is Imminent on Knight's Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, May 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Knight's coaching career at Indiana is in hands of university president Myles Brand, who will announce whether Knight will remain coach or be replaced as a result of investigation into alleged abusive behavior (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bob Knight's coaching career at Indiana is now in the hands of the university president, Myles Brand, who will announce Monday whether Knight will remain the head of the Hoosier men's basketball program or be replaced as a result of an investigation into alleged abusive behavior.</p>
        <p>Brand met today for 2 hours 20 minutes with eight of the university's nine trustees. Two of them, John Walda and Frederick Eichhorn, presented evidence of an investigation they began on March 23 when a former player, Neil Reed, alleged that Knight had put a hand to his throat during practice -- an allegation that was later corroborated by a videotape of the practice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bob Knight's coaching career at Indiana is now in the hands of the university president, Myles Brand, who will announce Monday whether Knight will remain the head of the Hoosier men's basketball program or be replaced as a result of an investigation into alleged abusive behavior.</p>
        <p>Brand met today for 2 hours 20 minutes with eight of the university's nine trustees. Two of them, John Walda and Frederick Eichhorn, presented evidence of an investigation they began on March 23 when a former player, Neil Reed, alleged that Knight had put a hand to his throat during practice -- an allegation that was later corroborated by a videotape of the practice.</p>
        <p>Late Saturday, Brand had met at his residence in Bloomington with Knight for two hours in what a university spokesman described as a vigorous discussion of the coach's behavior and status.</p>
        <p>The spokesman, Christopher Simpson, said Knight requested the meeting upon returning from a vacation in the Bahamas. It capped a day in which Knight issued an extraordinary public apology for his temper and past confrontations and made it clear he wanted to keep his job, which he has had for 29 seasons.</p>
        <p>''I have always been too confrontational, especially when I know I'm right,'' Knight said in a statement. ''I know as well as anyone does: I have to develop a more diplomatic approach. I'm not very good at just forgetting something and going on, and I am truly sorry about that.''</p>
        <p>Because today's trustees' meeting was an executive session, no vote could be taken, under the state's open meeting laws. The absent trustee, Stephen Ferguson, excused himself from the meeting because he is Knight's lawyer and negotiated the coach's contract.</p>
        <p>Simpson stressed that the final decision remains with Brand; it will be announced at a 4 p.m. Monday news conference. If Brand chooses to discipline Knight, he can fire him, administer a penalty or ask him to resign.</p>
        <p>''We received information, deliberated, discussed and received advice,'' Simpson said of the trustees' meeting. ''No decision has been reached. He has a full range of options, and his final decision will be made in concurrence with the board's wishes.''</p>
        <p>Walda issued a brief statement in which he said, ''The process has been productive and we're just about to conclude it.''</p>
        <p>In the months since the trustees were charged with investigating Knight, the coach has been accused of choking and punching an assistant sports information director, Kit Klingelhoffer, in the mid-1970's; intimidating an athletic department secretary, Jeanette Hartgraves, by throwing a vase against the wall in her office in 1988; accosting an assistant coach, Ron Felling, in late 1999; and upbraiding his boss, the athletic director Clarence Doninger, in a near altercation earlier this year.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
