<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Power Games Play Into Hands Of the Devils</title>
    <meta content="15DEVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Flyers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Philadelphia Flyers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2DA103BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Power Games Play Into Hands Of the Devils</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, May 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils defeat Philadelphia Flyers, 4-1, in first game of National Hockey League Eastern Conference championship series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils imposed their power early today, and it paid off handsomely: a goal 55 seconds into the game on their first attempt to test Philadelphia's rookie goaltender, Brian Boucher.</p>
        <p>The Devils scored two more goals in the first period, 26 seconds apart, and went on to win, 4-1, in the opening game of the Eastern Conference finals this afternoon at the First Union Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils imposed their power early today, and it paid off handsomely: a goal 55 seconds into the game on their first attempt to test Philadelphia's rookie goaltender, Brian Boucher.</p>
        <p>The Devils scored two more goals in the first period, 26 seconds apart, and went on to win, 4-1, in the opening game of the Eastern Conference finals this afternoon at the First Union Center.</p>
        <p>Every piece of the Devils' strategy worked almost to perfection against the Flyers. They got a goal from Bobby Holik, his first in 29 playoff games dating to 1997, and a power-play goal from Claude Lemieux. Scott Niedermayer scored the first goal and Petr Sykora regained a one-goal lead for the Devils after Mark Recchi scored for the Flyers at 8 minutes 20 seconds of the first period to tie it at 1-1.</p>
        <p>The Devils played with a great deal of discipline, taking only two penalties against the most efficient team in the playoffs with the man advantage. Not only did the Devils keep the Flyers without a power-play goal, they also scored one , by Lemieux at 5:19 of the third period, to seal the victory.</p>
        <p>The four-of-seven-game series will remain in Philadelphia for Game 2 on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>The Devils scored in the opening minute for the second consecutive game. Sykora scored 18 seconds into Game 6 the Maple Leafs on May 8.</p>
        <p>Today, Niedermayer's goal put the Devils ahead quickly in their first playoff meeting with the Flyers since 1995, when the Devils defeated Philadelphia in six games and went on to sweep the Detroit Red Wings in the Stanley Cup finals.</p>
        <p>''That early goal was huge,'' said John Madden, the Devils' indefatigable center and best player among the forwards who were killing penalties. ''We started early against Toronto and we wanted to do it here again.''</p>
        <p>Niedermayer, who took a pass from Randy McKay, scored with a shot from the right circle that sailed over Boucher's glove.</p>
        <p>Niedermayer's goal stunned the sellout crowd of 19,779 and the Flyers, who got the crowd back in the game eight minutes later when Recchi gathered a rebound of Daymond Langkow's shot and beat Martin Brodeur from the slot.</p>
        <p>Brodeur faced 36 shots, six times the number he faced against Toronto on May 8, when the Devils eliminated the Maple Leafs and set a league record for the fewest shots allowed in a game, regular season and playoffs -- six.</p>
        <p>''After the six shots that I had the last game, it's funny that I had the most saves in the playoffs in this game,'' Brodeur said. ''They saw what Toronto went through with us and they were taking shots from everywhere. It paid off for them with a goal.''</p>
        <p>Each team took 16 shots in the opening period, a wide-open affair that was more beneficial to the Devils, who seemed to have more purpose in their play once they entered the offensive  zone.</p>
        <p>Flyers Coach Craig Ramsay was rather impressed with the Devils' play in the first period.</p>
        <p>''They made some good plays, and they got some nifty goals real quickly,'' Ramsey said.</p>
        <p>Sykora scored on a backhander from the slot off a Jason Arnott pass, and Holik scored on a one-timer from the left circle with 1:56 left in the period. That goal was set up by Sergei Brylin's cross-ice feed.</p>
        <p>''That was the hockey game right there,'' Boucher said of the goals. ''I can't give them three goals like that in the first.''</p>
        <p>Holik made several big contributions. Devils Coach Larry Robinson used the line of Brylin, Holik and McKay to neutralize John LeClair and Recchi, Philadelphia's top players. Lemieux was one of several Devils who acknowledged the defensive contribution of Holik's line.</p>
        <p>''The key today was that Holik's line played a great game, and it was great to see Bobby get on the scoreboard,'' Lemieux said of Holik, who scored his first playoff goal since the 1997.</p>
        <p>''He's one of those streaky players like myself, and I think he's going to get hot.''</p>
        <p>Lemieux had 13 goals in the 1995 playoffs, when he was named the Most Valuable Player in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Holik, who scored his first playoff goal since Game 5 against the Montreal Canadiens in 1997, is never satisfied with his play or that of the Devils. He was the most severe critic of the Devils' play in the second period, when they had a two-goal lead.</p>
        <p>Robinson was also unhappy with the action in that period. His Devils had only four shots in each of the final two periods. ''We were a little too extreme defensively,'' Robinson said. ''Other times, we were also too extreme offensively. We were a little rusty after not playing for six days. We have to get our game legs back a little bit. Practicing and playing games are two different things.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
