<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ward Is Father Of Reinvention As a Go-To Guy</title>
    <meta content="15KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1DA103BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ward Is Father Of Reinvention As a Go-To Guy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbockers defeat Miami Heat, 91-83; tie Eastern Conference semifinal playoff series, 2-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A pivotal shot by Allan Houston struck awkwardly off the rim and ricocheted toward the nervous folks in the front row. But in one unruffled motion, Charlie Ward leaped over the sideline and hovered like a hummingbird as he grasped the ball, surveyed the desperate situation and then whipped the wayward rebound into the hands of Latrell Sprewell.</p>
        <p>At this moment, with just over two minutes left in a game on the verge of slipping away, the player who is so rooted in his faith began a spiritual healing for the Knicks in their second-round series against the Miami Heat. In one mesmerizing solo finish that left the Madison Square Garden crowd drenching the unassuming Ward with chants of ''Char-lie, Char-lie,'' the Knicks' hard-shell point guard was as tough as Samsonite while he scored the team's final 9 points, grabbed its last two rebounds and enabled the Knicks to preserve Game 4 with a 91-83 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A pivotal shot by Allan Houston struck awkwardly off the rim and ricocheted toward the nervous folks in the front row. But in one unruffled motion, Charlie Ward leaped over the sideline and hovered like a hummingbird as he grasped the ball, surveyed the desperate situation and then whipped the wayward rebound into the hands of Latrell Sprewell.</p>
        <p>At this moment, with just over two minutes left in a game on the verge of slipping away, the player who is so rooted in his faith began a spiritual healing for the Knicks in their second-round series against the Miami Heat. In one mesmerizing solo finish that left the Madison Square Garden crowd drenching the unassuming Ward with chants of ''Char-lie, Char-lie,'' the Knicks' hard-shell point guard was as tough as Samsonite while he scored the team's final 9 points, grabbed its last two rebounds and enabled the Knicks to preserve Game 4 with a 91-83 victory.</p>
        <p>In a rare show of emotion, Ward punched his fist in the air and even allowed a smile to cross an often stoic facade. Why not indulge in the moment? Ward knew who was watching him for the first time. His 11-week-old son, Caleb, spent yesterday afternoon oblivious to the tension as he drifted in and out of a sleep at his first Knick game. Swaddled in a Knick jersey, Caleb awoke to find his father had scored 9 of his playoff career-high 20 points in the fourth quarter to even the four-of-seven-game series at two games apiece.</p>
        <p>''Man, I felt like I should have my own team,'' Ward said as Houston laughed next to him on the postgame podium. ''For the first time, I felt like Allan and Latrell, you know, like the go-to guy.''</p>
        <p>Ward gave the Knicks renewed hope for Wednesday's Game 5 in Miami after their crushing loss in Friday's Game 3 -- an ending punctuated by Anthony's Carter's controversial floater -- and he also allayed the concerns by Jeff Van Gundy over how his team would respond.</p>
        <p>Less than an hour before Game 4, in an interview room deep in the Garden, Van Gundy called his team ''a fragile group.''</p>
        <p>Holding all the pieces together, Ward was fearless enough for everyone. In the chaotic end, as Patrick Ewing and Sprewell wilted with turnovers that allowed the Heat to pull within 5 points, at 84-79, Ward's teammates kept looking to him, as if searching for a lighthouse in the fog. With 1 minute 51 seconds left, only 17  seconds after he saved a rebound, the ball went back to Ward, who ducked into the paint and sent a bank shot around the looming Alonzo Mourning.</p>
        <p>As an encore, the old-school Ward, who is about as innovative as a butter churn, pulled a nifty crossover move out his pocket and lofted a jumper over Carter. Then, as the ''Char-lie'' chants grew louder, Ward fielded a pass from Sprewell and slayed whatever hope the Heat had as he sent a 3-pointer down the gut of the net with 36.1 seconds on the game clock. Suddenly, a shaky 5-point lead with 1:30 left was turned into a 10-point advantage by Ward's hustle and nerve.</p>
        <p>A flustered Mourning was not as calm. After prying lose a few critical rebounds from the Knicks -- who were outrebounded for the game, 48-37, but had a 6-4 edge in the fourth quarter -- he failed to capitalize when fouled. With his team down, 84-78, Mourning turned as frozen as he was in Game 2, when he missed 3 of 4 free-throw attempts over an 11-second span. This was the final blow for Mourning's forgettable day. Thanks to several mindless three-second calls he drew and a few aggressive double-teams by the Knicks, Mourning committed 9 of the Heat's 17 turnovers.</p>
        <p>''We gave them gifts constantly,'' said Mourning, who finished with 27 points and 14 rebounds. ''I take full responsibility for that. I am going to be touching the ball quite a bit, and I have to make better decisions. Nine turnovers is not acceptable.''</p>
        <p>Mourning had more turnovers than the Knicks did through three quarters. In a reverse of Game 3, the Knicks protected the ball as if it were as delicate as a hatched chick. After 19 turnovers Friday night, they turned the ball over only 11 times yesterday. Sprewell had four. He was merely one of the Knicks who seemed to fade in and out of the game. Sprewell had 14 first-half points, but finished with 16. He seemed to have a handle on Jamal Mashburn (13 points) but gave up a couple of 3-pointers, too.</p>
        <p>Houston had his moments, as well, but with Dan Majerle sticking to his skin like vinyl, he finished 6 for 16 from the field and scored 17 points. He also gave up 13 points and 12 rebounds to the scrap-metal Majerle.</p>
        <p>During a mostly nondescript afternoon by Ewing (12 points, 11 rebounds), who allowed Mourning a few too many deep catches in the post, he did send down a dunk on the break in the first quarter and drew a foul for a flashy 3-point play.</p>
        <p>''Charlie gave me a nice pass,'' Ewing said. ''I went up and dunked. Only you guys think I'm old.''</p>
        <p>Ward, at age 29, is not exactly young either. But he was the veteran leftover that remained yesterday. After the Heat took away Houston and Sprewell, after Miami sealed off Larry Johnson's post moves and kept Marcus Camby's active body in check, Ward was the one player who had a sliver of room to maneuver. In the open, Ward hit 3 of 6 3-pointers and was part of an 8-for-17 effort by the Knicks from beyond the arc that kept them in front of the Heat most of the game.</p>
        <p>''You can't leave Charlie open,'' said Pat Riley, who drafted Ward when he coached the Knicks. ''You can't expect that he is not going to burn you if you don't play him hard. We didn't not respect him. I thought he took advantage of some real good opportunities and made great plays.''</p>
        <p>He made one after another. But usually, Chris Childs finishes the game. Maybe Van Gundy was going to play Ward anyway, but once Childs picked up his fifth foul with 4:15 remaining, Ward was back on the floor. He picked up from where he left off in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>''We took a 20-second timeout early in the third,'' said Van Gundy, whose team had lost its 42-40 halftime lead and was down, 47-46. ''We were in a little bit of a funk. And Charlie drove -- not offensive, not defensively -- just mentally.''</p>
        <p>That's when Ward darted in for a driving fast-break layup, and emerged from beneath the Heat's lumbering big men unscathed. He was all over the floor, all game long. In the locker room afterward, Childs tapped Ward on the back with his toothbrush, got his attention and said: ''You were like four players out there, Charlie. You were everywhere.''</p>
        <p>Ward shrugged his shoulders, smiled and said, ''Yeah, I guess maybe I was.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>CHARLIE WARD's previous playoff scoring high was 15 points, against the Pacers on May 5, 1998. . . . PATRICK EWING's 12 points gave him 2,680 for his playoff career. He passed BILL RUSSELL's 2,673 points to move into 20th place on the league's career playoff scoring list.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
