<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Africa in an Uphill Fight Against Crime</title>
    <meta content="15AFRI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1199756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illiteracy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illiteracy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E4DC103BF936A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Africa in an Uphill Fight Against Crime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>KWAMASHU, South Africa</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Black South African government struggles to tame one of highest violent crime rates in world, six years after promising to transform apartheid-era police force that savagely enforced white rule into agency that actually solves crime; has failed in efforts to merge all of country's police, including 11 police forces from so-called black homelands, into effective national law-enforcement agency; many officers, trained by white regime to primarily suppress political dissent, have been recruited with little regard to educational qualifications; more than 30 percent of 120,000-member force is illiterate and 11,000 officers lack driver's licenses; breakdown of policing in impoverished township of KwaMashu near Durban discussed; 30 of its 150 police officers cannot read or write, nearly half of 355 guns allocated to precinct were missing and linked to local crimes and nearly 80 percent of reported murders and robberies have gone unsolved over last four years; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this impoverished township of mud shacks and stunted dreams, the killers prowl, the bullets sing and most people no longer hope for justice. And when a national team of inspectors visited the local police station last year, they quickly discovered why.</p>
        <p>More than 200 criminal cases were assigned to detectives who were either dead or dismissed from the force, the team's confidential report shows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In this impoverished township of mud shacks and stunted dreams, the killers prowl, the bullets sing and most people no longer hope for justice. And when a national team of inspectors visited the local police station last year, they quickly discovered why.</p>
        <p>More than 200 criminal cases were assigned to detectives who were either dead or dismissed from the force, the team's confidential report shows.</p>
        <p>Nearly half of the 355 guns allocated to the station were inexplicably missing, and some were linked to local crimes.</p>
        <p>The inspectors found two-year-old blood samples that never made it to the crime lab, forgotten bullets that never underwent ballistics testing. In this community of 2.5 million people near Durban, the station has only one battered van to respond to emergency calls.</p>
        <p>Over the last four years, nearly 80 percent of the reported murders and robberies have gone unsolved.</p>
        <p>Six years after South Africa's first black government promised to transform the apartheid-era police force that savagely enforced white rule into an agency that actually solves crime, justice here still follows its numbingly predictable course. The families weep and most criminals go free.</p>
        <p>The breakdown of policing in KwaMashu reflects both the ugly legacy of apartheid and the missteps of a black government that is still struggling to tame one of the highest violent crime rates in the world.</p>
        <p>In 1994, South Africa's first black government had the unenviable task of merging all the country's police, including 11 police forces that belonged to the so-called black homelands, into one national law enforcement agency. The police officers, who were trained by the white regime primarily to suppress political dissent, were often recruited with little regard to educational qualifications. As a result, they often have to struggle to solve serious offenses: even today, more than 30 percent of the 120,000-member national force is illiterate, and more than 11,000 officers do not have driver's licenses.</p>
        <p>And today the government, like governments in the former Soviet bloc, emerging from authoritarian rule into uncertain democracy, is still struggling to cope.</p>
        <p>Appalled by the collapse of law and order in KwaMashu, the government sent scores of soldiers and police officers from across the country to patrol this besieged community last September as part of a new national assault on crime. And by January of this year, the newcomers had recorded an 21 percent dip in murders and hundreds of arrests.</p>
        <p>But three months ago, the inspectors quietly released a second report with troubling implications for the new strategy. Despite the continuing, high-profile operation here, the inspectors found no improvement in the quality of investigations or crime analysis conducted by local police.</p>
        <p>The confidential reports, which were provided to The New York Times by two senior law-enforcement officials, illustrate the enormous challenge confronting President Thabo Mbeki as he strives to fulfill promises to crack down on crime that he made when taking office last summer.</p>
        <p>''It was doomed to fail,'' said Hlabekisa Mncwango, the acting station commissioner in KwaMashu, of the lagging effort to upgrade the performance of officers here. ''How could we expect improvement?''</p>
        <p>Behind the red-brick walls of this squat, neglected police station, about 30 of the 150 officers cannot read or write. As of last September, not one detective had taken a course in ballistics or forensics, an internal memo shows.</p>
        <p>While the government has promised to upgrade this station, local officers routinely run short of police cars, handcuffs and even colored pins to track robberies and murders on a neighborhood map.</p>
        <p>And high-level officers wonder openly how the community will cope when the team of outsiders -- which has the lion's share of police resources -- leaves.</p>
        <p>''You're talking about creating a new world,'' said Mr. Mncwango, who in January took over the station in KwaMashu. ''Well, we need new people and we need more training. If you put new wine in old skins, does it work? We're telling these policemen to pull themselves up by their bootstraps, but we're not giving them the power or the resources to do it.''</p>
        <p>After the African National Congress came to power in 1994, people here prayed that the new black government would improve law enforcement and purge their memories of years of police incompetence and brutality. But there is no escaping the past in KwaMashu.</p>
        <p>Both the township and the police were created by apartheid. Blacks were forcibly moved here in the 1960's. Some two decades later, the white government began secretly supporting the feared KwaZulu homeland police, an all-black force linked to hit squads, gun running, intimidation and assassinations of supporters of the African National Congress, who dominate this township.</p>
        <p>Today, KwaMashu is a sprawling jumble of cinderblock homes, and lush green hills, mud shacks and twisting dirt roads, a place where the new South Africa still wrestles with its bitter inheritance of poverty, violence and deep-rooted suspicion of the police.</p>
        <p>The police officers here have sworn allegiance to the new flag and promised to ''prevent, combat and investigate crime'' as required by the new Constitution.</p>
        <p>But, like many other officers, they seem to be unable or unwilling to do so.</p>
        <p>Nationally, the police make arrests in only 45 percent of murder cases and 12 percent of robberies in South Africa, compared to 70 percent of murders and 30 percent of robberies in the United States.</p>
        <p>And while the failures of policing here owe much to the past, it is also clear that the black government, too, has stumbled. In the early years, the government focused primarily on building trust between the community and the widely discredited police force, offering human rights courses for officers and creating community forums for citizens to voice concerns.</p>
        <p>Improving basic policing was simply not the top priority.</p>
        <p>''The very basic issues around effective policing were put on the back burner over the past five years,'' said Eric Pelser, who worked as a civilian adviser to the previous Minister of Safety and Security, Sydney Mufamadi, between 1996 and 1999.</p>
        <p>''The political assumption was that the police were competent but brutal,'' said Mr. Pelser, who is now a senior researcher at the Institute for Security Studies. ''What wasn't particularly realized was that some of the brutality came out of basic incompetence.''</p>
        <p>The situation only worsened as crime rates soared and the police force lost 20,000 members through attrition and buyouts. A moratorium on hiring -- intended to pare down the bloated civil service -- meant that a shrinking pool of officers found themselves overloaded with more and more cases.</p>
        <p>In 1996, this country ranked first in the world in the number of murders, rapes, robberies and violent thefts per capita, police statistics show.</p>
        <p>Between 1997 and 1998, the last two full years for which statistics are available, the numbers of robberies, burglaries and thefts soared, while murders held steady and rapes decreased slightly.</p>
        <p>Very soon, the issue of crime, which some government officials had dismissed as mere carping by  disgruntled whites, became increasingly urgent, because it began to be seen as discouraging foreign investment and fueling emigration.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mbeki has been credited for handling the crime issue with an increasing sense of urgency. He replaced Mr. Mufamadi with the more aggressive Steve Tshwete and hired the country's first black police commissioner, Jackie Selebi, a highly regarded former diplomat and administrator.</p>
        <p>The government has also created an elite team of college-educated law enforcement agents, similar to the F.B.I., known as the Scorpions, to tackle organized crime and high-profile cases. And officials are determined to increase the representation of blacks, who currently make up more 50 percent of the force, in the higher ranks.</p>
        <p>Teams of soldiers and officers are temporarily supplementing the staffs of the 217 troubled police stations, including KwaMashu, that handle more than 50 percent of the country's crime. Preliminary results look promising.</p>
        <p>Between July and December, the rapid-response teams set up 18,000 roadblocks, searched 57,000 vehicles, made 53,000 arrests and recorded declines in crime of 12 to 20 percent in Kimberley, Kroonstad and Randburg, officials say. And for the first time in years, public confidence in the police has soared, surveys show.</p>
        <p>But officials here say the plan still leaves troubled stations without staff, resources and training to cope after the outsiders leave.</p>
        <p>For while the quick-response team, mostly made up of white officers, came equipped with bullet-proof vests and all-terrain vehicles for their temporary assignment here, the black officers who still handle complaints and investigations routinely run short of handcuffs, vests and uniforms.</p>
        <p>When Alfred Hlongwa's wife was shot and wounded three months ago, for example, that one van for emergency calls was unavailable.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hlongwa, a maintenance man, had already rushed his wife to the hospital, and he begged the police to search his house for clues, to interview witnesses, to find the intruder. But the two available officers had to take another emergency call.</p>
        <p>They told him, he said, to collect the evidence himself.</p>
        <p>And so while his daughters scrubbed away their mother's blood, Mr. Hlongwa carefully collected the spent cartridges from the bedroom floor, the front stoop, the carefully-swept dirt outside his mud house.</p>
        <p>''My daughters were crying, asking me who was the culprit,'' Mr. Hlongwa, 46, said bitterly, remembering that rainy day in February. ''I said I didn't know. I don't think we'll ever know.'' In the police station, Mr. Hlongwa's wife is just another brown folder, another case never properly investigated. But the five cartridges that sit uncollected in Mr. Hlongwa's house offer one of the most tangible examples of the limitations of the new national strategy.</p>
        <p>''I have been to KwaMashu and we have stations in the Eastern Cape that look even worse.'' said Assistant Commissioner Johan Burger, who is helping coordinate the new national police strategy, when asked about the problems here. I look at these police stations and shake my head. I can't believe what I'm seeing.''</p>
        <p>''We want to fix these stations,'' said Mr. Burger, who said additional resources and staff training will be devoted to troubled stations. ''Let's put our focus on three years. And let's admit to everyone that we won't be able to solve all our problems in the first year.''</p>
        <p>But many people in this country have already given up on the police.</p>
        <p>Most whites have retreated to houses surrounded by high walls and protected by expensive alarm systems in neighborhoods patrolled by private security companies.</p>
        <p>Blacks, who are the most frequent victims of violent crime in this country, often turn to vigilante violence. In a recent survey of 971 KwaMashu residents, nearly 60 percent said they believe local people solve crimes better than the police.</p>
        <p>Last month, when a robber got caught breaking into a hostel for migrant workers, the workers did not even bother to call the police. Instead, they stoned him to death.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
