<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheney More Generous by His Own Numbers</title>
    <meta content="Y06CHEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/politics/06CHEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICAN RUNNING MATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EED71639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheney More Generous by His Own Numbers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>ALLENTOWN, Pa., Sept. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Republican vice presidential candidate Dick Cheney, who defends his charitable contributions as 'appropriate' and insists he should be given credit not only for direct contributions but also for speaking fees he directed to charity and for corporate gifts that matched his own donations; he challenges suggestions that his generosity should be measured by comparing his direct contributions of $209,832 over last 10 years to his income of $20,677,742; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential candidate, today defended his charitable contributions as ''appropriate'' and insisted he should be given credit not only for direct contributions but also for speaking fees he directed to charity and for corporate gifts that matched his own donations.</p>
        <p>Answering reporters' questions on a campaign flight from Washington, Mr. Cheney challenged the suggestion that his generosity should be measured by comparing his direct contributions of $209,832 over the last 10 years to his income of $20,677,742, a standard by which he gave 1.01 percent of his income.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential candidate, today defended his charitable contributions as ''appropriate'' and insisted he should be given credit not only for direct contributions but also for speaking fees he directed to charity and for corporate gifts that matched his own donations.</p>
        <p>Answering reporters' questions on a campaign flight from Washington, Mr. Cheney challenged the suggestion that his generosity should be measured by comparing his direct contributions of $209,832 over the last 10 years to his income of $20,677,742, a standard by which he gave 1.01 percent of his income.</p>
        <p>He also counted $89,500 in speaking fees and $142,820 in matching gifts. Neither is a charitable contribution under the federal tax laws.</p>
        <p>''About four hundred forty-some thousand dollars were directed to charity, either direct contributions or honorariums or matching funds from the boards that we sat on,'' he said. ''I thought that was appropriate.''</p>
        <p>By his measure, that would equal 2.14 percent of his income. Asked if he considered that level ''generous,'' Mr. Cheney replied, ''I answered your question.''</p>
        <p>When a reporter, noting that he is a multimillionaire, asked him, ''What do you think is a proper level of giving for someone who has millions of dollars, in terms of percentage?'' he replied: ''I think that's a choice that individuals have to make in terms of what they want to do with their resources. It's not a policy question. It's a private matter. It's a matter of private choice.''</p>
        <p>According to the Internal Revenue Service, average taxpayers give about 2 percent of their income to charity. In 1997, the last year for which figures are available, those with incomes of $1 million or more gave an average of 4.5 percent. The last year that the income of Mr. Cheney and his wife, Lynne, was below $2 million was 1992, when he was secretary of defense and they earned $258,394.</p>
        <p>Later today, an aide explained that Mr. Cheney's first concern when he started making a lot of money in the private sector was providing for his children and grandchildren, and that the $442,152 represented only the start of substantial lifetime contributions he expected to make to charity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, who last week released the first two pages of his tax returns for each of the last 10 years, but not the full returns, said he and his wife had decided not to identify the charities they had given money to. He said, ''It was everything from the United Way to Capital Partners for Education in Washington, which provides scholarships for inner-city kids to go to parochial school, and a whole range of things in between.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney said he had rejected a chance to have $3.5 million worth of stock options in the Halliburton Company vest before the election because ''that is traditionally not the way we do business at Halliburton.''</p>
        <p>He also said that while he had received hundreds of thousands of dollars when he left the board of Electronic Data Systems to run for vice president, as The New York Times reported on Saturday, that money was deferred earnings from previous board service.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICAN RUNNING MATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
