<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stepping Aside at an Operatic Oasis; Founding Director of the Santa Fe Opera Looks Back on 43 Years of Innovation</title>
    <meta content="06CROS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/arts/06CROS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Santa Fe Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crosby, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaddes, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6D81339F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1934" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stepping Aside at an Operatic Oasis; Founding Director of the Santa Fe Opera Looks Back on 43 Years of Innovation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA FE, N.M.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with John Crosby, who is stepping down as general director of Santa Fe Opera; Richard Gaddes, his successor, comments; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The costumes, props and scenery used in the Santa Fe Opera's five summer productions are being packed for storage, and the singers and choristers who held the spotlight are en route to their next engagements. But as the company's backstage staff wraps up the loose ends, a more figurative curtain is descending, slowly and gracefully, on a long stretch of the company's history. On Sept. 30, just as the new concert season gets under way in the world's arts centers, John Crosby will step down as the general director of this adventurous company, which he founded in 1957 and has run since.</p>
        <p>Having built an opera house in the middle of the Southwestern desert and quickly established it as an important stop on the summer festival circuit, Mr. Crosby, 74, will turn over the reins to Richard Gaddes. As the associate general director for the last five years, Mr. Gaddes has been Mr. Crosby's right-hand man; and as the founder of a similar venture in St. Louis, he knows about running an opera company. He has invited Mr. Crosby to return to conduct Strauss operas, his specialty, next summer and in 2002. Otherwise Mr. Crosby is to exert no influence on the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The costumes, props and scenery used in the Santa Fe Opera's five summer productions are being packed for storage, and the singers and choristers who held the spotlight are en route to their next engagements. But as the company's backstage staff wraps up the loose ends, a more figurative curtain is descending, slowly and gracefully, on a long stretch of the company's history. On Sept. 30, just as the new concert season gets under way in the world's arts centers, John Crosby will step down as the general director of this adventurous company, which he founded in 1957 and has run since.</p>
        <p>Having built an opera house in the middle of the Southwestern desert and quickly established it as an important stop on the summer festival circuit, Mr. Crosby, 74, will turn over the reins to Richard Gaddes. As the associate general director for the last five years, Mr. Gaddes has been Mr. Crosby's right-hand man; and as the founder of a similar venture in St. Louis, he knows about running an opera company. He has invited Mr. Crosby to return to conduct Strauss operas, his specialty, next summer and in 2002. Otherwise Mr. Crosby is to exert no influence on the company.</p>
        <p>''I think when you stop, you stop,'' Mr. Crosby said, speaking barely above a whisper throughout an interview in his office on the company's grounds here. ''I think it's very important that you recognize that you can't manage in the background. You can't be breathing down somebody's neck.''</p>
        <p>That is not to say that relinquishing the company will be easy.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I think I haven't thought about anything else for 45 years,'' he said. ''I fall asleep worrying about it and wake up worrying about it.''</p>
        <p>That worrying led to the creation of something unusual and, even today, slightly out of place here. The highway that runs past the company's grounds on a hill overlooking Santa Fe is otherwise known for casinos, Indian pueblos and glorious views of desert plateaus. A sign marks the company's home as a local landmark, yet some 65 percent of its audience comes from outside New Mexico. The company has mixed feelings about the imbalance, which Mr. Gaddes said he would like to redress.</p>
        <p>A visitor to the company's comfortable, technologically up-to-date theater might not fully appreciate how daring was Mr. Crosby's notion of establishing a company here when he began contemplating it in the early 1950's. The wide highway that connects Albuquerque, the closest major airport, to Santa Fe was then a rustic two-lane road, and the drive that now takes 50 minutes took two and a half hours. More to the point, Santa Fe itself was not clamoring for an opera company. But Mr. Crosby said it had the kind of audience that would support one.</p>
        <p>''First of all, and very important, Santa Fe had a long history of what I like to call hospitality to the arts,'' said Mr. Crosby, who was born in New York but began visiting Santa Fe as a child because its dry climate was good for his asthma. ''It was a community that had a flourishing art colony, if you will: painters, poets, writers, sculptors. And strangely, from that galaxy of the arts, music was rather missing. So it seemed to me that the community would receive this missing link warmly.</p>
        <p>''The second thing was, you have to try and remember how different the world of classical music was in the summertime in the 1950's. It was nothing by comparison to today. So there was an abundance of unemployed classical music talent, both vocal and instrumental. Goodness, in our first season I think probably one-third of our orchestra was from the Metropolitan Opera. They had two choices, either to stay home and paint the house, or put the kids in the car and come out to Santa Fe for the summer.''</p>
        <p>He assembled a company of 65 performers for his first season, which opened with ''Madama Butterfly'' on July 3, 1957, just a few days short of his 31st birthday. The budget that summer was $110,000, about $60,000 of which he had raised in donations, with the rest covered largely by ticket sales. For the season just ended the company had a payroll of 550 and a budget of $11 million.</p>
        <p>Its home has expanded as well. Its first house was a 480-seat open air theater, which burned down in 1967. A theater seating 1,890 served the company for 30 years and was replaced in 1998 by a new 2,130-seat house designed by James Stewart Polshek and Partners of New York.</p>
        <p>The company's real attraction, though, is its programming. Although it by no means neglected the standard repertory, contemporary and rarely staged works -- from Handel to Henze -- have won it an international audience. An early coup of Mr. Crosby's was persuading Igor Stravinsky to oversee the production of his ''Rake's Progress'' during the company's first season.</p>
        <p>''I felt that it would not make sense to try to run a museum of opera in a small mountain town like Santa Fe,'' Mr. Crosby said. ''You can have all the 'Bohemes' and 'Carmens' you want in New York all winter, with brilliant international casts, and you don't have to come here to see them. But if you have an interest in some unusual things, then you will come along.''</p>
        <p>All told the company offered nearly 50 world and American premieres during Mr. Crosby's tenure, including works by Hindemith, Hans-Werner Henze (his ''Venus and Adonis'' this year was his sixth work to be given its United States premiere by the company), Gian-Carlo Menotti, Krzysztof Penderecki, Martin David Levy, Carlisle Floyd, Peter Lieberson, David Lang, Judith Weir and Tobias Picker.</p>
        <p>Schoenberg's ''Jakobsleiter'' and ''Von Heute auf Morgen,'' Shostakovich's ''Nose'' and several rarely heard Strauss operas also had their first American performances here. So did a pair of Baroque operas by Cavalli. And because the company gave the American premiere of the two-act version of Berg's ''Lulu'' in 1963, it was given the right to stage the American premiere of the full work in 1979, after the third act was belatedly published.</p>
        <p>''Santa Fe has been a huge influence on the American opera scene, the way Glyndebourne influences opera in England, and Aix-en-Provence influences opera in France,'' said Matthew Epstein, the artistic director of the Lyric Opera of Chicago and for the last 20 years a consultant in Santa Fe as well. ''You walk across the deck here on a summer evening, and you see the movers and shakers of the opera world. And when an opera has been a success here, it is suddenly looked at by other companies.''</p>
        <p>This has also been a good place to spot singers whose careers are about to take off. James Morris, Sherrill Milnes, Faith Esham, Ashley Putnam, Neil Shicoff, Judith Blegen and Brent Ellis all participated in the apprentice program for young singers. So did David Gockley, who is now the director of the Houston Grand Opera. Jose Van Dam, Kiri Te Kanawa and Bryn Terfel all made their American debuts here, and Benita Valente, Frederica von Stade, Hakan Hagegard, Catherine Malfitano, Maria Ewing, Thomas Hampson, Ben Heppner and Susan Graham had starring roles here early in their careers.</p>
        <p>''When I was in college at Texas Tech in Lubbock, I used to drive up and get standing-room tickets,'' said Ms. Graham, who grew up not far from here, in Roswell. ''It was my first exposure to professional opera, and it really did help define my dream.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Graham, a mezzo-soprano who has built an international career since her first performances here in 1989, has sung in several of the Strauss productions conducted by Mr. Crosby.</p>
        <p>''He's not a man who likes to call a lot of attention to himself,'' she said of his rehearsal manner. ''He won't yell, won't holler over stage noise. But he knows how he wants to approach every nuance in the Strauss operas, and he gave me a lot of input on interpretation and emotional matters. He never says more than a sentence at a time, but those sentences are densely packed with information. You have to listen carefully.''</p>
        <p>There is a sense of confidence here about the company's future. For one thing, there is not much mystery about Mr. Gaddes. He began working here as an artistic administrator in 1969 but left to found the Opera Theater of St. Louis in 1976. There are many similarities between the Santa Fe and St. Louis companies; both perform in the summer and present a similar repertory mixture.</p>
        <p>''That was not a coincidence,'' Mr. Gaddes said. ''I always say that John Crosby sired the Opera Theater of St. Louis. The whole concept was modeled on Santa Fe, and part of the idea was that the apprentices here would feed into St. Louis. Which they did.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gaddes returned to Santa Fe in 1988, first as a consultant, then as associate general director, a title that Mr. Crosby said was meant to give him authority but not necessarily to make him his chosen successor. That decision, he said, was the board's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gaddes seems intent on maintaining many of the traditions that Mr. Crosby has established. Among the works he has announced for next season are Berg's ''Wozzeck,'' Strauss's ''Egyptian Helen'' and a Mozart rarity, ''Mitridate.'' He has commissioned new works from Aaron Jay Kernis, Bright Sheng and Kaija Saariaho and is bringing in the director Peter Sellars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crosby is keeping his own plans to himself. He has given up the New York residence he maintained for many years, and will split his time between Santa Fe and Palm Springs, Calif. And he is thinking about writing what he calls ''a journal'' about the company.</p>
        <p>''It's not a book,'' he said. ''I'm not a writer, and I don't want to try to be. But there are some wonderful little tales of the early days that are not known, and I have the feeling that if I put them down, they might serve some purpose 10, 20 or 30 years down the line, if someone wants to write a history of the institution.''</p>
        <p>Beyond that, the only activity he said was on his agenda was driving around in the silver Rolls-Royce convertible he bought last year. A visitor noted that a convertible seemed an odd choice for someone living in a climate where a half-hour's drive is likely to take one through four short rainstorms.</p>
        <p>''Yes, that's true,'' he said. ''But I so much enjoy pulling the top down that I do it too frequently. It's an old one, a 1985, and I had to do a lot of work on it. But it will outlive me; that's all I care about. And you see that's something I can do: I can spend my time washing it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
