<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Travel; Wine is taking on a bigger role in the business- and first-class cabins of international flights.</title>
    <meta content="Y06TRAV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/travel/06TRAV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Delta Air Lines Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharkey, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chase, Ken</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Business Travel (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D81639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Travel; Wine is taking on a bigger role in the business- and first-class cabins of international flights.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joe Sharkey</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharkey, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wine is taking on bigger role in business- and first-class cabins of international flights; Ken Chase, Delta Airlines' wine consultant who runs carrier's wine program called Vinum, comments on competition with other airlines (Business Travel column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU probably don't want to be reading this if, like so many hard-pressed business travelers these days, you're crammed into some awful middle-row seat in coach on an international flight, counting the hours till arrival and wondering how you're going to squeeze past that fat guy sleeping in the aisle seat to get to the bathroom.</p>
        <p>This column is about what's going on up there behind the curtain in the expensive seats. Party time, is what.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU probably don't want to be reading this if, like so many hard-pressed business travelers these days, you're crammed into some awful middle-row seat in coach on an international flight, counting the hours till arrival and wondering how you're going to squeeze past that fat guy sleeping in the aisle seat to get to the bathroom.</p>
        <p>This column is about what's going on up there behind the curtain in the expensive seats. Party time, is what.</p>
        <p>Business-class and first-class seats are where the airlines make most of their money and where they try to attract their most loyal customers. In the last year or so, the competition for that market has become fierce, as airlines scramble to outdo one another with bigger seats, better food, more movie selections than a supermall Cineplex -- and, yes, even wine.</p>
        <p>A magazine called Business Traveler International does an annual survey article, ''Cellars in the Sky,'' in which a panel of experts ranks the wines served in business class on about 40 world airlines. The current top 10: Finnair, Aeromexico, Delta Air Lines, Thai Airways, Virgin Atlantic, EVA Air, Spanair, Continental Airlines, Alitalia and LanChile.</p>
        <p>Ken Chase, a self-described ''classically trained wine merchant with an international reputation spanning the globe,'' pronounces himself happy to see such robust competition. That's partly because Mr. Chase has been busy promoting the efforts of one of those airlines, Delta, to associate its recently revamped business-class brand with high-quality wine service.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chase, who is Delta's wine consultant, isn't just flogging wine. He is positively proselytizing for it, even enlisting Delta flight attendants in voluntary wine-tasting seminars.</p>
        <p>''Wine consumption is not going up very much in the United States, but we're drinking better wine,'' Mr. Chase said. Good times translate into more business travelers with a taste for wine. Among them, incidentally, are the highly sought-after hordes of young men and women with dot-com incomes who are ready to shed beer-bottle tastes from their not-so-distant college days for the best from the vineyards.</p>
        <p>''They may not yet know a lot about wine, but they know it's an important part of the lifestyle package,'' Mr. Chase said. By and large, he added, ''they know a few favorite labels'' and don't experiment much. ''The idea here is to introduce the business-class customer to a very wide variety of excellent wines.''</p>
        <p>All major airlines pay attention to wine in the premium cabins. But obviously, not many people are going to select an international airline exclusively or even mostly based on the quality of the wine.</p>
        <p>''This is just one of many product enhancements to upgrade the experience for our international business passengers,'' said John Kennedy, a spokesman for Delta, which has dropped first-class seating on international flights in favor of an upgraded business class.</p>
        <p>Domestically, Mr. Kennedy said, an amenity like top-shelf wine doesn't matter all that much. ''Then it's  basically, 'How do I get from New York to Atlanta; the wine's O.K. but I don't have to drink it, and who cares anyway as long as I get there on time,' '' he said. ''But on an 8-  or 12-hour trip, especially when you've spent $6,000, you want a little more than just transportation.''</p>
        <p>Delta's new wine-service program has a brand name, Vinum. Passengers in business class can choose selections from dozens of labels on a wine list that runs to 24 pages, Mr. Chase said.</p>
        <p>To help encourage wine connoisseurship, Mr. Chase says that he has  been preaching among the ranks of Delta's 20,000 flight attendants. Incidentally, if there is one thing that airline flight attendants do not welcome these days, it is extra work in the crowded skies -- including uncorking fancy wines for pampered passengers.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Chase, whose wine-consulting company is based in Canada, has been wily. He came up with three ways to get at least some flight attendants enthusiastically on board.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chase holds wine-tasting parties around the country, inviting off-duty flight attendants to come in, sample a variety of excellent wines, and listen to him talk on the subject. He also publishes a wine newsletter for flight attendants and festoons flight attendant bulletin boards with helpful information. And he is putting the finishing touches on a recording of a wine course on compact disc that will be distributed to Delta attendants this fall.</p>
        <p>And then there is the all-expenses- paid trip to what he calls the Vinum Academy at a chateau on the Cotes du Rhone in southern France. This year, 16 Delta flight attendants, chosen from about 1,300 who have so far submitted entries in a wine essay-question contest, will attend the weeklong wine seminar taught by Mr. Chase and other international wine experts at the Chateau de Rochegude near Avignon.</p>
        <p>''We take over the whole castle for the week,'' he said. Graduating flight attendants become ''wine ambassadors'' and receive gold pins that indicate they know their stuff.</p>
        <p>''We don't want wine to be a chore for them,'' he said. The ones who have participated in the seminars and last year's academy ''have become very enthusiastic'' about wine, he said, adding that senior flight attendants are starting to convey the love and lore of fine wine downward to the younger flight attendants.</p>
        <p>''We like that trickle-down effect,''  he said.</p>
        <p>The Business Travel column  appears each Wednesday. E-mail:  jsharkey@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">The Business Travel column
&lt;br&gt;appears each Wednesday. E-mail:
&lt;br&gt;jsharkey@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
