<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miami-Dade Mayor Wins Bulk Of Votes but May Face Runoff</title>
    <meta content="06MIAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/national/06MIAM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Penelas, Alex (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DB1739F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miami-Dade Mayor Wins Bulk Of Votes but May Face Runoff</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Sept. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mayor Alex Penelas, who is seeking re-election, wins bulk of votes in an open primary contest against nine opponents, but final outcome remains undecided; needs 50 percent of vote to win second term without runoff (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeking re-election as mayor of Miami-Dade County, Alex Penelas today won the bulk of votes in an open primary contest against nine opponents. But hours after the polls closed, it was still unclear whether he had the 50 percent needed to win a second term without a runoff.</p>
        <p>With 62 percent of the precincts reporting, Mr. Penelas had 51 percent of the vote, compared with 21 percent for Miguel Diaz de la Portilla, a county commissioner who had been expected to offer the strongest challenge, and 20 percent for Jay Love, a Miami businessman. The other contenders ran far behind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seeking re-election as mayor of Miami-Dade County, Alex Penelas today won the bulk of votes in an open primary contest against nine opponents. But hours after the polls closed, it was still unclear whether he had the 50 percent needed to win a second term without a runoff.</p>
        <p>With 62 percent of the precincts reporting, Mr. Penelas had 51 percent of the vote, compared with 21 percent for Miguel Diaz de la Portilla, a county commissioner who had been expected to offer the strongest challenge, and 20 percent for Jay Love, a Miami businessman. The other contenders ran far behind.</p>
        <p>Political experts here said that even if Mr. Penelas did not win outright, he would handily win a second term if the race went on to an Oct. 3 runoff.</p>
        <p>Mr. Penelas, who is 38 and who at one time had been mentioned as a possible running mate for Vice President Al Gore, seemed destined for the national political stage as late as March.</p>
        <p>Then, with television cameras from around the country and the world trained on him, he said he would not allow his police department to aid any effort by the federal authorities to remove a 6-year-old Cuban boy, Elian Gonzalez, from the home where Miami relatives kept him in defiance of a federal order to return him to Cuba.</p>
        <p>The mayor ''played for the moment,'' J. P. Monroe, a professor of political science at the University of Miami, said. ''It pushed him off the stage.''</p>
        <p>Political experts here say Mr. Penelas had to decide between defying the federal government and defying the wishes of a majority of Cuban-American voters. More than 44 percent of registered voters in Miami-Dade County are Cuban-American, according to statistics from the county supervisor of elections.</p>
        <p>''It inoculated him'' against Election Day revenge by Cuban-Americans, Mr. Monroe said.</p>
        <p>At the polls, Cuban-Americans said they recognized his sacrifice, and rewarded him.</p>
        <p>''Perhaps he did risk his political future on a national level, but here he is our hero,'' said Liliana Morales, 59, a Cuban-American who has lived in Miami since 1974. ''This just shows you what this community means to him. He is willing to risk his political future to stand up for his people.</p>
        <p>''He might not be liked among other groups, but here the majority is Hispanic and we think he did the right thing.''</p>
        <p>Political experts said Mr. Penelas was in some ways in an impossible situation. If he had sided against the emotional tide that was running through Miami, he would have lost his office and his power base.</p>
        <p>As anger against the federal government washed through parts of the county during and after the Elian standoff, many people here, especially blacks and Anglos, said they felt pushed aside by Mr. Penelas.</p>
        <p>They promised to get even at the polls.</p>
        <p>''I am mainly voting against Penelas because of how he handled the Elian debacle,'' said Jamin O'Brien, a 32-year-old filmmaker who lives in Coconut Grove. ''That left egg on the face of the entire community.''</p>
        <p>But such a backlash cannot really harm Mr. Penelas, Mr. Monroe said, adding: ''There's not enough to worry about. It's not just the sheer numbers, but their discipline.''</p>
        <p>Cuban-Americans, especially older ones, are a reliable voting bloc. Mr. Penelas courted them, strongly.</p>
        <p>''He has run no more than a token campaign in English,'' said Kevin Hill, an associate professor of political science at Florida International University.</p>
        <p>''People thought that whites and blacks would never forgive him, but they tend not to vote'' when they are angry, Professor Hill said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Love, who entered the race in part because of that division in the community, ran surprisingly well, even edging ahead of Mr. Diaz de la Portilla as the early returns came in.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
