<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First, Three Big Debates</title>
    <meta content="06WED1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/opinion/06WED1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commission on Presidential Debates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russert, Tim</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Larry King Live (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Meet the Press (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DD1739F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First, Three Big Debates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial opposes Gov George W Bush's demand that three 90-minute televised debates between him and Vice Pres Al Gore be replaced by one such debate and two 60-minute appearances on Meet the Press and Larry King Live; says additional joint television appearance by the two candidates can be scheduled once the three debates sponsored by bipartisan Commission on Presidential Debates are nailed down</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No events in a presidential campaign are more crucial to public involvement in the electoral process than the cycle of debates involving the major candidates in the fall. This week, however, Gov. George W. Bush is demanding that instead of three televised encounters sponsored by the bipartisan Commission on Presidential Debates that has run the events since 1988, only one such debate take place, coupled with two other joint appearances with Vice President Al Gore -- one on ''Meet the Press'' and the other on ''Larry King Live.''</p>
        <p>The problem with Mr. Bush's demand is that it needlessly junks a system that has been fair to both Republicans and Democrats, and it could greatly reduce the number of viewers likely to tune in. Mr. Bush's search for a safer debate environment also looks like a tactical loser for him, since it undercuts his declaration that he is ready for leadership in any and all circumstances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No events in a presidential campaign are more crucial to public involvement in the electoral process than the cycle of debates involving the major candidates in the fall. This week, however, Gov. George W. Bush is demanding that instead of three televised encounters sponsored by the bipartisan Commission on Presidential Debates that has run the events since 1988, only one such debate take place, coupled with two other joint appearances with Vice President Al Gore -- one on ''Meet the Press'' and the other on ''Larry King Live.''</p>
        <p>The problem with Mr. Bush's demand is that it needlessly junks a system that has been fair to both Republicans and Democrats, and it could greatly reduce the number of viewers likely to tune in. Mr. Bush's search for a safer debate environment also looks like a tactical loser for him, since it undercuts his declaration that he is ready for leadership in any and all circumstances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides say he is pressing his proposal because he does not like the formats from previous elections, particularly the formal appearance of two candidates at lecterns. The Bush campaign argues that this setup and the looser ''town meeting'' format both play to Mr. Gore's strengths and that Mr. Bush would prefer sitting down at a table in a conversation between the two candidates and a respected moderator. But the presidential debate commission has said it would be amenable to discussions on format once everyone agrees to participate in the debates themselves. There is no reason the candidates cannot agree to have Mr. King or Tim Russert of NBC's ''Meet the Press'' moderate one of the commission's three debates, as Mr. Bush wants.</p>
        <p>Any news organization has the right to offer the candidates a chance to debate, and the more debates the better. But the candidates and the national party leaders have an obligation to see that the commission debates are nailed down before any others are added to the schedule. This flows from the fact that the presidential debate commission was established jointly by Republican and Democratic leaders in 1987. Its honorary chairmen are Ronald Reagan, Jimmy Carter and Gerald Ford, and the commission has been resolutely bipartisan in its approach. One of its goals was to avoid candidates' backing out of debates over scheduling conflicts and to help networks minimize similar conflicts with their own fall programs.</p>
        <p>In years past, the 90-minute debates have drawn from 50 million to 97 million viewers. Television experts say that a 60-minute debate on only one network, which Mr. Bush wants, would probably not draw more than 20 million viewers in prime time. That is too small a number for the debates to fulfill their historic purpose. Picking a single network, as Mr. Bush proposes, also opens the door for the kind of broadcast turf wars that the commission has been able to avoid.</p>
        <p>There is room, however, to indulge some of Mr. Bush's frivolous demands. If he continues to be uneasy about holding the first debate at a site near the John F. Kennedy Library in Massachusetts, Mr. Gore should agree to meet his opponent at a facility named for a Republican. As for the format issue, the ideal solution would be for Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore to be allowed one format of their own choosing, and some sort of compromise on the third debate. But again, we would urge the Gore campaign toward maximum flexibility in making Mr. Bush comfortable.</p>
        <p>Where Mr. Gore should take a firm line, though, is in continuing to insist that Mr. Bush agree to the three commission debates with ''roadblock,'' or all-network, coverage. When those debates are set, then the candidates can do any number of additional debates on Mr. King's or Mr. Russert's show or anyplace else, for that matter. The public is served by more debates, not fewer -- and by preservation of the primacy of the Commission on Presidential Debates.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
