<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Rapper's Life on the Hip-Hop Road: Attitude, Revelry and Togetherness</title>
    <meta content="06BACK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/arts/06BACK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Elvis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fiore, Chris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Backstage (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Elvis Mitchell</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E5DE1639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Rapper's Life on the Hip-Hop Road: Attitude, Revelry and Togetherness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELVIS MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Elvis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elvis Mitchell reviews movie Backstage, directed by Chris Fiore; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''I came to blow it down, and I'm gonna blow it down,'' DMX says of his turn onstage in the concert documentary ''Backstage,'' which follows the 1999 ''Hard Knock Life'' tour headed by Jay-Z and several other rappers, including the likable and funny Beanie Sigel, Redman, Memphis Bleek and others, along with a cameo by an effusive Busta Rhymes, who has the cheerfulness of new money.</p>
        <p>DMX, who's so prolific and sometimes repetitive he may get his own wing at Tower Records, has a remarkable and combative stage presence. Bombastic and hotblooded, he holds court in a singular fashion, exercising sheer force of will to pull the spotlight down on himself and demanding the crowd's attention: ''That's the need to be heard,'' he states, offering his worldview. (''He epitomizes the have-nots,'' the Def Jam Music producer Irv Gotti says of the lean, prowling star.) His portion of the performance is unlike the family vibe that permeates the shows of the other rappers on the tour. They include Jay-Z, who rescued his hit ''Hard Knock Life'' from the inanity of the movie version of ''Annie'' and built a generation's anthem around the original song's tossed-off chorus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''I came to blow it down, and I'm gonna blow it down,'' DMX says of his turn onstage in the concert documentary ''Backstage,'' which follows the 1999 ''Hard Knock Life'' tour headed by Jay-Z and several other rappers, including the likable and funny Beanie Sigel, Redman, Memphis Bleek and others, along with a cameo by an effusive Busta Rhymes, who has the cheerfulness of new money.</p>
        <p>DMX, who's so prolific and sometimes repetitive he may get his own wing at Tower Records, has a remarkable and combative stage presence. Bombastic and hotblooded, he holds court in a singular fashion, exercising sheer force of will to pull the spotlight down on himself and demanding the crowd's attention: ''That's the need to be heard,'' he states, offering his worldview. (''He epitomizes the have-nots,'' the Def Jam Music producer Irv Gotti says of the lean, prowling star.) His portion of the performance is unlike the family vibe that permeates the shows of the other rappers on the tour. They include Jay-Z, who rescued his hit ''Hard Knock Life'' from the inanity of the movie version of ''Annie'' and built a generation's anthem around the original song's tossed-off chorus.</p>
        <p>Jay-Z used his stature to create the tour he wanted. Instead of being coerced to go out with an R&amp;B act to make him more accessible (as is mentioned in the movie), Jay-Z flexed his three-million-record sales muscle to surround himself with the rappers he likes. Like Spike Lee's ''Original Kings of Comedy,'' which shows the unanimity of purpose among four professional but extremely competitive comedians, ''Backstage'' provides a glimpse into the lives of tough and cooperative black entertainers.</p>
        <p>With the exception of DMX, who seems to seal himself off from his fellow performers -- ''The only part of the tour I like is the one hour I'm onstage,'' he says, and a handwritten sign warns that only his beloved pit bull is allowed to visit him before his show -- the rappers spend copious hang time eluding and flirting with groupies. (Their faces are obscured by dots of various colors and sizes and with messages, including ''Your Ad Here.'') It's the standard life of revelry and exhaustion, something that has been a staple of concert music.</p>
        <p>''Backstage'' deals with that as well as the performers' awareness of the way rappers are perceived. The tour was in Denver when the Columbine High School shootings took  place, and Jay-Z makes a point of contributing the profits from the Denver show to the school. At another point Redman notes that he had seen a mosh pit while touring with Everclear: ''If that ever happened at a hip-hop show, they'd shut it down,'' he muses.</p>
        <p>Where things get really tense and interesting is in the stances of the management companies. Damon Dash, head of Roc-A-Fella Records, is furious because Def Jam upstages Roc-A-Fella's artists by usurping props like jackets; the Def Jam jackets, by the way, do the job because they're quite fly. Since Jay-Z is a Roc-A-Fella artist, and the focal point of the show -- ''I came all the way from Montana to see Jay-Z,'' a young white fan enthuses -- Mr. Dash's anger seems justified.</p>
        <p>The film would have been better served had it given a more complete picture of the shrewdness that has made Def Jam such a player, although hard-core fans (and ''Hard Knock'' fans) know of the rivalries in the rap world. As Ja Rule says, ''As long as you're black, it's gonna be a hustle.''</p>
        <p>''Backstage'' isn't as good as the rap documentaries ''Rhyme and Reason'' and ''The Show,'' but it still casts a keen, observant eye (even though video fatigue sets in) on this world.</p>
        <p>BACKSTAGE</p>
        <p>Directed and edited by Chris Fiore; produced by Damon Dash; released by Dimension Films. Running time: 99 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jay-Z, DMX, Method Man, Redman, Beanie Sigel, Memphis Bleek, DJ Clue, Amil,  Ja Rule, Irv Gotti and Mr. Dash.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
