<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="06PUBL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/nyregion/06PUBL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228371"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conde Nast Publications Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinem, Gloria</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macfarquhar, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bale, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nathan, Judith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerik, Bernard B (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fine, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DE1739F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL MacFARQUHAR with Thomas J. Lueck</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J; Macfarquhar, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Feminist writer Gloria Steinem marries businessman and political activist David Bale; Judith Nathan, described as Mayor Rudolph Giuliani's special friend, attends swearing-in ceremony for new Police Comr Bernard B Kerik; Conde Nast promotes Deborah Fine to vice president (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Feminist Takes the Vows</p>
        <p>It was, GLORIA STEINEM admits, not exactly the type of institution she thought would have her as a member.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Feminist Takes the Vows</p>
        <p>It was, GLORIA STEINEM admits, not exactly the type of institution she thought would have her as a member.</p>
        <p>But the 66-year-old feminist writer got married for the first time during the weekend to DAVID BALE, 61, a South African-born businessman and political activist who lives in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''Obey,'' needless to say, went unmentioned in the vows.</p>
        <p>The two chose a civil ceremony drawn from the traditions of the Cherokee Indians, which uses the word ''partners'' where other nuptials might mention ''husband and wife.'' The wedding took place at sunrise on Sunday at the Oklahoma home of WILMA MANKILLER, the former principal chief of the Cherokee nation.</p>
        <p>''Though I have worked many years to make marriage more equal, I never expected to take advantage of it myself,'' Ms. Steinem said in a written statement. ''I'm happy, surprised and one day will write about it, but for now, I hope this proves what feminists have always said: that feminism is about the ability to chose what's right at each time of our lives.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Steinem noted briefly that her decision to marry was based on love and the fact that marriage is now more equitable. Several longtime friends expanded on her reasons.</p>
        <p>''He is just a wonderful, wonderful, extraordinary man,'' said SUZANNE BRAUN LEVINE, a former writer for Ms. magazine. ''He is smart and generous and very attractive and really loves her.</p>
        <p>''It is very corny, but maybe it is a wonderful message,'' Ms. Braun Levine added. ''It was never the right person at the right time. Being 66 is not the typical right time. Honestly, she is as stunned as we all are.''</p>
        <p>The couple's decision to get married was an impulsive one taken while they were attending a spiritual retreat organized by the Cherokees. The bride wore jeans and a white shirt; the groom, black clothes and an Indian belt.</p>
        <p>It was the third marriage for Mr. Bale, whose four children include the actor CHRISTIAN BALE (''American Psycho.'')</p>
        <p>No honeymoon is planned. The newlyweds said they would divide their time between Los Angeles and New York.</p>
        <p>They met in October 1999 at a Los Angeles benefit for Voters for Choice, a political action committee that Ms. Steinem helped found and Mr. Bale supported.</p>
        <p>The First Friend At a Ceremony</p>
        <p>The most visible Nathan in New York may no longer be a hot dog stand.</p>
        <p>JUDITH NATHAN, MAYOR RUDOLPH W. GIULIANI's close friend, sat front and center at a festive swearing-in ceremony yesterday for Police Commissioner BERNARD B. KERIK and First Deputy Commissioner JOSEPH P. DUNNE on the steps of City Hall.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nathan, seated with members of Mr. Kerik's family, frequently snapped pictures and nodded encouragement while the mayor spoke. Immediately after the ceremony, she was whisked up the stairs into City Hall by an unidentified escort.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani announced in May that he was seeking a separation from his wife, DONNA HANOVER. Ms. Hanover plans to continue her community service work as the city's first lady and live with the couple's two children at Gracie Mansion until the end of Mr. Giuliani's mayoralty in December 2001.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nathan is increasingly at the mayor's side in public.</p>
        <p>A Rumor Misfires</p>
        <p>The drumbeats in the media world were fervently predicting over the weekend that DEBORAH FINE, the publisher of Glamour magazine since November 1999, would be ousted immediately. A dip in advertising pages as well as circulation figures had attracted the ire of STEVEN T. FLORIO, the chief executive and president of Conde Nast Publications, various publications reported.</p>
        <p>Instead, Conde Nast announced yesterday that Ms. Fine, who started at the company 20 years ago, was being promoted to a vice presidency. It is the kind of promotion usually announced at big company gatherings, but a spokesman said the organization had taken the step to express support for Ms. Fine at a time when she was being smudged publicly.</p>
        <p>NEIL MacFARQUHAR with Thomas J. Lueck</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
