<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pakistani Leader Voices Little Hope for India Talks</title>
    <meta content="Y06PAKI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/world/06PAKI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: KASHMIR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">India-International Relations-Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Timor</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musharraf, Pervez (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/East Timor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/East Timor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arbitration, Conciliation and Mediation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4D81639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pakistani Leader Voices Little Hope for India Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Gen Pervez Musharraf, Pakistan's military ruler, who says there is no hope of solving explosive issue of Kashmir through negotiations with India; will appeal to world leaders at UN General Assembly's Millennium summit in New York for type of international mediation that ended Indonesian occupation of East Timor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pakistan's military ruler said today that he saw no hope of solving the explosive issue of Kashmir through negotiations with India and that he would appeal to world leaders on Wednesday for the type of international mediation that ended the Indonesian occupation of East Timor.</p>
        <p>The Pakistani general, Pervez Musharraf, who took power in a coup last Oct. 12, said in an interview that India had squandered several recent opportunities to start serious talks with the Kashmiris, as well as with Pakistan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pakistan's military ruler said today that he saw no hope of solving the explosive issue of Kashmir through negotiations with India and that he would appeal to world leaders on Wednesday for the type of international mediation that ended the Indonesian occupation of East Timor.</p>
        <p>The Pakistani general, Pervez Musharraf, who took power in a coup last Oct. 12, said in an interview that India had squandered several recent opportunities to start serious talks with the Kashmiris, as well as with Pakistan.</p>
        <p>''Unless there is mediation, strong mediation, justice cannot come about,'' General Musharraf said. ''Mediation is definitely required, and East Timor provides an excellent example of how the situation can be solved if the world community shows the will.''</p>
        <p>General Musharraf, who remains chairman of the Pakistani joint chiefs of staff and calls himself the country's chief executive, will speak on Wednesday, on the first day of a three-day summit meeting of more than 150 world leaders. Prime Minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee of India, who is scheduled to speak on Friday, cut short his visit because of health problems and is not expected in New York until Thursday. Officials of both governments said there had been no requests from either side for a meeting of the two leaders.</p>
        <p>In the interview in his hotel suite, General Musahrraf, 56, relaxed and wearing a short-sleeved sport shirt and khaki slacks, also spoke of the problems that he has encountered in his anticorruption drive and explained in some detail his plans for restoring democracy ''from the grass roots up'' in Pakistan. The country's Supreme Court has given him three years to complete the process.</p>
        <p>His plan to ''bring to book people who squandered the nation's wealth'' -- his list includes two former prime ministers, Nawaz Sharif, now in jail, and Benazir Bhutto, who is in self-imposed exile -- ''is slow going because of obstacles,'' he said.</p>
        <p>General Musharraf, his aides said, is trying to set an example of austerity in a country where elected leaders have lived in mansions and traveled with huge entourages, staying in the best hotels. In New York, he is at the Roosevelt Hotel, owned by Pakistani International Airlines, and has brought 20 aides and his wife.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the targets of his anticorruption drive, which Pakistanis have greeted enthusiastically, he said, ''These are white-collar crimes in which these people have been involved, which are not very easy to investigate and get the facts out.''</p>
        <p>He said finding assets abroad was not easy, and bringing the money home was even more difficult.</p>
        <p>General Musharraf has also met opposition to his plans to make Pakistanis pay taxes, which only 1 million people in a population of 140 million do now. A process to assess property values led to a 25-day strike by shopkeepers, ''but they've come around now,'' the leader said. House and factory assessments are going better, he added.</p>
        <p>His plans for starting to restore democracy at the local level through nonpartisan elections, he said, grew out of the reality that at the grass roots ''democracy has been denied to the people of Pakistan.''</p>
        <p>He plans to give local officials not only administrative powers, but also the power to raise money and to decide how to spend it. Provincial-level voting will come next. ''Then see what remains that the center should control,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At the national level, he expects political parties to take part in elections. ''I am certainly not against any parties,'' he said. ''We are not banning parties as such, at the provincial level or at the national level.''</p>
        <p>General Musahrraf, who has been accused by India of supporting Islamic militants in Kashmir and who is thought to be facing a rising tide of militancy in the military, denied strongly that the army was in danger of succumbing to fundamentalism. ''This is a total misperception of the military in Pakistan,'' he said. ''The military in Pakistan, the army in particular, is the most disciplined, the most well organized, the most well administered. There is no question of differences within the army.''</p>
        <p>General Musharraf spoke at the most length about the Kashmir issue and other areas in which, he said, India has faulted Pakistan for crises without any evidence. Indians have accused Pakistan of fomenting anti-Christian violence and supporting rebels in Punjab and the remote Indian northeast, as well as in Kashmir. General Musahrraf blamed the international news media for often accepting the charges at face value.</p>
        <p>Pakistan has long argued for international help in solving the issue of Kashmir, a disputed Himalayan territory that has been the scene of several wars between India and Pakistan and is considered a dangerous flashpoint between two nuclear-armed nations. But General Musharraf was more categorical than his predecessors in dismissing Indian promises to settle the issue between the two governments. India has always rejected offers of international help, including offers from Secretary General Kofi Annan.</p>
        <p>The United Nations never recognized Kashmir as part of India, just as East Timor was never recognized as Indonesian, General Musharraf said. ''When they talk of bilateralism, actually, that means they don't want to do anything,'' he said of India. ''So that time is over.''</p>
        <p>He accused the Indian government of trying to suppress the decadelong insurrection in Kashmir with 700,000 troops and paramilitary fighters. A cease-fire was aborted this summer when a Kashmiri rebel group, the Hizbul Mujahideen, demanded that Pakistan be included in talks with India, and India contended that any negotiations had to be held within the context of the Indian Constitution, meaning that Kashmir be recognized as an integral part of India.</p>
        <p>Security Council resolutions passed in 1948, after the partition of India into largely Hindu India and Muslim Pakistan, called for a plebiscite allowing the people of Kashmir to choose which country to join. The vote was never held.</p>
        <p>General Musharraf said he believed that most Kashmiris would vote for union with Pakistan. Most experts and many Kashmiris say they would be much more likely to choose independence or substantial autonomy if the choices were broadened. Pakistan has never been eager for a vote.</p>
        <p>SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: KASHMIR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
