<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="06DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DF1739F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Health Insurance Premiums Are Increasing 10% to 30%  Health insurance premiums are increasing 10 percent to 30 percent nationwide, according to employers, insurers and regional business groups familiar with rates being paid by dozens of companies. Driven largely by escalating drug costs, the double-digit increase is the third in a row for many companies.</p>
        <p>The rising premiums suggest that apart from the most restrictive, bare-bones health maintenance organizations, managed care is no longer keeping medical costs down. The increasing costs come at a time of rising concern about health care costs, particularly drug costs, in Medicare. The increases revive a contentious issue that clouded the early years of the Clinton administration. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Health Insurance Premiums Are Increasing 10% to 30%  Health insurance premiums are increasing 10 percent to 30 percent nationwide, according to employers, insurers and regional business groups familiar with rates being paid by dozens of companies. Driven largely by escalating drug costs, the double-digit increase is the third in a row for many companies.</p>
        <p>The rising premiums suggest that apart from the most restrictive, bare-bones health maintenance organizations, managed care is no longer keeping medical costs down. The increasing costs come at a time of rising concern about health care costs, particularly drug costs, in Medicare. The increases revive a contentious issue that clouded the early years of the Clinton administration. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush's proposal to redesign Medicare and offer drug benefits to the elderly puts him squarely in line with his party's drive to change the course of the program by reducing the role of government and increasing the role of insurance companies. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Utility Deal Highlights Consolidation  The $3 billion acquisition of Niagara Mohawk in upstate New York by the National Grid Group of Britain highlights the efforts of large, ambitious electricity concerns to swallow local companies and fashion regional giants. Shares of Niagara Mohawk rose $1.88, to $15.75. The Northeast, perhaps more than any other region, has become a key staging ground for consolidation, because it was among the first places in the country where states deregulated the power industry. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Nasdaq Falls in Technology Slump  Technology stocks fell broadly, sending the Nasdaq composite index lower, led by Intel. Meanwhile, weakness in drug stocks dragged down the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index. The Nasdaq composite index fell 91.15 points, or 2.2 percent, to 4,143.18. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index slumped 13.69 points, or 0.9 percent, to 1,507.08, but the Dow Jones industrial average rose 21.83 points, or 0.2 percent, to 11,260.61. [C9.]</p>
        <p>First-Class Wine Cellars in the Sky  The competition for business-class and first-class passengers has become fierce as airlines scramble to outdo one another with bigger seats, better food -- and even wine. For example, Delta's business-class passengers get to choose from dozens of wines in a 24-page wine list. Joe Sharkey: Business Travel. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Infonet Seen in Talks for Equant  Infonet, a data communications company in California, has had exploratory talks about buying Equant, the Dutch telecommunications company, people close to the talks said. The discussions are in early stages and a deal is not imminent, the people said. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Life Has Been His Thesis  Some chief executives started businesses while in college, but not Fred Poses, chief executive of American Standard. He spent much of his undergraduate days at New York University playing pool. Then he enrolled in the graduate program, but never obtained his M.B.A. because he refused to write a thesis. ''A thesis is too narrowly focused, and it has nothing to do with real life,'' he said. ''I've spent a lifetime finding out how things work and how you can make them better. That has been my real education.'' The Boss. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Dismissal Fought in Virus Case  Philippine investigators asked prosecutors to reconsider a decision to dismiss criminal charges against a former computer student accused of releasing an e-mail program that caused billions of dollars in damage to computers and software worldwide in May. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Pele Goes to Work for Oil Company  In a new role as good-will ambassador for the Brazilian oil giant Petroleo Brasileiro, the soccer icon Pele, who turns 60 next month, is lending the considerable weight of his name to a company with international aspirations. Petrobas is the world's seventh-largest publicly traded oil company. [C4.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
