<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Leaders Arrive, and a City Sits Up and Notices</title>
    <meta content="06NATI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/world/06NATI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Dean E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E5DB1739F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Leaders Arrive, and a City Sits Up and Notices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Dean E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World leaders arrive, New York City, for three-day Millennium summit of UN General Assembly; crush of limousines carrying VIP's causes traffic jams across East Side; spectacle caused by arrivals spills into virtually every nook and cranny of Manhattan, as New Yorkers and visitors alike are forced to cope not only with traffic jams, but also security precautions and demonstrations; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The summit meeting of world leaders gets under way today at the United Nations, but most of New York and its thousands of visitors could not wait to open the curtain on what promises to be a world-class sideshow.</p>
        <p>Traffic was backed up across the East Side yesterday because of a crush of limousines carrying V.I.P.'s everywhere from the United Nations Plaza Hotel to the Bronx Zoo. (Denis Sassou-Nguesso, president of the Congo Republic, skipped some preconference hobnobbing to tour the Congo Gorilla Forest exhibit.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The summit meeting of world leaders gets under way today at the United Nations, but most of New York and its thousands of visitors could not wait to open the curtain on what promises to be a world-class sideshow.</p>
        <p>Traffic was backed up across the East Side yesterday because of a crush of limousines carrying V.I.P.'s everywhere from the United Nations Plaza Hotel to the Bronx Zoo. (Denis Sassou-Nguesso, president of the Congo Republic, skipped some preconference hobnobbing to tour the Congo Gorilla Forest exhibit.)</p>
        <p>Demonstrators, some beating drums, some shouting with bullhorns and some practicing silent meditation, squeezed into Dag Hammarskjold Plaza, the global soapbox for the week. Whether anyone was listening did not seem important.</p>
        <p>''There is no peace without Yahweh's 613 laws of peace,'' a religious group from Texas chanted. The reply from a pro-Taiwan group: ''Say no to China.'' And members of the Chinese spiritual movement Falun Gong kept the yelling to themselves.</p>
        <p>''We just focus inside,'' one of the meditators said.</p>
        <p>Kofi Annan, the United Nations secretary general, called the three-day conference a ''defining moment for the world's leaders and for the United Nations.'' [Page A12.] To be sure, some of the world's most vexing problems, from poverty to disease, will be debated by presidents, prime ministers, kings and crown princes.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, President Mohammad Khatami of Iran delivered a speech at a one-day conference ahead of the summit meeting, in which he noted that his country is one of the world's oldest civilizations and promoted his campaign for a global ''dialogue among civilizations.'' [Page A12.]</p>
        <p>Discussions also began among four African presidents on Zimbabwe's troubled land reform program. More than 700 other meetings, dealing with issues around the world, are expected to follow.</p>
        <p>But yesterday, it was not easy to see the diplomacy past the preconference spectacle, which spilled into virtually every nook and cranny of Manhattan and promised to continue through the week. Even as Mr. Khatami spoke, hundreds of demonstrators marched down 47th Street in opposition to his government, their protest filling one slot in a day of events and counterevents.</p>
        <p>''We have seen this in bits and pieces before but never like this all together,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer, the New York Democrat, who released a letter to Madeleine K. Albright, the secretary of state, requesting that the city be reimbursed for the $10 million it is spending for tasks like security and traffic control.</p>
        <p>Technicians at the Waldorf-Astoria, home for the week to about 30 leaders including President Clinton, finished installing a telephone network that includes four miles of additional cable, untold pieces of high-tech gadgetry and several rooftop satellite links. Maintenance workers at the United Nations, meanwhile, rushed to shore up a rain-soaked ceiling in a meeting room where breakfast is to be served today to more than 150 guests.</p>
        <p>It seemed that every New Yorker had a gripe about the inconvenience.</p>
        <p>A German tennis player, Nicolas Kiefer, advanced to the quarterfinals at the United States Open in Queens but only after a sleepless weekend at his hotel, the United Nations Plaza. Mr. Kiefer said he had ''a very bad night'' on Sunday because there were four security alerts. The Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, one of 18 dignitaries considered high security risks by the police, is among the hotel's guests.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiefer said he had since moved to the Waldorf. ''I think tomorrow is the same thing again,'' he said, after learning that Mr. Clinton is staying there.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who has a history of using United Nations gatherings to dress down his least favorite world leaders, attacked President Fidel Castro of Cuba, who is making his first visit to New York in several years.</p>
        <p>''I understand and sympathize with the sense of injustice that much of the Cuban community feels with regard to Fidel Castro,'' Mr. Giuliani said at a Midtown news conference. ''He's taken the land of many people, displaced families, killed people.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Castro will get his chance to turn some heads today when he addresses the summit meeting's opening session.</p>
        <p>North Korean leaders did not even make it to New York. They abruptly returned home from Germany after being subjected to security checks at the airport in Frankfurt. Choe Su Hon, the North Korean deputy foreign minister, blamed the United States for the checks, carried out by American Airlines, which apparently caused the delegation to miss its flight. The State Department said the problem may have been a result of the Koreans' not notifying American officials of their travel plans.</p>
        <p>In Harlem, the main speaker was a no-show, and the crowd outside a funeral home across the street was bigger than the news media contingent. But the Friends of Zimbabwe pressed ahead with its publicity campaign, one of an array of organizations and people across the city screaming, ''Hey, look at me!''</p>
        <p>Roger Wareham, a Brooklyn lawyer, unveiled a poster of President Robert Mugabe of Zimbabwe at the Mount Olivet Baptist Church on Malcolm X Boulevard. The Rev. Charles Curtis, pastor of the church, spoke of an international political and media campaign to discredit Mr. Mugabe. And Amadi Ajamu, the group's publicity chief, handed out a press release announcing the Zimbabwean president's appearance tomorrow night at the church, a sort of coming-out party for the African leader.</p>
        <p>''The problem is that he is not really well known in the black community,'' Mr. Wareham said. ''People know Fidel,'' he said of Mr. Castro, ''but if they've heard of Mugabe in the mainstream media, they think he is some kind of maniac.''</p>
        <p>There was a flurry of press releases, some written by hand, sent to news organizations around the city.</p>
        <p>The first lady of South Korea, Hee Ho Lee, would like it known that she will help raise money at the Y.M.C.A. in Flushing for H.I.V.-infected children. Kamalesh Sharma, India's ambassador to the United Nations, will be happy to answer questions about a book he edited, ''Imagining Tomorrow: Rethinking the Global Challenge.'' The American Anti-Slavery Group, with the help of the Guardian Angels, will try to make a citizen's arrest on President Omar Hassan al-Bashir of Sudan.</p>
        <p>Mikhail S. Gorbachev, the former Soviet leader, will be talking about the ''state of the world'' at a $5,000-per-person conference at the New York Hilton and Towers. The Pakistan Muslim League USA will condemn military rule in Pakistan.</p>
        <p>Ruby Anderson did not write a press release, but she is starving for some attention as well. She runs Al's Delicatessen at what has become ground zero during the week, 44th Street between First and Second Avenues. Al's lies behind a barricade.</p>
        <p>Customers who asked for Al's by name would have been allowed yesterday to slip past the police line, but none seemed to know this and so what would have been the 1 p.m. sandwich rush became a thin trickle of Secret Service agents, police officers and the occasional regular from the nearby Nigerian Embassy.</p>
        <p>After five years in the area, Mrs. Anderson can tell the difference. ''I can see if they're Secret Service or State Department or with the detectives or with the policemen,'' she said. ''They all behave different.''</p>
        <p>At that, three men whisked in, placed orders for sandwiches and headed for a table in the back corner of the room. The one who seemed to be in charge was clearly a figure of note, Mrs. Anderson determined, someone ''very down to business.''</p>
        <p>The customer was Leon Fuerth, Vice President Al Gore's national security adviser, and he polished off a turkey sandwich and a side of cole slaw over a talk with two staff members that one of them described only as ''important.''</p>
        <p>''He didn't care for his bagel from the Delta Shuttle,'' confided the staff member. With its paucity of customers, Al's was the perfect place to talk foreign policy on the down-low. ''It gave us an opportunity to engage in our discussion in a typical New York environment,'' he said.</p>
        <p>SUMMIT IN NEW YORK: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
