<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 U.S. Teams Win Decisively, And Bridge Semifinals Start</title>
    <meta content="06CARD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3DE1639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="347" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 U.S. Teams Win Decisively, And Bridge Semifinals Start</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>MAASTRICHT, the Netherlands, Sept. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Both United States open and women's teams advance to semifinals of World Bridge Championship (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Both United States teams won convincing victories in their quarterfinal matches at the World Bridge Championships here this afternoon, and the semifinal play began this evening.</p>
        <p>The American open team players, George Jacobs, Ralph Katz, Howard Weinstein, Steve Garner, David Berkowitz and Larry Cohen, were never in difficulty in the quarterfinal against Austria, winning by 72 imps after gaining in each of the five sessions. They have a sterner task in the semifinal against Poland, which has also been playing superbly and winning its matches easily. The Polish players defeated Iceland today by 81.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Both United States teams won convincing victories in their quarterfinal matches at the World Bridge Championships here this afternoon, and the semifinal play began this evening.</p>
        <p>The American open team players, George Jacobs, Ralph Katz, Howard Weinstein, Steve Garner, David Berkowitz and Larry Cohen, were never in difficulty in the quarterfinal against Austria, winning by 72 imps after gaining in each of the five sessions. They have a sterner task in the semifinal against Poland, which has also been playing superbly and winning its matches easily. The Polish players defeated Iceland today by 81.</p>
        <p>After 10 deals tonight the Americans led Poland by 8 imps.</p>
        <p>The semifinalists are the four countries that won the qualifying pools last week. The other match is between Italy and England, who were tied after 10 deals. The Italians, who were favored by many before play began nine days ago, have overpowered all opposition. Today they won by 92 against the strong Brazilian team. The English team won by 21 against Norway, surprising some observers. This is the first time England has played as such: the World Bridge Federation now recognizes England, Scotland and Wales as separate entities, rather than Britain.</p>
        <p>The American women's team consists of six players from Texas: Joan Jackson, Robin Klar, Peggy Sutherlin, Petra Hamman, Shawn Quinn and Mildred Breed. They played well in defeating the Netherlands today by 32, exacting a measure of revenge: the Dutch defeated another American team in Bermuda in January, winning the Venice Cup by the remarkable margin of half an imp.</p>
        <p>The Americans are now playing Norway, whose players snatched a victory by 5 in the quarterfinal after trailing almost throughout against Taiwan. After 10 deals the Americans led Norway by 27.</p>
        <p>In the other semifinal, Germany is playing Canada. After six deals, Canada led by 6. The Germans overwhelmed China today, winning by 119, while Canada held on to beat South Africa by 35.</p>
        <p>In both series, the final will begin Thursday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
