<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hospital Chief To Lead Aetna Managed Care</title>
    <meta content="Y06AET$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/business/06AETN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aetna US Healthcare</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowe, John W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1D71639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hospital Chief To Lead Aetna Managed Care</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr John W Rowe, chief executive of Mount Sinai NYU Medical Center and Health System, is named president and chief executive at Aetna US Healthcare; in Aetna, country's largest health insurer, Dr Rowe takes over company that is faced with difficult task of improving customer relations while raising prices of managed-care coverage (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John W. Rowe, who oversaw one of the largest hospital mergers in New York City and in the process became one of the industry's most prominent executives, was named president and chief executive of Aetna U.S. Healthcare late yesterday.</p>
        <p>In Dr. Rowe, the chief executive of the Mount Sinai N.Y.U. Medical Center and Health System, Aetna is hiring a well-known geriatrics specialist who has helped his hospital, a combined unit of the two big urban medical centers, stay afloat in extremely troubled times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John W. Rowe, who oversaw one of the largest hospital mergers in New York City and in the process became one of the industry's most prominent executives, was named president and chief executive of Aetna U.S. Healthcare late yesterday.</p>
        <p>In Dr. Rowe, the chief executive of the Mount Sinai N.Y.U. Medical Center and Health System, Aetna is hiring a well-known geriatrics specialist who has helped his hospital, a combined unit of the two big urban medical centers, stay afloat in extremely troubled times.</p>
        <p>In Aetna, the country's largest health insurer, Dr. Rowe takes over a company that is faced with the difficult task of improving customer relations while raising prices for managed-care coverage. Last month, the company reported a 17 percent drop in second-quarter profit; in a preliminary proxy statement filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission on Friday, it reported profit margins of less than 2 percent. Dr. Rowe will begin on Sept. 15.</p>
        <p>Through mergers, Aetna acquired U.S. Healthcare, the NYLcare unit of New York Life Insurance and Prudential Health Care, which had lost money for the Prudential Life Insurance Company of America.</p>
        <p>Under a former chief executive, Richard Huber, Aetna became a favorite target for angry doctors and other critics of managed care. William H. Donaldson, Mr. Huber's successor, has tried to calm the waters by relaxing controls on patient care, thereby risking higher internal costs, and reduced profits or perhaps losses.</p>
        <p>Wall Street analysts have urged Mr. Donaldson to find an experienced chief for the health care business, which will be spun off into a single company. Such a search is no easy task at a time health maintenance organizations have had troubles of their own.</p>
        <p>Once Aetna completes the planned spinoff of its health care unit, Dr. Rowe will become chief executive of the single company and Mr. Donaldson will remain chairman, a spokeswoman for Aetna said.</p>
        <p>Aetna and Dr. Rowe come together in a climate of some hostility between hospitals and insurers. Dr. Rowe, like his counterparts in New York, has complained of financial stress in recent years, brought on in part by what they have said is increased pressure from managed-care companies.</p>
        <p>''I see a lot of dissatisfaction with health insurance processes,'' Dr. Rowe said, ''and I think that Aetna, because of its strength as the largest health insurance company in the nation, has an opportunity to play a very significant role to change this. I am very excited about this new platform.''</p>
        <p>The Mount Sinai-N.Y.U. center is in better shape than many other medical centers in New York, though that may seem analogous to being the healthiest patient in an intensive care ward. The center earned only about $20 million on $1.7 billion in revenue last year and expects to earn roughly the same on $1.8 billion in revenue this year, partly through budget cuts like the elimination of consultants and of some management positions. The N.Y.U. hospitals ran at a deficit, a spokesman said.</p>
        <p>While the merged medical centers have increased their share of business even as others around them lost patients over the last few years, cash flow is still tight.</p>
        <p>''I would characterize Mount Sinai-N.Y.U. Health as stronger than most in the New York marketplace,'' said Liz Sweeney, a director in health care ratings at Standard &amp; Poor's, which rates the hospital's bonds BBB+, or investment grade, with a stable outlook. ''But from a national perspective, it is weaker than what we see at other organizations around the country.''</p>
        <p>New York trails its national counterparts in several ways. Managed care came late to the region, leaving many doctors and hospitals flat-footed. More important, the state had a regulated pricing policy for hospitals until 1997, and when deregulation was introduced in 1997, competition suddenly became part of the landscape.</p>
        <p>Adding the Balanced Budget Act of the same year, which reduced some payments to hospitals under Medicare, and the arrival of managed care in the marketplace, hospitals were suddenly like retailers, battling for customers and increasing their marketing budgets to sell things like pretty maternity wards and prominent doctors. Some centers have since filed for bankruptcy.</p>
        <p>''New York hospitals tend to be highly leveraged,'' Ms. Sweeney said. ''Their balance sheets tend to be thin.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Rowe, who is 56, has made many moves to help his merged center gain strides. He came to Mount Sinai in 1988 as president of the hospital and medical school and set his sights on a modernization of the campus. A one-million-square-foot inpatient center designed by I. M. Pei was added in 1993, and two other new  buildings went up later while older ones were overhauled.</p>
        <p>He also built up the center's home health agency, where revenue increased to $59 million last year from $3 million in 1998. On Dr. Rowe's watch, Mount Sinai's medical school gained stature; in 1997, the school received $97.7 million in support from the National Institutes of Health. While New York University and Mount Sinai did not meld their medical schools or clinical departments, the merged unit has saved about $24 million in administrative costs.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rowe is among New York's more accessible hospital executives and enjoys giving interviews on topics ranging from health care economics to gerontology.</p>
        <p>A professor of medicine at Mount Sinai's School of Medicine, he often goes on rounds with residents, during which he has been known to chat about acute renal failure, brag about the hospital's savings on its meal program and recall banter once exchanged with I. M. Pei.</p>
        <p>Before joining Mount Sinai, he was the founding director of the division of aging at Harvard Medical School and chief of gerontology at Beth Israel Hospital in Boston. He has written extensively on geriatric medicine and aging.</p>
        <p>''This is a big win for Aetna,'' said James R. Tallon, the president of the United Hospital Fund, a philanthropy group. ''The issues facing the insurance industry and health care industry are complicated long-term issues, and someone of Jack's stature can only be positive for Aetna.''</p>
        <p>And while some could argue that Dr. Rowe is joining forces with a semi-adversary of sorts, Ms. Sweeney of Standard &amp; Poor's said that could also work in Aetna's favor.</p>
        <p>''Health plans and hospitals sit across from each other in negotiations,'' she said. ''So from that perspective, I am sure he is valuable to them. But it could seem like now he is part of the problem.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
