<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Mountains Are Almonds</title>
    <meta content="06ALMO$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000913T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NATIONAL ORIGINS: CALIFORNIA'S CENTRAL VALLEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Almonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7DD1639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2381" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Mountains Are Almonds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>HURON, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of almond industry in California's Central Valley, which produces 70 percent of world's supply of almonds, nation's top horticultural export; vast groves are in midst of intensive harvest season as growers rush to get crop hulled and shelled, packed and shipped before fall rains; recipes; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY are among the oldest cultivated foods on earth, the stuff of Greek myths, a prized ingredient of the pharaohs' breads, a staple of Biblical feasts. They are believed to have originated in China and Central Asia, and their pinkish white blossoms and graceful branches call to mind the cherry trees whose botanical family they share. Transported to the Mediterranean by the traders of the Silk Road, they have been an important commodity since the Middle Ages.</p>
        <p>But here in the flat, hot, rich farmlands of California's Central Valley, almonds are nothing so much as big business. The state's 6,000 growers produce more than 600 million pounds a year, more than 70 percent of the world's supply and virtually 100 percent of domestic production. Almonds far outpace wine, oranges, apples and raisins as the United States' top horticultural export, worth close to $800 million annually. Eat marzipan in Germany or almonds salted in the shell like ballpark peanuts in India or China, and odds are high the nuts came from California.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY are among the oldest cultivated foods on earth, the stuff of Greek myths, a prized ingredient of the pharaohs' breads, a staple of Biblical feasts. They are believed to have originated in China and Central Asia, and their pinkish white blossoms and graceful branches call to mind the cherry trees whose botanical family they share. Transported to the Mediterranean by the traders of the Silk Road, they have been an important commodity since the Middle Ages.</p>
        <p>But here in the flat, hot, rich farmlands of California's Central Valley, almonds are nothing so much as big business. The state's 6,000 growers produce more than 600 million pounds a year, more than 70 percent of the world's supply and virtually 100 percent of domestic production. Almonds far outpace wine, oranges, apples and raisins as the United States' top horticultural export, worth close to $800 million annually. Eat marzipan in Germany or almonds salted in the shell like ballpark peanuts in India or China, and odds are high the nuts came from California.</p>
        <p>These late summer weeks are crunch time in the long, endless groves. The fruit has ripened, its outer gray-greenish hull has cracked open to reveal a pale, crackly perforated inner shell, inside which a jewel is nestled: the moistly crunchy, brown-skinned nut itself. The harvest, from early August to Halloween, is a 7-day-a-week, 24-hour-a-day affair, as growers rush to get their crop hulled and shelled, packed and shipped before the fall rains make the groves a soggy mess.</p>
        <p>The groves are vast, more like factories than farms, stretching up the spine of the state for 400 miles. Though the landscape is broken by the occasional cottonwood tree, it is not a place of roadside stands. Here the tomatoes lie in great heaps waiting to be processed into paste, and cotton grows in endless seas. There are no mom-and-pop shops with bags of almonds, the way one finds paper sacks of boiled peanuts in Georgia. Even a family farm, like Chris Woolf's, is an industrial sort of operation. The tidy farm lunchroom, a small building with whitewashed walls, Mexican tile floors and Fiestaware plates, does not feature almonds on the menu.</p>
        <p>Time was, workers walked the groves tapping trees with tall poles to shake the fruit to the ground. Now an armada of diesel-powered mechanical shaking machines (one leading model is the Shock Wave Shaker) grip trees with rubber-coated hydraulic pincers, creating custom-made mini-earthquakes of trembling trunks and branches and hailstorms of falling nuts up and down the orchard rows.</p>
        <p>''What do you compare that to?'' asked Stacey Kollmeyer, the communications manager of the Almond Board of California and a third-generation almond hand, as the ground rumbled and a tornado of dust rose from a shaking Sonora almond tree on the Woolfs' farm here the other day. ''It's like the tree's being electrocuted.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Woolf, 38, is the very model of a modern major almond grower, producing something on the order of six million pounds of nut meat a year on a couple of thousand acres of family-owned and leased land about an hour southwest of Fresno, just off Interstate 5 in the San Joaquin Valley. His family has been farming almonds (and cotton, tomatoes, pistachios, garlic, onions and oranges) since 1973, and now has a full, vertically integrated operation, starting with an almond nursery of some 300,000 seedlings and ending with a processing plant (owned in partnership with the Harris cattle ranching family) that hulls, shells and ships about 20 million pounds a year, most of it for direct overseas export.</p>
        <p>''It's just so important not to have a breakdown at this time of year,'' Mr. Woolf said as he checked in with Jose Jimenez, a worker operating a new $95,000 shaker, one of six in the Woolf family fleet, from inside its compact, air-conditioned cab.</p>
        <p>A graduate of the University of California at Berkeley, with a degree in history, Mr. Woolf also has an M.B.A. in agribusiness from the University of Santa Clara, and is what's known in the trade as a handler, one of about 100 growers officially responsible for recording the weight and quality of growers' almonds, collecting assessments for the Almond Board; his farm also serves as a site where the United States Agriculture Department's inspectors assess the crop. He is also in the middle of a one-year term as chairman of the Almond Board, created in 1950 to help market almonds.</p>
        <p>As such, Mr. Woolf is squarely astride what has amounted to an explosion in the California almond crop. Almonds were first brought to the state in the 18th century, by the Franciscan padres who founded the chain of coastal missions, but the trees suffered in the misty, moist conditions near the Pacific, and only a hundred later were successfully planted inland.</p>
        <p>The Central Valley has been prime almond terrain for most of the 20th century, but the crop has quadrupled over the last 30 years as efficient production, ideal growing conditions, economies of scale and growing demand for almonds in everything from breakfast cereal to specialty oils has given the state a virtual corner on the world market, with countries like Spain, Italy and Greece together producing not even a third of California's yield.</p>
        <p>Anne Gingrass, the chef at Hawthorne Lane in San Francisco, uses almonds year-round, and in ways that are not always obvious. In a risotto with dried red chilies and goat cheese, she chops up almonds and cooks them with the rice so they attain a similar texture as the grains, and, she added, they round out the flavor and heat of the chilies. She also uses them to thicken chicken soup, pureeing the almonds with the broth.</p>
        <p>''Hazelnuts are so strong, pine nuts are unpredictable -- you don't know if you're going to get a bad one, and they're really fatty,'' she said. ''Almonds are subtle.''</p>
        <p>Almonds, long promoted in culinary lore as a hedge against intoxication if eaten with wine, have also benefited from a recent wave of nutritional and dietary revisionism. Like all nuts, they are high in fat, but mostly in mono-unsaturated fat, the kind that predominates in canola and olive oils and avocados, and is celebrated for its ability to lower harmful cholesterol. Several current diets, like the Zone, by Barry Sears, celebrate almonds for their satiating qualities and their ability to help satisfy cravings for less healthy fats. Almonds contain beneficial calcium, potassium and magnesium, all protections against high blood pressure. They are also potent sources of anti-oxidants, which have been linked to protection against cancer and heart disease.</p>
        <p>An ounce of almonds, about 24 whole nuts, has 164 calories.</p>
        <p>An almond tree in commercial production today begins with a hardy root stock grown from a peach pit (another botanical relative), onto which a more delicate almond cutting is grafted. Trees can begin producing nuts in about five years (two or three years shorter than pistachios) and reach peak productivity at about 10 years, which tapers off to almost nothing by age 25 or so. The annual production cycle -- and forecast of the year's yield -- begins romantically around Valentine's Day with the bloom, when orchards are transformed into spectacular oceans of pale pink blossoms.</p>
        <p>Because almonds are not self-pollinating, different varieties are planted in alternating rows, and more than a million beehives are brought by commercial beekeepers into the state each winter to pollinate trees. It is a fraught time, and a whole year's crop depends on the vagaries of wind and weather.</p>
        <p>''The bees won't fly if it rains,'' Mr. Woolf said, talking of this year's spotty bloom, which is expected to produce a crop about 25 percent below last year's record yield. ''They won't fly if it's under 54 degrees. We knew we'd have a lower crop.''</p>
        <p>Once the nuts have been shaken to the ground, another set of machines, a bit like street sweepers, blow and rake them into neat rows between the trees, and still others with whirling rubber-toothed paddles come and pick them up into a wagon. They are taken to the Harris-Woolf processing plant nearby and piled in like batches, covered with plastic sheeting and fumigated.</p>
        <p>Then comes the hulling and shelling, which is the province of Dean Nelson, a former banker from Arizona who used to handle the Woolf family account and decided a few years ago to return to his roots as a Utah farm boy by coming to run the almond plant. It's a spiffy operation, worthy of Rube Goldberg, in which the almonds move along a series of elevators and conveyors, under rollers and over shaking perforated trays with a series of successively finer holes. Nothing (except dust) gets wasted. First the hulls are cracked off completely and piled in giant mounds to be hauled off as a feed supplement for dairy cattle.</p>
        <p>Then the brittle, almost papery inner shells are cracked and separated, in part using air blasts and suction. They become livestock bedding. Finally, the brown nuts fall through a series of slots to be sized, graded, weighed and, ultimately, packed for shipment in 2,000-pound wood containers or 50-pound cardboard boxes. The plant's annual electric bill is about $130,000, most of it racked up in the hundred days of harvest.</p>
        <p>The biggest problem is, as Mr. Nelson puts it: ''Every time you move an almond, you take a chance of chipping it up.'' The chipped ones fetch less at market, and go for products from candy bars to blanched almonds for baking and cooking. The unscarred nuts are reserved for snacking and fancy use, with the most popular variety -- -- the nonpareil, the fat, perfectly shaped nut in a can of smoked almonds or atop a fine pastry -- accounting for nearly 40 percent of California's total production.</p>
        <p>Some of the nuts hulled at Harris-Woolf are bound for shipment to Blue Diamond, the giant cooperative that handles about 35 percent of all the state's production and is the single largest processor. Most are sent directly to brokers for sale.</p>
        <p>The big growth market at the moment is China, which now accounts of 25 percent of American export sales and now buys more than 25 million pounds a year. So the almond growers are thrilled at the prospect of lower tariffs once China enters the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Woolf may sell globally, but he still grows locally, something he made clear as he walked a row of ripening trees the other day.</p>
        <p>''It's not rocket science,'' he said, ''but a lot of farming is just checking. The best sign of management is seeing the owner's footprints in the dirt.''</p>
        <p>ALMOND PLUM TARTS  Adapted from ''New Food Fast,'' by Donna Hay (Whitecap Books, 1999)  Time: 35 minutes</p>
        <p>1/2 cup blanched whole almonds  4 small plums or apricots  4 ounces (1 stick) butter, at room temperature</p>
        <p>1/2 cup superfine sugar  2 large eggs  1 teaspoon vanilla extract</p>
        <p>1/3 cup all-purpose flour  Lightly sweetened whipped cream, for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 400 degrees. Using a food processor, chop almonds until finely ground; do not allow to become a paste. Transfer to a bowl and set aside. Cut a small cross into stem end of each plum, and remove pit; set plums aside.</p>
        <p>2. In bowl of food processor, combine butter and sugar. Process until smooth. Add eggs, vanilla, flour and ground almonds. Process until just combined.</p>
        <p>3. Divide almond mixture among four 1-cup pudding or souffle dishes. Press a plum, cut side up, into center of batter; a portion of the plum will remain above the batter.</p>
        <p>4. Bake until filling is puffed and golden, 15 to 20 minutes. Garnish tarts with a dollop of whipped cream. Serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>ALMOND-AND-HAZELNUT-CHIP MACAROONS  Adapted from ''Desserts: Mediterranean Flavors, California Style,''  by Cindy Mushet (Scribner, 2000)  Time: 1 hour</p>
        <p>2/3 cup whole hazelnuts, shelled  2 cups whole natural almonds, shelled  1 1/4 cups sugar  2 to 3 large egg whites  2 tablespoons apricot jam  1 teaspoon minced lemon zest.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 400 degrees. Spread hazelnuts across baking sheet, and bake until skins are lightly browned, about 5 minutes; do not turn off oven. Roll nuts in a clean kitchen towel. Pressing lightly on towel, roll back and forth to loosen skins of nuts. Transfer skinned nuts to a food processor. Chop until nuts are the size of chocolate chips.  Transfer to a bowl and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Spread almonds on a baking sheet and bake until lightly browned, about 5 minutes; remove from heat. Reduce oven to 350 degrees. Allow nuts to cool, and place in bowl of a food processor. Add sugar, and process until almonds are very finely ground, 30 to 40 seconds. Add 2 egg whites, jam and lemon zest. Pulse until blended; mixture should be thick and tacky when pressed with fingertip.  If dry, add a teaspoon of remaining egg white, and pulse; repeat if necessary to reach desired consistency.</p>
        <p>3. Transfer mixture to a large bowl. Add hazelnuts, and knead by hand until blended. Lightly wet hands to prevent sticking. Divide dough in half, then divide each half into 8 pieces, for a total of 16 pieces. Shape pieces into balls, and place eight balls on each of two parchment-lined baking sheets.</p>
        <p>4. Position oven racks in top and center thirds of oven. Bake macaroons until golden brown, 18 to 22 minutes, reversing baking sheets from front to back and top to bottom halfway through cooking time. Store for up to one week in an airtight container, or freeze for up to one month.</p>
        <p>Yield: Sixteen 3-inch macaroons.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL ORIGINS: CALIFORNIA'S CENTRAL VALLEY  Correction:  September 13, 2000, Wednesday  A word was omitted last Wednesday from an article in this section about almond farming in California. The affected sentence should have read, ''Almonds were first brought to the state in the 18th century, by the Franciscan padres who founded the chain of coastal missions, but the trees suffered in the misty, moist conditions near the Pacific, and only a hundred years later were successfully planted inland.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 13, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A word was omitted last Wednesday from an article in this section about almond farming in California. The affected sentence should have read, ''Almonds were first brought to the state in the 18th century, by the Franciscan padres who founded the chain of coastal missions, but the trees suffered in the misty, moist conditions near the Pacific, and only a hundred years later were successfully planted inland.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
