<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="06TRAN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1DB1739F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Transactions</p>
        <p>Baseball  MLB--Suspended Tampa Bay Devil Rays OF Gerald Williams for five games, RHP Dave Eiland, RHP Tony Fiore, RHP Cory Lidle and manager Larry Rothschild for three games, and fined each an undisclosed amount for their parts in a brawl in an Aug. 29 game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Transactions</p>
        <p>Baseball  MLB--Suspended Tampa Bay Devil Rays OF Gerald Williams for five games, RHP Dave Eiland, RHP Tony Fiore, RHP Cory Lidle and manager Larry Rothschild for three games, and fined each an undisclosed amount for their parts in a brawl in an Aug. 29 game.</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Recalled LHP Juan Alvarez from Edmonton of the PCL and RHP Ben Weber from Erie of the Eastern League.  BOSTON RED SOX--Recalled INF Morgan Burkhart from Pawtucket of the International League. Sent RHP Dan Smith outright to Pawtucket.  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Recalled OF McKay Christensen, INF-OF Jeff Liefer, INF Greg Norton and RHP Kip Wells from Charlotte of the International League.  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Optioned RHP David Riske to Buffalo of the International League.  DETROIT TIGERS--Activated RHP Dave Mlicki and 1B Hal Morris from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled 1B-OF Dusty Allen from Toledo of the International League. Purchased the contract of LHP Kevin Tolar from Toledo.  KANSAS CITY ROYALS--Recalled OF Dermal Brown and RHP Dan Murray from Omaha of the PCL.  NEW YORK YANKEES--Purchased the contract of LHP Randy Keisler from Columbus of the International League. Recalled INF Alfonso Soriano and RHP Darrell Einertson from Columbus and placed Einertson on the 60-day disabled list.  TEXAS RANGERS--Purchased the contracts of C Randy Knorr and OF Ruben Sierra from Oklahoma of the PCL. Recalled RHP Darwin Cubillan and INF Kelly Dransfeldt from Oklahoma. Moved LHP Mike Munoz from the 15-day to the 60-day disabled list.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Recalled INF Chris Woodward from Syracuse of the International League. Purchased the contract of OF Chad Mottola from Syracuse. Designated INF Kevin Witt for assignment.</p>
        <p>National League  ARIZONA DIAMONDBACKS--Recalled RHP Geraldo Guzman and OF Jason Conti from Tuscon of the PCL.  ATLANTA BRAVES--Recalled INF Mark DeRosa and INF Wes Helms from Richmond of the International League. Purchased the contracts of INF Tim Unroe, C Mike Hubbard and OF Pedro Swann from Richmond. Recalled RHP Kevin McGlinchy from an injury rehabilitation assignment at Richmond.  CHICAGO CUBS--Waived RHP Matt Karchner. Recalled INF Julio Zuleta, INF Chad Meyers and INF Augie Ojeda from Iowa of the PCL. and purchased the contract of catcher Mike Mahoney from Iowa.  CINCINNATI REDS--Recalled INF Brooks Kieschnick and RHP Keith Glauber from Louisville of the International League. Moved C Eddie Taubensee from the 15-day to the 60-day disabled list.  COLORADO ROCKIES--Transferred OF Larry Walker from the 15-day to the 60-day disabled list. Recalled RHP Pete Walker from Colorado Springs of the PCL. Activated RHP Giovanni Carrara from the 15-day disabled list.  LOS ANGELES DODGERS--Activated SS Kevin Elster from the 15-day disabled list.  MONTREAL EXPOS--Recalled RHP Jeremy Powell, LHP Stan Spencer and SS Tomas De La Rosa from Ottawa of the International League.  NEW YORK METS--Recalled INF Joe McEwing from Norfolk of the International League.  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Placed INF Kevin Nicholson on the 60-day disabled list. Purchased the contract of INF Greg LaRocca from Las Vegas of the PCL.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  National Football League  JACKSONVILLE JAGUARS--Placed TE Damon Jones on injured reserve. Signed TE Greg DeLong.  MINNESOTA VIKINGS--Signed LB Gabe Northern. Released TE Matt Cercone from the practice squad.  NEW YORK GIANTS--Re-signed CB Ramos McDonald. Waived TE-S Brody Heffner-Liddiard and signed him to the practice squad. Released FB Michael Jones from the practice squad.  SAN DIEGO CHARGERS--Signed DE Neil Smith to a two-year contract.  TAMPA BAY BUCCANEERS--Announced the retirement of LT Paul Gruber.  TENNESSEE TITANS--Released CB Ty Howard. Reinstated CB Denard Walker from a one-game suspension. Released WR Chris Coleman from the practice squad. Signed G Aaron Koch to the practice squad.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League  ANAHEIM MIGHTY DUCKS--Re-signed C Matt Cullen to a one-year contract.  COLORADO AVALANCHE--Signed LW Brad Larsen and D Stewart Malgunas.  EDMONTON OILERS--Signed F Shawn Horcoff to a three-year contract.  PITTSBURGH PENGUINS--Signed G Sebastien Caron.  VANCOUVER CANUCKS--Signed LW Dody Wood.</p>
        <p>SOCCER  Major League Soccer  MLS--Fined Miami Fusion F Roy Lassiter $500 for failure to leave the field in a timely fashion after a game on Aug. 30, Dallas Burn D Ricardo Iribarren $500 for violent conduct in a game on Aug. 30 and Chicago Fire F Ante Razov $250 for making an obscene gesture at the crowd in an Aug. 23 game.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE  BIG SOUTH CONFERENCE--Announced Birmingham-Southern will join the league as a full member in fall 2003.  DEPAUL--Announced the resignation of Deborah Rutkowski-Murphy, women's track and field coach. Named Gordon Thomason women's track and field coach.  MICHIGAN--Dismissed G Kevin Gaines from the basketball team for violating team policy.  NYU--Named Rich Mueller men's golf coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
