<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Handyman 101: English a Must</title>
    <meta content="06MYJO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/business/06MYJO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MY JOB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Building Service Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ponichtera, Marek</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Skomial, Marcin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E6D81339F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Handyman 101: English a Must</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAREK PONICHTERA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ponichtera, Marek</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marek Ponichtera My Job column, written with Marcin Skomial, on working as building superintendent; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I set out for America 10 years ago with my new wife and $500 that I had borrowed from friends. My wife's uncle picked us up at Kennedy Airport. He was the only person we knew in this country -- and he was unemployed. My wife soon got a part-time job as a cleaning lady for a family in Brooklyn. I couldn't find work, so I helped her out. I did whatever I was told to do: sweeping the walk, washing windows, changing bulbs. As payment, we received free room and board, but no money. The family didn't speak Polish, but somehow we were able to communicate through sign language and an English-Polish dictionary that I always carried with me.</p>
        <p>Finally, a year later, I got a job as a mason's helper at a construction site. I carried 50-pound loads of bricks around -- not easy, as I weigh about 140 pounds -- and I put in 10 to 12 hours a day, 6 days a week. My poor English was a worse disadvantage than ever. Once, a worker asked me to bring him a hammer. I nodded and fetched a screwdriver. He burst out laughing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I set out for America 10 years ago with my new wife and $500 that I had borrowed from friends. My wife's uncle picked us up at Kennedy Airport. He was the only person we knew in this country -- and he was unemployed. My wife soon got a part-time job as a cleaning lady for a family in Brooklyn. I couldn't find work, so I helped her out. I did whatever I was told to do: sweeping the walk, washing windows, changing bulbs. As payment, we received free room and board, but no money. The family didn't speak Polish, but somehow we were able to communicate through sign language and an English-Polish dictionary that I always carried with me.</p>
        <p>Finally, a year later, I got a job as a mason's helper at a construction site. I carried 50-pound loads of bricks around -- not easy, as I weigh about 140 pounds -- and I put in 10 to 12 hours a day, 6 days a week. My poor English was a worse disadvantage than ever. Once, a worker asked me to bring him a hammer. I nodded and fetched a screwdriver. He burst out laughing.</p>
        <p>It was about then that I enrolled in a class to learn English. I also picked up other trade skills, and in 1992 I got a job doing carpentry, electrical work and painting.</p>
        <p>Two years later, I was hired as superintendent of a residential building on West 85th Street. The pay and free housing seemed like a good deal, but I quickly realized I had my work cut out for me. I was responsible for the whole building, and anyone who needed something done in his apartment called me to do it.</p>
        <p>Once, on a Sunday evening when I was getting ready to go out to a movie with my wife, my intercom started ringing. Someone had a leak in his apartment and the water had dripped into the apartment underneath. It took me two hours to solve that problem, and when I got back to our apartment, my wife handed me a sheet of paper with two other assignments: in both cases, a toilet had gotten clogged and the tenant was in desperate need of a plunger.</p>
        <p>In 1995, my boss asked me to supervise the renovation of apartments at a much larger building he owned on West 90th Street. Although my title was still superintendent, I no longer had to deal with leaks and clogged toilets. I hired a porter to take care of those chores, while I sat in my office in the basement, ordering paint and Sheetrock and hiring workers, mostly newly arrived Poles who couldn't speak English.</p>
        <p>Once, my boss started shouting at a group of them unloading steel pipes from a truck to work faster. They ignored him. When I saw what was happening, I hurried to explain to him that none of them understood a word he was saying.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, I am surprised at how rude people can be. Perfect strangers will make disdainful comments about my work clothes, which are often spattered with paint, for example.</p>
        <p>One Sunday, when my porter was off duty, a lady asked me to come to her apartment immediately to fix her air-conditioner. While I was working, she asked me about my family and background. At some point, she started to express dissatisfaction with my Polish accent and the fact that I came from a formerly Communist country. It didn't seem to matter to her that she herself came from Romania -- and had a Romanian accent.</p>
        <p>MY JOB Written with Marcin Skomial.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Written with Marcin Skomial.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
