<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man to Admit To Murdering 3 L.I. Patients</title>
    <meta content="06DOC.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/nyregion/06DOC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poisoning and Poisons</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Veterans Affairs Medical Center (Northport, Li)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swango, Michael J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Samarco, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Siano, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Serini, Aldo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poisoning and Poisons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EEDC1739F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man to Admit To Murdering 3 L.I. Patients</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LeDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., Sept. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Swango, former physician who authorities say poisoned patients from Ohio to Zimbabwe but continued to find medical jobs, will plead guilty in federal court to charges that he killed three patients at Northport Veterans Affairs Medical Center on Long Island in 1993 by poisoning them; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former physician who the authorities say poisoned patients from Ohio to Zimbabwe but continued to find medical jobs will plead guilty in federal court Wednesday to charges that he killed three patients at a Long Island hospital in 1993, prosecutors said today.</p>
        <p>The former doctor, Michael J. Swango, will admit that he murdered the three men with poison while working at the Northport Veterans Affairs Medical Center on Long Island, according to Gary R. Brown, the assistant United States attorney who is prosecuting the case. Beyond that, Mr. Brown would offer no particulars about the plea agreement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former physician who the authorities say poisoned patients from Ohio to Zimbabwe but continued to find medical jobs will plead guilty in federal court Wednesday to charges that he killed three patients at a Long Island hospital in 1993, prosecutors said today.</p>
        <p>The former doctor, Michael J. Swango, will admit that he murdered the three men with poison while working at the Northport Veterans Affairs Medical Center on Long Island, according to Gary R. Brown, the assistant United States attorney who is prosecuting the case. Beyond that, Mr. Brown would offer no particulars about the plea agreement.</p>
        <p>But an official familiar with the negotiations between prosecutors and lawyers for Mr. Swango, 45, said that by accepting the deal he would avoid the death penalty in New York and extradition to Zimbabwe, where the authorities have issued a warrant for Mr. Swango's arrest on charges that he poisoned seven patients, five of them fatally, when he worked there from November 1994 to July 1995.</p>
        <p>The official said  that the former doctor would also plead guilty Wednesday before Judge Jacob Mishler of United States District Court to mail and wire fraud charges. Within the description of those charges, Mr. Swango is accused of assaulting two patients in Africa, another elderly patient at the Veterans Hospital and a patient at Ohio State University Hospitals, all of whom died in his care, the official said.</p>
        <p>Randi Chavis, a lawyer for Mr. Swango, would not comment on the plea agreement.</p>
        <p>With the agreement, prosecutors say they will close the book on one of the most bizarre and unsettling stories in modern medicine. It seemed that no matter where Mr. Swango went, allegations, suspicion and death followed. According to the book ''Blind Eye: The Terrifying Story of a Doctor Who Got Away With Murder'' (Simon &amp; Schuster, 1999), by James B. Stewart, questions about Mr. Swango began to surface as early 1982, when he was a medical student at Southern Illinois University. After an inordinate number of his patients died, classmates called him Double-0 Swango, joking that he had a license to kill.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors believe that while working as an intern the next year at Ohio State University Hospitals, Mr. Swango murdered or tried to murder a number of patients by injecting them with poison. In his plea, it is expected that Mr. Swango will also acknowledge that he lied to the hospital investigators in connection with the death of the Ohio State Hospitals patient, Cynthia McGee, 19, in January 1984. Prosecutors said that Mr. Swango murdered her by giving her a potassium injection that caused her heart to stop.</p>
        <p>After several mysterious deaths, but no hard evidence, the Ohio State University Hospitals ended Mr. Swango's neurosurgery residency. He then returned home to Illinois, where he got a job as a emergency medical technician with the Adams County Ambulance Service. While working there, he got into a dispute with co-workers and laced their doughnuts and coffee with ant killer. Five people became ill but no one died. Mr. Swango served two years of a five-year sentence.</p>
        <p>When released from prison, Mr. Swango applied to residency programs in West Virginia and Iowa, but administrators noticed his falsified records, and his applications were rejected. He tried a third time in 1993 at the Veterans hospital in Northport, N.Y., and was accepted. The day after he was hired, his first patient, Dominic Buffalino, fell into a coma and died.</p>
        <p>Three more patients died of lethal injections delivered by Mr. Swango, prosecutors said: Thomas Sammarco, 73; George Siano, 60; and Aldo Serini, all of Long Island. Mr. Swango will plead guilty to their murders on Wednesday, prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>Officials charged Mr. Swango with the three murders in July, just as he was about to be released from prison in Colorado, where he was serving a three-and-a-half-year term for lying his way into the Northport hospital. After exhuming the men's bodies, forensic experts determined that they had indeed been poisoned.</p>
        <p>''I've heard the news this afternoon'' Mr. Siano's stepdaughter, Roselinda Conroy, said today about the plea agreement. She said she had always assumed that her father had died from natural causes. ''I'm absorbing it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Relatives of Mr. Buffalino said that they were happy that a serial killer would be removed from society, but would remain dissatisfied until the cause of his death was properly identified. ''I'm glad he can't kill anymore, but I would like to see some answers in terms of my brother,'' said Andrew Buffalino, 70, of Huntington. ''My interest now is one thing. I want to see an autopsy report.''</p>
        <p>After Northport officials learned of Mr. Swango's criminal record, they fired him. He became a physician at Mnene Mission Hospital in Bulawayo, Zimbabwe, using forged documents form the Federation of State Medical Boards. He is still wanted in that country.</p>
        <p>Mr. Swango was eventually arrested in 1997 in Chicago while waiting for a flight to Saudi Arabia, where he had a new job as a doctor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
