<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reaching for the Stars, Selling Drugs on Earth</title>
    <meta content="06TURN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/arts/06TURN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adetuyi, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pras (Prakazriel Michel)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rule, Ja</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Turn It Up (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EED61F30F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reaching for the Stars, Selling Drugs on Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews movie Turn It Up, written and directed by Robert Adetuyi; Pras (Prakazriel Michel) and Ja Rule star (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's been called screen presence, star quality and charisma. But a more apt word for the buzz exuded by the stars of the rickety rap melodrama ''Turn It Up'' might be attitude. The projection of attitude (with a capital A) is a basic ingredient of hip-hop performance, and it's one reason rappers seem able to make the transition from music to movies far more easily than their rock-and-roll forerunners. Long before appearing in the films, they were already rehearsing their roles.</p>
        <p>The typical rap record, after all, is an action-adventure film (minus the visuals) in which the performer struts a personal fantasy of urban life. And in ''Turn It Up,'' which has been touted in advance as the hip-hop answer to ''Purple Rain,'' the rappers Prakazriel Michel (better known as Pras) and Ja Rule (making his movie debut) hold the screen with a brash, swaggering arrogance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's been called screen presence, star quality and charisma. But a more apt word for the buzz exuded by the stars of the rickety rap melodrama ''Turn It Up'' might be attitude. The projection of attitude (with a capital A) is a basic ingredient of hip-hop performance, and it's one reason rappers seem able to make the transition from music to movies far more easily than their rock-and-roll forerunners. Long before appearing in the films, they were already rehearsing their roles.</p>
        <p>The typical rap record, after all, is an action-adventure film (minus the visuals) in which the performer struts a personal fantasy of urban life. And in ''Turn It Up,'' which has been touted in advance as the hip-hop answer to ''Purple Rain,'' the rappers Prakazriel Michel (better known as Pras) and Ja Rule (making his movie debut) hold the screen with a brash, swaggering arrogance.</p>
        <p>Pras, a founding member of the Fugees, plays Diamond, an up-and-coming rapper from Brooklyn, and Ja Rule is Gage, his thuggish manager and best friend since childhood. As the movie opens, Diamond has already acquired an underground reputation for his rap performances in after-hours clubs. He and Gage are recording a demo with funds made from low-level drug deals arranged by Mr. B (Jason Staham), a sinister and vicious British drug czar with ties to the record business. One of Mr. B's closest pals is a record president known only (and symbolically) as Mr. White (John Ralston).</p>
        <p>Diamond is also trying to hold together a volatile relationship with his girlfriend, Kia (Tamala Jones), who announces that she's pregnant and pressures him into making a commitment. One sure sign of Diamond's ambivalence about the relationship is his refusal to give her his cell phone number.</p>
        <p>Everything explodes at once. Diamond's mother suddenly dies, and his father, Cliff (Vondie Curtis-Hall), who had vanished years earlier, appears out of the blue and invites himself to stay with his still-resentful son. And without consulting Diamond, Gage goes on the criminal rampage to acquire the big bucks to pay for an independently produced record.</p>
        <p>Robert Adetuyi, who wrote and directed ''Turn It Up,'' has a sharp ear for streetwise dialogue and an eye for seedy urban ambience. His screenplay captures the urgency, impatience and frustrations of impoverished musicians just one recording away from becoming millionaires. The story takes for granted Diamond's and Gage's illicit interim self-support system, implying without judgment that this is the way it's often done in the rap world.</p>
        <p>But in the film's more intimate scenes, the dialogue turns wooden and self-conscious. And as the movie goes along, it loses track of its subplots. Its minor characters, especially the robotic Mr. White, who talks like an Eddie Murphy imitation of Richard Nixon, are implausible. And what are we to make of the prodigal father who abandoned his wife and young son to pursue a career as a jazz pianist, then sank into alcoholism and now exudes a sagelike authority and wisdom? The complicated father-son relationship, which could have been a movie in itself, is left unexplored.</p>
        <p>Eventually ''Turn It Up'' deteriorates into a gory shoot-'em-up gangster movie with a quick-fix ending that leaves many threads dangling. It could have been something more.</p>
        <p>The movie is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It has profanity and some gory violence.</p>
        <p>TURN IT UP</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Robert Adetuyi; based on a story by Ray Cory Daniels, Chris Hudson and Kelly Hilaire; director of photography, Hubert Taczanowski; edited by Jeff Freeman; music by Frank Fitzpatrick; production designer, Ina Mayhew; produced by Guy Oseary and Happy Walters; released by New Line Cinema. Running time: 100 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Pras (Diamond), Vondie Curtis-Hall (Cliff), Ja Rule (Gage), John Ralston (Mr. White), Jason Statham (Mr. B.), Tamala Jones (Kia), Eugene Clark (Marshall) and Chris Messina (Baz).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
