<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>National Grid Announces Niagara Mohawk Purchase</title>
    <meta content="Y06UTI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/business/06UTIL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Grid Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Niagara Mohawk Holdings</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E3D81639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>National Grid Announces Niagara Mohawk Purchase</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Grid Group of Britain acquires Niagara Mohawk Co, upstate New York power company, for $3 billion; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>So far, the names have stayed the same among the small utilities that serve communities from the Mississippi to the Atlantic, and from Maine to Florida. But that masks the efforts of the large, ambitious electricity concerns that are rapidly swallowing local companies to fashion regional giants. Yesterday's acquisition of Niagara Mohawk, in upstate New York, by the National Grid Group, of Britain, emphasizes that trend.</p>
        <p>The $3 billion National Grid purchase, confirmed yesterday, comes on the heels of two other mergers. A month ago, the FPL Group of Florida, merged with Entergy to create a Gulf Coast company with more than six million customers, making it the nation's largest utility. Weeks later, FirstEnergy acquired GPU of New Jersey for $4.5 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>So far, the names have stayed the same among the small utilities that serve communities from the Mississippi to the Atlantic, and from Maine to Florida. But that masks the efforts of the large, ambitious electricity concerns that are rapidly swallowing local companies to fashion regional giants. Yesterday's acquisition of Niagara Mohawk, in upstate New York, by the National Grid Group, of Britain, emphasizes that trend.</p>
        <p>The $3 billion National Grid purchase, confirmed yesterday, comes on the heels of two other mergers. A month ago, the FPL Group of Florida, merged with Entergy to create a Gulf Coast company with more than six million customers, making it the nation's largest utility. Weeks later, FirstEnergy acquired GPU of New Jersey for $4.5 billion.</p>
        <p>''Virtually every utility in the country is willing to sit down and talk with anyone who presents a serious proposal,'' said Tia Barancik, a lawyer with LeBoeuf, Lamb, Greene &amp; MacRae who specializes in utilities.</p>
        <p>The Northeast, perhaps more than any other region, has become a key staging ground for consolidation because it was among the first places in the country where states deregulated the power industry. That, in turn, created opportunities for utilities to streamline their businesses, add new ones and generally make more money than they had in the past. As a result, local utilities have been hooking up, as Consolidated Edison is in the process of doing with Northeast Utilities.</p>
        <p>Moreover, deregulation has drawn the interest of outsiders like National Grid. Within the last year, the company acquired two other Northeast utilities, New England Electric Systems and the Eastern Utilities Association. Its purchase of Niagara Mohawk would give National Grid about 3.3 million electricity customers, making it the ninth-largest electric utility in the country, and 540,000 natural gas customers.</p>
        <p>The National Grid acquisitions, analysts say, represent a shift in the kind of mergers that will unfurl within the industry in the next few years. Until recently, companies of similar size often made deals, normally with little reason except to get bigger and keep competitors at bay. As a result, their shares often took a drubbing. Now larger companies are pursuing smaller companies to build a position in a particular market and to fill certain niches.</p>
        <p>Indeed, National Grid seems to be moving to create an entity that will distribute power across one of most densely populated parts of the country. None of National Grid's holdings, including Niagara Mohawk, actually generate power. Under deregulation, they sold their power plants and now buy electricity from various plants, apparently with an eye to getting the lowest price for themselves and the customer.</p>
        <p>Analysts say the addition of Niagara Mohawk to National Grid's earlier acquisitions will give the combined company more power to bargain for cheaper rates when it buys electricity. National Grid also stated that by streamlining staff and instituting more efficient business practices, the expanded company would save about $90 million in the first four years after the merger became official.</p>
        <p>Niagara Mohawk's customers could probably ''receive a healthier company,'' said Barry Abrahamson, senior electric utility analyst with PaineWebber. The company was near bankruptcy a few years ago under the burden of about $3.5 billion in long-term contracts for highly expensive electricity it had bought a decade earlier, as part of a state and federal initiative. Niagara Mohawk has paid about $900 million of that debt and National Grid will assume the rest.</p>
        <p>Niagara Mohawk's shares rose $1.88 yesterday, to $15.75. That is well short of the $19 a share the deal works out to, no doubt reflecting that with all the regulatory hurdles, it could well take a year before the acquisition is complete. In addition, it must sell its Nine Mile Point nuclear plant in upstate New York before the merger goes through.</p>
        <p>Despite National Grid's incursions into the Northeast, ratepayer advocates remain somewhat wary of the deal, since they know little about the British company. They point out, for example, that the industry attrition rate is lower than what is expected in the merger, and therefore the savings from the deal may be less than predicted. Under an agreement with the state, Niagara Mohawk is also allowed to keep most of the savings from a merger for five years, rather than pass them along to customers.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
