<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Gets Worse for Raymond</title>
    <meta content="MB014705" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228434"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS: U.S. OPEN -- NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Black, Cara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Likhovtseva, Yelena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raymond, Lisa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stubbs, Rennae</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollander, Sophia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E2DB1739F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Gets Worse for Raymond</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sophia Hollander</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hollander, Sophia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cara Black and Yelena Likhovtseva defeats women's doubles top-seeded team of Lisa Raymond and Rennae Stubbs at US Open (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Lisa Raymond walked briskly off the court after a disjointed doubles performance, sympathetic cheers became a scattering of chiding boos. The top-seeded team of Raymond and Rennae Stubbs had fallen to the 10th-seeded Cara Black and Yelena Likhovtseva, 6-3, 6-4, in the quarterfinals of the U.S. Open.</p>
        <p>On match point, Stubbs was forced to hang her head after her attempted return fizzled into the net.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Lisa Raymond walked briskly off the court after a disjointed doubles performance, sympathetic cheers became a scattering of chiding boos. The top-seeded team of Raymond and Rennae Stubbs had fallen to the 10th-seeded Cara Black and Yelena Likhovtseva, 6-3, 6-4, in the quarterfinals of the U.S. Open.</p>
        <p>On match point, Stubbs was forced to hang her head after her attempted return fizzled into the net.</p>
        <p>It was a sour end to a traumatic two weeks for Raymond, who was left off the United States Olympic team despite being the No. 1 ranked doubles player in the world. Over the first nine days of the Open, she discussed how painful the snub was, both personally and professionally, and expressed her belief that she had earned the right to be chosen.</p>
        <p>But she could not make it to the semifinals, where she would have faced Serena and Venus Williams, who moved confidently across the court in their 1-6, 6-1, 6-3 victory over Chanda Rubin and Sandrine Testud.</p>
        <p>Serena was chosen to compete in the doubles competition at the Olympics, and her purple mesh spandex, bouncy demeanor and bursts of laughter on the court were in stark contrast to the tight stares and white and gray-trimmed outfits of Raymond and Stubbs.</p>
        <p>''The whole couple of weeks has been a little bitter for me,'' Raymond said after her match, as Stubbs sat slumped beside her, a cap tugged down to shade red-rimmed eyes. ''Obviously it's a disappointing loss. I don't think we were ever really comfortable out there. You know, they got a little lucky.''</p>
        <p>Trailing by 3-4 in the second set, Raymond missed an easy overhead. A point later, down by 30-0, Stubbs stared as a shot sailed swiftly past her and landed inside the line. In disgust, she dropped her racket and put her hand over her eyes.</p>
        <p>On game point, Stubbs missed an easy overhead and screamed in frustration. Stubbs and Raymond would not win another game.</p>
        <p>''I think we went out there a little nervous,'' Raymond said. ''We knew what was at stake.''</p>
        <p>What was at stake was an Open title and an implied statement to Billie Jean King, who selected the Olympic team.</p>
        <p>''We felt we had a really good chance of winning this tournament and, you know, when the conditions or things start going against you, I think you let your emotions get a little too involved,'' Raymond said.</p>
        <p>Sophia Hollander</p>
        <p>TENNIS: U.S. OPEN -- NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
