<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOD CHAIN</title>
    <meta content="06CHAI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EFDF1639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOD CHAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELISSA CLARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recycling Deep-Frying Oil</p>
        <p>Q.: What is the best way to keep deep-frying oil after use? How long will it last?</p>
        <p>A.: Before you plan to save the oil, make sure it has not taken on any burnt or unpleasant nuances, or the flavors of whatever was fried in it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Recycling Deep-Frying Oil</p>
        <p>Q.: What is the best way to keep deep-frying oil after use? How long will it last?</p>
        <p>A.: Before you plan to save the oil, make sure it has not taken on any burnt or unpleasant nuances, or the flavors of whatever was fried in it.</p>
        <p>You can avoid this by maintaining the proper temperature when frying, usually 365 degrees; use a thermometer to monitor the heat.</p>
        <p>If the oil overheats, it can begin to smoke and break down, adding an unpleasant taste. Oil that is too hot can also burn food, leaving an acrid flavor in the oil. Fish out any stray particles, which will otherwise burn.</p>
        <p>After deep-frying, let the oil cool completely, then strain it through a coffee filter or paper towel, or through a fine sieve lined with cheesecloth. The oil can then be tightly covered and refrigerated for several months.</p>
        <p>It should only be reused once, since repeatedly bringing it up to the high temperature needed for deep-frying can cause it to break down.</p>
        <p>Deep-fryers have a thermostat that automatically controls the temperature so that there is less chance of foods burning and ruining the oil. Often the oil used in them can be reused more than once. Follow the guidelines that are in the machine's manual.</p>
        <p>Understanding Sesame Oils</p>
        <p>Q.: What is the difference between light and Asian sesame oils?</p>
        <p>A.: Sesame oil ranges from straw-colored and gently flavored to mahogany-hued and assertive, depending on how the seeds were treated before being pressed.</p>
        <p>Light sesame oil is extracted from fresh, raw sesame seeds and has a soft, nearly neutral flavor that makes it suitable for salad dressings and delicate sauces. It is also good for sauteing and deep-frying since it can be heated to a very high temperature before it starts to smoke.</p>
        <p>Dark sesame oil, usually called Asian, is pressed from deeply toasted seeds. The darker the oil, the nuttier, smokier and slightly more bitter its flavor. Because of the oil's concentrated character, most recipes call for adding small amounts to dishes after they are cooked, or to uncooked sauces and dressings.</p>
        <p>Both kinds of oil are sold in large supermarkets. Look for the light sesame oil in health food stores, and the toasted sesame oil in Asian and specialty markets.</p>
        <p>MELISSA CLARK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
