<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Joined By Hip: Food And TV</title>
    <meta content="06MEDI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/living/06MEDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000909T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MIXED MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food Network</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDF1639F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1414" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Joined By Hip: Food And TV</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla column on Food Network's fall lineup of shows; notes network is growing by replacing instructional cooking shows with shows thate are purely entertainment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY biggest disappointment while previewing the Food Network's new fall lineup last week was that the ''Naked Chef'' was dressed. If I dedicate a full half-hour of my life to a scrupulous inspection of a new Generation Z (yes, he looks that young) kitchen whiz from England, I expect more in return than a winning smile and a recipe for vodka-soused watermelon.</p>
        <p>But I have to concede that Jamie Oliver still managed to hold my attention, even after he explained that ''naked'' referred to the food: ''We're stripping down a recipe.'' At least I think that's what he said; Mr. Oliver, who catapulted to BBC stardom after a producer spotted him cooking in a British restaurant, has a heavy accent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY biggest disappointment while previewing the Food Network's new fall lineup last week was that the ''Naked Chef'' was dressed. If I dedicate a full half-hour of my life to a scrupulous inspection of a new Generation Z (yes, he looks that young) kitchen whiz from England, I expect more in return than a winning smile and a recipe for vodka-soused watermelon.</p>
        <p>But I have to concede that Jamie Oliver still managed to hold my attention, even after he explained that ''naked'' referred to the food: ''We're stripping down a recipe.'' At least I think that's what he said; Mr. Oliver, who catapulted to BBC stardom after a producer spotted him cooking in a British restaurant, has a heavy accent.</p>
        <p>Not that it matters. I wasn't watching the new shows to revel in the wisdom of such cooking tips as Mr. Oliver's advice to ''just bash the hell out of it.'' What captivated me was how far the Food Network has evolved from trying to teach people to cook.</p>
        <p>While the glitz and silliness of shows like ''Iron Chef'' and ''The Two Fat Ladies'' may have alienated serious cooks, they have brought more viewers to the network. After a financial struggle that cost it an estimated $88 million in the seven years since its startup, media analysts predict that the network will break even this year. It is growing by replacing the shows featuring cooks behind counters -- the sort of programs that dominated the airwaves during the first four decades of television -- with shows that are purely entertainment. This fall's lineup will feature even more of the escapades, exotic locales and celebrity chefs that have seized control of the network's prime time schedule in the last couple of years.</p>
        <p>With instructional programs relegated to daytime hours, the Food Network has reserved the coveted prime time slots for ''very sexy programs that satisfy viewers' cravings for entertainment over education,'' said Eileen Opatut, the network's senior vice president of programming.</p>
        <p>That means lots of moody, jerky footage of the Naked Chef wandering around rain-slicked streets buying cheese; think MTV meets ''The Blair Witch Project'' over appetizers. On another new show, ''Ming's Quest,'' the celebrity chef Ming Tsai travels around the country in hot pursuit of the live ingredients he will later cook on location. Along the way, he dresses in waterproof orange slicks to haul in lobster traps or a wet suit to dive for abalone off the California coast. On ''B. Smith With Style,'' the host, Barbara Smith, barely talks about food at all. Sure, she can squeeze in a quick segment with Bobby Flay, but count on the program to focus more on such issues as container gardening and how to braid hair (''Let's talk about extensions'').</p>
        <p>By sacrificing the serious to embrace the ludicrous (no, you did not dream it, the ''Three Dog Bakery'' show did feature chefs who cooked for pets), the Food Network has developed from a rinky-dink channel with six hours of programming recycled four times in each 24-hour cycle into an infotainment enterprise that now reaches beyond the 50 million American households who subscribe to its schedule of 31 television shows. Celebrity chefs now parade around the country -- you can get the New Orleans chef Emeril Lagasse's autograph if you happen to be in Las Vegas on Sept. 17. And the network's Web site, Foodtv.com, attracts 1.7 million visitors a month and has a collection of every recipe on every program.</p>
        <p>''While the television network is our core business and will stay the core business,'' said Judy Girard, the network's general manager, ''we are in the process of reviewing almost every department to allow us to develop the brand beyond the actual network.''</p>
        <p>The network bears little resemblance to the cable channel that its creator, CNN's first president, Reese Schoenfeld, started in late 1992 with two hours of programming and a jaunty motto: ''A network for people who eat.'' The earliest programs included ''Getting Healthy,'' a program on nutrition, ''Food News and Views'' with the co-anchors Donna Hanover and David Rosengarten delivering updates on the drawbacks of drinking too much liquor, and ''Eating Lite,'' which featured low-fat ethnic recipes. The only recognizable celebrity ancestor was Robin Leach's explorations of the food fetishes of the rich and famous.</p>
        <p>''It's not what I intended when we started, when it was less entertainment-oriented than it was instructional, but they've done a terrific job of broadening the audience,'' said Mr. Schoenfeld, who is writing a book about the history of CNN called ''Me and Ted Against the World.''</p>
        <p>The reason for its appeal? ''The network has managed to take food and turn it into in a glamorous hobby,'' said Robert Thompson, the director of the Center for the Study of Popular Television at Syracuse University. ''It has the same effect as rock 'n' roll on a whole generation of viewers. We've gotten to a point in our culture where you're hip if you've discovered the latest hot program on the Food Network.''</p>
        <p>The channel's growing popularity is an indication that its programs satisfy Americans with a voracious, if contradictory, interest in food. On one hand, the number of restaurants in the United States rose 65 percent from the early 1970's to the mid 1990's, to 815,000 from 492,000. On the other, Americans cook less. Almost half of all weekday meals are made in a half hour or less, says the NPD Group, which studies consumer trends.</p>
        <p>But the real success of the Food Network is that despite its current scarcity of instructional content, ''people kid themselves into thinking that watching it is an educational experience,'' said Garth Jowett, who directs the University of Houston's School of Communication and is writing a book about the social history of television. ''So while most people see the experience of watching TV as a guilty pleasure, they feel justified watching these programs.''</p>
        <p>Evidence of the network's current approach emerged in the mid-1990's, when it decided to revamp the image of Mr. Lagasse. His ''Essence of Emeril'' had been among the most popular early Food Network offerings. With ''Emeril Live,'' the network added a band, a studio audience and celebrity guests to Mr. Lagasse's routine and created its first superstar chef; an onslaught of 50,000 callers clamoring for tickets disrupted service at a New Hampshire call center in 1998.</p>
        <p>The lesson was obvious. ''During prime time, people want entertainment, and you're not going to get a significant number of viewers with a chef behind the counter,'' said Eric Ober, who was the network's president from 1998 until early this year and is now the chief executive of the Internet career services company Vault.com. ''My feeling was, let's get out of the studio. So we made the decision to do that during prime time: food would be fun, action, adventure and excitement.''</p>
        <p>Overall last year, the network had a 0.2 rating, which means that 84,000 people were watching on any given day, according to Derek Baine, a senior analyst at Paul Kagan Associates. Before 1999, the network wasn't rated because viewer numbers were too low. That rating doesn't put the Food Network at the top of the heap -- the largest cable networks, like USA or TNT, generate a 1 rating. The Food Network is more comparable to networks like ESPN2 or Headline News, Mr. Baine said.</p>
        <p>But it is growing. In the last two years, the network has been picked up by cable operators across the country, and the number of homes where it is available has nearly doubled, up to 50 million from 28 million.</p>
        <p>''It's impressive that they've been able to sign on that many subscribers in their short life, especially when you consider that there are only 100 million TV households in the United States,'' Mr. Baine said. ''They're in half of them.''</p>
        <p>Which makes me wonder: what are all those households eating for dinner tonight? Not the vodka watermelon, I hope.</p>
        <p>MIXED MEDIA  Correction:  September 9, 2000, Saturday  The Mixed Media column of the Dining section on Wednesday, about the increased popularity of the Food Network on cable television, misspelled the surname of its founder. He is Reese Schonfeld, not Schoenfeld. The column also misstated the first year in which the network received a Nielsen rating. It was 1995, not 1999.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 9, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>The Mixed Media column of the Dining section on Wednesday, about the increased popularity of the Food Network on cable television, misspelled the surname of its founder. He is Reese Schonfeld, not Schoenfeld. The column also misstated the first year in which the network received a Nielsen rating. It was 1995, not 1999.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
