<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women Are From Venus, Horses Are From Heaven</title>
    <meta content="06BERN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/arts/06BERN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pierson, Melissa Holbrook</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dark Horses and Black Beauties: Animals, Woman, a Passion (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D71F30F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women Are From Venus, Horses Are From Heaven</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Bernstein reviews Dark Horses and Black Beauties: Animals, Woman, a Passion by Melissa Holbrook Pierson; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DARK HORSES AND BLACK BEAUTIES  Animals, Woman, a Passion  By Melissa Holbrook Pierson  Illustrated. 254 pages. W. W. Norton. $22.95.</p>
        <p>There comes a time in almost every girl's life when she falls in love with horses. This phenomenon, this quality of nature, is easily observable, but Melissa Holbrook Pierson more than observes it; she muses on it to deep and lyrical effect in ''Dark Horses and Black Beauties,'' her new collection of slender and delicate essays on horses and women. Ms. Pierson loves horses, and they are a major subject here, but a deeper concern is for the human animal, its need for love, its propensity for cruelty, its habit of imposing ardently wishful meanings on brute or tender nature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DARK HORSES AND BLACK BEAUTIES  Animals, Woman, a Passion  By Melissa Holbrook Pierson  Illustrated. 254 pages. W. W. Norton. $22.95.</p>
        <p>There comes a time in almost every girl's life when she falls in love with horses. This phenomenon, this quality of nature, is easily observable, but Melissa Holbrook Pierson more than observes it; she muses on it to deep and lyrical effect in ''Dark Horses and Black Beauties,'' her new collection of slender and delicate essays on horses and women. Ms. Pierson loves horses, and they are a major subject here, but a deeper concern is for the human animal, its need for love, its propensity for cruelty, its habit of imposing ardently wishful meanings on brute or tender nature.</p>
        <p>Along her somewhat meandering path Ms. Pierson does provide a few hard and interesting facts about the special relationship between girls (and women) and horses. ''Facts?'' she writes. ''Of the United States Pony Club's 14,000 members, four-fifths are girls. . . . A survey taken a few years ago by the British magazine Gallop! found that three-quarters of women who own horses would as soon give up their husbands as their horses; 90 percent would rather have a new horse than a new baby. . . . Only 22 percent of Canadian horse owners are male.''</p>
        <p>Some of that is less persuasive than Ms. Pierson makes it out to be; after all there is a difference between what 90 percent of female horse owners might want and what 90 percent of women want. But there's no point in arguing the general proposition that many women love horses.</p>
        <p>This sentiment is behind a vast literature, thousands of novels, and Ms. Pierson cites a few of them to give a bit of the spirit of the woman-horse love affair and the trembling fantasies that it creates. She covers historical issues like the fierce 19th-century debate over whether women should ride astride or sidesaddle. She makes telling observations on what might be seen as the connections among aristocratic thinness, money, social snobbery and horses.</p>
        <p>''Keeping a horse in Manhattan is the epitome of expansive wealth,'' she writes in one passage, ''and of the weird perversions that money can buy, as if money were of such little concern that you might consider installing a half-acre of grass lawn with a stream and a waterfall somewhere on East 58th Street.'' She describes a woman she knows who cannot stand not to see her horse, which she keeps at the Claremont Stables on the Upper West Side of Manhattan, every day. ''She is investigating the possibility of having fresh alfalfa flown in from the West, because it is the finest in the land,'' Ms. Pierson writes, maintaining a  sympathetic distance from what has turned love into narcissism.</p>
        <p>Horses, in other words, are elements in the great vain comedy of human affairs, and Ms. Pierson has a good eye for foibles. But her essays mostly have an autobiographical edge to them, she being a woman who loved horses as a little girl and has fallen in love with them as an adult. Her writing has a austere quality to it, a formal restraint that, given the subject, makes one think of dressage, of riding crops, leather boots, of subtle motions in the saddle.</p>
        <p>Several themes are evoked, among them ruminations on the character of horses and on the reasons girls become so smitten. ''We are attracted to horses, in particular, because they echo our own tentative whispers but do so in a bold, ringing call; they speak with certainty of exactly those things we are most unsure of in ourselves. For the qualities that most define the equine species are the ones most suppressed currently in the human: raw sexuality, fear, open vulnerability and need, uncomplicated drive.''</p>
        <p>Is that the explanation? Certainly it is an interesting hypothesis, the horse as a kind of echo of the deeper female qualities. But Ms. Pierson offers it only as a thought, a possibility, and that is characteristic of this writer whose intellectual delicacy seems inconsistent with aggressive opinions. ''I myself have become almost addicted to the taste of the unknowable, and sometimes gorge on it in the middle of the night, straight out of the container and with no sauce,'' she writes. ''With this revelation, I hereby give up all pretense of offering some final explanation of why girls love horses with the abiding passion they do. Instead, I invite you to the feast of uncertainty.''</p>
        <p>In her autobiographical mode Ms. Pierson recounts her efforts to learn to ride and to listen to horses. She is not an anthropomorphist, being wise enough to understand that humans do not generally know what is going on in a horse's mind. She does, however, verge on the sentimental at times, or at least on the mystical, as when she wants to believe that horses are more intelligent than we are, or that they can read our minds.</p>
        <p>Her most impassioned remarks have to do with cruelty to animals, and she brings us, with her usual poise, into the very abbatoir, the dog food factories where most horses end their lives. ''We decide who lives and who dies,'' she writes, with a resigned sort of acceptance of human supremacy. ''The worthless die.''</p>
        <p>If there is sentimentality in this, Ms. Pierson puts up a spirited defense of it. And anyway you don't have to be persuaded by everything she says to appreciate the play of her mind, which is subtle and quick; coltish, one wants to say, and one would be right.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
