<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MetroStars Hope Goalie Is a Keeper</title>
    <meta content="06SOCC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/06/sports/06SOCC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Fusion</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DB1739F935A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MetroStars Hope Goalie Is a Keeper</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Sept. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MetroStars defeat Miami Fusion, 2-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One game may not be enough evidence, but the MetroStars have most likely found a goalkeeper for the Major League Soccer playoffs that start next week. The problem is they will have to share Paul Grafer with the Long Island Rough Riders of the A-League.</p>
        <p>In his first start, Grafer showed some promise tonight in the MetroStars' 2-1 victory over the Miami Fusion in the regular-season finale in front of of 12,369 at Giants Stadium. Grafer made six saves, but was not quite a model of confidence. He must be given credit, however, for making some good decisions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One game may not be enough evidence, but the MetroStars have most likely found a goalkeeper for the Major League Soccer playoffs that start next week. The problem is they will have to share Paul Grafer with the Long Island Rough Riders of the A-League.</p>
        <p>In his first start, Grafer showed some promise tonight in the MetroStars' 2-1 victory over the Miami Fusion in the regular-season finale in front of of 12,369 at Giants Stadium. Grafer made six saves, but was not quite a model of confidence. He must be given credit, however, for making some good decisions.</p>
        <p>''There were moments he was solid,'' General Manager Nick Sakiewicz, a former goalkeeper, said of Grafer. ''It's extremely tough to come into this league from the A-League.''</p>
        <p>Grafer Said: ''There were a couple of bloopers, but I felt comfortable. Play is quicker in this league and the players can turn it up a notch more than the A-League.''</p>
        <p>Grafer's lone crucial mistake of the night was the goal by Diego Serna, who scored four goals against Tim Howard in Miami's 4-1 victory over the MetroStars on Saturday in Miami. Howard has joined the United States Olympic team.</p>
        <p>Serna's goal came with 7 minutes left after the MetroStars had scored goals by Mike Petke in the 10th minute and Adolfo Valencia on a penalty kick in the 82nd minute.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars had numerous chances for other goals, but kept missing, with Clint Mathis the most guilty party.</p>
        <p>The man who set a league record by scoring five goals three games ago, missed the target from a good position at least three times.</p>
        <p>''This is what happens to goal scorers,'' Coach Octavio Zambrano, said about Mathis's failures. ''Sometimes, they don't go in.''</p>
        <p>Zambrano said he was generally pleased with Grafer's performance. ''He did well, considering he had one practice with us.''</p>
        <p>Grafer had lost 12 of 13 games in the league with Colorado in parts of two seasons before he joined the Rough Riders, where he played all 28 games this season and won 16. Grafer will play for the Rough Riders on Friday in a playoff game against Toronto and play for the MetroStars on Saturday night at New England, where the MetroStars conclude their regular season.</p>
        <p>Zambrano said the most important thing for Grafer was having to concentrate playing for two teams. ''It's difficult to adjust playing with different defenses in front of you,'' Zambrano said. ''The speed of play and the velocity of the shots is different in the two leagues.''</p>
        <p>The MetroStars said they had plenty of confidence on Grafer because he looked extremely good in the emergency practice that Zambrano staged on Monday. The word that Petke actually used for Grafer's performance in practice was ''phenomenal.''</p>
        <p>Zambrano's heart might have dropped to his stomach just before intermision when Grafer came off his line to gather the ball and came up empty.</p>
        <p>Luckily for Grafer and the MetroStars, Tyrone Marshall completely missed the target in one of the most embarrassing moments in the game.</p>
        <p>CORNER KICKS</p>
        <p>The MetroStars raced onto the field for Tuesday night's home regular-season finale game holding the Eastern Conference trophy that was presented to them minutes earlier by Commissioner DON GARBER. It was the first title of any kind for the team, the players dedicated it to the fans. Players lined up for the traditional team picture before the kickoff holding a huge sign that read ''This One Is for You.''</p>
        <p>A fracas at the end of the game resulted in four ejections, two from each team. ORLANDO PEREZ and ROY MYERS were ejected from the MetroStars, and JAY HEAPS and IVAN McKINLEY from Miami. They will all miss the last game of the season for their teams. . . . The game was rather physical with 38 fouls, 24 by Miami, which is virtually eliminated from the playoffs. . . . The MetroStars (17-11-3, 54 points) said they were aiming to finish first in the league in the regular season.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
