<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zedillo Says He Takes Pride In Improvements for Mexico</title>
    <meta content="Y02ZED$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Ginger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zedillo, Ernesto (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E6DD1030F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zedillo Says He Takes Pride In Improvements for Mexico</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINGER THOMPSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thompson, Ginger</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Sept. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Ernesto Zedillo, in State of Union address, says reforms initiated by his administration have helped make Mexico better country than when he took office six years ago (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a State of the Union address delivered with solemn nostalgia, President Ernesto Zedillo declared today that he was leaving Mexico a better country than when when he took office six years ago.</p>
        <p>True to his typically guarded and technocratic style, Mr. Zedillo, a Yale-educated economist, extolled the measures that he took to save Mexico from financial ruin, and he boasted about the transparent elections that have propelled the nation on a seemingly irreversible course toward democracy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a State of the Union address delivered with solemn nostalgia, President Ernesto Zedillo declared today that he was leaving Mexico a better country than when when he took office six years ago.</p>
        <p>True to his typically guarded and technocratic style, Mr. Zedillo, a Yale-educated economist, extolled the measures that he took to save Mexico from financial ruin, and he boasted about the transparent elections that have propelled the nation on a seemingly irreversible course toward democracy.</p>
        <p>''Mexicans now have all the ingredients of a modern democracy,'' Mr. Zedillo said in his prepared remarks, ''individual guarantees, civil liberties, a multiparty system, free elections, pluralism and now, as a result of the determination of our citizens, the alternation of parties in power.''</p>
        <p>The address, known in Mexico as the Informe, was also a painful final rite for the one-party dynasty that has controlled Mexican politics for most of the last seven decades.</p>
        <p>Two months ago, Mr. Zedillo's Institutional Revolutionary Party was defeated in the most open and competitive presidential elections in Mexican history. The man who will take office on Dec. 1, Vicente Fox Quesada, will be the first president in 71 years to be chosen by the people, rather than by his predecessor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox chose not to attend the ceremonies in the Legislative Palace so as not to distract attention from Mr. Zedillo's address. But Mr. Fox's electoral victory permeated the atmosphere, and Mr. Zedillo respectfully acknowledged the president-elect in his address.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Zedillo, 48, whose term began in 1994 with a devastating peso devaluation and civil unrest in Chiapas, the speech was a triumphant political finale.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zedillo did not mention his Institutional Revolutionary Party by name. Its leaders are still rankled by their defeat.</p>
        <p>Still, with sentimental appreciation and praise for the government -- for the public schools, health centers and scholarship programs that helped him move from a gritty working-class childhood to Yale and onto the presidency -- Mr. Zedillo offered the PRI a veiled farewell.</p>
        <p>''I believe all of us, absolutely all of us, have to acknowledge one fact,'' he said. ''Mexico has completed its journey toward democracy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zedillo arrived unexpectedly at the presidency after the assassination of the PRI candidate, Luis Donaldo Colosio, in 1994. And tonight he offered personal reflections about his time in office and his faith in the future.</p>
        <p>Noticeably absent were references to the litany of unpopular policies, unfulfilled promises and scandals that have plagued his administration.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Mr. Zedillo's former tourism minister and campaign finance manager, Oscar Espinosa, disappeared after facing charges that he had embezzled $45 million in government money in his years as regent of Mexico City.</p>
        <p>Next, the director of a vehicle-registration program, hired by the administration, was detained by international law enforcement agents on charges of torture during Argentina's military dictatorship.</p>
        <p>The president tried to explain his commitment to the unpopular economic programs that he initiated at the start of his presidency, including a $100 million bailout to save Mexican banks and to secure loans to some of the wealthiest business leaders.</p>
        <p>''The crisis severely damaged people's living standards in 1995,'' Mr. Zedillo said. ''Yet I am certain that the damage would have been much greater and longer lasting had we not adopted the decisions.''</p>
        <p>Newspaper polls show that many people have accepted that hard reality and that Mr. Zedillo is enjoying the highest popularity ratings of his presidency. Seven out of 10 Mexicans polled by the newspaper Reforma said they approved his performance as president, compared with three out of 10 five years ago.</p>
        <p>Most of that popularity is generally attributed to the democratic reforms instituted in the Zedillo administration, reforms that led to the creation of the autonomous Federal Electoral Institute, to the election of the first opposition-led Congress and, ultimately, to Mr. Fox's election.</p>
        <p>Apparently ignoring a recent political riot in the state of Mexico in which at least nine people were killed, Mr. Zedillo added, ''We can attest that suspicions, recriminations and electoral conflicts have been resigned to history.''</p>
        <p>The president has been receiving much colder treatment from his own party's leaders. They who fault him for the party's losing the presidency, although the PRI keeps a narrow majority in both houses of the legislature.</p>
        <p>The presidential loss has thrown the party into the worst crisis of its history.</p>
        <p>''It is true that the president's relationship with the party is fragile,'' a PRI senator, Humberto Roque Villanueva, said. ''There is a certain feeling of injustice that the PRI paid the political costs of the policies, while the government enjoys prestige.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
