<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH DEFENDS AD THAT ASSAILS GORE</title>
    <meta content="02BUSH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ISSUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buddhism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buddhism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5DB1030F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH DEFENDS AD THAT ASSAILS GORE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI and ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank; Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., Sept. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush defends Republican advertisement that challenges credibility and character of Vice Pres Al Gore; says his pledge to change tone of politics will not prevent him from raising questions about Gore's truthfulness and leadership abilities; says commercial, which brings up Gore's 1996 fund-raising appearance at Buddhist temple, is way to undermine public confidence in Gore's own accusations against him; Bush photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush today defended a new advertisement that challenges the credibility and character of Vice President Al Gore and signaled that his frequent pledge to ''change the tone'' of politics would not prevent him from raising questions about Mr. Gore's truthfulness and leadership abilities in the coming weeks.</p>
        <p>In an extended interview on his campaign plane, Mr. Bush repeatedly remarked that the Democrats had now run $30 million in advertisements against him. And he cast the new Republican commercial ridiculing Mr. Gore and bringing up the vice president's 1996 fund-raising appearance at a Buddhist temple as a way to undermine public confidence in Mr. Gore's own accusations against him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush today defended a new advertisement that challenges the credibility and character of Vice President Al Gore and signaled that his frequent pledge to ''change the tone'' of politics would not prevent him from raising questions about Mr. Gore's truthfulness and leadership abilities in the coming weeks.</p>
        <p>In an extended interview on his campaign plane, Mr. Bush repeatedly remarked that the Democrats had now run $30 million in advertisements against him. And he cast the new Republican commercial ridiculing Mr. Gore and bringing up the vice president's 1996 fund-raising appearance at a Buddhist temple as a way to undermine public confidence in Mr. Gore's own accusations against him.</p>
        <p>''If this is what's going to happen in the campaign, we've got to lay the groundwork: this is a fellow that will say anything,'' Mr. Bush said, referring to Mr. Gore. ''The point is, this is a way to help inoculate me about what has come and is coming.'' [Excerpts, Page A14]</p>
        <p>He later said that ''the Republican Party is putting people on notice that he is willing to exaggerate in order to win, to curry their favor.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush spoke, for about 45 minutes, at a pivotal moment in his campaign. He was not only heading into the Labor Day weekend and the final two months of the race, but also trying to emerge from a bumpy two weeks during which he was often thrown off his chosen message and put on the defensive.</p>
        <p>In addition, there have been accumulating signs that Mr. Bush's sustained advantage over Mr. Gore in the polls has vanished. In recent days, several nationwide polls have shown the race to be a dead heat, and a Newsweek poll released today found Mr. Gore with a lead of 10 percentage points.</p>
        <p>Even today, on his campaign plane, Mr. Bush was being pelted with questions that had nothing to do with his designated themes of the week. During an impromptu news conference, reporter after reporter sharply questioned him about how the attack commercial, which is being run by the Republican National Committee with the Bush campaign's approval, squared with his promise to take the high road.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was tongue-in-cheek,'' he told reporters. ''This ad came up after about $30 million of advertisements that had been attacking me and my record and I'm glad they came to my defense.''</p>
        <p>Asked whether he was raising questions about Mr. Gore's truthfulness, he said, ''No, I'm just saying this is a man who'll say things, like, he's for campaign funding reform and then conveniently forgets he went to the Buddhist temple.''</p>
        <p>Over the subsequent interview, Mr. Bush projected a demeanor that was alternately intense and jocular, cutting and funny, and that never showed any fissures of worry. He went out of his way to assert that he was pleased with the state of the race.</p>
        <p>''I just want to tell you what my mood is, if you don't mind,'' he said, unprompted. ''I feel great. I do. I feel comfortable. My spirits are high.''</p>
        <p>But he exhibited subtle, fleeting flashes of irritation when the topic turned to questions about the finances of his running mate, Dick Cheney, and, earlier, when questioning about the Republican National Committee's advertisement went on for more than 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>''Is this interview on one ad?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Told there more subjects to come, he said, ''Then keep going, will you?''</p>
        <p>On the question of Mr. Cheney's retirement package, which includes lucrative stock options in Halliburton, an energy services company that could be affected by federal policy, Mr. Bush said he had known about the package when he picked Mr. Cheney as a running mate.</p>
        <p>''He will deal with the options issue in a way that is comforting to the people,'' Mr. Bush said. ''Dick Cheney's an honest man.''</p>
        <p>(Later in the day, Mr. Cheney announced that if elected, he would forfeit the stock options he had not yet been able to exercise.)</p>
        <p>At another moment, Mr. Bush's eyes grew wet as he reflected, in an almost elegiac tone, on the ''amazing experience'' of running for president.</p>
        <p>''I am so honored to be one of two coming down the stretch -- I am,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Asked why he was suddenly teary, he said, ''I'm not teary. I'm tired.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush referred several times to his father's presidential campaigns, drawing comfort from the lessons of the past and the perspective it gave him. He acknowledged that many political analysts believed he could not beat an incumbent administration in peaceful, prosperous times.</p>
        <p>But he noted that a different kind of conventional wisdom proved wrong when his father defeated Michael S. Dukakis in 1988. He recalled how pundits at the time cited the ''Van Buren factor,'' which was the idea ''that no sitting vice president could possibly be elected because it had never happened since Martin Van Buren.''</p>
        <p>He continued, ''Therefore George H. W. Bush could not possibly win,'' and added that each campaign brought ''a historical certainty that always seems to get defeated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush provided some insight into how his campaign would engage Mr. Gore over the next few weeks, making clear that he would keep trumpeting the accusation that Mr. Gore and President Clinton had squandered their time in the White House and failed to do what they had told Americans they would.</p>
        <p>''I find it amazing -- and I think America will, too -- that some of the same campaign issues they ran on in '92 are issues they run on in the year 2000,'' Mr. Bush said, lumping Mr. Gore and Mr. Clinton together. He mentioned Medicare reform, Social Security reform and a middle-class tax cut.</p>
        <p>Asked how he would persuade Americans that the Democratic administration, not the leaders of the Republican-led Congress, bore the blame, he said, in reference to Mr. Gore, ''It sounds like this is a campaign where they're going to be willing to say, 'Give me credit for things that went well, but let's blame others for failure.' And to me I think Americans will realize that's not what a leader does.''</p>
        <p>He brushed aside any suggestion that voters might decide that his engagement of Mr. Gore contradicted his promise to ''change the tone,'' a claim so central to his candidacy that it was the designated theme -- printed on banners -- for the week coming straight out of the Republican National Convention.</p>
        <p>''This is politics,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>He then drew a distinction between campaigning and governing -- between advertisements and his willingness, if elected, to work with Democrats like Senators John B. Breaux of Louisiana and Bob Kerrey of Nebraska on issues like Medicare.</p>
        <p>In much the same manner that he dealt with questions about the advertisements, Mr. Bush dismissed any idea that voters were paying attention to the debate over presidential debates and the fact that he has not agreed to the three forums proposed by the bipartisan Commission on Presidential Debates. Mr. Gore has accepted those invitations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said that this was a familiar replay of his campaign for governor in 1994, when the incumbent, Ann Richards, a Democrat, accused him of dodging debates.</p>
        <p>Mocking the Richards camp, he said: ''I remember it clearly. 'He won't debate! He won't debate! He won't debate! He won't debate!' And we debated, and that was it.''</p>
        <p>In his remarks about the Republican attack advertisement, Mr. Bush made clear he did not like Mr. Gore's frequent assertions that the Texas governor was not offering policies that were specific enough on matters like prescription drug benefits.</p>
        <p>Asked why the Republicans had chosen to run the advertisement now, he referred anew to the $30 million in Democratic commercials, then added, ''The rhetoric started getting a little harsh: 'put up or shut up.' '' Mr. Gore has used that phrase to goad Mr. Bush to put out more specifics on his policy proposals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush now plans to release a Medicare prescription drug plan next week. Until now he had outlined some broad principles and spoken positively of one bipartisan bill in the Senate.</p>
        <p>He insisted today that he ''always planned'' to provide more detail. He said he also planned to return to the issue of military preparedness next week.</p>
        <p>But he said that he did not intend to fill in more particulars of his call to divert some of the Social Security payroll tax to individual investment accounts. ''My Social Security position is where it is,'' he said, saying he thought voters understood the fundamentals of what he was proposing.</p>
        <p>On foreign policy, Mr. Bush said that despite his and Mr. Cheney's criticisms of the administration's peacekeeping missions, he would not recall American troops from Bosnia and Kosovo immediately if elected, ''because I understand the commitment to which we'll be bound.'' He added, ''But I will work with our allies to lay the groundwork to begin  to take up more of the peacekeeping role in Bosnia and Kosovo.''</p>
        <p>The tone of Mr. Bush's remarks during the interview meandered from a serene confidence about his chances of victory to an almost nostalgic distance from the race.</p>
        <p>He talked for a minute or two at one point about how important it was to use the campaign to build a governing mandate for the first 100 days of a Bush presidency.</p>
        <p>''I believe I'm going to win, and when I win, I want to get some things done,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he also talked about the privilege of being a part of history, no matter the outcome.</p>
        <p>''It's been a great journey,'' he said. ''I'm going to look back on these days.''</p>
        <p>He said repeatedly that he trusted the judgment of the American people, although he did not always like it, mentioning his father's failed 1992 re-election effort as an example.</p>
        <p>And if voters ultimately decided against him, as well?</p>
        <p>''Seriously, I would respect that,'' he said. ''I'm not going to like it.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ISSUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
