<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Life Change for A.C.L.U. Chief. Not That Words Fail Him.</title>
    <meta content="Y02LIV$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/02/national/02LIVE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227280"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Social Activism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Ira Glasser</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Civil Liberties Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kristof, Nicholas D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glasser, Ira</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E3D61330F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Life Change for A.C.L.U. Chief. Not That Words Fail Him.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kristof, Nicholas D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FINALLY, Ira Glasser clams up. For several entire nanoseconds, he is embarrassed and fumbling for words.</p>
        <p>He has waxed on for three hours, impossible to turn off, a logorrheic torrent full of aggressive pride about the people he associates with professionally: skinheads, Nazis, pornographers, fascists, Communists and any additional species of -ists that might offend the public.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FINALLY, Ira Glasser clams up. For several entire nanoseconds, he is embarrassed and fumbling for words.</p>
        <p>He has waxed on for three hours, impossible to turn off, a logorrheic torrent full of aggressive pride about the people he associates with professionally: skinheads, Nazis, pornographers, fascists, Communists and any additional species of -ists that might offend the public.</p>
        <p>No question has come close to wobbling him. Did he suppress the free-speech rights of his children? Is it awkward for a nice Jewish guy from New York City to sit down with neo-Nazis? Does he ever defend nice people? It is hard enough to get a question in, and he grabs each one -- almost literally, his arms flailing over his desk -- and answers it easily, with the calm assurance of a major league hitter facing a Little League pitcher.</p>
        <p>Then he is asked a question that stops him: Where is his computer? The rush of words halts, and for an eighth of an instant he has no idea what to say. ''You have discovered my Luddite secret,'' Mr. Glasser admits. Ruefully, he picks up a pen in one hand and a yellow pad in the other and explains that he uses them rather than a computer, adding: ''They never crash. They never get viruses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Glasser, who is 62, has ushered the American Civil Liberties Union into the new century, helping to transform it in his 22 years as executive director, and yet, it turns out, he left himself behind, at least in technological terms. But he will have time to catch up and get his first cell phone and desktop computer, for the A.C.L.U. will announce next week that he is retiring on July 1.</p>
        <p>The retirement will be a milestone for the 300,000-member organization, and a nationwide search for a successor is already beginning. But one of Mr. Glasser's legacies is that after having taken over at a time of financial crisis, in the aftermath of the group's defense of the right of Nazis to march in the heavily Jewish community of Skokie, Ill., he leaves a smoothly running, financially strong organization that he says (with the faintest hint of regret) will get along just fine without him.</p>
        <p>Colleagues say Mr. Glasser, for all his own lack of intimacy with anything more technical than a pen and paper, will be remembered as a modernizer -- as a 1960's rebel who turned himself into a fund-raiser, manager and chief executive and who turned the civil liberties union from a chaotic group of young lawyers in threadbare offices with pizza crusts lurking under broken chairs into a quasi corporation whose 18th-floor headquarters in Lower Manhattan have the hushed feel of a law firm.</p>
        <p>''Ira Glasser changed,'' mused Samuel Walker, a professor of criminal justice at the University of Nebraska who is the author of a history of the A.C.L.U. ''He was an issue-driven person, and never in his wildest dreams -- or nightmares -- would he have thought of becoming a manager. Now he can talk to you about mailings and their response rates for two hours.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Glasser plans to devote his retirement not to grand new crusades but to family, basketball and beaches. In a fund-raiser recently, family members bought him the opportunity to play one-on-one for 10 minutes with the former Knick Walt Frazier -- and he nearly bursts with pride as he relates that the game ended in a tie, 12-12.</p>
        <p>MR. GLASSER, born and raised in New York City, was an odd leader for the A.C.L.U., in that he never studied law; until diverted by the 1960's, he was a math professor at Queens College and Sarah Lawrence. It was good training: of all the audiences he has faced, he says, none have been so hostile as college students in required freshman calculus. (In budget meetings at the A.C.L.U., Mr. Glasser shows off his math skill by calculating sums faster in his head than people around him with a calculator.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Glasser joined the civil liberties union's New York affiliate in 1967 and ever since has been energetically defending the rights of people to express sentiments that he abhors. One fond moment came in 1968, when George C. Wallace, whose segregationist views were the opposite of Mr. Glasser's, was running for president and was denied use of Shea Stadium to hold a rally. Mr. Glasser went to meet Mr. Wallace's lieutenants and introduced them to the lawyer he had arranged to defend their right to use the stadium: Eleanor Holmes Norton, a black woman who is now the District of Columbia's delegate to the House of Representatives.</p>
        <p>Nadine Strossen, the law professor who serves as A.C.L.U. president, a nonmanagerial  position, said Mr. Glasser's greatest legacy was to have helped forge the group into a truly nationwide organization, with 53 offices around the country. Another of his legacies, one that annoyed some members, is that he developed a broader agenda that in addition to the organization's longtime emphasis on free speech underscores gay rights, legalized abortion, affirmative action, free expression on the Internet and hostility to racial profiling. In addition, he has put less emphasis on litigation and much more on cultivating public opinion.</p>
        <p>Yet even if Mr. Glasser is not a lawyer and has helped move the A.C.L.U. away from its traditional focus on the courts, callers trying to reach him around midday are sometimes told that he is away because of ''a very important court appointment.''</p>
        <p>That means he is off playing basketball.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
