<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Miller Aside, A Wild Year For the N.F.L.</title>
    <meta content="02FREE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Mike Freeman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6DE1330F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Miller Aside, A Wild Year For the N.F.L.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Freeman Sports of The Times column discusses outlook for 2000-2001 NFL season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS little tidbit comes from the comedian Dennis Miller, who as the new analyst for ''Monday Night Football'' has gotten more press than Al Gore. It definitely falls under the category of too much information.</p>
        <p>After Bud Adams, the owner of the Tennessee Titans, was interviewed by a sideline reporter during a preseason game last month, the camera caught Adams's full mane of dark, wavy hair. Miller remarked, ''Is that artificial turf we just saw?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS little tidbit comes from the comedian Dennis Miller, who as the new analyst for ''Monday Night Football'' has gotten more press than Al Gore. It definitely falls under the category of too much information.</p>
        <p>After Bud Adams, the owner of the Tennessee Titans, was interviewed by a sideline reporter during a preseason game last month, the camera caught Adams's full mane of dark, wavy hair. Miller remarked, ''Is that artificial turf we just saw?''</p>
        <p>The remark must have made the hair of some National Football League officials stand on end. Here was Miller, before tens of millions, basically saying one of the owners was wearing a toupee. Adams has since made it known his hair is 100 percent real, baby. Maybe when Miller and the Monday night crew make their return trip on Oct. 16 for Tennessee's game against Jacksonville, Miller can run his hands through it just to be sure.</p>
        <p>When Miller, who has never played the game, never coached it, and never covered it, is one of the biggest stories of the coming National Football League season, it is either going to be very boring or very interesting.</p>
        <p>Listen to your trusty football expert -- it will be the latter. This might be one of the most exhilarating seasons ever, better than last year's, when the Rams became the first team in league history to go from last in their division to Super Bowl champion.</p>
        <p>The 2000 season begins tomorrow, and never has the sport been so wide open. Any team can win, and good stories are circulating like a Miller joke on a Tuesday morning.</p>
        <p>In St. Louis, the best pickup for the Rams was Trung Canidate, who will spell running back Marshall Faulk. The rookie with the election year name will end up being one of the defending champions' most valuable players.</p>
        <p>The Philadelphia Eagles strongly believe they are a playoff team. They're right.</p>
        <p>The Denver Broncos think they will win the American Conference West. They're right.</p>
        <p>The Carolina Panthers feel the National Conference West can be stolen from the Rams. They're wrong.</p>
        <p>Jamal Anderson and Terrell Davis, two stars coming off knee injuries, will each gain more than 1,300 yards. Edgerrin James in Indianapolis will get 1,500. Stephen Davis in Washington will have 1,800.</p>
        <p>Daniel Snyder, the owner of the Redskins, will explode by Week 5, and Coach Norv Turner will be on the Dallas sideline by next season.  Wide receiver Keyshawn Johnson will be lobbying the Buccaneers' brass to trade for the Jets' backup thrower Ray Lucas by the first week of October.</p>
        <p>Jacksonville's Tom Coughlin will win nine games this year, quit, and then coach Notre Dame for the next decade.</p>
        <p>The Jets will start 0-2 and then make the playoffs. Despite their denials, quarterback Vinny Testaverde and Jets Coach Al Groh have already gotten into at least one argument. That's a fact. Bill Parcells will coach again, probably in Miami. That's a fantasy -- for Dolphins fans.</p>
        <p>The Giants' Ron Dayne is privately miffed at fan and news media reaction over his slow preseason start. Tiki Barber will be the team's offensive most valuable player. Michael Strahan will have 12 sacks. Kerry Collins will throw only eight interceptions and Coach Jim Fassel will get a two-year contract extension after making the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The Baltimore Ravens' Ray Lewis, who did not have a pleasant off-season, will lead all linebackers in tackles, sacks and interceptions, and be named the league's defensive M.V.P.</p>
        <p>Jake Plummer remains bitter with Bill Walsh for calling him the next Joe Montana, saying it is a weight on his shoulders he did not need or want. Peyton Manning is the next Montana, and Ryan Leaf is still a dud.</p>
        <p>The Ravens will win the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>And what would an N.F.L. season be without a few players in trouble with the law? Oakland signed Andre Rison this week, despite the fact that the wide receiver faces legal problems in four states. They include allegedly writing $158,000 in bad checks to a jewelry store in Missouri, giving the police a fake name after a bar fight in Wisconsin, owing $34,000 in child support to a son, which may lead to garnished wages in California, and a trial on felony charges that he took $1,000 in recording equipment from a Kansas music store.</p>
        <p>''I'm a beautiful father, and I've got a beautiful life,'' he said. ''I'm not saying I'm a saint. I'm not saying I'm perfect. And I'm not saying I'm wrong. But I am a Raider.''</p>
        <p>Amen to that.</p>
        <p>This is going to be a good season.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
