<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knoblauch Promotion A Surprise To Torre</title>
    <meta content="02KNOB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Knoblauch, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4DC1030F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knoblauch Promotion A Surprise To Torre</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees infielder Chuck Knoblauch rejoins team following rehabilitation assignment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch was supposed to continue his rehabilitation assignment apart from the Yankees this weekend, but George Steinbrenner apparently swooped in yesterday and decided that the recuperating second baseman would rejoin the team immediately.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch has tendinitis in his right elbow and has not played in a game since Aug. 2, so it seemed logical for him to continue his rehabilitation stint before trying to return to a team chasing a postseason berth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch was supposed to continue his rehabilitation assignment apart from the Yankees this weekend, but George Steinbrenner apparently swooped in yesterday and decided that the recuperating second baseman would rejoin the team immediately.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch has tendinitis in his right elbow and has not played in a game since Aug. 2, so it seemed logical for him to continue his rehabilitation stint before trying to return to a team chasing a postseason berth.</p>
        <p>But Knoblauch was in uniform in last night's 4-2 victory over the Twins, even though Manager Joe Torre admitted that he was not sure when Knoblauch would be able to play.</p>
        <p>''I got a call this morning that Chuck was going to come back to New York,'' General Manager Brian Cashman said. When asked why Knoblauch's itinerary had changed, he said, ''I don't know.'' .</p>
        <p>Torre added: ''That decision was made in Tampa. You'd have to ask those people down there.'' Tampa is a code word for Steinbrenner, the team's principal owner. Although Torre did not criticize the decision to activate Knoblauch, he seemed uncomfortable with it.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch has been throttled by an assortment of elbow, wrist and forearm injuries this season and he injured his left knee while he was recuperating in Tampa, Fla., after being disabled for the first time in his 10-year career on Aug. 7.</p>
        <p>''This is not the time of year to experiment,'' Torre said. ''It isn't that he's not capable. Physically, he hasn't played in a while. For that reason, he'd be uncomfortable, as I would.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch, who received a cortisone shot Tuesday and will try to toss a baseball lightly today to see if it has worked, is also uncertain about the rest of his season.</p>
        <p>''I guess I'll find out if I ever get in a game or get any at-bats or anything like that,'' Knoblauch said. ''I really don't know. For a good while, I was going through full workouts. You can do all that, but, when you get in a game it's different.''</p>
        <p>Torre has recently expressed skepticism about whether Knoblauch, who has not played second base since July 24, could get himself prepared to play in the final month of the season.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch had one at-bat during his stint on the disabled list so Torre figures that he will use Knoblauch as a pinch-runner or a pinch-hitter and see if his role can expand from there.</p>
        <p>If Knoblauch is used sporadically and in these minor roles, it does not seem as if it will enable him to get closer to regaining his starting position.</p>
        <p>So yesterday's move might be an indication that the team does not expect the 32-year-old Knoblauch to return to play second this season.</p>
        <p>''My goal is to get out there and play second base and not be a D.H. or a pinch-hitter or a pinch-hitter,'' Knoblauch said. ''Worst case scenario, I might have to settle for that.''</p>
        <p>Torre was more optimistic about Ramiro Mendoza, who threw batting practice in Tampa yesterday and rejoined the Yankees last night, too.</p>
        <p>Mendoza has tendinitis in his right shoulder, but the Yankees are hoping that he can pitch in a simulated game on Sunday or Monday and then perhaps be prepared to make his first appearance since July 29.</p>
        <p>Torre said Mendoza would preferably be used in a lopsided game the first time he pitches, which is the sort of experimentation that will not be available for Knoblauch.</p>
        <p>''It's different with a pitcher then it is for a player,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Cashman said that Knoblauch needs to show the Yankees ''he can come back from the elbow pain'' and that would make the Yankees ''the best team that we can possibly.''</p>
        <p>Even though there are fewer chances for Knoblauch to be the designated hitter because of the additions of Glenallen Hill and Jose Canseco, Torre noted that Knoblauch might match up better than either slugger against some pitchers and added, ''If I had the choice, I'd like to have him.''</p>
        <p>Knoblauch was eerily composed as he discussed a season that is unfolding and vanishing before his eyes. He does not know when his elbow will feel sound again so he does not know when he will play again.</p>
        <p>''You got to play the hand you're dealt,'' Knoblauch said. ''If I can't do it, I can't do it. There's nothing I can't do to change that. Whatever way it's going to be, good or bad, you got to live with it.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
