<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Singapore Journal; Soapbox Orators Stretch the Limits of Democracy</title>
    <meta content="Y02SIN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Singapore</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hong Lim Park (Singapore)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mydans, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E2DE1030F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Singapore Journal; Soapbox Orators Stretch the Limits of Democracy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mydans, Seth</byline>
      <dateline>SINGAPORE, Sept. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Singapore, in experiment in free speech, allows citizens to speak out legally in public without permit in Hong Lim Park; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Late at night, when he hoped nobody was looking, Ong Chin Guan said, he scouted the scene and hid an old wooden drawer in the bushes. He had already told his boss he would not be coming to work today. And he had whispered his plans to a few trusted friends.</p>
        <p>''After that, all my friends kept a distance from me,'' said Mr. Ong, 38, who drives a bus for a living. ''They didn't call me the whole week. Most of my friends, they were afraid.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Late at night, when he hoped nobody was looking, Ong Chin Guan said, he scouted the scene and hid an old wooden drawer in the bushes. He had already told his boss he would not be coming to work today. And he had whispered his plans to a few trusted friends.</p>
        <p>''After that, all my friends kept a distance from me,'' said Mr. Ong, 38, who drives a bus for a living. ''They didn't call me the whole week. Most of my friends, they were afraid.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ong was undaunted. When the sun came up this morning, he pulled his old drawer from the bushes, placed it squarely in the center of Hong Lim Park, climbed up onto it and began to speak.</p>
        <p>His subject was the declining birthrate in Singapore, but that didn't really matter, even to Mr. Ong. What mattered was that -- trembling a little and smiling nervously -- he had become one of the first citizens of Singapore to speak out legally in public without a permit.</p>
        <p>All day long, as the sun grew hot, then faded again on the other side of the tiny park, more men climbed onto stools, benches and plastic milk crates to speak their minds and inaugurate Singapore's new experiment in free speech: Speakers' Corner.</p>
        <p>Some spoke about the issues of the day as small clumps of people listened: high government salaries, low birthrates, immigration and, yes, free speech. Some shared with the public their personal grievances: a contract dispute, a delayed pension payment, an irritating son-in-law.</p>
        <p>All knew they were making history.</p>
        <p>''I came because I feel proud to be a Singaporean,'' said Mr. Ong, who described himself as ''just a man in the street, a Tom, Dick and Harry.''</p>
        <p>''We are really opening up,'' he said. ''We are globalizing. And now we are one of the few countries in the world to have a Speakers' Corner. Do you have a Speakers' Corner in America?''</p>
        <p>Indeed, there may not be another public forum quite like the one in Singapore. From now on, it is to be open every day from 7 a.m. to 7 p.m., but only to people who show their identification cards and register first with the police. Their names are posted on the police station wall and will remain on file for five years.</p>
        <p>The speakers are not to use megaphones or microphones or musical instruments -- though they are free to bring their own boxes to stand on -- and they are not to touch on sensitive issues of race, language or religion.</p>
        <p>And they must watch what they say. Speakers here will be subject, just like everybody else, to the Internal Security Act, under which they can be jailed without trial as threats to national security, and to the laws against libel and slander that have been vigorously employed in Singapore to harass and bankrupt opposition politicians.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Ong and his timorous friends, speakers here must also combat one of the strongest weapons Singapore uses to keep its people quiet: self-censorship.</p>
        <p>In a poll conducted last month by the Chinese-language newspaper Lianhe Zaobao, 9 out of 10 people said that if they disagreed with any government policies they would not say so in public. One-third said they wouldn't even tell their family and friends.</p>
        <p>''My friends see the opposition politicians prosecuted and they are afraid,'' Mr. Ong said. ''After I come here maybe they will say, 'Wow, you can speak and nothing happened to you!' ''</p>
        <p>Free speech is a difficult issue for Singapore, a tiny, multi-ethnic city-state of four million people that sees itself as a sort of gravity-defying bumble bee -- surviving and succeeding through sheer force of effort and inventiveness.</p>
        <p>To muffle any ethnic conflicts and build its resource-poor economy, it has chosen the path of tight government controls on just about everything, from financial investment to artistic expression to chewing gum, which is forbidden.</p>
        <p>At the heart of these controls are laws and regulations that include censorship of film, television, publications, music and the arts. Access to the Internet is controlled, and home television satellite antennas are banned.</p>
        <p>The government controls the only television network and the only newspaper publishing house.</p>
        <p>And if Mr. Ong had wanted to speak out in public before today -- or if he wished to speak today in any place other than Hong Lim Park -- he would need a special, hard-to-get permit from the police.</p>
        <p>Last year, an opposition politician, Chee Soon Juan, was jailed twice for speaking in public without a permit. Among the things he said: ''It's time to break the atmosphere of fear, to say it's all right to criticize the government, to hold it accountable for its actions.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the divide between the government and its critics is not a wide one in Singapore. Even dissidents like Mr. Chee acknowledge that the ruling party is responsible for the nation's success and prosperity and seek only careful, incremental changes.</p>
        <p>And even the country's rulers -- who hold 81 of the 83 seats in Parliament -- acknowledge that Singapore must loosen up and lighten up in order to stay on the crest of an ever-faster-moving and more flexible economic future.</p>
        <p>And so, in their Singaporean way, they are trying to mandate (and calibrate) free speech, artistic expression, creativity and risk-taking.</p>
        <p>''In the next decade, we need to think and act like revolutionaries,'' said Prime Minister Goh Chok Tong in his National Day speech last month. ''We have to change national and individual mind-sets and attune them to a very different future.''</p>
        <p>The future will not be kind to people and nations that play safe, as Singapore has come to do, he said. The nation and its leaders will need a change of mind-set every bit as daunting as the one Mr. Ong had to undergo when he dragged his wooden drawer out of the bushes and climbed onto it this morning to speak.</p>
        <p>Even some of those who acknowledge the need for more free expression -- like Singapore's creator, Senior Minister Lee Kuan Yew -- find it a bit distasteful.</p>
        <p>''I mean, crazy artistes or crazy painters or playwrights who write trash and pretend that it's art -- we'll just have to put up with it,'' he said not long ago.</p>
        <p>And the authorities will have to put up with Bellamy Cai, 54, a graphic designer, who stood on a stool at Speakers' Corner today, waved the morning's newspaper and declared, ''What they do in Parliament, they never fight for the bloody issues.''</p>
        <p>Or Antonio Rio, 67, a former prison guard unhappy with his pension who complained: ''I wrote to the prime minister in June but no reply! No reply! No courtesy at all.''</p>
        <p>Or Richard Kwek, also 67, a taxi driver, who offered what sounded like his usual monologue about government misdeeds for free today -- no meter ticking -- and asserted, ''Taxi drivers are 70 percent against the government.''</p>
        <p>They will have to contend, too, with a new generation of political activists who are already working for more openness. One of these is James Gomez, 35, who recently self-published -- and got away with it -- a slim book called ''Self Censorship: Singapore's Shame.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gomez arrived today at Speakers' Corner as the shadows were lengthening in the late afternoon, bringing with him several even younger idealists who are helping him create an on-line discussion network called Think Center.</p>
        <p>''While we celebrate Speakers' Corner as a psychological lightening of the restrictions on free speech, let's keep it in perspective,'' Mr. Gomez said. ''What we need is more opposition in Parliament, a repeal of restrictions on free speech, more independent institutions.''</p>
        <p>But in the meantime, he said, he was happy to accept any opening the government provides.</p>
        <p>''Let's come here and exercise our right to free speech,'' he said, ''and get over our fear of public speaking.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
