<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Likes of Brahms, Beside a Lazy River</title>
    <meta content="02BARG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2DF1330F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Likes of Brahms, Beside a Lazy River</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>the likes of brahms, beside a lazy</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Olga Bloom began presenting her Bargemusic chamber concerts in 1977, the idea of offering performances in a floating room seemed both novel and slightly eccentric in the way that musical life beyond the walls of New York's big, well-endowed concert halls often is. Mrs. Bloom's enthusiasm for music and musicians radiated from her converted coffee barge, and both musicians and listeners began flocking to her series.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the draw at first had to do with the unusual setting or the need to support something that was clearly a worthy effort. But the novelty aspects gave way to more solidly musical reasons. Bargemusic, with its audiences of around 150 -- and its seats reserved with strips of paper giving the ticket holders' names -- offers the kind of intimacy that lets the music be what it was meant to be, a form of personal communication, rather than the spectator sport it can be in the larger halls. The sense of scope is abetted by the stunning view of Lower Manhattan through a bay window behind the stage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Olga Bloom began presenting her Bargemusic chamber concerts in 1977, the idea of offering performances in a floating room seemed both novel and slightly eccentric in the way that musical life beyond the walls of New York's big, well-endowed concert halls often is. Mrs. Bloom's enthusiasm for music and musicians radiated from her converted coffee barge, and both musicians and listeners began flocking to her series.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the draw at first had to do with the unusual setting or the need to support something that was clearly a worthy effort. But the novelty aspects gave way to more solidly musical reasons. Bargemusic, with its audiences of around 150 -- and its seats reserved with strips of paper giving the ticket holders' names -- offers the kind of intimacy that lets the music be what it was meant to be, a form of personal communication, rather than the spectator sport it can be in the larger halls. The sense of scope is abetted by the stunning view of Lower Manhattan through a bay window behind the stage.</p>
        <p>Given all that, it isn't surprising that Bargemusic is flourishing. It now offers concerts year round, and it has lately doubled its schedule to four performances (of two programs) a week. It has also adopted an almost collective approach to programming. Instead of a de facto music director assembling the programs and inviting colleagues to play them, a handful of Bargemusic regulars divide up the season, each coordinating several weeks' worth of concerts.</p>
        <p>The two programs offered this weekend were arranged by Ronald Thomas, the cellist, who used big works by Mozart and Brahms as the centerpiece of each. The Thursday program (repeated last night), opened with Mozart's Oboe Quartet (K. 370) and ended with Brahms's Piano Trio in B (Op. 8), with two Rhapsodies by Loeffler separating them. For the concerts tonight and tomorrow afternoon, the main attractions are the Mozart Clarinet Quintet and the Brahms Clarinet Trio, with Schumann's ''Fairy Tales'' as a preface.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas's colleagues on Thursday were Edmund Battersby, the pianist, Keisuke Ikuma, an oboist, Nai-Yuan Hu, a violinist and Vivek Kamath, a violist who plays in the New York Philharmonic. As is usually the case here, the performances benefited from a combination of polish and casualness: that is, the sound of fine musicians who know the music but who have not rehearsed it to within an inch of its life.</p>
        <p>The Mozart, for example, unfolded at a comfortable tempo and seemed to breathe so freely and naturally that one was almost tempted to take for granted its ornate surfaces and elegant construction. Mr. Ikuma's fleet oboe playing and sharply marked phrasing was a periodic reminder of those qualities, as was the general warmth of the string tone. In the first movement of the Brahms the slight tensions between Mr. Thomas's and Mr. Hu's intonation afforded the sense of an emotional drama taking place, rather than of a performance skirting derailment.</p>
        <p>The musicians also made a reasonable case for Loeffler's Rhapsodies (1905), uneven as they are. These easygoing confections for oboe, viola and piano betray an array of influences: there was an almost Debussian Impressionism in the keyboard harmonies, yet the singing viola and oboe lines veered more in the direction of English pastoralism.</p>
        <p>For the concerts tonight and tomorrow, Mr. Thomas, Mr. Hu, Mr. Kamath and Mr. Battersby will be joined by Thomas Hill, a clarinetist.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
