<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Are Up, But Trim Gains; Trading Is Light</title>
    <meta content="Y02STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EFD71330F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Are Up, But Trim Gains; Trading Is Light</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nasdaq composite index rises 27.98 points, or 0.67 percent, to 4,234.33; Dow Jones industrial average climbs 23.68 points, or 0.21 percent, to 11,238.78, and Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index gains 3.09 points, or 0.2 percent, to 1,520.77; bond market closes early for Labor Day weekend; yield on 10-year Treasury note slips to 5.68 percent--its lowest since July 1999--from 5.72 percent; price rises 10/32, to 100 18/32; graph on Dow Jones industrial average; charts on stocks with large price percentage gains and losses and US key interest rates (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stock and bond prices rose only slightly yesterday, even after new reports indicated that the economy was slowing enough to preclude another interest rate increase by the Federal Reserve in the near future.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department said that new jobs, excluding laid-off census workers and strikers, were created at a much slower pace in August and that there was a small rise in the unemployment rate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stock and bond prices rose only slightly yesterday, even after new reports indicated that the economy was slowing enough to preclude another interest rate increase by the Federal Reserve in the near future.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department said that new jobs, excluding laid-off census workers and strikers, were created at a much slower pace in August and that there was a small rise in the unemployment rate.</p>
        <p>Also, the National Association of Purchasing Management reported a decline in its factory index.</p>
        <p>More important, these reports came on top of other economic data and warnings of lower profits and slower revenue growth from some retailers and technology companies that all reflect a slowing economy. Based on some of this earlier data, Federal Reserve policy makers had already decided to leave their benchmark short-term interest rate unchanged at 6.5 percent when they met a week and a half ago.</p>
        <p>While some analysts still disagree, it seems that many investors now think that the Fed has finished raising interest rates in its effort to slow economic growth and curb inflationary pressure. This is the feeling despite the Fed policy makers' having said after their last meeting that they were still worried about inflationary pressure.</p>
        <p>The new data, said Richard E. Cripps, chief market strategist at Legg Mason Wood Walker in Baltimore, ''just highlighted the idea that the Fed is out of the market as a factor for the foreseeable future.''</p>
        <p>But because both the stock and bond markets have rallied as this view formed over the last few weeks, the reaction yesterday was muted.</p>
        <p>Since the end of July, the Nasdaq composite index had climbed 11.7 percent before trading yesterday, while the Dow Jones industrial average rose 6.6 percent and the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index increased 6.1 percent. In the bond market, the yield on the 10-year Treasury note, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, had already dropped to 5.72 percent on Thursday from just above 6 percent at the end of July.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the bond market closed early for the Labor Day weekend, and many were watching stocks from the beach -- also contributing to the muted response. Volume on the New York Stock Exchange was 768.45 million shares, well below the year's average of about a billion shares a day. ''You would have expected to have seen some profit taking after a good month and a long weekend ahead of you,'' Mr. Cripps said.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq, which performed best of the major indexes, rose 27.98 points yesterday, or 0.67 percent, to 4,234.33. The Dow industrials climbed 23.68 points, or 0.21 percent, to 11,238.78, and the S.&amp; P. 500 rose 3.09 points, or 0.2 percent, to 1,520.77. All three indexes gave up much of the gains they had made early in the day. Market breadth was positive.</p>
        <p>Still, the S.&amp; P. is now just under 7 points from its record and the Dow is 484 points below its record. The Nasdaq, which had suffered most from the technology sell-off earlier this year, has rebounded somewhat and needs to add a further 814 points to match its record. For the year, the Nasdaq is now up 4.06 percent, while the S.&amp; P. 500 has climbed 3.51 percent. The Dow is still off 2.25 percent.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the yield on the 10-year Treasury note slipped to 5.68 percent -- its lowest since July 1999 -- from 5.72 percent on Thursday. The price rose 10/32, to 100 18/32.</p>
        <p>Some technology and oil stocks led the market higher yesterday. Hewlett-Packard rose $4.25, to $125.25, while Texaco climbed 71 cents, to $52.21. The telecommunications company Global Crossing jumped $5.06, to $35.13, after it raised its sales forecast for the year.</p>
        <p>Some financial stocks finished lower, led by J. P. Morgan, down $7.50 to $159.69. Viant, a Web site designer, plunged by $5.69, to $8.19, after reporting that it expected a third-quarter loss because companies were reassessing their Internet strategies.</p>
        <p>After excluding the layoff of temporary census workers and those on strike against Verizon, nonfarm payrolls rose by 140,000 in August, well below the 222,000 average for the first seven months of the year. There was a surprising drop of 79,000 manufacturing jobs, while construction employment remained flat. The unemployment rate inched up to 4.1 percent from 4.0 percent.</p>
        <p>The National Association of Purchasing Management reported that its factory index dropped to 49.5 in August from 51.8 in July.</p>
        <p>Richard Berner, the chief United States economist at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, said the data ''has a soft tone to it'' and this indicated that third-quarter growth was going to be slower than expected.</p>
        <p>But he maintained that ''by and large the economy is doing quite well, despite these numbers.'' And he was not ready to declare that the Federal Reserve is finished raising interest rates, in part because of inflationary effects from the sharp rise in energy prices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cripps also warned that if the economy continued to slow, corporate earnings would become a concern for investors. The first two quarters of this year have seen extraordinary earnings growth, of more than 20 percent. But ''earnings numbers are going to decelerate along with the economy,'' Mr. Cripps said. ''This fact hasn't hit the broad market as yet. But it could if the slowdown continues.''</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
