<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Reform-Minded Voters Bush Can't Do Without</title>
    <meta content="02WITT$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wittmann, Marshall</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E1DF1330F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Reform-Minded Voters Bush Can't Do Without</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marshall Wittmann</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wittmann, Marshall</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>The Re</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that it appears the presidential contest will be a race to the finish, the battle will be intense for the support of the most dynamic force in the American electorate, the independent voter. It is these voters, who are not affiliated with either major political party, who are behind the tremendous volatility in the presidential polls over the past few weeks.</p>
        <p>Al Gore has aggressively courted the independents by focusing on issues in which they have shown an interest -- pledging to fight special interests and move on campaign finance reform -- as well as by choosing a maverick Democrat, Joe Lieberman, as his running mate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that it appears the presidential contest will be a race to the finish, the battle will be intense for the support of the most dynamic force in the American electorate, the independent voter. It is these voters, who are not affiliated with either major political party, who are behind the tremendous volatility in the presidential polls over the past few weeks.</p>
        <p>Al Gore has aggressively courted the independents by focusing on issues in which they have shown an interest -- pledging to fight special interests and move on campaign finance reform -- as well as by choosing a maverick Democrat, Joe Lieberman, as his running mate.</p>
        <p>George W. Bush, by contrast, has made only modest efforts to appeal to independents on the reform issues that are dear to them. To swing these voters his way, he should reconsider his failure to embrace the reform agenda that made Senator John McCain a viable opponent to him in the early primaries.</p>
        <p>The independents include the Reagan Democrats, the Clinton Republicans, soccer moms and those who rarely vote, as well as the Perotistas of 1992 who put a former wrestler in the Minnesota governor's mansion. There is also the Stewart factor, typified by the ponytailed office clerk in a television commercial who instructs a middle-aged boss on how to use the Internet to trade stocks. Stewart is likely to be fiscally conservative, socially moderate and turned off to politics as usual.</p>
        <p>To win the votes of Stewart and the other independents, Republicans will need more than campaign aesthetics to show Mr. Bush as a ''different kind of Republican.'' He has rejected the harsh partisan tone of the House Republicans, but he has failed to embrace the proposals for reform that have energized independent voters in the past.</p>
        <p>First, Governor Bush should find a way to the separate himself from the special interests that are anathema to many independents. He cannot afford to remain as close as he has been in the past to corporations like those he favored with tax cuts in Texas.</p>
        <p>A great vulnerability of Vice President Gore is the fund-raising scandals, despite his vow to sign a bill reforming the campaign finance system. Yet unlimited soft money contributions seem to have become a Republican sacrament, binding big-business lobbyists and the religious right. Without taking a 180-degree turn on the issue, Governor Bush  could call for the elimination of all corporate, union and individual soft money in return for raising limitations on so-called hard money contributions.</p>
        <p>The Democrats are likely to skewer Mr. Bush and the other oilman on the Republican ticket, Dick Cheney, as the J. R. Ewing dream team. Mr. Cheney's lavish severance package from Halliburton further reinforces that image. To deflect this attack, the Republicans should take on corporate welfare as discordant with fiscal conservative principles. Mr. Bush should find a corporate sacred cow to skewer, perhaps the notorious federal sugar subsidy or innumerable loopholes.</p>
        <p>Finally, the Bush campaign should place more emphasis on debt reduction rather than a huge tax cut targeted to the most wealthy. In opinion surveys, independents and followers of Ross Perot have consistently placed debt retirement before tax cuts. Without walking away from his tax plan, Governor Bush should reassure voters that he will move to postpone the cuts in the future if revenues were not sufficient for tax reduction.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush embodies many of the qualities the largely centrist, fiscally conservative independents are looking for in a president. It should not be difficult for him to make the logical moves on political reform that would secure their support.</p>
        <p>Marshall Wittmann, who is joining the Hudson Institute as a senior fellow, was deputy assistant secretary of health under George Bush.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Marshall Wittmann, who is joining the Hudson Institute as a senior fellow, was deputy assistant secretary of health under George Bush.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
