<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Snubbing Chronology As a Guiding Force in Art</title>
    <meta content="02CHRO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boxer, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EFDF1330F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Snubbing Chronology As a Guiding Force in Art</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH BOXER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boxer, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several recent museum exhibitions that mixed works from different time periods had critics up in arms, but antichronology is becoming increasingly popular and many curators are reshaping their collections according to subject rather than time periods; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A little war against time has begun. Last year, when the Museum of Modern Art opened the show ''Modern Starts: People, Places, Things,'' the first part of ''MOMA 2000,'' Cezanne's ''Bather'' from 1885 was found hanging next to a 1993 Rineke Dijkstra photograph of a pale boy in a maroon bathing suit.</p>
        <p>A few months later the Tate Modern, in its permanent collection, lined up Matisse's sculptures of women's backs before a firing squad of ink drawings of nude women by a contemporary artist named Marlene Dumas. And at the modern art museum at the Georges Pompidou Center Henri Rousseau's 19th-century ''War'' faced off against a Picasso sculpture from 1950, ''Girl Jumping Rope.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A little war against time has begun. Last year, when the Museum of Modern Art opened the show ''Modern Starts: People, Places, Things,'' the first part of ''MOMA 2000,'' Cezanne's ''Bather'' from 1885 was found hanging next to a 1993 Rineke Dijkstra photograph of a pale boy in a maroon bathing suit.</p>
        <p>A few months later the Tate Modern, in its permanent collection, lined up Matisse's sculptures of women's backs before a firing squad of ink drawings of nude women by a contemporary artist named Marlene Dumas. And at the modern art museum at the Georges Pompidou Center Henri Rousseau's 19th-century ''War'' faced off against a Picasso sculpture from 1950, ''Girl Jumping Rope.''</p>
        <p>The critics were up in arms. What got them was not the mixing of media or the mixing of masterpieces with lesser works. It was the mixing of time periods. As Jed Perl, an American art critic, put it in The New Republic, ''Chronology, that backbone of the historical sense, has been collapsed into some kind of postmodern time warp.''</p>
        <p>David Sylvester, a British art critic, wrote in The London Review of Books that ''chronology is not a tool of art-historical interpretation which can be used at one moment, discarded at another.'' Rather, he said, ''It's an objective reality, built into the fabric of the work.''</p>
        <p>Despite the criticism, antichronology is now the rage. The Brooklyn Museum of Art, the Denver Art Museum and the High Museum of Art in Atlanta have all rehung their painting and sculpture collections according to subject instead of chronology. And ''The Art Book,'' published by Phaidon, ''debunks art-historical classifications'' (in its words) by arranging artists alphabetically instead of chronologically. That is, Picasso is found next to Piero della Francesca and Manet next to Mangold.</p>
        <p>The one thing curators seem to agree on about antichronology is this: Chronology and time are only the surface issues. The deeper issues are genealogy and history, whether there is a great lineage of art, a natural progression of one art movement after another leading up to the grand finale, abstraction.</p>
        <p>In art history, said Linda Nochlin, the Lila Acheson Wallace Professor of Modern Art at the Institute of Fine Arts in New York, ''there is a tendency to use chronology as teleology,'' as proof of a march toward a goal. ''To the degree that a nonchronological hang can destroy that,'' she said, she approves. ''The main thing is to break up the idea of an uninterrupted flow.''</p>
        <p>What is the problem with flow? The problem is the flow chart. In 1936 Alfred H. Barr Jr., the founding director of the Museum of Modern Art, created a diagram to go with the exhibition ''Cubism and Abstract Art.'' It showed the evolution of various movements or, as they are now called, ''isms'': Neo-Impressionism, Fauvism, Cubism, Futurism, Expressionism, Orphism, Suprematism, Constructivism, Dadaism, Neoplasticism, Purism, Surrealism. And all the isms led to abstraction.</p>
        <p>With its Hegelian aura of inevitability and objectivity, the Barr diagram is the casus belli of the chronological war. In ''Tate Modern: The Handbook,'' Iwona Blazwick and Frances Morris, who developed the conceptual framework for the new museum's displays, note that Barr's chart ''came to dominate most modernist collections around the world,'' and that it ''is still used to delineate art into periods and movements.''</p>
        <p>That chart ''was the religion of modern art, like the chart of the House of Windsor,'' said Robert Rosenblum, a professor of fine arts at New York University. ''It represented truth. This one married that one and begat that one.'' It was neat, easy to absorb and difficult to eliminate. Floor plans were designed with the diagram in mind. As Nicholas Serota, the director of the Tate, wrote in ''Experience or Interpretation,'' the modern art museum became a one-way narrative, ''a single path with no byways and only occasional opportunities for exit.''</p>
        <p>Now museums are working to undo the diagram. Why now, at such a late date? Almost everyone thinks the millennium was a motivating factor. Ms. Blazwick said, ''The idea of starting with 1900 and marching to 2000 was -- well, there is such a thing as museum fatigue.'' Charles Stuckey, a curator at the Kimbell Art Museum in Fort Worth, cited ''the pressures of political correctness.''</p>
        <p>''They want to show that the history of art is not about masterpieces,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Tom Crow, the director of the Getty Research Institute, said the theoretical ideas from art history and the social sciences are finally seeping into museums.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, bucking Barr is now a museum sport. Some have tried the non chronological approach. Others have gone for the hyperchronological approach.</p>
        <p>In 1991 Mr. Stuckey ''raked together'' the contemporary and modern collections of the Art Institute of Chicago and showed them strictly chronologically, without regard for geography, medium or movement. ''It was a new way to look at the collection, and it brought out works that had fallen between the cracks,'' he said. ''It's rather neutral politically. It's nonbiased.'' Like an alphabetical approach, ''it gives no advantage to a group or a place,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Guggenheim Museum's ''1900,'' a show put together by Mr. Rosenblum that examines a slice of art from 1897 to 1903, with few works from the modernist canon, was another radical response. ''I like to shuffle the deck of isms,'' Mr. Rosenblum said. ''Showing everything done at the same time is antichronological in a sense,'' because there is no time passing, no progress. It is a snapshot of a moment.</p>
        <p>The catalog for the second part of ''MOMA 2000,'' ''Making Choices,'' took a swipe at chronology, too. Rather than surveying a sweep of time, the book explored core samples of four years: 1929, 1939, 1948, 1955.</p>
        <p>So far, though, the most popular way of bucking Barr is the antichronological hang. Both ''Tate Modern: The Handbook'' and the Museum of Modern Art's catalog for ''Modern Starts'' reproduced Barr's diagram as a kind of cautionary tale. And both made it their business to get across the idea that there is no one true history, but rather many.</p>
        <p>The Tate Modern's installation has no single pathway through it. And Ms. Blazwick noted that in the new museum you can see that ''everything is constructed.'' Even the wall labels are signed now, and each one expresses the view of its author. In each gallery, Ms. Blazwick said, you can tell that ''someone made a decision.'' That is, ''by selecting one thing, we are also rejecting something.'' There is no natural order, no objective truth.</p>
        <p>And there is no one modernism. The word ''modern,'' Ms. Blazwick said, ''is so flexible and multivalent that we think of it in terms of modernisms: plural not singular.'' So modern has become postmodern, a potpourri of choices. Or as John Elderfield, chief curator at large at the Museum of Modern Art, put it: ''We're not replacing one orthodoxy with another. We want to show that what was happening until now was an orthodoxy.'' It is a process of defamiliarizing the familiar.</p>
        <p>Yet there is something oddly familiar about the new antichronological hangs. The Tate Modern and the Museum of Modern Art, after pondering various options -- including organizing the collection or exhibition according to geography, or around certain manifestos or important exhibitions, or by modes of fabrication, or by color, or according to the prevailing thinkers -- independently came up with those old-fashioned categories called genres.</p>
        <p>The Museum of Modern Art took three categories for ''Modern Starts'' -- people, places, things. The Tate took four genres -- still life, landscape, nude and history painting -- and then loosened them up. In both cases, though, it was back to the future.</p>
        <p>The nonchronological hang is an old notion. In the 18th century museums were just collections of loot, Mr. Elderfield noted. And before that there were Wunderkammern, cabinets of wonders, curiosities and grotesques, organized every which way. The shift began when the Louvre opened to the public after the French Revolution and assumed a didactic function.</p>
        <p>''Arranging paintings in terms of schools and countries was a 19th-century invention,'' Mr. Elderfield said. ''There was a ''passion to systematize.'' So the resurrection of genres in installations is a way of leapfrogging backward over the 19th-century obsession with linear progress and evolution.</p>
        <p>''There is no natural way to hang things,'' he said, just as in biology there is almost no natural way to categorize things. ''All taxonomies are subjective except species.'' And in art history there are no species.</p>
        <p>Everyone seems to agree that every hanging is biased and incomplete. So maybe  the chronology war comes down to whether to dwell on the biases or not. Donna De Salvo, a curator at Tate Modern said, ''We want to allow things to feel unsettled,'' to let people see that museums are constructions, not givens. Or as Ms. Blazwick put it, ''We are trying to make the institution more transparent.''</p>
        <p>Others say that too much transparency obscures the art. ''Of course every historical view is partial,'' Mr. Stuckey said. ''But I think the best system is where you're unaware that someone has arranged it. A curator should walk on the sand without leaving his footprints.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
