<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: Giving Theme Parks a Whirl; Europeans Warm to an American-Style Entertainment</title>
    <meta content="Y02PAR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amusement Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2D71330F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: Giving Theme Parks a Whirl; Europeans Warm to an American-Style Entertainment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>DRONTEN, the Netherlands</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American-style amusement parks have become increasingly popular in Europe; Economic Research Associates says in last decade number of theme parks in Europe has increased by a third, to 83 established parks, while number of admissions has risen two-thirds, to 101 million, and revenues doubled, to $2.2 billion; last year, Europe's 83 parks averaged about 1.2 million visitors each, far fewer than 2 million that attended each of America's 226 parks; Americans spend about $30 during visit to park, while Europeans average only $22 a visit; graphs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A paunchy kangaroo used to perch atop the entrance to the old Walibi Flevo theme park here, a red ''W'' on its sweater for the Walibi Group of Belgium, which ran the park.</p>
        <p>The kangaroo is gone now, and the old gate is, too, replaced by a pastel-and-aluminum Art Deco facade, capped with the name Six Flags Holland. On masts nearby flutter the flags of the Netherlands, Belgium, Germany, France, Spain and the United States -- the countries where the American owner, Six Flags Inc., operates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A paunchy kangaroo used to perch atop the entrance to the old Walibi Flevo theme park here, a red ''W'' on its sweater for the Walibi Group of Belgium, which ran the park.</p>
        <p>The kangaroo is gone now, and the old gate is, too, replaced by a pastel-and-aluminum Art Deco facade, capped with the name Six Flags Holland. On masts nearby flutter the flags of the Netherlands, Belgium, Germany, France, Spain and the United States -- the countries where the American owner, Six Flags Inc., operates.</p>
        <p>It may seem odd that the Dutch and other Europeans, surrounded by glories like the canals of Amsterdam and the museums and churches of Brussels, would flock to an American-style theme park.</p>
        <p>But they do. Europeans visited amusement parks in record numbers this summer, stirred by spreading affluence, booming tourism and greater variety. In the last decade the number of theme parks in Europe has increased by a third, to 83 established parks, according to Economics Research Associates, which tracks the industry, while the number of admissions has risen two-thirds, to 101 million, and revenues doubled, to $2.2 billion.</p>
        <p>The expansion is gathering momentum and drawing outside investment, notably from the United States, transforming the European industry, long known for family-owned mom-and-pop parks. Last year, Europe's 83 parks averaged about 1.2 million visitors each, far fewer than the 2 million that packed into each of America's 226 parks.</p>
        <p>And once inside, Americans were induced into spending an average of $30 a visitor, against $22 in Europe. ''Our trans-Atlantic cousins can still teach us a few things,'' David Camp, an analyst in London for Economics Research Associates, wrote to clients recently.</p>
        <p>But as Europeans rush to catch up, the Continent is increasingly luring American park operators who have expertise in design and marketing.</p>
        <p>In addition to buying the park and five others in Europe from Walibi in 1998, Six Flags last year acquired Warner Brothers Movie World, in Germany's densely populated Ruhr basin, and another Warner studio park being built outside Madrid. The theme park unit of Universal Studios also acquired control of Spain's biggest park, Port Aventura, on the Costa Dorada near Barcelona. Universal, a part of the Seagram Company, which is being acquired by the French conglomerate Vivendi, has ambitious plans to transform Port Aventura into Europe's No. 2 park after Disneyland Paris.</p>
        <p>Not to be outflanked, Disney announced a major expansion last year of its site at Marne-la-Vallee, east of Paris, including a new studio park alongside Disneyland Paris.</p>
        <p>European companies are getting into the action, too. Global Family Attractions, the theme park division of Lego System, of Denmark, will open a $138 million theme park south of Munich in 2002. Like Lego's other parks in Denmark, Britain and California, it will be based on Lego blocks. In Spain a $400 million park, Terra Mitica, opened its gates this summer near Alicante in the southeast, and as many as 20 other projects are in the works.</p>
        <p>Not that selling Europeans on magic kingdoms and Wild West villages comes easily. In Belgium, laws prevent students from working more than one month a year, so Six Flags continually trains new crops of students for summer jobs. And not every slogan translates well. For a season's-end Halloween festival, Six Flags marketing experts puzzled over whether to call it a Fright Fest, then dropped the name as untranslatable.</p>
        <p>Nor is every project an automatic winner. In Spain, investors, including the Ogden Corporation of New York, built a park called Isla Magica on the site of the 1992 Seville world's fair. But Isla Magica ran up nothing but losses after it opened in 1997, a victim of poor marketing and high costs. Last spring, after a consortium of Spanish banks effectively took over Isla Magica, Ogden bailed out and sold its theme park interests to a Greek investor.</p>
        <p>Six Flags' strategy in the Netherlands, a kind of pilot project for its European parks, illustrates the impact of fresh investment and aggressive marketing. When the old Walibi park closed in October, Six Flags mobilized hundreds of workers from a dozen countries to complete almost $40 million of improvements, including rides like a 115-foot Ferris wheel, and four additional roller coasters. To generate more spending in the park, Six Flags increased restaurant capacity by 50 percent and installed 20 pushcarts offering snacks.</p>
        <p>To draw visitors back, Six Flags introduced a season pass, good at all its parks. To nudge visitors to buy the pass, it increased the single-entry ticket to 41 Dutch gilders, about $17, from 33. The season pass is 160 gilders. Spending for television and radio ads was sharply increased; to draw visitors for events like conventions, weddings and birthday parties, marketing executives fanned out to schools, social clubs and businesses.</p>
        <p>''These were good facilities doing a reasonable profit,'' said Daniel P. Aylward, Six Flags' managing director for Europe. Mr. Aylward, a veteran at turning American parks around, ducks and bobs as he shows a visitor through the park, snatching up litter as he walks. ''But there were lots of opportunities for advertising and marketing.''</p>
        <p>For local politicians and planners, the investments and the jobs are welcome. In the Netherlands, the number of park employees, some of them poorly paid performers, has grown to 700 from 300 in two years. In Madrid, much of the $300 million investment in the new Warner studio park is being borne by regional governments. While Six Flags will manage the park when it opens in 2002, it will have only 5 percent ownership.</p>
        <p>Herman Otte, 38, who knew the old Walibi park, drove 60 miles recently from his home north of Amsterdam after hearing about the refurbished Dutch park in a television commercial. ''It's more attractive for children, and far larger,'' he said, as his family made its way to a snack bar from the new Looney Tunes area, where Bugs Bunny and his pals had cavorted in a musical sketch. Earlier, Mr. Otte and his daughter Yanique, 3, had enjoyed the big new Ferris wheel. ''She wasn't afraid,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Such visitors cheer executives at Six Flags' American parent, for whom Europe brings the promise of renewed investor favor. After Six Flags, then called Premier Parks, went public in 1996, its share price roughly tripled in two years. The shares have tumbled by 50 percent since the start of the year, though, with analysts citing this summer's bad weather in parts of the United States and a kind of consumer fatigue with leisure and entertainment products.</p>
        <p>''They clearly view Europe as a very ripe market to expand their business,'' said Jill S. Krutick, an analyst with Salomon Smith Barney. Last month, she cut her recommendation back a notch, to outperform from buy. ''In Europe, there's an enormous opportunity to consolidate the market,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Kieran E. Burke, Six Flags' 43-year-old chairman and chief executive, described the thrust into Europe as but one part of a broader international strategy that included Latin America, where Six Flags operates a park outside Mexico City, and Asia, where it is looking for places to invest.</p>
        <p>''In many respects,'' he said, ''we are really just getting started,'' adding that the planned expansion would have ''significant ramifications for the value of the company.''</p>
        <p>In Europe, as in the United States, the Six Flags strategy is to operate regional parks, mostly for nearby day trippers, who often become season ticket holders who might drop into the parks more often, if only for a few hours at a time.</p>
        <p>At Universal Studios, by contrast, the goal is to transform Port Aventura, which this season was renamed Universal Studios Port Aventura, into a destination park, perhaps adding a studio park to the existing theme park, as well as hotels and golf courses.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Tom Williams, chairman of Universal Studios' theme park group, does not hesitate to say the goal is ''to turn this single-gated attraction into a year-round family resort.''</p>
        <p>Port Aventura, which opened in 1995, packed in three million visitors this year by the end of July, roughly the number it drew in all 1999, when attendance rose 11 percent from the year before. Under Universal's management, Port Aventura this year opened a $30 million submarine ride, Sea Odyssey, and next season plans another blockbuster, Temple of Fire, in which visitors walk through flames. Last year, Port Aventura was employing roughly 3,000 people, generating $85 million in revenue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams appears to be leading the expansion of Port Aventura into an all-year destination resort along the lines of Universal Studios Escape in Orlando, whose creation he oversaw before taking his current job a year ago. The immediate plans for Spain, he said, involve building two 500-room hotels for occupancy in 2003, with meeting rooms allowing Universal to draw business and convention travelers, focusing on a European market that Disney once had pretty much to itself. Unlike Paris, with its cool and cloudy climate, Barcelona, much like Orlando, boasts 300 days of sunshine a year and average temperatures of 72 degrees. Indeed, the city was the runner-up to Paris when Disney chose the location for its European park in 1985.</p>
        <p>For the moment, the 7 million annual admissions at the Six Flags parks in Europe are little more than half the 12.5 million Disneyland Paris packed in last year, and Disney is hardly in danger of losing its leadership position. Last year, Disney, which owns 39 percent of the company that runs Disneyland Paris, announced plans for a new $615 million 62-acre park that will focus on film studios, animation and television.</p>
        <p>James Rasulo, the 15-year Disney veteran who is chief executive of the French unit, Euro Disney, said attendance at the site should rise from 12.5 million visitors last year to 17.5 million when the new park opens in April 2002. To accommodate the increase, Disney is negotiating with tour operators and hotel management companies to build new hotels with a total of 1,500 rooms, to add to the six hotels with 5,160 rooms it now operates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rasulo says the pattern in Europe apes that in America. Improvements in the design and management of regional parks are lifting the image of theme parks generally, ultimately benefiting the market leader, Disney.</p>
        <p>''Most of these guys are mimicking us, in the layout of their parks, in the handling of people,'' he said. ''It's exactly the pattern you had in the United States: more professionalism, and that drove more business.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
