<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Squabble About Motives Dominates Democratic Race</title>
    <meta content="02PRIM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="NEW YORK PRIMARY: 34th State Senate District" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227222"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hicks, Jonathan P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Velella, Guy J (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koppell, Lorraine Coyle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benedetto, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koppell, G Oliver</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5DF1330F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1093" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Squabble About Motives Dominates Democratic Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hicks, Jonathan P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series examining primary contests in New York State focuses on 34th State Senate district, represented by Republican Sen Guy Velella; voters will have choice between two candidates in Democratic primary, Lorraine Coyle Koppell, lawyer and wife of former state attorney general G Oliver Koppell, and Michael R Benedetto, teacher and a Bronx Democratic district leader; map of district, which encompasses parts of Bronx and Westchester County; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the Democratic Party working feverishly to win enough contests to regain control of the state Senate, the party is setting its sights on districts like the one represented by State Senator Guy Velella. Mr. Velella, a Republican who represents an area in the Bronx with a largely Democratic electorate, is seen as one of several vulnerable incumbents.</p>
        <p>While it is a district the Democrats say they can win in November, the party is locked in a harsh contest to determine who will be the nominee there, the 34th State Senate District. Voters will have a choice between two candidates in the Sept. 12 Democratic primary: Lorraine Coyle Koppell, a lawyer who is also the wife of former state attorney general, G. Oliver Koppell, and Michael R. Benedetto, a public elementary school teacher who is a Bronx Democratic district leader.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the Democratic Party working feverishly to win enough contests to regain control of the state Senate, the party is setting its sights on districts like the one represented by State Senator Guy Velella. Mr. Velella, a Republican who represents an area in the Bronx with a largely Democratic electorate, is seen as one of several vulnerable incumbents.</p>
        <p>While it is a district the Democrats say they can win in November, the party is locked in a harsh contest to determine who will be the nominee there, the 34th State Senate District. Voters will have a choice between two candidates in the Sept. 12 Democratic primary: Lorraine Coyle Koppell, a lawyer who is also the wife of former state attorney general, G. Oliver Koppell, and Michael R. Benedetto, a public elementary school teacher who is a Bronx Democratic district leader.</p>
        <p>The race is seen as significant because it represents a local contest between two opponents with some degree of might behind them. Mrs. Koppell has widespread name recognition and has raised a considerable amount of money. On the other hand, Mr. Benedetto is being supported by the Bronx Democratic organization and many of the public officials in the area.</p>
        <p>But it is also being watched eagerly because of the longstanding close relationship between Mr. Velella and the Bronx Democratic leader, Assemblyman Roberto Ramirez. Some Bronx Democrats, Mrs. Koppell foremost among them, have accused Mr. Ramirez of trying to help Mr. Velella by encouraging Mr. Benedetto to run and thereby producing a bruising primary battle that would drain Mrs. Koppell's resources before the general election.</p>
        <p>For months, Mrs. Koppell, 53, had the Democratic stage to herself and had begun early this year to raise money and to put together a campaign organization. But she was discouraged by Mr. Ramirez, who told her that a vigorous state Senate race would generate votes in the general election for the Republican candidate for United States Senate. At the time, Mr. Ramirez said, he had expected that that candidate would be Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who has won his mayoral races in the past with an overwhelming majority in the 34th State Senate District.</p>
        <p>But then within a few weeks of her discussion with Mr. Ramirez, Mrs. Koppell found an opponent in Mr. Benedetto, who officially entered the race. That led Mrs. Koppell to assert that Mr. Ramirez had engineered opposition to her candidacy.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there is any question about it,'' Mrs. Koppell said. ''Roberto Ramirez asked Mike Benedetto to run. And it was to hurt my candidacy and to help Guy Velella.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedetto, 53, said he is deeply offended by such remarks. ''Roberto Ramirez never asked me to run,'' Mr. Benedetto said. ''I went to him and told him that I wanted to run for the seat. Just look at the arrogance of Mrs. Koppell, who thinks that everyone should run their campaign under the Koppell timetable. I have a history in this district and I am the stronger candidate.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, he is no stranger to elective politics, having run for office a number of times, always unsuccessfully. He first ran for the state Assembly -- against Mr. Velella -- in 1976 and has been active in various Democratic clubs in the Bronx for years since then. Two years later, he ran for the state Senate against a Republican incumbent, Senator John D. Calandra. In 1980, he ran again for state Senate, but lost in the Democratic primary to Mr. Calandra, who had also pursued the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>Taking a break from politics, Mr. Benedetto then started a local newspaper, The Bronx Times Reporter. He returned to politics in 1988, when he ran for the position of Democratic district leader, a position he has held since. He said he was prompted to run for the Senate by the prospect of Mrs. Koppell winning the primary.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Koppell, too, has been involved in community affairs. A former president of the Bronx Women's Bar Association, Mrs. Koppell has offered free legal representation and advice to a number of nonprofit organizations in the district. She has raised about $150,000 for the race so far and is being supported by Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi, Public Advocate Mark J. Green and several officials who represent Riverdale. Mr. Benedetto said he has so far raised about $35,000.</p>
        <p>In campaigning, Mrs. Koppell and Mr. Benedetto sound similar themes. They both talk about the need to reduce the sizes of classes in the public schools in the district and the importance of getting more money for New York City schools from Albany.</p>
        <p>On crime, Mr. Benedetto gives prominence to the need to raise the salaries of police officers and to support stronger laws. Mrs. Koppell emphasizes the need for stricter gun control laws and for the police and community groups to work more closely together.</p>
        <p>The shape of the 34th State Senate District resembles a horseshoe, running from the Riverdale and Belmont sections of the Bronx into Westchester County and back into the east Bronx neighborhoods of Pelham Bay, Country Club and Throgs Neck. And geography has become part of the debate in this race.</p>
        <p>Mr. Benedetto insists that he would be a more formidable opponent to Mr. Velella because he comes from Throgs Neck, the portion of the district that is the most heavily populated. Because Mrs. Koppell lives in Riverdale on the opposite end of that horseshoe, Mr. Benedetto insists that she has less in common with most of the voters in the district.</p>
        <p>''She comes from Riverdale, a chunk of the district that represents maybe 10 percent,'' Mr. Benedetto said. ''She is really out of tune about what this district is all about.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Koppell called her opponent's logic ''stupid and childish.'' Referring to Mr. Benedetto, she said: ''He lives in one house and I live in one house. The issue is not where we live. It's who can do the better job.''</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PRIMARY  34th State Senate District</p>
        <p>Articles in this series are examining individual primary contests in Congressional and local districts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
