<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="02TRNS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EEDB1030F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League</p>
        <p>ANAHEIM ANGELS--Activated C Matt Walbeck from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled INF Justin Baughman and RHP Ben Weber from Edmonton of the PCL. Purchased the contract of LHP Bryan Ward from Edmonton.  BOSTON RED SOX--Recalled LHP Sang Lee from Pawtucket of the International League. Activated OF Izzy Alcantara from the 15-day disabled list and recalled him from Pawtucket.  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Recalled RHP Chad Bradford, INF Craig Wilson and C Josh Paul from Charlotte of the International League. Purchased the contract of RHP Matt Ginter from Birmingham of the Southern League. Optioned RHP Rocky Biddle to Birmingham.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL  American League</p>
        <p>ANAHEIM ANGELS--Activated C Matt Walbeck from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled INF Justin Baughman and RHP Ben Weber from Edmonton of the PCL. Purchased the contract of LHP Bryan Ward from Edmonton.  BOSTON RED SOX--Recalled LHP Sang Lee from Pawtucket of the International League. Activated OF Izzy Alcantara from the 15-day disabled list and recalled him from Pawtucket.  CHICAGO WHITE SOX--Recalled RHP Chad Bradford, INF Craig Wilson and C Josh Paul from Charlotte of the International League. Purchased the contract of RHP Matt Ginter from Birmingham of the Southern League. Optioned RHP Rocky Biddle to Birmingham.</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND INDIANS--Recalled RHP Jim Brower, LHP Cameron Cairncross, OF Dave Roberts and RHP Jake Westbrook from Buffalo of the International League. Placed Westbrook on the 60-day disabled list. Purchased the contract of RHP Chris Nichting from Buffalo.  DETROIT TIGERS--Activated 1B Tony Clark and C Robert Fick from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled LHP Sean Runyan from Toledo of the International League. Purchased the contract of Rodney Lindsey from Jacksonville of the Southern League.  KANSAS CITY ROYALS--Activated C Jorge Fabregas from the 15-day disabled list.  MINNESOTA TWINS--Recalled OF Brian Buchanan from Salt Lake of the PCL.  YANKEES--Activated 2B Chuck Knoblauch and RHP Ramiro Mendoza from the 15-day disabled list. Transferred LHP Alan Watson from the 15- to the 60-day disabled list. Purchased the contract of OF Ryan Thompson from Columbus of the International League. Recalled RHP Craig Dingman from Columbus.  OAKLAND ATHLETICS--Recalled C A.J. Hinch from Sacramento of the PCL. Activated RHP T.J Matthews from the 15-day disabled list.  SEATTLE MARINERS--Activated OF Jay Buhner from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled RHP Frankie Rodriguez, OF Charles Gipson and RHP Kevin Hodges from Tacoma of the PCL. Purchased the contract of INF Brian Lesher from Tacoma.  TAMPA BAY DEVIL RAYS--Recalled OF Kenny Kelly and LHP Trevor Enders from Orlando of the Southern League and INF Jace Brewer from Charleston, SC of the South Atlantic League. Activated INF Damian Rolls from the 60-day disabled list. Sent RHP Billy Taylor outright to Durham of the International League.  TEXAS RANGERS--Activated LHP Darren Oliver from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled RHP Jonathan Johnson from Oklahoma of the PCL.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Designated LHP Eric DuBose for assignment. Transferred OF DeWayne Wise and 2B Homer Bush from the 15 to the 60-day disabled list. Recalled OF Vernon Wells from Syracuse of the International League.</p>
        <p>National League</p>
        <p>ATLANTA BRAVES--Recalled INF Steve Sisco, OF George Lombard and RHP Jason Marquis from Richmond of the International League. Purchased the contract of C Mike Hubbard from Richmond.  CHICAGO CUBS--Recalled INF Jose Nieves from Iowa of the PCL.  CINCINNATI REDS--Signed SS David Espinosa and C Dane Sardinha. Recalled LHP Hector Mercado from Louisville of the International League. Activated RHP Osvaldo Fernandez from the 15-day disabled list.  LOS ANGELES DODGERS--Activated INF Chris Donnels from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled LHP Onan Masaoka and C Paul LoDuca from Albuquerque of the PCL. Purchased the contract of RHP Luke Prokopec from San Antonio of the Texas League.  ST. LOUIS CARDINALS--Recalled OF Thomas Howard from Memphis of the PCL.  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Recalled RHP Will Cunnane from Las Vegas of the PCL.  SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS--Added C Scott Servais to the roster. Recalled RHP Miguel Del Toro, INF Pedro Feliz and INF Damon Minor from Fresno of the PCL. Purchased the contracts of INF Juan Melo and OF Terrell Lowery from Fresno, and RHP Ryan Vogelsong from Shreveport of the Texas League.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL  National Basketball Association</p>
        <p>MIAMI HEAT--Re-signed F Harold Jamison.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL  National Football League</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND BROWNS--Signed QB Doug Pederson to a two-year contract.  SEATTLE SEAHAWKS--Claimed CB Paul Miranda off waivers from the Indianapolis Colts.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY  National Hockey League</p>
        <p>RANGERS--Agreed to terms with F Jason Dawe.  SAN JOSE SHARKS--Signed LW Larry Courville. Re-signed D Christian Gosselin.  COLLEGE  COLGATE--Named Bernard Emple assistant track coach.  IOWA--Dismissed F Rob Griffin from the basketball team for violating team policy.  LEMOYNE--Named Meaghan Coleman women's assistant basketball coach.  MAINE--Named Natalie Jutras women's assistant basketball coach.  RPI--Named Ivan Moore interim men's assistant ice hockey coach.  RIDER--Named Dean Edwards men's assistant basketball coach.  ST. JOSEPH'S--Named Ellen Stenrud women's assistant soccer coach.  ST. JOSEPH'S, IND.--Named Rick O'Dette baseball coach.  UNLV--Named DelVaughn Alexander wide receivers coach.  UTAH STATE--Named Philip Alicea assistant track coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
