<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Competing Annual Events Held by Bangladeshi Groups</title>
    <meta content="02FOBA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bangladeshi-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federation of Bangladeshi Associations of North America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bangladesh League of America</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0D61230F931A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Competing Annual Events Held by Bangladeshi Groups</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fourteenth annual convention of Federation of Bangladeshi Associations of North America, known as Fobana, is being held in two places, at Madison Square Garden and at a cetering hall in Astoria, Queens; events are sponsored by two groups, each claiming name of Bangladesh League of America in long-simmering dispute (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last four weeks have been strange ones for many Bangladeshi-Americans.</p>
        <p>First, Bengali-language newspapers received a mysterious white powder in the mail, with threatening notes alluding to an annual cultural convention that was the subject of a simmering dispute. Then, two Bangladeshi groups each claimed to be the official host of that convention. The two groups, each claiming the name Bangladesh League of America and contending the other was an imposter, took each other to court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last four weeks have been strange ones for many Bangladeshi-Americans.</p>
        <p>First, Bengali-language newspapers received a mysterious white powder in the mail, with threatening notes alluding to an annual cultural convention that was the subject of a simmering dispute. Then, two Bangladeshi groups each claimed to be the official host of that convention. The two groups, each claiming the name Bangladesh League of America and contending the other was an imposter, took each other to court.</p>
        <p>The cases are still pending. Meanwhile, each group had sought to block the other from holding its convention this weekend, but after a judge said there was not enough time to settle the dispute before the weekend, the groups decided to withdraw those motions and go ahead with two separate events. Their decision was first reported yesterday in Newsday.</p>
        <p>So the 14th annual convention of the Federation of Bangladeshi Associations of North America, known as Fobana, is being held in two places, at Madison Square Garden and at a catering hall in Astoria, Queens.</p>
        <p>The trouble began at last year's Fobana convention in Atlanta, when New York City was chosen as the site of this year's meeting. Sayeed-ur Rabb, editor of The Weekly Thikana, a Bangladeshi newspaper, who says he is a member of the real Bangladesh League of America, accepted the designation as this year's convention host. Shelley E. Mubdi, a real estate broker, who was not at the Atlanta event and says he is president of the real Bangladesh League of America, says Mr. Rabb falsely posed as a member of his group when he accepted the designation.</p>
        <p>Both events began last night. They feature Bangladeshi artists and cultural seminars and continue through the weekend.</p>
        <p>The Federal Bureau of Investigation is still looking into who sent the letters with the white powder to the Bengali-language newspapers. James Margolin, an F.B.I. spokesman, said yesterday that tests on the powder showed ''no indication of any chemical agent,'' but he would not say what the substance was.</p>
        <p>Abu Taher, executive editor of The Weekly Bangla Patrika, which received an envelope on Aug. 2 containing white powder, said that the enclosed letter began, ''Fobana Alert: Take the sweet taste of nerve gas.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rabb said yesterday that he feared the controversy surrounding the convention would keep people away from his event, at Madison Square Garden, which he initially said would draw up to 15,000 people.</p>
        <p>''They are trying to destroy us,'' he said of Mr. Mubdi's group. ''They are misleading and lying.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mubdi could not be reached yesterday, but his lawyer, Helen J. Lukievics, said Mr. Rabb and the woman he says is president of the Bangladesh League of America, Rani Kabir, were ''identity thieves'' who were trying to usurp the leadership of the organization.</p>
        <p>The Bangladesh League of America was incorporated in 1947 under the name the Pakistan League, state records indicate. Both Mr. Mubdi and Mr. Rabb are claiming they are the members of that group. But Mr. Rabb formed another organization, called the Bangladesh League of America, New York, last year after the Atlanta convention.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rabb's lawyer, Andrew Moulinos, said yesterday that the New York group was a chapter of the original group. But Mr. Mubdi contended in court papers that Mr. Rabb formed the group when Mr. Mubdi's group refused to recognize Ms. Kabir as the president of the League, and created a group with a similar name to confuse matters.</p>
        <p>After the events, the groups will return to court to resolve the question of who are the legitimate leaders of the League.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the strife has some Bangladeshi-Americans wondering if Fobana, a symbol of Bangladeshi pride and unity, is causing more harm than good.</p>
        <p>''The spirit of Fobana was to get united all the Bangladeshi living in the United States and Canada,'' said Mr. Taher, of The Weekly Bangla Patrika. ''Now it's a symbol of enmity, a symbol of division, a symbol of all the bad things.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
