<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women Trying to Be Madonnas: The Biblical Variety, That Is</title>
    <meta content="RV234750" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ontological-Hysteric Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nintzel, Ken</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pageant (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D91330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women Trying to Be Madonnas: The Biblical Variety, That Is</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Ontological Theater performance of Ken Nintzel's theater piece Pageant; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Pageant'  St. Mark's Church</p>
        <p>The images of womanly beauty that come to life in ''Pageant,'' Ken Nintzel's shrewd, silly and ravishingly detailed new theater piece for the Ontological Theater, can be seen on walls throughout the world. They are pinup girls of a less fleshly order than, say, Betty Grable. But there's no denying the pull of their feminine mystique, and their resemblance to Madonnas in the Renaissance rooms of major museums is strong enough to make you catch your breath.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Pageant'  St. Mark's Church</p>
        <p>The images of womanly beauty that come to life in ''Pageant,'' Ken Nintzel's shrewd, silly and ravishingly detailed new theater piece for the Ontological Theater, can be seen on walls throughout the world. They are pinup girls of a less fleshly order than, say, Betty Grable. But there's no denying the pull of their feminine mystique, and their resemblance to Madonnas in the Renaissance rooms of major museums is strong enough to make you catch your breath.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nintzel's bold conceit is to present three contestants vying to incarnate the single most represented female figure in Western art. In the largely wordless ''Pageant,'' which runs through this weekend, these women (played by Stacy Dawson, Jesse Hawley and Beth Kurkjian) take turns assuming poses that embody phases of the Virgin's life, from the Annunciation to the Assumption, while a slyly solemn Archangel Gabriel (Darren Anderson) acts as M.C.</p>
        <p>Set before a wall with a triptych of recessed portals, with an assortment of crude but evocative props (from plastic infants to cardboard seraphim), ''Pageant'' clearly knows its iconography. It also revels in the dismantling of it. Between ritualistic poses, the contestants are seen smoking and sipping diet soda as they are primped by stylists and hairdressers in Giotto-era clothing. There are also those moments, found in any pageant, in which things go hilariously wrong, when cues are missed and curtains jam.</p>
        <p>''Ah, to be young, gifted and impious,'' you may think. Yet the overall effect of ''Pageant,'' which features background music ranging from Mozart to Steve Reich, is neither satire nor sacrilege. Celestial camp it may be, but the show affirms that camp is often a form of worship. Mr. Nintzel's take on his subject is as passionate as it is clinical. While coolly considering the artificiality of its spiritual images, ''Pageant'' never denies their beauty.</p>
        <p>The evening occasionally loses its hypnotic hold, notably in a choreographed Pieta sequence. Ultimately, though, it registers as a funny and oddly moving reminder of the human urge to portray transcendence, to achieve the mystical through the insistently material tools to which artists are limited.</p>
        <p>BEN BRANTLEY</p>
        <p>THEATER IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
