<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Suits Filed Against Health Insurers</title>
    <meta content="Y27HEAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aetna Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cigna Healthcare</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Foundation Health Systems Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pacificare Health Systems</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Prudential Health Care Plan Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Healthcare Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freudenheim, Milt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E7DF1330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Suits Filed Against Health Insurers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MILT FREUDENHEIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freudenheim, Milt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New batch of lawsuits accuses six big managed care companies of misleading health plan members; latest court actions, filed in federal district court in Miami, accuses insurers--Aetna, Cigna, Foundation Health Systems, Pacificare Health Systems, Prudential Health Care and United Healthcare--of failing to disclose to plan members that they offered rewards to doctors and other employees who denied payments for care and who limited hospital admissions; suits also contend companies defrauded members in violation of federal anti-racketeering law, which provides for treble damages (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new batch of lawsuits accuses six big managed care companies of misleading health plan members. The suits were filed Friday in a federal district court in Miami, where a judge recently promised a speedy decision in a similar suit against Humana Inc.</p>
        <p>Like the Humana suit, the latest court actions accuse the insurers -- Aetna, Cigna, Foundation Health Systems, Pacificare Health Systems, Prudential Health Care and United Healthcare -- of failing to disclose to plan members that they offered rewards to doctors and other employees who denied payments for care and who limited hospital admissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new batch of lawsuits accuses six big managed care companies of misleading health plan members. The suits were filed Friday in a federal district court in Miami, where a judge recently promised a speedy decision in a similar suit against Humana Inc.</p>
        <p>Like the Humana suit, the latest court actions accuse the insurers -- Aetna, Cigna, Foundation Health Systems, Pacificare Health Systems, Prudential Health Care and United Healthcare -- of failing to disclose to plan members that they offered rewards to doctors and other employees who denied payments for care and who limited hospital admissions.</p>
        <p>The suits also contend that the companies defrauded members in violation of the federal anti-racketeering law, which provides for treble damages.</p>
        <p>The lawyers, who were involved in huge settlements in earlier suits against tobacco companies, said they would seek to combine dozens of suits against Humana and the six insurers in a single case.</p>
        <p>''We think it would lead to a faster resolution to have everything in one court,'' said Stephen Neuwirth, a partner of David Boies of Armonk, N.Y. Mr. Boies was recently appointed as one of two lead plaintiffs' lawyers in the Humana case. Richard F. Scruggs of Mississippi is the other lead plaintiffs' lawyer.</p>
        <p>Brian Boyle, a lawyer for Humana, said the company did not want the consolidation of the latest suits to slow down a ''fast track'' schedule that the judge had set to consider a Humana motion for dismissal. He contended that the suits were ''without legal merit'' and should be dismissed.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court recently ruled, in a unanimous decision, that an Illinois woman could not claim a breach of fiduciary duties, under a federal pension and health care law, to sue her health plan. While the high court did not address the disclosure issue, Mr. Boyle said, the decision would be ''very very helpful to defendants.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, the plaintiffs' lawyers insisted that the ruling did not apply to their suits.</p>
        <p>Foundation, a big California managed care company, ''will contest the consolidation in Florida,'' a spokesman said. Industry lawyers have contended that the companies have different products and policies and should not be lumped together.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boyle said 11 suits against Humana had been consolidated at the company's request. Judge Frederico Moreno set a July 7 deadline for Humana to submit its dismissal motion and scheduled a hearing on it for Aug. 17.</p>
        <p>If the judge lets the case proceed, the plaintiffs must file their arguments for seeking class-action status by Aug. 15 and Humana must respond by Sept. 14.</p>
        <p>Lawyers on both sides expect to add two more suits against Humana, which were filed on behalf of doctors. Archie Lamb, a plaintiffs' lawyer in Birmingham, Ala., said his group also wanted to include suits by doctors against Aetna, Cigna, Foundation, Pacificare, Prudential (now a unit of Aetna), and the Blue Cross of California unit of Wellpoint Health Networks.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the other defendants declined to comment, saying they had not seen the new suits, which became available in Miami only yesterday. Mr. Neuwirth said the Boies-Scruggs group would seek to have the cases consolidated by the multidistrict panel of federal judges in late July.</p>
        <p>James A. Lane, a managed care analyst at Salmon Smith Barney, said that 33 suits seeking class-action status had been filed against insurers between Oct. 3 and May 25. Most were filed in federal courts. None has been certified as a class action.</p>
        <p>The suits also contend that the managed care companies conspired to adopt similar operating practices at industry meetings sponsored by companies selling guidelines, by standard-setting and accrediting groups, and by trade groups.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
