<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Campaigns on Issues of a 'Different' Republican</title>
    <meta content="Y27BUS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress of Racial Equality (Core)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Immigration and Naturalization Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDA1330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Campaigns on Issues of a 'Different' Republican</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican presidential candidate Gov George W Bush campaigns in New York City, where he presents himself as 'different kind of Republican;' describes immigrant-friendly approach to bureaucratic Immigration and Naturalization Service; addresses Congress of Racial Equality, making broad appeal to black voters; will dedicate week to making appeal across party lines to groups that traditionally lean Democratic; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush continued yesterday to present himself as a ''different kind of Republican,'' describing an immigrant-friendly approach to the bureaucratic Immigration and Naturalization Service and making a broad appeal to black voters in an address in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush lauded racial harmony in a dinner speech before the Congress of Racial Equality at the Hilton Hotel in Midtown. He said he wanted to finance mentoring programs for children whose parents were in prison and to rally ''the vast armies of compassion.'' Among those on the dais were Wayne LaPierre, executive vice president of the National Rifle Association; Bob Grant, the conservative radio talk-show host; Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani; and descendants of Thomas Jefferson and his wife, Martha, and others thought to be descended from Jefferson and his slave Sally Hemings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush continued yesterday to present himself as a ''different kind of Republican,'' describing an immigrant-friendly approach to the bureaucratic Immigration and Naturalization Service and making a broad appeal to black voters in an address in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush lauded racial harmony in a dinner speech before the Congress of Racial Equality at the Hilton Hotel in Midtown. He said he wanted to finance mentoring programs for children whose parents were in prison and to rally ''the vast armies of compassion.'' Among those on the dais were Wayne LaPierre, executive vice president of the National Rifle Association; Bob Grant, the conservative radio talk-show host; Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani; and descendants of Thomas Jefferson and his wife, Martha, and others thought to be descended from Jefferson and his slave Sally Hemings.</p>
        <p>Karen P. Hughes, Mr. Bush's spokeswoman, said Mr. Bush was dedicating himself this week to making a broad appeal across party lines to groups that traditionally lean Democratic. Today he plans to discuss welfare-to-work programs in Michigan, and the next day he plans to speak in Ohio about removing barriers to those with disabilities.</p>
        <p>On immigration, the Texas governor said yesterday that he would propose legislation to split the Immigration and Naturalization Service into two agencies, one to deal with law enforcement and the other to provide services to immigrants.</p>
        <p>For years, officials across the political spectrum have supported reconstructing the unwieldy immigration service, and two bills are moving through the Republican-controlled Congress to do so.</p>
        <p>Addressing the League of United Latin American Citizens yesterday at a conference in Washington, Mr. Bush spoke in brief generalities, saying that as president he would ''reform the I.N.S.'' and that he wanted a ''more humane'' approach to immigration.</p>
        <p>His aides said later that while Mr. Bush would propose his own legislation, he favored the approach of Senator Spencer Abraham, Republican of Michigan, and Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts. Their bill is viewed by pro-immigration groups as more helpful to immigrants than the House bill proposed by Representatives Lamar Smith of Texas and Harold Rogers of Kentucky, both Republicans.</p>
        <p>The chief difference in the bills is that the Senate's, in splitting the agency, would put one person in charge to supervise both the law enforcement and service functions to make sure that they took consistent approaches.</p>
        <p>Pro-immigrant groups worry that if the agency is split, the law enforcement branch would consume most of the money and the services for immigrants would get short shrift. The enforcement side gets most of the agency's money now, but backers of the Senate bill hope that would change.</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, Mr. Bush's spokesman, said the governor was not endorsing any particular legislation but added, ''There are no differences between the governor's bill and Senator Abraham's bill.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bush's language was vague and his view seems to differ little from that of the Clinton administration, the point was to distinguish himself from the stricter Republican immigration politics of yore.</p>
        <p>''It's outreach,'' Mr. Fleischer said. ''It's the governor following through on his promise that the Republican Party has to be the party of inclusion, for single moms, for new citizens coming to America. It's different from a lot of the sights and sounds that people have been hearing from the Republican Party in recent years.''</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign has been working to change the reputation the party gained in 1994 when some prominent Republicans, including Pete Wilson, then the governor of California, backed a California ballot proposition that would deny medical and education services to children of illegal immigrants. Mr. Bush did not comment directly on the proposition, which voters overwhelmingly endorsed, saying he did not want to tell another state what to do, but he said he would educate all children.</p>
        <p>The governor also said yesterday that he would grant tourist visas to immigrants who were waiting for their visas if their spouse or child had already received permanent residency status. Now, such family members are ineligible to visit, on the theory that they would try to stay in the United States illegally.</p>
        <p>Frank Sharry, executive director of the National Immigration Forum, a Washington advocacy group for immigrants, said in an interview that Mr. Bush's proposal to split the immigration service was ''not exactly a profile in courage,'' since almost everyone supported it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharry said it was more interesting that Mr. Bush had not mentioned other issues of importance to Latino voters and especially immigrants, like the H-1B visa bill, which would increase the number of visas for high-tech workers from abroad. Mr. Bush supports increasing the number of visas, but Republicans -- and Democrats, particularly those from organized labor -- are divided over whether this is a good idea.</p>
        <p>''He didn't speak to the tough issues, though he's trying to present himself as a new kind of Republican,'' Mr. Sharry said.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore is to address the League of United Latin American Citizens on Friday. Douglas Hattaway, a Gore spokesman, said Mr. Gore wanted to streamline the immigration agency.</p>
        <p>''Bush would start from square 1,'' Mr. Hattaway said, ''and we don't think that's necessary.''</p>
        <p>Commenting more broadly on Mr. Bush's approach, Mr. Hattaway said: ''Bush is clearly trying to make himself out to be a different kind of Republican by appearing friendly to immigrants. But under his leadership in Texas, Hispanics are not doing as well as other residents.''</p>
        <p>Hispanics in Texas, he continued, were disproportionately poor, in part because Texas has a minimum wage of $3.35 per hour, compared with the federal minimum of $5.15 per hour.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
