<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warnaco Counters a Calvin Klein Lawsuit With One of Its Own</title>
    <meta content="Y27WAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210721"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jeans (Apparel)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Warnaco Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Klein, Calvin, Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Calvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6DE1330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="404" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warnaco Counters a Calvin Klein Lawsuit With One of Its Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Warnaco Group Inc answers lawsuit by Calvin Klein Inc by filing its own set of unusually personal charges against designer and his namesake company; Warnaco is seeking nearly $1 billion in damages from Calvin Klein Inc and the designer; complaints against company include defamation, breach of good faith and interference with its business practices; Warnaco is also asserting that Mr Klein was so derelict in his design duties that he hurt jeanswear business; Warnaco is suing Klein himself, claiming that he defamed company with 'malicious public statements' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Warnaco Group Inc. answered a lawsuit by Calvin Klein Inc. by filing its own set of unusually personal charges against the designer and his namesake company yesterday.</p>
        <p>Warnaco, which makes underwear and jeans under the Calvin Klein label, is seeking nearly $1 billion in damages from Calvin Klein Inc. and the designer. The complaints against the company include defamation, breach of good faith and interference with its business practices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Warnaco Group Inc. answered a lawsuit by Calvin Klein Inc. by filing its own set of unusually personal charges against the designer and his namesake company yesterday.</p>
        <p>Warnaco, which makes underwear and jeans under the Calvin Klein label, is seeking nearly $1 billion in damages from Calvin Klein Inc. and the designer. The complaints against the company include defamation, breach of good faith and interference with its business practices.</p>
        <p>Warnaco is also asserting that Mr. Klein was so derelict in his design duties that he hurt the jeanswear business. In addition, Warnaco is suing Mr. Klein himself, claiming that he defamed the company with ''malicious public statements.''</p>
        <p>In a terse statement, Linda J. Wachner, Warnaco's chief executive, said her company was forced into the suit to protect its reputation and the Klein trademarks, which are a valuable asset. ''Warnaco is acting on behalf of its shareholders to protect its business interests as well as its co-ownership of the Calvin Klein trademarks,'' she said.</p>
        <p>As of 5 p.m. yesterday, Calvin Klein said it had not seen the suit. But in response to a statement by Warnaco, the company said, ''Warnaco's announcement is a thinly veiled attempt to divert attention from the fact that Warnaco has been systematically violating its agreements with Calvin Klein Inc.''</p>
        <p>The suit and countersuit have taken on a personal tinge. Last month, Mr. Klein surprised the fashion world by seeking to end his ties to Warnaco. It is his largest licensee, providing about 40 percent of the estimated $160 million in annual design and royalty fees that make up the overwhelming bulk of Calvin Klein's revenue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein accused Warnaco and Ms. Wachner of ''diluting'' the quality of his brand by distributing merchandise in unauthorized channels like Costco and B. J.'s Wholesale Club. He also accused Ms. Wachner of being unprofessional and abusive.</p>
        <p>The timing could not have been worse for Ms. Wachner. She was already under pressure from at least one irate investor because Warnaco, which also sells apparel under names besides Calvin Klein, had repeatedly missed earnings estimates, and its stock has been in decline.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
