<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Visionary or Myth Maker: 2 Portraits of a C.E.O.</title>
    <meta content="Y27RIV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Banana Kelly</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waldman, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Yolanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3DB1330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Visionary or Myth Maker: 2 Portraits of a C.E.O.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY WALDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waldman, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses career of Yolanda Rivera, head of Banana Kelly; Rivera is seen as either visionary in regard to housing and community planning or as myth maker, who has taken credit for Banana Kelly's achievements that predate her tenure as chief executive; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An 11-year-old girl, living in a building abandoned by its landlord, growing to adulthood in a forsaken South Bronx, begins to translate for her parents and neighbors in Housing Court.</p>
        <p>That resonant image, frequently recounted, marks the beginning of Yolanda Rivera's career in housing and community development. That career has culminated with her reign as the chief executive of Banana Kelly, the South Bronx nonprofit organization that is now among the borough's dominant landlords.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An 11-year-old girl, living in a building abandoned by its landlord, growing to adulthood in a forsaken South Bronx, begins to translate for her parents and neighbors in Housing Court.</p>
        <p>That resonant image, frequently recounted, marks the beginning of Yolanda Rivera's career in housing and community development. That career has culminated with her reign as the chief executive of Banana Kelly, the South Bronx nonprofit organization that is now among the borough's dominant landlords.</p>
        <p>Her supporters say she has been a visionary, and cite glowing press coverage, like a 1997 Ms. magazine article titled ''Yolanda Rivera, Dream Maker.''</p>
        <p>Her critics say ''myth maker'' is more appropriate -- in some press coverage, they say, Ms. Rivera has taken credit for Banana Kelly achievements that predate her tenure as chief executive. And, they say, that tenure has been ruinous.</p>
        <p>Both camps agree only that she has left a very strong mark on an agency that was once the neighborhood's pride and is now a source of controversy.</p>
        <p>''Yolanda has taken the organization and made it her own,'' said Harold De Rienzo, Banana Kelly's founder.</p>
        <p>Few dispute that Ms. Rivera has charm and eloquence in abundance, although some see that as a mixed blessing. The group ''suffers from what a lot of community groups do: the strengths and weaknesses of a charismatic leader,'' said Bruce Dale, a former board member.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rivera has embraced -- and sometimes insisted that tenants and employees do the same -- a variety of psychological theories and management philosophies, the latest being a form of group therapy called ''health realization,'' which she says ''is about how we love ourselves.''</p>
        <p>A graduate of Lehman College and a former protege of the Rev. Louis Gigante, the founder of the Southeast Bronx Community Organization, she knew well the South Bronx's political landscape when she took Banana Kelly's reins in 1991.</p>
        <p>But she did not have experience running a multimillion-dollar corporation.  And in part because she had battled delinquent landlords and recalcitrant banks in the past, Ms. Rivera distrusted outsiders and professionals, Mr. Dale and others said.</p>
        <p>She also failed to cultivate potential  allies among elected officials and other community leaders.</p>
        <p>''I don't have a godfather,'' she said.</p>
        <p>That fact -- and the context of a South Bronx where community development groups have sometimes competed viciously for government spoils -- helps explain her desire for control, her defenders say. Banana Kelly was a relatively small organization sandwiched between the empires of Father Gigante and Ramon Velez, who tried to take over Banana Kelly's board in 1985.</p>
        <p>''I don't think Yolanda can trust very many people,'' Mr. Dale said.</p>
        <p>But her consolidation of control has raised concerns, not least about her remuneration. In 1995, her compensation was $76,440; by 1997, it was more than $170,000, according to the organization's tax returns. She has sometimes taken a salary, she said, and sometimes billed the agency as a consultant.</p>
        <p>Such procedures have also raised concerns about the agency's bookkeeping.  The 1998 tax return reports that Ms. Rivera earned $37,854, although she said in an interview that her salary had been consistent for several years.</p>
        <p>''It must show up somewhere else,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her control of both the board and the organization has also prompted uneasiness. In 1996, she proposed not only that her salary be raised to $100,000, but also  that Banana Kelly pay nearly $33,000 of her personal income taxes, according to a former board member. The board member said she had objected to the proposal, then received a resolution saying it had been unanimously approved. Ms. Rivera said the resolution was a mistake, but the board member resigned in protest.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rivera owns two homes in Old Saybrook, Conn., where she has lived for much of the last two decades, making use of a Banana Kelly apartment when she wanted to stay in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>For at least a year, Ms. Rivera has also been living in a house on a private road in  Riverdale, the Bronx. She described the house as an office for the River Holding Company, which she established in 1998 to do real estate development.</p>
        <p>Her critics say a comfortable life and its locus outside the South Bronx distanced her from Banana Kelly's community. It is a community she characterizes as fertile ground for rumors, lies and misunderstandings, but one she says she continues to love.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
