<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>European Official Opposes WorldCom-Sprint Merger</title>
    <meta content="Y27PHO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Worldcom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sprint Communications Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Qwest Communications International Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">US West Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Telekom</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monti, Mario</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1D61230F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>European Official Opposes WorldCom-Sprint Merger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO and DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David; Romero, Simon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mario Monti, top antitrust officer of European Commission, says he will advise commission to block WorldCom from buying Sprint unless companies significantly alter terms of deal; Qwest Communications Interational's $57 billion takeover of US West receives final federal regulatory approval; analysts say Qwest's choice to conclude deal may come at cost of potentially more lucrative link with Deutsche Telekom, Europe's largest communications concern; German company entered into, and then abruptly broke off, merger talks with Qwest earlier this year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The top antitrust officer of the European Commission said yesterday that he would advise the commission to block WorldCom from buying Sprint unless the companies significantly altered the terms of the deal.</p>
        <p>In another development in the rapidly consolidating telecommunications industry, Qwest Communications International's $57 billion takeover of U S West received final federal regulatory approval yesterday, allowing the closing of a transaction that nearly fell apart when Qwest considered dropping the deal in favor of a buyout offer from another company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The top antitrust officer of the European Commission said yesterday that he would advise the commission to block WorldCom from buying Sprint unless the companies significantly altered the terms of the deal.</p>
        <p>In another development in the rapidly consolidating telecommunications industry, Qwest Communications International's $57 billion takeover of U S West received final federal regulatory approval yesterday, allowing the closing of a transaction that nearly fell apart when Qwest considered dropping the deal in favor of a buyout offer from another company.</p>
        <p>But analysts say Qwest's choice to conclude the deal may come at the cost of a potentially more lucrative link with Deutsche Telekom, Europe's largest telecommunications concern. The German company entered into, and then abruptly broke off, merger talks with Qwest earlier this year.</p>
        <p>Apprehension over whether the Denver-based Qwest lost an opportunity has grown in recent days with signs that regulatory authorities in Europe could block WorldCom's takeover of Sprint. That could make the two companies, No. 2 and No. 3 in American long-distance, potential takeover targets for Deutsche Telekom.</p>
        <p>Europe's top antitrust officer, Mario Monti, citing his concern about the amount of Internet traffic the merged WorldCom and Sprint would carry, said yesterday that the companies would have to devise an ''exceptional'' remedy before the commission's July 12 deadline to win his approval.</p>
        <p>Executives and lawyers for WorldCom and Sprint continued to meet with officials from the Justice Department yesterday in an attempt to salvage the proposed $115 billion deal that they announced in October, according to people close to the negotiations. Among the possibilities is the sale of Sprint's long-distance and Internet businesses, leaving WorldCom with only the Sprint PCS wireless division.</p>
        <p>Justice Department officials are worried primarily about the effect the combination would have on phone rates within the United States. The Europeans, meanwhile, are concerned about the size of the companies' Internet businesses, which carry Web traffic between local phone companies and large service providers like America Online.</p>
        <p>Mr. Monti, the head of the commission's competition ministry, took a hard line yesterday, saying the companies had failed thus far to make an acceptable proposal and that the time for such plans had passed.</p>
        <p>''The deadline for remedies is over,'' he said, according to Reuters.</p>
        <p>He added that with its deadline looming, the commission would consider a new plan only under ''exceptional circumstances.'' He declined to be more specific.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for WorldCom and Sprint declined to comment. Shares of WorldCom fell 25 cents, to $37.50, while Sprint's stock was down 25 cents, to $59.5625.</p>
        <p>For Qwest, the approval from the Federal Communications Commission yesterday came after a review of the company's plan to divest itself of parts of its long-distance business in 14 states, a requirement of the Telecommunications Act of 1996. Touch America, a unit of the Montana Power Company, is buying some of Qwest's assets for $200 million.</p>
        <p>''This leaves us in the position to complete this merger,'' said Matt Barkett, a spokesman for Qwest. ''A deal with another company would have to come at another time.''</p>
        <p>The main reason a deal between Qwest and Deutsche Telekom did not materialize was because U S West was opposed to it out of concern its own takeover by Qwest would not be completed, a development that could have led to a drop in the company's share price. U S West, also based in Denver, went so far as to suggest a protracted legal battle would ensue if Qwest backed out of its intent to acquire the company.</p>
        <p>''The Germans have a hole burning in their pocket, they want to buy something so badly,'' said Scott Cleland, the managing director of the Legg Mason Precursor Group in Washington.</p>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom's intentions to create a global network are well known. In an effort to expand across the Atlantic, the company may be seeking to use its stock, which is thought to be highly valued, as a currency to acquire a large American telecommunications company.</p>
        <p>When the Qwest-U S West deal is completed, it will be the first major combination between large local and long-distance telephone companies. Shares of Qwest rose 56 cents to $52.9375, while U S West climbed $1.28, to $90.375. The prospects for Qwest remain bright to some analysts.</p>
        <p>''For Qwest, it's either acquire or get acquired after it digests U S West,'' said Andrew Hamerling, a telecommunications analyst with Banc of America Securities. ''I think Qwest is terribly attractive to any company seeking to expand.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
