<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trenton Issues Rules to Curb Use of Force By the Police</title>
    <meta content="27FORC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1DA1330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trenton Issues Rules to Curb Use of Force By the Police</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Police officers in New Jersey will be restrained from firing on moving vehicles and required to intervene before fellow officer uses force illegally under new rules issued in response to two fatal shootings of drivers by state troopers in last two years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Police officers in New Jersey will be restrained from firing on moving vehicles and required to intervene before a fellow officer uses force illegally, under new rules issued today in response to two fatal shootings of drivers by state troopers in the last two years.</p>
        <p>The revisions to the state's 15-year-old guidelines on use of force, which will apply to officers in all state and local departments, for the first time specifically address the discharging of firearms at moving vehicles, although many large police departments, like New York City's, have had similar rules for years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Police officers in New Jersey will be restrained from firing on moving vehicles and required to intervene before a fellow officer uses force illegally, under new rules issued today in response to two fatal shootings of drivers by state troopers in the last two years.</p>
        <p>The revisions to the state's 15-year-old guidelines on use of force, which will apply to officers in all state and local departments, for the first time specifically address the discharging of firearms at moving vehicles, although many large police departments, like New York City's, have had similar rules for years.</p>
        <p>Noting that ''firearms are not generally effective in bringing moving vehicles to a rapid halt,'' the new rules prohibit firing solely to disable a car or truck. And the rules bar officers from firing at a vehicle, or anyone inside, unless the officer ''reasonably believes: (1) there exists an imminent danger of death or serious bodily harm to the officer or another person; and (2) no other means are available at that time to avert or eliminate the danger.''</p>
        <p>Attorney General John J. Farmer Jr. based the revised guidelines and a new policy statement on recommendations of a 21-member advisory panel, which he convened in February after two controversial shootings. In April 1998, state troopers shot three unarmed men after stopping their van for speeding. The troopers, John Hogan and James Kenna, said the van had shifted into reverse and started backing up toward them. Last September, the troopers were indicted on attempted murder and assault charges.</p>
        <p>Last June, Stanton Crew of Morristown was killed and his passenger injured when two troopers and two municipal police officers fired 27 shots into his car after a high-speed chase on Interstate 80. Official accounts said that his car collided with a police cruiser, forcing it against an embankment, and that he tried to drive away even after being penned in by two cruisers, threatening the safety of officers approaching on foot. In December, a grand jury declined to indict any of those four officers.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for two of the victims in the 1998 shooting, David G. Ironman, said today that the new guidelines -- particularly the language forbidding firing at a vehicle unless ''no other means'' exist to avoid or eliminate the threat -- should already have been understood by police officers. ''You would presume that it would've been common sense long ago, but I guess they feel it's more important to spell it out now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The new rules state that firing at or from a moving vehicle entails a greater risk to innocent people, both to those on the street jeopardized when a fleeing suspect is shot and loses control of his or her vehicle, and those inside a suspect's vehicle but not involved in the acts which prompted the use of force.</p>
        <p>Paul H. Zoubek, first assistant attorney general, said New York City officers were barred from shooting at a moving vehicle unless someone inside it was shooting at them. ''We chose to go with the 'imminent danger' standard after an examination of incidents in New Jersey,'' he said, citing incidents in which officers were dragged from motor vehicles.</p>
        <p>The new use-of-force policy mandates that officers intervene where possible to prevent other officers from using force illegally, and failing that, to report such incidents to the authorities. ''Officers are encouraged to do whatever they can to interrupt the flow of events before a fellow officer does something illegal and before any official action is necessary,'' the policy states.</p>
        <p>Under the new rules, officers will be required to undergo training twice a year in the use of force, and to file reports with the county prosecutor when using any kind of force or firing a gun causes injury or death.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
