<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>17 Percent Increase in Prescription Drug Costs Hit Elderly Hardest, Study Finds</title>
    <meta content="Y27DRU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Express Scripts Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E0DA1330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>17 Percent Increase in Prescription Drug Costs Hit Elderly Hardest, Study Finds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study released by Express Scripts of St Louis, drug benefits company, finds spending on prescription drugs increased record 17.4 percent in 1999 and that elderly people experienced largest cost increases; its findings detailed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spending on prescription drugs increased a record 17.4 percent last year, and elderly people experienced the largest cost increases, a new study by a drug benefits company said.</p>
        <p>The study, released today by Express Scripts of St. Louis, said about half of the total increase in drug spending was a result of higher costs for a typical prescription.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Spending on prescription drugs increased a record 17.4 percent last year, and elderly people experienced the largest cost increases, a new study by a drug benefits company said.</p>
        <p>The study, released today by Express Scripts of St. Louis, said about half of the total increase in drug spending was a result of higher costs for a typical prescription.</p>
        <p>Greater use of prescription drugs and the introduction of new products were responsible for the rest of the increase, the study said.</p>
        <p>Express Scripts manages drug benefits for 38.5 million people. The study is based on the experiences of 9.6 million people around the nation with commercial insurance -- workers, retirees and dependents, chosen to be representative of the larger group.</p>
        <p>Barrett Toan, president of Express Scripts, said last year's increase accelerated a trend observed since 1993, when the company began monitoring changes in drug spending.</p>
        <p>New drugs were a significant factor contributing to the increase in spending last year, as doctors and patients quickly accepted two drugs used to treat arthritis, Vioxx, made by Merck &amp; Company, and Celebrex, marketed by Searle and Pfizer, the study said.</p>
        <p>More generally, it said, drugs introduced since 1992 accounted for a remarkable 41 percent of drug spending last year and for 25 percent of all prescriptions filled last year.</p>
        <p>The study comes just two days before the House is expected to vote on proposals to provide prescription drug coverage to Medicare beneficiaries. One-third of the 39 million Medicare beneficiaries have no insurance to help pay drug costs.</p>
        <p>Statistics compiled by Express Scripts show why elderly people feel a pressing need for such coverage and why many members of Congress worry about the costs.</p>
        <p>Spending on prescription drugs averaged $387.09 a person last year, up 17.4 percent from the average of $329.83 in 1998, Express Scripts reported.</p>
        <p>But costs rose most rapidly for older Americans, it said.</p>
        <p>The average price for a prescription last year rose 18 percent for women age 70 to 79, 20 percent for women 80 and older, 9 percent for men age 70 to 79 and 11 percent for men 80 and older, the study said.</p>
        <p>The report said that Enbrel, a new drug for rheumatoid arthritis, contributed more to the increase in drug spending last year than more celebrated drugs like Viagra. Enbrel, produced by genetic engineering, may cost $1,000 a month.</p>
        <p>In its report, Express Scripts made these observations:</p>
        <p>*The number of prescriptions for antihistamines increased 18.4 percent last year. In 1999, as in the two previous years, use of antihistamines increased more than the use of any other type of drug. The increase was driven by heavy advertising for products like Claritin, Allegra and Zyrtec.</p>
        <p>*Cholesterol-lowering drugs were the second-fastest growing category last year, as the number of prescriptions increased 18.1 percent. Lipitor, made by Warner-Lambert, and Zocor, made by Merck, accounted for much of the growth.</p>
        <p>*Use of antidepressant drugs increased 11.3 percent last year. As the stigma of mental illness is reduced and more people become aware of the symptoms of depression, they are more likely to receive drug therapy.</p>
        <p>*Use of gastrointestinal drugs increased nearly 10 percent last year, in part because of advertising for products like Prilosec.</p>
        <p>Express Scripts said that prescription drug prices rose substantially more last year than the prices of other major goods and services like food, housing and transportation.</p>
        <p>The prices of generic drugs rose an average of 7 percent last year, while prices of brand-name medications rose an average of 5.8 percent, the report said. Generic versions of brand-name drugs typically cost less, but federal officials say they are therapeutically equivalent.</p>
        <p>Among the drugs with the largest price increases last year were thyroid medications, narcotic painkillers and estrogen replacement products.</p>
        <p>Synthroid, a synthetic thyroid hormone sold by the Knoll Pharmaceutical Company, accounted for much of the increase in thyroid drug costs, while Premarin, made by Wyeth-Ayerst Laboratories to treat symptoms of menopause and osteoporosis, accounted for much of the increase in estrogen therapy prices, the report said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
