<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reds Power Way Past Cardinals</title>
    <meta content="27NAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NATIONAL LEAGUE: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cincinnati Reds</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Rams</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cincinnati Reds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/St. Louis Rams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE4D81330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reds Power Way Past Cardinals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cincinnati Reds defeat St Louis Cardinals, 3-2; other National League results noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Reds got homers from Ken Griffey Jr. and Dmitri Young last night in a 3-2 victory over St. Louis in the opener of their series in Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>The Reds won for only the fifth time in 19 games, moving seven and one-half games behind the Cardinals in the National League Central. The division's top two teams play a total of seven times in 11 days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Reds got homers from Ken Griffey Jr. and Dmitri Young last night in a 3-2 victory over St. Louis in the opener of their series in Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>The Reds won for only the fifth time in 19 games, moving seven and one-half games behind the Cardinals in the National League Central. The division's top two teams play a total of seven times in 11 days.</p>
        <p>Griffey got the crowd of 32,850 revved by hitting a two-run homer in the first off Garrett Stephenson (9-4). Young added a two-out homer to right field in the fifth that stayed fair by a few feet and snapped a 2-all tie.</p>
        <p>Stephenson is 1-4 in June, with the Cardinals scoring a total of 10 runs in his five starts.</p>
        <p>Griffey's 23rd homer extended his hitting streak to 10 games and left him fourth in the league in homers. He has homered five times during the 10-game streak.</p>
        <p>Denny Neagle (6-2) held Mark McGwire down to a single and two strikeouts in his first three at-bats. McGwire, who is 3 for 18 career against the left-hander with nine strikeouts, was still shaking his head when he reached the bat rack after fanning in the fourth.</p>
        <p>McGwire's seventh-inning single to left over the Reds' infield shift extended his hitting streak to 10 games.</p>
        <p>Neagle gave up seven hits in seven and two-thirds innings, including Eric Davis's two-run homer that tied the game in the fourth.</p>
        <p>It was Davis's first homer since his grand slam off Neagle on May 7.</p>
        <p>PADRES 9, DODGERS 5: Bret Boone hit a two-run homer and doubled in three more runs during an eight-run second inning against Orel Hershiser as San Diego won in Los Angeles, extending the Dodgers' losing streak to five games.</p>
        <p>The Padres rocked Hershiser (1-5) for eight runs on six hits and three walks in just one and two-thirds innings. The 41-year-old right-hander was starting on one day's rest, having thrown 27 pitches during a rain-delayed one and one-third innings of a 6-1 loss Saturday at St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Brian Meadows (6-5) allowed six hits in seven and two-thirds innings. He walked three and struck out five.</p>
        <p>DIAMONDBACKS 6, ASTROS 1: In his first major league at-bat, Alex Cabrera hit a two-run home run in host Arizona's victory.</p>
        <p>And one day after being recalled from Class AAA Tucson to replace the injured Matt Williams, Danny Klassen had a home run and a run-scoring single for Arizona.</p>
        <p>Cabrera, a 28-year-old first baseman was called up Monday to take the roster spot of the injured right-hander Todd Stottlemyre.</p>
        <p>Armando Reynoso (5-6) allowed five hits in seven innings for the Diamondbacks. Octavio Dotel (1-5) was the loser despite striking out a career-high 13 batters in six innings for the Astros.</p>
        <p>GWYNN TO HAVE SURGERY: Tired of being reduced to a part-time player, Tony Gwynn will undergo arthroscopic surgery on his troublesome left knee today.</p>
        <p>Gwynn, a Padres outfielder, is hoping that doctors will only have to clean out the joint, which has little cartilage left in it from five previous operations. In a best-case scenario, the 40-year-old Gwynn figures he will miss four to six weeks.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jan Fronek will perform the surgery with Dr. Steven Copp at Green Hospital Scripps Clinic in La Jolla, Calif. If doctors find more serious damage or decide to perform a procedure to get new cartilage to grow, Gwynn may miss the rest of the season.</p>
        <p>Gwynn has been bothered by inflammation in the knee off and on this season, and he has had to have it drained seven times since spring training. When he was on the disabled list earlier this season, he had injections of a substance that stimulates bodily fluid to lubricate the joint.</p>
        <p>''I do feel that this is the best thing to do,'' Gwynn said. ''I've done everything else they've asked me do. I took the injections, I played every other day, I've iced it for 15 to 16 hours a day. I've got to do what I want to do, and I want to continue to play. To me, this is my best option. I hate to sit on the bench.''</p>
        <p>Gwynn did not start the last eight games, but he did make two pinch-hitting appearances. He was placed on the 15-day disabled list yesterday.</p>
        <p>An eight-time National League batting champion, Gwynn has 3,108 hits in his 19-year career. He is hitting .323 with 12 doubles, 1 homer and 17 runs batted in this season.</p>
        <p>The Padres also put the right-handed starter Stan Spencer on the disabled list yesterday because of a strained right elbow, which is expected to keep him out for four to six weeks.</p>
        <p>Spencer was 2-2 with a 3.26 earned run average in eight starts since his promotion from Class AAA Las Vegas on May 12.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL LEAGUE: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
