<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bold Warrior Soars Over a Romantic Triangle</title>
    <meta content="27BAYA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Ballet Theater</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DA1230F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bold Warrior Soars Over a Romantic Triangle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews American Ballet Theater's production of La Bayadere, performed by two different casts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''La Bayadere'' has it all: love, longing and lust, intrigues and betrayals, earthly cataclysms and heavenly redemptions. It also has many sequences of sumptuous dancing, including one of the most beautiful episodes ever created for an ensemble. No wonder the ballet has delighted audiences ever since Marius Petipa choreographed it in 1877. It continued to work its wonders when American Ballet Theater presented it at weekend performances at the Metropolitan Opera House.</p>
        <p>Natalia Makarova's production, based on Petipa, pays serious attention to the plot concerning a romantic triangle involving Solor, a handsome warrior; Nikiya, the Indian temple dancer he loves, and Gamzatti, the Rajah's daughter he is expected to marry for reasons of state. The dramatic action, though extravagant, is never merely silly. And fine dancers made the ballet exciting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''La Bayadere'' has it all: love, longing and lust, intrigues and betrayals, earthly cataclysms and heavenly redemptions. It also has many sequences of sumptuous dancing, including one of the most beautiful episodes ever created for an ensemble. No wonder the ballet has delighted audiences ever since Marius Petipa choreographed it in 1877. It continued to work its wonders when American Ballet Theater presented it at weekend performances at the Metropolitan Opera House.</p>
        <p>Natalia Makarova's production, based on Petipa, pays serious attention to the plot concerning a romantic triangle involving Solor, a handsome warrior; Nikiya, the Indian temple dancer he loves, and Gamzatti, the Rajah's daughter he is expected to marry for reasons of state. The dramatic action, though extravagant, is never merely silly. And fine dancers made the ballet exciting.</p>
        <p>There was a passionate ''Bayadere'' on Saturday afternoon. Julio Bocca was a bold warrior whose dramatic gestures were grandly scaled and, soaring with energy, he conquered the air in his solo passages. Julie Kent danced Nikiya with a lovely sense of freedom in her upper body, and she let her arm movements sweep smoothly through space. Sandra Brown made Gamzatti's steps and gestures sharp, and when she faced Nikiya in a dramatic confrontation, it was like a meeting of tigers.</p>
        <p>On Friday night another cast offered a different yet equally valid interpretation. Susan Jaffe and Vladimir Malakhov moved with great fastidiousness as Nikiya and Solor. Their delicacy and refinement proved especially convincing in the otherworldly Kingdom of the Shades scene. In the earthly scenes, they sometimes seemed emotionally remote. But Irina Dvorovenko was a haughty Gamzatti.</p>
        <p>At both performances the ensemble (led by Yan Chen, Gillian Murphy and Michele Wiles on Friday and Oksana Konobeyeva, Ekaterina Shelkanova and Ms. Wiles on Saturday) displayed an exquisite unanimity in the demanding and justifiably celebrated Kingdom of the Shades scene. These specters moved and stood still as if they formed a single collective being.</p>
        <p>There were also admirable characterizations of secondary roles. The virtuosic solo for the Bronze Idol was danced with a sense of mounting intensity by Herman Cornejo on Saturday. On Friday Joaquin De Luz emphasized the angularity of the movements, so that this idol did come to resemble a magically animated sculpture.</p>
        <p>Victor Barbee was a High Brahmin with a commanding presence on Friday. On Saturday Robert Hill turned the character into a pinched ascetic; in another country and century, this Brahmin might have served as an Inquisitor. Vladislav Kalinin on Friday and Gennadi Saveliev on Saturday looked equally grotesque as the capering Head Fakir. Ethan Brown was a suave Radjah on both occasions.</p>
        <p>Ermanno Florio conducted Ludwig Minkus's tuneful and dramatically supportive score at both performances.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
