<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First Union To Shut Down Money Store</title>
    <meta content="Y27BAN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">First Union Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Money Store Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E3DC1330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First Union To Shut Down Money Store</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First Union Corp says it will close Money Store lending operation, get out of some businesses and scale back others; banks says overhaul will reduce earnings by $2.8 billion, most of it stemming from decision to immediately shut down Money Store; about 2,350 Money Store employees will lose their jobs, including about 360 in New Jersey, where operation was founded (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Abandoning its longtime strategy of growing by gobbling up banks and financial companies, the First Union Corporation said yesterday that it would close the Money Store lending operation, get out of some businesses and scale back others.</p>
        <p>The bank said the overhaul would reduce earnings by $2.8 billion, most of it stemming from the decision to immediately shut down the Money Store, a second-mortgage lender pitched relentlessly in television ads by the retired baseball players Phil Rizzuto and Jim Palmer. About 2,350 Money Store employees will lose their jobs, including about 360 in New Jersey, where the operation was founded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Abandoning its longtime strategy of growing by gobbling up banks and financial companies, the First Union Corporation said yesterday that it would close the Money Store lending operation, get out of some businesses and scale back others.</p>
        <p>The bank said the overhaul would reduce earnings by $2.8 billion, most of it stemming from the decision to immediately shut down the Money Store, a second-mortgage lender pitched relentlessly in television ads by the retired baseball players Phil Rizzuto and Jim Palmer. About 2,350 Money Store employees will lose their jobs, including about 360 in New Jersey, where the operation was founded.</p>
        <p>First Union, the sixth-biggest bank in the country, bought the Money Store for $2.1 billion two years ago in one of the last big purchases in a long string of deals engineered by its former chief executive, Edward Crutchfield. Now, Mr. Crutchfield's successor, G. Kennedy Thompson, is repudiating much of that growth strategy by shrinking the company, which is based in Charlotte, N.C., to focus on its core businesses of banking and brokerage.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day, we're saying we made a bad acquisition,'' Mr. Thompson said, referring to the Money Store. He said First Union was unlikely to buy any more banks and had no plans for any significant acquisitions any time soon.</p>
        <p>The cost of making that reversal is high. First Union said it would take charges against earnings and reserves for future losses that would total about $3.8 billion. The savings from the changes should add back about $1 billion, for a net reduction in earnings of $2.8 billion over the next few quarters, Mr. Thompson said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson surprised analysts by projecting that First Union would earn 72 to 74 cents a share in the second quarter, before restructuring charges of at least $3 a share. The consensus estimate of analysts had been 85 cents a share before the announcement, according to First Call/Thomson Financial.</p>
        <p>First Union's shares gained 6.25 cents yesterday, to $27.875, as some investors expressed relief that the bank's new management was taking the painful steps to refocus on its core businesses. The stock had dropped more than 27 percent in the last three weeks as fears of bad news spread among investors when the bank stopped talking about its earnings prospects.</p>
        <p>Sandra Flannigan, an analyst at Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, reduced her near-term rating on First Union's stock but kept her long-term buy rating on it. ''This restructuring is really a move by the new management team to put the missteps of the past behind,'' Ms. Flannigan said. ''We're going to see a great deal more focus, accountability and financial discipline.''</p>
        <p>Among the changes First Union plans are the sale of its mortgage-processing operation to Wells Fargo, the sale of its credit card business and the cleansing of its loan portfolio by selling $500 million of nonperforming loans. First Union also plans to sell or close about 90 bank branches, mostly in the Southeast and mid-Atlantic states.</p>
        <p>First Union is closing all 38 of the remaining branches of Money Store, 12 of which are in New Jersey and New York. Money Store also has processing operations in the New Jersey towns of Warren and Pennington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson said First Union would set aside $620 million to ''immunize ourselves against further losses'' from Money Store's $12 billion loan portfolio. But he said he did not suspect fraud in the representations that were made by Money Store at the time of the sale, nor did he blame the investment bankers from Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Company, who received an undisclosed fee from First Union for performing due diligence on the deal.</p>
        <p>Money Store's advertising-driven lending business had been quite profitable for the Turtletaub family that ran it until First Union bought it. But in the late 1990's, as other lenders began competing for so-called subprime borrowers, Money Store's customers started repaying their loans early by refinancing them elsewhere. Early repayment is the bane of lenders like Money Store because it decreases the value of a loan that the lender, in turn, has borrowed against to raise money to make more loans.</p>
        <p>The subprime lending business has been through a classic boom-and-bust cycle on Wall Street in the last several years. After flourishing for a few years, high-risk consumer lending crashed, sending some lenders into bankruptcy and others into the arms of acquirers.</p>
        <p>''Subprime lending has come full circle,'' said Marni Pont O'Doherty, an analyst with Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods. ''A couple of years ago, Wall Street was falling all over itself to underwrite these things.''</p>
        <p>Conseco, a big insurance company, is trying to sell Green Tree Financial after Green Tree, which specializes in mobile-home loans, caused huge losses at Conseco. With Green Tree already on the auction block, First Union recognized that it would have had trouble finding a buyer for the Money Store and chose to cut its losses, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Doherty noted that Conseco's purchase of Green Tree closed on June 30, 1998, the day First Union purchased Money Store.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
