<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="27PUBL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210714"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Newark Museum (NJ)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alliance Capital Management</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mercado, Jose</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Samuel C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Rosetta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DF1330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column; photographer Jose Mercado discusses taking photographs at melee in Central Park; Alliance Capital Management to be corporate sponsor of Military Salute Week; Newark Museum Director Samuel C Miller hosts lunch for his wife Rosetta; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a Wrong Place At the Right Time</p>
        <p>The credit line in Time magazine looked like one for a professional photographer: ''Jose Mercado -- Corbis Sygma.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a Wrong Place At the Right Time</p>
        <p>The credit line in Time magazine looked like one for a professional photographer: ''Jose Mercado -- Corbis Sygma.''</p>
        <p>But the photographs were of the rampage in Central Park that followed the National Puerto Rican Day parade. Similar images showing potential suspects had appeared in newspapers in New York. They were taken by an amateur with a video camera. An amateur who now has an agent, the Corbis Sygma agency.</p>
        <p>''They contacted me'' about selling images from the videotape to newspapers and magazines, Mr. Mercado said yesterday. He said he did not know how much he might make from his deal with Corbis Sygma, which represents photographers around the world. Sygma told him his earnings ''would be in the thousands,'' he said. ''I get a 60 percent cut off of whatever they sell it for.'' (PETER BOLIOLI, the news editor at Corbis Sygma, declined to discuss the financial arrangements.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Mercado, who is 24 and works in the stockroom of the Barnes &amp; Noble store at Third Avenue and 47th Street, said he had taken his camera along because the friend who had gone with him to past Puerto Rican Day parades was in Texas this year.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Maybe I could record some footage for you,' '' Mr. Mercado said. ''I was planning to surprise him with some footage of the parade. It was kind of hard to believe this was happening in front of your eyes. The first thought was, 'Keep rolling, I'm getting some good stuff here.' It doesn't happen very often that you happen to be in front of something that's so crazy. I just decided, shoot it before I lose the opportunity.''</p>
        <p>Flying Toward A Moving Target</p>
        <p>DAVE H. WILLIAMS'S company, Alliance Capital Management, is the main corporate sponsor of Military Salute Week 2000, which used to be called Fleet Week. Alliance gave about $500,000 to nonprofit military support groups in connection with Military Salute Week. So when the Navy offered to let Mr. Williams fly in a Navy jet that would land on an aircraft carrier, he did not hesitate. He said yes.</p>
        <p>His wife, REBA WHITE WILLIAMS, went along for love, not frequent-flyer miles. ''He had to talk me into it,'' said Mrs. Williams, who resigned as chairwoman of the city's Art Commission last year and sued Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani during a feud over flagpoles in city parks. ''Not much makes me afraid,'' she said of the landing. ''This did.''</p>
        <p>But the weekend flight from Norfolk, Va., to the aircraft carrier Harry S. Truman in the Atlantic went as smoothly as such things can go. The best part, to hear Mrs. Williams tell it, was that the Harry S. Truman turned out to be larger than she had expected.</p>
        <p>''I'm sort of hung up on World War II movies'' with aircraft carriers that had improbably small flight decks,'' she said. ''This thing was unbelievably big. It's 4.5 acres. The number of people on it was something like 5,000. The town I grew up in, Lillington, N.C., only had about 1,000.''</p>
        <p>Ladies Who Lunch</p>
        <p>SAMUEL C. MILLER, the former director of the Newark Museum, had lunch yesterday with his wife, ROSETTA, and 15 of her friends -- all women. ''This is the first time I've ever hosted a ladies' lunch,'' Mr. Miller said.</p>
        <p>The next thing he said underscored that fact.</p>
        <p>''It was my idea to have corsages for the ladies,'' he said. ''But at the florist I forgot to inspect them, and I see there are no pins, so I guess you'll have to carry them or put them in the bodice.''</p>
        <p>Before dessert someone started handing over presents for Mrs. Miller to open. Mr. Miller handed her a box, saying, ''I want everybody to see this, before they start drifting out.''</p>
        <p>Someone asked if he had bought it on a recent European trip.</p>
        <p>He said he had.</p>
        <p>''I didn't exactly smuggle it,'' he explained. ''You know that box on the customs form where you can check off a gift worth under $250?'' Women around him nodded knowingly. ''I always start looking guilty over Greenland.'' (The present turned out to be a necklace, bracelet and ring.)</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
