<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From the President's Statement on the Budget Surplus</title>
    <meta content="Y27BTE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDA1330F934A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From the President's Statement on the Budget Surplus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Pres Clinton's news conference, where he raised projection of budget surplus by nearly $1.3 trillion for next decade (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from President Clinton's news conference today on the South Lawn of the White House about revised figures for the nation's budget surplus, as recorded by the Federal News Service, a private transcription agency:</p>
        <p>In 1993 when I became president, the federal budget deficit was $290 billion. It was projected to rise to $455 billion this year. The American people wanted a better future, and we offered a new economic course of fiscal discipline, expanded trade, and greater investment in our people and our future. The result has been the longest economic expansion in history, a fiscal turnaround that is stronger, frankly, than any of us had imagined.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from President Clinton's news conference today on the South Lawn of the White House about revised figures for the nation's budget surplus, as recorded by the Federal News Service, a private transcription agency:</p>
        <p>In 1993 when I became president, the federal budget deficit was $290 billion. It was projected to rise to $455 billion this year. The American people wanted a better future, and we offered a new economic course of fiscal discipline, expanded trade, and greater investment in our people and our future. The result has been the longest economic expansion in history, a fiscal turnaround that is stronger, frankly, than any of us had imagined.</p>
        <p>In fact, in each year since 1993, both economic growth and federal revenues have surpassed our forecasts, and this year is no exception. Today, as required by law, I am releasing the mid-session review of the budget. It shows that our overall budget surplus this year will be $211 billion, more than a $700 billion improvement over where we projected to be in 1993. And we're forecasting a surplus for the next 10 years that is over $1 trillion larger than was forecast just four months ago.</p>
        <p>The American people should be very proud of this news. It's the result of their hard work and their support for fiscal discipline. It's proof that we can create a better future for ourselves when we put our minds to it. And it provides a tremendous new opportunity to build an even brighter future if we sustain our prosperity by maintaining our fiscal discipline.</p>
        <p>These new surpluses put us in a position to achieve something that would have seemed unimaginable in 1993. As this chart shows, we can now pay down the debt completely by 2012, a year earlier than we projected just four months ago. . . .</p>
        <p>Now, why should we do this? Because by paying down the debt, we can keep interest rates lower and free up more capital for private-sector investment, creating more jobs and economic growth for years and years to come.</p>
        <p>We can eliminate the burden of paying interest on the debt, which today takes up 12 cents of every federal tax dollar. We can use part of this savings, as I have suggested, to extend the solvency of Social Security to 2057 and of Medicare to 2030.</p>
        <p>Now, think about what this means. A 6-year-old today -- we may have some out here -- is living in an America that is $3.5 trillion in debt. If we follow the course I am laying out, we can eliminate that debt by the time the child enters college. The economy will be stronger, his parents' incomes will be greater, the interest rates on college loans will be lower. And 12 years from now, people of my generation will be entering retirement, knowing that Social Security and Medicare will be there for them.</p>
        <p>Quite simply, an economic plan that invests in our people and pays down the debt is the wisest choice we can make to honor our values and ensure a better future for our children.</p>
        <p>To that end, I propose that we follow Vice President Gore's recommendation and lock away that portion of the surplus that comes from the Medicare taxes people pay. Medicare payroll taxes should not be used to finance tax cuts or other spending. They should be saved for Medicare and Medicare alone. There is already broad bipartisan support for saving the Social Security surplus for debt reduction. It's time to do the same for Medicare, by taking Medicare off budget.</p>
        <p>By protecting both Social Security and Medicare surpluses, we can lock in $2.7 trillion of debt reduction in just the next 10 years, enabling us to get the debt entirely gone by 2012. Before we make any other major budget decisions this year, I ask Congress to come together across party lines to protect the Medicare surplus.</p>
        <p>Now, a lot of people are saying that because this is an election year, Congress won't get much done. It does not have to be that way. Today, I called House Speaker Hastert and Senator Lott with a proposal to break the logjam and do what we all say we want to do.</p>
        <p>We all say we want to provide prescription drug coverage to the millions of senior and disabled Americans on Medicare who currently lack it. I have presented my plan; the Republicans have presented theirs.</p>
        <p>We all say we want to end the marriage penalty. I have presented my plan; the Republicans have presented theirs. I believe their marriage penalty, standing on its own and not part of an overall commitment to fiscal discipline and also tilting, I believe, too much toward upper-income Americans, is too big and not targeted toward those who need it most.</p>
        <p>But if we can all agree to take Medicare off budget and not use Medicare money for tax cuts or for other spending, then I have told the Republican leaders I would like to make a simple offer. If Congress will pass a plan that gives real voluntary Medicare prescription drug coverage, available and affordable to all seniors and consistent with the principles of my plan, costing roughly $250 billion over 10 years, then I will sign a marriage penalty relief law which also costs roughly $250 billion over 10 years.</p>
        <p>This is a proposal for a true compromise. It asks each party to accept some of the positions of the other party in the name of progress. By adopting the vice president's plan to save the Medicare surplus, we will achieve the most significant strengthening of Medicare since the proposal was created in 1965 and deliver the largest tax relief to families in decades. These are goals that both parties and all Americans agree on.</p>
        <p>It would be wrong to let politics keep us from seizing the opportunity . . . We can take these actions and still have, according to our new budget projections, substantial resources left over for future budget priorities.</p>
        <p>Now, I want to remind the people, however, that this is just a budget projection. It would not be prudent to commit every penny of a future surplus that is just a projection and therefore subject to change. Fiscal discipline helped to create these surpluses; fiscal discipline is what we should continue as we determine how best to use them.</p>
        <p>In my mid-session review, therefore, I propose to set aside a $500 billion reserve for America's future, a fund that could eventually be used for any number of key priorities, from retirement savings, to tax cuts, to investments in education, research, health care and environmental protection, to further debt reduction. We should set aside this reserve fund.</p>
        <p>At this late date in the fiscal year, with elections looming, it would unrealistic and imprudent for those of us in Washington to decide what to do with this money. That's something that should be debated in the coming months and decided on by the American people this fall. Our obligation is to move forward on those issues that have been fully debated, where there is bipartisan agreement for action.</p>
        <p>So this summer, let's set aside the Medicare surpluses and pay down the debt. Let's pass a voluntary prescription drug benefit for seniors and disabled Americans on Medicare, and marriage penalty tax relief for American families.</p>
        <p>When that's done, I hope we will also raise the minimum wage, pass a strong, enforceable patients' bill of rights, pass a juvenile justice bill that closes the gun-show loophole, hate crimes legislation and the new markets legislation, and make key investments in education, health care and the environment.</p>
        <p>Then, in the election, let's have a vigorous debate about how the remainder of these new surpluses can best be used to advance our nation. It's the right debate to have, and I think we can all agree that it's a debate we are very fortunate to be able to have.</p>
        <p>How we use these surpluses in this moment of prosperity will determine America's future for decades to come. Nothing will more surely determine it than making the right choices, if we do the right things to keep our prosperity going, to extend its benefits to people and places not yet fully part of it, to help Americans balance the demands of work and family, to seize the remarkable potential and meet the challenges of globalization and the revolutions of science and information technology.</p>
        <p>This is a good day for America. We ought to preserve it for the future and make the most of the moment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
