<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid the Isolation, Finally, a Friend; A Movement to Confront Hidden Abuse in Immigrant Families</title>
    <meta content="16ASIA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/nyregion/16ASIA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E3D91E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid the Isolation, Finally, a Friend; A Movement to Confront Hidden Abuse in Immigrant Families</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>She arrived in New York less than four years ago, a bride from India hoping for a good life with a man who bragged of being a millionaire. The reality broke her heart and nearly cost her life.</p>
        <p>Pervinder Kaur, the hopeful bride, knew very little English and less about America. Alone and vulnerable, she saw herself turned into a prisoner of her in-laws' home, forbidden to make friends outside the family. Her husband tried to force her to turn over money, then beat her, she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>She arrived in New York less than four years ago, a bride from India hoping for a good life with a man who bragged of being a millionaire. The reality broke her heart and nearly cost her life.</p>
        <p>Pervinder Kaur, the hopeful bride, knew very little English and less about America. Alone and vulnerable, she saw herself turned into a prisoner of her in-laws' home, forbidden to make friends outside the family. Her husband tried to force her to turn over money, then beat her, she said.</p>
        <p>But two phone calls set her free. Finally, she called the police, who got an ambulance and sent her to a hospital. Later, she called Sakhi.</p>
        <p>''Sakhi is my family now,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Sakhi -- the name means ''female friend'' in Hindi -- is a still-struggling, 10-year-old support group based in Manhattan and run by South Asian women to help other women from India, Bangladesh, Pakistan, Nepal and Indians in the Caribbean. It is part of a growing movement led by young South Asian-Americans who want to confront social issues that have often been taboo in their homes and neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Sakhi teaches women about their rights and how to exercise them in the United States. Among its services, the group helps women find places to live. It also offers language assistance and legal advice in court cases and dealings with city services. Sakhi volunteers, some of whom are lawyers, sometimes accompany women to the courts, or to interviews with the police or other city agencies.</p>
        <p>Similar organizations have formed in recent years in Connecticut, Pennsylvania, Illinois, Texas, California and Washington State. They all offer not just help, but also the comfort of a familiar culture in an alien world.</p>
        <p>''They spoke so nicely to me,'' Ms. Kaur said in a soft voice, remembering her first contact with Sakhi volunteers. ''They talked in my language. Until then, I could not talk about it, what had happened. I always started to cry.''</p>
        <p>Now, there is a chronicler for the work of these organizations and the issues they confront. Margaret Abraham -- born in India, a Ph.D. from Syracuse, head of the sociology department at Hofstra University -- could be just one more story drawn from the most successful new immigrant group in the United States.</p>
        <p>Statistically, Indians have the best educations and earn the most money among new Americans. They enjoy an annual wage almost double the national average, and wield buying power of as much as $20 billion each year, according to the news magazine India Today.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Abraham was troubled by something not readily discussed among South Asians here, the domestic violence that arrived in the social baggage of migrants from the Indian subcontinent. She began to wrestle intellectually with what she called ''the myth of the model minority.''</p>
        <p>''Any strong community is one that celebrates and takes pride in its achievements, but also acknowledges and takes action against its social problems,'' she said. ''That makes for a stronger community.''</p>
        <p>In most of South Asia, the status of women, Hindu and Muslim, is measurably the lowest in the world. Women like Ms. Kaur often arrive in New York as brides in arranged marriages, strangers to American life and to the men they marry.</p>
        <p>Thousands of miles from home and family, they are easily victimized. Fearful of summary deportation and unable to make themselves understood to the police and the courts, where they sometimes meet derision if not hostility, they endure abuse in silence. Some die.</p>
        <p>As a sociologist, Dr. Abraham said, she saw abuse compounded by the failure of social and legal services to deal effectively with poor, often illiterate, non-English-speaking victims of any ethnic group. With the encouragement of Hofstra, she set out to document the phenomenon of violence in South Asian families. This year, her book, ''Speaking the Unspeakable: Marital Violence Among South Asian Immigrants in the United States,'' was published by Rutgers University Press.</p>
        <p>Dr. Abraham's book, which not only tells a series of tragic stories but also looks at ways women fight back, reinforces the experiences of Sakhi volunteers.</p>
        <p>They have seen women in New York who have been psychologically wounded, physically battered, beaten and burned. In India, by its government's own figures, at least 6,000 brides are burned to death every year because the dowry they bring to a marriage is deemed too small -- or because a husband decides he does not really like the woman selected for him by his parents.</p>
        <p>Megha Bhouraskar, legal counsel to Sakhi, said the organization grew out of a demonstrable need. ''Existing organizations were calling individuals, saying, 'We have such-and-such person in our office,' and there were language issues or cultural issues -- a communications problem.'' Volunteers were found to help.</p>
        <p>''At that point, none of us had this expertise,'' Ms. Bhouraskar said. ''Some of the situations involved women we knew personally, and we would have never known that they were in this situation except that we got a call.''</p>
        <p>Courts and welfare organizations frequently do not understand the dynamics of an extended South Asian family, where an abused woman may need a restraining order not only against her husband but also against her in-laws, said Prema Vora, who was Sakhi's executive director until last month.</p>
        <p>It is hard to quantify domestic violence among South Asians in New York, said Dr. Abraham, because the work of Sakhi and other organizations is relatively new and Indian immigrants have been reluctant to explore the issue.</p>
        <p>With the help of research from Columbia University's Social Intervention Group, Sakhi has begun to develop a local database. The organization gets 15 to 30 new calls for help each month.</p>
        <p>The New York City Police Department is working with Sakhi to train officers to deal with abuse in South Asian families. And in recent months, Sakhi has moved into new territory, taking its campaign to Hindu temples, Sikh gurudwaras and churches that Indian Christians attend, said Dr. Abraham, whose South Indian family is Catholic, part of India's Christian minority, from the state of Kerala.</p>
        <p>Hindu temples are important institutions for women fighting domestic violence because they are avenues for working within Indian culture, not in conflict with it. Moreover, some temples here are susceptible to a rising tide of Hindu fundamentalism in India. Indian-American women want to deliver a different message.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to take space in the community and not let the fundamentalists define it for us,'' Dr. Abraham said. ''Our community cannot be defined by one group. We are a huge spectrum of people.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Abraham, who is married to an Indian and has a 7-year-old son, was criticized at first for airing the subject of violence. ''There was negative reaction: 'Why are you bringing this out?' '' she said. ''We have not just addressed the issue of domestic violence, but challenged the myth of a model minority and also addressed issues of class, race and caste.''</p>
        <p>Purvi Shah, a writer and graduate student in English literature at Rutgers University in New Jersey, said her generation's job was to ''provoke our community not to accept violence.''</p>
        <p>''We spoke first of domestic violence because that was an easy, coherent, immediate problem,'' she said. ''But now, if we look at the directions we're moving, we also look broadly at issues of sexual violence and incest,'' subjects about which there is still a huge silence in among Indians, she added.</p>
        <p>Young Indian women, and men, are showing a greater interest in social issues, both here and in India, the women at Sakhi say. Gulab Bhouraskar, a ceramic artist and Megha Bhouraskar's mother, recalls a time when New York had only a few professional families from India preoccupied with establishing themselves in a new country.</p>
        <p>''We were building a community, and our thoughts were like, 'Where do you find a grocery store, where do you find a priest, where do you find fresh cilantro' -- it was those basic issues,'' Gulab Bhouraskar said. ''But over a number of years, the community has grown and all levels of society have come, so all issues have come.''</p>
        <p>Most women in South Asia are illiterate, and as more are brought here as brides or domestic laborers, the pool of vulnerable women grows. To them, the outside world is strange and terrifying. Even taking a subway train can be intimidating. That was Pervinder Kaur's story.</p>
        <p>Her new husband -- who, she soon discovered, had been married and divorced three times -- first put her to work in a gas station. Then, as she became more confident, he confined her to the family home. They had a daughter. ''He knew I loved her,'' Ms. Kaur said. ''He threatened to take her away from me.''</p>
        <p>The story could have ended in violence and death, as others have. But Sakhi helped her through her husband's arrest (the case is pending), a divorce, English lessons and training as a medical assistant. Living alone with her daughter now, she is a new woman. To prove it, she shows photographs of herself as a frightened immigrant, taken only a few years ago. The contrast with the confident woman she has become is startling. Ms. Kaur is so self-assured that she continues to worship at the Sikh gurudwara her ex-husband attends. It sets an example for others, and is an act of bravery, Dr. Abraham said.</p>
        <p>Less than two years after those two fateful telephone calls that changed her life, Ms. Kaur said, ''I feel very good. And now I know a lot about this country.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
