<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stunts and Thrills at Daybreak; Competitive Hysteria Drives the Morning News Programs</title>
    <meta content="16TUBE$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/business/16TUBE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239331"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EED8113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stunts and Thrills at Daybreak; Competitive Hysteria Drives the Morning News Programs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dakota, a dog, was mad as hell and wasn't going to take it anymore.</p>
        <p>It was hard enough to tolerate all the morning news-show producers crowding into his Silicon Valley town house at 2:30 a.m., maneuvering to get the first interview with his owner. Dakota was big news: just a few days earlier, he had been saved from a dangerously cold airplane cargo hold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dakota, a dog, was mad as hell and wasn't going to take it anymore.</p>
        <p>It was hard enough to tolerate all the morning news-show producers crowding into his Silicon Valley town house at 2:30 a.m., maneuvering to get the first interview with his owner. Dakota was big news: just a few days earlier, he had been saved from a dangerously cold airplane cargo hold.</p>
        <p>But the 10-year-old Basenji really lost it when CBS producers became angry at being bumped to last in the interview line and descended on Mike Bell, the dog's owner, during a live CNN appearance, taking off his microphone and cutting the interview short.</p>
        <p>''The dog starts growling,'' Mr. Bell said. ''He freaks out the guy who does the sound, who falls back into my refrigerator and my dog attacks him and tries to bite him. I just couldn't believe how cutthroat the morning news was.''</p>
        <p>But, he recalled: ''The calmest people there were with NBC. They were just sitting back and enjoying it.''</p>
        <p>The story sums up the state of the morning news shows. Despite massive assaults by CBS and ABC the last two years, NBC's ''Today'' still stands confidently at the top of the heap. In the meantime, rest assured, America: while you sleep, network producers are conniving hard to serve up your first jolt of information and perky chat each morning.</p>
        <p>In fact, the competition behind the scenes is the fiercest in morning-show  history, longtime producers say. Accusations and counteraccusations are flying -- about stolen guests, outright sabotage and petty thievery. In essence, it's similar to the great old newspaper movies like ''The Front Page.''</p>
        <p>''There's an air of hysteria,'' said Steve Friedman, executive producer of the CBS ''Early Show,'' who previously ran ''Today.'' ''I've never seen this before, and I've been doing this a long time.''</p>
        <p>This is a profit-driven hysteria. The morning is the only time when the audience for network news is actually growing. The three morning programs pulled in nearly $400 million in revenue just through July -- nearly $100 million more than the three major evening network newscasts, according to estimates by Nielsen Monitor-Plus. What's more, though there is a difference of less than $20 million in revenue between NBC's first place ''Nightly News'' and CBS's third-place ''Evening News,'' there was a difference of nearly $150 million in revenue between the first-place ''Today'' and the third-place ''Early Show.'' And, by the end of July, ''Today'' had taken in nearly $80 million more than its closest competitor, ''Good Morning America,'' according to Nielsen.</p>
        <p>The main reason given for the growth in audience is the strong economy. More people are up and about before 9 a.m. because more people are working. Whatever the reason, with so much at stake, the  networks are plowing more resources than ever into the shows. In fact, NBC extended the length of its show this month from two hours to three, taking on ABC's vaunted ''Live with Regis.''</p>
        <p>The entrance of CBS's ''Early Show'' -- a year ago Nov. 1 -- and changes to ABC's ''Good Morning America'' clearly raised the intensity of the fighting. ''Early Show's'' Bryant Gumbel, Jane Clayson and their $30 million new glass studio off Central Park added a whole new team of competitors. Things had already begun heating up the previous January, when ABC brought in Diane Sawyer and Charles Gibson to be co-hosts of a sagging ''Good Morning America.''</p>
        <p>But neither show has cut much into Katie Couric and Matt Lauer's very significant lead on ''Today.'' Though ''Early Show'' has gained on ''Good Morning America'' among young women, it is doing only as well as the third-place show it replaced, ''CBS This Morning,'' in the overall ratings. And though Ms. Sawyer and Mr. Gibson have raised the profile and ratings of ''Good Morning America,'' its audience still falls as much as two million viewers below that of ''Today,'' which stands at six million. Last week, the audience of ''Today'' was the equivalent of those of its competitors combined.</p>
        <p>Even his competitors give Jeff Zucker, the executive producer of ''Today,'' credit for keeping the NBC show fresh. But, to some degree, the continued success is based on simple inertia: groggy morning viewers are a notoriously intransigent lot. It is difficult to lure them from a program they have come to watch as they throw on their clothes, brush their teeth and prepare children for school.</p>
        <p>And there is only so much the programs can do to lure viewers from the enemy. The morning format is believed to be rigid by necessity, leaving little room for ingenuity. The prevailing wisdom is that in the first half hour of the shows, which begin at 7 a.m., most viewers are heading to work and want hard news and traffic and weather information. As time ticks by, the stay-at-home crowd becomes dominant and so the shows gradually switch to softer segments about health, cooking, dieting and preening.</p>
        <p>But just because segments are softer, does not mean the competition is any less fierce.</p>
        <p>The programs, for example, duel over bookings for their Friday outdoor concert series. On a Friday morning in June, Dionne Warwick was singing to an audience of hundreds in Manhattan's Bryant Park for ''Good Morning America.'' A few blocks away, at Rockefeller Center, Sting sang to an audience of thousands for ''Today.''</p>
        <p>In the middle of a song, Ms. Warwick was drowned out by a ''Today'' show helicopter, which hovered low overhead panning the crowd and Ms. Couric said, ''We're looking at Bryant Park, where I understand some kind of concert is going on.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zucker said he had sent the helicopter in the spirit of fun.</p>
        <p>But Shelley Ross, the ''Good Morning America'' executive producer, called the stunt ''shameful.'' She also accused ''Today'' of sending interns to the Bryant Park concert to persuade people to leave and see Sting, an accusation Mr. Zucker denies.</p>
        <p>Another way to draw viewers, of course, is the old-fashioned way: landing exclusives, at which ''Today'' has a distinct advantage. Because of its large audience, ''Today'' is often the first stop on the media publicity train for celebrities and news makers. When it comes to morning bookings, ''You start with 'Today,' period,'' said one prominent entertainment publicist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zucker said that sentiment allowed him to avoid much of the sniping in which his competitors must engage.</p>
        <p>''By and large, we've tried to stay out of that fray,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His competitors beg to differ.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ross has charged Mr. Zucker with spitefully holding guests who  are making the rounds of all the shows for too long, throwing off her schedule. A ''Today'' representative said the program would never intentionally hold a guest to hurt a competitor.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ross, however, is in no way considered an angel. In fact, her competitors say she is a key ingredient in the morning war flambe.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ross came to ''Good Morning America'' with a reputation as a tough and aggressive producer. She cut her teeth as a young woman at The Miami Herald and The National Enquirer, where she was a reporter and editor. Later, she led ABC's news magazine coverage of the O. J. Simpson case.</p>
        <p>In February, ''Today'' accused Ms. Ross of throwing off its schedule by keeping Darva Conger, the bride in the Fox show, ''Who Wants to Marry a Multimillionaire?'' in its studio too long for her to make an  appearance on NBC.</p>
        <p>''Good Morning America'' further rankled ''Today'' last month when it publicly ribbed it for showing taped programs during its first week in Sydney, Australia, where it was based for the Olympics. Australia is 15 hours ahead of New York and the ''Today'' producers wanted to show  Mr. Lauer and Ms. Couric in daylight.</p>
        <p>During live reports from Sydney,  ''Good Morning America'' flashed messages on the screen like ''Really Live'' and ''Hey, it's really dark now!''</p>
        <p>Citing that example, Mr. Friedman, a morning producer for 21 years, said he blamed ''Good Morning America'' in general, and Ms. Ross in particular, for causing an unprecedented level of distrust between the programs.</p>
        <p>''It's a mean-spirited show,'' he said, echoing words Ms. Ross has used to describe ''Today.'' ''They are worse than I've ever seen. When these people tell you something, you check your wallet.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman is no wallflower (he sometimes carries a Louisville slugger to meetings). But he pointed to the case last month of a Pittsburgh skydiving student who was caught on a plane's landing gear during a jump. He dangled for more than 40 minutes before the plane was safely landed.</p>
        <p>''Early Show'' producers jumped on the story and paid for the pilot, the student and the man who owned the skydiving school to fly to New York.  They were put up in the Plaza Hotel the day before their appearance.</p>
        <p>ABC producers found out they were staying at the Plaza and asked them to come to tape an interview for their morning show.</p>
        <p>''I said it didn't feel right to me morally for me to do that,'' said Don Bick, who owns the skydiving school.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bick said he relented after ''Good Morning America'' agreed to pay for another night in the city, and promised, in writing, not to show its taped interview until after the live interview with the ''Early Show'' was complete.</p>
        <p>In the written promise, ''Good Morning America'' said it would tape the interview ''with the full intention'' of showing it after the live one was shown on CBS. The guests were driven to the ''Good Morning America'' studios and interviewed around midnight.</p>
        <p>The next morning, Mr. Friedman said, he nearly exploded when he noticed on a control room monitor that ''Good Morning America'' had begun showing its taped segment about the skydiver as his program's live interview was still taking place.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bick said, ''I felt like somebody's whore at that point.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ross said the men had participated in her program happily. And she said: ''We really did honor the spirit of the commitment that we made to them. We had an agreement that CBS would go first and they went first.''</p>
        <p>She also said the taped interview was not seen until 45 seconds into her skydiving segment, leaving only about 40 seconds of actual interview overlap.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ross denied she is mean-spirited.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing mean-spirited; This is about journalism,'' she said. ''I think that we operate within the time-honored journalism traditions of competition.''</p>
        <p>She added, ''I think competition is healthy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
