<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exuding Confidence, Avoiding Complacency</title>
    <meta content="Y16MEM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/politics/16MEMO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239355"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E3DE1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exuding Confidence, Avoiding Complacency</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only an hour or so after Gov. George W. Bush's well-reviewed performance in Wednesday night's presidential debate, one of his top aides called to tell him that he ''just became the president of the United States.''</p>
        <p>The next morning, as his campaign plane flew low over Washington, the pilot publicly announced, ''If you look over to your left, Governor, there's your new home.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Only an hour or so after Gov. George W. Bush's well-reviewed performance in Wednesday night's presidential debate, one of his top aides called to tell him that he ''just became the president of the United States.''</p>
        <p>The next morning, as his campaign plane flew low over Washington, the pilot publicly announced, ''If you look over to your left, Governor, there's your new home.''</p>
        <p>And throughout that day, at rallies in Langhorne, Pa., and Grand Rapids, Mich., politicians essentially jumped to the same celebratory conclusion, with Gov. Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania proclaiming, ''I know a blowout when I saw one, and I saw one last night during the debates.''</p>
        <p>Small wonder that by late Friday afternoon, as Mr. Bush's week on the campaign trail ended, he jittered across the tarmac in Pontiac, Mich., like a human pinball machine, juiced by electricity, lit from within, beaming and bopping.</p>
        <p>With little more than three weeks until Election Day, Mr. Bush and his aides are exuding a mood as helium-buoyant as at any other point in the 16 months of his campaign.</p>
        <p>They feel that he aced last week's debate and turned the tide of polls decidedly in his favor, and they seem to be operating in a zone of comfort and joy, or at least are successfully projecting that image.</p>
        <p>And there is some wisdom and potential benefit in that: many political scientists say that late-deciding voters often break in favor of the candidate who is perceived to be on the surest path to victory. But there is danger, too, in all of the Austin ebullience, because the Bush campaign has fallen prey to overconfidence in the past.</p>
        <p>In the days immediately before the Republican primary in New Hampshire, Mr. Bush went sledding, bowling and snowmobile riding, obviously unprepared for the landslide victory Senator John McCain of Arizona ended up posting. Just weeks later, the Bush campaign was surprised again when Mr. McCain beat the Texas governor in the Michigan primary.</p>
        <p>One senior Republican official who advises the Bush campaign said he did not believe that Mr. Bush and his aides, for all their brio, were letting themselves be lulled into a false sense of security this time around.</p>
        <p>''I don't think they're anywhere near overconfident,'' he said. ''I think they're confident, but they're also being careful.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Bush campaign is in some ways beginning to pull out all the stops. This week, it is sending Mr. Bush's mother, Barbara Bush, out to campaign in the crucial swing states of Michigan and Pennsylvania, and next week, it is putting 28 fellow Republican governors in four airplanes to spend several days crisscrossing the country for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>But the adviser acknowledged that Mr. Bush has a tendency toward excessive optimism, citing as an example his selection in July of Dick Cheney, the former defense secretary and a longtime Bush family friend, as a running mate.</p>
        <p>Many Republican officials still see that choice as an indication that Mr. Bush felt so serene atop the polls that he put emotional preference before political strategy. Mr. Cheney, after all, is from Wyoming, a solidly Republican state with only three electoral votes, and his conservative voting record in Congress would seem to have little appeal to moderate swing voters.</p>
        <p>But several political analysts said that what Mr. Bush and his campaign may be doing now, with their constant trumpeting of recent polls that show Mr. Bush edging ahead of Mr. Gore, is trying to weave an aura of imminent triumph. It could make a difference.</p>
        <p>''There's a mild bandwagon effect for the leader,'' said Michael Lewis-Beck, a professor of political science at the University of Iowa, referring to what often happens in the electorate in a campaign's waning days. ''Success breeds more success, and people like to back winners.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lewis-Beck said he thought  Mr. Gore would prevail, based on a predictive formula that weighs factors like the health of the economy and the approval ratings for the incumbent administration.</p>
        <p>But he noted that the candidate who voters believe will win is often the one who does, so campaigns have a powerful interest late in the game in portraying themselves as being ahead.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Bush and his allies might be accused of pushing it a bit far.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, the Bush campaign produced a news release with the headline that Mr. Bush was ''leading Al Gore among the next generation of women voters,'' and Mindy Tucker, a spokeswoman for Mr. Bush, drew reporters' attention to this development in a conference call today.</p>
        <p>The surveys Ms. Tucker was referring to were either commissioned by or conducted among the Girl Scouts, and the respondents were 11 to 17 years old.</p>
        <p>Chris Lehane, a spokesman for the Gore campaign, said the Bush campaign was ''gloating,'' while Mr. Gore and his aides have ''always had a gloat-free zone.''</p>
        <p>''I think it shows a degree of hubris,'' Mr. Lehane said, ''and my guess is voters are not going to react to it very well.''</p>
        <p>But even as Mr. Bush's supporters flash broad smiles, their language suggests an awareness that the Republican presidential nominee still has to work to convince hesitant, ambivalent voters that he is adequately prepared to run the affairs of the country.</p>
        <p>The word Mr. Ridge used on Thursday afternoon to sum up Mr. Bush's debate performance was ''presidential,'' and he made a point of saying it twice.</p>
        <p>Senator Trent Lott of Mississippi, the majority leader, insisted on NBC's ''Meet the Press'' this morning that Mr. Bush was ''ready'' for the presidency, which happened to be the same locution Gov. John Engler of Michigan repeated several times at a Bush rally on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>That same evening, aboard his campaign plane, Mr. Bush had an exchange with the press corps that revealed a keen awareness of the disparaging questions about the depth of his knowledge and a keen interest in putting that chatter to rest.</p>
        <p>A reporter jokingly asked Mr. Bush if she could leave the plane through the less crowded front door, which Mr. Bush uses, instead of the back door, noting that the rear exit was ''separate'' but not ''equal.''</p>
        <p>''Plessy v. Ferguson!'' Mr. Bush exclaimed, showing off his familiarity with the 1896 Supreme Court decision that instituted a separate-but-equal doctrine to permit racial segregation in public facilities. His grin was gargantuan.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
