<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Plays Decide for Redskins As Immovable Objects Meet</title>
    <meta content="16WASH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/sports/16WASH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE0DC1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Plays Decide for Redskins As Immovable Objects Meet</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>LANDOVER, Md., Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Battle of the Beltway offered 112 plays, but the game was determined by the battles on two critical ones. The Washington Redskins won today on both counts and beat the Baltimore Ravens, 10-3, here at FedEx Field before 83,252 fans dressed in a smattering of Redskins burgundy and Ravens purple, fun-loving fans who throughout the game taunted one another and enjoyed the rivalry of teams that are feuding neighbors.</p>
        <p>Then the players took the rivalry a step further.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Battle of the Beltway offered 112 plays, but the game was determined by the battles on two critical ones. The Washington Redskins won today on both counts and beat the Baltimore Ravens, 10-3, here at FedEx Field before 83,252 fans dressed in a smattering of Redskins burgundy and Ravens purple, fun-loving fans who throughout the game taunted one another and enjoyed the rivalry of teams that are feuding neighbors.</p>
        <p>Then the players took the rivalry a step further.</p>
        <p>Norv Turner, the Redskins' coach, described the game as ''a fight where people laid it on the line for four quarters.'' He said there was some ''hittin' '' and some ''bangin.' ''</p>
        <p>So much hittin' and bangin' that points were at a premium. It was a 3-3 game with little threat of either team scoring more points except on two critical possessions: the Ravens with the ball seconds before halftime, and the Redskins with the ball early in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>With 2 minutes 57 seconds left before halftime, the Ravens recovered a Stephen Davis fumble at the Washington 42-yard line and then drove to the 1. On a first-and-goal play with 10 seconds remaining and with two timeouts left, the Ravens tried a pass in traffic near the middle of the end zone. Baltimore quarterback Tony Banks was looking for tight end Shannon Sharpe, but found Washington linebacker Kevin Mitchell instead. Mitchell, who is in his sixth pro season, made his first career interception. So, at halftime, rather than a Baltimore lead of at least a field goal, the score remained tied at 3-3.</p>
        <p>That was the score when, with 14:18 left to play, Davis atoned for his fumble. He took the handoff on second-and-7 at the Baltimore 33. Washington guessed that Baltimore would blitz. Washington guessed right. Left tackle Chris Samuels and left guard Keith Sims opened a hole that Davis sped through. He caught Baltimore safety Rod Woodson midway through with a stiff arm and churned the 33 yards into the end zone with what proved to be the game-winning touchdown.</p>
        <p>Two plays. Two big chances. The Baltimore offense failed, but the Washington offense nailed it. Both teams now own 5-2 records.</p>
        <p>After the game, Deion Sanders said that Mitchell's theft might turn out to be the Redskins' play of the season.</p>
        <p>Mitchell was more modest. ''I don't know about that,'' he said, ''but it turned this game around, because I feel if they had gone in for the touchdown we'd have been down, 10-3, and we would have had to come out in the second half fighting, trying to catch up. It changed the momentum and it gave us an opportunity to come out and take the lead. I don't think Banks saw me. I'm glad I caught it; I've been dropping the ball in practice.''</p>
        <p>The Redskins' defense dominated the Ravens' offense, which has not scored a touchdown in its last three games. Matt Stover has scored the team's last 34 points, including today's 51-yard second-quarter field goal that tied the score minutes after Kris Heppner's 37-yarder had put Washington ahead, 3-0.</p>
        <p>''It came down to one play; they made one play and we made no plays,'' Sharpe said. ''How can you go 60 minutes without making one play on offense? In my 11 years, I have never seen anything like this. We have to go back to square one and find a way to get the ball in the end zone. Right now, offensively, we are killing our team. I know we can score more than 3 points.''</p>
        <p>Not today.</p>
        <p>''One play for them; it was like a boxing match that is so close and then one punch and down we go,'' Ravens middle linebacker Ray Lewis said. ''My job is to play defense and not evaluate our offense. We are not an 0-7 team; we're 5-2. We will stay together and figure things out.''</p>
        <p>Banks threw for only 135 yards and an interception, but Washington's Brad Johnson was not much better (158 yards, 1 interception). The numbers for both teams were similar in a game that boiled down to two plays. Two plays the Redskins won.</p>
        <p>Baltimore has played three consecutive road games, and five of its first seven games this season have been road games. The Ravens talked about going home for games against Tennessee and Pittsburgh to fix their offense and build more momentum.</p>
        <p>Washington, meanwhile, has won four straight. ''It's nice to put a game like that together where everyone contributes,'' Turner said. ''Everyone comes out and says, 'I had a part in that win.' ''</p>
        <p>Brian Billick, Baltimore's coach, said: ''It was the kind of game that was advertised: a tough, physical game. They were able to make the one big play, the run by Stephen Davis, that we weren't and that was the difference. We kind of figured it would come down to that.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
