<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Within the G.O.P., Concern and Criticism That Lazio's Campaign Is Adrift</title>
    <meta content="16CAMP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/politics/16CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5D91E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Within the G.O.P., Concern and Criticism That Lazio's Campaign Is Adrift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD and ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rick A. Lazio showed up at the Rotary Club in Rochester last week, about as friendly a setting as a Republican candidate in New York State could ask for, to explain why he was running for the United States Senate against Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio began by declaring that New York should send a New Yorker to Washington, and said it was time to ''restore a sense of honor'' to public life, two obvious shots at his opponent. He then talked about his Congressional record, called for bipartisanship in Washington and promoted a few details of his ''mainstream tax relief plan.'' From there, it was back to the subject of trust, onward to his personal life story (the ''grandson of Italian immigrants'') and, finally, back on the attack, as he belittled Mrs. Clinton as a big-spending Democrat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rick A. Lazio showed up at the Rotary Club in Rochester last week, about as friendly a setting as a Republican candidate in New York State could ask for, to explain why he was running for the United States Senate against Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio began by declaring that New York should send a New Yorker to Washington, and said it was time to ''restore a sense of honor'' to public life, two obvious shots at his opponent. He then talked about his Congressional record, called for bipartisanship in Washington and promoted a few details of his ''mainstream tax relief plan.'' From there, it was back to the subject of trust, onward to his personal life story (the ''grandson of Italian immigrants'') and, finally, back on the attack, as he belittled Mrs. Clinton as a big-spending Democrat.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Lazio loped from subject to subject, reading in an even monotone from a lectern, his audience sat, still and silent, for almost the entire 30 minutes of the speech.  The applause at the end was perfunctory.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Lazio, this was a typical moment on the campaign trail. And it captured what many Republicans view as the state of his candidacy against Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Three weeks before Election Day, Mr. Lazio's campaign is described by his own supporters as adrift and unfocused. The candidate, they say, is without a clear message at time when he most needs one, and in danger of getting lost in the October news tumult of a presidential campaign, strife in the Middle East and the possibility of a Subway Series.</p>
        <p>There is growing evidence that Mr. Lazio is paying a price for some of his early tactical calculations, in particular, taking his support in upstate New York for granted, which allowed Mrs. Clinton to make inroads in the predominantly Republican area while he kept a light schedule. Similarly, his decision to let July and August pass without trying to acquaint New Yorkers with his record and beliefs seems to be complicating his efforts to gain traction now.</p>
        <p>''He has no message -- it is troubling both about the campaign and the candidate,'' said one of Mr. Lazio's most active supporters, who, like other Republicans who expressed concern about his candidacy, asked not to be identified.</p>
        <p>''I'm surprised. I still think he could win this race,'' the supporter said. ''But I didn't expect him to be completely silent in terms of defining himself in the early stages of the campaign, and I didn't expect him to adopt this odd closing-week strategy of being relentlessly positive.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio is now beset by conflicting advice from supporters on matters including whether he should attack Mrs. Clinton or talk about his own record, and where he should travel in the last few weeks of his campaign. And this barrage of advice is coming over the transom of a campaign organization that consists of often competing camps -- and that is notably short of advisers with expertise in the peculiarities of New York politics and with any ideological loyalty to the candidate.</p>
        <p>During a campaign stop in Goshen over the weekend, Mr. Lazio sharply disputed the suggestion that his candidacy was adrift. ''I think our message is very strong,'' he said, a note of exasperation in his voice.</p>
        <p>''We've been talking about education,'' he continued. ''We've been talking about accountability. We've been talking about teacher competency tests. About lowering taxes. Creating jobs. The relevance of character. A number of these things. We've been talking about the need to have somebody with experience, who has been able to get the job done, who has been able to work in a bipartisan fashion. Now if that's not a message, I don't know who is listening.''</p>
        <p>No one is asserting that Mr. Lazio's candidacy is in peril. Although several polls over the last month have shown Mrs. Clinton with a lead of 5 to 10 percentage points, three weeks is a long time in a campaign in New York, and most strategists say they think a majority of the remaining undecided voters will end up choosing Mr. Lazio rather than Mrs. Clinton, who remains a highly polarizing figure. He also has a substantial fund-raising advantage over Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Lazio's supporters express worry that the window is closing, a concern that seems to have taken hold even in his campaign offices. Mr. Lazio's advisers responded to questions about his difficulties by noting the complications in entering the race so late, and in running in a state with a large majority of Democratic voters. The remarks had the ring of a pre-emptive defense to criticism from Republicans nationwide  should Mrs. Clinton win this high-profile election.</p>
        <p>''There's only one Republican Senate candidate in America who's gained 30 points in the last 100 days, and who is running 20 points ahead of the presidential candidate, and that is Rick Lazio,'' said Mike Murphy, Mr. Lazio's senior campaign adviser. ''These mystery whiners should help Rick Lazio instead of carping from their plush armchairs.''</p>
        <p>The biggest concern voiced by Republicans is over what appears to be Mr. Lazio's difficulty in settling on a defining theme. At first, Mr. Lazio's advisers said, the candidate contended that he could win the contest by stepping aside and letting Mrs. Clinton become the issue. However, it now appears that this strategy is enough to win Mr. Lazio only about 40 percent of the vote, and there is some division among his aides about what he should do next.</p>
        <p>Some advisers, among them Mr. Murphy, have been pushing him to attack Mrs. Clinton, contending that the path to victory is to portray her as such a loathsome figure that she cannot win 50 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>''At this point, the only way he wins is by driving up Hillary's negatives even further,'' said one Republican strategist with ties to the Lazio campaign. ''The positive stuff might have been a fine strategy when it had time to work, but I don't think there's time anymore.''</p>
        <p>But other Lazio advisers say that attacking Mrs. Clinton is a waste of time. ''People already know it; we've known from the get-go that her negatives are high,'' said the Erie County Republican chairman, Robert E. Davis.</p>
        <p>These different strains of thought have been reflected in the varying messages coming from the Lazio camp. Two weeks ago, for example, Mr. Lazio's aides were telling reporters that the candidate was going to run a positive, issue-oriented campaign. But on Saturday, even as Mr. Davis was saying that Mr. Lazio needed to talk about himself, his campaign was shipping out a videotape of a new advertisement attacking Mrs. Clinton. ''Can you name three things that Hillary Clinton has done for New York?'' the announcer asks.</p>
        <p>Many days go by in which Mr. Lazio says little about policy initiatives or other proposals that might make him the subject of a news story. He has given only two major policy speeches -- on tax cuts and education -- since joining the race. As a result, he often cedes the story of the day to Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's difficulties have been complicated by his need to navigate tensions between Gov. George E. Pataki, who is pushing his candidacy, and Rudolph W. Giuliani. When Mr. Lazio joined the race in June, he started almost entirely from scratch; he did not, for example, move into Mr. Giuliani's campaign headquarters, which were up and running. Some of Mr. Giuliani's associates said that decision contributed to Mr. Lazio's slow start.</p>
        <p>The two central figures inside the campaign, Mr. Murphy and the campaign manager, Bill Dal Col, are based in Virginia. Mr. Murphy was the consultant to the Republican presidential campaign of Senator John S. McCain of Arizona, and has used and borrowed heavily from Mr. McCain's campaign tactics, like the use of a bus to carry Mr. Lazio around the state. ''John McCain lost this state,'' one top New York Republican complained. ''Define yourself as someone who is a winner here.''</p>
        <p>Other influences on Mr. Lazio include Mr. Pataki and his political organization, and Mr. Lazio's associates and friends from his Long Island campaigns.</p>
        <p>Others who have a lower profile in the race, but still have the candidate's ear, include Mr. Lazio's former campaign manager in Congressional races, Assemblyman Philip M. Boyle; Andrew Siben, a lawyer and close friend; Michael Moriarty, the candidate's brother-in-law and campaign counsel; and Carlyle Gregory, a Washington-area political consultant Mr. Lazio has used in the past.  Mr. Boyle called complaints about the campaign ''overstated.'' ''I think obviously you have a melding of different groups, but we are all unified in the same goal,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio has raised and dropped a number of themes over the last six weeks: from a passing reference to calling for a missile defense shield, to what his advisers described as an effort to reach out to black and Hispanic voters, to a promised address on foreign policy that was scheduled, then postponed, and is about to be rescheduled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murphy, though, said it would be a mistake to infer that the campaign was unsure of what it was doing, or where it was going.</p>
        <p>''We have a fabulous final three weeks in the can that we're about to uncork,'' he said. ''We have this thing planned like D-Day. We're going to take the grumps to school on how to win a campaign in New York.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
