<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Community Debates Its Role in the Debate</title>
    <meta content="Y16SAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/politics/16SARA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239368"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CREDIBILITY ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DB1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1360" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Community Debates Its Role in the Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <dateline>SARASOTA, Fla., Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It all started over a shortage of desks in a crowded high school biology class, and became, for many people here, a lesson in political science.</p>
        <p>''It was real exciting for the first 18 hours, and then it got a little scary,'' said Randy Ellis, who, with the best of intentions, sent a note and an accompanying newspaper clipping about school overcrowding to Vice President Al Gore. The clipping's photograph showed Kailey Ellis, Mr. Ellis's 15-year-old daughter, standing in a crowded classroom at Sarasota High School.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It all started over a shortage of desks in a crowded high school biology class, and became, for many people here, a lesson in political science.</p>
        <p>''It was real exciting for the first 18 hours, and then it got a little scary,'' said Randy Ellis, who, with the best of intentions, sent a note and an accompanying newspaper clipping about school overcrowding to Vice President Al Gore. The clipping's photograph showed Kailey Ellis, Mr. Ellis's 15-year-old daughter, standing in a crowded classroom at Sarasota High School.</p>
        <p>First, his note became a tidbit by Mr. Gore in a televised debate with Gov. George W. Bush of Texas on Oct. 3. Kailey thought it was cool that it made national television, and Mr. Ellis was proud he had called the problem -- part of a larger national issue -- to the vice president's attention.</p>
        <p>But then Republicans used a misstatement in Mr. Gore's comment -- the vice president said Kailey ''has to stand'' when she had stood for only one day on the ninth day of classes -- to question the vice president's credibility.</p>
        <p>Fueled by indignant reaction from the school's principal, Dan Kennedy, and other school officials who resented having their highly rated high school used on national television to make a point about education problems, Bush campaign workers said Mr. Gore's statement showed that he would embellish a truth for political gain.</p>
        <p>High-ranking Republicans have feted Mr. Kennedy, a Republican who said he was not that politically active before this, as a kind of hero.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in this affluent coastal city south of Tampa Bay, miffed residents have told Mr. Ellis he should be ashamed of himself for giving the city ''a black eye,'' Mr. Ellis said.</p>
        <p>And in a backlash to the backlash, many people in Sarasota said Mr. Kennedy and Wilma Hamilton, the Sarasota County Schools superintendent, seemed more concerned about their reputations than about a legitimate overcrowding problem in a system facing budget problems.</p>
        <p>''It put a lot of people on the defensive,'' said Helen M. Matthews, 75, who said she has not made up her mind whom she will vote for. ''They know they have problems in the schools, but they didn't want to see that aired around the country.''</p>
        <p>It makes Mr. Ellis, who happens to be a Republican himself, shake his head. ''It was nonpolitical,'' said Mr. Ellis, a general manager at a Sarasota restaurant, of his decision to send the note to Mr. Gore while he was helping prepare lunch for the vice president during a campaign stop before the debate.</p>
        <p>He gave the note to a steward aboard Air Force Two, and never expected to hear about it again.</p>
        <p>''I just want my daughter to have a quality education, and 36 to 40 kids in one class is too many,'' he said, referring to cuts in staff at the school and others in the county that have resulted in swelling classes.</p>
        <p>Kailey's science class was intended for 24 students but had 36 students in it on the ninth day of classes, when a Sarasota Herald-Tribune photographer snapped her picture.</p>
        <p>Kailey was standing near the back of the room because there was not a desk for her. The school, and others here, are absorbing a $17 million budget cut in the district, long rated one of the state's best academically.</p>
        <p>A remedy, a tax increase earmarked for schools, was rejected in a July referendum, forcing cuts of 100 teachers and another 100 aides, bus drivers and custodians. Students in several classes did not have desks well into the first first two weeks of school, and teachers said the overcrowding would, certainly, lead to a decline in the level of education they could provide.</p>
        <p>''I had an opportunity to get a message to Washington,'' Mr. Ellis said. If he had been catering Mr. Bush's lunch instead, he would have done the same, Mr. Ellis said.</p>
        <p>But when Mr. Gore, in the Oct. 3 debate, referred to Mr. Ellis's note as a sign of a need for increased spending in education, he said of Kailey's classroom, ''They can't squeeze another desk in for her, so she has to stand.''</p>
        <p>By then, a classmate had given his desk to Kailey, and, sitting in a chair, shared the desktop with her.</p>
        <p>''It was verb tense,'' Mr. Ellis said of Mr. Gore's mistake. '' 'She has to stand,' Gore said, instead of saying she had to stand. We've been asked if Gore stretched the truth. In my view, he used it to drive home a point, and it was a good point.</p>
        <p>''The funny thing is, it looks like I'm defending Al Gore, and I'm a Republican. My name was mud around Sarasota.''</p>
        <p>The national media, pundits and talk show hosts, Mr. Ellis said, seized on comments by Mr. Kennedy, whom he said he respects, and other school officials, who said Mr. Gore exaggerated the overcrowding problem.</p>
        <p>''No one is denying that we need additional funding, but we are not representative of all the problems in education, and we are not a decaying school in crisis,'' said Mr. Kennedy, who plans to join forces with Kailey, Mr. Ellis and others here to try and push for a new referendum to help ease the effect of not just this year's budget shortfall, but also future ones.</p>
        <p>''It's vitally important that students feel good about their school,'' Mr. Kennedy said, and the whole nation saw it ''trashed'' in a presidential debate.</p>
        <p>His comments rebutting Mr. Gore's claim included a column in The Wall Street Journal that bore the headline: ''Note to Gore: Sarasota High Is Not a Sob Story.'' It delighted Republicans here and around the nation.</p>
        <p>In a Republican fund-raiser here last week for Representative Bill McCollum, who is running against Bill Nelson, the state insurance commissioner, for the Senate, Mr. Kennedy was singled out by Senator Trent Lott, the majority leader.</p>
        <p>''I could almost give you a bearhug,'' Mr. Lott said to Mr. Kennedy. ''Thanks for defending your school.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kennedy said politics had nothing to do with his response to Mr. Gore's comments.</p>
        <p>The schools superintendent, Ms. Hamilton, also said politics played no role in her decision to strongly rebut the image of the school Mr. Gore put forth.</p>
        <p>She said she also voiced strong concern about overcrowding, but those comments were not so widely aired.</p>
        <p>''We were only interested in making sure the whole truth was out,'' she said. Students were forced to stand, she said, but only temporarily.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hamilton said she is apolitical, and has to be, because of her job. But she concedes that the vice president's comments pricked her pride, and the pride of others here.</p>
        <p>Everyone, Mr. Ellis said, seemed to miss the point. It was not that Mr. Gore made what he called a small mistake in recounting the problem, but that the problem exists.</p>
        <p>''If it's happening here in one of the best school districts in the state, what's it like in the other districts?'' Mr. Ellis said.</p>
        <p>That, Mr. Ellis said, should be the story.</p>
        <p>''You just can't teach 36 to 40 kids, not today,'' said John L. Hegener, a retired teacher.</p>
        <p>The schools are still overcrowded, and that issue, people here say, is just not enticing enough to draw much attention.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellis said his family is glad the spotlight has dimmed.</p>
        <p>He said he has been undecided about the race, but figures he will ''vote for my party.''</p>
        <p>But he and his family will never look at an election quite the same again.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CREDIBILITY ISSUE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
