<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milosevic's Ex-Communists Are Reborn Yet Again</title>
    <meta content="Y16YUG$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/world/16YUGO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239380"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1369" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milosevic's Ex-Communists Are Reborn Yet Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <dateline>NIS, Serbia, Oct. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Zoran Radovanovic, 30, wears his hair slicked back close to his head and a black shirt under a colored jacket. The new local leader in Nis of Slobodan Milosevic's Socialist Party of Serbia, he is already speaking of the need to transform the party and ''change a large number of the leaders.''</p>
        <p>The successor of the Communist Party, the Socialist Party of Serbia, with Mr. Milosevic at the helm, had dominated politics in Serbia and led the ruling coalition for the previous 10 years. But in the elections on Sept. 24, it suffered a resounding defeat -- not just in Mr. Milosevic's failed bid to retain the Yugoslav presidency, but also in races for key cities like this one, Serbia's third largest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Zoran Radovanovic, 30, wears his hair slicked back close to his head and a black shirt under a colored jacket. The new local leader in Nis of Slobodan Milosevic's Socialist Party of Serbia, he is already speaking of the need to transform the party and ''change a large number of the leaders.''</p>
        <p>The successor of the Communist Party, the Socialist Party of Serbia, with Mr. Milosevic at the helm, had dominated politics in Serbia and led the ruling coalition for the previous 10 years. But in the elections on Sept. 24, it suffered a resounding defeat -- not just in Mr. Milosevic's failed bid to retain the Yugoslav presidency, but also in races for key cities like this one, Serbia's third largest.</p>
        <p>Many members were stunned, and were left scrambling for cover as other Serbs began to demand a wholesale accounting for the abuses of power over the last decade. Some Socialist officials have left their posts and turned off their cellular phones; diehards remain in their offices, refusing to acknowledge the election results and still vowing allegiance to Mr. Milosevic. An energetic few, like Mr. Radovanovic, are already talking of drastic changes needed to reinvent the party.</p>
        <p>One of the first indications of internal disarray came last week when the president and vice president of the Socialist Party in Nis, Pera Milanovic, an industry director, and Branimir Djordjevic, the university chancellor, announced their resignations from their party posts and denounced top leaders for the party's ''catastrophic failure'' at the polls.</p>
        <p>They said in a statement that Mr. Milosevic had dragged the party down, and forced a politically disastrous union with the United Yugoslav Left, an unpopular party headed by his wife, Mira Markovic. They described his delay in accepting the presidential election results -- not until a mass popular revolt in Belgrade resulted in the demonstrators' seizing Parliament as well as a key lever of power, state television -- as ''unthinkable behavior.''</p>
        <p>''It means he does not deserve to be the head of the party,'' they said, adding that he and his party's extremely unpopular general secretary, Gorica Gajevic, should resign immediately.</p>
        <p>The new party leadership ignored the men's resignations, dismissing them on their own the next day. The young Mr. Radovanovic took over but within a day was silenced, told not to speak to the press.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, though, more party members have criticized the leadership, prompting Ms. Gajevic to resign before she was pushed last Thursday. A party congress has been scheduled for Nov. 25 and a split in the party is likely, with even supporters of Mr. Milosevic -- who remains officially a fugitive, in his villa in Belgrade under police protection -- saying that he may have to go.</p>
        <p>In the Socialist headquarters here in Nis in recent days, there was a surliness in the air. Party workers in the dingy lobby refused to give out leftover campaign posters, saying they did not want them ''misused.'' Upstairs, a secretary barred the way to Mr. Radovanovic's office, forcing him to come out of a side door and personally admit visitors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Radovanovic said he was already looking forward to forging a future as a strong opposition party. ''We want to analyze all our mistakes,'' he said, ''and take an honest look at what our political opponents have done'' before heading into elections for the Parliament in Serbia, where Yugoslav power truly lies, on Dec. 24. ''We are going to modernize and for sure we are going to change, and maybe change a large number of the leadership.''</p>
        <p>He outlined a vision for the Socialist party -- which never really shifted from its Communist base -- one more like the social democratic ideals adopted in the last few years by former Communist parties in much of the old Soviet bloc.</p>
        <p>Despite such talk of modernizing, Mr. Radovanovic still rolled out some old-style responses. He denied that there had been political repression or curbs on the news media under Mr. Milosevic. Ignoring accusations from Mr. Milosevic, his wife and their associates that opposition leaders had been in the West's pocket, he said the party did not oppose cooperation with Western countries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Radovanovic and those who want to transform the Socialist party face an enormous task. As workers and ordinary citizens lost their fear of the authorities, the party's base appeared to crumble, exposing Mr. Milosevic's grip on power in recent years as broad but thin. Across Serbia, workers have ousted party bosses from their posts in major industries, students have demanded the resignations of university deans, and journalists have taken over control of their newspapers.</p>
        <p>At Nitex, the big state textile company in Nis, some 1,000 striking workers gathered at company gates last Monday to demand the resignation of the general director, Mile Novakovic, a Communist who turned Socialist and ran the company, the workers say, as a fief for 30 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Novakovic saw this coming and had resigned the night before. ''If he had been there we might have lynched him,'' said Ljiljiana Canic, a machine operator who was thrown out of her job in March after going on strike.</p>
        <p>She and others received threats on the phone last Sunday night, but spurred on by the uprising in Belgrade three days earlier, they were determined to oust the factory boss whom they blamed for increasingly hard working conditions and pitifully low wages.</p>
        <p>''The workers had no rights, no dignity,'' said Zoran Tosic, 40, a newly elected trade union leader. ''He did not consider them human, just to be exploited.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Canic added, ''He used to brag that he had the cheapest work force in town.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Tosic listed houses, apartments and cars that Mr. Novakovic and his son -- who was the company's Belgrade representative -- had amassed over the years.</p>
        <p>An opposition politician and former employee of the factory, Branislav Jovanovic, has been chosen by workers to replace Mr. Novakovic -- at least until the Serbian government officially appoints a new director, the timing of which in the current state of chaos is unknown.</p>
        <p>The Socialists have bitterly complained that their people are being chased illegally from their jobs in an orchestrated campaign by political opponents. Many such firings are being carried out at local level, by workers and students venting years of frustration and disgust.</p>
        <p>Socialist officials who have gained local trust have been allowed to remain at their posts. Mr. Milanovic, the former party president in Nis, has remained head of the city's machine industry company with the workers' approval. Students in nearby Leskovac said the dean of their biochemistry faculty should stay, since he had joined the Socialist party under pressure only a few months ago, and had walked in demonstrations last year with them.</p>
        <p>The once-powerful Socialist mayor of Leskovac, Zivojin Stefanovic, has felt the brunt of popular anger. On the night that Parliament and state television were seized in Belgrade, people ransacked and burned his family home in Leskovac, overturning and smashing his car.</p>
        <p>''That's democracy,'' he said angrily a few days later, throwing down photos of his burned house on the table. He remains in charge at city hall, having won a majority for the Socialists in Leskovac, although the Democratic Opposition of Serbia is contesting a number of seats that could change the balance of power.</p>
        <p>Even in this southern region, known as the ''red belt'' where support for Mr. Milosevic was always strongest, the Socialists lost votes on Sept. 24.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stefanovic said he would not fight to keep his position. Then, animated once more, he added: ''Just you wait. Prices of bread and cooking oil are already going up. People will realize and you will see -- we</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
