<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Piazza Seems to Have Eye for St. Louis Pitching</title>
    <meta content="16SHEA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/sports/16SHEA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EFD91E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Piazza Seems to Have Eye for St. Louis Pitching</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Piazza led the National League in grand slams this year, with three in the regular season. So it seemed his kind of moment when he came to the plate with the bases loaded in the sixth inning last night against the St. Louis Cardinals in Game 4 of the National League Championship Series at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Piazza, the Mets catcher, already had a double and a mammoth home run to help his team to an 8-6 lead. The capacity crowd cheered loudly when he walked to the plate to face pitcher Mike Timlin, and some fans chanted ''M.V.P.'' because they thought Piazza was the league's most valuable player.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Piazza led the National League in grand slams this year, with three in the regular season. So it seemed his kind of moment when he came to the plate with the bases loaded in the sixth inning last night against the St. Louis Cardinals in Game 4 of the National League Championship Series at Shea Stadium.</p>
        <p>Piazza, the Mets catcher, already had a double and a mammoth home run to help his team to an 8-6 lead. The capacity crowd cheered loudly when he walked to the plate to face pitcher Mike Timlin, and some fans chanted ''M.V.P.'' because they thought Piazza was the league's most valuable player.</p>
        <p>This time, however, Piazza grounded to third baseman Fernando Tatis, who muffed the pickup. Piazza was safe at first, a run scored from third, and Piazza had another run batted in. He finished the night with two R.B.I. as the Mets beat the Cardinals by 10-6 to take a three-games-to-one lead in the four-of-seven series that resumes tonight at Shea.</p>
        <p>''Honestly, sometimes I get almost too pumped and I get out of my game,'' Piazza said of such moments. ''Obviously, they expect a big hit every time. I try to do the best I can. Timlin's got nasty stuff. It kind of ran in. Fortunately, the ball kicked up on Tatis.''</p>
        <p>Piazza spoke at about midnight in a press room. He wore a blue cap that said Bomb Squad. It was a gift from a New York police officer, who entered the locker room before the game with a crew and with dogs who sniffed for explosives. The increased police presence was part of an anti-terrorism effort as a result of tense political conditions in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>With two hits last night, Piazza is 6 for 13 in this series for a .462 average. He has two home runs and four R.B.I. It is quite an improvement from the .214 with no R.B.I. in four games against San Francisco in the division series.</p>
        <p>Despite a regular season with impressive statistics -- a .324 average, 38 home runs, 113 R.B.I. -- Piazza finished the schedule with a slow bat. It seemed fair to wonder if the grind of catching most games had worn down his energy, the way it seemed to in 1999, when he went 6 for 33 in eight postseason games. Piazza seems revived against St. Louis's pitching.</p>
        <p>''It's always been just from the position I play,'' he said. ''It's been a long year. I've taken a lot of lumps. It's tough, physically, to stay 100 percent. But I'm fortunate that toward the end I got some rest and I was able to recuperate a little bit, and I've been swinging the bat fairly well.''</p>
        <p>With many in the city hoping for a World Series between the Mets and the Yankees, someone asked Piazza about the possibility of again facing Roger Clemens, the Yankee pitcher who hit Piazza in the head during an interleague game in July. He smiled when he heard it.</p>
        <p>''Starting already?'' he said of the Clemens question. ''Hopefully, ask me about that after we win tomorrow.'' Is he eagerly anticipating the Series? ''To be honest with you, I haven't thought about it; I'm sort of numb and focused,'' Piazza said. ''Now is not the time to reflect or think about it.''</p>
        <p>Another dimension of Piazza's performance, his defensive play, remains filled with positives and negatives. On the plus side was a play last night in the top of the eighth. With two strikes, Cardinals center fielder Jim Edmonds tipped a pitch foul. It bounced off the heel of Piazza's glove, but before it fell to the ground, Piazza lunged to his left and caught the ball for the out. On Saturday he made another great play, leaning over a plexiglass barrier to catch a pop fly before it fell into the seats.</p>
        <p>But other aspects of his defense are less polished. Piazza is not noted for throwing out runners who try to steal bases. And his coverage of home plate on throws from the outfield can be interesting. One such play came in the Cardinals' fifth inning, when Edgar Renteria hit a fly ball to Timo Perez in right field with one out and the Mets ahead, 8-4.</p>
        <p>Carlos Hernandez, tagging from third, came down the base line. Piazza, covering the plate, did not catch the bouncing ball cleanly for what could have been an inning-ending double play. The Cardinals cut the Mets' lead to 8-5 and scored again with two out.</p>
        <p>Regarding a chance to clinch in Game 5, Piazza said: ''Obviously, we want to end it right here. I mean, that's our goal. That's our plan.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
