<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giving Today's Rockefellers A Dime for Their Thoughts</title>
    <meta content="16JAME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/arts/16JAME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E6D9113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giving Today's Rockefellers A Dime for Their Thoughts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A promo for ''The Rockefellers'' lays out the family's many traumas, from public scorn to crises of conscience, then asks the derisive question ''Who wants to be a millionaire?'' The obvious answer is ''Everybody.'' Yet this two-part family portrait (the season opener of ''American Experience'' on PBS) views the Rockefellers in the sympathetic way in which the so-called ''cousins'' would like to be seen.</p>
        <p>Several cousins -- now in middle age, they are the dynasty's fourth generation, descended from the original robber baron John D. Rockefeller -- are interviewed on camera, presenting themselves as philanthropists burdened by a moral responsibility as heavy as the weight of their money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A promo for ''The Rockefellers'' lays out the family's many traumas, from public scorn to crises of conscience, then asks the derisive question ''Who wants to be a millionaire?'' The obvious answer is ''Everybody.'' Yet this two-part family portrait (the season opener of ''American Experience'' on PBS) views the Rockefellers in the sympathetic way in which the so-called ''cousins'' would like to be seen.</p>
        <p>Several cousins -- now in middle age, they are the dynasty's fourth generation, descended from the original robber baron John D. Rockefeller -- are interviewed on camera, presenting themselves as philanthropists burdened by a moral responsibility as heavy as the weight of their money.</p>
        <p>Seeing the Rockefellers as the poor little rich family is too much of a stretch; it's safe to say most people would trade places. But if that narrow, even naive perspective is the flaw in this group portrait, it is linked to its greatest strength. Constantly fascinating, ''The Rockefellers'' offers an unexpectedly vivid journey inside the family, creating an intimate sense of how each generation's dominant son resolved not to be like his father.</p>
        <p>The consequences for the country were immense. The documentary charts the epic influence of the family on American culture: monopolizing the oil industry, building Rockefeller Center, helping to found the Museum of Modern Art and so on down the generations. More profoundly it finds in the Rockefellers the embodiment of the enduring American tension between our Puritanical roots and our insatiable lust for money and power.</p>
        <p>Though John D. founded Standard Oil and the family's fortune, the true Rockefeller legacy began a generation before, with his father, a bigamist and traveling con man nicknamed Devil Bill. Reacting against his lowlife father, John D. ruthlessly built an empire, making secret deals with the railroads, putting smaller oil companies out of business, never losing a night's sleep over it while instructing his children in strict Christian self-denial. He became the most reviled man in America when his business tactics were made public, and he looked the part. In a parade of photographs, John D. has the sternest look and iciest blue eyes imaginable.</p>
        <p>His nervous son, nicknamed Junior, had enough guilt and insecurity for both of them. ''Riches breed but sin,'' he told a Bible class he taught. He devoted his life to giving away money through the Rockefeller Foundation, trying to erase the stain attached to the family name.</p>
        <p>Ron Chernow, author of ''Titan,'' the best-selling biography of John Sr., is first among the astute experts who tell this compelling story. Interviews with Junior's surviving sons are less substantial but viscerally charged. David Rockefeller, who became president of the Chase Manhattan Bank, recalls being taught as a child to keep track of his allowance in a ledger book. Laurance Rockefeller tells of breeding bunnies and selling them to the Rockefeller Institute.</p>
        <p>Part 2 (to be shown next Monday) is less focused, its attention spread over Junior's five sons. It rightly concentrates on Nelson Rockefeller, governor of New York in the 1960's and early 70's, a failed presidential candidate and a figure whose gigantic ambitions and appetites made him the opposite of his nervous, devout father.</p>
        <p>To see film of Nelson diving into crowds, buying a salami as he campaigns on the streets of New York City, spending more money on the governor's race than had ever been spent before, is to witness a combination of raw ambition and noblesse oblige that would have done his grandfather proud. This family biography can only begin to explore a personality that led Nelson to divorce and remarry at a time when such actions were sure to damage his hopes for the White House.</p>
        <p>What the documentary lacks in complexity, however, it makes up for in sheer liveliness. And though the film doesn't make the connections, the Rockefellers' provocative behavior echoes through the present.</p>
        <p>Like Nelson, Bill Clinton and Rudolph W. Giuliani have seen the messiness of their private lives take on political consequences, as the line between hubris and political suicide becomes murky. In recent months, during the federal government's antitrust action against Microsoft, editorialists have regularly compared Bill Gates to John D. Rockefeller. Gentle though it is, ''The Rockefellers'' hints at depths that the cousins prefer to ignore.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN EXPERIENCE  The Rockefellers  PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 9)</p>
        <p>Part 1 written, produced and directed by Elizabeth Deane; Sarah Holt, editor. Part 2  written, produced and directed by Adriana Bosch; Jon Neuburger, editor. Cinematography by Terry Hopkins; music by Michael Bacon; David Ogden Stiers, narrator. Ms. Deane, program executive producer. ''American Experience'' is a production of WGBH Boston; Margaret Drain, executive producer; Mark Samels, senior producer.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
