<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Seattle Sluggers Awaken at Same Time</title>
    <meta content="16PINS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/sports/16PINS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0DA1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Seattle Sluggers Awaken at Same Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM SPOUSTA</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He trotted toward first base and admired the mayhem he had just created for the Yankees. As Alex Rodriguez rounded the bag, he looked back at the two runners crossing the plate and smacked his hands together in satisfaction.</p>
        <p>Finally, the Seattle Mariners, particularly their heart-of-the-order stars, had produced something other than misery and failure in the American League Championship Series. Rodriguez, Edgar Martinez and John Olerud -- the Nos. 3, 4 and 5 hitters -- had symbolized the Mariners' offensive shortcomings against the Yankees until three dramatic swings in the fifth inning of today's Game 5.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He trotted toward first base and admired the mayhem he had just created for the Yankees. As Alex Rodriguez rounded the bag, he looked back at the two runners crossing the plate and smacked his hands together in satisfaction.</p>
        <p>Finally, the Seattle Mariners, particularly their heart-of-the-order stars, had produced something other than misery and failure in the American League Championship Series. Rodriguez, Edgar Martinez and John Olerud -- the Nos. 3, 4 and 5 hitters -- had symbolized the Mariners' offensive shortcomings against the Yankees until three dramatic swings in the fifth inning of today's Game 5.</p>
        <p>With the Mariners trailing by 2-1, Rodriguez, Martinez and Olerud accounted for all five runs in the rally and woke up a sleepy Safeco Field crowd that did not want to witness a Yankee victory party on its turf. The 6-2 victory sent the four-of-seven-game series back to New York for Game 6 on Tuesday night, with the Yankees leading, three games to two, and the Mariners hoping they can beat Orlando Hernandez, who is 7-0 in the postseason.</p>
        <p>''Pray a lot, for one thing,'' Rodriguez said when asked what his thoughts were about facing El Duque, who held the Mariners to one run in Game 2. ''We just want to get this to a Game 7, extend it somehow, some way, and make it difficult on these New Yorkers.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Mariners rediscovered the art of clutch hitting in an interesting way. They chose not to take batting practice before the game, opting instead for a team meeting in the clubhouse. With a .183 team batting average through the first four games, the decision proved wise and led to eight hits and six runs, which was one more than the Mariners had scored in the previous four games.</p>
        <p>If anything, the Mariners learned what the Yankees experienced late in the regular season and during their tough five-game division series victory over Oakland: slumps, no matter how poor, can be broken.</p>
        <p>In a complete reversal of fortune, Rodriguez delivered a two-run single, which was followed by consecutive home runs by Martinez and Olerud, who were each batting .214 for the series before cracking long drives over the center-field wall.</p>
        <p>''We hadn't done anything in scoring situations, and to have Alex come through and drive in those runs, that was a huge relief for us,'' said Olerud, who was robbed of another home run by Bernie Williams's leaping catch in the fourth inning.</p>
        <p>Olerud finished with two hits, while Rodriguez and Martinez had one each. Jay Buhner, the No. 6 batter, awoke as well, going 2 for 4 after starting the series 0 for 6.</p>
        <p>''Basically, all the pressure is on them now,'' said Lou Piniella, the Mariners' manager. ''They're supposed to win.''</p>
        <p>The pivotal fifth inning started with a bunt single by Mark McLemore and escalated until the Mariners scored five runs. After Rickey Henderson drew a walk, Mike Cameron moved both runners to second and third with a sacrifice bunt. Still, such smart baseball strategy had so far not guaranteed that the Mariners would score.</p>
        <p>With first base open at that point, Yankees Manager Joe Torre said he considered intentionally walking Rodriguez to take his chances against Martinez and Olerud, setting up a possible double play. ''One danger with loading the bases for Edgar is he knows you have to throw him a strike, and he's pretty darn patient,'' Torre said. ''Instead, I was hoping to give up a run for an out, get one at a time.''</p>
        <p>Rodriguez changed all that on the first pitch from Jeff Nelson, who had relieved the Yankees' starter, Denny Neagle. Rodriguez lofted a solid single to left field, scoring McLemore and Henderson and setting the stage for Martinez and Olerud.</p>
        <p>''Joe has managed a great series so far,'' Piniella said, ''but with Edgar and Olerud, it was a tough proposition either way.''</p>
        <p>Hitting in general has been a tough proposition for the Mariners. But taking advantage of scoring opportunities with clutch hits had been nonexistent since the Mariners' 2-0 victory in Game 1 at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>At .286 and with a solo home run in Game 1, Rodriguez (4 for 14) was having the best series of the three. Martinez and Olerud were each 3 for 14, and had yet to feel anything but frustration with runners in scoring position. Until today's fifth inning.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if we're going to have batting practice when we get to New York,'' Martinez said. ''But the way we've been swinging the bats, I think it's good to just relax and go from here to the game. It worked today.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
