<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>La Russa, in Starting Kile, Thinking Much Too Hard</title>
    <meta content="16CHAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/sports/16CHAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEFD91E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>La Russa, in Starting Kile, Thinking Much Too Hard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony La Russa, the thinking man's manager, thought the St. Louis Cardinals would be best served by having Darryl Kile, their 20-game winner, pitch last night's Game 4 against the Mets, working on only three days of rest instead of the usual four. That way, La Russa explained, Kile could pitch Game 7, if there was a Game 7.</p>
        <p>''Darryl is best suited for it,'' La Russa said, ''and it's our best shot if it goes seven games.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tony La Russa, the thinking man's manager, thought the St. Louis Cardinals would be best served by having Darryl Kile, their 20-game winner, pitch last night's Game 4 against the Mets, working on only three days of rest instead of the usual four. That way, La Russa explained, Kile could pitch Game 7, if there was a Game 7.</p>
        <p>''Darryl is best suited for it,'' La Russa said, ''and it's our best shot if it goes seven games.''</p>
        <p>After watching the game last night, the thinking man's manager might want to give that assessment another thought.</p>
        <p>Kile lasted one batter into the fourth inning. He faced 19 batters in all. Eight of those batters banged hits. Three others walked. The Mets battered Kile for seven runs. The Mets won, 10-6, and took a commanding three-games-to-one lead in their second successive National League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>''He's been protected all year long so that he'd have that little extra for this time of the year,'' La Russa had said the day before. ''I think he'll go out there with his normal, really good stuff and pitch like he's pitched all year, where he's had really good command.''</p>
        <p>Timo Perez led off the Mets' half of the first inning by lashing Kile's third pitch into the right-center-field gap for a double.</p>
        <p>''I can't control anything other than a pitch I throw and how well I throw it,'' Kile had said.</p>
        <p>Edgardo Alfonzo bashed Kile's fourth pitch along the right-field line for a double, driving in Perez.</p>
        <p>''You just have to time and time again stay ahead in the count, make quality pitches when you have a chance to get out of an inning quickly, try to stop any momentum when they get going,'' Kile had said.</p>
        <p>Mike Piazza took the first two pitches for balls, then drove the third pitch over J. D. Drew's head in right field for a double. Alfonzo, having held at second to see if Drew would catch the ball, stopped at third.</p>
        <p>''The job I've got to do,'' Kile had said, ''is throw as many quality pitches as I can for however many pitches I'm out there.''</p>
        <p>Robin Ventura drilled Kile's ninth pitch to right-center for a double, driving in Alfonzo and Piazza. Jim Edmonds, the third batter in the game, had given the Cardinals a quick lead with a two-run home run. Now the Mets led, 3-2.</p>
        <p>''Darryl's a pro's pro,'' La Russa said before the game. ''He's been so impressive. We're looking forward to having him out there tonight. Physically, he's set up really well for it.''</p>
        <p>No team had ever hit four consecutive doubles in a League Championship Series game, let alone begun the first inning with four doubles from the first four batters. Todd Zeile, the Mets' fifth batter, did not add his name to the double list. He hit a grounder to third base for the first out.</p>
        <p>''If you look throughout the course of the season,'' Kile had said, ''there's days where you have good stuff, and there's days where you don't. Your job as a pitcher is to try to find a way to win.''</p>
        <p>Then Benny Agbayani smashed a fly ball well beyond the fancy-fielding Edmonds in center. Now the Mets had five doubles and four runs. No team had ever struck five extra-base hits in any inning of any League Championship Series game.</p>
        <p>''No matter if you're coming back early or you have extra rest or whatever,'' Kile had said, ''my job is to go out there with whatever hand I've been dealt as far as stuff-wise and try to compete and try to battle and make as many quality pitches as I can and give our guys a chance.''</p>
        <p>Jay Payton lofted a fly ball that was clearly headed for the left-field stands, but it arrived in the stands just on the foul side of the orange pole that is the line of demarcation for home runs. Payton swung at the next pitch, too, but missed it for strike three. Mike Bordick hit a grounder up the middle but was thrown out at first. The inning, mercifully for Kile, was over.</p>
        <p>Unlike Kile, Pat Hentgen, the Cardinals' scheduled starter in tonight's game, will pitch with long rest, 16 days of it. Hentgen said he wouldn't have a problem with short rest and ''I don't think Darryl does either, or otherwise he wouldn't be pitching.''</p>
        <p>The right-handed Bobby Jones, the Mets' pitcher, began the bottom of the second inning with a fly to center field. Perez slapped a single to left center, then stole second.</p>
        <p>''I've been a guy that throws a lot all the time,'' Kile had said. ''Pretty much play catch every day, whether it's on three days, four days or if you have an off day or something, six days.''</p>
        <p>Alfonzo hit a fly to center for the second out. Kile walked Piazza intentionally, then walked Ventura unintentionally. Zeile swatted a double to left field, sending Perez and Piazza home. Zeile then scored as Agbayani singled to center.</p>
        <p>''Again,'' Kile had said, ''if you look at it from this perspective, my job is to go out there when Skip says it's my turn to go and battle as hard as I can and compete as hard as I can for as long as I can. Hopefully, when I come out of the game, we're on top.''</p>
        <p>When Kile left the game after walking Perez in the fourth inning, the Mets led, 7-2.</p>
        <p>''I know his history is not great with three days' rest,'' La Russa said before the game, ''but we're not in an ideal situation with our rotation.''</p>
        <p>Kile had started 12 games in his career on three days of rest. He had won three times and lost eight, compiling a 6.98 earned run average.</p>
        <p>''I pitched terrible,'' Kile said, refusing to blame his performance on abbreviated rest. ''I warmed up great, felt great, felt strong. I went out there and the ball was up the whole game and they hit every ball hard. The bottom line is I made a lot of mistakes and they hit them all.''</p>
        <p>To Kile, the most important pitch he made was the hanging breaking ball Zeile hit for the two-run double. What were the pitches the Mets swatted for doubles?</p>
        <p>''It doesn't matter which pitch you throw,'' he said. ''They're all up in the zone. When that happens, pitches flatten out and they're very hittable. I threw a lot of hittable pitches and they hit them.''</p>
        <p>For the Cardinals to play that Game 7 La Russa talked about having Kile pitch, they will first have to win what for them are two other Game 7's.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
