<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Texas Democrats Say Bush Exaggerated State Spending on Health Care for Uninsured</title>
    <meta content="Y16HEA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/politics/16HEAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239348"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CREDIBILITY ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DF1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="872" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Texas Democrats Say Bush Exaggerated State Spending on Health Care for Uninsured</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three Texas state legislators said today that Gov. George W. Bush had exaggerated state spending on health care for uninsured people in Texas, taking credit for large amounts of charity care provided by private doctors and hospitals.</p>
        <p>The legislators, all Democrats, made the assertions in separate interviews today and in a letter to Vice President Al Gore, the Democratic candidate for president. The Bush campaign rejected the criticism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three Texas state legislators said today that Gov. George W. Bush had exaggerated state spending on health care for uninsured people in Texas, taking credit for large amounts of charity care provided by private doctors and hospitals.</p>
        <p>The legislators, all Democrats, made the assertions in separate interviews today and in a letter to Vice President Al Gore, the Democratic candidate for president. The Bush campaign rejected the criticism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, the Republican presidential nominee, has repeatedly accused Mr. Gore of embellishing and distorting the truth. Aides to Mr. Gore said he would try to turn the tables on Mr. Bush this week, highlighting instances in which Democrats believe the governor has overstated his commitment to the health and welfare of indigent Texans.</p>
        <p>On three occasions in their debate last week, Mr. Bush said, ''We spent $4.7 billion a year in the state of Texas for uninsured people.'' However, a recent report by the state comptroller says $3.5 billion, or three-fourths of that amount, resulted from charity care provided by doctors and hospitals and care financed by local governments or charitable institutions.</p>
        <p>The letter to Mr. Gore, to be released at a political event in St. Louis on Monday, says Mr. Bush's statements on health care in Texas were misleading.</p>
        <p>''Of the $4.7 billion referenced by the governor,'' the letter says, ''$3.5 billion consists of charitable care provided by hospitals in their emergency rooms, private physicians, charities, local governments and free clinics, none of which is paid for by the state.''</p>
        <p>The letter was signed by senior members of the Texas House of Representatives: Elliott Naishtat, chairman of the Human Services Committee; Glen Maxey, vice chairman of the committee; and Garnet F. Coleman, vice chairman of the Public Health Committee.</p>
        <p>Dan Bartlett, a spokesman for the Bush campaign, said Governor Bush did not mean to imply that all of the $4.7 billion was state money.</p>
        <p>''The governor was merely explaining that, contrary to Al Gore's distortions, people in Texas do have access to health care,'' Mr. Bartlett said. ''We have a double safety net to make sure that people who don't have insurance receive the care they need.''</p>
        <p>In a report last month, summarizing data from 1997 to 1999, the Census Bureau said that 24 percent of Texans had no health insurance. The figure was higher in Texas than in any other state, the bureau said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett said this problem had existed for decades and could be partly attributed to the fact that Texas was ''a fast-growing state with a large immigrant population.'' Hispanic Americans are twice as likely to be uninsured as the general population, in part because many work for small businesses that do not offer coverage.</p>
        <p>But the Democratic state legislators contend that Mr. Bush bears some of the responsibility.</p>
        <p>In the debate, Mr. Bush acknowledged that the Children's Health Insurance Program ''got a late start'' in Texas. The reason, he said, is that the State Legislature ''meets only four months out of every two years.''</p>
        <p>But the legislators said Mr. Bush had resisted their efforts to make coverage available to children in families with incomes up to twice the poverty level (up to $28,300 for a family of three).</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett confirmed that Mr. Bush had initially wanted to limit eligibility to families with incomes up to 1.5 times the poverty level. He said Mr. Bush was concerned about the cost and the ''spillover effects'' on other programs, particularly Medicaid.</p>
        <p>In aggressively seeking out people eligible for the new children's health program, states invariably find other youngsters who qualify for Medicaid, so Medicaid costs tend to increase.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush ultimately accepted the more generous eligibility criteria favored by the State Legislature, but Democratic legislators said he had helped delay coverage for needy Texas children.</p>
        <p>Congress created the Children's Health Insurance Program under a law signed by President Clinton in August 1997. Texas used some of the money to expand its Medicaid program in 1998. The Texas Legislature created a separate program in 1999, and the state has enrolled more than 110,000 children since it began taking applications in April of this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maxey said enrollment could have begun earlier if the state had done more planning and preparation.</p>
        <p>Stan Dorn, director of the Health Consumer Alliance, a consumer assistance group based in California, said, ''Texas missed a golden opportunity to provide health insurance for low-income children in 1998 by using the proceeds of a settlement with the tobacco industry.''</p>
        <p>Under the settlement, Texas is to receive $15.3 billion over 25 years. Dan Morales, a Democrat, was attorney general of Texas in January 1998, when the settlement was negotiated. Mr. Morales wanted to earmark some of the money for immediate use in the Children's Health Insurance Program.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush and legislative leaders of both parties insisted that decisions about how to spend the money should be made by the State Legislature, which did not meet until 1999.</p>
        <p>''The attorney general did not have the constitutional authority to decide unilaterally how the money should be spent,'' said Mr. Bartlett, a spokesman for the governor.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE CREDIBILITY ISSUE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
