<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using a Bit of 007 to Keep Spies in Check</title>
    <meta content="16SCAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/technology/16SCAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COMPRESSED DATA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0DA113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using a Bit of 007 to Keep Spies in Check</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For those who have ever had the sneaking suspicion that someone is spying on them, Mick W. Stwertnik is selling a device to help them figure out whether they have valid concerns or need to consider counseling.</p>
        <p>The Plus Guard, a hand-held gadget the size of a makeup compact, lets users scan their surroundings for hidden audio bugs or wireless miniature cameras that may be be capturing sounds or pictures. When such a surveillance device is in the area, a red light goes on and an alarm on the Plus Guard sounds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For those who have ever had the sneaking suspicion that someone is spying on them, Mick W. Stwertnik is selling a device to help them figure out whether they have valid concerns or need to consider counseling.</p>
        <p>The Plus Guard, a hand-held gadget the size of a makeup compact, lets users scan their surroundings for hidden audio bugs or wireless miniature cameras that may be be capturing sounds or pictures. When such a surveillance device is in the area, a red light goes on and an alarm on the Plus Guard sounds.</p>
        <p>''For example, if somebody hides a hidden camera transmitter in your bedroom or bathroom, this device will pick up the transmission and tell you there's a camera,'' said Mr. Stwertnik, vice president for sales at the NCG Company in Anaheim, Calif., which sells the surveillance snooper for $42 (www.theplusguard .com).</p>
        <p>But the question is, just how prevalent are hidden cameras? Is each home, hotel room or public restroom a potential set for Big Brother?</p>
        <p>Mr. Stwertnik insists that the use of hidden devices will become more prevalent as the cost of surveillance equipment drops. Not long ago, he said, miniature wireless cameras were $2,000 to $3,000 but now can be bought for $300 or less.</p>
        <p>Potential customers for the Plus Guard, he said, might include people concerned that their former spouses  seem to know too much about their private lives or parents worried about their children at college who must share a dormitory suite and bathroom.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Stwertnik's own anecdotal evidence has not uncovered rampant surveillance of friends, neighbors and strangers. In the two months since Mr. Stwertnik began United States distribution of the Plus Guard, which is made by a Tokyo company, Ram Electronics, he has sold 100 of the gadgets. So far, he has received  no reports of customers' uncovering hidden cameras or bugs. But it is only a matter of time, he insisted.</p>
        <p>Don't say you haven't been warned.</p>
        <p>MATT RICHTEL</p>
        <p>COMPRESSED DATA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
