<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Actor Sees Politics in Editing of Film</title>
    <meta content="16FILM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/business/16FILM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DEEDA113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Actor Sees Politics in Editing of Film</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX KUCZYNSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''The Contender,'' the DreamWorks SKG film released last Friday, Gary Oldman plays a balding, nasty Republican congressman bent on destroying the reputation of an elegant, righteous Democratic vice presidential nominee, played by Joan Allen. And Mr. Oldman, who in real life is politically conservative, is furious.</p>
        <p>In the November issue of Premiere magazine, Mr. Oldman and his manager, Douglas Urbanski, also a producer of the film, argue that DreamWorks massaged the movie's editing process so that Mr. Oldman's character is portrayed as a villain -- not as the multifaceted Republican hero Mr. Oldman agreed to play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''The Contender,'' the DreamWorks SKG film released last Friday, Gary Oldman plays a balding, nasty Republican congressman bent on destroying the reputation of an elegant, righteous Democratic vice presidential nominee, played by Joan Allen. And Mr. Oldman, who in real life is politically conservative, is furious.</p>
        <p>In the November issue of Premiere magazine, Mr. Oldman and his manager, Douglas Urbanski, also a producer of the film, argue that DreamWorks massaged the movie's editing process so that Mr. Oldman's character is portrayed as a villain -- not as the multifaceted Republican hero Mr. Oldman agreed to play.</p>
        <p>The actor is quoted in Premiere as saying he was angered by the duplicity of DreamWorks and was surprised that ''more people have not been murdered in the entertainment industry.''</p>
        <p>Last week, DreamWorks executives denied the film was deliberately cut to cast the Republican character in a harsh light. They said Mr. Oldman had first seen a director's cut of the movie that ran three-and-a-half hours, in which his role was more substantial and the political nuances perhaps more right-leaning, and that might be why he felt misled. But that version was never intended for theatrical release.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Urbanski is sticking to his guns. ''The movie endeavored to show that in politics there are no good guys and bad guys. It is not black and white,'' he said of the film's original intent. ''But given the very loud professed public opinions of those at DreamWorks, it can't help but raise the question that if this movie clicks with the critics or at the box office, is there a chance that it is the ultimate political commercial?''</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Katzenberg, one of the three owners of DreamWorks, said in an interview last week that ''The Contender'' was not cut to slant the film, which was released two weeks before the election, nor was Mr. Oldman's role diminished because of his political allegiances off-screen.</p>
        <p>''Gary Oldman has given an Academy Award-winning performance,'' Mr. Katzenberg said. ''We will be supporting him with the best possible Oscar campaign that we can.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
