<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adding Manners to Muscle To Make a Football Team</title>
    <meta content="Y16MAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/national/16MANN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3D7113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adding Manners to Muscle To Make a Football Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>PERRINE, Fla, Oct. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Thursday nights in the fall, it is Eddie Estes' job to help with the heavy hitting and pushing, to whack the other guy so hard he will see stars and finally plunge helplessly to the ground, after a bone-crushing tackle.</p>
        <p>On the football field, there is no such thing as a gentleman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Thursday nights in the fall, it is Eddie Estes' job to help with the heavy hitting and pushing, to whack the other guy so hard he will see stars and finally plunge helplessly to the ground, after a bone-crushing tackle.</p>
        <p>On the football field, there is no such thing as a gentleman.</p>
        <p>But at Coral Reef Senior High School, a public school in this suburb  south of Miami, proper etiquette is required of Eddie, 17, and other players to stay on the team.</p>
        <p>That is because his coach, Ernest Perkins, is not like many other head football coaches. Just as surely as he wants to build better linebackers and quarterbacks, Mr. Perkins wants to build better human beings.</p>
        <p>And that is why, in addition to requiring each of his 79 players to run more than a mile every day and lift weights almost as often, Mr. Perkins insists that they take hourlong etiquette classes, about once a month during football season.</p>
        <p>In a game that is notorious for its aggressive nature and players' violent, boorish tendencies, teaching etiquette might seem contradictory. But at Coral Reef there are only two options under coach Perkins -- behave like a ''man of honor'' or watch from the sidelines.</p>
        <p>''There are too many disrespectful and uneducated athletes out there,'' Mr. Perkins said. ''If you play by my rules, you're going to be a complete athlete, and etiquette is a huge chunk of that.''</p>
        <p>As a part of the etiquette training, the players learn poise, how to engage in gentle conversation and the art of tying a necktie.</p>
        <p>During a class this week, players gathered in the library as Myoushi Jones, an etiquette teacher from Miami, demonstrated table manners using an overhead projector.</p>
        <p>''You want to be able to dine like a diplomat,'' Mrs. Jones said. ''Because people will invite you out all the time to discuss business.''</p>
        <p>''Don't forget what Oscar Wilde once said,'' she added. ''He said, 'The world was my oyster, but I used the wrong fork.' ''</p>
        <p>The players nodded, some smiling.</p>
        <p>''So, who can tell me the proper way to eat soup?'' Mrs. Jones asked as she held up an empty soup bowl.</p>
        <p>''If there are two handles on the bowl, it is O.K. to pick up the bowl and sip,'' one player said. Mrs. Jones beamed in agreement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perkins, who had taught a similar program at a competing high school, brought the classes to Coral Reef three years ago after watching the confused looks on his players' faces during a banquet.</p>
        <p>Since then, the classes have grown more advanced, although the team's record has slipped. But the goal is to augment play rather than improve it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perkins does not only require his students to learn about dressing well, he expects them to practice what they have learned. Every Monday at school, even as temperatures reach the 90's, each player is required to wear a crisp, long-sleeved white shirt, tailored black or gray dress slacks and a black Coral Reef High School football necktie, with the initials C.R. at the bottom.</p>
        <p>They are also required to carry a briefcase.</p>
        <p>''It's about dress for success,'' Mr. Perkins said. ''It's about the future. I don't want to see my guys on the corner. I want to see them on the Wall Street corner. That's the plan.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
