<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Testaverde's Example of Quiet and Resilient Heroism</title>
    <meta content="16RHOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/sports/16RHOD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239364"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DB1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Testaverde's Example of Quiet and Resilient Heroism</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <dateline>FOXBORO, Mass.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHILE Subway Series fever permeated New York City, up here in the anonymity of a New England autumn, the Jets laid the foundation of a season and put a quarterback's career in perspective, if not back on track.</p>
        <p>This was an afternoon in which running back Curtis Martin, the heart and soul of the Jets, scored three touchdowns and battered a hard-nosed New England defense for 143 yards in the Jets' 34-17 victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHILE Subway Series fever permeated New York City, up here in the anonymity of a New England autumn, the Jets laid the foundation of a season and put a quarterback's career in perspective, if not back on track.</p>
        <p>This was an afternoon in which running back Curtis Martin, the heart and soul of the Jets, scored three touchdowns and battered a hard-nosed New England defense for 143 yards in the Jets' 34-17 victory.</p>
        <p>It was an afternoon in which the tough linebacker Mo Lewis anchored a Jets defense that was alternately crunching and suffocating. The defense forced six turnovers and produced a touchdown when Lewis batted a ball that Victor Green intercepted and carried it in.</p>
        <p>Even the Jets' special teams were stellar. They accounted for a crucial first down on a fake field goal in the second quarter when Lewis took a quick pitch and ran for a first down. Four plays later, the Jets scored.</p>
        <p>But in an odd way, on an afternoon dominated by so many other elements, an important sliver of this day belonged to Vinny Testaverde, the Jets' battered quarterback.</p>
        <p>Quietly, Testaverde turned in a performance that was heroic, not so much for the numbers he posted (15 for 23 for 139 yards), but for his resilience, for hanging in there, for leading by example.</p>
        <p>Last week, Testaverde was injured on the Jets' first offensive play of the game by Pittsburgh's Jason Gildon. He left with a pinched nerve in his neck. He has been struggling with nerve damage in his neck since he was hit in the first game of the season against New England, and the pain radiates throughout his non throwing arm, causing weakness and numbness.</p>
        <p>Without him, the Jets lost in a rout last week; the loss created doubts among Jets fans where there had been optimism. The bulging disk in his neck and the tingling sensation in his left arm were still there yesterday afternoon. ''There's still some numbness in my hand,'' he said.</p>
        <p>After yesterday's game, Testaverde said he was resigned to the fact that the pain will be with him throughout the season. He'll take the cortisone shots to deaden the pain.</p>
        <p>''I'll expect the tingling sensation down my left arm,'' he said. ''If that's all it is, I'm fine with it. If it stays like this, I'm fine with it.''</p>
        <p>In 1998, Testaverde was reborn. He won the American Football Conference passer rating title. The most important statistic was his touchdown-to-interception ratio of 29 to 7, fourth best in National Football League history.</p>
        <p>In many ways, Testaverde has been haunted by the success in 1998, when the Jets came within a game of reaching the Super Bowl. But even when he reached the A.F.C. championship game, many football experts still doubted his ability to avoid mistakes and make sound decisions in key moments of games.</p>
        <p>Last season, in the first half of the first game, Testaverde ruptured his Achilles' tendon while diving for a fumble and missed the rest of the season. This season, he was benched for one series against Tampa Bay but came back to lead the Jets to a come-from-behind victory.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Testaverde was efficient and functional. Far from his pre-1998 years, when he felt he had to do all things and be all things, this Testaverde took what he could and nothing more.</p>
        <p>''Coach Parcells sat me down and told me I don't have to do everything,'' he said of Bill Parcells, who was the Jets' coach when he arrived. ''Everybody has to earn their paycheck.''</p>
        <p>Nothing complex: the passing game is not awesome. The leading receivers on the team are the running backs -- Curtis Martin (23 catches) and Richie Anderson (24). Wayne Chrebet and his fellow starting wideout Dedric Ward combined for only three completions yesterday. They had only 34 receptions going into the game. Laveranues Coles, the third-round draft choice from Florida State and the team's truest sprinter, caught 6 passes for 53 yards.</p>
        <p>Testaverde turns 37 on Nov. 13. Is his body beginning to break down?</p>
        <p>''It seems everybody wants to talk about my age,'' he said. ''Maybe I'm stubborn, but I don't want to admit this has anything to do with my age. This is part of playing in the N.F.L., the risks of the job.''</p>
        <p>Testaverde is teaching lessons and may not know it. Ray Lucas, the quarterback in waiting, said he learned a huge lesson yesterday.</p>
        <p>''I'm still learning from him,'' Lucas said. ''Today he taught me about toughness.''</p>
        <p>This is Testaverde's formula for redemption: One great runner.  Strong defense. Sure-handed, short, efficient passing game.</p>
        <p>''We're a pretty good team, we're not great,'' Testaverde said. ''For us to be successful, we have to play as a team. One thing we have that other teams don't have is mental toughness. After everything we went through last season, with all the injuries, we're mentally tough. That's why we're 5-1.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
