<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Writer Wildly Tearing Up His Life to Feed His Art</title>
    <meta content="16SHAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/arts/16SHAP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239323"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E3D8113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Writer Wildly Tearing Up His Life to Feed His Art</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES SHAPIRO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BELLOW  A Biography  By James Atlas  Illustrated. 686 pages. Random House. $35.</p>
        <p>''I write from about 8 o'clock in the morning until 1,'' Saul Bellow once told an interviewer. ''Then I go out and make my mistakes.'' As James Atlas makes clear in this exhaustively researched biography, Mr. Bellow's literary output and his mistakes have been equally prodigious.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BELLOW  A Biography  By James Atlas  Illustrated. 686 pages. Random House. $35.</p>
        <p>''I write from about 8 o'clock in the morning until 1,'' Saul Bellow once told an interviewer. ''Then I go out and make my mistakes.'' As James Atlas makes clear in this exhaustively researched biography, Mr. Bellow's literary output and his mistakes have been equally prodigious.</p>
        <p>He has produced one of the most remarkable bodies of work by an American novelist: most notably ''Dangling Man'' (1944), ''The Adventures of Augie March'' (1953), ''Seize the Day'' (1956), ''Henderson the Rain King'' (1959), ''Herzog'' (1964) and ''Humboldt's Gift'' (1975). He has also racked up most major literary awards, including a Pulitzer Prize, three National Book Awards and in 1976 the Nobel Prize in Literature.</p>
        <p>Viewed in retrospect Mr. Bellow's long reign near the top of the American literary scene seems inevitable, almost preordained. Yet Mr. Atlas shows that it was anything but. He offers us glimpses of Mr. Bellow, unemployed and unpublished, writing at his mother-in-law's house while his young wife went off to work. At 25 he had yet to sell a story.</p>
        <p>Fifteen years later, though a National Book Award winner, Mr. Bellow was disappointed that his fourth novel, the much admired ''Seize the Day,'' had barely sold 5,000 copies, and was still accepting money from a father who was contemptuous of his literary aspirations. Mr. Bellow himself, Mr. Atlas shows, was never in doubt about his talent.</p>
        <p>Because each of his novels reaches deeply into his past, offering ''a bulletin on his own condition'' invariably distorted by nostalgia and spite, Mr. Bellow has long had misgivings about anyone's relying on his fiction to get an accurate fix on his life. ''Biography,'' he warned, ''is a specter viewed by a specter.''</p>
        <p>''Bellow'' isn't an authorized biography, but, as Mr. Atlas tells us, Mr. Bellow didn't refuse him, as he has refused others, permission to quote freely from letters, manuscripts and unpublished work. Mr. Bellow, who turned 85 last summer, was eventually won over by Mr. Atlas's dogged persistence. When Mr. Atlas asked Mr. Bellow's son Dan, ''Why did he let me do it?,'' Dan explained, ''He realized that you weren't going to go away.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Atlas the central dynamic in Mr. Bellow's career has been his tendency ''to tear up his life to feed his art'': it ''was as if he needed some obstacle, some impediment, to define himself against.'' Mr. Atlas's primary interest, then, is less Mr. Bellow's ideas or philosophy (which leave him cold) than the stormy marriages and literary friendships that became fodder for his fiction. Much of this hefty biography is taken up with the fallout of Mr. Bellow's failed marriages. (He is now with a fifth wife, 44 years his junior, with whom he had a daughter last year.)</p>
        <p>Like the women in Mr. Bellow's novels, Mr. Atlas argues, the ''women in his life remained for him secondary figures who served his own fantasies of them as providers, entrappers, sexual predators.'' For Mr. Atlas, Mr. Bellow's philandering and sexism were ''still well within the normal range of male chauvinism for his day''; he is more persuasive in tracing Mr. Bellow's trouble with women back to the central trauma of his life: the death of his mother when he was a teenager, a loss Mr. Bellow never properly mourned. The men in his life haven't fared much better: Mr. Bellow regularly missed the funerals of close friends, reviled his enemies and never forgave a negative reviewer. ''Bellow wasn't a nurturing person,'' Mr. Atlas suggests, because ''he wanted the nurturing.''</p>
        <p>Weaving together the artistic triumphs and personal crises, Mr. Atlas captures the enormous excitement that greeted each of Mr. Bellow's groundbreaking novels of the 1950's and early 60's. He also shows how challenges to the establishment in the 1960's and early 70's upended Mr. Bellow's familiar role as outsider and victim. Where Mr. Bellow, the youngest son of poor Jewish immigrants, had long struggled to gain a foothold within ''the WASP literary establishment,'' he now found himself defending the high culture that had finally embraced him and was now under siege.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bellow grew older, Mr. Atlas writes, ''the bones of a deeply conservative, xenophobic vision of life emerged more clearly.'' The low point was Mr. Bellow's unfortunate remark: ''Who is the Tolstoy of the Zulus? The Proust of the Papuans? I'd be glad to read him.''</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Atlas's approach depends on discovering chunks of Mr. Bellow's life in his art, he tends to underestimate the extent to which Mr. Bellow has utterly transformed events from his life in his fiction, even when surface similarities teasingly remain. Mr. Bellow himself has chastised Mr. Atlas for ''confusing fact with fiction.''</p>
        <p>In practice this means that Mr. Atlas can confidently declare that a character's first sight of his wife in ''Herzog'' ''faithfully reproduces'' Mr. Bellow's own experience, and he can insist, over Mr. Bellow's objections, that ''Humboldt's Gift'' is really a portrait of Delmore Schwartz (the subject of Mr. Atlas's previous biography) and then accuse Mr. Bellow of failing to get Schwartz right.</p>
        <p>At the heart of this book is an unanswered question: Do the many unsettling facts Mr. Atlas unearths about Mr. Bellow's personal life devalue the novels, which he sees as emerging directly from Mr. Bellow's experiences? Or, alternatively, does Mr. Bellow's art somehow transcend the life, in which case why bother writing (or reading) literary biography? It is hard to understand why Mr. Atlas would spend more than a decade amassing the facts of Mr. Bellow's life and then sidestep the question of how they affect how he -- and by extension we -- now judge the novels and Mr. Bellow's place in the pantheon of American writers. It is the only serious flaw in a biography unlikely to be surpassed for some time.</p>
        <p>The most melancholy page in ''Bellow'' appears in the acknowledgments, where Mr. Atlas lists those who have helped him who have since died, including Ralph Ellison, Leon Edel, Irving Howe, Saul Steinberg and Diana and Lionel Trilling. The list underscores the extent to which Mr. Atlas's ''Bellow'' is not only a compelling story of a great and flawed writer, one who continues to demand our attention, but also a portrait of an extraordinary (and now rapidly receding) epoch in the history of American letters.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES James Shapiro is a professor of English at Columbia University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Shapiro is a professor of English at Columbia University.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
