<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tale of Recovery From a Bad Boy Of Letters; Will Self Explores the Dangers Of Self-Obsession and Drugs In a Dark, Impudent Satire</title>
    <meta content="16SELF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/arts/16SELF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE3D9113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tale of Recovery From a Bad Boy Of Letters; Will Self Explores the Dangers Of Self-Obsession and Drugs In a Dark, Impudent Satire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was no moment of crisis, no particular cataclysm that forced the novelist Will Self finally to renounce the destructive habits that were overrunning his life. Unless you count the time he was caught taking heroin on Prime Minister John Major's campaign plane.</p>
        <p>''It was humiliating,'' said Mr. Self, 39, the author of 10 novels and short-story collections, with uncharacteristic brevity. But the incident, which got him very publicly fired from his reporting job at The Observer of London, also helped enhance his personal mystique as the baddest of London's bad-boy novelists. (Martin Amis, the previous holder of the title, was already pushing 50.) ''Let me put it this way: it's not like anybody was refusing to serve me a drink,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was no moment of crisis, no particular cataclysm that forced the novelist Will Self finally to renounce the destructive habits that were overrunning his life. Unless you count the time he was caught taking heroin on Prime Minister John Major's campaign plane.</p>
        <p>''It was humiliating,'' said Mr. Self, 39, the author of 10 novels and short-story collections, with uncharacteristic brevity. But the incident, which got him very publicly fired from his reporting job at The Observer of London, also helped enhance his personal mystique as the baddest of London's bad-boy novelists. (Martin Amis, the previous holder of the title, was already pushing 50.) ''Let me put it this way: it's not like anybody was refusing to serve me a drink,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That was three years ago. It was sometime last year that Mr. Self decided he had had enough: enough of the drugs, enough of the drinking, enough of the explosive argumentative nights and the inevitable fallings-out with friends. His latest novel, ''How the Dead Live,'' is the first book he has written, he said recently, while under the influence of no illegal substances of any kind.</p>
        <p>''You know in those movies where you see the stereotypical shambolic drunk, that absolutely culturally recognized person who cannot control intoxication, who's unmanageable?'' he asked. ''Well, I just didn't buy it, but that was me.''</p>
        <p>It is odd to hear Mr. Self, with his spiky intellect; deep, lazily amused voice; considerable charisma; and formidably havoc-wreaking reputation, speak in the earnest language of recovery. He is as visually striking as his fiction, full of lush, show-offy words, is linguistically striking. Tall and lean, with a narrow, angular face of which the nose is the most prominent feature, he suggests a camel of superior intelligence. As he sits in his artfully decorated living room in South London, smoking (it will be the next habit to go, he promises), he looks at times like Joe Camel himself.</p>
        <p>Because he has three children -- two from his first marriage, which ended in 1993, and one from his second, to a newspaper columnist who has helped bring rigor and stability to his life -- Mr. Self's self-imposed detox regime has been of necessity quick and rooted in practicality. He flew to upstate New York and spent several days shivering and being sick in bed at the house of one of his brothers, who lives there now, and then went to Manhattan to interview the feminist Andrea Dworkin for a 4,000-word magazine article. Later he presented himself at a 12-step recovery program.</p>
        <p>''It would be lovely to go into some sort of F. Scott Fitzgerald 'Tender Is the Night' sanitarium where someone is going to bring you cucumber sandwiches with the crusts cut off,'' he said. ''But how much better to have to face the bills and the kids and the responsibilities you have, as soon as possible.''</p>
        <p>''How the Dead Live'' is full of familiar Selfian touches. There are broad satires on modern life, relentlessly splenetic opinions and clever linguistic riffs that he may well have included for his own amusement. London is ''an encrustation upon a scab''; a dull restaurant is made up of ''the bland feeding the bland''; workers from a drug-treatment center arrive with ''sinisterly avaricious promptitude.'' It is a book that has divided critics, as Mr. Self's novels often do, with the general complaint being that he can sometimes let his formidable talents run too wild.</p>
        <p>''The unruliness and extravagance of Self's writing is both his strength and his failing,'' wrote Katie Owen in The Sunday Telegraph. ''His exorbitant imagination is stimulating, his wordplay dazzling, but in his longer fiction he seems carried away by his own powers, his satirical effect blunted.''</p>
        <p>Most critics agreed that this book was more disciplined than earlier novels, with more of a classically linear narrative. It can be read another way, too: as a sobering cautionary tale about the perils of drug taking. One of its main characters, Natasha, is a beautiful, charming, selfish and doomed heroin addict.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to write about the awful karmic outcome of having a materialist, self-conscious, self-obsessed life,'' Mr. Self said of the novel. ''In the process of engaging with it, on one level I realized I was going to have to clean myself up. Natasha's fate is, in part at least, an admonition to myself.''</p>
        <p>The novel chronicles the painful death and unhappy afterlife of one Lily Bloom, an angry Jewish American expat in London who succumbs to breast cancer and then finds herself assigned -- maybe for eternity -- to Dulston, a boring London dead people's suburb filled with boring London dead people. As she tries to make her way through her death -- she joins ''Personally Dead,'' a self-help group in which the recently deceased discuss topics like ''Why Are We Dead?,'' and takes a job in a public relations agency in which none of her colleagues notice that she is, in fact, not alive -- she finds that dying has not solved her problems.</p>
        <p>''It's about somebody who believes that reflective self-consciousness and the identity that that engenders is the paramount aspect of what it means to be a person,'' he said. ''Lily won't let go of that reflective self-consciousness, won't let go of that thinking I, so after death she is confronted by the disintegration of it.''</p>
        <p>Lily is based largely on Mr. Self's own mother, an American who lived in London. (Mr. Self's father, an English college professor, died several years ago.) His ambivalence toward her -- he describes their relationship as ''fetid and embroiled'' -- was not helped by the discovery, after she died in 1988, that she had been keeping a diary of her bitterness and unhappiness for 40 years. Among other things, she turned her caustic eye on her own son.</p>
        <p>''It was a shock to read what she wrote about me, because it was there in cold print,'' he said. ''But it was mixed up with an enormous amount of pain and pathos. I got into hard drugs and was very seriously ill with it when I was young, and it was devastating for her, and I have no doubt that it really hurt her. I can only feel sorry about that and feel sorry for my part in it.''</p>
        <p>In some ways it is less surprising that Mr. Self finally weaned himself from drugs than that he was able to produce so much fiction, and at such a high pitch, while gripped in their vise. His addiction came in his teens, when, he said, he was ''anti-authority, anti-society, anti-police: a risk-taking countercultural juvenile delinquent.'' He worked at various jobs and didn't start writing in earnest until his mother died, but his output since has been prodigious. In addition to the fiction he has produced a steady stream of profiles, reviews and columns for British newspapers.</p>
        <p>''For 10 years I would isolate myself, get off drugs, write and then go back on again, on and off, on and off, on and off,'' he said. ''It was awful of course. It's awful and terrible for the people around you. Of course I functioned at a level. I looked after my kids and changed nappies and earned money and cleaned the house. But I was getting so addled that I couldn't pass a sentence. I was lucid enough to write, but I was getting to the point where all alcoholic and drug-addicted writers get, where I was starting to parody myself.''</p>
        <p>His fiction is most notable for its use of an imagination that manages to be bizarre and weirdly plausible at the same time, with strangely skewed worlds that are still internally consistent. ''I've never been attracted by naturalism,'' he said. ''Why paint up what people seem to think is a commonly perceived world when with just a few little tweaks you can make them believe that sanity is a mere statistical correlate, or that chimpanzees are the successful species in the world?'' he said, speaking of ''The Quantity Theory of Insanity,'' his first novel, and ''Great Apes,'' which was published in 1997.</p>
        <p>But will his imagination suffer without the drugs?</p>
        <p>''There are certainly other ways to write,'' Mr. Self said. ''I don't think I'll ever be a kind of diaphanous creature in a silk dressing gown writing in violet ink and taking infinite pains over sentences. I'll always have this kind of extreme, fanatical quality about writing. Do I think I'll be able to produce better books if I'm more mellow? I hope so.''</p>
        <p>And maybe the books will be happier, too. ''Maybe I can get there to experience some peace of mind and some joie de vivre and to write about those things,'' Mr. Self said. ''It really is, on the whole, terra incognita for me. I'm up for grabs now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
