<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reluctant Stars Turn Bull Run into a Texas Trot</title>
    <meta content="Y16BUL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/national/16BULL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6DD1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reluctant Stars Turn Bull Run into a Texas Trot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSS E. MILLOY</byline>
      <dateline>JARRELL, Tex., Oct. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Somewhere up in he-man heaven, Ernest Hemingway must be spinning like a lathe.</p>
        <p>About 800 people gathered just north of this small farming community on Saturday to witness the first-ever ''Running of the Bulls -- Texas Style,'' and although the event's sponsors had promised excitement to match the Pamplona tradition immortalized by Mr. Hemingway in ''The Sun Also Rises,'' most observers went away underwhelmed.</p>
        <p>Oh, the atmosphere was festive and colorful, with karaoke singers belting out country tunes, a blimp circling overhead and cowboys wearing belt buckles the size of frying pans. The fine bulls and brave young men were there as well, and you could see the fear in their eyes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Somewhere up in he-man heaven, Ernest Hemingway must be spinning like a lathe.</p>
        <p>About 800 people gathered just north of this small farming community on Saturday to witness the first-ever ''Running of the Bulls -- Texas Style,'' and although the event's sponsors had promised excitement to match the Pamplona tradition immortalized by Mr. Hemingway in ''The Sun Also Rises,'' most observers went away underwhelmed.</p>
        <p>Oh, the atmosphere was festive and colorful, with karaoke singers belting out country tunes, a blimp circling overhead and cowboys wearing belt buckles the size of frying pans. The fine bulls and brave young men were there as well, and you could see the fear in their eyes.</p>
        <p>The bulls' eyes, that is.</p>
        <p>The setting, in a mowed cornfield  flanked by mobile homes and hills like white grasshoppers, sported hundreds of Not Responsible For Accidents signs and, some felt, lacked the charm of the old Spanish city's cobblestone streets.</p>
        <p>The bulls, mostly Herefords, Watusis and Brahmans, were primarily beef cattle as opposed to the long-horned fighting bulls used in Pamplona.</p>
        <p>And, instead of the nearly 100 runners who had paid $75 to participate, only 19 men and one woman showed up to make the run on Saturday near this town north of Austin.</p>
        <p>''Perhaps they had second thoughts,'' suggested the event's organizer, Derik Strelsky, a former rodeo performer.</p>
        <p>That is not unlikely, given that the two-page waiver the runners had to sign began, ''By participating in this event you may die or become seriously injured.''</p>
        <p>The waiver also warned runners to be wary of other participants while running: ''These individuals may be mentally ill, criminally insane, drunk, under the influence of illegal drugs, and/or armed with deadly weapons.''</p>
        <p>Despite the waiver's suggestions regarding their mental health, most runners seemed merely interested in a little adventure.</p>
        <p>Jason Kinder, 31, a software systems administrator from Dallas, said, ''This is my chance to meet hot blond chicks.''</p>
        <p>Kennard Bibb, 48, a physical therapist from San Antonio, said he was persuaded to run by residents of the retirement center where he works.</p>
        <p>''They got all pumped up when they heard about it,'' Mr. Bibb said, ''so I just volunteered to come run with the bulls and tell them what it was like.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bibb, at least, had a strategy. ''The game plan is to stay ahead of them and stay alive,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And what did his wife think of his participation? ''She thinks I'm crazy,'' Mr. Bibb said.</p>
        <p>For Pam and Wallace Henderson, who recently moved to Texas from Washington, running with the bulls offered an exhilarating adventure to share with their friends back East.</p>
        <p>''When I tell them what I'm doing they're not going to believe it,'' Mrs. Henderson, 53, said.</p>
        <p>''And, looking on the bright side, at least the bulls won't be trying to eat us,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her husband, a political consultant, said: ''I'm in Washington politics. We do this all the time, except there instead of running with the bull we're running from it.''</p>
        <p>Unlike the raucous free-for-all among thousands of runners and hundreds of bulls common in Pamplona, the Texas-style bull run had rules, lots of rules, which were explained at the registration desk.</p>
        <p>''No drinking?'' said one shocked Texan who was barred from participating because of the beer can in his hand. ''Who would do this sober?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Perhaps unaware of the origins of the bull running tradition, he walked away muttering, ''That's un-American.''</p>
        <p>As they approached the registration desk, Vicki Knutson, who was not running, asked first, ''Where's the beer?'' Her companion, who was running, asked, ''More importantly, where's the ambulance?''</p>
        <p>(It was parked behind a shed, Mr. Strelsky said.)</p>
        <p>As 20 bulls, mostly Herefords and Brahmans, were loaded into a chute, the runners waited in a roped off area called the bullpen sharing some gallows humor. ''Just think of the money we're saving by not flying to Spain,'' one said.</p>
        <p>While the runners eyed the bulls, one participant, Eric Allen, a Waco television reporter who was wearing a coat and tie, asked them: ''Well, you've seen the competition, what do you think?''</p>
        <p>''I think we'll do O.K.,'' Mr. Henderson replied.</p>
        <p>''Michael Johnson never had this kind of motivation,'' said another runner referring to the American sprinter who won the men's 400 meters at the Olympics in Sydney.</p>
        <p>Spectators lined the corridor of cattle fencing as the big moment neared, chanting, ''Go, go, go.'' The runners spread out, some near the gates, some a respectful 30 to 40 yards away. After an expectant pause, the crowd cheered as the gates were thrown open and the runners started their dash.</p>
        <p>The bulls, however, seemed merely confused. They mooed softly and then began to walk leisurely down the corridor. It took several cowboys on horseback to finally urge them into a half-hearted canter, but by then most of the runners had already reached the arena.</p>
        <p>''Here I was running for all I was worth and I looked back and I was all alone. The bulls were way back at the other end. Man, that was embarrassing,'' Mr. Allen said.</p>
        <p>They released the bulls a second time with the cowboys trying to make the bulls more energetic, and at least one of the runners was actually touched by a bull as it strolled past. Or so he said.</p>
        <p>There was one casualty: a dog wandered into the run and was kicked.</p>
        <p>''We'll try again next year, maybe with some livelier bulls,'' vowed Mr. Strelsky after the event. ''Maybe that will get us more runners.''</p>
        <p>Isn't it pretty to think so?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
