<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Economy; As Apple prepares its next-generation operating system, it is again in a complex dance with its old nemesis, Microsoft.</title>
    <meta content="16NECO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/technology/16NECO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/New Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EFDA113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Economy; As Apple prepares its next-generation operating system, it is again in a complex dance with its old nemesis, Microsoft.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Markoff</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO sit down in front of the stunning computing control screen that defines the new Apple Macintosh OS X operating system is to be struck not just by the shock of the new, but also by the startling return of the old.</p>
        <p>The software, expected to reach the market early next year, is still in the test phase. But any longtime personal computer user who has a chance to try it out will almost instantly recognize that beneath the new software, with its screens of lollipop colors, beats the heart of Steven Jobs's 11-year-old Nextstep operating system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO sit down in front of the stunning computing control screen that defines the new Apple Macintosh OS X operating system is to be struck not just by the shock of the new, but also by the startling return of the old.</p>
        <p>The software, expected to reach the market early next year, is still in the test phase. But any longtime personal computer user who has a chance to try it out will almost instantly recognize that beneath the new software, with its screens of lollipop colors, beats the heart of Steven Jobs's 11-year-old Nextstep operating system.</p>
        <p>It is almost as if you can hear Lex, the young hacker in the movie ''Jurassic Park,'' delightedly exclaim: ''This is Unix. I know this stuff!''</p>
        <p>And that should be cause for concern. Nextstep, a variant of the Unix operating system, received high technical and aesthetic marks when Mr. Jobs introduced it in 1989 as the software to run the computer produced by Next, the company he founded after leaving Apple Computer. But like Next,  the Nextstep operating system ultimately failed in the marketplace.</p>
        <p>The fact that Mac users will be asked to move into the future by stepping into the past underscores the largest difficulty for Mr. Jobs, since he returned to run Apple Computer in 1997.</p>
        <p>For while the stock market punished Apple this month for the slower than expected sales of Apple's nifty G4 Cube computer, the more crucial question for Mr. Jobs's company is whether it can successfully move its millions of customers from their current software systems to its yet-to-be-finished Mac OS X operating system.</p>
        <p>The software is meant to be the first completely new Apple operating system since the company introduced the Macintosh computer in 1984. Apple's inability the last decade to bring to market a modern operating system that addresses both the consumer and business markets has clearly become Mr. Jobs's biggest challenge.</p>
        <p>The art of transitions between technology generations is an increasingly vexing one for the entire computer industry, of course, not just Apple. When handled well, technology transitions can advance bold strokes of corporate strategy. In the mid-90's, for example, Apple deftly managed the shift from the Motorola 68000 microprocessor to the Power PC chip designed with Motorola and I.B.M.</p>
        <p>And a similar achievement was probably Microsoft's single most important technological accomplishment: the company's success in the middle of the last decade in pulling the computer industry with it from MS-DOS to Windows 95.</p>
        <p>But, in fact, Microsoft's success was aided by Apple's repeated failure in the 1990's -- before Mr. Jobs's return -- to grapple with its own software challenge. Apple's fumbling of its operating system future created the original opening for Windows 95 and ultimately permitted Bill Gates and Microsoft to consolidate their hold on the desktop computer industry.</p>
        <p>Apple, which a decade ago had enviously high profit margins and a solid technology lead, subsequently started multiple operating system development projects and even entered into an alliance with I.B.M. based on one of the projects, known as Pink -- an effort that collapsed under its own technological and bureaucratic weight.</p>
        <p>All Apple's operating system efforts have tried to update or replace the original Macintosh operating system, which was quickly lashed together in the early 1980's. But over the years, rather than being revamped or replaced, the Mac operating system has  simply accumulated layers of barnacles and baling wire.</p>
        <p>In stark contrast has been Microsoft's success in pushing and pulling its customers forward to each new generation of its software. Now, though, Microsoft is facing its own challenge. The company is trying to converge its Windows 2000 and Windows 98 operating systems into a single software system, one that is code-named Whistler and is meant for the consumer market. Whistler may hold its own potential pitfalls for Microsoft because it is an effort to herd  the entire computer industry -- from desktop to corporate computing center -- into a one-size-fits-all corral.</p>
        <p>But Apple's challenge is even more extreme. Feedback from the Macintosh users who are trying the new systems so far has been mixed, as they try to become acquainted with the Mac OS X user interface, which operates differently in many ways from the traditional Macintosh interface.</p>
        <p>That in itself may be the largest challenge presented to a user of Mac OS X. While new software is able to run both original and new applications -- an obvious user benefit -- jumping back and forth between the old and new interfaces is a jarring experience that can leave a user feeling lost.</p>
        <p>And although Mr. Jobs's designers have done a remarkable job shielding the Macintosh user from the intricacies of the Nextstep-Unix genetic material in the software, its fiendish complexities are lurking just below the surface. Whether that legacy will ultimately be seen as the good breeding of industrial strength software or vestigial code from an earlier era remains to be seen.</p>
        <p>But the biggest potential problem for Mac OS X could be the delayed appearance of other software applications intended to capitalize on it.</p>
        <p>A visit to Apple's Mac OS X Web site reveals pointers to only a handful of test programs that take full advantage of the new system. And none of them are from major software companies.</p>
        <p>For example, Ray Ozzie, who created the innovative Lotus Notes program in the early 90's, is about to start Groove Networks, a company that has the industry buzzing about its new software. But Mr. Ozzie's company, concentrating on the Windows world, has deferred work on an Apple version. Mr. Ozzie said there was no point developing programs for the older Mac System 9 and that he judged Mac OS X as not yet mature enough to start work on.</p>
        <p>Even more potentially unsettling for Apple, Microsoft's Macintosh Office development team said last week that the group, which has just released the Office 2001 applications suite designed for Apple's current operating system, had only recently started work on a OS X version. Kevin Browne, general manager of Microsoft's Macintosh business unit, said the development team was uncertain when a version for the new Macintosh operating system would be finished.</p>
        <p>That, of course, may be the final irony. The arrival of Microsoft's Macintosh Office will be vital to the success of the new Macintosh OS X. So as Steve Jobs struggles to bring the Macintosh back to the future, he remains dependent on his past nemesis and current ally, Bill Gates.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
