<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revived Mets Just One Victory Away From the Series</title>
    <meta content="16METS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/sports/16METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E7D81E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1356" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revived Mets Just One Victory Away From the Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was his turn in the batting cage, so Edgardo Alfonzo politely removed himself from a conversation with reporters before the fourth game of the National League Championship Series last night.</p>
        <p>''Excuse me,'' Alfonzo said. ''I've got to go kill somebody here.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was his turn in the batting cage, so Edgardo Alfonzo politely removed himself from a conversation with reporters before the fourth game of the National League Championship Series last night.</p>
        <p>''Excuse me,'' Alfonzo said. ''I've got to go kill somebody here.''</p>
        <p>Alfonzo, the Mets second baseman, has become more than an on-field warrior. He is a team leader, and he did not like the relaxed atmosphere around the Mets in Game 3, a blowout loss to the Cardinals. ''Our attitude should be more aggressive, from the dugout to the field,'' he said.</p>
        <p>After Game 3, Alfonzo told Todd Pratt, the reserve catcher, that the Mets were playing as if they were down in the series, not up. To Pratt, the message was clear: the Mets' bench players had to show more energy, and they gathered last night and decided to do so.</p>
        <p>The Mets got it right this time, playing with passion from the start. They beat the Cardinals, 10-6, at Shea Stadium and now stand one victory from their first National League pennant since 1986. The Mets' No. 1 starter, Mike Hampton, can pitch them to the World Series tonight in Game 5.</p>
        <p>The Mets were alive on the bench and the diamond. They fell behind, 2-0, in the top of the first inning but stormed back, hammering away at the Cardinals' best pitcher, Darryl Kile, as the players on the bench whooped it up.</p>
        <p>''It's a team thing, and they keep things lively,'' said third baseman Robin Ventura, who hit the fourth of five Met doubles in the first inning. ''When stuff starts happening, they react to it. That's how big innings happen.''</p>
        <p>When Ventura's double knocked in Alfonzo and Mike Piazza, 10 Mets burst from the dugout to greet them on the field, embracing the players and the 3-2 lead the Mets had claimed. They would never trail again.</p>
        <p>The Cardinals outhit the Mets, 11-9, but the Mets bunched their runs in the early innings to overwhelm St. Louis. The Mets led, 7-2, after two innings, and when starter Bobby J. Jones faltered in the fifth, Glendon Rusch came on to earn the victory by pitching three scoreless innings.</p>
        <p>Piazza had a home run, a double and three runs scored, Ventura knocked in three runs and Timo Perez scored three times. In this game, the Mets were unfazed by a situation that had doomed them on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Three batters into the game, the Cardinals were ahead by two runs. If there was ever a here-we-go-again moment, it was this, because the Mets had experienced it in their 8-2 loss Saturday.</p>
        <p>That day, Fernando Vina led off with a single, Edgar Renteria reached on a bunt and Jim Edmonds doubled in two runs. Last night, Vina doubled, Renteria bunted him to second and Edmonds hit a two-run homer.</p>
        <p>The Mets' situation could not have been much worse. They were down by two runs and knew they would have to get to Kile early, because he tends to improve as the game goes on.</p>
        <p>But Kile was working on three days' rest, a situation in which he has been awful in his career. Mets first baseman Todd Zeile noticed a difference of about four miles an hour off Kile's fastball, and Kile had to use it, because he was not getting called strikes on his curveball.</p>
        <p>The Mets went to work on Kile early in the count. Perez whacked a ground-rule double that bounced over the right-field wall, extending his postseason hitting streak to seven games. Alfonzo ripped the next pitch down the right-field line for another double.</p>
        <p>The Mets had closed the gap to 2-1, with Piazza up next. That was especially bad news for Kile, whom Piazza devours. In 35 career at-bats off Kile (including a 2-for-3 performance in Game 1), Piazza had 13 hits, for a .371 average. He got ahead in the count, 2-0, then extended his arms and did what he does best, stroking a sizzling liner that kept carrying over right fielder J.D Drew's head.</p>
        <p>Alfonzo, who thought Drew might make the catch, had to hold up at third. No matter -- two pitches later, Ventura doubled both runners in. After Zeile grounded out, Benny Agbayani swung on a 3-0 pitch and blasted a double off the wall in left-center.</p>
        <p>The Mets had a 4-2 lead, and their five doubles were the most in one inning in N.L.C.S. history. Zeile, the only Met without a double among the first six hitters, got his in the next inning, when he thumped a hanging curveball into the left-field corner, scoring two runs. Agbayani singled in another run to put the Mets in front, 7-2.</p>
        <p>After home runs by Will Clark and Piazza, the Mets had an 8-3 lead when Jones, who tossed a one-hit shutout in his last start to clinch the division series against the Giants, unraveled in the fifth. He gave up three hits to start the inning, and Manager Bobby Valentine called for Rusch.</p>
        <p>''I've said all along that one of the keys to this series was to keep me out of the games,'' Rusch said. ''If I'm coming in, one of our starters is in trouble. Fortunately tonight, I guess, I came in at the right time.''</p>
        <p>Rusch allowed two of the runners he inherited to score in the fifth, but he worked a scoreless sixth and seventh to turn the game over to the Mets' late-inning tandem of John Franco and Armando Benitez.</p>
        <p>The game could have gotten more interesting in the sixth. With Ray Lankford on first and two outs, Zeile dived to his right to snare a hard grounder by Carlos Hernandez and then beat the Cardinals' catcher to the bag. With the score 8-6 at the time, the injured slugger Mark McGwire would have pinch hit.</p>
        <p>''That was the place to take a shot,'' Cardinals Manager Tony La Russa said. ''He was on deck.''</p>
        <p>Strong defense continued to aid the Mets. In the seventh, Perez ran down a fly ball in the right-field corner and fired in to second to catch Shawon Dunston, who was trying to tag up. That play ended the inning. Besides the mental lapses, poor defense also hampered the Cardinals, who allowed two unearned runs on two errors by Fernando Tatis in the sixth.</p>
        <p>The Mets hit well, fielded well and capitalized on the Cardinals' mistakes. One more game like this, and they can hold up their end of the Subway Series date. They know their attitude will not impede them.</p>
        <p>''The key for us is to come in tomorrow and want to put these guys away, and not have that same mentality we had when we were up 2-0,'' center fielder Jay Payton said. ''I don't think that'll be the case. We're up 3-1 now, and none of the guys in here want to go back to St. Louis. I think we'll come in tomorrow with the same mentality we had today, and hopefully that'll carry over.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Mets catcher MIKE PIAZZA has patellar tendinitis in his right knee, the same ailment afflicting the Cardinals' MARK MCGWIRE, Manager BOBBY VALENTINE said.  Piazza apparently was injured on Saturday, said Valentine. ''We'll keep watching it,'' he said. . . . Valentine said he still intends to start RICK REED in a potential Game 7 of the N.L.C.S. despite Reed's performance on Saturday, when he allowed five runs and eight hits.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: 2000 PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
