<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fox Pursuing a Gentler Reality</title>
    <meta content="16FOX.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/business/16FOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6D8113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1158" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fox Pursuing a Gentler Reality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Good pets won't be going bad and faux millionaires with dicey pasts won't be marrying unsuspecting gold diggers, but the Fox network soon will have game show contestants trying to survive military-style boot camp, unmarried couples testing their fidelity on an island filled with male and female models and longtime girlfriends trying to compel their boyfriends to propose on a show called ''Surprise Wedding.''</p>
        <p>Welcome to the reformed Fox, where animals once attacked and the world's worst drivers once careered out of control. After last year's highly publicized scandal over the Fox special, ''Who Wants to Marry a Multimillionaire?'' the network swore off all shows of that ilk, declaring it would no longer pursue shows that smacked of ''exploitative material.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Good pets won't be going bad and faux millionaires with dicey pasts won't be marrying unsuspecting gold diggers, but the Fox network soon will have game show contestants trying to survive military-style boot camp, unmarried couples testing their fidelity on an island filled with male and female models and longtime girlfriends trying to compel their boyfriends to propose on a show called ''Surprise Wedding.''</p>
        <p>Welcome to the reformed Fox, where animals once attacked and the world's worst drivers once careered out of control. After last year's highly publicized scandal over the Fox special, ''Who Wants to Marry a Multimillionaire?'' the network swore off all shows of that ilk, declaring it would no longer pursue shows that smacked of ''exploitative material.''</p>
        <p>The directive, from the Fox Entertainment chairman, Sandy Grushow, last winter promised that the reality specials that made Fox famous (or infamous) were ''gone, over.'' It would seem this might have finally clipped the wings of television's most imaginative purveyor of reality programming, Mike Darnell, the Fox executive responsible for those memorable Fox specials of sweep months past.</p>
        <p>But reality programming is, in reality, bigger than ever at Fox this season, with more than 90 episodes of reality series already in some stage of development along with 25 to 30 hours of specials. And the man in charge of all of it is the same Mike Darnell, working under the title of executive vice president for alternative programming for the Fox network.</p>
        <p>''I'm busier than I have ever been,'' Mr. Darnell said. ''After 'Survivor' hit so big for CBS last summer, it only underscored the commitment here to reality. We also have seven hours of brand-new programming in prime time, and some of that won't work, which means they'll be calling on me for replacement shows.''</p>
        <p>Then there is a looming strike by actors and writers, threatened for mid-2001, which would create the need for reality programming.</p>
        <p>''It's been really crazy,'' Mr. Darnell said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, with shows like ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire'' on ABC and ''Survivor'' and ''Big Brother'' on CBS pushing up ratings expectations for network entertainment shows, there has never been a greater need for Mr. Darnell's specialty, or a specialist like Mr. Darnell.</p>
        <p>''I'm a fan of the form and a fan of Mike Darnell,'' said Gail Berman, the president of Fox Entertainment. ''He gives off the kind of energy that is so rare inside Hollywood offices.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Darnell said it was the ''worst day of my life'' when it was revealed that the contestant at the center of ''Who Wants to Marry a Multimillionaire'' had been the subject of two restraining orders from women he had dated. But Mr. Darnell is now so recovered from that episode, that he allows himself to feel a certain validation at the way reality programming is preoccupying the program chiefs at every network.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't call it vindication for myself,'' Mr. Darnell said in a telephone interview. ''I'm just happy to see shows like 'Millionaire' and 'Survivor' getting the respect they deserve.''</p>
        <p>But one senior executive at Fox, a unit of the News Corporation, said that the months since the ''Multimillionaire'' fiasco have been ''personally difficult for Mike.'' Still, the executive said, the demand for reality programming at Fox has never been greater. ''We're stockpiling the stuff, and Mike's in charge of it,'' he said. ''Of course, he's being more closely watched.''</p>
        <p>The main feature of that scrutiny is the hiring of the accounting firm PricewaterhouseCoopers as a ''risk-management consultant.'' The company will examine every reality programming idea, look for potential dangers and screen every contestant. The other senior Fox executive said Pricewaterhouse would be ''creating scenarios for every possible bad thing that might happen.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. Berman, this does not mean Fox is only looking for tame ideas. ''Hopefully, we don't get ourselves into too much trouble,'' she said. ''I don't mind getting into a little trouble. We want things to be at least a little provocative.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Darnell himself acknowledges a shift in his creative thinking, away from any show with risk to life and limb (as in animals attacking humans or high-speed vehicles heading for collisions). Now, he says, his ideas lean more toward ''the fun of relationships.''</p>
        <p>Take ''Surprise Wedding,'' a special scheduled for next month, one of those intensified ratings periods known as sweep months. The idea is to recruit five young women who have had trouble dragging their longtime boyfriends to the altar. They have volunteered to take part in an elaborate ruse that will induce the boyfriends to accompany them to Las Vegas, on the pretext that the girlfriends have won a makeover contest. While they are supposedly  off getting their makeovers, the men will get a ticket to a Las Vegas show.</p>
        <p>But the show turns out to be them. They will wind up on a stage in front of 1,500 people. Their previous experiences with their girlfriend will be revealed, and they will get the chance to redeem themselves by proposing on the spot -- whereupon they will be married instantly. Mr. Darnell says the pressure will lead at least four of the five men to take the plunge. As for the other one, he said, ''If he refuses, we'll give the girl an enormous singles package of gifts.''</p>
        <p>Another idea is ''I Want A Divorce,'' in which soon-to-be divorced couples will compete for their assets. He described this one as ''totally light hearted'' and added that while the couple may ''play for the dining room set,'' they would not likely play for any big assets like the house. Some Fox executives have expressed skepticism that the show will ever make it into production.</p>
        <p>But ''Love Cruise'' and ''Temptation Island'' are already produced and will be on the air in January, Mr. Darnell said. In the first, a group of singles cruise around dating one another and voting the losers off a ship until, as Mr. Darnell put it, ''The couple most in love wins.''</p>
        <p>''Temptation Island'' will bring a group of unmarried couples onto an island stocked with spectacular-looking men and women. The game is who will succumb to temptation. Individuals can block out the most likely tempter or temptress so their beloved can't go off with that person.</p>
        <p>''People are fascinated by relationships,'' Mr. Darnell said. ''I think these shows will be very relatable.''</p>
        <p>On Mr. Darnell's future slate are shows like ''Hotel Getaway,'' which features couples on a free trip to an idyllic resort that actually is booby-trapped to make their stay miserable with bad food, noise and obnoxious guests. The couple who stays the longest wins a prize.</p>
        <p>Mr. Darnell acknowledged the airwaves could become so glutted with reality shows that it would be harder for one to break through. ''But a good one will always work,'' he said. ''I think the form is here to stay.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
