<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Meola's Shutout Gives Wizards the Title</title>
    <meta content="16SOCC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/sports/16SOCC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Wizards</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Fire</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EEDF1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Meola's Shutout Gives Wizards the Title</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kansas City Wizards defeat Chicago Fire, 1-0, to win Major League soccer championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Kansas City Wizards mobbed their goalkeeper, Tony Meola, and the Chicago Fire was in disbelief after Kansas City's 1-0 triumph this afternoon in the championship game of Major League Soccer's fifth season.</p>
        <p>Miklos Molnar scored the lone goal, in the 12th minute of the game, before a sun-soaked crowd of 39,159 at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium. Kansas City made the goal stand up with tight defensive play and brilliant goalkeeping by Meola, who was voted the game's most valuable player. Meola was credited with 10 saves but appeared to make many more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Kansas City Wizards mobbed their goalkeeper, Tony Meola, and the Chicago Fire was in disbelief after Kansas City's 1-0 triumph this afternoon in the championship game of Major League Soccer's fifth season.</p>
        <p>Miklos Molnar scored the lone goal, in the 12th minute of the game, before a sun-soaked crowd of 39,159 at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium. Kansas City made the goal stand up with tight defensive play and brilliant goalkeeping by Meola, who was voted the game's most valuable player. Meola was credited with 10 saves but appeared to make many more.</p>
        <p>''Tony made these kinds of saves all season,'' Coach Bob Gansler of the Wizards said. ''He just made a few more today. We always depend on Tony, and he came through for us again today.''</p>
        <p>Meola made three spectacular saves in the last 10 minutes to preserve the victory for the Wizards, who captured the league title after finishing next to last a year ago. Kansas City's turnaround was even more remarkable than the one by the MetroStars, who won their division after finishing last in the league last season.</p>
        <p>The game matched a Chicago team that had the league's best offense during the regular season and a Kansas City team that had the best defense, but no one could tell which was better at what in the first half.</p>
        <p>Kansas City fooled those who believed it would emphasize defense by pushing players forward from the outset. The strategy paid off in the 12th minute, primarily through a brilliant individual effort by Kansas City midfielder Matt McKeon. McKeon took the ball from Diego Gutierrez on the right side of the midfield in his zone, avoided Chris Armas with a sprint down the right flank and crossed the ball into the middle of the small penalty area.</p>
        <p>Chicago midfielder Jesse Marsch came across from the other side and had a chance to clear the cross but misplayed the ball, allowing Molnar to touch it into the lower right corner, past the sprawled goalie, Zach Thornton.</p>
        <p>There were some gaps in Kansas City's defense, mostly because of poor decisions, but Chicago's offense failed to take advantage.</p>
        <p>The closest Chicago came to scoring in the first half was in the 26th minute, when Hristo Stoitchkov's shot from 12 yards hit the left post. Chicago had several chances in the second half, but the closest it came was when Gutierrez hit the crossbar in the 53rd minute. Meola thwarted all the other threats by the Fire.</p>
        <p>''We tried to push from the beginning, and they scored the first time they came in our area,'' Coach Bob Bradley of Chicago said. ''This is a big disappointment on our end because we came here for the championship and it didn't happen.''</p>
        <p>Gansler, who was voted the league's coach of the year, said all the credit for Kansas City's turnaround belonged to the players.</p>
        <p>''Coaches get awards when the players perform and an Amtrak schedule when they don't,'' Gansler said to the delight of Lamar Hunt, who attended the game. Hunt, the investor-operator of the Wizards and the Columbus Crew, has been one of the biggest financial backers of the league.</p>
        <p>The league has realized that reducing the number of games during the regular season has become a necessity and will cut the schedule to 28 games from 32 for next season.</p>
        <p>Despite a slight decline in attendance and in television ratings, M.L.S. has re-signed all 12 major sponsors, but the number of live games on ABC will most likely be reduced to two from six: the All-Star Game and the championship game. ESPN will keep virtually the same schedule.</p>
        <p>Next year's championship game will be played at the league's only soccer-specific stadium, in Columbus, Ohio. The site of the All-Star Game will be decided around the end of the year, with San Jose and Dallas the strongest candidates.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
