<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patents; Inventions to cull more music from the Internet and indulge in better karaoke, too.</title>
    <meta content="16PATE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/technology/16PATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFD9113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patents; Inventions to cull more music from the Internet and indulge in better karaoke, too.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOT long ago, if someone threw a party and wanted her own dance music, she could cobble together a party tape by painstakingly recording selected songs onto a cassette, an especially tortured process if you were trying to tape Top 40 music from the radio.</p>
        <p>Now, of course, it is commonplace to download thousands of popular songs from the Internet without even being in the room at the time. The software that makes this possible, like Napster, creates perfect digital copies that can be retransmitted indefinitely. That has caused legal battles over copyright infringement and royalty abuse. It also requires a lot of bandwidth for the download and knowledge of which songs or musicians one is after.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOT long ago, if someone threw a party and wanted her own dance music, she could cobble together a party tape by painstakingly recording selected songs onto a cassette, an especially tortured process if you were trying to tape Top 40 music from the radio.</p>
        <p>Now, of course, it is commonplace to download thousands of popular songs from the Internet without even being in the room at the time. The software that makes this possible, like Napster, creates perfect digital copies that can be retransmitted indefinitely. That has caused legal battles over copyright infringement and royalty abuse. It also requires a lot of bandwidth for the download and knowledge of which songs or musicians one is after.</p>
        <p>James Logan is betting that there are plenty of people who would be perfectly satisfied with collections of favorite songs from the radio if they were not so much trouble to put together. So he and two co-inventors have patented a technology that makes it possible to download music from radio broadcasts onto a hard drive and then automatically sort the songs into personalized playlists. Mr. Logan says the music can be legally copied with his invention under the law that allows consumers to make home audio and video recordings for their own use.</p>
        <p>His calls his product SongCatcher, and it borrows the concept of time-shifting used in products like TiVo and ReplayTV, which enable viewers to record television shows for playback anywhere from a few minutes to a few hours later. To start, a user needs a computer, the SongCatcher software (downloaded from SongCatcher.com), and a radio receiver with a digital tuner or a computer U.S.B. tuner card. A cable from the headphone jack in the receiver to the audio input line of the computer connects the two.</p>
        <p>Once the system is set up, the user would turn on his radio and computer. As the radio played, the software would digitize the analog radio signal and download the broadcasts onto the computer's hard drive. Mr. Logan said 24 hours of broadcasts would require 1.4 gigabytes of storage. All of the songs played during that time would be compared with a database of that day's broadcasts from the 1,000 largest radio stations in the country.</p>
        <p>The software would then identify the songs using a technology called fingerprinting, Mr. Logan said. It compares segments of a song with those in the database, looking for a match.</p>
        <p>''Fingerprinting works like voice recognition, in the same way that the human mind recognizes a song after hearing four or five notes,'' he explained. ''We can program a computer to do the same thing.''</p>
        <p>After the software identifies the song by name and artist, it creates a list of the titles.</p>
        <p>''You might have 400 songs on your jukebox, and then overnight another 25 songs are added in bold face,'' Mr. Logan said. ''You can go back later and decide which songs you want to keep or delete. If there is a group or a song you don't like, you can hit the 'never again' button. If you don't like the Backstreet Boys or 'N Sync, you can screen them out.''</p>
        <p>The company is also working on software that will create a ''hunt list,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''The system will look for specific songs, and when it records them, it will highlight that and tell you that it has found them,'' Mr. Logan added.</p>
        <p>The system can also be used as the person monitors radio broadcasts in ''real time.'' The software includes a buffer that stores five minutes of broadcasts. When a listener hears a song he likes, he can press a ''save'' button and the song will be downloaded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Logan said that all of this was legal because ''there is no file transfer going on.''</p>
        <p>''The Audio Home Recording Act of 1992 solidifies the consumer's right to record off the airwaves,'' he said. ''And the recording companies shouldn't see this as a threat to their business. It's not a perfect copy; it's taken from an FM signal, and sometimes D.J.'s talk over the beginning of the songs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Logan, along with Daniel Goessling and Richard Goldhor, received patent 6,088,455.</p>
        <p>Singing to the Internet may not sound like the most reliable way to retrieve the name of a song, but a Japanese inventor has just won a patent for a Web-based music search engine that he says compensates for a bad voice or an incorrectly rendered tune when scanning its database for a melody.</p>
        <p>The inventor, Tomonari Sonoda of Tokyo, won a patent for a software system that takes a sung melody as a search query. A person would input his request by singing, humming or whistling the melody into a microphone. The melody would be turned into a digital signal and then analyzed for the pitch and time length of notes in each musical sequence. Bad singing could be adjusted for by calculating the difference in pitch and intervals between adjacent notes. Those calculations are then compared with music sequences in a database until a match is found.</p>
        <p>In his patent, Mr. Sonoda says the system can be used to retrieve songs from a database in a karaoke machine, to shop for specific songs on CD's in a music store, or to request certain songs via a mobile phone while driving. He also said the system could be installed in multiple devices and then connected, so several people could sing their queries in unison, like a chorus. Mr. Sonoda received patent 6,121,530.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
