<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Recruits Governors and Women for Final Stretch</title>
    <meta content="Y16BUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/politics/16BUSH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE STRATEGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E0DD1E3FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Recruits Governors and Women for Final Stretch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <dateline>AUSTIN, Tex., Oct. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beginning the final phase of the presidential campaign, Gov. George W. Bush plans to send the nation's Republican governors in a three-day fly-around to battleground states as well as deploy a phalanx of women and his onetime bitter primary rival, Senator John McCain of Arizona, to woo swing voters.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign said 28 of Mr. Bush's fellow Republican governors, including his brother Jeb, of Florida, plan to converge on Austin on Sunday for a rally.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beginning the final phase of the presidential campaign, Gov. George W. Bush plans to send the nation's Republican governors in a three-day fly-around to battleground states as well as deploy a phalanx of women and his onetime bitter primary rival, Senator John McCain of Arizona, to woo swing voters.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign said 28 of Mr. Bush's fellow Republican governors, including his brother Jeb, of Florida, plan to converge on Austin on Sunday for a rally.</p>
        <p>They then plan to split onto seven planes and crisscross the country for Mr. Bush, making 45 stops in 24 states. Altogether the states represent 316 electoral votes, and 22 of the states voted for President Clinton in 1996.</p>
        <p>The effort, in many ways, brings the Bush campaign back to its origins. The initial groundswell for Mr. Bush's candidacy began with the recognition inside the Republican Party that its governors were winning elections even as the Congressional branch of the party was falling into disfavor and losing seats. And from the moment Mr. Bush won re-election in 1998, he drew on his fellow governors as a mainstay of his candidacy and as his base of support in the Republican primaries.</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, a spokesman for Mr. Bush, said the governors would lend emphasis to Mr. Bush's campaign theme that he is not a creature of the nation's gridlocked capital. ''It's a strong reminder that Governor Bush is cut from a different cloth from most of the Washington politicians,'' Mr. Fleischer said. ''He's an outsider to Washington and comes from the more reformist, bipartisan wing of our party.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides said the governors would showcase their ideas and records in education and tax-cutting. The one Republican governor who will not be participating is Cecil H. Underwood of West Virginia, who is in a tough re-election fight. Mr. Fleischer said the effort would cost the Bush campaign about $500,000.</p>
        <p>As soon as the third presidential debate concludes in St. Louis on Tuesday night, both campaigns move into the final stretch.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore also is stepping up his use of campaign surrogates. Tipper Gore and Hadassah Lieberman are campaigning for their husbands. And this weekend, the former federal housing secretary Henry G. Cisneros, who was once the mayor of San Antonio, began an effort for the Gore campaign to lead surrogate campaigners in criticizing Mr. Bush's record in Texas.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign is trying to use Mr. Bush's record in Texas to underscore its argument that Mr. Bush puts the interests of the wealthy and corporate interests before those of average Americans. Mr. Gore has been citing in particular statistics that show Texas last among the 50 states in families with health insurance coverage.</p>
        <p>Douglas Hattaway, a spokesman for Mr. Gore, used the announcement of the governors' tour to keep up the same theme and charge that Texas has not been aggressive in signing up children for a federal health insurance program.</p>
        <p>''Maybe they can do a better job than he did of explaining his failed leadership in Texas,'' Mr. Hattaway said. ''Many Republican governors have managed to expand children's health care,'' he said, arguing that Mr. Bush had not followed their lead.</p>
        <p>Even before the governors begin their campaign swing, Mr. Bush will send a team of women to the hotly contested states of Wisconsin, Michigan and Pennsylvania. The group includes Bush's wife, Laura; Lynne Cheney, the wife of his vice-presidential running mate Dick Cheney; and Barbara Bush, the former first lady. Condoleezza Rice, Mr. Bush's chief foreign policy adviser, and Cindy McCain, the wife of Mr. McCain, will also join the effort.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is leading among women, but Mr. Bush has been making inroads. Mindy Tucker, an aide to Mr. Bush, said the women would talk about issues important to women such as education, health care, safety and violence.</p>
        <p>''They'll not only talk about the governor's priorities as president of the United States, but also what he's done in Texas,'' Ms. Tucker said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush himself is beginning his campaign week in President Clinton's home state, Arkansas. Later in the week, he will be joined by Mr. McCain in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain's substantial victory over Mr. Bush in New Hampshire, the nation's first primary state, forced the Texan into a bitter primary race.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE STRATEGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
