<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EBay Faces Suit on Sale of Fake Goods</title>
    <meta content="16EBAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/16/technology/16EBAY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001018T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001016T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0D8113FF935A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="992" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EBay Faces Suit on Sale of Fake Goods</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA GUERNSEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a case closely watched by critics of online auctions, a California judge has allowed six people to proceed with a lawsuit that strikes at the core of how eBay runs its business.</p>
        <p>The ruling, last Wednesday, involves a lawsuit filed by people who say they bought autographed sports memorabilia later found to be fake. The lawsuit asserts that eBay, the largest online auction operator, has a responsibility to ensure the authenticity of the sports memorabilia sold through its World Wide Web site.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a case closely watched by critics of online auctions, a California judge has allowed six people to proceed with a lawsuit that strikes at the core of how eBay runs its business.</p>
        <p>The ruling, last Wednesday, involves a lawsuit filed by people who say they bought autographed sports memorabilia later found to be fake. The lawsuit asserts that eBay, the largest online auction operator, has a responsibility to ensure the authenticity of the sports memorabilia sold through its World Wide Web site.</p>
        <p>EBay, which lists about four million items for sale daily, has repeatedly argued that it merely operates a venue for sales and cannot be held liable for fraudulent transactions. Company officials have said that if eBay were forced to verify every piece of listed merchandise -- or even only sports memorabilia -- eBay would not be able to offer consumers such a large marketplace.</p>
        <p>Last week's ruling came from Judge Linda B. Quinn of Superior Court in San Diego County, where the lawsuit was filed in April. The ruling was a preliminary response to eBay's assertion that the case should be dismissed.</p>
        <p>Though she did not grant a dismissal, Judge Quinn sided with eBay on several points and told the plaintiffs to restate their case in terms that would more specifically rebut eBay's arguments.</p>
        <p>The case is based in part on a California law governing the sale of sports memorabilia. EBay is based in San Jose, Calif.</p>
        <p>Legal experts say they are watching the case because while several states have laws intended to protect consumers from fraudulent auctions, most of them were written before the Internet made  online auctions possible.</p>
        <p>''It is definitely an open issue as to whether online auctions like this should be regulated under those state auction statutes,'' said Thomas Bell, a lawyer in Seattle who specializes in Internet law.</p>
        <p>In the California case, six eBay users filed the complaint after discovering that several autographed baseballs and other sports items carried what law-enforcement officials said were forged signatures. Also included as defendants in the suit are nine sellers and authenticators of sports memorabilia, most of whom live in San Diego and who have been investigated or indicted by federal officials for their roles in what the Federal Bureau of Investigation says is a nationwide swindle.</p>
        <p>James C. Krause, the plaintiffs' lawyer, said his clients wanted to recoup the $1,100 they spent on the items, and to stop eBay from providing what they said was a channel for the sale of fake merchandise. Mr. Krause has requested class-action status for the lawsuit, which could turn the case into a multimillion-dollar complaint including anyone who can prove that they have unwittingly bought counterfeit sports memorabilia on eBay.</p>
        <p>The judge is scheduled to begin considering the request for class-action certification on Nov. 17. Lawyers on both sides say a final judgment on the case will probably not come until next year.</p>
        <p>The case may hinge on how the judge interprets a section of the Telecommunications Act of 1996. The law says that Internet service providers are not liable for the material that is sent out over their networks.</p>
        <p>EBay declined to comment on last week's ruling, but in court documents, it has said it is not an auctioneer since it does not list the items for sale, does not write the descriptions of the items and does not have the items in its possession at any time. As a result, eBay's lawyers say, the California law on sports memorabilia dealers does not apply to eBay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Krause said he intended to argue that eBay was a ''content provider,'' rather than a service provider.</p>
        <p>The lead plaintiff is Lars Gentry, an Illinois resident who used eBay to buy four baseballs whose signatures were found to be forged. He also bought a couple of ''cuts'' -- documents that feature the autographs of famous sports figures -- that were found to be forged.</p>
        <p>Mr. Krause is using the California law, adopted in 1992, to support several key parts of the case. The law forbids dealers -- including auctioneers -- to represent items as collectibles if they include forged signatures. It also requires dealers to certify that items are authentic. Under the law, people who have been misled by dealers are entitled to recover 10 times the sales price of the items purchased. Mr. Krause says  the law applies to eBay because the company is essentially an auctioneer.</p>
        <p>''The statute is there for the people to rely upon,'' said Mr. Krause, adding that eBay was 'not doing a good job of protecting the public.''</p>
        <p>The lawsuit also accuses eBay of not revoking the privileges of the sellers after receiving complaints from other users who asserted that the goods were fraudulent. EBay has said that it makes a good-faith effort to protect its users, and the company has taken a few steps recently to deter fraud, including an announcement in July telling its users that some sellers of sporting items had used fake certificates of authority to entice buyers.</p>
        <p>EBay has said it would no longer list items that featured those certificates. The eBay users who were named in the F.B.I.'s indictment are facing probation or suspension from the Web site, according to Kevin Pursglove, eBay's spokesman.</p>
        <p>Meg Smith, a fellow at Harvard's Berkman Center for Internet &amp; Society, said the lawsuit illustrated the dilemmas that face online auction services. ''EBay is caught in the cross-fire here,'' she said. If the providers of the service make no effort to protect its users, ''they look like a bad corporate citizens,'' she said. ''But the more responsibility they take, the more they look like an auctioneer and the less they look like they are just a forum.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 18, 2000, Wednesday  An article in Business Day on Monday and a related article yesterday about a lawsuit against eBay referred imprecisely to a preliminary ruling in the case. In that ruling, which was made last Wednesday, the judge granted eBay's request to dismiss the complaints in their current form. But she let the plaintiffs refile the case with more specific arguments, accusing eBay of neglecting to protect consumers from sales of forged sports memorabilia in its online auctions. The judge did not support eBay's motion to dismiss the case itself. On Monday, the plaintiffs responded by refiling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 18, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Monday and a related article yesterday about a lawsuit against eBay referred imprecisely to a preliminary ruling in the case. In that ruling, which was made last Wednesday, the judge granted eBay's request to dismiss the complaints in their current form. But she let the plaintiffs refile the case with more specific arguments, accusing eBay of neglecting to protect consumers from sales of forged sports memorabilia in its online auctions. The judge did not support eBay's motion to dismiss the case itself. On Monday, the plaintiffs responded by refiling.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
