<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Senate's Philosopher-King</title>
    <meta content="13PURDUMT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hodgson, Godfrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moynihan, Daniel Patrick (Sen)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gentleman From New York, The: Daniel Patrick Moynihan (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D6163CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1528" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Senate's Philosopher-King</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Todd S. Purdum</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Todd S Purdum reviews book The Gentleman From New York: Daniel Patrick Moynihan: A Biography by Godfrey Hodgson; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE GENTLEMAN</p>
        <p>FROM NEW YORK</p>
        <p>Daniel Patrick Moynihan: A Biography.</p>
        <p>By Godfrey Hodgson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 452 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $38.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE GENTLEMAN</p>
        <p>FROM NEW YORK</p>
        <p>Daniel Patrick Moynihan: A Biography.</p>
        <p>By Godfrey Hodgson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 452 pp. Boston:</p>
        <p>Houghton Mifflin Company. $38.</p>
        <p>Only one sitting member of the United States Senate had an honored seat at the funerals of both Richard M. Nixon and Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis. Only one has written or edited 18 books (at last count). Only one has tended bar in Hell's Kitchen and taught at Harvard, corrected John F. Kennedy's arithmetic and William Jefferson Clinton's decorum. And only one, it seems more than safe to say, owns a splendid oil painting of a brooding boy by the Irish artist Jack B. Yeats, the poet's brother.</p>
        <p>More to the point, perhaps only one or two other senators among the 100 now serving would merit a full-scale intellectual and political biography, which is the task that the British journalist Godfrey Hodgson has set himself in this lucid, engaging study of the life and career of Daniel Patrick Moynihan, the Senate's philosopher-king. Moynihan is to retire at the end of this session, after more than four decades in the thick of American politics, and ''The Gentleman From New York'' lands in a depressing election year as a bracing reminder of the enduring potential for honor and intellect in a calling no longer thought of as full of either -- and of the possibility of poetry, too.</p>
        <p>Coming to terms with Moynihan is not easy, for he has spent a political lifetime confounding would-be allies and enemies alike. Baptized a Catholic and born a Democrat, as he likes to say, he began his career as a stalwart postwar New Dealer, in the mold of F.D.R. and Averell Harriman, an early boss, then became a fiercely proud New Frontiersman. Bruised by the tumult of the 1960's and the furor surrounding his much-misunderstood report on the collapse of the black family, Moynihan became for a time the right's favorite liberal, or the left's favorite neocon, or both, before emerging again in the Reagan and Clinton years as a staunch defender of the liberal tradition.</p>
        <p>Hodgson's affectionate goal is to chronicle this ideological odyssey, which he deftly summarizes in his introduction as ''a parade.'' But from the beginning, he makes it clear that it is folly to seek any label that fits Moynihan, except perhaps skeptic (and at that a skeptic of an unusually hardheaded, bighearted variety). ''His greatest gift is to handicap the intellectual horses,'' Hodgson, the author of ''America in Our Time,'' writes in a typically felicitous passage. ''He picks up tips about their form, decides which ones will run and run and sticks his intellectual and political wad on the ones he thinks will be winners. There have been some slow coaches and some fallers. But the record of his form book is truly imposing.'' Indeed, from his early promotion of auto safety to his warnings about the social dislocation of a generation of poor children, from his prescient conviction that the Soviet Union would collapse of its own weight to his understanding of the havoc that the Reagan-era budget deficits would play with domestic spending, from his determination to restore the grandeur of Pennsylvania Avenue in Washington to his support for a similar effort at Pennsylvania Station in New York City, Moynihan has been ahead of his time. To put it another way, he has been right.</p>
        <p>Neither Moynihan nor his formidable wife and chief political counselor, Elizabeth, is known to suffer fools gladly. And in a book dedicated to the couple and written with their cooperation, Hodgson gives due regard to the senator's streaks of arrogance and temper, to his difficulties in retaining staff members, to the number of onetime friends who became enemies, to his philosophical about-faces. But perhaps more striking, given Moynihan's long run on the national stage, are the durability and diversity of his friendships across ideological lines and the modesty with which, in the twilight of his career, he regards his and his government's ability to be right, or at least to do big things right. Moynihan's skepticism, Hodgson writes, ''is not because of any ideological objection to government.'' It is, rather, ''part of a pessimism, almost a melancholy, about the workings of the universe and its human inhabitants which is culturally, if not theologically, religious in nature, and is quite compatible with cheerfulness, even ebullience, about the actual workings of government.''</p>
        <p>Suffice it to say that such a melancholy pessimism is not standard equipment for American politicians circa 2000, and Moynihan's fellow legislators, especially his fellow Democrats, have always been among his toughest critics. Few big bills, few big battles for a cause, much big talk, goes the refrain (which often includes an unfavorable contrast with his Massachusetts colleague Edward M. Kennedy). Hodgson cops a kind of plea to the first two charges and proceeds to argue that Moynihan's stock in trade is something rarer, big ideas.</p>
        <p>These ideas have been the principal source of his professional reputation and the principal cause of his greatest professional pain, never more so than with the report he wrote in 1965 as a Labor Department official in the Johnson administration, ''The Negro Family: The Case for National Action.'' In this document, forever after known as the Moynihan Report, Moynihan, himself the child of a home that was thrown from middle-class stability into penury and turmoil when his will-o'-the-wisp father abandoned it, argued that a mass abdication of the duties of fatherhood by black men was imperiling their wives and children, condemning them to poverty and despair and their society to what he later called ''a new and wholly unexpected range of social conflict.''</p>
        <p>In some of the biography's most compelling passages, Hodgson contends that what Moynihan was advocating was nothing more or less than what came to be known as affirmative action. But, thanks in part to incomplete press accounts and the tumult of the times, Moynihan was accused of blaming the victim, and suffered the unsparing criticism of an interracial, interfaith array of civil rights advocates, psychologists and sociologists. This rebuke set Moynihan off on a wandering trajectory that led to academia (Wesleyan, Harvard) and ultimately to his service as a domestic policy adviser in the Nixon White House, where he managed to get in trouble all over again by suggesting that race relations could benefit from a period of ''benign neglect.'' (He meant a break from overheated oratory, but that's not how he was heard.)</p>
        <p>It seems probable that Moynihan never quite recovered from the bitterness of those days. It seems equally likely that his involuntary unmooring from partisan orthodoxy made possible the best and most penetrating moments of his political career, which has stretched to four Senate terms of scrutinizing the Central Intelligence Agency, advocating mass transit, defending poor children and bringing New York State untold old-fashioned pork.</p>
        <p>Hodgson is at his best in describing Moynihan's evolving interior intellectual monologues. In this he is aided by access to voluminous published and private writings, including a youthful diary that details Moynihan's romances and brief psychoanalysis when he was a Fulbright scholar at the London School of Economics (as well as 35 years of friendship, begun when he and the Moynihans were neighbors in Washington). His account of the senator's early years owes an acknowledged debt to ''Pat,'' Douglas Schoen's 1979 biography. The passions and political maneuverings of Moynihan's years as Nixon's ambassador to India and Gerald R. Ford's to the United Nations are vigorously dispatched.</p>
        <p>Just over 125 pages are devoted to Moynihan's Senate career, covered chronologically, a logical organizing scheme but one that sometimes keeps a reader to-ing and fro-ing between chapters on similar topical material, as do earlier chapters about the Moynihan Report (its writing is handled in one, the storm over its reception in another). Here again, Hodgson is most interesting in describing Moynihan's intellectual modus operandi (the carefully chosen issue, the well-placed op-ed piece) rather than his legislative one.</p>
        <p>Hodgson deals briefly but directly with Moynihan's reputation as a tippler, subscribing to the conventional view that his capacity has always been large, that his appetite seldom if ever affected his performance and that his consumption, with age, has dwindled chiefly to Tio Pepe, a dry sherry that his staff calls ''the Mexican ambassador,'' as in ''The senator's with the Mexican ambassador.'' In the end Hodgson portrays a grand old man, at peace with his impending retirement (if much more skeptical about his potential successor, Hillary Rodham Clinton, than he is inclined to acknowledge) and likely to be remembered ''as the man who -- in the face of a generation that thought it had abolished the need for government -- had the lucidity and the courage to restate the enduring propositions of the American political creed.''</p>
        <p>Todd S. Purdum, who covered Senator Moynihan as a Washington correspondent for The Times, is the chief of the paper's Los Angeles bureau.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Todd S. Purdum, who covered Senator Moynihan as a Washington correspondent for The Times, is the chief of the paper's Los Angeles bureau.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
