<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Faith Healer</title>
    <meta content="13REEDLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, Kit</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nair, Anita</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Better Man, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E5D6163CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Faith Healer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kit Reed</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, Kit</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kit Reed reviews book The Better Man by Anita Nair (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Better Man</p>
        <p>By Anita Nair.</p>
        <p>288 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Picador. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Better Man</p>
        <p>By Anita Nair.</p>
        <p>288 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Picador. $23.</p>
        <p>NOBODY'S alone in the Indian village of Kaikurussi. There's too much going on at close quarters. Villagers drop in and out of one another's lives in dizzying profusion, telling their stories and collecting new ones to work into the web of gossip that supports them. Under such circumstances, public opinion can push even the best man into behaving badly, as the Indian writer Anita Nair demonstrates in her thickly populated first novel, ''The Better Man.''</p>
        <p>Spared from dying in a train wreck, Bhasi has taken his narrow escape as a sign. It's time to change his life. He's a healer now, he declares in an opening monologue. An educated man turned house painter, Bhasi is more interested in repairing souls than decorating houses. ''Damaged lives,'' he explains, ''fill my world as much as flaking paint.''</p>
        <p>Also known to the villagers as One-Screw-Loose Bhasi, the painter is on a mission to fix them as well. ''I do not capsulate healing with compounds and equations packed into little pink and blue gelatin caps,'' he explains. Instead he hears people's complaints and, using the right combination of herbs and subtle suggestions, helps them recover. So when the retirement plans of a government bureaucrat named Mukundan Nair collapse and he moves back to Kaikurussi, Bhasi rejoices. The man with a mission has found the patient of a lifetime.</p>
        <p>Introducing Mukundan, the author shifts the novel from Bhasi's monologue into the third person. As a boy, Mukundan ran away to escape his father's cruelty, then turned his back on his entire family. Now, many years later, he has left a narrow, well-ordered city life to return to a village that is cluttered with Nairs, including his crusty old father, Achuthan, and Krishnan Nair, a doddering cook and major-domo.</p>
        <p>Troubles proliferate. In fact, the minute Mukundan explores the old homestead, his mother's ghost appears to reproach him. (She fell to her death on the stairs -- his fault, she implies, for not being there to prevent it.) Mukundan is a bad fit in the village. To make things worse, he's still afraid of his father.</p>
        <p>Although Achuthan moved across the road many years ago to live with his mistress, he drops in on his son every day, belaboring him with rhetorical questions. And Mukundan is so intimidated that he mumbles anything to please him. To relieve the tension, Mukundan copes in the way that he has ever since he was a boy, by writing letters. To the postmaster. To the phone company. To the employer of a murdered villager. Even his prayers sound like letters to God.</p>
        <p>Mukundan is obviously a prime candidate for Bhasi the healer: '' 'My mother . . .' he began and then suddenly stopped. . . . For a moment he wished it were night. When shadows encouraged the darkness of the soul to venture outside. When he could sit across from Bhasi. . . . When he could let feelings, pent-up for so many decades, wash over his listener and leave Mukundan himself feeling empty and light.''</p>
        <p>Eventually, Mukundan does confide in Bhasi, but the healing process is impeded by a village intrigue involving a schemer named Power House Ramakrishnan. There is as well the matter of the married woman Mukundan has fallen in love with. If he moves her into his house before her divorce becomes final, what will his father think? What will the village think?</p>
        <p>Some novels know where they're going from the very first sentence, and the delight for the reader is in their velocity -- in following the arrow as it speeds for the target. This one seems to discover what it's about as it goes along. Bhasi's opening monologue reads like an afterthought tacked on to bring all the pieces together.</p>
        <p>A genial, meandering tale filled with false alarms and diversions, ''The Better Man'' is slowed by loops in the story, by abandoned threads of plot. Charming as it is, the novel gathers momentum only at the end, when Bhasi and Mukundan find themselves at odds just in time for the drama of conflict and resolution.</p>
        <p>Kit Reed's new novel, ''@expectations,'' will be published this fall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kit Reed's new novel, ''@expectations,'' will be published this fall.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
