<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Book of Hours</title>
    <meta content="13MOORHOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moorhouse, Geoffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Hannah</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Little Saint (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDA143CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Book of Hours</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Geoffrey Moorhouse</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moorhouse, Geoffrey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Geoffrey Moorhouse reviews book Little Saint by Hannah Green; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LITTLE SAINT</p>
        <p>By Hannah Green.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 276 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $25.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LITTLE SAINT</p>
        <p>By Hannah Green.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 276 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $25.95.</p>
        <p>In 1975, Hannah Green and her husband, Jack Wesley, discovered on the old pilgrim route from Le Puy to Santiago de Compostela, a hill village called Conques, where French is a second language and the native patois is derived from the ancient langue d'oc. So enchanted were the Americans that Conques became an alternative to their home in New York, and eventually they were regularly commuting between the two. Not only were they accepted by the Conquois, but they were integrated into the life of the village, the ultimate compliment to and privilege of the urban incomer to any rural community. Sophisticated outsiders can often be caught patronizing the peasants without even intending to, but no such crassness seems to have occurred here. Instead, Green and her husband became simply 'Annah and Monsieur Jacques, and their gift for friendship was obviously valued.</p>
        <p>This book, which Green was finishing at the time of her death in 1996, is a result of that happy conjunction, and I don't believe I've come across anything as good since Elliot Paul (does anyone still read him nowadays?) was writing ''The Life and Death of a Spanish Town'' and ''A Narrow Street'' over half a century ago. But Paul's superb evocations of place and people lacked the spiritual element that is Green's great driving force.</p>
        <p>As a 13-year-old in Ohio, a newly confirmed Episcopalian, she had thrilled to the distinctive cadences of the Book of Common Prayer (''Therefore with Angels and Archangels, and with all the company of heaven''), but she was ''a stranger to saints.'' That was Roman Catholic and Orthodox territory -- until in middle age, with one highly regarded novel (''The Dead of the House'') to her name, she found herself besotted with the patron and presiding spirit of Conques, the 12-year-old girl who was martyred not far away in Agen toward the end of the Great Persecution in A.D. 303, just before the emperor Constantine made Christianity officially acceptable. Most respectable hagiologies are not at all sure that St. Foy actually existed (in common with many another sanctified legend), but no such doubts are entertained in Conques, which has lived by, with and for Foy since her bones were interred there 500 years after her death.</p>
        <p>This is not simply a matter of paying regular devotion to the figure, encrusted with jewels, that is enshrined in the treasure house near the Romanesque church, or of a steadfast belief that the martyred child performed miracles and was capable of bilocation. The fact is that Foy is even now the great reference point for almost everything that happens, day in and day out, to the Conquois: when they are working in their gardens, when they are bringing their beasts down from the sloping pastures, when they are gathering the walnuts and chestnuts that were once the staple diet of an isolated and impoverished village, when they make the sign of the cross as they cut into a loaf of bread. Monsieur Charlou's two massive cows, Fleurou and Parisii, may be exceptions to this general reverence, but on Green's evidence, I wouldn't go to the stake for that.</p>
        <p>It is through the medium of St. Foy that the cast list of Conques gradually unfolds: Pere Andre, whose health was broken by the Germans, now custodian of the shrine in his white monk's habit, with his powerful intellect and absolute devotion to the saint; Madame Benoit, who was an 11-year-old angel in the local Passion play and is now a 91-year-old widow, a bit dotty in her piety; Le Fraysou, the garbage man, whose family has lived in Conques for 400 years and bequeathed him a fine tenor voice, which he exercises melodiously as he works; Rosalie, a farmer's wife who grows magnificent vegetables and tells Green where she can be found at a given hour by using a wayside cross as a guidepost; Remy, a gruff and upright old bachelor who generally smells of stale urine and bows to Green every time they meet; even the tragic figure of Jean Segelat, an artist who can recite reams of poetry by heart, who is, ''he told me once, exactly an inch taller than Napoleon'' and who has never got over his beloved Emanuelle's suicide. There are many others, but not, it seems, any young people, who have gone away to find work in the towns, as they do in rural communities from one end of Europe to the other.</p>
        <p>Praying to St. Foy is the same as praying to the Virgin Mary, according to Madame Benoit, who is both obsessive in her devotion and levelheaded in what she believes. ''Life is an envelope,'' she tells Hannah. ''We come from the unknown and we are going toward we know not where in this envelope we call our life.'' She thinks that, with St. Foy's help, the Conquois may understand this more easily than most because they are deeply rooted in a place of pilgrimage, having grown into their faith through many generations and centuries.</p>
        <p>For Green, arriving at the same point is much more sudden and dramatic. On her very first day in Conques, she stood listening to Pere Andre at the shrine, ''my mind immense with ecstasy, my throat constricted with awe and tenderness,'' and from then on there was no looking back: ''And it is more than tenderness, it is wonder and delight and admiration.'' She becomes convinced that ''something was there, some force or power that could be felt and that could affect one whether one willed it so or no.'' As she looks out at ''the great majestic volume of the church, I feel this immense and yet somehow humble, warming earth presence which is God filling the ancient church, swelling it somehow from silence into sound.'' This is the way people speak when they are seriously falling in love. Frequently, Green can say what she feels only by resorting to the language of infatuation.</p>
        <p>There are many jewels in this book, quite apart from those that sparkle and glow in the prodigious shrine. There's a highfalutin' idea in some quarters that the only creative writing is to be found in fiction, in verse and in drama, but ''Little Saint'' demonstrates what a silliness that is. Here is a wonderfully imaginative response to everything Green encountered in France, originating in that part of the true writer's being where intuition and visions begin. And the formative influence of the prayer book that Archbishop Cranmer first supervised, which reached its present form in 1662, employing the most elegant and luminous language ever devised for liturgical purposes in the English-speaking world, is very clear in Green's instinct for words. The majority of novels aren't half as well written as ''Little Saint,'' and the only lame phrase is the title (by another hand, I suspect), which suggests a sentimental religiosity that couldn't be further from the truth. Green also has a great eye for significant detail, which enables her to note a thrush singing at midday as if it were twilight and to make intelligible the tangled loyalties and jealousies that surfaced during World War II, when some villagers risked their lives in the Resistance and others denounced their neighbors.</p>
        <p>Among many things, this is a book about the writing of a book: ''Even though it is still only partway to where it will be, and even though I have many times despaired of being able to make it as good as it must be, still it has already brought so much to me as I work to bring it to life and inform it, absorbing knowledge, which in turn is absorbing me and leading me toward Christ the Word.'' At bottom and essentially, you see, this is a book about Faith -- which, as it happens, is how Foy translates into English from the patois of Conques. I would give quite a lot to have written it myself.</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Moorhouse's most recent books are ''Sun Dancing'' and ''Sydney.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Geoffrey Moorhouse's most recent books are ''Sun Dancing'' and ''Sydney.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
