<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Shadow Man</title>
    <meta content="13RIDINGT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1221978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lichtenstein, Rachel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sinclair, Iain</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rodinsky's Room (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5D6163CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Shadow Man</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Riding</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Riding reviews book Rodinsky's Room by Rachel Lichtenstein and Iain Sinclair (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RODINSKY'S ROOM</p>
        <p>By Rachel Lichtenstein and Iain Sinclair.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 338 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Granta Books. $29.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RODINSKY'S ROOM</p>
        <p>By Rachel Lichtenstein and Iain Sinclair.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 338 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Granta Books. $29.95.</p>
        <p>With his death in 1986, Gedaliah Lichtenstein set in motion the bizarre sequence of events that led to this book. He was no sooner buried than his 17-year-old granddaughter, Rachel Laurence, dropped her Anglicized surname and legally reclaimed Lichtenstein. A few months later, inspired by her grandfather's dream of becoming an artist, she began attending art college. She spent her summers tracing remnants of Jewish life in Poland, the land that Gedaliah fled in the 1930's. And for her graduation thesis, her chosen topic, Jewish immigration to England, led her to the East End of London, where her grandfather first settled.</p>
        <p>Up to this point, Lichtenstein's search for roots was perhaps not that unusual. Then her journey took a curious turn. While visiting the old Jewish quarter of Whitechapel, she learned of a hermit who more than 20 years earlier had vanished from his room above the Princelet Street synagogue. For more than a decade, it was as if David Rodinsky had never existed. Then, in 1980, his room was opened, revealing books and writings in several languages as well as documents covered with cabalistic symbols. Suddenly he took his place in local Jewish lore as a scholar and mystic. Yet by the early 1990's, his life and disappearance had still not been explained.</p>
        <p>Lichtenstein took it upon herself to break the case. ''I felt Rodinsky had chosen me to tell his story, and I wanted to ensure it was told as accurately as possible,'' she writes in ''Rodinsky's Room,'' her gripping account of her decade-long investigation into who the real Rodinsky was and what happened to him. At this level alone, the book reads like a psychological thriller. Yet what makes ''Rodinsky's Room'' so enthralling is that it works at several other levels. It is also the story of a personal, cultural and religious voyage that leads a half-Jewish Englishwoman to embrace Orthodox Judaism in Israel, to visit death camps in Poland and to delve into the tattered remnants of Jewish immigrant life in London. Adding another dimension, the book is written with Iain Sinclair, an English novelist and essayist who not only observes Lichtenstein in her obsessive search for Rodinsky but also provides valuable context through his rich knowledge of hidden London. Their collaboration -- they write alternate chapters -- works exceptionally well.</p>
        <p>When Lichtenstein first entered 19 Princelet Street, it was no longer an active house of worship, yet its past life seemed all too present. ''The faded purple cushions of the bimah were covered in tattered prayer shawls that looked as if they had been sitting there for decades,'' she writes. ''The wrought-iron balcony was thick with dust and cobwebs. Various artifacts from the attic were strewn around the floor. I cried.'' Soon, she learned that her grandfather's first London home was only a few doors away, that her grandparents may have been married in the synagogue. ''I knew I was meant to be there,'' she recalls.</p>
        <p>Her first plan was to become an artist-in-residence in the building, now called the Heritage Center. The center's director even approved the idea, but the young artist felt paralyzed. Instead, she found herself increasingly drawn to Rodinsky's attic room and the puzzle of his life.</p>
        <p>Years earlier, his papers had been removed to dry out; now they had been returned in boxes. The room offered strange clues: indecipherable symbols on the keys of a dilapidated piano; a cabalistic diagram hidden behind a wardrobe. Lichtenstein began emptying the boxes and made more finds: notebooks revealing Rodinsky's knowledge of Sumerian, Arabic, Japanese, Hebrew, Yiddish, Greek, Russian and Egyptian hieroglyphics; kosher food packets and religious books suggesting he held Orthodox beliefs; hand-drawn maps recording journeys around London; a letter referring to his sister's death.</p>
        <p>But Lichtenstein discovered no photograph of Rodinsky and, as she expanded her inquiries, she met few people who remembered more than a passing crouched figure in old clothes. She went to a local library and found articles about the changing neighborhood, as well as one by Sinclair entitled ''The Man Who Became a Room.'' Soon afterward, she met Sinclair, who shared what he knew about Rodinsky. But as a novelist, he seemed happy to live with the mystery. ''The Princelet Street room, its shifts and moods, its objects and furniture, is all we have,'' he writes.</p>
        <p>Lichtenstein wanted more. She learned he had died on March 4, 1969, of bronchopneumonia in Epsom, Surrey, at 44. Why Epsom? The area included five psychiatric hospitals, one of which, Longrove, had burned down five years earlier. She had spread word of her search around Whitechapel and was led to Bella Lipman, who had lived below Rodinsky. ''In her opinion he was no genius,'' she writes; ''in fact, she described him as almost retarded.'' Lichtenstein met Rodinsky's cousin, Ethel, who spoke of his unbalanced mother, his early years in a foster home, his unhappiness prior to his disappearance.</p>
        <p>Lichtenstein ''kept breaking away, withdrawing, resuming other projects,'' Sinclair writes. ''But it was no good. Rodinsky, the idea of Rodinsky, had become a dybbuk. The soul of a dead person who enters the body of a living human and directs their conduct.'' Lichtenstein spent time in Israel and came close to committing herself to Orthodoxy, but was pulled back by her uncompleted quest. She traveled again in Poland. She had a child, whom she named David. All along she was building her case.</p>
        <p>A retired social worker from the Jewish Welfare Board told her that Rodinsky's internment in a psychiatric hospital was no proof that he was mad. She needed this reassurance. ''The Longrove was the kind of place that was full</p>
        <p>of cabalistic geniuses and religious scholars wrapped up in the world of metaphysics,'' the man said. ''In that period there were many mistakes made. Many of the nurses were Asian, many of the doctors from Middle Europe, there were very serious communication problems.''</p>
        <p>Appropriately, though, it was while on another trip to Poland, searching for the shadows of her grandfather as well as of Rodinsky, that Lichtenstein met an Englishman, David Jacobs, who would lead her to Rodinsky's grave. More than likely, he said, it could be found in the old Jewish cemetery at Waltham Abbey. A telephone call to the Epsom records office confirmed this, and soon Lichtenstein and Jacobs were standing before a shallow gravel plot, with no headstone and only a tin plaque. ''David stood with me in silence,'' she writes. ''Finally, I opened my prayer-book and together we read the Kaddish.'' The circle had finally closed. She had exercised her birthright, as Sinclair put it, as ''someone who could read the history of the room as an analogue of their own undisclosed heritage.''</p>
        <p>Alan Riding is the European cultural correspondent of The Times, based in Paris.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alan Riding is the European cultural correspondent of The Times, based in Paris.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
