<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Couple's 'Crazy' Adventures</title>
    <meta content="13BOAT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BOATING REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Herb</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pardey, Lin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pardey, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EED9123FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Couple's 'Crazy' Adventures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERB McCORMICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccormick, Herb</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Herb McCormick profiles Lin and Larry Pardey, who for last 30 years have chronicled their adventures on series of sailboats they have built themselves; their devotion to ultrasimple, cost-conscious voyaging is legendary, but also ripe for criticism from those who believe cruising boats must be equipped with hefty diesel engines and copious electronics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1969, when Lin and Larry Pardey set out from Southern California aboard the 24-foot Seraffyn, their engineless self-built wooden cutter, they traveled on the winds of modest expectations. ''We'd never had a reasonable holiday in our working lives and we just wanted to do something that was all about sailing,'' Larry said. ''The thought of cruising around Mexico for a few months with time off was just cool.''</p>
        <p>Three decades later, the act of sailing -- and the art of chronicling their adventures -- remains the axis around which the Pardey's peripatetic lifestyle spins. With 11 books and 4 videos to their credit and more than 100,000 miles of voyaging behind them, Larry, 60, and Lin, 56, show no signs of slowing down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1969, when Lin and Larry Pardey set out from Southern California aboard the 24-foot Seraffyn, their engineless self-built wooden cutter, they traveled on the winds of modest expectations. ''We'd never had a reasonable holiday in our working lives and we just wanted to do something that was all about sailing,'' Larry said. ''The thought of cruising around Mexico for a few months with time off was just cool.''</p>
        <p>Three decades later, the act of sailing -- and the art of chronicling their adventures -- remains the axis around which the Pardey's peripatetic lifestyle spins. With 11 books and 4 videos to their credit and more than 100,000 miles of voyaging behind them, Larry, 60, and Lin, 56, show no signs of slowing down.</p>
        <p>''When we started out our motto was 'As long as it's fun,' '' Lin said. ''I guess now it's 'As long as we're able.' But we're still having these crazy experiences and they're always different.''</p>
        <p>Last week the Pardeys slipped into Newport, R.I., on the 29-foot-6-inch Taleisin, which Larry built from teak and black locust, and which the couple moved aboard in 1983. Having left the sweltering Chesapeake Bay about a month before, the Pardeys swung north using one of the basic guidelines that is crucial to all their routing decisions.</p>
        <p>''We didn't like it there,'' Larry said. ''Too hot. And we'd been invited to a classic-boat rendezvous in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''So we took off and brought our home with us. How many people can do that?''</p>
        <p>The Pardeys have been an inspiration to plenty of neophyte voyagers. But their devotion to ultrasimple, cost-conscious voyaging has also been ripe for both lampooning and criticism, particularly from those who believe cruising boats must be equipped with hefty diesel engines and copious electronics. ''Well, we see a lot of people out there who spend all their time fixing their refrigeration and stuff,'' Larry said.</p>
        <p>The Pardeys' writing career was launched when, in the early 70's and anchored with Seraffyn among a dozen similarly modest boats near the Panama Canal, Lin read a magazine article that stated the perfect size for a cruising boat was 57 feet. In anger, she zipped off a rebuttal letter. It led to the birth of a career that has financed countless adventures.</p>
        <p>And Larry insists it was economics, not philosophy, that led them to sail Seraffyn without an engine, a practice they have continued with Taleisin. ''When we first set off we could live in Mexico for $200 a month,'' he said. ''The way we looked at it, a $3,000 engine cost 14 months of freedom. We never dreamed of going cruising and being comfortable, we just dreamed of going.''</p>
        <p>The Pardeys also have some steadfast opinions on the state of long-distance voyaging. For navigation they carry two sextants but forgo Global Positioning System navigation, which most mariners insist is a necessity for contemporary cruising. And they believe that many sailors, especially inexperienced ones, are being subtly coerced into buying equipment they do not need.</p>
        <p>''You put the word safety on some of this gear and it's like saying the word motherhood; it's sacred,'' said Lin, who knows that her views are controversial. ''So, some sailors can't figure out what they need and what they don't need. And they don't set out until they buy all the so-called safety gear they can find.</p>
        <p>''What's happening is that people aren't being told to learn the necessary skills to give them confidence, to learn how exciting and safe and maneuverable a sailboat can be,'' she said. ''An extra block and tackle to rig a preventer on the boom, a spare halyard, a kerosene lamp if you lose electric power -- that's safety gear.''</p>
        <p>The Pardeys are also not fans of the long-distance cruising rallies that have become so popular in the last decade, in which groups of boats -- for a fee -- travel the globe in packs for security and companionship.</p>
        <p>''That's fine, but a lot of these people are in such a hurry that they're irresponsible,'' Larry said. They get someplace, drop the anchor and go ashore for a guided tour. Their boats are unattended and if they drag anchor and hit someone, it's no big deal. They have insurance. But it's a problem for the people they run into.''</p>
        <p>Today, as they ease closer toward retirement age, if not spirit, the Pardeys find themselves working about six months a year and traveling for the balance. They are also involved in charity work on the Chesapeake Bay, and will open their simple, remarkable boat to the public during the United States Sailboat Show in Annapolis, Md., in early October.</p>
        <p>THE BOATING REPORT Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
