<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 8-13-00: On Language; Franken--</title>
    <meta content="WLN132607" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nicholson, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shelley, Mary (1797-1851)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">On Language (Times Column)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Frankenstein (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0D8113CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 8-13-00: On Language; Franken--</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Safire</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire On Language column on prefix 'franken,' reference to Dr Victor Frankenstein, who created monster in Mary Shelley's novel, that is being used throughout Europe by members of antigenetic movement to describe genetically-altered foods; on issue of sentence fragments in light of Republican Party chairman Jim Nicholson's release under headline encapsulating his party's message for presidential campaign, 'Renewing America's Purpose. Together' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The hottest combining form in populist suspicion of science was coined in a letter to The New York Times on June 2, 1992, from Paul Lewis, professor of English at Boston College.</p>
        <p>Commenting on an Op-Ed column criticizing the Food and Drug Administration's decision to exempt genetically engineered crops from case-by-case review, Professor Lewis held, ''Ever since Mary Shelley's baron rolled his improved human flesh out of the lab, scientists have been bringing such good things to life.'' After this reference to Dr. Victor Frankenstein, who created the monster in Ms. Shelley's 1818 novel, the academic letter writer shot a bolt of juice into the lifeless coinage dodge with ''If they want to sell us Frankenfood, perhaps it's time to gather the villagers, light some torches and head to the castle.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The hottest combining form in populist suspicion of science was coined in a letter to The New York Times on June 2, 1992, from Paul Lewis, professor of English at Boston College.</p>
        <p>Commenting on an Op-Ed column criticizing the Food and Drug Administration's decision to exempt genetically engineered crops from case-by-case review, Professor Lewis held, ''Ever since Mary Shelley's baron rolled his improved human flesh out of the lab, scientists have been bringing such good things to life.'' After this reference to Dr. Victor Frankenstein, who created the monster in Ms. Shelley's 1818 novel, the academic letter writer shot a bolt of juice into the lifeless coinage dodge with ''If they want to sell us Frankenfood, perhaps it's time to gather the villagers, light some torches and head to the castle.''</p>
        <p>And that's what they did! ''Genetic engineering'' was not then a scary enough phrase. The science of making foods more productive or resistant to disease had noncontroversial roots in hybrid corn pioneered in 1923, but ethical concerns about cloning merged with worries about mad-cow disease and suited the promotion of ''organic'' foods. A frightening metaphor was needed, and the Franken- prefix did the trick.</p>
        <p>A Boston Globe reporter wrote in 1992 that Frankenfood ''summed up nicely the monstrous unnaturalness of such controversial new products as genetically enhanced tomatoes and chromosome-tinkered cows,'' and quoted the delighted Lewis, today chairman of the English department, saying: ''It has a phonetic rhythm, it's pithy and you can use the Franken- prefix on anything: Frankenfruit. . . . Frankenair. . . . Frankenwater. It's a Frankenworld.''</p>
        <p>Since then, biotechnophobes and other members of the antigenetic movement have denounced Frankenseeds, Frankenveggies, Frankenfish, Frankenpigs and Frankenchicken, lumping them together as fearsome Frankenscience. In The Chicago Tribune, David Greising wrote in 1999 of Frankenfarmers supported by Frankenfans arguing with Frankenprotesters about unfounded Frankenfears.</p>
        <p>Frankly, there's no telling when or how it will end. It has enhanced the sales of the metaphysical novel that Ms. Shelley's husband, the poet Percy Bysshe Shelley, encouraged her to write, and has not harmed sales at ''Frank'n'Stein,'' the fast-food chain whose hot dogs and beer I find delectably inorganic.</p>
        <p>At the American Dialect Society, Laurence Horn says: ''I was hoping somebody might have coined Frankensense by now. This would be sort of the opposite of common sense, maybe as a description of politicians' motivations for a creatively stupid piece of legislation.''</p>
        <p>But this play on frankincense, an aromatic gum resin used in religious ceremonies, has not caught on. ''Alas,'' says the dialectologist Horn, ''all the Web site usages I can find for Frankensense seem to be unintended misspellings of the traditional Christmas gift. You can tell because there's an equally orthographically challenged rendering of myrrh.''</p>
        <p>No Sentence Fragments</p>
        <p>Jim Nicholson, the G.O.P. chairman, sent out a release under a header encapsulating his party's message for the current campaign: ''Renewing America's Purpose. Together.''</p>
        <p>This raises the issue of sentence fragments. Slogans -- from the Gaelic sluagh- (army) gairm (yell), or ''battle cry'' -- need not be complete sentences. A Republican slogan in the 1928 campaign was ''Hoover and Happiness, or Smith and Soup Houses,'' which contained no verb. (The Democratic response four years later, ''In Hoover We Trusted, Now We Are Busted,'' was a comma splice of two complete sentences and helped elect F.D.R.) Some facetious slogans of the 70's were sentences (''Support Mental Health or I'll Kill You'') and some were not (''Dog Litter -- An Issue You Can't Sidestep'').</p>
        <p>I have long rallied to battle cries containing verbs. ''Keep Cool With Coolidge'' strikes me as more forceful than ''Rum, Romanism and Rebellion,'' the ill-chosen phrase that sank James Blaine's campaign against Grover Cleveland, though both phrases were alliterative gems. ''Vote as You Shot,'' with its two verbs, stirred Ulysses Grant's followers, while ''Elect a Leader Not a Lover'' savaged Nelson Rockefeller, and ''Make Love Not War'' signs danced at demonstrations in the 1960's. All these were short sentences studded with the action of verbs and not passive sentence fragments.</p>
        <p>What is a sentence fragment? A decade ago, I collected a bunch of ''fumblerules'' that demonstrated the errors they intended to correct. These ranged from ''Don't Use No Double Negatives'' to ''Avoid Cliches Like the Plague,'' and included ''No Sentence Fragments.'' I confidently passed along the conventional pop-grammarian wisdom that a sentence should contain a complete thought and thus required a verb.</p>
        <p>Not so fast (as sentence-fragmenters say). James McCawley, the late linguistics master at the University of Chicago, took issue with my knee-jerk pedagogy. First, he noted that a sentence should express, rather than be, a complete thought. This was no nit-pick; the example he gave was the answer to ''What did he buy?'' ''A hatrack.'' McCawley wrote that ''A hatrack expresses exactly the same thought as He bought a hatrack and hence doesn't express any less complete a thought: the difference between the full sentence and the sentence fragment is not in the completeness of the thought expressed but in the completeness of the form in which it is expressed.''</p>
        <p>Furthermore, McCawley instructed me that ''for something that occupies the position of a sentence to be a 'sentence fragment,' it is not necessary that it not contain a verb.'' The fragment of an expressed thought -- not a complete sentence -- can indeed contain a verb: Lincoln's anguished ''And the war came'' is an example.</p>
        <p>Seized of the great grammarian's clarifying subtlety, and willing after 10 years to rethink my pronouncement (and allowing for sloganeering license), I cannot now denounce the current Republican slogan as blatantly incorrect.</p>
        <p>That slogan -- Renewing America's Purpose. Together.'' -- may be choppy prose and less than catchy or rousing. And putting ''together'' at the end, freestanding, rather than at the beginning as ''Together Renewing America's Purpose,'' seems to make the unity pitch appear to be an afterthought. But the two expressed thoughts cannot be easily denounced as an offense to good grammar. Just awkward.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
