<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends: Your Move; And Now for Something Completely Different . . .</title>
    <meta content="13BERK$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4DD123FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1262" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends: Your Move; And Now for Something Completely Different . . .</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Gore's introduction at Democratic convention will play down his last eight years, even though Gore has been most productive, industrious vice president in modern times; photo; speakers will rattle on about Tennessee farm boy, Harvard student, Vietnam enlistee, reporter and senator, calculating that Gore needs to be seen as his own man; Gov George W Bush, perhaps unfairly, will claim leadership role although he is far less seasoned (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NO matter whether you think Al Gore should be the next president, give him this much: He has transformed the vice presidency, the subject of generations of derision, into more than the butt of jokes. Not content to languish at state funerals, Mr. Gore has been the most productive and industrious vice president in modern times.</p>
        <p>Even Gov. George W. Bush, in a rare compliment to his rival, volunteered recently that Mr. Gore had been a good No. 2.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NO matter whether you think Al Gore should be the next president, give him this much: He has transformed the vice presidency, the subject of generations of derision, into more than the butt of jokes. Not content to languish at state funerals, Mr. Gore has been the most productive and industrious vice president in modern times.</p>
        <p>Even Gov. George W. Bush, in a rare compliment to his rival, volunteered recently that Mr. Gore had been a good No. 2.</p>
        <p>So it is remarkable that Mr. Gore's political coming out here this  week has been designed not merely as the usual paean to the party's new standard-bearer, but also as a production that will neglect, obscure and even expunge his time in what he calls the ''Square Office,'' only 18 steps down the blue-carpeted corridor from the Oval Office.</p>
        <p>Instead, the program calls for speaker after speaker to rattle on about Al Gore the Tennessee farm boy, Al Gore the Harvard student, Al Gore the enlistee in Vietnam, Al Gore the reporter, Al Gore the House member, Al Gore the senator and -- blithely skipping the last eight years -- Al Gore, the man of the future.</p>
        <p>Forget that Mr. Gore championed an ambitious program to streamline the federal bureaucracy, or that he was the point man in relations with Russia, or that he bested Ross Perot in a debate, clearing the path for the North American Free Trade Agreement. Until he deletes the word ''vice'' from his title, the political calculation is that Mr. Gore will not be seen as his own man.</p>
        <p>Perhaps unfairly, Governor Bush, who presides over a single state (one in which the chief executive office is notably weak) and is far less seasoned in governing, can more easily claim the leadership mantle because he, at least, is in charge of something.</p>
        <p>In fact, voters are apt to say Mr. Bush is as experienced a leader as Mr. Gore. Asked in a poll taken in late March whether Mr. Gore's performance as vice president made them more or less likely to support him, 28 percent of registered voters said more likely, 27 percent said less likely and 43 percent said it made no difference.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's most aggressive move to submerge his vice presidency came last week when he named a No. 2 of his own. By making history in picking Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, the first Jewish running mate of a major party, Mr. Gore succeeded in persuading at least some voters to take another measure of him as a decisive, imaginative leader.</p>
        <p>Yet in unveiling Senator Lieberman, Mr. Gore was so determined to shed his own service as No. 2 that he made no reference to the office itself or to his first-hand knowledge of why it is vital to have a capable second-in-command. The Gore campaign has been so determined to blot out the vice president from Al Gore that his title was intentionally not included in mentions of him  in the Democratic platform.</p>
        <p>Some strategists and academics argue that it is folly for Mr. Gore to flee from the governing credentials that would seem to be his most compelling selling point. If anything, they argue, six years after the Gingrich revolution that catapulted Washington outsiders into power, voters may be ready for tested steadiness.</p>
        <p>Gary Jacobson, a political science professor at the University of California at San Diego, said, ''His strongest suit is, 'You've never had it so good.' He needs to nail down the case that the good times we're all enjoying can be attributed to the Clinton-Gore administration.''</p>
        <p>SCOFFING at the notion that Mr. Gore should be dwelling on his tenure in the White House, William Daley, the Gore campaign chairman, said: ''He'd be murdered by you all if he was trying to take credit for all he's done in the last eight years. People want to hear what you're going to do as president. They don't want to walk down Memory Lane.''</p>
        <p>Memories may be the single biggest reason Mr. Gore refuses to embrace his vice presidency -- but those memories are of President Clinton. The belief among many Gore advisers is that the president's transgressions have so soiled the White House that recitations of Mr. Gore's accomplishments would immediately be tainted by association, or revive talk of the vice president's own lapses, like his attending a fund-raiser at a Buddhist temple. The one subject Mr. Gore is happy to recall, and may well underscore at the national convention, is his contribution to the longstanding economic boom.</p>
        <p>But there is far more at play than Mr. Gore trying to break free from his boss. His advisers say they realize through polling and focus groups that the vice president desperately needs to spruce up his image. ''They know Al Gore's been vice president, or they have an impression of stiff and boring,'' Mr. Daley said. ''But here's a guy who's had a full life.''</p>
        <p>The desire to reintroduce Mr. Gore and play up his human side has been a constant in his campaign, and his career, often to little avail.</p>
        <p>If nothing else, campaign advisers say that when Mr. Gore takes center stage, they want voters to remember these facts: He opted to serve in Vietnam at a time when many young men were finding excuses not to. He is passionate about protecting the environment. He stood boldly on his own in the Senate and, over the objections of prominent Democratic leaders, voted for the use of force in the Persian Gulf war. He is such a family man that he thinks nothing of altering his schedule so he can watch his children play lacrosse.</p>
        <p>The Gore camp is playing up such biographical snippets to address the central paradox of the Gore candidacy: advisers fear the very skills that make Mr. Gore a successful sidekick -- he is disciplined, dutiful and loyal -- are not the qualities people look for in a president.</p>
        <p>The notion is that voters want an engaging leader who is not simply a loyal trooper. They do not think someone deserves the Oval Office simply because he has diligently climbed the rungs of power. ''You don't remind people what you were  when you're looking for a promotion,'' said Marla Romash, a longtime adviser to Mr. Gore. ''You want to convince them that you're up for the bigger job.''</p>
        <p>ONLY three times in the last 80 years has a sitting vice president run on his own after eight years in office, and both Mr. Nixon and Mr. Bush had to struggle to get voters to stop thinking of them as junior partners.</p>
        <p>In 1960, Vice President Richard Nixon didn't even want the popular president, Dwight Eisenhower, stumping on his behalf, so eager was he to get out of his boss's shadow.</p>
        <p>This is the problem that has now fallen to Mr. Gore, who knows full well that for every commercial his campaign runs that features the candidate surrounded by his family or extolling his vision, Republicans intend to portray him just where he does not want to be seen: in service to his country.</p>
        <p>''He can not make the eight years vaporize,'' said Mark McKinnon, Mr. Bush's chief media strategist. ''They are there, and he has to live with them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
