<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Place Your Bet: A Vegas Casino, or a Virtual One?</title>
    <meta content="13SLAS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BACKSLASH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Backslash</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2DF153FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Place Your Bet: A Vegas Casino, or a Virtual One?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <dateline>LAS VEGAS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matt Richtel column assesses threat to conventional gambling casinos posed by Internet gambling sites; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NERVOUS casino executives are lobbying to make Internet gambling an illegal activity, concerned that their business will falter if people can stay at home and play on their personal computers.</p>
        <p>But regular casinogoers here say the executives have nothing to worry about. They contend that the Internet and Las Vegas are such vastly different worlds that it is kind of like comparing apples and oranges in a slot machine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NERVOUS casino executives are lobbying to make Internet gambling an illegal activity, concerned that their business will falter if people can stay at home and play on their personal computers.</p>
        <p>But regular casinogoers here say the executives have nothing to worry about. They contend that the Internet and Las Vegas are such vastly different worlds that it is kind of like comparing apples and oranges in a slot machine.</p>
        <p>''I would never gamble on the Internet,'' said a corporate vice president visiting from Lexington, Ky. ''There's no way to believe you're getting accurate odds,'' he added with a scoff.</p>
        <p>But he and his girlfriend, who works in marketing and public relations, said they felt good about their chances playing the Wheel of Fortune slot machine at the Mirage Hotel.</p>
        <p>It's not that they were winning money -- just the opposite -- but three times the slot machine came up one roll short of delivering a row of three sevens. Those near misses seemed to demonstrate to the couple that a jackpot might be just around the corner.</p>
        <p>''If that would have turned one more time,'' he said to his girlfriend as he inserted his third $20 bill into the machine, ''it would have been big money. Big money!''</p>
        <p>Not only do casino patrons seem to trust the gambling odds in Las Vegas more than they do those of the 700 or so Internet casinos, but they also note that there is more to this colorful city than just losing money. It's an experience that can't be replicated on a PC monitor.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to sit at home in the dark just hitting my mouse button over and over,'' said Ken Harrison, 30, from San Francisco.</p>
        <p>He would rather not be at home, lost in his own dark world, pouring electronic money into a dreary electronic box connected to a central server and with a video monitor displaying animated images.</p>
        <p>This is a subject that Mr. Harrison knows something about, since at that moment (noon, roughly -- though it is hard to tell, as casinos are kind enough to omit potential distractions like clocks and windows) he was sitting in the dark at the Treasure Island casino, pouring real money into  one of the new computerized slot machines that are connected to servers,  and watching animated images of fruit, police officers and bags of money whirl by.</p>
        <p>Asked if this experience wasn't entirely unlike sitting at home in the dark playing on a computer, Mr. Harrison replied, ''Good point.'' He then put another nickel into the machine.</p>
        <p>''People around here do look pretty zoned out,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But hanging out here, Mr. Harrison added, was still a far more social experience than playing at home. ''Gambling at home by yourself is like drinking alone,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Back at the Mirage, the executive from Kentucky agreed. ''The Internet is so impersonal,'' he said, standing next to a man playing video poker alone and downing free gin gimlets.</p>
        <p>The bread-and-butter patrons of Las Vegas say that there is another important way in which this place differs from online casinos: it's not in the Caribbean. In fact, they often speak ill of the Caribbean, where most online casinos are based. They are skeptical about trusting off-shore virtual casinos to process credit cards and return winnings.</p>
        <p>Of course, some places here pretend to be in the Caribbean. Consider the Lagoon Saloon, a Mirage lounge that brochures call an ''island paradise.''</p>
        <p>''The Internet is full of disreputable characters,'' said an air traffic controller from Albuquerque who was playing the Who Dunnit slot machine at the Mirage.</p>
        <p>At least in Vegas, you have some idea of who the bad actors are, like Bugsy Siegel, the gangster who was one of Las Vegas's founding fathers, and whoever invented sequins.  ''Vegas has a history; you know what you're getting,'' the Albuquerque man said. Which is? ''I always come hoping to win, but I never do,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THE fact that he and other casino patrons trust how things will turn out in Las Vegas isn't its only draw -- nor the only reason that casino executives should feel confident about their prospects.</p>
        <p>Their casinos offer an unparalleled opportunity to sit in the dark in front of a monitor wearing whatever suits one's fancy, compulsively hitting buttons and pulling levers, smoking and drinking as if cigarette rationing and Prohibition were about to return.</p>
        <p>Best of all, casino patrons say, it is absolutely nothing like gambling over the Internet.</p>
        <p>BACKSLASH Matt Richtel reports on technology for The Times. His column about living and working in the technology maelstrom appears the second Sunday of each month.  E-mail: mrichtel@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Matt Richtel reports on technology for The Times. His column about living and working in the technology maelstrom appears the second Sunday of each month.
&lt;br&gt;E-mail: mrichtel@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
