<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chamber Music Fest Off on Strong Footing</title>
    <meta content="13THEA$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridgehampton Chamber Music Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodgers, Mary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E0D61F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chamber Music Fest Off on Strong Footing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mary Rodgers, composer and screenwriter, comments on upcoming Bridgehampton Chamber Music Festival, of which she is board member; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT 69, Mary Rodgers is not only accustomed to multiple identities, she can play them all, and not just one at a time.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rodgers, daughter of the composer Richard Rodgers, has won acclaim as a composer, with the musical ''Once Upon a Mattress.'' After musical comedy, she made an indelible imprint on the world of children's literature; then she wrote the screenplay for her classic book ''Freaky Friday.'' After three more screenplays for Disney, she concluded, with finality, that screenwriting was ''repulsive work.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT 69, Mary Rodgers is not only accustomed to multiple identities, she can play them all, and not just one at a time.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rodgers, daughter of the composer Richard Rodgers, has won acclaim as a composer, with the musical ''Once Upon a Mattress.'' After musical comedy, she made an indelible imprint on the world of children's literature; then she wrote the screenplay for her classic book ''Freaky Friday.'' After three more screenplays for Disney, she concluded, with finality, that screenwriting was ''repulsive work.''</p>
        <p>The meaningful work is ''keeping your eye out for new talent,'' she said. That she does as chairwoman of both the Rodgers and Hammerstein Organization and the Juilliard School. ''At my age, you make connections for people,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But as a board member of the Bridgehampton Chamber Music Festival, Ms. Rodgers, who has had a home in Quogue for 17 years, has discovered and is indulging ''a new love for me.''</p>
        <p>''Chamber music is the most personal communication among musicians,'' Ms. Rodgers said. ''There's no conductor. You breathe together. Steve Sondheim says it is almost erotic.''</p>
        <p>Marya Martin, the festival's founder and artistic director said, ''Mary goes all out, and she comes to every concert.'' Kenneth S. Davidson, who is married to Ms. Martin, is one of two vice chairmen of the Juilliard School.</p>
        <p>Talking about connections, it may seem inevitable that songs by Adam Guettel, Ms. Rodgers's son, are to be featured at 6:30 tonight in the chamber recital at the Bridgehampton Presbyterian Church, 2427 Montauk Highway.</p>
        <p>Yes and no. Mr. Guettel, 35, is an acclaimed new voice -- yes, he sings, too -- in theater. He has been acknowledged as a standard bearer for new directions in musicals, fusing classical and contemporary forms, crossing centuries, paying homage to the formal and bringing in the funk, all with idiosyncratic flair.</p>
        <p>Yet, tonight's is the first program that can remotely be called ''popular'' -- Ms. Martin's designation -- in her 17 seasons, which are more likely to include a trio by Borodin, a quartet by Mozart and a quintet by Dvorak. ''Last year, I started working on getting Adam here and now this is the year we have Audra too,'' said Ms. Martin, referring to the musical theater star Audra McDonald, a champion of Mr. Guettel's distinctive sounds.</p>
        <p>''I seized the moment to make music in such a beautiful place,'' Mr. Guettel said, ''and I was amazed that Audra was available.'' For Ms. Martin, the chamber music series is ''a little oasis of old values, like stepping back in time; our little festival is not the focus of the glitzy Hamptons scene.''</p>
        <p>''Myths and Mood Swings'' is the title of tonight's program, which also features a newly arranged third movement, ''Prayer,'' from Michael Kamen's symphony ''New Moon in the Old Moon's Arms'' and John Moravec's trio ''Mood Swings.''</p>
        <p>About Mr. Guettel's selections, among others from his recorded song cycle, ''Myths and Hymns,'' which was produced at the Joseph Papp Public Theater in an expanded 1998 concert titled ''Saturn Returns,'' he said, ''I will play guitar for Audra and we will sing two duets.'' One is taken from that cycle; the other is from his 1996 off-Broadway musical, ''Floyd Collins,'' based on a 1925 incident about a man trapped in a cave in Kentucky.</p>
        <p>Ms. Martin, who plays the flute in her programs, said, ''When I first heard Adam's music, I knew I wanted to get in the middle of those harmonies and tone colors; it's the same thing, the same love, that makes me want to play Bach, Beethoven and Brahms.''</p>
        <p>She may have been expecting a more traditional Broadway sound from Mr. Guettel, given his pedigree. ''I didn't grow up with Rodgers and Hammerstein around,'' Ms. Martin said. ''I'm a New Zealander.''</p>
        <p>Recalling the musical beginnings of Adam Guettel, too early to notice as it happened, she said: ''He was just bopping along when he was 18 months old. That was when his 4-year-old brother died and I suppose we didn't pay that much attention.</p>
        <p>''Then I discovered him singing. At 3, he was at the piano.''</p>
        <p>Then a piano teacher was called in, Ms. Rodgers recalled, and said, ''I've never taught a 3-year-old before.''</p>
        <p>''Just let him enjoy the music,'' Ms. Rodgers said. An all-encompassing life in music was in the making -- and schools and teachers that were tuned into ''accommodating his passions.''</p>
        <p>A 9-year-old boy soprano, Adam Guettel was in the New York City Opera children's chorus. At 11, he was a soloist. At 13, he formed a jazz group with two friends.</p>
        <p>''When he was 16,'' Ms. Rodgers said, ''I could say, well, certain minor criticisms. When he was 17, I thought, 'I better shut up.' He was writing stuff so far beyond what I could do or talk about.''</p>
        <p>Adam Guettel was 14 when Richard Rodgers died. ''The effect of his musical language inspires me,'' Mr. Guettel said. ''The more I hear it, the more I respect it. And his work supports my artistic endeavors. It's been my own personal N.E.A. grant.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
