<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>They Have a Right to Sing the Blues, and a Reason</title>
    <meta content="13JENN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/13/arts/13JENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davies, Debbie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tedeschi, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Block, Rory</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jennings, Dana</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE5DC1E3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1353" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>They Have a Right to Sing the Blues, and a Reason</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANA JENNINGS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jennings, Dana</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dana Jennings article explores reasons why white, middle-class women, including Debbie Davies, Susan Tedeschi and Rory Block, are embracing blues music; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHY do white women sing the blues?</p>
        <p>It's grueling work to peer over the broad shoulders of old masters like Son House, Robert Johnson and Howlin' Wolf. It's anonymous work, too, to play an African-American music that evolved in the Mississippi Delta and then hoboed the Illinois Central north to Chicago, where it got electrified and citified. The blues were the birthright of a tribe of wronged, restless black men. They belonged to a dirt-road world of mule work and shotgun shacks, to sharecroppers who in their bosses' eyes were still just a commodity, the Emancipation Proclamation be damned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHY do white women sing the blues?</p>
        <p>It's grueling work to peer over the broad shoulders of old masters like Son House, Robert Johnson and Howlin' Wolf. It's anonymous work, too, to play an African-American music that evolved in the Mississippi Delta and then hoboed the Illinois Central north to Chicago, where it got electrified and citified. The blues were the birthright of a tribe of wronged, restless black men. They belonged to a dirt-road world of mule work and shotgun shacks, to sharecroppers who in their bosses' eyes were still just a commodity, the Emancipation Proclamation be damned.</p>
        <p>How can a white, middle-class woman in the year 2000 inhabit -- and be inhabited by -- a music forged in that hateful crucible? Yet it happens, enriching the culture.</p>
        <p>Women, for all their apparent gains, still grapple with the prospect of marginal lives, with the commodification of their spirit, their bodies. Isn't Britney Spears just a singing toy marketed by jaded and cynical men? It's one of our culture's deep secrets, but women are still second-class citizens, more readily accepted when heeled to pornographic submission and so often vilified at any hint of ambition. Consider the persistent attacks on Hillary Clinton's image.</p>
        <p>Every move a black man makes in our society is still freighted with levels of meaning. Every move a woman makes carries freight, too. To get along in our white-male-dominated culture (I'll confess: I'm a 42-year-old white man) blacks and women must be subtler, be quick studies -- and that's a blues attitude. Women, too, must know how to work from the fringes, where the blues were born -- born not just on the margins of culture, but on the margins of black culture.</p>
        <p>As the Mississippi bluesman R. L. Burnside said in an interview last year: ''The way people was treated back in those olden days, that's what the blues is all about. Working for the man, you couldn't say nothing, but you could sing about it, you know?''</p>
        <p>There's no shortage of white women searching for Robert Johnson: the singers Angela Strehli and Lou Ann Barton; the boogie piano players Marcia Ball and Deanna Bogart; the singer-guitarists Rory Block, Joanna Connor, Debbie Davies, Sue Foley and Susan Tedeschi; and blowing harp, Annie Raines.</p>
        <p>The question why is uncomfortable because often what the questioner means is: ''What are you doing singing the blues? You're not black.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Block says, ''It's not your skin, it's your soul.''</p>
        <p>Popular music offers hard lessons in exploitation. The music industry has always been racist and sexist, with a history of taking advantage of blacks and women. And the current tone of popular music, oozing over-the-top sex and violence, feels more and more like pro wrestling with a soundtrack.</p>
        <p>So, a white woman singing the blues -- who won't sell her body (or her soul) to MTV -- is a defiant, admirable figure. But the blues have always been opposition music, singing the blues a celebration of outlaw culture. Squeaky-voiced pseudo-vixens with hyperactive breasts need not apply.</p>
        <p>There's no doubt that white women have a right to the blues, but some stumble at the roadblock between the blues and the merely bluesy. (Sorry, but Bonnie Raitt is only bluesy.) It's the difference between the fire and the firefly, between Little Richard and Pat Boone. As the late Muddy Waters once said, ''Ain't too many left that play the real deep blues.''</p>
        <p>Still, there are juke joints of the soul where the would-be blueswoman must work hard and honest to get past the spiritual bouncer. Rory Block, Sue Foley and Susan Tedeschi are three who've done that.</p>
        <p>Ms. Block, born in Princeton, N.J., and raised in New York City, says that as a young woman ''I thought about nothing but blues, dreamed, loved, breathed and ate blues.''</p>
        <p>On her two most recent albums, ''Confessions of a Blues Singer'' and ''Gone Woman Blues,'' Ms. Block covers bluesmen like Robert Johnson, Son House (whom she knew), Charley Patton and Blind Willie McTell. Her playing is perfect, her singing otherworldly as she wrestles with ghosts, shadows and legends. ''I still don't think there is anything as glorious and beautiful as an old blues or country song,'' Ms. Block writes in the liner notes to ''Confessions.''</p>
        <p>Her wrestling with these 78 r.p.m. blues is almost as beautiful.</p>
        <p>As America's rural past vanishes, becomes varnished by theme-park revisionism, the blues face the same questions of authenticity as modern country music. (Most current country singers are just SUV's wearing cowboy hats.) But to play the deep blues, does a player need to be born to fish fries and knife-on-the-frets Saturday nights? Ms. Tedeschi doesn't think so.</p>
        <p>''You can relate the blues to anything that hurts you deeply,'' she said in an interview. ''I don't think you have to go out in the cotton fields anymore.''</p>
        <p>The blues have always reserved the right to change, to meet the player's needs, the culture's. The Texas blues differ from Mississippi's. As do the blues from Chicago, New Orleans, the Piedmont. There are spiritual geographies, too; there's plenty of room for the white woman's blues.</p>
        <p>But if on some gray days those middle-class blues don't feel quite right, there's still new, raw blues by old black men from Mississippi like R. L. Burnside, T-Model Ford and Robert Belfour. These men and their brethren still play true blues so stripped down that you can see the bondo between the notes. When T-Model Ford rasps, ''I've been shot, and I've been cut,'' the hair bristles on the neck of the listener, who doesn't doubt Mr. Ford for a moment.</p>
        <p>Unlike Mr. Ford, too many performers, black and white, male and female, want to slick up the music, to snip the barbwire of the blues.</p>
        <p>For Sue Foley, the blues are very much alive. At 16, she sang Memphis Minnie moaners in Ottawa bars. That was a year after hearing James Cotton blow his harp live. ''I never had experienced something so real and human,'' Ms. Foley said in a recent interview on the ''It's a Girl Thang'' Web site. ''So down to earth, my entire soul was lifted.'' On her latest album, ''Love Comin' Down,'' Ms. Foley's got that blues feeling to complement her strong guitar. No question, she has those old Ottawa Delta blues on this fine, swampy album.</p>
        <p>And Ms. Tedeschi, currently touring with B. B. King and Buddy Guy, devoured her father's Lightnin' Hopkins and Mississippi John Hurt records growing up in Norwell, Mass., and never shook the blues after that.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tedeschi learned a few lessons. The opening of ''Rock Me Right,'' the first song on her 1998 album ''Just Won't Burn,'' is one of the most riveting moments in recent recorded blues. When she howls, ''You say you haven't been rocked in a long, long time,'' it's the vocal equivalent of a hopped-up '64 Chevy Impala peeling out on a dirt road, spitting rocks and gravel.</p>
        <p>Someone paid attention, because she was nominated for a Grammy for best new artist, shocking Ms. Tedeschi, who didn't seem to fit in with the other nominees: Britney Spears, Christine Aguilera, Macy Gray and that legendary bluesman Kid Rock.</p>
        <p>So, why do white women sing the blues?</p>
        <p>''I want to be the female Clarence (Gatemouth) Brown,'' Ms. Foley says, explaining that she wants to be 75, a wicked guitarist ''and ornery as hell.''</p>
        <p>T-Model Ford would understand.</p>
        <p>MUSIC Dana Jennings, a novelist and editor at  The New York Times, writes frequently about popular music.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dana Jennings, a novelist and editor at
&lt;br&gt;The New York Times, writes frequently about popular music.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
