<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haitians Cry 'Assassin' Outside Queens Home</title>
    <meta content="13PROT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Haiti</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Laurelton (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Immigration and Naturalization Service</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waldman, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Constant, Emmanuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Florestal, Pierre</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DD133FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haitians Cry 'Assassin' Outside Queens Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY WALDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waldman, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>About 30 people gather at Laurelton, Queens, home of Emmanuel Constant, former paramilitary leader from Haiti, to protest Constant's presence in US; several women shout 'Assassin' and 'Murderer'; coalition of Haitian and human rights groups has tried to persuade US government to extradite Constant to Haiti for trial; outrage at his presence in heavily Caribbean neighborhood prompted Immigation and Naturalization Service to detain him for a year; he was abruptly released in 1996, raising suspicions that Constant, who has said he was paid informer for Central Intelligence Agencvy, struck deal with US government: his freedom for his silence; Pierre Florestal, host of radio show on Radio Soleil d'Haiti, says Constant's life of relative impunity symobilizes way US has too often treated Haiti and its people; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>High-pitched wails and angry shouts pierced the damp quiet of a Queens neighborhood yesterday morning as about 30 people gathered at the home of a former paramilitary leader from Haiti to protest his presence in the United States.</p>
        <p>Outside the white stucco house in the Laurelton neighborhood where the former leader, Emmanuel Constant, has lived on and off since 1994, several women shouted ''Assassin'' and ''Murderer.'' They shook and gyrated and bent to the ground,  watched by police officers in a van and on the sidewalk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>High-pitched wails and angry shouts pierced the damp quiet of a Queens neighborhood yesterday morning as about 30 people gathered at the home of a former paramilitary leader from Haiti to protest his presence in the United States.</p>
        <p>Outside the white stucco house in the Laurelton neighborhood where the former leader, Emmanuel Constant, has lived on and off since 1994, several women shouted ''Assassin'' and ''Murderer.'' They shook and gyrated and bent to the ground,  watched by police officers in a van and on the sidewalk.</p>
        <p>''Toto is a criminal,'' the women shouted, using the name by which Mr. Constant, the former leader of the right-wing Front for the Advancement and Progress of Haiti, is commonly known.</p>
        <p>''Must go,'' the crowd responded.</p>
        <p>''We want him to give up,'' said Mimose Lambert, one of the women leading the chanting. Mr. Constant's  group has been accused of killing and torturing thousands of supporters of Jean-Bertrand Aristide in the early 1990's.</p>
        <p>A coalition of Haitian and human rights groups has tried to persuade the United States government to extradite Mr. Constant to Haiti for trial. And this is not the first such protest demanding his arrest.</p>
        <p>Outrage at his presence in a heavily Caribbean neighborhood prompted the Immigration and Naturalization Service to detain him for a year. He was abruptly released in 1996, raising suspicions that Mr. Constant, who has said he was a paid informer for the Central Intelligence Agency, struck a deal with the United States government: his freedom for his silence.</p>
        <p>Pierre Florestal, 64, the host of a radio show on Radio Soleil d'Haiti, said Mr. Constant's life of relative impunity symbolized the way the United States had too often treated Haiti and its people. Without accountability for those who tortured, maimed, terrorized and then fled to exile, Mr. Florestal said, the victims could not heal.</p>
        <p>Later, about 20 protesters walked to Rigaud Realty on Linden Boulevard, where Mr. Constant works as a real estate broker. They carried posters of Mr. Constant in a suit and tie flashing the victory sign, and they were trailed by six cars, including one with a poster showing a body by a pool of water and a message that the dead person was a victim of Mr. Constant's group.</p>
        <p>''Shame, shame, shame on you, Rigaud,'' the protesters shouted outside the real estate office. The owner, Patrick Rigaud, was inside but would not comment. A worker said Mr. Constant had not been there in three or four weeks.</p>
        <p>At one point, the protesters said, a man threatened that he would ''be back to take care of'' them because they supported Mr. Aristide, the priest and former Haitian president who was ousted in a coup in 1991.</p>
        <p>The protesters' sentiments appeared to have broad currency. One Haitian man, a limousine driver who gave his name as Daniel, stood across the street from the protest, describing it over a cell phone to a friend. ''I describe Toto as an animal, not a man,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Nor is Mr. Constant the only Haitian with ties to the country's repressive past believed to be living in Queens. At one point during the protest, outside Mr. Constant's home, members of the crowd spotted a man they said had been a senator in Haiti.</p>
        <p>''Criminal,'' they yelled. ''Criminal.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
