<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clocks and Carousels, Paintings, Too</title>
    <meta content="13CENT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222095"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Lester</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEED91F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clocks and Carousels, Paintings, Too</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS and LESTER BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Lester; Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes central Connecticut attractions, including myriad museums; list of lodgings and eateries; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR many nutmeggers, Bristol, New Britain and other center-of-the-state towns are terra incognita. ''You're going where?'' a friend responded when we said that we were planning a two-day outing to explore the sights there. ''You'll be back by dark,'' his wife predicted.</p>
        <p>Certainly the attractions of central Connecticut are underpublicized, yet it is home to one significant treasure house of art and three unusual museums, a homey minor league baseball park, a first-rate amusement park and towns with their fair share of history and architectural diversity. In short, there are things of interest for visitors of various ages if you have the time and curiosity to meander and explore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR many nutmeggers, Bristol, New Britain and other center-of-the-state towns are terra incognita. ''You're going where?'' a friend responded when we said that we were planning a two-day outing to explore the sights there. ''You'll be back by dark,'' his wife predicted.</p>
        <p>Certainly the attractions of central Connecticut are underpublicized, yet it is home to one significant treasure house of art and three unusual museums, a homey minor league baseball park, a first-rate amusement park and towns with their fair share of history and architectural diversity. In short, there are things of interest for visitors of various ages if you have the time and curiosity to meander and explore.</p>
        <p>With two friends we headed out one mid-week morning on the Merritt/Wilbur Cross Parkway, then via Exit 61 to Route 10, and arrived in Cheshire in time for lunch. We were attracted to the restaurant Brix by the words ''Mediterranean cuisine'' and were pleased with our goat cheese-red pepper salad, Caesar salad and spinach-ricotta pizza as well as a fresh blueberry-raspberry tart.</p>
        <p>Our plan for a hike along Cheshire's restored part of the Farmington Canal in Lock 12 Park Trail was derailed by a sudden summer storm, but a few miles farther, in Southington, we had a rain's-eye view of the graceful First Congregational Church (circa 1830), with its stately spire. Our main afternoon goal was a few miles farther in New Britain, so this meant skipping the Barnes Museum, an 1836 house with its original furnishings, in Southington. Next time.</p>
        <p>This wasn't our first visit to the New Britain Museum of American Art, but this time there was a special attraction. The show ''Connecticut Impressionists,'' which runs until Aug. 27, includes paintings by Childe Hassam, Maurice Prendergast, William Chadwick, Willard Metcalf and more than 40 other artists of the late-19th and early-20th-century school of art.</p>
        <p>The museum's own collection of 4,500 works ranges from early naive paintings of 1740 to the Hudson River school of Frederick Church and Thomas Cole, the Impressionists, the Ash Can school, up to Abstract Expressionism and Pop art.</p>
        <p>A pride of the collection is ''The Arts of Life in America,'' Thomas Hart Benton's vibrantly colored images of the 1920's on the walls of one small room. These epic murals, created for the old Whitney Museum in New York, were sold when the Whitney moved uptown.</p>
        <p>The museum is in a residential neighborhood, next to 90-acre Walnut Hill Park, which was designed by Frederick Law Olmsted. After a brief spin through the park, with its Art Deco bandshell, we headed west to Bristol and our bed-and-breakfast inn, Chimney Crest Manor. What we found was a magnificent house, in the English country house hotel style.</p>
        <p>The name Chimney Crest Manor doesn't do justice to the huge Tudor style, multichimneyed brick mansion. There are 32 rooms in the house, with just five guest rooms (two are suites). Cynthia Cimadamore, the owner with her husband, upgraded us, since only one suite was occupied. We got an enormous two-room suite with fireplace, window seat and welcome amenities: a fruit bowl and bottled water.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Cimadamore provided us with two restaurant recommendations, a detailed map of town and precise written instructions to both. Later, after a much too large dinner at the tavern-like Cottage restaurant, we returned to the manor's comfortable double living room (with a fireplace at each end), where a decanter of sherry awaits guests.  The next morning, fortified by a hearty breakfast, we decided to explore Federal Hill, where the manor is situated and where Bristol's elite settled when the town was the nation's clockmaking center. It boasts a collection of outstanding Georgian, Colonial, Italianate, Greek Revival and Victorian houses, mostly concentrated in five or six blocks.</p>
        <p>Some of the streets seem almost vertical, so steep they make walking difficult. A leisurely drive-by is more practical, beginning at the Federal Hill Green where the handsomely steepled Greek Revival First Congregational Church can be seen. The fun of such browsing is choosing one's own favorite houses. We found especially exuberant Castle Largo (230 Center Street), a miniature brick castle in Second Empire and Gothic Revival style, and the A. L.Sessions house (25 Bellevue Avenue), known as the Wedding Cake, built in opulent Georgian Revival style of red sandstone, brick and shingles.</p>
        <p>A friend who grew up in Bristol urged us to visit Lake Compounce Amusement Park, which calls itself New England's Family Theme Park. Its wooden roller coaster dates from 1927 and its 1911 carousel is an Edwardian-style jewel. Expecting to see a faded old park with peeling paint and rickety rides, we were delighted by the new and renovated structures freshly painted in gumdrop colors, the scenic lake and beach with paddle boats. A trolley, a miniature train that circles the lake, and many food pavilions add to the panorama. The Victorian-style, green-trimmed white-frame pavilion has been spruced up. In its Starlight Ballroom in the 1930's and 1940's jitterbugs danced to the music of Tommy Dorsey and Glenn Miller (among many big bands) and swooned to the songs of Frank Sinatra. In 1997, we learned, the Kennywood Entertainment Company of West Mifflin, Pa., took over and completely renovated the park. New features included a water park (Splash Harbor), children's bumper cars and a 70-foot paddlewheeler (Mark Twain). Boulder Dash, the newest thrill ride, is nearly a mile long and built into a forested hillside.</p>
        <p>Compounce seems very accessible and reasonable, compared to many big name theme parks ($6.95 general admission, with free rides on the trolley, train and lake boat, $23.95 for all the rides all day long, $16.95 for anyone under 52 inches tall for all rides all day). Furthermore, lines to all the rides seemed very short.</p>
        <p>A park spokesman, Richard Bisi, said that a recent accident with a 5-year-old boy in the water park area has prompted the park ''to close the water slide until an aquatic safety expert can evaluate and issue a report.''</p>
        <p>It was mid-morning on a weekday when we meandered through the park, and there were already scattered groups of families and teen-agers. We could hear the squeals of roller coaster riders as Skycoaster came barreling along at 65 miles an hour. We wanted to try the Ghost Hunt, an interactive spooky ride in the dark, but it was lunchtime and we had a full day ahead.</p>
        <p>After a quick salad and pasta lunch at Confetti, a simple restaurant in nearby Plainville with a Mediterranean theme and modest prices, we were off to the American Clock and Watch Museum, in the 1801 frame Miles Lewis House at the bottom of Federal Hill. It was easy to spot by the huge freestanding clock on the corner. Inside, the museum was daunting, with more than 1,700 clocks and 1,600 watches on display, many in working order. In fact, dozens of the clocks strike on the hour, making the whole museum reverberate.</p>
        <p>Until 1800, we learned, most clocks in America were imported. It was Eli Terry who revolutionized the craft by developing interchangeable parts. A major new exhibition is entitled ''Connecticut Clockmaking and the Industrial Revolution.'' It features a simulated clockmaker's shop of 1800, where you push a button and hear Terry's account of his life as an apprentice. A 20-minute video relates the history of Bristol clock making. At one time there were 100 clockmakers in Bristol. One of them, Chauncey Jerome, by 1850 was turning out a phenomenal 280,000 clocks a year. With that kind of production, no wonder Bristol had become the largest clockmaking town in the world by mid-century.</p>
        <p>We stopped next at the New England Carousel Museum. Stepping inside was like walking into a time-frozen menagerie, with scores of antique and new, brightly painted and gilded carousel animals of all sorts, but especially horses. Our guide showed us how the sides of the carved animals that onlookers saw were much more elaborate than the sides that faced the center pole. ''Expert carvers did the outsides, the apprentices did the other sides,'' our guide said. We learned that Marcus Charles Illions was the ''kingpin of carvers'' of carousel beasts, that real horsehair was used in the tails and manes, nails were not supposed to be used in the wooden horses, and most carousel makers were out of business by the 1930's.</p>
        <p>But to pose as a carousel expert, you can talk about jumpers (horses carved as if all four hoofs are off the ground), prancers (with only the front hoofs in the air) and standers (with at least three hoofs on the ground).</p>
        <p>Now it was time to head toward home. The Lock Museum of America in Terryville, just six miles west of Bristol, sounded intriguingly offbeat. The town, named after Eli Terry's son, began by producing locks for trunks and cabinets in 1833 and eventually turned out 100 million locks of all kinds. Lock making was at one time Connecticut's major industry and the museum displays locks, keys, locksmith tools, instruments and hardware. But the museum, along with 11-acre Tomasso Nature Park in Plainville, with its trails, knolls and wetland observation areas, will have to wait for our next trip.</p>
        <p>And next time, we vowed, we'll time our visit to the New Britain Rock Cats schedule so we can take in a game at one of our favorite, old-fashioned ballparks.</p>
        <p>A Jaunt Around the State's Center</p>
        <p>Among places to stay in central Connecticut:</p>
        <p>CHIMNEY CREST MANOR, five rooms; doubles $95, suites $165, plus tax, includes full breakfast. 5 Founders Drive, Bristol; 860-582-4219.</p>
        <p>CAPTAIN JOSIAH COWLES PLACE, two rooms; doubles $75 plus tax, includes full breakfast. 184 Marion Avenue, Southington; 860-276-0227.</p>
        <p>RADISSON INN-BRISTOL, 120 rooms; doubles $109, plus tax. 42 Century Drive, Bristol; 800-333-3333 or 860-589-7766.</p>
        <p>RAMADA INN, 105 rooms; doubles $89.95, plus tax. 400 New Britain Avenue (Route 372), Plainville; 860-747-6876 or 800-446-4656.</p>
        <p>And, among places to eat:</p>
        <p>BRIX, 1721 Highland Avenue (Route 10), Cheshire; 203-250-0120. Mediterranean food in pleasant surroundings.</p>
        <p>CONFETTI, 393 Farmington Avenue (Route 10), Plainville; 860-793-8809. Mediterranean food; cheerful open-air terrace.</p>
        <p>FATHERLAND, 450 South Main Street, New Britain; 860-224-3345. Hearty Polish food in simple storefront setting.</p>
        <p>NARDI'S OLD MILL, 493 South End Road, Plantsville (Southington); 860-620-0300. Italian fare in converted barn.</p>
        <p>PAGLIACCI'S, 333 East Street, Plainville; 860-747-0331. Italian fare.  P.B. and L.B.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
