<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="13INDE$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Selleck, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Running Mates (TV Program)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E1DA1E3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anita Gates</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>If Real Conventions Lack</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A VIRTUAL unknown compared with ''Rebecca,'' MY COUSIN RACHEL (1952) isn't even on video. This elegant Daphne du Maurier costume drama is heavy on atmosphere, with a melodramatic score and romantically bleak black-and-white Cornwall scenery. But it was and is most notable for the performance of a 26-year-old British actor making his American film debut. Richard Burton won a best newcomer Golden Globe Award and an Oscar nomination for his role as a rich young man whose cousin (the man who reared him) dies mysteriously during an extended stay in Italy. Olivia de Havilland is convincingly charming and evil, alternately, as the cousin's new bridge and now widow, whom Burton's character suspects of having killed him. But then, oops, he falls in love with her. Henry Koster directed - Saturday at 9 p.m. on Channel 13.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A VIRTUAL unknown compared with ''Rebecca,'' MY COUSIN RACHEL (1952) isn't even on video. This elegant Daphne du Maurier costume drama is heavy on atmosphere, with a melodramatic score and romantically bleak black-and-white Cornwall scenery. But it was and is most notable for the performance of a 26-year-old British actor making his American film debut. Richard Burton won a best newcomer Golden Globe Award and an Oscar nomination for his role as a rich young man whose cousin (the man who reared him) dies mysteriously during an extended stay in Italy. Olivia de Havilland is convincingly charming and evil, alternately, as the cousin's new bridge and now widow, whom Burton's character suspects of having killed him. But then, oops, he falls in love with her. Henry Koster directed - Saturday at 9 p.m. on Channel 13.</p>
        <p>There is no greater argument for film simplicity than OUR TOWN (1940), based on Thornton Wilder's Pulitzer Prize-winning play. Directed by Sam Wood, it has the production values of an early ''Playhouse 90,'' but maybe that's the cinematic equivalent of the play's bare stage. The film, which begins exactly a century ago in the imaginary Grover's Corners, N.H., is about George and Emily, next-door neighbors who grow up to fall in love, and the everyday drama that makes human life both painful and too wonderful to let go. The young lovers are played by Martha Scott, who created the role in the original Broadway production, and an improbably young (22) William Holden. Try to ignore the ridiculous happy ending the filmmakers have tacked on. In the play, as everyone who was awake during freshman English knows, Emily dies in childbirth. That's the whole point - Thursday at 8 p.m. on Channel 55.</p>
        <p>Bud and Deanie, the high school sweethearts of Elia Kazan's SPLENDOR IN THE GRASS (1961), lived (fictionally) only 20 years or so after George and Emily, but their problems had a different kind of intensity. Warren Beatty and Natalie Wood make the agonies of young love and frustrated desire palpable and heartbreaking. William Inge's screen-play may be sentimental, but it's powerful too and it spoke for a generation of adolescents whose repressed parents didn't understand them - Tuesday at 9:15 p.m. and Tuesday/Early Wednesday at 4:15 a.m. on AMC.</p>
        <p>Klaus Kinski makes one scary-looking Count Dracula in Werner Herog's NOSFERATU THE VAMPIRE (1979), which is like no other vampiremovie you've seen (with the possible exception of F.W. Murnau's 1921 silent film). It's slow, almost ponderous at times, all the better to appreciate its serisouly stylish cinematography. Isabelle Adjani is wonderful as a take-charge Lucy, and she plays her scenes with Kinski like a silent-film heroine, all eyes and mannequin poses. Bruno Ganz is excellent as her husband, who bring sthe Transylvanian terror into his village, where the townspeople attribute all the sudden deaths to plague - Wednesday at 11:15 a.m. and 6 p.m. and Thursday at 9:15 a.m. on IFC.</p>
        <p>What's a pretty young lobbyist to do whent he president of the United States calls to ask her on a date? Assume he's a friend playing a joke, of course, and hang up on him. Bad start. Annette Bening plays the lobbyist who finds love - and career complications - with a widowed chief executive (Michael Douglas) in Rob Reiner's endearing romantic comedy THE AMERICAN PRESIDENT (1995). Ms. Bening has appeal to spare, and Michael J. Fox is a charmer as an aide who tries to keep the president's love life private - Sunday at 5:30 p.m. on TNT.</p>
        <p>- Anita Gates</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
