<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Remains Destination Of Choice For Investors</title>
    <meta content="13VIEW$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic View</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFD8143FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Remains Destination Of Choice For Investors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph Kahn Economic View column credits strong, sustained US economy and currency for American investments remaining the global first choice; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE United States has been living through extraordinary economic times for so long now that fresh milestones sometimes pass with a yawn. With growth rates over 5 percent, subdued inflation, low unemployment, high productivity and strong corporate profits -- all with the expansion already a decade old -- it is hard to surprise people with good news.</p>
        <p>But here is another sweet nugget to chew on: The unusually large gap between the performance of the United States economy of those of its main peers, Europe and Japan, is proving more sustainable than many economists expected. And the strong dollar that helped make it all possible continues to defy gravity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE United States has been living through extraordinary economic times for so long now that fresh milestones sometimes pass with a yawn. With growth rates over 5 percent, subdued inflation, low unemployment, high productivity and strong corporate profits -- all with the expansion already a decade old -- it is hard to surprise people with good news.</p>
        <p>But here is another sweet nugget to chew on: The unusually large gap between the performance of the United States economy of those of its main peers, Europe and Japan, is proving more sustainable than many economists expected. And the strong dollar that helped make it all possible continues to defy gravity.</p>
        <p>Months after the sharp correction in the Nasdaq began last April, the dollar has not only failed to plunge against the yen and the euro as was once widely expected, but it has actually retouched its record highs against the euro and held steady against the yen.</p>
        <p>Indeed, stock market nervousness aside, foreigners have arguably never had as much faith in the future of the American economy as they do today. The dollar's value is determined, in the simplest sense, by the confidence that the world has in the United States. And nothing that is happening here has persuaded foreigners that they would do better to put their money elsewhere.</p>
        <p>The old economic laws suggest that this cannot go on indefinitely. In a sense, the United States has been living on borrowed money, running the largest trade and current account deficits in its history. That makes it more vulnerable to the whims of foreign trading partners. Fortunately, they seem to be as smitten by America's technology revolution as Americans are.</p>
        <p>''They are not flinching,'' said Edward Yardeni, chief economist at Deutsche Bank Securities in New York. ''In terms of the new economy, Europe is still somewhat behind and Japan is seriously behind, and they cannot afford not to be here.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most popular script for a so-called hard landing of the American economy begins with a stock market correction, followed by a plunge in the supercharged dollar, reflecting the world's lowered hopes for growth and profits here.</p>
        <p>If this country's major trading peers -- Europe, Japan, Canada and Mexico -- stopped recycling the dollars they earn by selling goods here into productive investments here, the dollar would quickly lose its strength. That would make imports more expensive, contribute to inflation, cause the Fed to raise interest rates and further undermine the stock market.</p>
        <p>Treasury Secretary Lawrence H. Summers has been sufficiently concerned about such an outcome for the past year that he traveled the globe urging the country's economic peers to prod their economies to grow faster so that the world could ''balance up,'' not ''balance down.'' Europe has been growing only half as fast as the United States, and Japan's economy is flat, worsening the already severe American trade deficit.</p>
        <p>A HARD landing could still happen if the stock market takes another dive. But the 30 percent correction in the Nasdaq was no minor blip, and it only slightly unnerved dollar investors, who have since sent the United States currency higher.</p>
        <p>Exactly why is speculative. But the consensus is that foreign investors view America's technology prowess as far more resilient than a stock market bubble. And they are willing to keep investing in what is essentially a seller's market -- the high dollar making assets here very expensive.</p>
        <p>One way that shows up is through mergers and acquisitions of American companies by foreigners, which have quickened this year from the already extraordinary rate of 1998 and 1999. Through early August, foreign companies had announced 1,202 deals to buy American companies, with the purchases valued at $266 billion. For all of 1999, there were 1,701 deals valued at $305 billion.</p>
        <p>If that enthusiasm continues, it is not inconceivable that the record current account deficit could continue to expand without jeopardizing the dollar and the economy.</p>
        <p>Rudi Dornbusch, an economics professor  at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, says the United States, with its younger population, has long had lower savings rates and higher investment rates than Europe and Japan. That was true even when Japan seemed to be years ahead in manufacturing efficiency. But it is still true today, when both Japan and Europe lag far behind in technological innovation, he said.</p>
        <p>''People who were worried about our deficit were wrong because they underestimated the appeal of our new economy,'' Mr. Dornbusch said. ''It's as though there's both an oil and a gold rush, and it's all happening here.''</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
