<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Up-Island</title>
    <meta content="13DINE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yellowfin (Surf City, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corcoran, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6D61F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Up-Island</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CORCORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corcoran, David</byline>
      <dateline>SURF CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Corcoran reviews Yellowfin restaurant in Surf City, NJ; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS you head north on Long Beach Boulevard, the four- and five-lane 1960's-style drag strip that forms the spine of Long Beach Island, the land suddenly seems to broaden at the end of Surf City.</p>
        <p>This is a pleasing illusion: the island actually narrows at this point. But Surf City marks the end of one Long Beach Island and the beginning of another -- the boundary between what you might call the township of T-ShirtBagelPizzaRealtyIceCream MiniatureGolf and the more relaxed, spread-out, genteel and (why beat around the bush?) moneyed upper island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS you head north on Long Beach Boulevard, the four- and five-lane 1960's-style drag strip that forms the spine of Long Beach Island, the land suddenly seems to broaden at the end of Surf City.</p>
        <p>This is a pleasing illusion: the island actually narrows at this point. But Surf City marks the end of one Long Beach Island and the beginning of another -- the boundary between what you might call the township of T-ShirtBagelPizzaRealtyIceCream MiniatureGolf and the more relaxed, spread-out, genteel and (why beat around the bush?) moneyed upper island.</p>
        <p>In more ways than one, Yellowfin lives right at this cusp. Three years old, it crams 70 seats and a kitchen into a small white box that once held an Italian restaurant. Judging by the throngs who packed it on recent Thursday and Friday evenings, it seems to draw customers from all parts of the island and perhaps even the mainland. But in style and ambition, it is very up-island.</p>
        <p>Greg Mann, the 37-year-old chef and owner, went to restaurant management school but discovered in the course of knocking around from restaurant to restaurant that he really liked to cook. Almost any chef these days will trumpet his reverence for fresh seasonal ingredients, and Mr. Mann is no exception, boasting of his special relationship with the guys who bring in the tuna and swordfish at the docks at Barnegat Light. But unlike many chefs, he is never timid.</p>
        <p>He has a self-taught cook's confidence in his own palate, and his flavors work together and sing out like a brass band. Items like preserved lemons and wasabi and mango are not all that exotic anymore (except, perhaps, on Long Beach Island), but Mr. Mann knows how to use them to liven and deepen his dishes without overpowering them.</p>
        <p>About the decor, well, it doesn't overpower the food either. There are some odd and endearing touches -- lovely hand-painted sconces, mahogany overhangs that suggest Japanese pavilions -- but there's no concealing that this room is a shoebox, with closely packed tables and a high noise level.</p>
        <p>The service is friendly and down-island efficient, with virtually no waiting between courses, though some of the companionable, black-T-shirt-clad young waiters are pretty vague about just what they're serving. Prices are high for a bring-your-own-wine place, averaging $50 for three courses, coffee, tax and tip.</p>
        <p>The meal begins with a basket of thick and superb focaccia, and if you don't pace yourself you may find your appetite flagging after the first course. Every appetizer we tried was almost entree size. Two specials one recent evening made brilliant and generous use of fresh lobster: chunks of tail on a bed of spinach, the lobster's sweetness offset by preserved lemon; and a salad that combined lobster, bacon, mango and tomatoes with a toss of mesclun in a bright lemony vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>Tuna sashimi, its quality living up to Mr. Mann's boasts, was wrapped in a fabulously crunchy crust of black and white sesame seeds, and paired with a roll in which the flavors of seaweed and cilantro and hot pepper ricocheted like drumbeats. Grilled calamari rings came in a copper pan on a bed of frisee, fragrant with basil pesto. Buried under a great mound of tricolor salad dressed with mellow balsamic vinaigrette was a trove of pencil-thin grilled baby asparagus -- and as if that weren't enough, two flutes of herbed goat cheese in fried won ton wrappers. Two appetizers missed the mark: steamed chicken dumplings were stingingly oversalted, and tuna tartare was disagreeably stringy, as if made from scraps left over from the sashimi.</p>
        <p>Still hungry? Almost all the main courses continue in this bountiful vein. Not surprisingly, the tuna that made great sashimi also made a great entree, bolstered by wasabi mashed potatoes and bok choy in miso vinaigrette. Four fresh, perfectly seared scallops the size of golf balls sat atop cooked spinach and beneath a haystack of fried shredded sweet potato, surrounded by peppery beet-chive vinaigrette. Seared red snapper, a special, had a nuttiness that went well with a demi-glace sauce scented by pear and thyme.</p>
        <p>Overcooking, a constant hazard with fish, can strike unexpectedly at Yellowfin. Halibut, thick and mild, proved a terrific match for preserved lemons and garlic-strewn yuca, the potatolike Latin American root vegetable. But the next night it had been cooked a minute too long. And while my grilled salmon was great fun, with its grapefruit-avocado salsa, a fellow diner reported that on an earlier night it had been inedibly dry.</p>
        <p>A few meat dishes are on the menu, perhaps wanderers from Fin, a steakhouse Mr. Mann has opened in Harvey Cedars. Beef tenderloin is enormous and delicious, and so are the garlic mashed potatoes and mesclun salad that accompany it. No one at our table had the courage to try porterhouse steak, at 28 ounces and $42 the sumo wrestler on this heavyweight menu.</p>
        <p>You might not think you could manage dessert at this point, but if you're determined to try, you can do well. A napoleon made with perfect slices of sweet mango, crisp sheets of phyllo and whipped cream couldn't have been better. Nor could a special, plum crisp, in a six-inch cast-iron pan. Three sorbets in a tall blue glass -- cabernet-raspberry, passion fruit and ginger -- were as bracing as a day at the beach.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Mann opened Yellowfin, he thought the May-through-October schedule was the life for him. During the summer he'd knock himself out at the shore; the rest of the year he'd travel and ski. But he couldn't adjust to the winter's slower pace. ''I got bored,'' he admitted.</p>
        <p>So this year he plans to take the show on the road, adding Yellowfin North, in Windham, N.Y. Fortunately, his flavors are the kind that travel anywhere.</p>
        <p>Yellowfin  104 Long Beach Boulevard, Surf City  (609) 494-7001</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Crowded and lively shoebox of a dining room.  SERVICE -- Friendly and efficient.  SMOKING -- None.  WINE LIST -- B.Y.O.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Tuna sashimi, grilled shrimp, tricolor salad, crab cake, lobster salad, grilled calamari; seared tuna, beef tenderloin, scallops, seared red snapper; mango napoleon, plum crisp, sorbets, orange creme brulee.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers: $6 to $14; entrees: $19 to $28 (one special is $42); desserts: $7.  HOURS -- Dinner: 5 to 11 p.m. daily, May through October.  CREDIT CARDS -- Diner's Club, MasterCard, Visa.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- All on one level.  RATINGS -- Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
