<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Karen Mikhael, Lewis Porter</title>
    <meta content="13MIKH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MIKHAEL, KAREN (KAREN PORTER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PORTER, DR. LEWIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6DA173FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Karen Mikhael, Lewis Porter</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Karen Mikhael and Dr. Lewis Porter are to be married today at the bride's home in New Canaan, Conn. Patrick Tiani, a justice of the peace in New Canaan, will officiate.</p>
        <p>The bride is the reading specialist and language arts support teacher at the Osborn Public School in Rye, N.Y. She graduated from SUNY College at Oswego and holds a master's degree in reading instruction from Michigan State University. She is a daughter of the late Dorothy and Gustav Ritter of Ridgewood, Queens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Karen Mikhael and Dr. Lewis Porter are to be married today at the bride's home in New Canaan, Conn. Patrick Tiani, a justice of the peace in New Canaan, will officiate.</p>
        <p>The bride is the reading specialist and language arts support teacher at the Osborn Public School in Rye, N.Y. She graduated from SUNY College at Oswego and holds a master's degree in reading instruction from Michigan State University. She is a daughter of the late Dorothy and Gustav Ritter of Ridgewood, Queens.</p>
        <p>Dr. Porter is a jazz pianist, an author and a professor of music at the Newark campus of Rutgers University. He graduated from the University of Rochester and received a master's degree in counseling from Northeastern University and a Ph.D. in musicology from Brandeis University. He is a son of Carol Lebost of Tamarac, Fla., and the late Arthur Porter, who lived in Greenville, S.C.</p>
        <p>Over the last few years, Dr. Porter and Ms. Mikhael occasionally crossed paths in the hallways of the Osborn Public School, where his two children are students. They always noticed each other, even among the throngs of children, but never spoke.</p>
        <p>''Back in November of last year, Lewis was wearing a wool beret one rainy morning, and I think I started falling in love with him then,'' Ms. Mikhael said. ''He looked so adorable and handsome, and I could tell there was a bit of loneliness about him, just a bit, and it really touched me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Porter actually was a bit lonely: he had been divorced in 1994 and hadn't been in a relationship since. Finally, on March 14th of this year, he found the courage to speak to Ms. Mikhael. ''I was dropping my daughter off, and there was Karen right in the hallway,'' he remembered. ''We only talked for two minutes, but I made sure to find out if she was single during those two minutes. I said, 'Is your husband a teacher, too?' Luckily, she didn't say, 'Oh, you're so obvious.' ''</p>
        <p>In fact, her reply was far different. ''I said, 'Oh, no, I'm divorced twice,' '' she recalled. ''And when I said it, I gently touched his arm and let it linger.''</p>
        <p>As soon as he returned home, he sent her an e-mail message, asking her out for tea, coffee or dinner. She chose dinner. ''We had the first date on a Friday,'' he remembered. ''On Saturday, I called her and we talked for a few minutes and I said, 'I feel like seeing you today.' And she said, 'Come on over.' ''</p>
        <p>After that, they saw each other practically every day and found they had all kinds of similarities, some far-fetched. Both are vegetarians who love Chopin. Both avoid strawberries and alcohol and favor black clothes. And they are definite romantics. They love candlelight and whispering compliments to each other.</p>
        <p>''We have anniversaries all the time,'' Mr. Porter said. ''The 24th is an anniversary because March 24th was our first date; the 11th, because I proposed to her on May 11; the 13th, because we're going to get married on the 13th; and the 14th, because that's when I first sent her an e-mail. We're eventually going to have an anniversary on every day -- were working on that.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
