<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exploring Korean-Japanese Offerings</title>
    <meta content="13CART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="A LA CARTE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gaya (Syosset, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scholem, Richard Jay</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5D91F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="684" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exploring Korean-Japanese Offerings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD JAY SCHOLEM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scholem, Richard Jay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Jay Scholem reviews Gaya, Korean-Japanese restaurant in Syosset, Long Island (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH Korean restaurants are proliferating in Flushing and Manhattan, until a few months ago on Long Island they had been as rare as Elvis sightings in Seoul. The few that tried sputtered and quickly closed. Now there are two on Jericho Turnpike in Syosset and another just opened down the road in Commack.</p>
        <p>Gaya, at 333 Jericho Turnpike (516-682-8282), the newest of the group, is, like the others, Korean with a hyphen -- in this case, Korean-Japanese. The hyphens serve two purposes. They call attention to the important influence Chinese and Japanese cuisine have had on Korean cooking and they hedge the restaurant's bet by offering more familiar fare. Because Korean food isn't a suburban mainstay, Gaya, with its clean, spare, high-ceilinged Asian look, will be a first-time adventure for many, one that might seem exotic and at times even bewildering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH Korean restaurants are proliferating in Flushing and Manhattan, until a few months ago on Long Island they had been as rare as Elvis sightings in Seoul. The few that tried sputtered and quickly closed. Now there are two on Jericho Turnpike in Syosset and another just opened down the road in Commack.</p>
        <p>Gaya, at 333 Jericho Turnpike (516-682-8282), the newest of the group, is, like the others, Korean with a hyphen -- in this case, Korean-Japanese. The hyphens serve two purposes. They call attention to the important influence Chinese and Japanese cuisine have had on Korean cooking and they hedge the restaurant's bet by offering more familiar fare. Because Korean food isn't a suburban mainstay, Gaya, with its clean, spare, high-ceilinged Asian look, will be a first-time adventure for many, one that might seem exotic and at times even bewildering.</p>
        <p>An array of seven to nine appetizers is automatically delivered to diners who order from the Korean menu.  The five flavors pivotal to Korean cooking -- sweet, salty, bitter, hot and sour -- are evident in those initial tidbits: Kimchi, packing a sneaky back-of-the-mouth jolt, soothing marinated cucumbers, slightly salty dried fish, sturdy strips of marinated arrowroot, bland potato salad with apples and carrots, bean sprouts, omelet-like fritters and tangy cooked celery. After we finished them, our obliging waitress asked: ''What did you like? Do you want more?'' A champion gourmand at our table replied, ''Everything,'' and so we had 18 little dishes of appetizers.</p>
        <p>Here are a few observations that might be useful at Gaya:</p>
        <p>*Koreans, who are in the majority among diners here, eat with chopsticks, spoons and their fingers. (Forks are available.)</p>
        <p>*Entree portions are small to medium size and Koreans often order a variety of them.</p>
        <p>*Much of the barbecuing is accomplished on portable grills brought to the table.</p>
        <p>*Although Korean preparations are often spicy, there are an almost equal number of mild dishes here. Even the ones with kick aren't blowtorch hot, and rice, noodles and broth are used to tame the more tempestuous dishes.</p>
        <p>Although the Koreans are fish eaters, meat is most highly prized, especially barbecued and braised beef. There are eight meat selections here, all eaten Chinese soong-style on large sandwich-like lettuce leaves filled with grilled victuals, shredded onions and lettuce, garlic circles and green peppers (give a pass to the strong tasting, off-putting, pulpy soy-based sauce). The marinated, razor-thin corned beef ($15.95), prime rib ($16.95) and short rib ($16.95) chunks were all juicy and tasty, but the chicken nuggets ($15.95) were a tad dry.</p>
        <p>Other recommended non-incendiary choices are pa jun ($11.95), a thin pancake-shaped offering infused with scallions and squid; mon doo gook ($8.95) and duk man doo gook ($8.95), or deep bowls of savory beef broth, thick with won ton-like dumplings, shards of beef, eggs and noodles and in the latter half-dollar size slivers of slightly doughy but welcome rice cakes.</p>
        <p>The only major disappointment sampled at Gaya was chick hwe naeng myun ($11.95), tasteless brown arrowroot starch noodles, hard-boiled eggs, vegetable and mushy skate fish.</p>
        <p>Even timid-tongued souls should probably try at least one knock-your-socks-off hot and spicy concoction.  Our choice was kyook gae jang ($8.95), a spirited, scorching soup, dense with shredded beef and vegetables that will command everyone's attention. If ordered last, it will be followed by Gaya's only dessert, a plate of cool, ripe, refreshing on-the-house watermelon.</p>
        <p>While the Japanese food here is more subdued than the Korean, it is not an afterthought but an equal partner</p>
        <p>To receive anything but the parade of Korean starters, diners must target the Japanese side of the menu for pre-entree nibbles. All four we sampled were top-notch: slightly salty, boiled soybeans called edamane ($3.50) that are ideal for munching with drinks; five lightly peppered, pan-fried rare tuna rounds with ponz sauce ($5.50); eight tasty shrimp shumai ($4.50); and a noteworthy sushi sampler ($6.50) with five rather than the four promised pieces.</p>
        <p>A LA CARTE E-mail: licarte@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: licarte@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
