<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oldies Return to Concert Series</title>
    <meta content="13PLAY$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Playland (Rye, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Montalto, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowe, Claudia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E0DE173FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oldies Return to Concert Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA ROWE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rowe, Claudia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Audiences applaud Playland director Joe Montalto's decision to expand traditional summer 1950's music concerts to include singers and groups from 1980's; photos (M)to</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT Playland in Rye, tradition long dictated summer concerts filled with harmonious greasers and their snappy backup singers, those bands affectionately known as ''oldies.''</p>
        <p>This year, however, the amusement park has cast a much wider net. To get a sense of the bill, think back to early MTV. Think Loverboy, Flock of Seagulls (with those crazy hairstyles) and Survivor -- all of whom are part of the schedule this year -- along with Pat Benatar, that goddess in Spandex with the operatic voice, who will perform on the park's Music Tower stage on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT Playland in Rye, tradition long dictated summer concerts filled with harmonious greasers and their snappy backup singers, those bands affectionately known as ''oldies.''</p>
        <p>This year, however, the amusement park has cast a much wider net. To get a sense of the bill, think back to early MTV. Think Loverboy, Flock of Seagulls (with those crazy hairstyles) and Survivor -- all of whom are part of the schedule this year -- along with Pat Benatar, that goddess in Spandex with the operatic voice, who will perform on the park's Music Tower stage on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''I am so psyched to see Pat Benatar!'' said 40-something Karen Pecora, a secretary at the amusement park. ''I saw her at Giant Stadium like 15 years ago.''</p>
        <p>Joe Montalto, Playland's director, made the decision this spring to move away from the park's longtime 50's shows and include a broader sampling of performers. ''We always had oldies concerts,'' he said. ''But we're trying to appeal to more people this year.''</p>
        <p>Told that some might consider Ms. Benatar and Flock of Seagulls oldies, Mr. Montalto chuckled.</p>
        <p>''I understand that,'' he said. ''But we're trying to come up the chronological ladder a bit. A 15-  or 16-year-old might not be interested in the Flock of Seagulls, but his parents might. So while his parents are enjoying the show, he could be out enjoying the park. That's the thinking. There's a little something for everyone.''</p>
        <p>To make sure, the free concert series also offers a healthy dose of 60's and 70's nostalgia with bands like Felix Cavaliere's Rascals (remember ''Good Lovin' ''?), Toto and Starship (sans Grace Slick, of course).</p>
        <p>''It's kind of cool,'' Mr. Montalto said. ''If you're into music you've got to find somebody in there that you like, somebody who had a record that you enjoyed and might want to come out and see. My wife saw Orleans was playing and went 'Wow!' ''</p>
        <p>Ms. Pecora, who has been going to the Playland concerts for 10 years, said the shows draw all kinds.</p>
        <p>''You've got kids with yellow hair dancing in the aisles, but then my mother loves to come, too. And my girlfriend, who's in her 50's, brings her kids -- teenagers,'' she said. ''This newer 80's stuff I grew up with. I remember that Flock of Seagulls video, and it's not even uncool to listen to it anymore. It's all coming back.''</p>
        <p>The tacit understanding among concertgoers and promoters is that audiences will show up for the memories, not necessarily the vocals. Few expect their musical heros to sound the way they did 20 or 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>''Inevitably, there's some wear and tear,'' Mr. Montalto said.</p>
        <p>But not always. Many of the 1960's greats, like Johnny Maestro and the Brooklyn Bridge (''16 Candles'') sound as good as they ever did, the promoter insisted. ''The guy gets up there on stage, and he still sounds like he's 16! His voice doesn't age.''</p>
        <p>Ronnie Spector opened the concert series on Aug. 3, but ended up belting out ''Be My Baby'' in a rainstorm. Her fans, however, did not move until the last note was sung.</p>
        <p>''She gave a great show,'' Mr. Montalto said. ''She's been here before, and she's a trooper. She's used to playing to a packed house, and by the time her concert ended we were in a monsoon. But she gave a great show anyway. She put everything into it. If you're a Ronnie Spector fan it was a good night, even in the rain.''</p>
        <p>Playland, which is owned and operated by Westchester County, expects audiences of 5,000 to 7,000 for most shows. (Poor Ms. Spector, playing in a downpour, sang for fewer than 1,000.) Last year, Little Anthony and the Imperials drew 7,000 fans, and concert organizers expect Pat Benatar to eclipse that.</p>
        <p>''Flock of Seagulls? We really don't know,'' Mr. Montalto said before their show last Thursday. ''Do they still have the hair? I'm sort of hoping they do.''</p>
        <p>Schedule of remaining concerts:</p>
        <p>Tuesday, Pat Benatar (''Hit Me With Your Best Shot'').</p>
        <p>Thursday, Felix Cavaliere's Rascals (''Good Lovin' '').</p>
        <p>Aug. 24, Voices of Rock (lead singers from Beaver Brown, Loverboy, Orleans, Starship, Survivor and Toto).</p>
        <p>Aug. 31, Johnny Maestro and the Brooklyn Bridge (''16 Candles,'' ''The Worst That Could Happen.'').</p>
        <p>All concerts start at 7:30 p.m. Limited seating. Chairs and blankets permitted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
