<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Live Now: 8-13-00; Dead Air</title>
    <meta content="WLN132409" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Plotz, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D8113CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Live Now: 8-13-00; Dead Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Plotz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Plotz, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Political junkies, chew on this demoralizing fact: Al Gore and George W. Bush have already spent $150 million, and their campaigns get built-in coverage from the networks, yet not only have they failed to produce a spectacle as compelling as the World Wrestling Federation's ''SmackDown!'' they can't even muster the ratings of ''The King of Queens'' reruns.</p>
        <p>The first law in the modern entertainment state is that you have to know how to put on a really big show. We are a nation devoted to extravaganzas. Americans voraciously watch pageants and quiz shows; they fork over fat cash for rock concerts, Tony Robbins seminars and ''Riverdance''; they even tune in dutifully for such admittedly boring events as the Academy Awards. Winning a devoted audience doesn't seem to require any special Hollywood magic either. Every self-respecting pro sport can put on playoffs and a championship that mesmerizes millions of viewers. Even the military was able to stage-manage the Persian Gulf war -- a blowout by the first inning -- so that Americans were enthralled for more than a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Political junkies, chew on this demoralizing fact: Al Gore and George W. Bush have already spent $150 million, and their campaigns get built-in coverage from the networks, yet not only have they failed to produce a spectacle as compelling as the World Wrestling Federation's ''SmackDown!'' they can't even muster the ratings of ''The King of Queens'' reruns.</p>
        <p>The first law in the modern entertainment state is that you have to know how to put on a really big show. We are a nation devoted to extravaganzas. Americans voraciously watch pageants and quiz shows; they fork over fat cash for rock concerts, Tony Robbins seminars and ''Riverdance''; they even tune in dutifully for such admittedly boring events as the Academy Awards. Winning a devoted audience doesn't seem to require any special Hollywood magic either. Every self-respecting pro sport can put on playoffs and a championship that mesmerizes millions of viewers. Even the military was able to stage-manage the Persian Gulf war -- a blowout by the first inning -- so that Americans were enthralled for more than a month.</p>
        <p>But all the ''genius'' political consultants, all the hard and soft money and all the free media still produce a presidential campaign that goes down like cod-liver oil, featuring speeches that no one listens to and photo ops that no one wants to see. A population that won't miss a weekly election on ''Survivor'' can't be bothered to notice the world's most important political contest.</p>
        <p>Several explanations for this dismal failure present themselves. The snobs' conclusion: American voters are stupid. Faced with weighty policy debates, the theory goes, the average stupefied citizen simply crashes. This is nonsense, of course. Anyone who believes the campaign is too smart for voters isn't following it. Gore and Bush spend a lot less time discussing Medicare Part B than they do posing with Latina grandmothers in front of American flags. The campaign isn't too hard. It's too dull.</p>
        <p>Others have argued that the candidates themselves seem too remote, their lives of power and privilege too far removed from the everyday people whose interest they are courting. Which is just as far off base as the snobs' argument. Modern politics is infested with a ridiculous, phony populism. The candidates -- the smartest, savviest pols in the nation -- prove their presidential fitness by wearing jeans, flipping pancakes, reading to schoolkids and generally wallowing in their own mundanity. Gore can't stop being dull. Bush willfully suppresses his charisma in order to seem serious. That kind of aversion to stardom and celebrity isn't just impractical; it's downright un-American.</p>
        <p>A more compelling argument is that the campaign ignores the three fundamental requirements of drama: conflict, uncertainty and a great story. Politicians like to pretend campaigns are mano-a-mano death struggles, but in truth they are eerily devoid of direct conflict. The guiding principle is not clash of the titans, but parallel play. The business of flinging mud and whispering accusations is outsourced to campaign spokespeople and, on occasion, to the candidates' family members. But the candidates themselves don't squabble or wrestle. Bush and Gore won't meet till the debates in October, and even those encounters will be carefully sterilized. This disengagement, say the pundits, gives them ''stature.'' The candidates are staying above the fray -- but as a result, there's no fray and little worth watching.</p>
        <p>It is possible to stage a spectacle without conflict -- see ''Who Wants to Be a Millionaire'' -- but it's hard to reject both conflict and uncertainty. Any first-time producer knows to cut away at the moment of highest tension, to keep the audience on tenterhooks, ready to tune in next week. But the presidential campaigns leave nothing to guessing. Speeches are distributed in advance. Even the vice-presidential nomination, which should be the campaign's grand surprise, leaks out slowly and deliberately, allowing the campaign a no-risk preview of voters' response to any possible choice. Conventions are scripted to the second. Dissenting voices, if not entirely banished, are consigned to low-visibility venues like the South Dakota delegation at a 7 a.m. prayer breakfast. It's not a weeklong celebration of democracy. It's the North Korean Communist Party Congress. Is it any wonder no one wants to watch?</p>
        <p>Without conflict and uncertainty, a shapely narrative becomes crucial. Any tale that you care about arcs from beginning to middle to end. But the campaign doesn't manage to tell any story at all, and that is the fatal blow. This is a story: A young orphan discovers that he has magical powers and sets off to a school for wizards. He learns that the evil wizard who killed his parents is back, looking for a magic stone. Through a series of tests and puzzles, the orphan vanquishes his nemesis and is celebrated as a hero. This is not a story: Al Gore gives a speech in Clayton, Mo., on children's health; Al Gore gives a speech in Niles, Ill., on health care; Al Gore gives a speech in Bridgeville, Pa., on women's health. Wash, rinse, repeat till November.</p>
        <p>Worst of all, there is no solution in sight, for these relentlessly disappointing performances are governed by an iron logic. Now that cable, satellite, VCR's, the Internet have fragmented the American audience into 260 million pieces, national entertainment depends on narrowcasting. But national politics can't. Presidential candidates must appeal to a majority of all voters.</p>
        <p>Insurgents and third-party candidates can afford dramatic, erratic campaigns. They don't mind offending because they know they're going to lose. That's why the 1992 Republican convention, dominated by the culture warrior Pat Buchanan, was by far the most interesting convention in decades. It delighted conservative activists and drew good ratings -- and it was a monumental disaster. Among the major parties, any variation from the script is seen as a risk, in which the danger of alienating any voters outweighs the possible advantage of shaking things up. For now, campaigns remain boring because they have to be.</p>
        <p>The Safety First campaign will win Gore or Bush the election, but at a cost. The nation lives by the agenda of sports and entertainment. A president who can't understand that risks irrelevance. He won't know how to speak to his constituents, and we won't take the trouble to listen. Maybe it's time for another movie star in the White House.</p>
        <p>David Plotz is the Washington editor of Slate.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Plotz is the Washington editor of Slate.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
