<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Comedian, Old Jokes, Loyal Fans</title>
    <meta content="13COZY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic City (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sands Hotel and Casino (Atlantic City, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morley, Cozy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Atlantic City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DB173FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1499" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Comedian, Old Jokes, Loyal Fans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>For comedian, old jokes, loyal fans**Profile of Cozy Morley, 75, comedian and entertainer who has been South Jersey Shore institution since 1949 and still draws older crowd at Copa Room at Sands in Atlantic City, NJ; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S the season for Jersey corn, so Cozy Morley can hardly be blamed for bringing his version to the Sands Casino-Hotel.</p>
        <p>''Chinese man is named Isadore Schwartz,'' says Mr. Morley to those assembled for his Tuesday afternoon show, filling the vast Copa Room at the Sands. ''I ask him how did he get such a name. He says, 'I was on Ellis Island and they ask the man in front of me what his name is. He says, ''Isadore Schwartz.'' Then they ask me my name and I say, ''Sam Ting.'' ' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S the season for Jersey corn, so Cozy Morley can hardly be blamed for bringing his version to the Sands Casino-Hotel.</p>
        <p>''Chinese man is named Isadore Schwartz,'' says Mr. Morley to those assembled for his Tuesday afternoon show, filling the vast Copa Room at the Sands. ''I ask him how did he get such a name. He says, 'I was on Ellis Island and they ask the man in front of me what his name is. He says, ''Isadore Schwartz.'' Then they ask me my name and I say, ''Sam Ting.'' ' ''</p>
        <p>There are a few groans.</p>
        <p>''Sam Ting,'' Mr. Morley says with a wide toothy smile. ''Sam Ting. Get it? Oh, what an audience.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Morley has been telling his Sam Ting joke, and other similarly painful stories, since Sam Ting may have actually come through Ellis Island. And each Tuesday and Wednesday afternoon this summer, he is telling them again and again, filling the Copa Room with his fans.</p>
        <p>''Senior citizens, that's who comes now; some of them come every week to hear the same jokes,'' said Mr. Morley, putting on his tux in his miniscule dressing room backstage at the Sands. Mr. Morley said he didn't need much: a little room for his banjo, clarinet and ocarina, ''and someplace to put in my teeth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Morley has been a South Jersey Shore institution since the old comic Mickey Shaughnessey saw him performing his quasi-musical comic act in Philadelphia in 1949. Mr. Shaughnessey's buddy, Ed Suez, needed a nightly opening act for his North Wildwood club. Mr. Morley, then 23, figured it would be a good summer gig on his way up the entertainment ladder. The gig, with a few twists and turns, has lasted a half-century so far.</p>
        <p>I love Italian food. But the Italians, they're tough. Went to this Italian restaurant and ordered chicken in a basket. Every leg was broken.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morley grew up in the Irish neighborhood around Third and McKean Streets in South Philadelphia, a skinny boy who picked up music by borrowing instruments from the Mummers string bands whose clubhouses were nearby. He learned jokes on the street, and since the streets nearby also had Jewish, Polish, Italian and African-American people living on them, most of the jokes had an ethnic tinge.</p>
        <p>''I suppose none of my jokes are politically correct now, but when I learned them, that was what was politically correct, to make fun of yourself and everyone else. Just to make everyone laugh,'' Mr. Morley said. ''That wasn't the point, isn't now. Somehow it got changed around.''</p>
        <p>He said he was at once both shy and pushy. He wanted to get in bands, but had to put on an aggressive persona to overcome his shyness.</p>
        <p>''Every band I was in, I got on their nerves and they fired me,'' he said. Finally, he decided to go it alone, tell jokes and do silly songs. One South Philadelphia club owner thought he was the younger brother of another entertainer named Cozy Dolan. ''They called me Little Cozy,'' said Mr. Morley, whose given name is Thomas. ''I kept telling them I wasn't a Dolan. But it didn't matter.''</p>
        <p>And for the last 60 years or so, Mr. Morley's crowd has been quite cozy with his act.</p>
        <p>My wife is Polish. But sometimes . . . well. There were these three Polish guys at a bar. They were laughing and drinking away. One guy said, ''Me and my brothers here put together this jigsaw puzzle in three weeks.'' I said, ''So, what s the big deal?'' ''Well,'' the guy said, ''the box said 2 to 4 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Suez finally wanted to sell his North Wildwood club in 1958. He offered it first to Mr. Morley.</p>
        <p>''I told him I only had $10,000,'' Mr. Morley said, ''and he said he would take $5,000 down. And it was mine.''</p>
        <p>The place was named Club Avalon, but even Mr. Morley called it The Toilet. Mr. Suez hadn't put a dime into the place in years and Mr. Morley spent maybe three times that much, nailing in a few loose floorboards and shoring up the plywood tables. Still, fairly big names came to play the Club Avalon and its 1,100 seats during its glory days: Julius La Rosa, Johnny Ray, the Four Lads, Carmel Quinn. No matter who was there, Mr. Morley still did his act, which varied little from night to night.</p>
        <p>''I don't know, but people seemed to like it,'' said Mr. Morley, who never charged more than $2 for a drink at the club. ''They'd come week after week, year after year. Boy, did I love that place.''</p>
        <p>Though he played all over the Philadelphia and South Jersey area in the winter, Mr. Morley couldn't wait to open Club Avalon every Memorial Day. He'd play his banjo, tell old jokes, play his clarinet, tell more old jokes, play a trumpet or trombone and tell even more old jokes.</p>
        <p>But finally, he couldn't tell them any more at the Club Avalon. In 1989, the town condemned it and Mr. Morley was forced to tear it down. He said he fully intended to rebuild it, but he said the town told him he had lost all his grandfather clauses and would only be allowed to have 165 seats in the new club. So he sold the land, no doubt for a huge profit, said friends, who said Mr. Morley is a millionaire many times over from real estate investments in New Jersey, Pennsylvania and Florida. He admits to having homes in Florida and Wildwood, in addition to his primary residence along the Cooper River in Haddon Township in Camden County, where he lives with his wife, Bobbie.</p>
        <p>Yet still, at age 75, he performs as much as he can, even if the performances rarely vary. One casino or another has given him a venue through the 1990's and the Sands has invited him back after his summer run for another week at Christmas.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes I tell the jokes out of order,'' he said. ''But maybe that's a senior moment.''</p>
        <p>I didn't ask to be Irish and white. We just pop out. By the way, I don't buy that Jesus was Jewish. I think he was Irish. Look, he was 33 years old and still living with his mother. He was unmarried. He had 12 drinking buddies. And, look, if he was Jewish, he wouldn't be going to the Last Supper. He'd go to the Early Bird Special.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of every show is his signature paean to the South Jersey Shore, the song, ''On the Way to Cape May.'' It was something the writers Buddy Nugent and Joe Ginhart gave him to sing in 1947.</p>
        <p>The story was that Buddy had seven kids and as they drove to Wildwood, they made up a poem about the towns along the way, Mr. Morley said.</p>
        <p>So he brings out his banjo or plays clarinet with his three-piece orchestra and he and his audiences do a half-dozen choruses of the ditty every show: ''On the way to Cape May, I fell in love with you. On the way to Cape May, you made my dreams come true. I was captured by your smile, as we passed by Sea Isle. My heart was gone, when we reached Avalon, they sing. On the way to Cape May, Stone Harbor skies were blue. We were naming the day, when Wildwood came into view.''</p>
        <p>And now, Mr. Morley said, he is trying to interest Governor Whitman in a song he has written about the state, ''It's New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>''Gee, but it's great to live in a state like New Jersey,'' Mr. Morley sang in a tap-dance beat in the dressing room. ''Salt water taffy and sun. Gee, but it's fun to live in New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>But even if Mrs. Whitman isn't interested, Mr. Morley will go on with what has been good for him.</p>
        <p>''I know it's getting near the end,'' said Mr. Morley, fixing his black tie for perhaps only the 300,000th time in his career. ''But I'll continue on because everyone's been so good to me. I owe them that.''</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
