<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vacation Bible Schools Under Pressure</title>
    <meta content="13BIBL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="RELIGION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6D91F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vacation Bible Schools Under Pressure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on pressure facing vacation bible schools at churches in Westchester County, NY, as parents find they have less time and children are enrolled in sports programs or go to sleep-away camps; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the vacation Bible school run by Faith Lutheran Brethren Church in Briarcliff Manor on Monday morning, Elaine Hansen, a retired music teacher, gathered youngsters around a piano in the sanctuary and belted out a spirited rendition of ''Shine, Jesus, Shine'' with them.</p>
        <p>Relying on retired parishioners, stay-at-home moms and teachers on vacation, church leaders were able to enroll 150 students this year in a traditional, weekday summer Bible school.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the vacation Bible school run by Faith Lutheran Brethren Church in Briarcliff Manor on Monday morning, Elaine Hansen, a retired music teacher, gathered youngsters around a piano in the sanctuary and belted out a spirited rendition of ''Shine, Jesus, Shine'' with them.</p>
        <p>Relying on retired parishioners, stay-at-home moms and teachers on vacation, church leaders were able to enroll 150 students this year in a traditional, weekday summer Bible school.</p>
        <p>But at Mamaroneck United Methodist Church, the Rev. Dr. Linda Lee Stein said her church has given up on the idea of the daytime vacation Bible school and chosen instead to offer ''a newer model'' that meshed with parishioners' current life styles: five weekday nights for children and parents. The change allowed parents like Steve Gill, a banker, to dash home from work, change into jeans, tune up his guitar and lead children and adults in a religious songfest. Ordinarily, Mr. Gill would have turned down requests from his congregation to help out at the annual summer Bible School.</p>
        <p>In Ossining, however, there is no Bible school this summer. Three churches that have pooled resources for the annual event gave up on the idea altogether, instead praying ''that the Lord will supply more volunteers to help out next year,'' said Mirtha Pinto, Sunday school and vacation Bible school coordinator for Calvary Baptist Church. That church, along with two other churches in Ossining, Grace Alliance Church and the First Baptist Church, needed about 25 volunteers but were only able to recruit 10.</p>
        <p>''It's a very sad thing when three churches cannot provide an outreach children's program for the Ossining community for just one week a year,'' read a posting in Faith Lutheran Brethren's newsletter.</p>
        <p>From Westchester to the West Coast, vacation Bible schools have been forced to become increasingly innovative to survive in a world where sports, sleep-away camps and other programs compete for children's time, and many adults are at work during the day, said the Rev. Patrice Rosner, director of ministries in Christian education for the National Council of Churches of Christ in the U.S.A., an ecumenical body representing 35 denominations.</p>
        <p>''Also, most parents need to line up a whole summer's worth of activities for their kids,'' she said. ''Vacation Bible schools, which traditionally operate only in the mornings, are competing with an array of other offerings that go all day and all summer, which is better for working parents.''</p>
        <p>Thus, in White Plains the joint congregations at the Memorial United Methodist Church and the Central Korean United Methodist Church have given up on the idea of a traditional vacation Bible school, deciding instead to have a weekend intergenerational school ''because of the way people's lives function these days,'' said Bonnie Draeger, the unordained minister of education for the two churches.</p>
        <p>In 1994, on the 100th anniversary of vacation Bible school in the United States, the National Council of Churches reported that more than five million children spent a week or two each summer in such schools, with attendance growing steadily. Six years later, the organization had no current figures.</p>
        <p>But as a former editor for a religious publishing house, Ms. Rosner observed that to compete today, many Bible schools were adopting curriculums with ''catchy themes to bring kids into the church and give them a good time.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, at Faith Lutheran Brethren Church in Briarcliff Manor, the theme this year was the Outback Games, and a sign over the entrance to the church read, ''Welcome to Australia!'' In Mamaroneck, this summer's theme was ''Club Can-Do,'' with everyone wearing colorful T-shirts and caps and a large sign in the auditorium hall quoting from Philippians: ''I can do all things through Christ who strengthens me.''</p>
        <p>''We found we were competing with activities like baseball and soccer -- and losing,'' explained Sue Gill, the lay leader of the Mamaroneck United Methodist Church. Or as Dr. Stein said, ''We chose instead to meet people where they are on their journey.''</p>
        <p>While the original Bible schools were designed as evangelism tools, said Ms. Rosner, the focus in 2000 is on providing a moral compass for youth in a large and complicated world.</p>
        <p>The first vacation Bible school was started in Hopedale, Ill., by a Methodist minister's wife who wanted to offer youngsters the chance to sip lemonade and make crafts while sneaking in a little of the Old Testament. The idea caught on and eventually spread around the country. In 1907, a national organization for vacation Bible schools was founded and run mostly by lay people, with the group later being absorbed by the National Council of Churches.</p>
        <p>Vicky Nagel, a stay-at-home mom who is one of the coordinators of Faith Lutheran Brethren's school, summed up the goal of Bible schools today as ''giving kids something in life to hold on to.''</p>
        <p>''Let's face it,'' she said. ''It's a very tough world out there. There's a lot of competition to get ahead and do well, which is good, but also, what about taking time to reach out and help others along the way?''</p>
        <p>In addition to tapping into a group of young mothers like Mrs. Nagel, who are not working and can run the program, the Briarcliff church has recruited several retired women to work in the kitchen. It also has among its teachers this summer visiting members of a team of 15-  to 19-year-olds who are traveling the country as part of the Lutheran Church's outreach program. Like Justin Berkbigle, a 19-year-old college-bound student, some are hoping to enter the ministry.</p>
        <p>Similarly, at the First Baptist Church in Tarrytown, Regina Mignogna, a coordinator for the Bible school there, said a police detective in the narcotics division of the New York City Police Department will be taking a day off from work to teach at this year's Bible school, called Ark Avenue 2000 and based on the theme of Noah's Ark. It will run from Aug. 21 to 25. Another man, a nurse who works the night shift, will teach and tell stories two mornings instead of sleeping. And a retired dentist will donate his time on another day.</p>
        <p>''Like the others, we've gotten creative,'' Ms. Mignogna said. ''We've gotten smarter over the years.'' By scheduling the Bible school near the end of summer, the organizers hope to avoid competition from the many other activities that have already taken place.</p>
        <p>RELIGION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
