<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MetroStars Pull Out Victory to Tighten Grip on Division</title>
    <meta content="13SOCC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metrostars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Revolution</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DC133FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MetroStars Pull Out Victory to Tighten Grip on Division</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>MetroStars defeat New England Revolution, 2-1 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Lothar Matthaus playing in Major League Soccer for the first time in six weeks because of a slipped disk, the MetroStars ended a two-game losing streak with a 2-1 overtime victory over the New England Revolution tonight at soaked Giants Stadium before a crowd announced at 12,688.</p>
        <p>Adolfo Valencia scored both goals for the MetroStars (14-9-2), including the so-called golden goal three minutes into the overtime. Valencia got his winner with a powerful header from 6 yards after a corner kick on the right by Clint Mathis. Mathis, who had a sprained right ankle, was used as a substitute for the first time this season, entering the game in the 55th minute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With Lothar Matthaus playing in Major League Soccer for the first time in six weeks because of a slipped disk, the MetroStars ended a two-game losing streak with a 2-1 overtime victory over the New England Revolution tonight at soaked Giants Stadium before a crowd announced at 12,688.</p>
        <p>Adolfo Valencia scored both goals for the MetroStars (14-9-2), including the so-called golden goal three minutes into the overtime. Valencia got his winner with a powerful header from 6 yards after a corner kick on the right by Clint Mathis. Mathis, who had a sprained right ankle, was used as a substitute for the first time this season, entering the game in the 55th minute.</p>
        <p>''It was important for me to play when I'm really fit; it's nice to see that the team can win with me,'' Matthaus said with a smile. ''Now, I can concentrate on the MetroStars and nothing else.''</p>
        <p>Coach Octavio Zambrano was impressed with the way his MetroStars rallied after falling behind by a goal with three minutes left in regulation.</p>
        <p>''I'm extremely proud of the guys,'' he said. ''They pulled through and they were rewarded at the end.''</p>
        <p>Matthaus started the play that led to Valencia's first goal, which tied the score with two minutes left in regulation and one minute after New England's Wolde Harris had opened the scoring. Matthaus gave the ball to Mathis for the pass to Valencia, who beat Jurgen Sommer with a low shot from close range for his team-leading 12th goal of the season.</p>
        <p>The victory, the MetroStars' third of the season over New England, strengthened their position atop the Eastern Division, where they have an 11-point lead over the second-place Revolution (9-11-6).</p>
        <p>The MetroStars looked headed for defeat when Harris scored for the fifth consecutive game. Taking a pass from Mauricio Wright after a corner kick by John Harkes, Harris beat Mike Ammann from 10 yards. But Matthaus rallied the MetroStars with his pass to Mathis.</p>
        <p>It was another physical battle between the rivals, who committed 92 fouls in two previous games. This time there were 34 fouls and an ejection, the MetroStars' Steve Shak, for his second violent play in the game.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars played without midfielders Tab Ramos and Roy Myers because of a one-game suspension and duty with the Costa Rican national team, respectively. Without them, the MetroStars seemed to bypass the midfield by having Matt haus playing long passes to the forwards from his defensive position.</p>
        <p>With a slick field and the ball skidding, a number of Matthaus's long passes were slightly off target. As a result, there was little coordination around the penalty area, rarely putting any serious pressure on Sommer, the Revolution's goalkeeper.</p>
        <p>The MetroStars' first genuine chance came in the 52nd minute when Alex Comas entered the penalty area with authority on the right and passed to Mark Chung about 4 yards from the goal. The pass was to his right foot, however, and the shot by the left-footed Chung was blocked. He had another good chance in the 78th minute, but Sommer tipped his left-footed shot over the crossbar.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
