<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nothing Funny About Neagle's Start vs. Angels</title>
    <meta content="13YANK$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Anaheim Angels</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0DB133FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nothing Funny About Neagle's Start vs. Angels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>ANAHEIM, Calif., Aug. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anaheim Angels defeat New York Yankees, 9-6; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Denny Neagle seized the microphone on the Yankees' bus the other day and the stage was his alone, to do his Jim Carrey routine, as one teammate called it, generating a variety of faces, voices, jokes, inflections. The core members of the Yankees had never seen anything like it before, and laughter overwhelmed them.</p>
        <p>Nobody played music on the Yankees' flights before David Justice and Glenallen Hill hoisted their sound machines onto the plane. Luis Sojo is back and badgering others good-naturedly. The whole atmosphere around the team has changed -- a good change, some veterans believe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Denny Neagle seized the microphone on the Yankees' bus the other day and the stage was his alone, to do his Jim Carrey routine, as one teammate called it, generating a variety of faces, voices, jokes, inflections. The core members of the Yankees had never seen anything like it before, and laughter overwhelmed them.</p>
        <p>Nobody played music on the Yankees' flights before David Justice and Glenallen Hill hoisted their sound machines onto the plane. Luis Sojo is back and badgering others good-naturedly. The whole atmosphere around the team has changed -- a good change, some veterans believe.</p>
        <p>Neagle was not in a joking mood tonight, however, when his control failed him and he was ripped for six runs in one and two-thirds innings, including a grand slam by Troy Glaus -- the first of two homers by the Anaheim third baseman as the Angels whipped the Yankees, 9-6.</p>
        <p>Hill, Scott Brosius and Jose Canseco hit homers for the Yankees, who have bashed 45 homers in 29 games since the All-Star Game break.</p>
        <p>Neagle has lost three consecutive decisions, after winning his first two starts with the Yankees, and there is a long list of possible reasons. Neagle is in the process of negotiating a long-term deal with the Yankees; if this is distracting him, he would not be first player to be affected in this way. It could be that the American League hitters, informed and educated by their advance scouts, are learning more about Neagle.</p>
        <p>But it is most likely that Neagle is slumping. Like Orlando Hernandez, Neagle relies on his control, and his control was terrible tonight. He got through the first inning without allowing any runs, saved by the exceptional defensive plays of right fielder Paul O'Neill and first baseman Tino Martinez, but Neagle recognized the problems that he was having: he stood next to the pitching coach Billy Connors in the dugout and, talking fast, showed him how his mechanics were off, how his fastball was drifting, how his front shoulder was affecting his control.</p>
        <p>Hill crushed a homer estimated at 430 feet in the top of the second inning for the first run of the game, but that lead was immediately wiped out. Garret Anderson doubled to lead off the Angels' second, Bengie Molina singled, and Neagle walked Adam Kennedy walked on four pitches, loading the bases. Then he walked Benji Gil, Anaheim's No. 9 hitter, to force home a run. The Angels appeared to have a good idea of when Neagle was throwing his changeup and when he was throwing his fastball, and they were taking big, explosive swings.</p>
        <p>Darin Erstad popped up, the first out of the inning. But Glaus reached down for a 78-mile-an-hour changeup and drove it over the center-field wall, a grand slam. Two batters later, Mo Vaughn homered, finishing Neagle for the evening.</p>
        <p>Glaus hit his second homer of the game and 34th of the year in the fourth inning, when the Angels increased their lead to 9-3.</p>
        <p>Don Mattingly toiled in a business-like fashion, a style that was embraced by the former Yankees Manager Buck Showalter and fit the personalities of players like O'Neill, Martinez, Bernie Williams and Joe Girardi. Players who have joined the Yankees in recent years, from Chili Davis to Roger Clemens, have remarked at how serious the team is. Hill shaved his elaborately styled hair within a week of being traded to the Yankees, not wanting to stand out.</p>
        <p>But the newcomers have altered the clubhouse climate, the players say, Neagle and Hill with their humor, Justice with his music; everybody from Canseco to Jose Vizcaino to Luis Polonia is fitting in easily, pitcher David Cone said.</p>
        <p>''Their personalities are a perfect fit,'' Cone said. ''They all want to be here. It's a great change.''</p>
        <p>Said Derek Jeter: ''It's a good atmosphere -- they're all good guys. It's like they've been here for a long time; it's not like they're struggling to fit in.''</p>
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch said last week: ''If someone had been with the team before the All-Star break, then went away for a month and came back, he wouldn't believe how different it is. The difference is just incredible -- absolutely incredible.''</p>
        <p>There is a difference in the team on the field, as well; they have a sturdy four-game lead over the Boston Red Sox in the American League East. But after losing the first two games of the series here, the Yankees are searching for another winning streak.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DWIGHT GOODEN relieved DENNY NEAGLE, pitching four and one-third innings and allowing five hits, two walks and three runs.</p>
        <p>ORLANDO HERNANDEZ met with Yankees Manager JOE TORRE before Saturday night's game, a debriefing about El Duque's poor performance Friday; he gave up seven runs and nine hits in six and one-third innings. Torre seemed relieved by what Hernandez said. ''I'm confident it's just baseball that's on his mind, and the fact that he hasn't done well,'' Torre said, ''and he feels bad about that. It's tough for him to smile because he's not doing his job.'' . . . DAVID JUSTICE was out of the starting lineup for the second consecutive game tonight, to rest; Justice has been nursing a nagging leg injury. He will play Sunday, Torre said.</p>
        <p>The Yankees have had preliminary contract talks with the representatives for JEFF NELSON, their middle reliever who can become a free agent after this year. But with only six weeks left in the regular season, Nelson said, it makes sense to wait and test the open market, rather than negotiate a deal now. ''By no means does this mean I don't want to stay,'' he said. ''But who knows? Maybe if I wait, then the offer the Yankees make will be bigger. I might as well see what's out there.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
