<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q &amp; A</title>
    <meta content="13QNA.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DC103CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1222" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q &amp; A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL FREIREICH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aqaba to Jerusalem</p>
        <p>Q. We will arrive in Aqaba, Jordan, in November and plan to spend a couple of days in Petra and possibly Amman and then go to Jerusalem. What's the best way to arrange for transportation, lodgings and a private guide? -- B. P., Bellport, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A. Tours in Jordan usually include a few additional stops at places of historic significance beyond the ones you mention. The itinerary may vary, but the operators consulted -- Absolute Asia, Isram World of Travel and Petra Moon -- said they could  meet travelers' needs. Here's a glimpse of the standard itinerary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Aqaba to Jerusalem</p>
        <p>Q. We will arrive in Aqaba, Jordan, in November and plan to spend a couple of days in Petra and possibly Amman and then go to Jerusalem. What's the best way to arrange for transportation, lodgings and a private guide? -- B. P., Bellport, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A. Tours in Jordan usually include a few additional stops at places of historic significance beyond the ones you mention. The itinerary may vary, but the operators consulted -- Absolute Asia, Isram World of Travel and Petra Moon -- said they could  meet travelers' needs. Here's a glimpse of the standard itinerary.</p>
        <p>A private car picks you up in Aqaba for a journey of about an hour to Wadi Rum, where you hop aboard a Jeep for a two-hour exploration of the pastel desertscape that was the setting of the exploits of Lawrence of Arabia. You then travel about another hour to Petra, staying the night (and the second night) at the Movenpick Petra.</p>
        <p>On Day 2 a guide takes you from near the Petra Forum Hotel on horseback or foot (a walk of about 10 minutes) to the entrance to the Siq, a winding, mile-long defile. At its end stand the imposing Treasury and other sandstone monuments of Petra, a Nabatean city dating from the fourth century B.C. (One can no longer ride through the Siq itself.)</p>
        <p>The route on the third and fourth days depends on the tour operator. On Day 3, Isram and Petra Moon take you along the King's Highway, making several stops: Kerak, site of a 12th-century Crusader castle; Madaba, where the glorious mosaics include the oldest extant map of the Holy Land, dating to the sixth century and found in the Greek Orthodox Church of St. George; Mount Nebo, from which Moses is believed to have viewed the promised land; and, finally, Amman, at the Grand Hyatt.</p>
        <p>On Day 4, the Isram and Petra Moon tours go to Jerash and Ajloun and then leave you at the King Hussein Bridge, known across the border, in Israel, as the Allenby Bridge. Jerash is a remarkably well-preserved Greek-Roman city with a grand gateway built to honor the Emperor Hadrian's arrival in A.D. 129, as well as temples, baths and colonnaded streets. Ajloun is the site of a Crusader castle.</p>
        <p>The Absolute Asia schedule for Day 3 lists Jerash (but you can also request to see nearby Kerak) and a tour of Amman, where the day's last stop is the Grand Hyatt. On the next day you visit Madaba, Mount Nebo and the Hussein Bridge.</p>
        <p>As for the border formalities: To enter Jordan, you need a visa, which costs $45. You can download an application from www.jordanembassyus .org/visapage.htm. There's a consulate at 866 Second Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017; (212) 832-0119, fax (212) 832-5346. To enter Israel, you need only a United States passport.</p>
        <p>Here are details on the cost of the tours. Transportation, lodgings and admission fees are included (except where noted) and charges are per person, based on double occupancy.</p>
        <p>Absolute Asia, 180 Varick Street, New York, N.Y. 10014; (800) 736-8187 or (212) 627-1950, fax (212) 627-4090. Cost: $780, including the Wadi Rum trip, sightseeing with local guides in Petra and Jerash, a horse ride in Petra and four breakfasts. For a personal guide throughout: $925.</p>
        <p>Isram World of Travel, 630 Third Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10017; (800) 223-7460 or (212) 661-1193, fax (212) 370-1477. Tours can be booked only through a travel agent. Cost: $885, with local guides in Petra and Jerash and nine meals; for two, a private guide throughout is an additional $555. The tour of Petra is half a day; Wadi Rum is an extra $55 a person.</p>
        <p>Petra Moon Tourism Services, Post Office Box 129, Wadi Musa-Petra, Jordan; (962-3) 215-6665, fax (962-3) 215-6666; e-mail address: info@petramoon.com. Cost: $566, with local guides in Petra, Jerash and Ajloun, Wadi Rum excursion, 10 meals and Jordanian exit tax; $726 for a private guide. As for hotels, they are the Movenpick and Grand Hyatt ''or similar.''</p>
        <p>By Canal in France</p>
        <p>Q. We are planning to travel in France from Avignon to Bordeaux by river boat and canal barges on the Canal du Rhone et Sete, the Canal du Midi and the Canal Lateral a la Garonne. What companies or agencies can help us chart our course? -- Leonard W. Frey, Memphis</p>
        <p>A. What makes your proposed trip complicated is that no single company operates passenger boats on all the canals you mention. Covering the 300-mile route, which sets out essentially from the Mediterranean and goes almost as far as the Bay of Biscay, should take about four weeks. One reason for the slow pace is the many locks (about 135, depending on the route).</p>
        <p>The season runs from April through October, and arrangements should be made well in advance.</p>
        <p>Among the companies that can meet your needs are the Barge Lady, a broker for crewed boats, and Le Boat, which charters self-drive and crewed boats. Both point out that four weeks is an unusually long trip;  one to two weeks is more common. But it's your vacation, of course.</p>
        <p>The Barge Lady is at 101 West Grand Avenue, Chicago, Ill. 60610; (800) 880-0071 or (312) 245-0900, fax (312) 245-0952; bargelady.com. ''The boats will be of varying quality, from first class to deluxe,'' according to Ellen Sack, owner of the company. There will be no more than 12 passengers, she said, and the charge includes three meals and sightseeing every day, all wines and open bar.  The cost? ''Very roughly'' $13,000 a person, based on double occupancy, Ms. Sack said.</p>
        <p>The trip, she said, comprises four legs of six nights each: From Avignon to Beziers, from Beziers to Carcassonne, from Carcassonne to Toulouse and from Toulouse to Agen, outside Bordeaux.</p>
        <p>Le Boat is at 45 Whitney Road, Mahwah, N.J. 07430; (800) 992-0291 or (201) 560-1941, fax (201) 560-1945; www.leboat.com. Your trip will require three boats, according to Evelyn B. Gresser, founder of Le Boat. Noting that no self-drive boats are based in Avignon, she suggested starting in St.-Gilles, which is 15 miles south of Beaucaire, and going to Port Cassafieres. That, she said, allows one to visit some of the medieval towns in Provence.</p>
        <p>The second leg is from Port Cassafieres, past Carcassonne, to Castelnaurdry. Changing boats for the third and last time, you travel the 137-mile stretch to Le Mas d'Age nais, 60 miles from Bordeaux. One can travel a bit farther west, but because of strong currents self-drive boats can't get closer to Bordeaux, Ms. Gresser said.</p>
        <p>Cost is dictated by season and boat size. Assuming a four-week trip, the charge for April 15 to May 5 and Sept. 22 to Oct. 5 is $5,256 for a two-passenger boat and $8,136 for a four. From July 8 to Aug. 17, it is $7,056 for a two-passenger boat and $11,160 for a four. The starting date of your trip determines the rate for the entire cruise.</p>
        <p>PAUL FREIREICH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
