<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clintons Promise Not to Step Into Gore's Spotlight</title>
    <meta content="13HILL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FIRST LADY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DD133FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clintons Promise Not to Step Into Gore's Spotlight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Aug. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton says she and Pres Clinton will stay at Democratic National Convention just long enough to proclaim their support for Vice Pres Al Gore, then drop completely from sight, doing nothing that might steal attention from celebration surrounding Gore's presidential nomination, int; Gore's supporters have assailed both Clintons for embarking on vigorous schedule of pre-convention politicking and fund-raising that has distracted from climactic moment in Gore's career; Hillary Clinton discusses tangled ambitions and agendas of Pres Clinton, Gore, and herself; she says Gore faces different kind of opponent from one she faces in her quest for Senate seat from New York; says while Gov George W Bush is running explicitly as Republican, her opponent, Rep Rick Lazio, is seeking to obscure parts of his record to accommodate Democratic electoral terrain in New York; accuses him of deliberate obfuscation of his record and his votes in House; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton said today that she and President Clinton would stay at the Democratic National Convention just long enough to proclaim their support for Vice President Al Gore, and then drop completely from sight, doing nothing, she promised, that might steal attention from the celebration surrounding Mr. Gore's presidential nomination.</p>
        <p>''We're down, we're gone, absolutely,'' the first lady announced in an interview in a suite at the heavily secured Century City hotel where the Clintons are staying this week. ''We're going to be staying out of sight. Really. We want there to be nothing but a focus on the convention back in Los Angeles.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton said today that she and President Clinton would stay at the Democratic National Convention just long enough to proclaim their support for Vice President Al Gore, and then drop completely from sight, doing nothing, she promised, that might steal attention from the celebration surrounding Mr. Gore's presidential nomination.</p>
        <p>''We're down, we're gone, absolutely,'' the first lady announced in an interview in a suite at the heavily secured Century City hotel where the Clintons are staying this week. ''We're going to be staying out of sight. Really. We want there to be nothing but a focus on the convention back in Los Angeles.''</p>
        <p>''We don't want there to be any attention -- anywhere -- except on Joe and Al,'' Mrs. Clinton said, referring to Joseph I. Lieberman, the Connecticut senator Mr. Gore has chosen as his running mate.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who said she was speaking for herself and the president, made her remarks at a time when Mr. Gore's supporters have assailed them both for embarking on a vigorous schedule of pre-convention politicking and fund-raising that has distracted from this climactic moment in Mr. Gore's career.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton grew animated at the mention of the criticism, shaking her head vigorously to dispute the suggestion that the Clintons were overshadowing Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>''There is no more enthusiastic supporter of Al Gore than I am,'' she said. ''I just feel so strongly about his candidacy.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who is running for the United States Senate in New York, demurred when asked to describe how she and her husband intended to spend the rest of the week, though an aide said later that they would be going to a friend's waterside cabin in Lake Placid, N.Y. When asked if Mr. Clinton was aware of what the first couple would do once they finished their prime-time convention speeches on Monday night, Mrs. Clinton laughed, toyed with a glass of water on the round dining room table before her and responded evenly: ''Yes. Absolutely.''</p>
        <p>She discussed the tangled ambitions and agendas of three of the nation's best-known Democrats -- Mr. Clinton Mr. Gore and herself -- in the course of an interview in which she talked at length about her campaign against Representative Rick A. Lazio, and how she hoped the convention in general, and her 10-minute speech on Monday night, would provide a lift both to her campaign and to Mr. Gore's.</p>
        <p>The first lady, gazing across a smoggy expanse of Los Angeles from a window on the 19th floor of the St. Regis Hotel, argued that Mr. Lazio was, largely, a different kind of opponent from the one Mr. Gore faced in Gov. George W. Bush of Texas. Mr. Lazio, she asserted, repeatedly sought to obscure parts of his record to accommodate the Democratic electoral terrain in New York, while Mr. Bush has run more explicitly as a Republican.</p>
        <p>The first lady, with an edge of frustration in her voice, described it as a ''deliberate obfuscation of the record and the votes that were taken and a disclaiming of responsibility that I find troubling.''</p>
        <p>''I don't mind having a debate in a campaign with someone who says, you know, 'I don't think we should permit H.M.O.'s to be sued, and here are my three reasons,' '' Mrs. Clinton said. ''As opposed to someone saying, 'Well, I did support a patients' bill of rights.' ''</p>
        <p>She was referring to Mr. Lazio's support of limited Republican legislation to regulate H.M.O.'s, which Mr. Lazio has cited in response to Mrs. Clinton's criticism.</p>
        <p>''Or you know, 'I really am pro-choice, it's just that I'm on the conservative party line and I've given them a big wink about what I really mean, and I won't commit to defending Roe v. Wade in any Supreme Court nomination process in the Senate,' '' she said, continuing her remarks about Mr. Lazio. '' 'But, gee, take me at my word, because I want to be all things to all people.' ''</p>
        <p>''He's the Republican-conservative candidate,'' she said. ''New York is neither Republican nor conservative when it comes to guns and choice and education and health care and the economy.''</p>
        <p>In New York, Dan McLagan, a spokesman for Mr. Lazio, responded to Mrs. Clinton's remarks by taking note of the amount of time the first lady has devoted on this trip to raising campaign funds for her race. ''It's flattering that the first lady would take time out of her busy soft-money feeding frenzy to attack Congressman Lazio,'' Mr. McLagan said.</p>
        <p>The interview, one of a handful with New York reporters in time for the high-circulation Sunday newspapers, came as Mrs. Clinton continued to, in effect, use California as a base for her New York campaign in the midst of the convention festivities. A fund-raiser tonight in Malibu could raise anywhere from $1 million to $4 million for her.</p>
        <p>That fund-raiser was one of the events that drew some expressions of concern from Mr. Gore's supporters. Mrs. Clinton, though, asserted that she had taken pains to avoid any conflicts with Mr. Gore's campaign during their visits here.</p>
        <p>''Everything we're doing has been coordinated with the vice president and Tipper and top levels of our staff,'' she said, referring to the vice president's wife, Tipper. Mrs. Clinton emphasized her point by gesturing with a hand loaded down with a charm bracelet. Asked if that meant that she would allow Mr. Gore's advisers to review her speech before she delivered it on Monday, Mrs. Clinton grinned and responded: ''Of course I would. I haven't written it yet. I worked on it this morning. But you know -- if they want to see it, I'd be more than happy to show it to them. It's only 10 minutes long.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, she asserted there was no need for explicit coordination on what she should say. ''We know each other so well,'' Mrs. Clinton said, leaning back in a room that was empty except for a floral arrangement and trays of cookies and soft drinks. (She and the president were staying on another floor).</p>
        <p>''They don't need to give me talking points,'' she continued. ''We know what our talking points are for this administration.''</p>
        <p>As to her own campaign in New York, Mrs. Clinton said that Mr. Lazio was going to great lengths to camouflage his record, and pointed to his decision to spend a minimal amount of time at the Republican convention. ''I think that's why he didn't want to spend a lot of time in Philadelphia,'' she said, referring to the Republican convention two weeks ago. ''I think he's hoping that New Yorkers will somehow not know where he stands and what he has voted for in the past. I think now that the campaign is into the final stretch, that's going to be hard to avoid.''</p>
        <p>The first lady said she believed she was now entering a new phase of the race and expressed confidence that a contest that has seemed frozen -- with poll after poll showing her tied with Mr. Lazio despite her repeated attacks on his record -- would begin to move once the conventions were over and people considered the choice before them.</p>
        <p>''It's a question of time,'' she said. ''It's a question of issues. And people understanding what's really at stake in the election, and what the differences between us are.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE FIRST LADY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
