<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 More on Staten Island Are Ill With West Nile Virus; Infected Crow Is Found in Bronx</title>
    <meta content="13NILE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lueck, Thomas J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">West Nile Virus</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D6123FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 More on Staten Island Are Ill With West Nile Virus; Infected Crow Is Found in Bronx</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lueck, Thomas J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City health officials say two more Staten Island residents have been sickened by West Nile virus, bringing number of human cases confirmed this year to three; city officials also say that for first time dead crow infected with virus has been found in the Bronx, in East Tremont section; two pieces of news prompts city to announce another round of extensive pesticide spraying to kill mosquitoes that carry virus; chart on West Nile spraying schedule (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two more Staten Island residents, a 63-year-old woman and a 64-year-old man, have been sickened by the West Nile virus, bringing the number of human cases confirmed this year to three, New York City health officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>City officials also said that for the first time a dead crow infected with the virus had been found in the Bronx, in the East Tremont section. The two pieces of news prompted them to announce another round of extensive pesticide spraying to kill mosquitoes that carry the virus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two more Staten Island residents, a 63-year-old woman and a 64-year-old man, have been sickened by the West Nile virus, bringing the number of human cases confirmed this year to three, New York City health officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>City officials also said that for the first time a dead crow infected with the virus had been found in the Bronx, in the East Tremont section. The two pieces of news prompted them to announce another round of extensive pesticide spraying to kill mosquitoes that carry the virus.</p>
        <p>As with the first confirmed case in a human, in which a 78-year-old Staten Island man became ill in late July,  officials said these two people had received hospital treatment and were now recovering at home.</p>
        <p>''They appear to have a full recovery ahead of them,'' said Dr. Neal L. Cohen, the city health commissioner, who joined Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani at a City Hall press conference.</p>
        <p>Last year's outbreak, centered in Queens, killed 7 people and sickened 55 others. Hundreds more tested positive for infection but had no symptoms. The elderly, those with weakened immune systems and very young children are most at risk from infection.</p>
        <p>This year, the outbreak has been centered in Staten Island. ''It is critical that all New Yorkers, particularly the elderly and those who live on Staten Island, take precautions to reduce exposure to mosquitoes,'' Dr. Cohen said.</p>
        <p>But he said the dead bird found in the Bronx provided fresh evidence that mosquitoes carrying the virus  pose a threat across the city.</p>
        <p>Staten Island has already been sprayed twice since the first evidence of the virus was discovered there in early July. Yesterday, Mayor Giuliani said the the entire island would be sprayed by trucks tomorrow night into Tuesday morning and again by air starting Thursday night into Friday morning.</p>
        <p>The mayor also said that a broad swath of the central Bronx, in a two-mile radius around where the dead crow was found, would be sprayed by trucks starting Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>All of the spraying will be conducted between 10 p.m. and 5 a.m. Health officials said the pesticide used would be Anvil, a relatively nontoxic chemical that the city selected to fight the disease this summer.</p>
        <p>The new human cases come amid broadening evidence of disease-bearing mosquitoes in New Jersey and Westchester County. The Star Ledger in Newark reported yesterday that health officials planned to spray the Middlesex County borough of Carteret -- the first widespread  spraying in New Jersey this year -- from 7:30 p.m. to 11 p.m. Monday and again on Thursday, after dead crows bearing the West Nile virus were identified there.</p>
        <p>And officials in Somers, N.Y., told The Associated Press on Friday that  a so-called sentinel chicken -- set out as a precaution to track infected mosquitoes -- had been infected with the virus. But they said the area where the chicken had been placed had been sprayed with pesticide after the infection took place, and no more spraying was planned.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cohen said yesterday that the broadest evidence of the disease had been obtained from mosquito traps.  He said the latest analysis, of samples taken from July 25 to July 28, found 13 cases of infection on Staten Island and one in Central Park. But, he said, the city has no plans to spray a fresh dose over Central Park, since the park was sprayed on Aug. 4.</p>
        <p>Two species of mosquitoes, one that feeds at night and another that feeds in the day, had been found to carry the virus. Dr. Cohen said that the latest analyses had found the virus in a third species that feeds from dusk to dawn.</p>
        <p>Health officials said that the two Staten Island residents who most recently became sick had been infected by mosquitoes before the island was sprayed on Aug. 4. Symptoms of the virus generally do not become apparent until 3 to 15 days after the victim is bitten. Dr. Cohen said that in the three human cases, the virus had caused a type of meningitis, a less life-threatening illness than the encephalitis or inflammation of the brain that killed people last year.</p>
        <p>The victim's names have not been  disclosed. The officials said the 64-year-old woman, who lives in the Great Kills section, became ill on Aug. 4 and was admitted to a hospital on Aug. 6. The 63-year-old man, a resident of the Willowbrook section, became ill on July 31 and was hospitalized on Aug. 5, they said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
