<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Relocation, but the Quality Stands Pat</title>
    <meta content="13DINE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Villa D'este (Floral Park, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1DC1F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Relocation, but the Quality Stands Pat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Villa d'Este restaurant, which has moved to new location in Floral Park, Long Island; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CRIES of ''We've lost our lease'' were heard in Floral Park earlier this year. Villa d'Este, a 31-year-old mainstay, was moving to new digs a few blocks away on Jericho Turnpike.</p>
        <p>Regulars might miss the woody, old-fashioned charm of the original location, but the new spot is quickly winning them over. It's a light, airy, spacious storefront with white tablecloths, fresh flowers, carpeting, white walls, colorful art and huge chandeliers with gaslight-era globes. Large black leather chairs offer exceptional comfort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CRIES of ''We've lost our lease'' were heard in Floral Park earlier this year. Villa d'Este, a 31-year-old mainstay, was moving to new digs a few blocks away on Jericho Turnpike.</p>
        <p>Regulars might miss the woody, old-fashioned charm of the original location, but the new spot is quickly winning them over. It's a light, airy, spacious storefront with white tablecloths, fresh flowers, carpeting, white walls, colorful art and huge chandeliers with gaslight-era globes. Large black leather chairs offer exceptional comfort.</p>
        <p>The entire staff made the trek to the new place in June. That crew includes three chefs who have been at Villa d'Este for 28, 22 and 18 years, respectively. The owners have tried to update the menu by including a selection of prime steaks. We ordered the T-bone and the filet mignon and found them satisfying and cooked precisely to order.</p>
        <p>Still, it was the old favorites that turned our heads. They are dishes that loyal customers insisted be retained: chicken or veal with chestnuts, chicken porcini and scampi Villa. We sampled the last two and found them memory makers worth a special trip. The chicken porcini stars a lightly breaded cutlet of fill-the-plate proportions that is napped with a mushroom-laden brown sauce touched with cream. Every bit of that delicious sauce was mopped up with the restaurant's fine, sturdy rolls. The scampi, really five langostino tails wrapped in prosciutto, were tender, moist and tasty.</p>
        <p>The experienced dining room staff certainly knows the menu and is as warm and embracing as one could hope for. But the runners delivering the dishes have not been told who ordered which, and serving time becomes a ''Who gets the Caesar salad?'' auction.</p>
        <p>The menu states that each meat or fish entree is served with a choice of the vegetable of the day or a mixed salad. Unless diners speak up, waiters automatically bring the vegetable. Opt for the salad. The former is usually a ho-hum assembly of mixed vegetables and potato. The salad is small but appealing, with assorted greens, tomatoes, cucumbers, onions and radishes lightly glossed with a vinaigrette dressing.</p>
        <p>There is also the usual lineup of appetizers, done at Villa d'Este with above-average success.</p>
        <p>There were no disappointments among the starters we tried. The large, impressive seafood salad with tender calamari, firm shrimp, plump mussels, celery and olives was a hit. So, too, were the platter of roasted red peppers generously crowned with anchovies, the clams casino boasting crisp bacon and tender seafood, the classic escargots and the everything-it-should-be Caesar salad. The shrimp cocktail ($10.95) contained only three fellows but these firm giants were winners.</p>
        <p>Any pasta on the menu can be ordered as an appetizer for $6.95. We enjoyed the feathery, homemade gnocchi in a rich Bolognese sauce and the thin, light, spinach-filled cannelloni topped with bechamel sauce, cheese and butter.</p>
        <p>Standouts at entree time include two fish: Dover sole maxim in a delicate wine-lemon-shallot sauce and red snapper Livornese with a tomato sauce bursting with olives, onions and flavor. Four tasty rib lamb chops made a good showing, as did a fall-away-tender, long-simmered osso buco. The latter was actually two veal shanks in a lip-smacking sauce with noteworthy saffron rice.</p>
        <p>There's a trolley of tempting desserts that catches all eyes. The Italian cheesecake, so often a dry disaster, is a moist delight, flecked with lemon zest for added flavor. The airy chocolate mousse cake is a good pick, as are the perfectly cooked poached pear and the moist chocolate cake laced with raspberry jam.</p>
        <p>Villa d'Este  186 Jericho Turnpike, Floral Park  (516) 354-1355.</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Old Italian favorite in bright new quarters.  SERVICE -- Knowledgeable and nice but not seamless.  SOUND LEVEL -- Comfortable.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Shrimp cocktail, seafood salad, escargots, roasted peppers, Caesar salad, mixed salad, gnocchi, cannelloni, osso buco, chicken porcini, T-bone steak, filet mignon, lamb chops, red snapper Livornese, Dover sole, scampi Villa, all desserts.  WINE LIST -- About 30 predictable choices priced from the high teens to around $50 with most marked up approximately 200 percent.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers $5.25 to $10.95; pastas $11.95 to $13.95; entrees $14.95 to $27.95.  CREDIT CARDS -- All of them.  HOURS -- 5 to 10 p.m. Monday through Thursday, till 11 p.m. Friday and Saturday and 2 to 10 p.m. Sunday.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- No steps.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
