<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On to Los Angeles, Still Leaning Left</title>
    <meta content="13NACH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222313"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nachman, Jerry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2D6153FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On to Los Angeles, Still Leaning Left</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jerry Nachman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nachman, Jerry</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jerry Nachman Op-Ed article anticipates media coverage of Democratic national convention, and recalls bygone time when journalists held their own political views close (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>My phone is pulsating like a blender. The calls are from my press buddies. They're all coming, you know, to cover the Democrats. Years ago we'd be talking pegs, angles. Who's gonna defect in some platform fight? What caucus will Reagan try to charm to steal the nomination from Ford? Will Jesse apologize tomorrow night for the Hymietown thing? Dukakis definitely won't pick Bentsen; I got it nailed.</p>
        <p>This week the calls are about whether I can get them into the Playboy Mansion soiree and, hey, you're in TV, what about that Streisand thing? Are you, like, going?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>My phone is pulsating like a blender. The calls are from my press buddies. They're all coming, you know, to cover the Democrats. Years ago we'd be talking pegs, angles. Who's gonna defect in some platform fight? What caucus will Reagan try to charm to steal the nomination from Ford? Will Jesse apologize tomorrow night for the Hymietown thing? Dukakis definitely won't pick Bentsen; I got it nailed.</p>
        <p>This week the calls are about whether I can get them into the Playboy Mansion soiree and, hey, you're in TV, what about that Streisand thing? Are you, like, going?</p>
        <p>I'm relieved. Better they're talking parties than politics. When they talk politics I get irritated. Because most of the media coming to L.A.  should wear delegate badges rather than press passes. What's not new is that most newspeople are Democrats, even liberals. One accepted study reported that 91 percent of journalists polled voted for Bill Clinton in 1992; 43 percent of their fellow Americans did so that year.</p>
        <p>What is new is that newsies no longer try to keep their politics personal. There was a time when journalists held their political cards very close to the vest. But now they share.</p>
        <p>I remember returning to WCBS-TV in New York in the fall of 1994 to run the news department. Election Day arrived, and a Republican was elected governor. The next day the newsroom was in emotional shambles. Remember, most of them are kids. New York governors had been Cuomo or Carey for all the memory they had. Rockefeller was the name of a skating rink.</p>
        <p>The kids were keening. I thought I had walked into some large, collective shiva call. The staff was bereft. Those Republican guys, they explained with bewilderment and fear, had, like, taken over the Senate and the House, too. I think I heard a chorus of ''Kumbaya'' somewhere near the water cooler; I'm all but certain someone shouted ''Oh, the humanity!'' over by the assignment desk.</p>
        <p>The staff shuffled into my office to be consoled. Many of them believed me to be avuncular, another misperception I would have to work on. ''Children,'' I began, ''it is true that a Republican is the governor-elect of New York.'' Someone sniffled. I flipped a box of tissues in his direction. ''But you must remember that so are the governors of Massachusetts and Connecticut and New Jersey and California.'' I pointed out that Republicans had occupied the White House for 28 of the prior 42 years.</p>
        <p>There was a collective gasp: they had no idea aliens had landed in so many places. ''Now you, as journalists, must understand this pattern,'' I continued. ''This is not some putsch launched by skinheads running out of the mountains of Idaho. These are your neighbors and relatives who are voting for Republicans. Talk to them. Learn why. Find out that there may be more than one opinion about stuff like taxes and affirmative action.'' They shuffled out, vowing to soldier on.</p>
        <p>I considered and discarded the idea of sending out for pizza to cheer them up. I ordered some Chinese for myself and I wondered why most journos are liberals. It actually makes no sense because probably three-quarters of the stories we cover could be labeled under an omnibus umbrella: The government doesn't work.</p>
        <p>This all-purpose slug never changes. The reading scores are down in public schools; the West Side Highway still isn't fixed. The state police did do racial profiling -- and lied about it. Nuclear secrets are missing, and Illinois's death row is emptying out because the state screwed up. We traded arms for hostages and illegally gave the money to the contras. The park rangers started a forest fire and then couldn't put it out. Pick a paper, any paper. Watch a newscast, any newscast. Guaranteed: The top stories are some version of ''the government doesn't work.''</p>
        <p>So why would journalists, the same ones who uncover these stories and win all the big awards for doing so, believe that a bigger government, collecting more tax money and accumulating yet more power, would be more effective in educating people, housing them, providing their medical care, than it isn't now?</p>
        <p>I'll have this discussion again with my news friends over the next couple of days. They're all gonna be here. I think I'll hit the town meeting being thrown by The Nation and the barbecue Time is having for its new bureau chief. And maybe I'll mosey over to that ''Jam with Jon Corzine'' party at Luna Park. But I've gotta go to at least one of Arianna Huffington's salons. Wouldn't be right if I didn't.</p>
        <p>Jerry Nachman is executive producer of ''Politically Incorrect with Bill Maher.'' He is a former editor of The New York Post and ran the newsrooms at WCBS-TV and WNBC-TV.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jerry Nachman is executive producer of ''Politically Incorrect with Bill Maher.'' He is a former editor of The New York Post and ran the newsrooms at WCBS-TV and WNBC-TV.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
