<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; From Chile's Army, Little but the Sound of Fury</title>
    <meta content="13KRAU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222325"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pinochet, Augusto (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DE123FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; From Chile's Army, Little but the Sound of Fury</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>SANTIAGO, Chile</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chilean military, which still marches to stern martial music of Prussians who trainedarmed forces in 1885, are losing commanding position in Chilean society; photo; loss is dramatized by downfall of Gen Augusto Pinochet, who has been stripped of senatorial immunity and faces arrest and trial (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CHILEAN soldiers still march to the tune of the stern martial music -- the Badenweiler, Nibelung and Ferbelin -- that the Prussians brought with them in 1885 when Chile invited them to modernize its army. The soldiers' medals, uniforms and goose-stepping also evoke that era, making the force appear profoundly anachronistic, even in a nation as traditionbound as this one.</p>
        <p>But until recently, the misfit was only superficial. Even a decade ago, Chile's armed forces still had a powerful grip on the country, overseeing not only its defense, but also its economic and political affairs. A law unto themselves, they rousted dissidents from their beds and tortured and executed them at will.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CHILEAN soldiers still march to the tune of the stern martial music -- the Badenweiler, Nibelung and Ferbelin -- that the Prussians brought with them in 1885 when Chile invited them to modernize its army. The soldiers' medals, uniforms and goose-stepping also evoke that era, making the force appear profoundly anachronistic, even in a nation as traditionbound as this one.</p>
        <p>But until recently, the misfit was only superficial. Even a decade ago, Chile's armed forces still had a powerful grip on the country, overseeing not only its defense, but also its economic and political affairs. A law unto themselves, they rousted dissidents from their beds and tortured and executed them at will.</p>
        <p>Now, though, they are losing their commanding position in Chilean society. That became strikingly evident last week, as Gen. Augusto Pinochet, their former leader, was stripped of his senatorial immunity by the Supreme Court, clearing the way for his probable arrest and trial. In response, all the top military commanders could do was grumble, publicly and bitterly.</p>
        <p>''The political role of the military is diminishing little by little,'' said Francisco Javier Cuadra, a lawyer who was General Pinochet's chief of staff between 1984 and 1987. ''And as Pinochet leaves the stage, its profile will diminish even further.''</p>
        <p>Two major events created the slope the military is sliding down, which is all the more noteworthy because old authoritarian habits are returning in neighboring Peru and some other South American countries.</p>
        <p>One, of course, was the arrest of General Pinochet in London two years ago on a Spanish warrant charging him with gross violations of human rights, including kidnapping, murder and torture. The arrest  encouraged a rush of attention to human rights abuses in this usually closed society and emboldened prosecuting judges to investigate and charge scores of retired and acting police and military officers. When the prosecutions began, the general was not around to quash them. The military's accustomed impunity began to erode.</p>
        <p>Then the Chilean government, pressing for General Pinochet's return, argued that he should face Chilean rather than Spanish justice as a matter of sovereignty, and the military -- which does not want him to face any trial at all -- went along. Since March, when the general returned to Chile after the British released him on humanitarian grounds, he has been too weak to block the prosecutions of fellow officers.</p>
        <p>The other crucial event was Chile's election of Ricardo Lagos in January as the first Socialist president since 1973, when General Pinochet overthrew Salvador Allende with the help of the Nixon administration. In his first months in power, Mr. Lagos has pushed forward the economic deregulation policies first pioneered by General Pinochet and eliminated capital restrictions loathed by Wall Street.</p>
        <p>With Marxism no longer a problem, the United States, which strongly supported the  Pinochet coup, is now strongly backing civilian rule. Domestic fears of Communism have faded, too, removing the armed forces' chief argument for one of the largest per capita military budgets in Latin America. Chile's business community, while maintaining support for General Pinochet, has drawn back from pushing the military to intervene to protect him, because they know such turbulence would deter international credit, investment and trade as the country emerges from a recession.</p>
        <p>A third factor is simply the passage of time. Commanders have rotated, and the most senior of the Pinochet era have retired. Younger officers remain devoted to General Pinochet, but most focus on relations with the politicians who hold the purse strings for the new frigates, fighter jets and tanks they say they desperately need.</p>
        <p>Likewise, a new generation on the Supreme Court (only three of 20 justices remain from General Pinochet's time) has ruled that cases of missing people can be treated as kidnappings. Until a body is produced, a kidnapping case is considered open. The approach has opened a multitude of cases that had been shut by a 1978 amnesty for political crimes -- including killings -- decreed under General Pinochet.</p>
        <p>That pushed the armed forces to the negotiating table with human rights lawyers and led to top officers' signing a document in June that promised their assistance in finding the bodies of the missing, in exchange for testifying in private and receiving immunity. The agreement was the first time the military acknowledged that members of the security forces had played a role in the wrongful death of anybody and the first time it publicly retreated from old rebuttals that either the disappeared had been killed in civil conflicts or that they were not dead at all, but had merely left the country.</p>
        <p>''It was a great advance,'' said Mario Fernandez Baeza, President Lagos's defense minister. ''Only two years ago, a large sector of the society, including the armed forces in a quiet way, justified those abuses.''</p>
        <p>NOW, with even its border disputes with Peru and Argentina settled over the last three years, the military is trying to learn to live without enemies. That may mean living with new masters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lagos has begun negotiations with conservative lawmakers to change the constitution written during the Pinochet era, which gives the military special powers, including wide-ranging autonomy and representation in the Senate. He has also been forthright about claiming his superiority over the armed forces, on several occasions publicly scolding military chiefs.</p>
        <p>After Gen. Ricardo Izurieta, the army chief, defiantly told reporters he needed no one's permission to visit General Pinochet after last week's ruling, Mr. Lagos observed, sharply: ''The command of our country rests on what I decide.''</p>
        <p>Until recently such a clash would have sent shudders through Chile. But General Izurieta has learned to balance his relations with two civilian presidents and hard-liners within the armed forces unhappy that he has not better defended General Pinochet. After his words of defiance, he immediately reiterated the military's promise to seek the whereabouts of the missing. Mr. Lagos, for his part, said he did not mind that General Izurieta and other commanders made a courtesy visit to their old leader.</p>
        <p>''It's a completely regulated conflict,'' said Mr. Cuadra, the former Pinochet aide. ''It's political theater with both Lagos and Izurieta each playing a role and each knowing the other's lines in the libretto.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
