<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investing; KPMG Consulting Arm Looks Ready to Fly Solo</title>
    <meta content="13KPMG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KPMG Consulting Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Carole</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consultants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E6D6143FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investing; KPMG Consulting Arm Looks Ready to Fly Solo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Carole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles KPMG Consulting Inc; firm specializes in 'e-business services' to list of clients spanning business, government and education (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the busy market for initial public offerings -- especially for volatile Internet-related companies -- analysts tend to be wary, which makes their enthusiasm for a planned $2.83 billion stock sale announced last week by KPMG Consulting Inc. all the more remarkable.</p>
        <p>Through an alliance with Cisco Systems, which invested $1 billion in KPMG Consulting a year ago, the consulting group has specialized in what it calls ''e-business services'' to a client list that includes blue-chip companies, the Pentagon, the State Department and Yale University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the busy market for initial public offerings -- especially for volatile Internet-related companies -- analysts tend to be wary, which makes their enthusiasm for a planned $2.83 billion stock sale announced last week by KPMG Consulting Inc. all the more remarkable.</p>
        <p>Through an alliance with Cisco Systems, which invested $1 billion in KPMG Consulting a year ago, the consulting group has specialized in what it calls ''e-business services'' to a client list that includes blue-chip companies, the Pentagon, the State Department and Yale University.</p>
        <p>''It will be the largest technology services I.P.O. in history,'' said Karl Keirstead, vice president for equity research at Lehman Brothers. ''I think Wall Street will find it quite attractive,'' he added, in comparison with its competition. Two other big information-technology services companies, Electronic Data Services and the Computer Science Corporation, ''have been going through tough transitions,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''I think KPMG will be the first of the Big Five accounting firms'' to sell part of its consulting business to the public, said Moshe Katri, managing director at SG Cowen Securities, who follows the Sapient Corporation, a KPMG competitor. ''We expect the others to follow.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, federal regulators are hammering out tough new limits on accounting firms' ability to perform lucrative consulting work for their audit clients. Last Monday, an arbitrator separated Andersen Consulting from Arthur Andersen, the tax and auditing firm. Earlier this year, Ernst &amp; Young sold its consulting unit to Cap Gemini for roughly $11 billion, and PricewaterhouseCoopers is considering divesting itself of its consulting unit by year-end.</p>
        <p>In January, KPMG L.L.P. incorporated its consulting unit as a separate entity, 80.1 percent owned by KPMG and its partners and 19.9 percent by Cisco. KPMG Consulting announced plans in May for a $1 billion initial public offering, but in an amended prospectus filed last week with the Securities and Exchange Commission, it raised the offering to 324.2 million shares to be priced at $6.75 to $8.75 each. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter is to be the underwriter. After the sale, the public would own 55 percent of the company.</p>
        <p>Within five years, the accounting firm KPMG L.L.P. and its partners are to divest themselves of any common shares in the consulting company, which has applied to trade on Nasdaq under the symbol KCIN.</p>
        <p>Mr. Katri is positive about the new offering. ''In general, spending on information technology services is growing about 14 percent a year,'' he said. ''The biggest attraction of computer services is that investors don't bet on the technology itself, which may not work out. You're betting on consultants that use the best-of-breed technology.''</p>
        <p>KPMG is particularly well positioned, Mr. Keirstead added. ''All the Big Five firms are struggling to transition their business models and employee skill sets to capitalize on the demand for Internet consulting services,'' he said. ''In my view, KPMG has done the best job of making the transition, given that half of its revenues derive from Web consulting projects. That's what Wall Street wants to own today.''</p>
        <p>Andrew T. Burns, senior vice president at PaineWebber in San Francisco, said: ''It's a reasonable valuation. It's a discount to pure Internet professional services companies and a slight premium over the mainstay outsourcing companies like Electronic Data Services.''</p>
        <p>THE stock seems to be priced unusually low, compared with similar, $20-a-share offerings at the beginning of the year, said Gail Bronson, a consultant in Palo Alto, Calif., who also provides market commentary for IPO Monitor, a news and data Web site. ''What does that say,'' she asked, ''about the overall enthusiasm of the investment houses'' to which they made advance presentations?</p>
        <p>Even investors who are bullish on KPMG Consulting long term should steer clear of the initial offering, Ms. Bronson advised. ''No one should buy an I.P.O. in the first day that it trades, or even the first couple of weeks, until you see where the price settles out to,'' she said. ''Invariably, if it's a popular offering,'' she added, ''it will shoot up'' at first.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
