<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giambi Helps A's End Skid</title>
    <meta content="AME13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AMERICAN LEAGUE: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EFDB133FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giambi Helps A's End Skid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oakland Athletics defeat Detroit Tigers, 9-5; roundup of other American League game scores (M)3</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jason Giambi set another milestone yesterday as the host Oakland Athletics ended a six-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Giambi hit his 30th home run and Ben Grieve added a three-run homer, leading the A's over the Detroit Tigers, 9-5.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jason Giambi set another milestone yesterday as the host Oakland Athletics ended a six-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Giambi hit his 30th home run and Ben Grieve added a three-run homer, leading the A's over the Detroit Tigers, 9-5.</p>
        <p>Matt Stairs hit a sacrifice fly in the second and Giambi hit a two-run homer in the third, giving him 101 runs batted in. Giambi joined Jose Canseco (1986-88) as the only Oakland players to drive in 100 runs in three straight years.</p>
        <p>''It sounds like a broken record, but he's having a great year,'' A's Manager Art Howe said. ''He's doing the job day in and day out, and giving us opportunities to win.''</p>
        <p>Giambi also reached 100 R.B.I. quicker than any player in Oakland history, bettering Reggie Jackson's 1973 pace, when he got his 100th R.B.I. on Aug. 18.</p>
        <p>Tim Hudson (13-4) took a one-hit shutout into the seventh, but wound up allowing four runs and five hits in six-plus innings. Hudson is 4-0 against Detroit in four career starts.</p>
        <p>WHITE SOX 5, DEVIL RAYS 4: Carlos Lee homered and drove in the go-ahead run with a 10th-inning sacrifice fly as Chicago beat host Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>Magglio Ordonez, who went 4 for 4 with two R.B.I., opened the 10th with a single off Roberto Hernandez (3-4).</p>
        <p>Ordonez went to second on catcher Mike DiFelice's passed ball, moved to third on a balk and scored on Lee's homer to left field.</p>
        <p>Mark Buehrle (3-1) allowed one hit in one scoreless inning. Keith Foulke got three outs for his 21st save in 25 opportunities.</p>
        <p>The Devil Rays scored once in the eighth to tie it at 4-4. Greg Vaughn drew a two-out walk from Bob Howry, reliever Kelly Wunsch walked Fred McGriff on four pitches and Jose Guillen hit an R.B.I. single that deflected off third baseman Herbert Perry.</p>
        <p>INDIANS 5, MARINERS 4: Bartolo Colon struck out eight in seven innings, allowing just four hits as Cleveland recorded its eighth victory in 10 games.</p>
        <p>With the score at 2-2 in the fifth, Cleveland went ahead when Kenny Lofton doubled to center off host Seattle's John Halama (10-6) and scored on a double error -- first Mike Cameron kicked the ball, then shortstop Alex Rodriguez's relay throw was wild, going past third baseman Carlos Guillen and pitcher John Halama.</p>
        <p>David Segui had a two-run single in the eighth off Brett Tomko, who loaded the bases on walks to Lofton and Omar Vizquel, a sacrifice by Roberto Alomar and an intentional walk to Manny Ramirez.</p>
        <p>Bob Wickman got three outs for his fifth save in six chances, his fifth since Cleveland acquired him from Milwaukee on July 28.</p>
        <p>TWINS 6, BLUE JAYS 3: The rookie Mark Redman pitched six strong innings and Torii Hunter hit a two-run homer for host Minnesota.</p>
        <p>Redman (11-5) allowed one run, six hits, struck out three and walked one for the Twins, who have won six of their last 10.</p>
        <p>The left-hander, who leads A.L. rookies in victories, earned run average (4.43), strikeouts (99) and innings pitched (126), was in trouble just once -- in the second inning -- when Toronto got three of its hits and its only run off Redman.</p>
        <p>LaTroy Hawkins pitched two innings and struck out four of six batters to earn his eighth save in as many chances.</p>
        <p>Hunter, recalled from Class AAA Salt Lake City on July 29 to shore up Minnesota's outfield, hit an 0-2 pitch from Toronto starter Esteban Loaiza (6-9) over the right-field wall in the third with one on to give the Twins a 5-1 lead.</p>
        <p>RANGERS 6, RED SOX 3: Ricky Ledee hit a fourth-inning grand slam to back Rick Helling and host Texas beat the Red Sox, Boston's fifth loss in seven games.</p>
        <p>Ledee homered in the fourth off Tim Wakefield (6-7). It was his second career slam, his 10th homer of the season and his first since Texas acquired him from Cleveland on July 28. Ledee added a sacrifice fly in the eighth for his fifth R.B.I., matching his career high.</p>
        <p>Helling (14-8) allowed one run and four hits in seven innings, struck out five and walked three, improving to 7-1 in his last 10 starts.</p>
        <p>ORIOLES 12, ROYALS 11: Albert Belle hit a two-out, two-run homer to cap a four-run ninth inning, and Baltimore overcame Jermaine Dye's six R.B.I. for host Kansas City.</p>
        <p>Kansas City trailed by 8-3 in the fifth before taking an 11-8 lead in the eighth on a two-run single by Dye off Buddy Groom (5-3) and Mark Quinn's R.B.I. single.</p>
        <p>Delino DeShields hit a two-run single off Jerry Spradlin in the ninth and Belle followed with a homer off Ricky Bottalico (7-4), who blew a save for the seventh time in 20 chances.</p>
        <p>Brian Kohlmeier pitched the ninth for his third save in three chances.</p>
        <p>Dye, who matched his R.B.I. high, was 3 for 5 with a pair of homers, raising his total to a career-high 28, one more than he hit last year.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN LEAGUE: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
