<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Show Time for Al Gore</title>
    <meta content="13SUN1$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222352"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E7DB123FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Show Time for Al Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial previews Al Gore's appearance as Democratic presidential nominee</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In political analysis, the conventional question to ask at this point in the electoral calendar is this: What does a presidential candidate need to get from his party's national convention? Past candidates have used conventions to show they are strong enough, wise enough or steady enough to lead the nation. But it is hard to think of an exact precedent for the problem confronting Al Gore as he prepares to accept the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>He will arrive in Los Angeles on Tuesday as a career politician who clearly outmatches his opponent in governing experience, depth of knowledge and empathy for those Americans most in need of a government that is both competent and caring. Yet the most fundamental task of elective politics -- connecting with people and making them like him -- seems to elude Mr. Gore. Perhaps it can best be summed up by calling it his authenticity problem. Voters understand that Mr. Gore is smart. But they also see his seeming inability to make the theatrical part of politics feel like a genuine civic and patriotic experience. They know he is a good protege, but wonder if he has a controlling inner authority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In political analysis, the conventional question to ask at this point in the electoral calendar is this: What does a presidential candidate need to get from his party's national convention? Past candidates have used conventions to show they are strong enough, wise enough or steady enough to lead the nation. But it is hard to think of an exact precedent for the problem confronting Al Gore as he prepares to accept the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>He will arrive in Los Angeles on Tuesday as a career politician who clearly outmatches his opponent in governing experience, depth of knowledge and empathy for those Americans most in need of a government that is both competent and caring. Yet the most fundamental task of elective politics -- connecting with people and making them like him -- seems to elude Mr. Gore. Perhaps it can best be summed up by calling it his authenticity problem. Voters understand that Mr. Gore is smart. But they also see his seeming inability to make the theatrical part of politics feel like a genuine civic and patriotic experience. They know he is a good protege, but wonder if he has a controlling inner authority.</p>
        <p>These doubts, plus the disciplined if deceptive salesmanship of Gov. George W. Bush, have combined to produce months of erosion for Mr. Gore. He has seen slippage in the polls, in the level of cooperation between his campaign and the White House, and in his confidence on the stump. If he is going to win the office to which he has aspired since boyhood, Albert Arnold Gore Jr. needs to have a very good convention on several fronts.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Problem. In order to create shooting space, a basketball player has to ''get separation'' from the nearest defensive player. Mr. Gore has to achieve a separation from President Clinton's conduct and personal reputation in ways that go beyond simply failing whenever possible to mention his name. Mr. Bush and the Republicans believe that words like ''character,'' ''integrity'' and ''dignity'' are guided missiles that fly straight into the Democratic bunker. Since defending the president against such attacks is politically impossible, Mr. Gore has to create alternative definitions for himself and his party on the issues of presidential decorum and clean campaign money.</p>
        <p>He signaled his desire to do so by putting Senator Joseph Lieberman on the ticket, but having a devout running mate is not enough. The real trick will be using Mr. Lieberman to promote policies that are distinctively superior to Mr. Bush's in the areas of campaign finance and opposition to special interests. Mr. Gore promised last spring to make campaign finance reform his No. 1 domestic priority. Senator Lieberman, having a cleaner history, can elevate that promise into a major attack weapon against a Republican ticket that is expected to raise more than $200 million in soft money from corporations and wealthy individuals. Proper use of this issue could help the Democrats pull the John McCain independents away from the Bush-Cheney ticket.</p>
        <p>If he could curb his desire for attention, Mr. Clinton could help Mr. Gore achieve the aura of independence. That means giving a convention speech that depicts Mr. Gore as something other than a vessel for the Clinton legacy. In 1988, President Reagan helped George Bush overcome the wimp factor by hailing him as ''someone who's big enough and experienced enough'' for the job. If Mr. Clinton is not truly ready for Mr. Gore to have his turn, his inner grump will be visible lurking behind whatever oratorical scrim he erects. The president, in sum, must convince America that he believes Mr. Gore has virtues beyond being more similar to Bill Clinton than George Bush is.</p>
        <p>A Crisp Agenda. Anyone who paid even marginal attention to the Republican convention came away with a clear idea of what Mr. Bush plans to do if elected. He will spend most of the surplus on tax cuts. He will strengthen the military and emphasize a new missile defense system. He will build a private-investment component into Social Security and take unspecified steps to improve education.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore needs to leave an equally crisp paragraph in the heads of the voters after his convention. Senator Charles Schumer is right that Mr. Gore's paragraph has to be written around the concept of prosperity, forcing voters to acknowledge that American families are better off than they were under Mr. Bush's father or Mr. Reagan.</p>
        <p>Voters should know after Los Angeles that Mr. Gore would not risk Reagan-style deficits by spending the surplus on tax cuts. He would use it to secure Social Security and Medicare. He would aim some revenues at improving education and the environment. He would guarantee a Supreme Court that would not overturn the right to abortion. He would free the American political system from the corrupting influence of corporate money.</p>
        <p>Finally, in a personal declaration of independence, he should promise to provide a standard of White House behavior that would not require either public lying or public confessions by the chief executive.</p>
        <p>Performance. As a member of the rock 'n' roll generation, Mr. Gore no doubt remembers the Big Bopper's tribute to being ''real loose like a long-necked goose.'' But the plain fact is, if the man could loosen up he would already have done it. Moreover, he will come to the lectern in Los Angeles trailing many unfortunate sound bites. His early waffling on gun control and abortion financing, his exaggerations about Mr. Clinton's place in history and his evasions about White House fund-raising all cast doubt on the steadiness of his convictions and identity. More than anything, Al Gore needs to use his convention to address those concerns, and he can do so through both style and substance.</p>
        <p>On the stylistic side, no one doubts that Mr. Gore is the best demolition orator in American politics. He will, if he chooses, demolish Mr. Bush's budget arithmetic as thoroughly as he dismantled Bill Bradley's health plan. The problem is that Americans do not really prefer a counterpuncher as their first choice for president. Further, it is a quirk of Mr. Gore's speaking style that the more right he is, the more he irritates people. In this speech, as in no other of his life, he needs to avoid pummeling Americans with his book learning and talk instead about what he believes. For if you hack through the sound-bite detritus of a 24-year electoral career, it is possible to find the theme of a conviction that animates the vice president.</p>
        <p>He does want a government that is caring and active without being intrusive or controlling. In speech after speech he has returned to his desire to be the protector of working families. Mr. Bush has grafted onto his classic corporate Republican politics the view that government ought to be something other than an impassive referee that watches while the economy sorts out the losers and winners. But that benign vision does not have to be grafted onto Mr. Gore's politics. It is root and branch of his philosophy, the healthier part of his inheritance from Albert Gore Sr. and Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>In the weeks and months ahead, Mr. Gore's political fate will be determined by his ability to convey that conviction without shouting, waving his arms or relentlessly flailing his opponent and the public with yet another bunch of impeccably bundled facts. In the end, when choosing between the guy with the smirk and the smartest boy in the class, the voters will go for the man who seems anchored from within by some core of incorruptible belief.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
