<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Empire State Lights, Decoded: India Independence Day Already?</title>
    <meta content="13LIGH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000820T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MIDTOWN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Empire State Building (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rubinstein Associates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubinstein, Howard J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fass, Allison</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lighting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7DE153FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="436" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Empire State Lights, Decoded: India Independence Day Already?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLISON FASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fass, Allison</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rubinstein Associates president Howard Rubinstein explains nighttime light colors atop Empire State Building; sample list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Next weekend, the Empire State Building's lights will be green, white and orange. Some may wonder why.</p>
        <p>''Typically I look at the Empire State Building at night,'' said Rob Tallia, a creator of Not for Tourists, a guide to New York City,  ''wondering, 'Why is it purple tonight?' I was always trying to figure it out.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Next weekend, the Empire State Building's lights will be green, white and orange. Some may wonder why.</p>
        <p>''Typically I look at the Empire State Building at night,'' said Rob Tallia, a creator of Not for Tourists, a guide to New York City,  ''wondering, 'Why is it purple tonight?' I was always trying to figure it out.''</p>
        <p>The explanation for the lights next weekend is to honor India Independence Day with the colors of the Indian flag. Though India marks the holiday on Aug. 15, the building's lights coincide with the India Independence Day parade on Madison Avenue Aug. 20.</p>
        <p>But figuring out what the colors stand for can be hard for some of the holidays, events and groups honored each year. Red, white and blue on the Fourth of July is easy, but bafflers include red, yellow and green on June 10 (Portugal Day), red and white in early October (Pulaski Day) and blue, white and blue (first night of Hanukkah).</p>
        <p>''A lot of people want the lights to change'' for a cause, said Howard J. Rubinstein, president of Rubinstein Associates, which handles the building's public relations, ''but they can't change the lights of every day or every week.'' But, he added, if the lights changed for the ''independence dates of every country in the world, you would have to build another Empire State Building.''</p>
        <p>Usually the color patterns are planned in advance, with the building in white when not lighted a special color. Mr. Rubinstein would not give specifics about the criteria for the colors, but said Leona Helmsley and Peter Malkin, who head the group that controls the building, make the decisions.</p>
        <p>Though the building's policy is not to honor commercial products, corporate events, birthdays or other private occasions, in March 1995, when the blue M &amp; M was introduced, M &amp; M/Mars paid a few thousand dollars to turn the lights blue.</p>
        <p>''I would not encourage that kind of commercialism,'' said Mr. Rubinstein, who said he was not involved with that decision.</p>
        <p>ALLISON FASS</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MIDTOWN  Correction:  August 20, 2000, Sunday  An article in the Neighborhood Report pages last Sunday about the lights on the Empire State Building misspelled the surname of the building's public relations representative. He is Howard J. Rubenstein, not Rubinstein.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 20, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in the Neighborhood Report pages last Sunday about the lights on the Empire State Building misspelled the surname of the building's public relations representative. He is Howard J. Rubenstein, not Rubinstein.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
