<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Open Doors to Honor Jewish Heritage</title>
    <meta content="13ADVB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gruber, Ruth Ellen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1DC103CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="372" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Open Doors to Honor Jewish Heritage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUTH ELLEN GRUBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gruber, Ruth Ellen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jewish sites in 16 European countries plan to simultaneously open doors to public on September 3 for European Day of Jewish Culture; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jewish sites in 16 European countries will simultaneously open their doors to the public on Sept. 3 for a European Day of Jewish Culture, in recognition of Jewish heritage as an integral part of European tradition.</p>
        <p>The list includes about 300 sites, including synagogues, cemeteries, ritual baths,  museums and medieval ghettos in Austria, Belgium, Bosnia-Herzegovina, Bulgaria, Croatia, the Czech Republic, France, Germany, Greece, Italy, Portugal, Romania, Slovakia, Spain, Switzerland and Britain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jewish sites in 16 European countries will simultaneously open their doors to the public on Sept. 3 for a European Day of Jewish Culture, in recognition of Jewish heritage as an integral part of European tradition.</p>
        <p>The list includes about 300 sites, including synagogues, cemeteries, ritual baths,  museums and medieval ghettos in Austria, Belgium, Bosnia-Herzegovina, Bulgaria, Croatia, the Czech Republic, France, Germany, Greece, Italy, Portugal, Romania, Slovakia, Spain, Switzerland and Britain.</p>
        <p>In Italy alone, sites in nearly 40 towns and cities will be open, as will more than two dozen synagogues and Jewish cemeteries in the Alsace-Lorraine region of France.</p>
        <p>Concerts, lectures, performances, guided tours, exhibitions and other events are also planned. These range from a Jewish book fair in Bologna to concerts of Sephardic Jewish music and Jewish food tastings in Girona and Toledo, Spain, to publication of a new brochure on local Jewish history in Bratislava. In Florence,  the Italian Culture Minister Giovanna Melandri is to attend a ceremony formally inaugurating restoration of the ornate synagogue and Jewish museum at Via Farini, 4.</p>
        <p>Many of the sites on display date back centuries. Some, like the Old Jewish Cemetery in Prague, and the two medieval synagogues in Toledo, are world famous. Others, like the 18th-century synagogue in Pfaffenhoffen, France, are used as Jewish museums.</p>
        <p>But most, including the baroque synagogues in Carmagnola and other towns in Italy's Piedmont region, are generally closed to public access, little known or out of use.</p>
        <p>The initiative is coordinated by the European Council of Jewish Communities (www.ecjc.org), the Strasbourg-based Agency for the Development of Tourism of the Bas-Rhin (www.sdv.fr/judaisme/ journee/europ/3sept.htm), B'nai B'rith Europe (www.bnaibrith-europe.org/</p>
        <p>program.html), and the Red de Juderias de Espana (www.redjuderias.org), based in Girona. (Some of these sites do not yet list the full program.)</p>
        <p>The Council of Europe has included it as part of its campaign promoting ''Europe, a Common Heritage.''</p>
        <p>The event is an expansion of an Open Doors to Jewish Heritage program initiated in Alsace in 1996, which has grown each year since then.</p>
        <p>RUTH ELLEN GRUBER</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
