<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Testaverde Gets a Scare, And Jets Are Humbled</title>
    <meta content="13JETS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222432"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Ravens</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Baltimore Ravens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3DB133FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Testaverde Gets a Scare, And Jets Are Humbled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, Aug. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Baltimore Ravens defeat New York Jets, 10-0, in exhibition play; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde had felt nary a breeze in the first two preseason games, so effective was the protection that kept defenders from placing even a finger on him. And Testaverde was not pleased. He had prepared himself for contact, had marked the first hit as the next stepping stone in his grueling recovery from a ruptured Achilles' tendon. He was looking forward to being hit, he said, jesting only a bit.</p>
        <p>Watch what you wish for. Testaverde got hit tonight, and it must have felt like a body blow to the Jets. They received a chilling scare when Testaverde -- who had already been sacked once by Ravens linebacker Ray Lewis -- tried to scramble to his left and was pulled down by his closely watched ankles late in the second quarter of the Jets' 10-0 loss to the Ravens. Testaverde got up, but limped going to the sideline as the drive ended.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jets quarterback Vinny Testaverde had felt nary a breeze in the first two preseason games, so effective was the protection that kept defenders from placing even a finger on him. And Testaverde was not pleased. He had prepared himself for contact, had marked the first hit as the next stepping stone in his grueling recovery from a ruptured Achilles' tendon. He was looking forward to being hit, he said, jesting only a bit.</p>
        <p>Watch what you wish for. Testaverde got hit tonight, and it must have felt like a body blow to the Jets. They received a chilling scare when Testaverde -- who had already been sacked once by Ravens linebacker Ray Lewis -- tried to scramble to his left and was pulled down by his closely watched ankles late in the second quarter of the Jets' 10-0 loss to the Ravens. Testaverde got up, but limped going to the sideline as the drive ended.</p>
        <p>Then, the nightmare report: the Jets were icing Testaverde's left foot, the same foot that suffered the Achilles' injury. Testaverde knew immediately what it was. On the sack, his foot had been jammed into the ground by the Ravens' 330-pound defensive tackle Sam Adams. The diagnosis: turf toe.</p>
        <p>As the half ended, Testaverde, who had replaced Ray Lucas with 5 minutes 46 seconds remaining in the second quarter, walked gingerly to the locker room, his evening ended after two series and seven plays.</p>
        <p>The Jets also lost the rookie quarterback Chad Pennington to a sprained left knee in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>X-rays of Testaverde showed no break. Testaverde, who has had turf toe before, said he would know better after seeing how much the toe swells Sunday how long he will be out.</p>
        <p>It would take a remarkably rapid recovery for Testaverde to play in the Jets' final preseason game Friday against the Giants, which means he would enter the regular season having been in on just 41 plays. But had this been a regular-season game, Testaverde said, he could have returned to action.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't looking forward to not going back in there after being hit,'' Testaverde said. ''The good news is I'll be back very shortly. It's not a serious injury. The good thing is the Achilles held up. But the toe gave out.''</p>
        <p>Lucas sat beside Testaverde as the trainers worked on the toe.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'You all right?' '' Lucas said. ''He said, 'Yeah.' A toe with Vinny? After he had the Achilles? The guy will be back in three days.''</p>
        <p>Pennington, who started the second half, will certainly be out longer than that. He left the game early in the fourth quarter with a sprained left knee he suffered when he took a helmet to the knee on a tackle that spun him in the air like a helicopter blade. Pennington, who was not expected to play once the regular season began, said he would not need surgery, but the length of his rehabilitation remains uncertain.</p>
        <p>''You've got to get in the training room and start strengthening the muscles around the knee and thank God you don't have to have surgery,'' Pennington said. ''It just felt weird and uncomfortable and it didn't feel normal.''</p>
        <p>The injuries to Testaverde and Pennington made an already miserable evening for the Jets' offense immeasurably more disturbing. Testaverde had ceded the starting role tonight to Lucas so that Lucas, who had struggled against Green Bay with the second-string offense, could have a chance to work with the first-teamers. Not that it mattered. The first team tonight was absent receiver Wayne Chrebet, who was scratched with an undisclosed illness. And the offensive line -- so sturdy in the first two games -- was manhandled, giving up four sacks.</p>
        <p>''There were a lot of guys on the offensive line who got their opinion of themselves changed tonight,'' Coach Al Groh said.</p>
        <p>Lucas, under relentless pressure, saw three drives go nowhere, and the final drive he led end when Richie Anderson fumbled the ball on third and goal on the 1-yard line.</p>
        <p>When Testaverde relieved Lucas, his first pass was intended for the rookie receiver Laveranues Coles on the left sideline. But Ravens cornerback Chris McAlister broke first for the ball, which was poorly thrown, and stepped in front of Coles for an interception. McAlister threaded his way through the defense for a 33-yard touchdown return that gave the Ravens a 10-0 lead. In three games, Testaverde has thrown more passes that went for touchdowns for the other team (two) than he has for the Jets (one).</p>
        <p>The Jets got the ball back and four plays later, Testaverde was sacked for the first time. Two plays after that, Testaverde was down and the Jets were thunderstruck.</p>
        <p>The Jets had only one other good scoring opportunity, but Pennington committed his first mistake of an otherwise poised preseason. With the Jets at first and goal on the 1, Pennington aimed a pass for tight end Anthony Becht in the corner of the end zone. But Pennington did not put enough air under the pass and it was picked off.</p>
        <p>The Jets amassed just 238 yards of total offense and only Curtis Martin, who ran for 62 yards on eight attempts, looked like himself. In the course of one evening, the Jets' offense, which had been the strong suit of the preseason, had crumbled, suddenly looking as fragile as the quarterbacks.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Punter TOM TUPA, who is usually flawless, shanked his first punt for just 16 yards after handling a shaky snap from long snapper DENNIS O'SULLIVAN. . . . Cornerback AARON GLENN stayed home with an ankle sprain.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
