<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Deluge, Cars for Sunny Skies</title>
    <meta content="13CONV$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222288"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krebs, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2DF153FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1314" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Deluge, Cars for Sunny Skies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE KREBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krebs, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Listing of convertible model cars from major manufacturers priced at $150,000 or less; photos (M)a</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you live in the Northeast or Upper Midwest, you may be shopping for an ark. Who can think of convertibles when gray skies seem to bring showers almost daily?</p>
        <p>But the long-range forecast calls for sunshine -- someday -- and when it comes, a drop-top car will seem all the sweeter. And when it comes to convertibles, the choices have rarely been better, with several new cars out now. Here are models from major manufacturers priced at $150,000 or less:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you live in the Northeast or Upper Midwest, you may be shopping for an ark. Who can think of convertibles when gray skies seem to bring showers almost daily?</p>
        <p>But the long-range forecast calls for sunshine -- someday -- and when it comes, a drop-top car will seem all the sweeter. And when it comes to convertibles, the choices have rarely been better, with several new cars out now. Here are models from major manufacturers priced at $150,000 or less:</p>
        <p>ASTON MARTIN DB7 VANTAGE VOLANTE  $150,000; 420-horsepower V-12; rear drive; 4 seats; power top; glass rear window.</p>
        <p>The styling is beautiful and the V-12 power is impressive, but the DB7's real draw is the Aston Martin nameplate, which guarantees exclusivity almost anywhere.</p>
        <p>ACURA NSX-T  $88,745; V-6 (252 or 290 h.p.) rear drive; 2 seats; removable roof panels.</p>
        <p>An exotic, distinctively styled supercar with Honda quality and durability, this mid engine, race-inspired rocket is unlikely to leave you stranded.</p>
        <p>AUDI TT ROADSTER  $33,750, 180-h.p. 4, front drive and manual top; $39,450, 225-h.p. turbo 4, all-wheel drive, power top, glass window; four seats.</p>
        <p>Is there a cooler-looking car on the road than the TT coupe? Well, there's the 2001 TT roadster. Truly an all-season car, it is the only medium-priced convertible available with all-wheel drive for winter snows.</p>
        <p>BMW 323Ci  $35,560; 170-h.p. 6; rear drive; 4 seats; manual top; plastic window; power top optional.</p>
        <p>First, the 3-Series sedans were remade, then the coupes. This year, the convertible got a new platform, but it kept its great road manners. Other engines are coming.</p>
        <p>BMW Z3  $31,870 with 170 h.p. 6; $37,470 with 193-h.p. 6; rear drive; 2 seats; manual top; plastic window (power top optional).</p>
        <p>BMW M ROADSTER  $43,270; 240-h.p. 6; rear drive; 2 seats; power top; plastic window.</p>
        <p>A high-performance version of the sporty Z3, this pocket rocket can be highly entertaining in the hands of a skilled driver.</p>
        <p>BMW Z8  $128,700 with 394-h.p. V-8; rear drive; 2 seats; power top; glass window.</p>
        <p>James Bond already had a turn at the wheel of this limited-production roadster with 50's overtones, but it will be an unattainable dream for most people.</p>
        <p>CHEVROLET CAMARO  $24,915, 200-h.p. V-6; $29,290, 305-h.p. V-8; rear drive; 4 seats; power top; rear glass.</p>
        <p>PONTIAC FIREBIRD  $25,785, 200-h.p. V-6; $31,525, 305-h.p. V-8.</p>
        <p>Camaro and Firebird fans should get 'em while they can. After 33 years in G.M.'s lineup, they are likely to disappear, in their current form, in 2002. They're still relative bargains, though insurance can be costly.</p>
        <p>CHEVROLET CAVALIER Z24  $20,350; 150-h.p. 4; front drive; 4 seats; power top; glass window.</p>
        <p>PONTIAC SUNFIRE GT  $22,265; 150-h.p. 4.</p>
        <p>Two of the most affordable softtops around, the Cavalier and Sunfire come with a long list of standard equipment, including antilock brakes and traction control.</p>
        <p>CHEVROLET CORVETTE  $46,350; 345-h.p. V-8; rear drive; 2 seats; power top; glass window.</p>
        <p>The latest version of the Corvette, an American icon since 1953, keeps the character of past classics but improves on their weaknesses. It is now easy to climb in and out, and the trunk can carry two sets of golf clubs. For 2001, horsepower rises to 350.</p>
        <p>CHRYSLER SEBRING  2000 model: $25,070; 168-h.p. V-6; front drive; 4 seats; power top; glass window.</p>
        <p>Practical and relatively affordable, with a back seat that adults can actually use, the Sebring has been the nation's best-selling convertible for good reason. For 2001, an all-new Sebring comes with a 200-horse V-6.</p>
        <p>DODGE VIPER R/T 10  $67,950; 450-h.p. V-10; rear drive; 2 seats; manual top.</p>
        <p>Think of the Viper as a raucous street-legal race car. A new sport package for weekend warriors trades amenities and weight for 10 more horsepower.</p>
        <p>FORD MUSTANG  $22,135 (190-h.p. V-6); GT $26,035 (260-h.p. V-8); Cobra $32,370 (385-h.p. V-8); rear drive; 4 seats; power top; glass window.</p>
        <p>Ford celebrated the Mustang's 35th anniversary in 1999 with a redesign that gave the pony car sharper lines and some retro styling touches. A total remake is due in 2002, with a shift to the Lincoln LS platform.</p>
        <p>HONDA S2000  $32,440; 240-h.p. 4; rear drive; 2 seats; power top; plastic window.</p>
        <p>You'll feel like Mario Andretti as you goose the high-revving engine and quickly run through the short throws of the six-speed manual transmission. But the purity of the racecar design also results in a stiff ride, lots of noise and few amenities.</p>
        <p>JAGUAR XK SERIES  XK8 $71,795 (290-h.p. V8); XKR $82,395 (370-h.p. supercharged V-8); rear drive; 4 seats; power top; glass window.</p>
        <p>The XK is already a raving beauty with sumptuous accommodations and powerful engines; a Silverstone edition due later this year will give the cat even more power.</p>
        <p>MAZDA MIATA  $20,995; 140-h.p. 4; rear drive; 2 seats; manual top; glass window.</p>
        <p>Mazda started the roadster revival a decade ago with this car. Despite an onslaught of new rivals, the perky Miata still delivers the most smiles for the money.</p>
        <p>MERCEDES-BENZ CLK-CLASS  $48,745, 215-h.p. V-6; $56,245, 275-h.p. V-8; rear drive; 4 seats; power top; rear glass.</p>
        <p>Though the trunk space is skimpy for a car of this size, the CLK offers solid, classy, luxurious open-air motoring.</p>
        <p>MERCEDES-BENZ SL-CLASS  $83,245, 302-h.p. V-8; $129,595, 389-h.p. V-12; rear drive; 2 seats; power top; rear plastic.</p>
        <p>The SL, competing in the stratosphere of luxury roadsters, has worn the same basic body since 1990. A new one is in the works.</p>
        <p>MITSUBISHI ECLIPSE SPYDER  $23,842, 154-h.p. 4; $25,732, 205-h.p. V-6; front drive; 4 seats; power top; plastic window.</p>
        <p>The ''geo-mechanical'' styling of the Spyder, introduced as an '01 model last spring, has arcing lines, hard edges and ribbed panels. There is no longer an all-wheel-drive option.</p>
        <p>PLYMOUTH PROWLER  $43,725; 253-h.p. V-6; rear drive; 2 seats; manual top; glass window.</p>
        <p>With the Plymouth brand doomed, this caricature of a 1950's hot rod will become the Chrysler Prowler in a couple of years. The car's cartoonish appearance is a lot more fun than its performance.</p>
        <p>PORSCHE BOXSTER  $42,195, 217-h.p. 6; $50,695, 250-h.p. 6; rear drive; 2 seats; power top; plastic window.</p>
        <p>New this year, an S model adds a more powerful engine to the many charms of this midengine sports car.</p>
        <p>PORSCHE 911 CARRERA  $75,735; $81,165 with all-wheel drive; 300-h.p. 6; 4 seats: power top; plastic window.</p>
        <p>Many enthusiasts consider the 911 the epitome of sports cars. The classic look remains even after a total redesign.</p>
        <p>SAAB 9-3  $40,300 (185-h.p. turbo 4); SE $43,825 (205-h.p. turbo 4); Viggen $45,570 (230-h.p. turbo 4); 4 seats; power top; glass window.</p>
        <p>The name has changed from the 900 to the 9-3 in recent years, and engines were updated. Yet the basic structure is the same, and it feels dated.</p>
        <p>TOYOTA CAMRY SOLARA  $25,523; 135-h.p. 4; front drive; 4 seats; power top; glass window.</p>
        <p>Based on America's best-selling sedan, the Solara convertible is quiet, smooth and nicely finished, but don't expect sports car handling on curvy roads.</p>
        <p>TOYOTA MR2 SPYDER  $23,553; 138-h.p. 4; rear drive; 2 seats; manual top; glass window.</p>
        <p>A midengine design makes the new MR2 a great-handling roadster, but results in a near-total lack of storage. Unless you travel solo, the Miata is more practical.</p>
        <p>VOLKSWAGEN CABRIO  $20,515 (GL, manual top), $23,825 (GLS, power top with glass window); 115-h.p. 4; front drive; 4 seats.</p>
        <p>If you want an affordable convertible with European handling, this is your only choice.</p>
        <p>VOLVO C70  $44,075, 190-h.p. 5; $46,075, 236-h.p. 5; front drive; 4 seats; power top; glass window.</p>
        <p>The first Volvo to break out of the company's styling box, the C70 looks more impressive than it drives. Compared with rock-solid convertibles from some European manufacturers, the C70's structure can be shaky and its drivetrain feels coarse.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
