<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>De La Soul's Spirit Didn't Need City Streets</title>
    <meta content="13RAP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">De La Soul (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muro, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E3D71F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>De La Soul's Spirit Didn't Need City Streets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT MURO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muro, Matt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on De La Soul, 1980's hip-hop act from Amityville, Long Island, whose trio of musicians reject violence and vulgarity and whose fifth album, first of three-part series, has just been released; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>UNLIKE most hip-hop acts of the 1980's, De La Soul didn't hone its skills at block parties on the streets of New York City or Los Angeles; its members practiced on turntables set up in their suburban Long Island bedrooms.</p>
        <p>They didn't make a name for themselves at clubs like Hotel Amazon, a former hip-hop mecca on the Lower East Side in Manhattan; they performed at their high school in Amityville.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>UNLIKE most hip-hop acts of the 1980's, De La Soul didn't hone its skills at block parties on the streets of New York City or Los Angeles; its members practiced on turntables set up in their suburban Long Island bedrooms.</p>
        <p>They didn't make a name for themselves at clubs like Hotel Amazon, a former hip-hop mecca on the Lower East Side in Manhattan; they performed at their high school in Amityville.</p>
        <p>And though gangsta rap and hard-core acts were emerging as dominant musical forces, De La Soul rhymed about peace and whimsically proclaimed that it was the Daisy Age (Da Inner Sound Y'all).</p>
        <p>All the same, its 1989 debut album ''3 Feet High and Rising,'' which eventually sold more than a million copies, shot to the top of the rhythm-and-blues chart and showed that hip-hop could infiltrate Top 40 music by reaching No. 24 on the pop chart. The Long Island trio has been on center stage in the hip-hop universe ever since.</p>
        <p>Their fifth album, ''Art Official Intelligence: Mosaic Thump'' (Tommy Boy), the first of an ambitious three-part series, hit stores last Tuesday. It reveals just how far the three -- Posdnous (whose nickname is Plug One), Dave (Plug Two) and Maseo (Plug Three) -- have come from the days of throwing parties at a room they called ''the dugout'' on Dixon Avenue in Amityville.</p>
        <p>''It was a small hole,'' Maseo recalled. ''We would sell sodas for $1 or $2, have M.C.'s battling.'' (For those who aren't hip-hop savvy, M.C. is another term for rapper.)</p>
        <p>The album also certifies each De La Souler as a veritable elder of their trade, even though each of them has just edged past the age of 30. Old or not, De La Soul exudes at least as much youthful energy on ''Art Official Intelligence'' as on any of its previous releases.</p>
        <p>The group hasalso just headlined the Spitkicker tour, which traveled to cities across the country. With a lineup that includes thought-provoking artists like Common Sense, Talib Kweli and Pharoahe Monch, and hip-hop's jester, Biz Markie, the tour has provided a more lighthearted alternative to this summer's ''Up in Smoke'' tour. ''Up in Smoke'' includes Dr. Dre, Snoop Dogg and Eminem, gangsta rappers known for violent lyrics.</p>
        <p>Influential from the start, De La Soul, along with its former producer Prince Paul, pioneered on its debut album the use of skits -- a running dialogue between the song tracks -- as they wove together a narrative about a tongue-in-cheek television game show. Now, skits are routine.</p>
        <p>De La Soul was also in the vanguard of sampling -- a once controversial practice of appropriating other artists' music. The group was so willing to experiment that a lawsuit was filed against De La Soul by the former Turtles for sampling their 1968 hit ''You Showed Me'' without their permission.</p>
        <p>It's not unusual to hear snippets of rock, vintage jazz, soul, funk or reggae in contemporary hip-hop, but that eclecticism sounded novel when De La Soul mixed samples from songs by Michael Jackson, Steely Dan, Johnny Cash, Funkadelic and a recording of a French lesson in ''3 Feet High and Rising.'' This sampling style continued on their 1991 gold album, ''De La Soul Is Dead,'' which lifted samples from Bob Marley, Chicago, Stevie Wonder, Lou Donaldson, Parliament and even the soundtrack of ''Grease.''</p>
        <p>So how did a group from the suburbs of Long Island become trailblazers in what is thought to be inner-city music? That answer has a lot to do with Long Island -- or Strong Island, as De La Soul refers to it.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's and 80's, there was an exodus of black families from New York City to the suburbs. Dave (David Jolicouer) and Maseo (Vincent Mason) moved with their families to Amityville from Brooklyn as adolescents. Posdnous (Kelvin Mercer) moved at a young age from the Bronx. ''Our parents moved us into a world of boredom,'' Maseo said. ''It allowed our imaginations to go wherever they wanted.''</p>
        <p>With proximity to New York City, De La Soul could spend time in the capital of hip-hop while having space to develop a singular style at home. ''It allowed us to see what was going on in New York City,'' Maseo said. ''And then bring our own ideas to the table, because we didn't always have a lot of outside influence.''</p>
        <p>Dave agreed: ''The island has given us the opportunity to see more things. It broadened our horizons.''</p>
        <p>If the three had grown up in the city, they would have rhymed about the same subjects as other artists. ''We had the opportunity to soak in a lot more,'' Dave said. ''And that's why we are who we are today.''</p>
        <p>In their lyrics, Maseo, Dave and Posdnous, all of whom still live in or around Amityville, have always paid tribute to the Island. And a quick glance at some of their song titles, which include ''Long Island Wildin,'' ''Long Island Degrees,'' and ''Wonce Again Long Island,'' makes it apparent that the trio draws inspiration from their surroundings.</p>
        <p>De La Soul was part of the Native Tongues, a loose alliance of artists including A Tribe Called Quest and the Jungle Brothers known for idiosyncratic word play and a relatively lighthearted tone, and was the first of them to record. While other artists have embraced the violence of gangsta rap acts like N.W.A. or the materialism of rappers like Sean ''Puffy'' Combs, De La Soul has stuck to making music that mixes a good-time party vibe with rhymes that have intellectual weight.</p>
        <p>With De La Soul's refusal to capitalize on flashy hip-hop trends, their commercial success has waned at times. ''Buhloone Mindstate,'' their mellow jazz-infused album featuring the alto-saxophonist Maceo Parker (from James Brown's camp), sold only about 200,000 copies after it came out in 1993. ''Buhloone Mindstate,'' Maseo believes, is one of De La Soul's best albums. ''But nobody bought it,'' he said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>Their cerebral lyrics address topics that range from the playful to the odd to the deadly serious. Among the serious topics they address is ghetto life (''Ghetto Thang'') on their first album and incest (''Millie Pulled a Pistol'') on their second. Their third album, ''Buhloone Mindstate,'' touches on the responsibilities of fatherhood (''I Am I Be'') and the pressures on hip-hop artists to cross over and sell to white audiences (''Patti Dooke'').</p>
        <p>''Stakes Is High,'' their fourth release, was devoted to denouncing what they see as rogue factions of hip-hop, those that subscribe to little more than boasting about material wealth and sustaining a flashy image and another that is little more than thug mentality.</p>
        <p>In the song ''Sunshine,'' for example, Posdnous (pronounced POSS-da-noos) expresses his feelings about thugs in his distinct style of wordplay: ''Throwin' me criminal looks, y'all need to get in the books. Absorb some water in your melon instead of actin' like a felon.''</p>
        <p>In another song, ''The Bizness,'' De La Soul attacks materialistic, image-obsessed hip-hop artists (referred to as ''Shiny suit rappers and frosted MC's''). ''A force that's much greater than your Benz or your Lex,'' the song's chorus says, ''the engine to my comprehension is just too complex.'' In the same song, Dave warns: ''Do not connect us with those champagne-sippin' money fakers.''</p>
        <p>A new school of hip-hop artists is following De La Soul's lead. And the aesthetic of the Native Tongues seems to be recovering from the dominance of gangsta rap, which is big business in comparison. A new generation of rappers, like Mos Def and Common Sense, both of whom collaborated with De La Soul on ''Stakes Is High,'' align themselves with the Native Tongues family. On ''Black on Both Sides,'' Mos Def's 1999 gold album, he proclaims that he is a ''native son speakin' in the native tongues.''</p>
        <p>As for De La Soul's new release, Dave said, ''There's no theme, no underlying message for De La on this one.'' The trio seems to have been more concerned with having fun than with tackling issues on ''Art Official Intelligence.'' With adrenaline-fueled guest rappers like Busta Rhymes, Redman, the Beastie Boys, as well as the soul singer Chaka Khan, the overriding feel of the album is one with a party vibe.</p>
        <p>It also has a more mainstream feel than De La Soul fans might expect. A steady flow of catchy and infectious rhythms, a harder-than-usual sound and a horde of big-name guest rappers add to the more conventional flavor of ''Art Official Intelligence.'' It is possible that De La Soul has relaxed its position as the guardians of the hip-hop intelligentsia, now that other hip-hop artists like Mos Def are carrying some of the load. And since none of its albums have been as successful as its debut, ''3 Feet High and Rising,'' it's possible that De La Soul wants to reap the rewards of the hip-hop style that it helped to develop more than a decade ago.</p>
        <p>But De La Soul has not abandoned its integrity. The same kinds of obtuse rhymes and idiosyncratic wordplay abound on the album, which rolls from one solid track to the next. It hasn't abandoned issues, either. ''U Don't Wanna B.D.S.,'' the last track on the album, is as hardcore and aggressive sounding as gansta rap, but it is an attack on those who tote guns. And De La Soul uses the song ''Foolin' '' to attack rappers that it considers to be artificial, ones who fake roles and appropriate images to get ahead in the music business. To those rappers, Posdnous rhymes: ''Y'all silly, just a civily, I'm a soldier, troopin' in this path to the death when its over.''</p>
        <p>Judging from their careers, the three seem entitled to be regarded as hip-hop soldiers. Whether making gold albums or ones that are commercial failures, De La Soul continues to make music that they believe has depth and value.</p>
        <p>The title ''Art Official Intelligence'' says it best. ''The art that we do is official,'' Maseo said. ''And we're not afraid to embrace intelligence in what we do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
