<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reykjavik</title>
    <meta content="REYK.$31" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Reykjavik (Iceland)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ashenburg, Katherine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Iceland/Reykjavik</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Iceland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7D9103CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reykjavik</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE ASHENBURG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ashenburg, Katherine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Doing In travel article describes upcoming events, sightseeing, hotels and restaurants in Reykjavik, Iceland; photos; maps; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On his way to the nether world, the narrator of Jules Verne's ''Journey to the Center of the Earth'' makes quick work of Reykjavik, ''a town of two bleak, depressing Avenues'' where most people are busy drying and salting cod. Travelers from William Morris to W. H. Auden tended to agree, briefly condescending to Iceland's capital before heading for the hinterlands in search of sagas, volcanos or geysers.</p>
        <p>That attitude is ''so yesterday,'' as the young people who throng Reykjavik's hectic club scene might put it. In the 1990's, travel to the world's northernmost capital, tucked into Iceland's southwestern coast, increased by 13 percent. Part of the reason is Iceland's booming economy, with an accompanying rise in smart restaurants, fashion designers, art galleries (and prices).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On his way to the nether world, the narrator of Jules Verne's ''Journey to the Center of the Earth'' makes quick work of Reykjavik, ''a town of two bleak, depressing Avenues'' where most people are busy drying and salting cod. Travelers from William Morris to W. H. Auden tended to agree, briefly condescending to Iceland's capital before heading for the hinterlands in search of sagas, volcanos or geysers.</p>
        <p>That attitude is ''so yesterday,'' as the young people who throng Reykjavik's hectic club scene might put it. In the 1990's, travel to the world's northernmost capital, tucked into Iceland's southwestern coast, increased by 13 percent. Part of the reason is Iceland's booming economy, with an accompanying rise in smart restaurants, fashion designers, art galleries (and prices).</p>
        <p>Another is Bjork, the pop sensation who has made her country hip by association. And Reykjavik's pollution-free environment, heated by geothermal energy and powered by waterfalls, makes the city not only a happening place, but a healthy one.</p>
        <p>One of Reykjavik's chief charms predates the 90's: it is both easy and exotic. Easy because it is a mere five-hour flight from New York and almost everyone speaks a fluent, softly accented English. Exotic because it is a land apart.</p>
        <p>Icelanders speak an ancient language, unmarred by English incursions. Trees are scarce and volcanic rocks punctuate the landscape. And Reykjavik manages to be an appealing mixture of quaint old buildings and smashing new ones.</p>
        <p>As if that weren't enough to celebrate, Reykjavik is one of nine European Cities of Culture this year. It is also 1,000 years since Christianity came to Iceland, and since an Icelander named Leifur Eiriksson discovered America.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>This Saturday is not only the day of the Reykjavik Marathon, it is also Culture Night. This annual all-night spree, free all over the downtown and harbor area, combines outdoor performances, concerts, fairs and fireworks. Bars, restaurants, galleries and shops stay open till dawn.</p>
        <p>The millennial events are organized around the four elements, and this weekend's are devoted to fire, as harnessed by blacksmiths and potters. Blacksmiths, up to 200 from around the world, will create objects and art, using archaic tools and methods. Admission is free to see them in the City Hall, at Vonarstraeti.</p>
        <p>Hallgrimskirkja, a Lutheran church, soars above Reykjavik like a Gothic cathedral crossed with a volcanic mountain. On Aug. 26 at 8 p.m. and Aug. 27 at 5 p.m., the church, at Skolavorduholt, will be host to Voices of Europe, a youth choir made up of 10 choristers from each City of Culture. They will perform music from all nine cities, including a commissioned premiere from the Estonian composer Arvo Part. Tickets, at the Tourist Information Center, 2 Banka straeti, (354) 552-8588, are about $38, at 79 kronur to the dollar.</p>
        <p>From Sept. 2 to 10, the Reykjavik Jazz Festival takes over town, from City Hall to the Opera House and cafes and hotels in between. The musicians include Arni Egilsson, the Dave Holland quintet and the Reykjavik Big Band. Tickets range from free to $44; contact the festival at Post Office Box 8955, 128 Reykjavik, or by e-mail at reykavikjazz@mail .com.</p>
        <p>A star-studded International Literary Festival from Sept. 10 to 16 brings a score of writers from around the world to Nordic House, near the University of Iceland, to read and discuss their work. The authors -- including Gunter Grass, A. S. Byatt, Linn Ullmann, Andre Brink and Edward Bunker -- will read in their own languages in a nearby theater, and most days at noon, there will be open discussions in English. The events are free. Information: (354) 551-7030.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>Visitors can absorb a surprising amount of Icelandic history and art, and walk Reykjavik in the bargain, with the help of a free pamphlet, ''Artistic Treasures,'' from the Tourist Information Center. This walking tour of some of Reykjavik's many statues tells you, among other things, that Jon Sigurdsson, whose likeness stands in front of Parliament House, is the national hero: he called for independence from Denmark in the 1850's (it finally came in 1944).</p>
        <p>The Reykjavik Card offers bus travel and admission to a raft of diversions for 24 hours ($11.50), 48 hours ($15) or 72 hours ($19). The attractions include more than 15 galleries, museums and exhibitions, the zoo and Reykjavik's seven thermal pools. It is sold at hotels and wherever the card is honored.</p>
        <p>A well-spent 24 hours using the card might begin at Harbor House, 17 Tryggvagatu, (354) 511-5155, a converted 1930's warehouse that is now a dazzling showcase for contemporary art. Open Friday to Wednesday 11 a.m. to 6 p.m., and Thursday until 7 p.m. Regular admission is $5, free on Monday.</p>
        <p>A short walk away, at 15 Hversigata, is Culture House, (354) 545-1400, another new museum, devoted to Iceland's history. It has two thoughtfully designed anniversary exhibits (with English signs), on the Vikings' voyages and Christianity in Iceland. Open daily 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; regular admission is $3.80.</p>
        <p>After that, a walk along the Tjorn, Reykjavik's midtown pond, will take you to the National Gallery of Iceland, 7 Frikirkjuvegur, (354) 562-1000. It is modestly stocked with 19th- and 20th-century work, including an easy-to-digest summer exhibition on 20th-century Icelandic art. Open 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tuesday to Sunday. Regular admission $5, free on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>After dinner, you might board the No. 5 bus to Laugardalslaug, (354) 553-4039, the biggest of the city's thermal pools, all at 86 degrees Fahrenheit. Aside from the 50-meter pool, there are three ''hot pots'' that are as warm as 108 degrees, a water slide, whirlpool and steambath. Regular admission, $3.</p>
        <p>Next morning, you could take the No. 10 or 110 bus to Arbaerjarsafn, (354) 577-1111, an architectural museum with over 20 buildings from the 19th and early 20th century. Don't miss the turf-covered church, the dauntingly steep stairs in the houses and the rolled Icelandic crepes ($3.80) in the 1835 Restaurant. August hours are Tuesday to Friday 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., weekends 10 a.m. to 6 p.m., and Monday 11 a.m. to 4 p.m. From Sept. 1, there are tours on Monday, Wednesday and Friday at 1 p.m. Regular admission is $5.</p>
        <p>Two galleries, two museums, assorted bus rides and a spa experience -- not bad for 24 hours and $11.50.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>On the outside, Guesthouse Anna, 16 Smaragata, (354) 562-1618, fax (354) 562-1656, is an angular Futurist house, built in 1931; inside, it's furnished with family antiques and other comfortable pieces. Anna Tryggvadottir McDonald is an engaging Icelander with an accent from Atlanta, where she lived more than 30 years. She has 12 rooms, six with bath. It costs about $113 for a double with bath, including an Icelandic breakfast with bread, cold meats, cheeses and fruit.</p>
        <p>Hotel Leifur Eiriksson, 45 Skolavordustigur, (354) 562-0800, fax (354) 562-0804, has 29 rooms with bath, telephone and TV. Rooms are brightly but frugally furnished and a double is $145 with breakfast. The hotel is a stone's throw from the statue of its namesake by Alexander Stirling Calder (father of the mobile-maker)  in front of Hallgrimskirkja.</p>
        <p>Budget: Guesthouse Svala, 30 Skolavordustig, (354) 562-3544, fax (354) 562-3650, has a curvaceous Scandinavian gable and pleasant garden. The house, also near the Hallgrimskirkja, has nine unpretentiously furnished rooms all with three shared baths. A double costs $75, including breakfast. The proprietors own several other houses in the neighborhood, with about 20 rooms and suites in all for rent.</p>
        <p>Luxury: Hotel Holt, 37 Bergstadastraeti, (354) 552-5700, fax (354) 562-3025, calls itself ''the hotel in an art collection,'' and it's worth a stroll through the public rooms to see the collection of 19th- and 20th-century Icelandic paintings. They also hang in the characterful 42 bedrooms.  Doubles are $205.</p>
        <p>Hotel Borg, 9-11 Posthusstraeti, (354) 551-1440, fax (354) 551-1420, shares the Austurvollur, the old town square, with the Cathedral and Parliament House, and it, too, has been a landmark since 1930. Recently returned to its original Art Deco look, it has 50 rooms decorated with period and modern furniture. A double with breakfast goes for $222.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Reykjavik has several stylish new restaurants, the most original of which, Tveir Fiskar (Two Fish), 9 Geirsgata, (354) 511-3474, opened this spring on the harbor. It's a calm, plain room ornamented only with a frieze of fish and a sushi station. The bouillabaisse has a garlic-rich broth, and the skyr tart with citrus sauce is a fine way to meet the national dessert (skyr is midway between yogurt and cream cheese). Dinner for two with wine will cost about $125.</p>
        <p>Also new, and housed in an architectural pearl of a 1916 pharmacy, Apotek, 16 Austurstraeti, (354) 575-7900, has a cozy bar-cafe and a beautiful white main room with umbrella-shaped lamps. The food is equally tasteful: barely grilled tuna with ginger-roasted vegetables and three kinds of creme brulee with plum compote are typical offerings. Dinner for two, about $110. A glass of wine will add $7.60 to the tab.</p>
        <p>Good, inexpensive dinners are scarce in Reykjavik. Lunch is easier, especially in the museum cafes, where you can eat an open-faced smoked salmon sandwich in smart surroundings for about $7.50 (at Harbor House) or as many servings of cream of vegetable soup and homemade Parmesan bread as you like for about $9 (Culture House).</p>
        <p>The Primavera, 9 Austurstraeti, (354) 561-8555, a columned room in a heritage building, is also a good midday choice. The menu changes often, but the three-course lunch -- which  might include a creamy, garlicky fish soup, trout and a nut torte -- costs $20. Dinner with wine could easily be triple that.</p>
        <p>Not new, not chic, Laekjarbrekka, 2 Bankastraeti, (354) 551-4430, is the place to go for traditional Icelandic specialties. A red-and-black caviar mosaic of lumpfish and trout eggs on a blini, with a glass of Brennivin, the Icelandic schnapps, costs $18; sauteed blackbird breast with red currant sauce is $32. A modest bottle of wine costs $34. Laekjarbrekka also offers a daily tourist menu (two courses and coffee) for $23, or $11.50 for children under 12; children under 5 eat free. A recent example was green-pepper soup and ocean perch with sauce and vegetables.</p>
        <p>Salatbar Eika, 13 Posthusstraeti, (354) 562-7830, in a prime location on Austurvollur, has an all-you-can-eat buffet and salad bar for $11.25 ($5.70 for children). Avoid the watery fish soup and the herring in sweetish curry sauce and concentrate on the raw vegetables, tuna salad, good bread, chicken wings, yogurts and fruits. An individual bottle of wine or can of beer is $5.70.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN KATHERINE ASHENBURG wrote ''Going to Town: Architectural Walking Tours in Southern Ontario'' (McFarlane, Walter &amp; Ross).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">KATHERINE ASHENBURG wrote ''Going to Town: Architectural Walking Tours in Southern Ontario'' (McFarlane, Walter &amp; Ross).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
