<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GOING OUT</title>
    <meta content="13TOWN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE TOWNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3DD173FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="3060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GOING OUT</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; by fax to (212) 556-7219, or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An opinionated guide to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. Items may be submitted by mail to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036; by fax to (212) 556-7219, or by e-mail to njtowns@nytimes.com.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
        <p>CHALFONTE HOTEL ''Concerts by Candlelight'' featuring Festive Brass. Tuesday at 8:30 p.m. in the Henry Sawyer Room. Tickets: $7, or free with dinner. ''La Dolce Vita'' cabaret of movie songs of the 1960's, featuring Jilline Ringle. Through next Sunday. Performances are at 9 p.m. on Wednesday, Thursday, Saturday and Sunday evenings. Tickets: $20; $18 for students and older people; $8 for children under 12. 301 Howard Street, Cape May. (609) 884-8409.</p>
        <p>FAIR LAWN SUMMER MUSIC FESTIVAL Harold Lieberman leads the Big Band in a tribute to the Swing Era Bands. Today at 8:30 p.m.  Howard Tavin and Annette Sanders. Next Sunday at 8:30 p.m. Free. Memorial Park, Berdan Avenue, Fair Lawn. (201) 796-6746.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY PERFORMING ARTS CENTER ''Absolut Sounds of the City 2000,'' outdoor music series. Thursday evenings, 5 to 10 o'clock, through Aug. 31. Jorge Amorim (Latin jazz); K. J. Denhert and the New York Unit (urban Folk); Conglomerate Family and the World Citizens (rap); Felix Cabrera (Afro-Cuban blues/jazz). Free. Theater Square. 1 Center Street, Newark. (888) 466-5722.</p>
        <p>OCEAN GROVE SUMMER CONCERT SERIES Through Sept. 9. Great Auditorium Organ Recital featuring Gordon Tuck, organist, and Carol Williams, guest organist. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. Michael Feinstein. Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $28 (reserved); $23 (general admission). The Great Auditorium, Ocean Grove. (732) 988-0645.</p>
        <p>UNITARIAN UNIVERSALIST MEETING HOUSE  ''Summer Sings 2000,'' featuring the Shrewsbury Chorale, Jonathan Dimmock, guest conductor. Tuesday, 7:45 p.m. to 10 p.m. Tickets:  $5. 1475 West Front Street, Lincroft. (732) 946-7204.</p>
        <p>WALDWICK BAND A Concert of light classics, Broadway selections and marches, featuring Paul Wallace, clarinetist. Wednesday at 7:30 p.m. Free. McGowan Park, Bergen Turnpike, Ridgefield Park. (201) 664-2939.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>EATONTOWN PLAYHOUSE ''Three Murders and It's Only Monday,'' murder mystery comedy spoof. Through Aug. 27. Fridays at 8:30 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m.  Tickets: $17 for Fridays and Saturdays; $16 for Sundays; $15 for students and older people on Fridays and Saturdays; $10 for students and older people on Sundays. 37 Highway 35 North, Tower Shopping Center, Eatontown. (732) 460-0100.</p>
        <p>HUNTERDON HILLS PLAYHOUSE ''Razzmatazz,'' musical celebrating popular songs of the 20th century. Through Sept. 9 Monday through Saturday luncheon matinees beginning at 11 a.m.; Saturdays at 6:30 p.m.; Sundays at 3:30 p.m. Tickets: $39.50 to $51 (includes show and lunch/dinner). Exit 12 off Routes 78 and 22, Perryville. (800) 447-7313.</p>
        <p>LUMIA THEATER ''The Girl With the High Rouge,'' Vincent Sessa's surreal comic-drama, performed by the New Jersey Repertory Company. Through next Sunday. Thursday through Saturday at 8 p.m.; today and next Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $25. 179 Broadway, Long Branch. (732) 229-3166.</p>
        <p>LUMIA THEATER -- STAGE II ''Slow Fade to Black'' staged reading. Tomorrow at 2 p.m. and 7 p.m. Tickets: $7.50. 179 Broadway, Long Branch. (732) 229-3166.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL ''Rhinoceros.'' Through Aug. 27. Performances are Tuesdays through Saturdays at 8 p.m.; selected Saturdays and Sundays at 2 p.m. and selected Sundays at 7 p.m. Tickets: $21 to $38.  F. M. Kirby Shakespeare Theater, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (973) 408-5600.</p>
        <p>RITZ THEATER ''Broadway Overtures,'' the third presentation in the Ritz 2000 Concert Series. Friday and Saturday at 8 p.m.; next Sunday at 2 p.m. Tickets: $12.50. 915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn. (609) 858-5230.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
        <p>EATONTOWN PLAYHOUSE ''Otto the Clown.'' Saturday at 3 p.m. For ages 4 to 7. Tickets:  $7.50. 37 Highway 35 North, Tower Shopping Center, Eatontown. (732) 460-0100.</p>
        <p>MORRIS COUNTY PARK COMMISSION ''Dream Catcher Workshop.'' Wednesday at 2 p.m. Free. Preschooler Walk. Thursday at 2:30 p.m. Fee: $5 a child; pre-registration is required. Great Swamp Outdoor Education Center, 247 Southern Boulevard, Chatham Township. (973) 635-6629.</p>
        <p>NOYES MUSEUM OF ART ''Coffee Can Drums,'' Creative Sparks hands-on art activity. Saturday, 1 p.m. to 2 p.m. For children ages 6 to 12. Fee: $1 a child, plus regular admission: $3; $2 for children 12 to 17 and free for children under age 12. Preregistration is required. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848.</p>
        <p>PARSIPPANY PLAYHOUSE ''Heidi,'' the musical, presented by Allegro Productions. Tuesday through Aug. 22. Saturday performances at 11 a.m. and 2 p.m. Tickets: $10. 1130 Knoll Road, Parsippany. (973) 263-7020.</p>
        <p>Museums and Galleries</p>
        <p>HUNTERDON MUSEUM OF ART Lyanne Malamed, paintings and drawings. Through Sept. 10. ''Four Points of View: Artists From Lambertville.'' Through Sept. 10. Hours: Tuesdays through Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM ''Croquet: The Art of Play.' Through Oct. 15. Tuesdays through Sundays, noon to 7 p.m.; Sept. 9 through Oct. 15, course will be open Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $7; $4 for children. Will Barnet: A Timeless World.  Through next Sunday. Hours: Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Fridays and Saturdays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays and Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m. Admission: $5; $4 for older people and students; free for members and children under 12. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (973) 746-5555.</p>
        <p>MORRIS MUSEUM New Jersey Arts Annual:  ''Everything for the Home'' juried exhibition.  Through Nov. 17. ''A Collector's Vision: Selections From the Collections of Edmund W. Pease and Nurak Israsena.'' Through Sept. 17. Hours: Sundays, 1 to 5 p.m.; Tuesdays through Saturdays, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays to 8 p.m. Admission: $5; $3 for older people and children under age 3. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (973) 538-0454.</p>
        <p>NABISCO GALLERY ''Alchemy: Society of Layerists in Multi-Media.'' Through Sept. 6. Hours: daily, noon to 4 p.m. 100 DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (973) 503-2000.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM ''Building a Collection: Fine Art at the New Jersey State Museum.'' Through next Sunday. ''Leah Phyfer Sloshberg Collection of Fine Art.'' Through Sept. 3. ''The Art of Jack Delano.'' Through Sept. 4. ''Of Rock and Fire.'' On extended view. Hours: Tuesdays through Saturdays, 9 a.m. to 4:45 p.m.; Sundays, noon to 5 p.m. Free. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6464.</p>
        <p>WHEATON VILLAGE ''American Glass: 1900-2000,'' featuring more than 100 industrial and decorative pieces. Through Oct. 22. Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $7; $6 for older people; $3.50 for students. No admission charge to the Gallery of American Craft. Exit 26, Route 55, Millville. (800) 998-4552, extension 2756.</p>
        <p>Etc.</p>
        <p>GARDEN STATE EXHIBIT CENTER Antiques Weekend in Somerset. Saturday and next Sunday, 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Admission: $6; free for children under 16. Off Exit 10 of Route 287, 10 miles west of both the New Jersey Turnpike and the Garden State Parkway. (212) 255-0020.</p>
        <p>HISTORIC COLD SPRING VILLAGE Saturday Evening Concert Series. Through Sept. 2. Nice  'n Easy Trio. Saturday at 6:30 p.m. Village Gazebo. Free. Antique Show and Sale. Today, 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Admission: $5; $4 for older people; $3 for children, ages 3 to 12. 720 Route 9, three miles north of Cape May City. (609) 898-2300.</p>
        <p>LONG BEACH ISLAND FOUNDATION OF THE ARTS AND SCIENCES ''Sister To Sister: An Evening of Story Telling by Sisters,'' featuring Nancy Kavanaugh and Carolyn Rapp. Tomorrow, 8 p.m. to 9 p.m. Fee: $10 (registration is requested). ''Sister to Sister Workshop.'' Tuesday, 9:30 a.m. to 12:30 p.m. Fee:  $25. $15. 120 Long Beach Boulevard, Loveladies. (609) 494-1241, extension 300.</p>
        <p>MACCULLOCH HALL HISTORICAL MUSEUM ''The Chandeliers of Macculloch Hall'' special walking tour through the Museum. Today at 2 p.m. Tickets: $4; $3 for students and older people; free for children under 12. Admission includes the Museum and exhibits. 45 Macculloch Avenue, Morristown. (973) 538-2404.</p>
        <p>At the Casinos</p>
        <p>All tickets are available through Ticketmaster, (800) 736-1420.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC CITY HILTON Ray Charles. Today at 8 p.m. Tickets: $40 and $45. Trisha Yearwood. Friday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $45 and $50.  Grand Theater, Boston and Pacific Avenues. (609) 340-7200.</p>
        <p>BALLY'S PARK PLACE ''Legends in Concert,'' impersonations. Mondays through Thursdays at 3:30 and 7:30 p.m.; Saturdays at 8 and 10:30 p.m.; Sundays at 7:30 and 10 p.m. Tickets: $15 to $25. Park Cabaret, Boardwalk and Park Place. (800) 225-5977.</p>
        <p>CAESARS ATLANTIC CITY Steve Lawrence and Eydie Gorme. Thursday through next Sunday.  Thursday at 8 p.m.; Friday at 10 p.m.; Saturday at 9 p.m.; next Sunday at 8 p.m. Tickets:  $50. Circus Maximus Theater, 2100 Pacific Avenue. (800) 677-7469.</p>
        <p>CLARIDGE HOTEL ''Pump Boys and Dinettes,'' national tour of the Broadway musical. Through Sept. 24. Performances are Mondays through Thursdays at 8 p.m.; Saturdays at 9 p.m.; Sundays at 3 p.m. and 7 p.m. Tickets: $15, Sundays through Thursdays; $19, Saturdays. Palace Theater, Boardwalk and Park Place. (609) 340-3700.</p>
        <p>SANDS HOTEL AND CASINO Jerry Blavat. Thursday, 5 p.m. to 7 p.m. Bud Noble. Wednesday through Saturday, 6 p.m. to 10 p.m. Melissa Marshall Quartet. Wednesday through Saturday, 10:15 p.m. to 2:15 a.m. Copa Lounge. Free. The Diamonds. Through Sept. 10. Call for times. Tickets: $15. Cozy Morley. Tuesdays and Wednesdays through Aug. 30, at 3 p.m. Tickets: $15. Indiana Avenue and Brighton Park. (609) 441-4137.</p>
        <p>TROPICANA The Four Tops. Friday at 9 p.m.; Saturday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $45 and $35. Latin Fever Revue. Through Sept. 21. Call for times. Tickets: $9.90. ''Titanic: The Return,'' all new exhibition with more than 250 artifacts. Through Sept. 9. Hours: daily, 10 a.m. to 10 p.m. Tickets: $14.95; $6.95 for children, ages 5 to 11. Grand Exhibition Center, fourth floor, South Tower. Boardwalk and Brighton Avenue. (609) 340-4020.</p>
        <p>TRUMP MARINA Joan Jett and the Black Hearts. Friday at 10 p.m. Tickets: $28. Robert Schimmel. Saturday at 8 p.m. and 11 p.m.  Tickets: $25. The Shell. George Thorogood and the Destroyers. Saturday at 9 p.m. Tickets: $25 and $35. Grand Cayman. Huron Avenue and Brigantine Boulevard. (800) 777-8477.</p>
        <p>TRUMP PLAZA ''Dancin' in the Streets,'' a song and dance block party. Mondays and Thursdays at 4 p.m.; Tuesdays through Thursdays at 7:30 p.m.; Fridays at 9 p.m. and Saturdays at 8 p.m. Through Aug. 31. Tickets: $18; $12 for matinees. Boardwalk at Mississippi Avenue. (800) 759-8786.</p>
        <p>TRUMP TAJ MAHAL Pat Benatar. Today at 8 p.m. Tickets: $25 and $35. The Righteous Brothers. Saturday at 9 p.m.; next Sunday at 8 p.m. Tickets: $35 and $50. Xanadu. 1000 Boardwalk. (609) 449-1000.</p>
        <p>ON THE TOWNS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
