<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Business; Planning a Trip for 125? Send In the Specialty Agent</title>
    <meta content="13TRAV$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel Agencies and Agents</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levere, Jane L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Agencies and Agents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DF153FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1353" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Business; Planning a Trip for 125? Send In the Specialty Agent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE L. LEVERE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Levere, Jane L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on specialization taking place within travel agency industry; agencies acquire specific knowledge regarding specialized needs of various industries, groups and professions; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHARON S. TURNAU, president of Landmark Travel in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., knows what it means to be flexible.</p>
        <p>She once had to arrange five deliveries of airline tickets in one hour to a law firm whose flight itinerary kept changing. Another time, she had to have a lawyer literally pulled off a plane; the lawyer's deposition was in Columbus but her secretary had mistakenly sent her to Cleveland.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHARON S. TURNAU, president of Landmark Travel in Fort Lauderdale, Fla., knows what it means to be flexible.</p>
        <p>She once had to arrange five deliveries of airline tickets in one hour to a law firm whose flight itinerary kept changing. Another time, she had to have a lawyer literally pulled off a plane; the lawyer's deposition was in Columbus but her secretary had mistakenly sent her to Cleveland.</p>
        <p>''When she got off to change planes, the airline caught her and directed her to Columbus; she arrived on time for her deposition,'' Ms. Turnau said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Turnau, of course, is used to handling fluctuating plans and misdirected passengers. It comes with the turf as a specialty travel agent.</p>
        <p>Landmark Travel, whose clients include about 20 law firms, is one of a small group of agencies across the country that cater to specific industries and their varying demands. There are agencies that assist dance companies, whose performers require special hotel amenities, as well as agencies that cater to fashion and publishing executives who want only the most stylish accommodations. And someone has to help arrange transportation for the circus clowns and their animal sidekicks.</p>
        <p>Hoffman Entertainment Travel of Burbank, Calif., a division of McCord Travel Management, works with the entertainment industry, including production companies and film studios, while Valerie Wilson Travel Inc. of New York handles the fashion, publishing, financial and pharmaceutical industries. The World Travel Specialists Group, also in New York, makes arrangements for lawyers, bankers, consultants, advertising agencies and, most recently, dot-com companies that prefer face-to-face service to the Internet.</p>
        <p>Even individual agents are specializing: Marjorie Agriss, with Pisa Brothers Travel Services in New York, once worked as a travel agent for Broadway producers and now arranges trips for the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, the American Ballet Theater and the Big Apple Circus.</p>
        <p>Demand for specialty services has been rising, analysts say, because the travel industry is consolidating and because many of the larger agencies, and even some smaller ones, have become increasingly reluctant to pursue clients who may be more demanding and thus more time consuming and less profitable to handle. At the same time, some smaller independent agencies see specialization as a way to survive in the wake of commission cuts that have been made by airlines in recent years. (Today, commissions are 5 percent of the value of a ticket, and are also capped at $50 a round-trip domestic ticket and $100 a round-trip international ticket.)</p>
        <p>''These agencies are looking for customers who are less price-sensitive, who can pay them greater fees,'' said Robert Moss, a travel industry consultant in Belmont, Mass. ''They're trying to get away from selling a commodity product that everyone else sells.''</p>
        <p>The specialized agencies may bill for each transaction -- usually a minimum of $20 an airline ticket -- or charge a management fee that is generally 2 percent to 3.5 percent of their clients' travel expenditures. Some, like World Travel Specialists Group and Hoffman Entertainment, will even place agents in clients' offices.</p>
        <p>Clients say they do not mind paying these fees as long as the agency delivers, which means that it must understand their needs and provide around-the-clock hand-holding as well as discounts.</p>
        <p>''One advantage of working with an agency like W.T.S.G. is that their leverage in the travel business helps start-ups like ourselves that don't have the volume or the experience to get some discounts on our own,'' said Chuck Curtis, director of human resources for Need2Buy.com, a business-to-business online marketer based in Westlake Village, Calif.</p>
        <p>Paul Moskowitz, president and chief operating officer of the World Travel Specialists Group, says his company saves its clients, on average, 23 percent off published rates of airlines and hotels. Valerie Wilson, chairwoman of the agency that bears her name, says her clients save around 20 percent of published rates.</p>
        <p>Travel discounts can sometimes make or break a season for a performing arts company, Ms. Agriss said. ''One of the main things I do is to contact airlines for rates that make trips affordable, because I have clients, particularly nonprofits, who say that if I can't get the rates down, their tour won't happen,'' she said. ''They rely on me.''</p>
        <p>She recently negotiated a special $135 one-way fare for a group of Alvin Ailey dancers for a noon flight on American Airlines from Austin, Tex., to New York; the  unrestricted one-way fare on that route is around $800, Ms. Agriss said.</p>
        <p>Agencies also help clients with their travel-management policies, establishing rules about who can fly first class, for example, or  which expenses are reimbursable.</p>
        <p>Robert Baxter, senior vice president and chief financial officer of Odyssey Network in Studio City, Calif., a subsidiary of the pay-television company Crown Media Holdings, relies on Hoffman Entertainment for help in revising his company's travel policy in order to get cheaper fares. ''Half our travel is between Los Angeles and New York, and if we fly the wrong airline or go to the wrong airport, it kills us,'' Mr. Baxter said. ''So we modify our policy six or eight times a year to get savings.''</p>
        <p>For many specialty agents, change is constant. Jim Hagy, a partner in the Chicago law office of Jones Day Reavis &amp; Pogue, a client of the World Travel Specialists Group, estimates that his colleagues change their travel plans three times, on average, either before their departure or while traveling.</p>
        <p>The agents typically go with the flow. Having to extend a business trip recently in Milan, John R. Wilson, president of Vestimenta Inc., an apparel distributor in New York, asked Valerie Wilson Travel to rebook his airline ticket and extend his stay at the Hotel Principe di Savoia. ''During the fashion shows, Milan is absolutely a zoo,'' Mr. Wilson said. ''But the agency got me onto a later flight, and I didn't have to move out of my hotel, even though it was overbooked.''</p>
        <p>Specialized agents can also handle other requirements for their clients.</p>
        <p>Valerie Wilson must find hotels that match the tastes of her fashion and publishing clients. ''In Milan, for example, the more conservative fashion houses want to be at the Principe di Savoia,'' she said, ''while the trendier ones want to stay at the Four Seasons.''</p>
        <p>PERFORMING ARTS companies pose their own challenges. Many dancers belong to unions, whose rules may regulate the number of hours and times of day that they can travel. They also travel in large groups that include musicians and production and administrative staff. (The traveling American Ballet Theater has  about 125 people, each of whom usually has at least two pieces of luggage.)</p>
        <p>And the demands continue at the destination. Calvin Hunt, general manager of the first company of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, which travels 25 weeks a year, says his dancers' primary requirements are a bathtub, ''to soak their tired muscles''; room service, ''because they sleep late during the day and come home late at night''; and a swimming pool, where they can cross-train.</p>
        <p>''Finding hotels with these services that are also in close proximity to the theater where we're performing and that are not five-star is difficult,'' Mr. Hunt said.</p>
        <p>Not quite as difficult, however, as one of Ms. Agriss's recent assignments. In her work with the Big Apple Circus last year, she had to find a way to transport 17 dogs from Russia, accompanied by their trainer, by plane from Moscow to New York. That involved making special arrangements with Aeroflot, in addition to obtaining health certificates for the dogs. But some things were simply beyond her control, she said, recalling what happened after the plane touched down.</p>
        <p>''The customs guy was ready to check the dogs off when they got off the plane, but when they arrived, there were 21 of them.  One had had four puppies on the flight,'' she said. ''He let them all in.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
