<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Busy Newark Losing Monorail</title>
    <meta content="13PRAC$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222016"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monorails</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newark International Airport (NJ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Betsy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5D9103CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1388" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Busy Newark Losing Monorail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETSY WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Betsy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Betsy Wade Practical Traveler column on upcoming closing of five-year-old monorail at Newark International Airport, possibly until end of year, to correct flaw that causes rails to ice over in winter; describes alternatives offered by Port Authority; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS air travel set a record earlier this summer -- with major domestic airlines flying fuller planes than at any time since World War II -- Newark Airport, the New York area's busiest, was putting its monorail on sick leave. The system was partly shut for repairs on July 8 and will be completely closed after Labor Day, possibly till the end of the year.</p>
        <p>The five-year-old monorail has been handling 30,000 people a day, getting them, their luggage and wheelchairs in from car-rental sites and parking lots, shifting them among the three terminals and returning them to drop-off spots. Now, according to John S. Jacoby, assistant manager of airport services for Newark, the contractor must repair a flaw that causes the rails to ice over in winter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS air travel set a record earlier this summer -- with major domestic airlines flying fuller planes than at any time since World War II -- Newark Airport, the New York area's busiest, was putting its monorail on sick leave. The system was partly shut for repairs on July 8 and will be completely closed after Labor Day, possibly till the end of the year.</p>
        <p>The five-year-old monorail has been handling 30,000 people a day, getting them, their luggage and wheelchairs in from car-rental sites and parking lots, shifting them among the three terminals and returning them to drop-off spots. Now, according to John S. Jacoby, assistant manager of airport services for Newark, the contractor must repair a flaw that causes the rails to ice over in winter.</p>
        <p>The problem was not happy news for Newark, the nation's 11th busiest airport, which handled 33.9 million passengers in the 12 months that ended April 30, as against Kennedy Airport's 32.2 million. Newark, already in the midst of construction projects affecting most of its 2,000 acres, decided to postpone the full shutdown until after the summer crush. Mr. Jacoby said it was hoped the repair could be completed in three months, but a return by Thanksgiving is doubtful, he said.</p>
        <p>The monorail is now serving only the central portion of its normal route, linking Terminals A, B and C and Station D-1, the site for Avis, Hertz and National, and some parking. It skips three stops: D-2, a site for Budget and Dollar and the pickup  spot for off-airport rental companies; D-3, a parking area, and E, which serves a parking area, vans from hotels and motels and off-airport parking, and valet parking. The stops not reached by the monorail  are served by 35 buses marked by construction-orange signs. After Labor Day, more than 50 buses will fill in.</p>
        <p>How Much Time to Allow</p>
        <p>The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, which operates the airport, suggests that travelers using Newark allow at least 30 minutes more travel time than their airline recommends; it is probably smart to add 15 minutes more to figure out what you are doing. Here is a little help:</p>
        <p>All air passengers must at some point rely on rubber-tired wheels to get to Kennedy, La Guardia or Newark; short of using a helicopter, it remains impossible to get all the way without risking traffic tie-ups.</p>
        <p>Until a new station links the Amtrak-New Jersey Transit rail lines to a new monorail station, planned for a year from now, Newark has the poorest junction with rapid transit. Most New Jerseyans get there by car, and Mr. Jacoby believes they prefer it that way.</p>
        <p>He says the airport has 16,000 parking spots, and 6,500 more are being created in two huge garages, one by Monorail Station E and one by Continental's Terminal C. These are expected to open next year. Construction, however, is tearing up existing lots in sequence, and Mr. Jacoby says it is impossible to say from day to day how many spaces are lost. Despite this, he says, lots are seldom entirely filled; the big complaint is that people cannot park where they want.</p>
        <p>On holidays, when business travel slows and leisure travel rises, the long-term economy lots can be swamped with vacationers seeking $8-a-day rates. Then, Mr. Jacoby said, drivers may be directed to spaces in daily lots, where they are given parking checks that entitle them to a bargain: $8 instead of $24 a day. When everything does fill, he said, directions are posted to private  areas off the airport. In such situations, Mr. Jacoby said, the operators may distribute discount coupons.</p>
        <p>Ideally, travelers using private cars should enlist someone to drop them off. The bad part of that plan is the return, when the pickup person must call to see if the plane is on time, which in May happened only 66.4 percent of the time at Newark.</p>
        <p>Another alternative is valet parking, at $18 a day. Customers tell the attendants when they are due back, and get a phone number to call with changes. The car is brought from a remote lot in time for the return.</p>
        <p>Families with children who want to use the cheaper lots should budget time for two loops through congested roadways. On the first, an adult should deposit everyone else and all the bags to start the check-in. Then the driver should park and ride the free bus back to the terminal.</p>
        <p>Setting Out From Manhattan</p>
        <p>Getting to Newark from the east shore of the Hudson usually involves taking a bus from the midtown Port Authority Bus Terminal, Penn Station or Grand Central. The timetable says Olympia Airport Express, but Coach USA now owns the company. The fare is $11 one way, $20 round trip. A round-trip fare of $10 is available to passengers displaying Medicare cards or New Jersey Transit Reduced Fare identification cards. Reduced-fare MetroCards with photos, used in the New York City transit system by senior citizens, are not recognized.</p>
        <p>The right terminal at Newark is not an automatic choice, particularly if you are flying Continental, which handles half of Newark's passengers. It has flights at Terminals A, B and C, depending on the destination.</p>
        <p>Its flights to Chicago, Atlanta and Dallas leave from Terminal A. Terminal B is the international arrivals building, but Continental's London flights leave from there. The majority of the line's flights use Terminal C, although pressure like this summer's can cause the line to shift to any available gate: on June 30, the line reported 89.7 percent of its seats were filled, a record. A system called code-sharing also confuses the issue because a flight sold under one airline's name may be flown by another line out of that line's gate.</p>
        <p>Gates 10 to 39 are in Terminal A. Gates 40 to 68 are in Terminal B. Gates 70 to 121 are in Terminal C.</p>
        <p>Until Labor Day, the monorail is the best way to travel between terminals. It runs on the outside curve of the three terminals at the concourse level, reached by escalators and elevators.</p>
        <p>It accommodates wheelchairs and luggage carts. (Domestic passengers pay $1.50 to rent carts; people coming through Customs get them free.) In two midday tests, monorails arrived pretty promptly.</p>
        <p>The bypass buses, by Jacoby design, do not pick up passengers while they discharge them: they pick up, go someplace and discharge, then start over.</p>
        <p>Bus arrivals are designed to be five minutes apart. These buses are boarded in the outdoor bus bays to the left of each terminal as you exit.  The buses are tied into a global positioning system using satellites so that dispatchers can direct them  where they are needed.</p>
        <p>The buses frequently have luggage racks, but luggage carts cannot be rolled aboard, as they can onto the monorail. So passengers using bypass buses will have to cough up another $1.50 for a new cart. Wheelchairs also cannot go aboard the buses. Red-jacketed customer service representatives call for wheelchair-accessible vans.</p>
        <p>Meantime, despite the dust and mud outside, the inside of Terminal C presents a much improved environment. Staples, Speedo, the Museum Company, the Discovery Channel and other places to buy things you might want or need have opened in recent months.</p>
        <p>A counter that sells CD's is just outside the Continental Young Travelers Club, where children traveling alone await connecting flights if their parents pay a fee of $60 or more. On a recent Tuesday, eight young people were inside watching television; the Garden State Diner was S.R.O.</p>
        <p>Sets of benches have been placed at the marked meeting spots for limosine drivers; considering Newark's record for delays, it seems like a humane gesture.</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
