<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Loosening Up at Lord &amp; Taylor</title>
    <meta content="13PROF$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRIVATE SECTOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business and Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Jane T. Elfers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">May Department Stores Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lord &amp; Taylor</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elfers, Jane T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7DE153FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="978" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Loosening Up at Lord &amp; Taylor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article spotlights Jane T Elfers, head of May Department Stores division Lord &amp; Taylor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALTHOUGH dressed in a flowing, almost-formal black pants outfit by Yeohlee, Jane T. Elfers, the 39-year-old merchant promoted recently to be president of Lord &amp; Taylor, says she is instituting a new more relaxed dress code for executives -- and that she is leading by example. ''See?'' she said, jovially pointing to her feet, which were stuffed into a pair of pointed black pumps. ''No hose.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Elfers took the helm of Lord &amp; Taylor, a division of May Department Stores, in June, facing a tide of disappointing sales. Still, she has made it clear that she plans no sharp shift in strategy for this venerable retailer. Her incremental loosening of the dress code is a sign of her approach: an oh-so-gentle movement of the stores to a younger, funkier market, she has demonstrated, will be the hallmark of her tenure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALTHOUGH dressed in a flowing, almost-formal black pants outfit by Yeohlee, Jane T. Elfers, the 39-year-old merchant promoted recently to be president of Lord &amp; Taylor, says she is instituting a new more relaxed dress code for executives -- and that she is leading by example. ''See?'' she said, jovially pointing to her feet, which were stuffed into a pair of pointed black pumps. ''No hose.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Elfers took the helm of Lord &amp; Taylor, a division of May Department Stores, in June, facing a tide of disappointing sales. Still, she has made it clear that she plans no sharp shift in strategy for this venerable retailer. Her incremental loosening of the dress code is a sign of her approach: an oh-so-gentle movement of the stores to a younger, funkier market, she has demonstrated, will be the hallmark of her tenure.</p>
        <p>''You are going to see a lot of new, young and exciting designers,'' she said, ''but I think loyal customers will still be very comfortable with us.''</p>
        <p>By consensus, Ms. Elfers treads a delicate path. On one hand, much of Lord &amp; Taylor's charm comes from being among the last of the grand-dame Fifth Avenue stores to maintain its old-world ambience: the dressing rooms are clean and spacious, the staff is shockingly courteous and the merchandise is capaciously spaced.</p>
        <p>But its genteel atmosphere has also been a weakness in the increasingly competitive and vamped-up retail world. In the women's sportswear department, for example, the background music is more likely to be easy listening (think Chris Cross), where at Bloomingdale's, shoppers might be blasted with 'N Sync. Such ambiance has helped give Lord &amp; Taylor a reputation in the industry and among some shoppers for being out of touch with what is young and hip -- a potentially deadly faux pas in the retail world.</p>
        <p>Lacking clout with the profitable juniors market, the chain's 79 stores have seen sales per square foot decline from $237 in 1997 to $218 last year, as much of the rest of retailing was seeing a spectacular boom. Total sales have also suffered as the chain has relied heavily on markdowns to entice shoppers. ''They've trained their customers to play the coupon game,'' said Candace Corlett, a partner at WSL Strategic Retail, a consulting firm based in New York. ''You can see new-season merchandise and know that you will get it on sale with a coupon within the season. It is a self-defeating strategy.''</p>
        <p>Pressure for Lord &amp; Taylor to right itself has been compounded this year as May, which has been a smooth operator of chains including Foley's and Filene's, has stumbled. While Federated Department Stores, a big rival, has delivered strong sales increases, May's growth has been so disappointing that, according to First Call/Thomson Financial, stock analysts' consensus estimate for annual earnings has continued to drop.</p>
        <p>But Lord &amp; Taylor, which has been around for 174 years, has a loyal customer base that might be alienated by too much updating. ''If you look at the demographics of Lord &amp; Taylor, they are older,'' said Shari Schwartzman Eberts, a stock analyst at J. P. Morgan Securities. ''Of all the formats, they need to be the purest to the tradition  of the brand name,'' she said.</p>
        <p>If gradual change is the best path, the genial Ms. Elfers appears well suited for the job, by both temperament and training. Ms. Elfers grew up in Ho-Ho-Kus, N.J., and inherited her interest in the trade from her father, Thomas H. Taylor, who was a marketing executive at Sears. She graduated from Bucknell Univeristy in 1983 with a business degree and joined Lord &amp; Taylor in 1989 as a buyer.</p>
        <p>For the next 11 years, Ms. Elfers rose within the organization, which has a reputation for rewarding efficacy rather than revolutionary thinking. Her latest post was executive vice president  with responsibility for dresses, suits, sportswear, coats and accessories.</p>
        <p>At 39, Ms. Elfers is one of the youngest top executives in the business;  many of the stock analysts who follow May were unfamiliar with her record. She says Lord &amp; Taylor's problem is not so much that it attracts older customers, but that it is perceived that way. ''The younger customer is in the store,'' Ms. Elfers said. ''My job is to position Lord &amp; Taylor's image to make it more obvious that she is here'' -- without, of course, forgetting about its more traditional customers.</p>
        <p>A new campaign will begin soon, focusing on direct mail advertisements with modern, colorful presentations of more fashionable merchandise. For newspapers, the chain will keep its distinctive, classic pen-and-ink ads of women with tiny upswooped noses.</p>
        <p>ALL of that is not to say that Ms. Elfers is just starting a public relations campaign. She is changing the merchandise mix to appeal to a trendier customer. This spring, she introduced Betsey Johnson, a wild woman of fashion known for pushing the more outlandish colors and styles. She also added young contemporary collections by French Connection and Nine West Sportswear, as well as more offerings from the suddenly hot designer copycat genius, ABS by Allen B. Schwartz. In lingerie, amid the staid Maidenform bras and panties, there are now Lilly of France changeable bra straps in animal print and hot magenta. Coming soon to the shoe department will be teen-friendly Skechers.</p>
        <p>But such tweaking may not be enough in a roughly competitive, fast-cycling fashion environment.</p>
        <p>''If Wal-Mart and H &amp; M are setting the shopping culture,'' pondered Ms. Corlett, herself a loyal shopper, ''is there still a place for Lord &amp; Taylor? I hope so.''</p>
        <p>PRIVATE SECTOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
