<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bitter Rivals Leaving Town As They Feud Over Money</title>
    <meta content="13REFO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REFORM PARTIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reform Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ayres, B Drummond Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buchanan, Patrick J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hagelin, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6DF133FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bitter Rivals Leaving Town As They Feud Over Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr. and MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael; Ayres, B Drummond Jr</byline>
      <dateline>LONG BEACH, Calif., Aug. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reform Party limps out of town as two parties, each with its own ideology and nominee, after fractious national convention in Long Beach, Calif; both sides lay claim to party name, and to $12.6 million in federal campaign money; court battle can be expected between faction headed by Patrick J Buchanan and faction headed by John Hagelin; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Battered and sundered into competing factions, the Reform Party fought through the final hours of a bitter national convention today, then limped out of town as two parties, each with its own ideology and nominee.</p>
        <p>Both laid claim to the Reform Party name. But other than that, about the only thing they shared was a highly questionable future and the strong likelihood that they would end up in a campaign-crimping court battle this fall over the original party's remains and $12.6 million in federal campaign money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Battered and sundered into competing factions, the Reform Party fought through the final hours of a bitter national convention today, then limped out of town as two parties, each with its own ideology and nominee.</p>
        <p>Both laid claim to the Reform Party name. But other than that, about the only thing they shared was a highly questionable future and the strong likelihood that they would end up in a campaign-crimping court battle this fall over the original party's remains and $12.6 million in federal campaign money.</p>
        <p>Gone from this raucous four-day affair was the commanding presence of Ross Perot, who founded the Reform Party eight years ago and, with his rapid-fire talk of changing the federal bureaucracy, briefly made it a potent political force. A couple of years ago, when he sensed that the country, grown economically fat and seemingly content, had lost its appetite for him and political reform, he cut his ties to the party.</p>
        <p>It came hard aground here in Long Beach this week and broke in two. Try as they might, party officials could not put it back together.</p>
        <p>Patrick J. Buchanan, the former Republican presidential contender, took one part.</p>
        <p>John Hagelin, a soft-spoken perennial candidate who usually runs under the banner of the Natural Law Party, took the other.</p>
        <p>''At long last we have a home of our own,'' Mr. Buchanan said today after his faction chose him as its nominee. ''And this party we are building together is being built to last.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hagelin struck a similar note in his acceptance speech. ''This is your party,'' he told his cheering followers. ''Breathe strength into it. Grow it into America's next major party.''</p>
        <p>Beyond that, the two men agreed on nothing except perhaps the need for fair trade. They accused each other of just about every sin under the political sun, especially of trying to steal the party away.</p>
        <p>For a running mate, Mr. Buchanan on Friday selected Ezola Foster, a conservative black educator from Los Angeles, while Mr. Hagelin announced this afternoon that his choice was Nat Goldhaber, a multimedia executive and venture capitalist from Berkeley, Calif.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Buchanan saw it, when he joined the party last spring it was hardly a party at all. He said his presence would reinvigorate it, dismissing Mr. Hagelin as a political nobody.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Hagelin's view, Mr. Buchanan was a brazen opportunist on the down side of a political career seeking merely to further his own conservative social agenda. This agenda is crowded with hot-button issues like abortion, gun control and affirmative action, which Mr. Hagelin argued the party had always avoided.</p>
        <p>Both men arrived in Long Beach  intent on using the dispirited party as their vehicle to run for the presidency. The eventual nominee would get $12.6 million in federal campaign money for the fall run.</p>
        <p>Never mind that many national polls had Mr. Buchanan pulling less than 2 percent of the popular vote and Mr. Hagelin less than 1 percent. Or, as Russell Verney, who helped Mr. Perot found the party in 1992, put it in one of the few humorous moments of the week: ''It's a close one, all right. John Hagelin is within one point of Pat Buchanan.''</p>
        <p>The competition between the two men grew so intense and angry that they convened separate conventions and nominating processes in adjacent convention halls.</p>
        <p>Mr. Buchanan ended up with more delegates than Mr. Hagelin -- mainly, it appeared, because he had seized control of party machinery in many states with the help of the ''Buchanan Brigades'' from his earlier presidential runs. Mr. Hagelin accused the Brigades of having used everything from fraud to plain sneakiness to take over state organizations. He filed a complaint with the Federal Election Commission and said he would go to court if necessary to prove that he was Mr. Perot's deserving successor.</p>
        <p>In accepting his nomination tonight, Mr. Buchanan talked of ''new reforms,'' but they had little to do with changing government. Rather, he repeated what he has been demanding for the better part of a decade -- outlawing abortion, reining in ''arrogant, unelected judges, ending racial quotas and preferences.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hagelin talked reform and only reform in his acceptance speech. He also invoked Mr. Perot's name and memory.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot is still a hero to many Reformers. But since he cut off contact with the party -- he has seldom mentioned it publicly in almost two years -- there has been no grass-roots push to bring him back. The impression is that many party members are thankful for his contribution but feel that he has had his run.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REFORM PARTIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
