<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a Size 22 to a String Bikini</title>
    <meta content="13WEIG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MILESTONES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jenny Craig Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivera, Grisela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3DF163FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a Size 22 to a String Bikini</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Grisela Rivera, native of Venezuela, who has gone from 200 pounds to 150 with help of Jenny Craig weight-loss program in White Plains, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are women for whom weight is not an issue, for whom extra pounds are at worst an annoyance, not a self-image-threatening disaster. Grisela Rivera, a 31-year-old telephone cable splicer, is not one of them.</p>
        <p>As she tells it, she ''lived in the mirror'' -- although she hated what she saw.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are women for whom weight is not an issue, for whom extra pounds are at worst an annoyance, not a self-image-threatening disaster. Grisela Rivera, a 31-year-old telephone cable splicer, is not one of them.</p>
        <p>As she tells it, she ''lived in the mirror'' -- although she hated what she saw.</p>
        <p>Somehow, she was compelled to keep taking peeks, even stopping at shop windows to catch a glimpse of herself in the glass.</p>
        <p>Although people told her she had a beautiful face -- perfectly arched brows over big expressive eyes, a winning smile -- she was only 5 foot 3 and weighed 200 pounds.</p>
        <p>In January, the self-loathing got to be too much. She signed up for a weight-loss program. Now, six months later, she is 50 pounds lighter and feels like ''literally a new person.''</p>
        <p>''This has been a journey,'' she said at the Jenny Craig center here, where she is enrolled. ''I see I can change. I can create a new me.''</p>
        <p>Last month, a study at the University of Wisconsin was released suggesting that obesity may be triggered by a virus. Ms. Rivera is having none of that.</p>
        <p>''I liked to eat,'' she said. ''I always let myself eat whatever I wanted: French toast, bacon and eggs for breakfast; a big sandwich and French fries at lunch; steak with mashed potatoes and gravy at dinner. Now I eat five or six smaller, portion-controlled, balanced meals and snacks a day. It's about learning to take control of my life.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rivera, who lives in the northeast Bronx, was born in Venezuela. Her family came to the Bronx when she was a child and she went to public and then private schools. In junior high, when adolescents are perhaps their cruelest, she was teased about her heavy legs. In high school, she weighed 150 pounds, and the ribbing continued, although in a more subtle way.</p>
        <p>In high school, she recalled, she was lucky to be in the ''in'' crowd despite her weight.</p>
        <p>''I was confident on the outside, I had an outgoing personality, so my friends didn't realize how much I was hurting. And then, of course, in America, you keep seeing all of these ultra-thin models, pictures of totally skinny women. In Venezuela at least it's not considered a negative to be curvy, like I am. But in America, everyone wants to be rail thin.''</p>
        <p>After attending St. John's University in Jamaica, Queens, she got jobs with the phone company. She also had a baby, Antonio, who is now 2. The pregnancy put weight on, but it was an emotional wake-up call as well.</p>
        <p>''At my heaviest, at my worst,'' she said, ''I'd sit and cry and not even want to go out. Then suddenly I realized, I love this baby so much, how can I give this baby the love he needs when I don't feel love for myself. In order to really love him, I had to love me as well.''</p>
        <p>At Jenny Craig, she had sessions with a counselor, Amybeth Johnsen. They went over menus (a typical series of meals and snacks might be an oat bar and nonfat milk, an oatmeal cookie, a pan pizza with eight olives, mesquite-grilled chicken and a cup of flavored yogurt -- a far cry from her previous daily intake.) They discussed what weight loss meant on an emotional level. And they even compared notes on having babies -- Ms. Johnsen is six months' pregnant.</p>
        <p>On a recent day, they also conducted a kind of informal retrospective. Ms. Rivera, having just reached her desired weight, is now on a maintenance program that integrates her own foods with the prescribed ones. Ms. Johnsen went over some options with her, then took the conversation to a more emotional level:</p>
        <p>''Do you remember what you were like that first day you came in here?'' she asked. ''You were shy, quiet. Now you're radiant and confident.''</p>
        <p>''I was tired of being heavy,'' Ms. Rivera said, then suddenly pulled a tissue out of her bag and began sniffing back tears. ''I wanted to do better. I wanted to do something for myself, and now I have.''</p>
        <p>She dabbed at her eyes, tossed the tissue in a wastebasket. ''You know what I did? I threw out my big clothes. I gave them all away. I was a size 22; now I'm a size 6. Can you believe it? And you know what else I did?'' A big grin. ''I bought a brightly colored string bikini, and if I say so myself, I look pretty good in it.''</p>
        <p>MILESTONES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
