<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Workouts That Fit the Lives Of Harried Commuters</title>
    <meta content="13HEAL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Clubs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Larchmont (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Sports Club</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Town Sports International</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Worth, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4D61F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Workouts That Fit the Lives Of Harried Commuters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT WORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Worth, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>LARCHMONT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Sports Club and Town Sports, which have been opening outlets near train stations in New York metropolitan area suburbs in hopes of attracting commuters; scene at Sports Club's new outlet in Larchmont described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY weekday evening, as the northbound train stops at Larchmont and exhales a crowd of weary commuters, a dozen or so head for the New York Sports Club less than a quarter mile away.</p>
        <p>This has become a ritual at stations along the suburban lines that fan out from Manhattan near which two major fitness club chains have been building or buying facilities over the last five years. Operating clubs in the city as well as the suburbs, the chains hope to lure commuters by offering a choice of exercise in either spot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY weekday evening, as the northbound train stops at Larchmont and exhales a crowd of weary commuters, a dozen or so head for the New York Sports Club less than a quarter mile away.</p>
        <p>This has become a ritual at stations along the suburban lines that fan out from Manhattan near which two major fitness club chains have been building or buying facilities over the last five years. Operating clubs in the city as well as the suburbs, the chains hope to lure commuters by offering a choice of exercise in either spot.</p>
        <p>''It's definitely an urban-suburban strategy,'' said Alex Alimanestianu, chief development officer for Town Sports International, the owner of New York Sports Clubs, the largest chain in the New York area. ''We've built our cluster of clubs with a view to putting them where people live and work in a defined geographic area.''</p>
        <p>Town Sports, which operates 70 clubs in the New York metropolitan region, has bought clubs close to the train stations and major highways in Scarsdale, Larchmont, Mamaroneck, White Plains and Croton. Mr. Alimanestianu said that it was hard to find space close to train stations, but the rents were reasonable ''because retailers generally want to be on the main street.''</p>
        <p>Town Sports also owns clubs close to Penn Station and Grand Central Terminal to give commuters the option of exercising before they catch the train.</p>
        <p>''That's really been a cardinal principle of our site selection,'' he said. ''In any suburban location we want to be close to the transportation hubs, be they bus or train lines or the PATH train in New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>Bally Total Fitness, the nation's largest health club chain, has used the same approach. The company owns 40 clubs in the vicinity of New York City, including three in Westchester, and plans to build more.</p>
        <p>''We locate clubs where they can fit into the lives of members most naturally,'' said David Southern, an executive vice president at Bally.</p>
        <p>Studies have shown that health clubs draw 90 percent of their membership within a 10-  to 15-minute walking distance, said Bill Howland, director of research at the International Health, Racquet and Sports Club Association, a nonprofit group that tracks the industry.</p>
        <p>''This club is on my route,'' said Valerie Kirby, a dark-haired woman in a blue Nike workout suit, as she pumped her arms back and forth on a Lifefitness crosstrainer at the New York Sports Club in Larchmont.</p>
        <p>A banker with NatWest, Ms. Krauss said she catches the 5:13 train from Grand Central to Larchmont, then walks down the hill past the club on her way home. ''I'd rather go here than in the city, where I'm not sure I'll get to the train on time,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Like most commuters, Ms. Krauss has a narrow window for exercise. She has to be home by 7, when the nanny who takes care of her two children leaves. (The nanny, who is also a club member, then comes the Larchmont club for her own workout.) The club's site near the train station and just off Interstate 95 allows her to exercise without going out of her way.</p>
        <p>If her schedule changes and she is left with free time in the city, she can use another of the club's outlets, a few blocks from her office at 41st and Park Avenue. Her husband is also a member, she said, and he prefers to use one of the city outlets.</p>
        <p>So many of the Larchmont club's members are commuters that the train times dictate the ebb and flow of people here, the club's fitness manager, Geoffrey Braham, said.</p>
        <p>''With the train schedule, you kind of know -- the 6:31 pulls in, and you get a lot of people,'' Mr. Braham said.</p>
        <p>''I can see five or six people who took the train out here with me,'' said Kermit Patterson, a burly college student from Larchmont who is spending the summer working for an investment bank in the city and spends two hours at the club every day after work.</p>
        <p>The Larchmont club is typical in another sense: it was owned by an independent operator until New York Sports bought it and remodeled it two years ago.</p>
        <p>Although health clubs remain a highly fragmented industry, several large chains, including Town Sports and Bally, have been aggressively buying up independent clubs and smaller chains. Of the roughly 12,500 commercial clubs in the United States, 30 to 40 percent are owned by chains, up from about 25 percent five years ago, said Rick Devereux, director of operations at the international sports club association.</p>
        <p>The expanding suburban market has accelerated the pace of consolidation, because unlike their competitors, the chains can offer members the choice of a workout in any of dozens of regional facilities. All of New York Sports' membership plans, which run from $67 to $83 a month with initiation fees of between $149 and $199, allow members access to all the company's clubs, said Jodie Meltzer, the Westchester area manager for Town Sports.</p>
        <p>''It is a leveragable selling feature if you can say we can take care of you in Manhattan and in Rye,'' Mr. Howland said.</p>
        <p>Town Sports built its first suburban club in Great Neck on Long Island in 1986, Mr. Alimanestianu said. ''We noticed pretty quickly that people joining in the city were using the Great Neck club and people in Great Neck were using the city locations,'' Mr. Alimanestianu said. Half of Town Sports' 100 locations nationwide are now in suburbs.</p>
        <p>The company's expansion did not take off, however, until the mid- 1990's, when health club membership soared, fueled by the economic boom and the growing popularity of cardiovascular exercise.</p>
        <p>Club membership soared to 30.6 million members nationwide in 1999, from 20.7 million in 1990, reported Harvey Lauer, president of American Sports Data of Hartsdale, a company that specializes in sports and fitness research.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
