<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/Long Island; Filling the Area's Need for Large Conference Centers</title>
    <meta content="13LIZO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Huntington Station (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Huntington Townhouse</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hilton Hotels Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Marriott Hotels</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wyndham Hotel Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaman, Diana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silver, Rhonda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Manno, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4DF173FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/Long Island; Filling the Area's Need for Large Conference Centers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA SHAMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shaman, Diana</byline>
      <dateline>HUNTINGTON STATION</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Filling the Area's Need for Large Conf</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 148,000-square-foot New Huntington Townhouse here on Jericho Turnpike just east of Route 110 provides banquet space that no other Long Island caterer can match in size.</p>
        <p>It has a total of eight ballrooms. Five on the second floor have rollback walls that can create a 24,000-square-foot grand ballroom measuring 60 feet by 400 feet. It can seat 3,000 people and can handle 5,000 people for stand-up parties. A ramp at the rear of the building leads to the second floor, allowing tractor-trailers to drive into the ballroom. This means that it can also be used for trade shows and exhibition space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 148,000-square-foot New Huntington Townhouse here on Jericho Turnpike just east of Route 110 provides banquet space that no other Long Island caterer can match in size.</p>
        <p>It has a total of eight ballrooms. Five on the second floor have rollback walls that can create a 24,000-square-foot grand ballroom measuring 60 feet by 400 feet. It can seat 3,000 people and can handle 5,000 people for stand-up parties. A ramp at the rear of the building leads to the second floor, allowing tractor-trailers to drive into the ballroom. This means that it can also be used for trade shows and exhibition space.</p>
        <p>In all, the Townhouse, glittering with chandeliers and mirrors and gilded furniture, has 100,000 square feet of banquet and exhibition space, along with parking for 2,000 cars and gardens for outdoor parties on its 20-acre site. The remaining 48,000 square feet in the building are used for offices and other support services.</p>
        <p>But one thing the Townhouse lacks is a conference center and hotel rooms. And now Rhona Silver, who bought the property three years ago for $7.6 million from the estate of its original owner, Thomas Manno, is negotiating with several large hotel chains, including Hilton, Marriott and Wyndham, to build a 244-room hotel and conference center of up to 58,000 square feet next to the existing building.</p>
        <p>The proposed project, which would be built on what is now a parking lot on the eastern part of the property, was approved by the Town of Huntington when Mr. Manno was still the owner.</p>
        <p>Because of the strong economy, Long Island's hotel business has been thriving. What is lacking, business leaders say, is a major conference center with at least 60,000 square feet of meeting and exhibition space, combined with on-site hotel rooms.</p>
        <p>''There is no question that we have done a tremendous job in attracting midsize conventions, but we can't attract the larger ones if we don't have the facilities,'' said Mitchell Pally, the vice president for legislative and economic affairs at the Long Island Association, a nonprofit business group that has its offices in Commack. ''We have a variety of hotels, and we have a variety of large meeting places, but we don't have a place that offers both together.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Silver, who comes from a catering  background -- her parents, Pearl and Alvin Silver, now retired, ran a catering service in the Bronx and more recently in Cedarhurst -- said that when she bought the Townhouse, other investors who were also considering it held back because of ongoing controversy over the rebuilding of the nearby Walt Whitman Mall, which been damaged by a major fire in 1991.</p>
        <p>''I looked at the Huntington Townhouse from the point of view of a caterer, not a real estate developer, and what I could do with it as a catering hall,'' said Ms. Silver, whose husband, Elliot, and their two children, Matthew and Rebecca, help run the business.</p>
        <p>Under her ownership, the Townhouse has undergone some preliminary renovations: new carpeting and bathrooms, a new air-conditioning system and a new roof have been installed, and the gardens have been relandscaped.</p>
        <p>The access ramp to the grand ballroom on the second floor is vital to trade shows. For example, the Nassau-Suffolk Landscapers Association, which took over the entire building for two days in March, was able to exhibit gardens complete with waterfalls and ornamental ponds, along with dozens of pieces of large equipment that included backhoes, dump trucks and tractors.</p>
        <p>As part of one of the more spectacular weddings, the bride and bridgegroom arrived in the grand ballroom in a coach drawn by two white horses, a touch that added another $1,000 to the $40,000 affair. (On another occasion, the newlyweds plopped down on the lawn in front of their assembled guests in a hot-air balloon.)</p>
        <p>Once hotel rooms are added at the Townhouse, Ms. Silver said, ''we expect our business to double.'' ''We plan to turn the Townhouse into not just a catering facility but one where you can hold economic summits and conferences,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Under a preliminary design prepared by Brennan Beer Gorman Architects in Manhattan, the 58,000-square-foot conference center would connect the four-story hotel  and the existing building. Each of the three buildings would have its own entrance.</p>
        <p>''The Huntington Townhouse right now is basically a wedding palace,'' said Mario La Guardia, a partner in Brennan Beer Gorman. ''The conference center will service the corporations along Route 110 and Long Island as a whole.'' He estimated that the new building, as proposed, would cost around $50 million.</p>
        <p>Last year was a record for Long Island's  hotel business, said Robert Lipper, who owns Island-Metro Publications in Farmingdale, a company that tracks the local hotel industry.</p>
        <p>The overall occupancy rate last year stood at 79.3 percent, 3.5 million room nights were sold, and the average room rate for the fiscal year ending May 31 was $130 a night, he said.</p>
        <p>According to his figures, the region has  about 340 hotels, motels and B&amp;B's with a total of around 15,000 rooms, but only about 80 of those, with a total of 6,000 rooms, are corporate-level hotel accommodations.</p>
        <p>THREE limited-service hotels, without restaurants or pools, opened last year, two others are under construction, and others are planned. Mr. Lipper said, ''I tell developers, 'If you're going to build more hotel rooms, build them now, not five years from now because by then we might be over-hotelled and financing will be more difficult to get.' ''</p>
        <p>If the Townhouse project moves forward, it will be important ''for the entire region,'' said Dennis Sneden, the chief executive officer of the 1,000-member Huntington Chamber of Commerce.</p>
        <p>Several of the region's full-service hotels have the meeting and exhibition space combined with hotel rooms that some out-of-town groups are seeking, but they do not have the 60,000 square feet of meeting, banquet and exhibition space that some of the conventions need.</p>
        <p>The largest meeting spaces now offered by full-service hotels are 27,000 square feet at the 617-room Long Island Marriott Hotel and Conference Center in Uniondale; 23,000 square feet at the 200-room Harrison Conference Center in Glen Cove; and 21,000 square feet at the 371-room Melville Marriott.</p>
        <p>Although 60,000 square feet of exhibition and meeting space is available on a lower level at the Nassau Veterans Memorial Coliseum in Uniondale, the arena is best known for sports events and other entertainment rather than as a convention center.</p>
        <p>A 260,000-square-foot multipurpose building with a 60,000-square-foot field house that will be available for public trade shows and conferences is scheduled to open next month at the Brentwood campus of Suffolk County Community College. But groups booking there will have to find lodgings elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''It is important to have sleeping rooms attached to large space because of the logistics,'' said Anjali Poorswani, a senior associate at HVS International, a hotel consultant in Mineola. ''It's not like New York,  where you can take a taxicab to your hotel.''</p>
        <p>Michael Hollander, the president of the Long Island Convention &amp; Visitors Bureau,  in Hauppauge, estimated that 25 groups went elsewhere last year ''because we didn't have the space they wanted.''</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, the Forrestal Princeton Conference Center has 30,000 square feet of meeting and banquet space, plus 291 guest rooms, a sports center and other recreation, and in Rye Brook, N.Y., in Westchester County, the Doral Arrowwood Conference Center has 27,600 square feet of meeting space, 272 hotel rooms and a nine-hole golf course.</p>
        <p>These are just two examples of conference centers in the area that compete for the same convention business, ''It's not just places on Long Island that compete with each other,'' said Mr. Lipper of Island-Metro Publications.</p>
        <p>Carmen Marmosavinetti, the director for meetings and conventions at the visitors bureau, said her work was greatly hampered by the lack of a major convention center.</p>
        <p>The National Auctioneers Association, for example, had approached her six months ago. ''They really wanted to have their conference on Long Island because of the proximity to New York City,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The conference would have lasted a week and would have generated over $1 million for the local economy, she said. But the group needed about 60,000 square feet for its 2005 convention along with 600 hotel rooms for its 1,500 conference participants.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't sell them on the idea of bringing people in to multiple properties,'' Mrs. Marmosavinetti said. Instead, the group will hold its convention in Hershey, Pa.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
