<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="13GUID$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3DB1F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>Balloons shaped like shopping bags, polar bears, bunnies and apples take flight in Waldbaum's Balloon and Music Festival in Shirley. While the 75 hot-air balloons that go up at 6:30 p.m. Friday and 6:30 a.m. and 6.30 p.m. Saturday and next Sunday give the event its special appeal, basically it's a family affair, with daytime activities like performances by the National Marionette Theater, a Paul Bunyan Lumberjack Show and a Fire Jump High Dive. The evenings feature concerts at 8 o'clock by Chubby Checker and Mary Wilson and the Supremes on Friday and the Beach Boys on Saturday, and the Summer X Jam Concert with BBMak, Bosson and Take 5 on Sunday. The festival is from 1 p.m. to 10 p.m. Friday and 6 a.m. to 10 p.m. Saturday and Sunday at Brookhaven-Calabro Airport on William Floyd Parkway (888) 994-6824.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>Balloons shaped like shopping bags, polar bears, bunnies and apples take flight in Waldbaum's Balloon and Music Festival in Shirley. While the 75 hot-air balloons that go up at 6:30 p.m. Friday and 6:30 a.m. and 6.30 p.m. Saturday and next Sunday give the event its special appeal, basically it's a family affair, with daytime activities like performances by the National Marionette Theater, a Paul Bunyan Lumberjack Show and a Fire Jump High Dive. The evenings feature concerts at 8 o'clock by Chubby Checker and Mary Wilson and the Supremes on Friday and the Beach Boys on Saturday, and the Summer X Jam Concert with BBMak, Bosson and Take 5 on Sunday. The festival is from 1 p.m. to 10 p.m. Friday and 6 a.m. to 10 p.m. Saturday and Sunday at Brookhaven-Calabro Airport on William Floyd Parkway (888) 994-6824.</p>
        <p>'Wine Weekend'</p>
        <p>Just in case Long Islanders (and off-Islanders) haven't heard about eastern Long Island's growing importance in wine production, the Long Island Wine Council sponsoring a Wine Weekend 2000 on Friday through next Sunday. The event begins on Friday at 6:30 p.m. at Wolffer Estate Vineyards in Sagaponack with an art and wine seminar, ''Terroir -- Not for Wine Alone,'' and continues Saturday and Sunday with themed tastings and tours of 12 vineyards on the North Fork. These include ''Winemaking for Dummies'' from 1 p.m. to 3 p.m. at Ternhaven Cellars, Greenport (631) 369-5887.</p>
        <p>Some Folk</p>
        <p>Folk music of various stripes dominates the music scene this week.</p>
        <p>Today, from noon to 6 p.m., the Long Island Traditional Music Association holds its Long Island Fiddle Jamboree, led by Kenny Kosek, the bluegrass and western swing fiddler-singer, at the Brush Barn in Smithtown (631) 385-7363. Buddy Merriam and Backroads appear at 6:45 p.m. on Wednesday on Agawam Park in Southampton (631) 287-4377, and Peter, Paul and Mary play the Westbury Music Fair at 8 p.m. on Friday (516) 334-0800.</p>
        <p>In ethnic folk concerts, Croabh Rua plays Irish tunes at 3 p.m. today at Hallockville in Riverhead (631) 298-9782. It's Pakistani-American Night tomorrow at 8 p.m. at Eisenhower Park in East Meadow (516) 572-0252, while Paddy Noonan's Irish Merrymakers perform at 7 p.m. Tuesday at the Freeport Library (516) 379-3274. On Saturday, Scandinavian-American Night comes to Eisenhower Park at 8 p.m.; Regina Kujawa and Misha and Natasha Smirnova perform Slavic music and dance at 8:15 p.m. at Morgan Park in Glen Cove (516) 759-4581, and the Westbury Music Fair is host to ''Reggae Summerfest 2000'' at 8 p.m. (516) 334-0800.</p>
        <p>'Mask Project'</p>
        <p>Created as a fund-raiser in Tel Aviv and used later in London, Denver and San Francisco, the Mask Project has arrived on the Island. Some 500 masks, created by artists like Joe Reboli and celebrities like Katie Couric, J. Murray Abraham, Marty Lyons and Chris Mullin, will be on display through the fall at galleries like Hands on Clay and Gallery North in Setauket; the Gayle Willson Gallery in Southampton; the Long Island Childrens Museum in Garden City; and the Soundview Art Gallery in Port Jefferson. The works will be sold through an Internet auction (www.nymaskproject.com) and in person at a concluding gala on Oct. 15 at the Mall at the Source in Westbury. Sales will benefit the home care and hospice services of the Catholic Health Services of Long Island (877) 895-6275.</p>
        <p>Charitable Sports</p>
        <p>Either playing or watching, sporty Long Islanders who want to be charitable have three chances this week.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, golfers (and/or watchers) can take in the New York Jets and Friends Lobster-Clambake Golf Classic at the Long Island National Golf Club in Riverhead. The day, to benefit United Cerebral Palsy of Greater Suffolk, includes 18 holes of golf with such Jets as Marty Lyons, Gerry Philbin and Bobby Jackson; lunch; on-course refreshments like a ''margarita station''; contests and an auction. Golfers pay $350; watchers $175 (631) 232-0015. In Commack, at the Hamlet Golf and Country Club, the Hamlet Cup, a kind of preview of things to come in tennis at the United States Open, begins on Saturday and runs through Aug. 27 with such would-be champs as Patrick Rafter, Yevgeny Kafelnikov and Jan-Michael Gambill vying for $850,000 in prize money. The Interfaith Nutrition Network and Inner City Games-New York gain from the admission of $10 to $30 (631) 462-2600.</p>
        <p>Finally, on Saturday in East Hampton, celebrities on the East End take to the soft-ball field at Herrick Park at 3 p.m. for the annual Artists and Writers Game. The early lineup includes regulars like Ken Auletta, William Baldwin, Bill Beutel, Ben Bradlee, Ed Burns, Ken Burns, Mike Lupica and Roy Scheider. The $8 admission goes to the Retreat, East End Hospice and East Hampton Day Care (631) 725-1294.</p>
        <p>Shall They Dance?</p>
        <p>Dance dominates the final week of the Huntington Arts Council's 2000 Summer Arts Festival. The Commack-based New York Dance Theater, with Nicole Loizides of Momix and Abraham Miha of the Hartford Ballet as guest stars, gets things started today with a ballet program that includes pas de deux from ''Don Quixote'' and ''Le Corsaire'' and a work set to a Rodgers-Hammerstein medley. On Thursday, the Saltaire Foundation for the Arts takes over with the Shakespeare Project, an exploration of the plays through dance and music. With speech, sound, mime and dance set to a jazz score by the D. D. Jackson Trio, on Friday  Dave Gonzalez recreates Orpheus's  search for Eurydice, and ''Delgadina,'' a Chilean magic tale, in ''Mytholojazz.''</p>
        <p>Finally, on Saturday, Donald Byrd/the Group arrive at Heckscher Park with Jazz Train, a dance-dance theater work. All performances are at 8:30 p.m. (631) 271-8423.</p>
        <p>Classic Comedy</p>
        <p>For its final entry of the season, the Bay Street Theater goes back to the classics -- the American classics, that is -- with ''You Can't Take It With You,'' the 1936 Pulitzer prize-winning play by Moss Hart and George S. Kaufman. Directed by Jack Hofsiss, the comedy about an eccentric family's encounter with members of the Wall Street establishment, sports a cast of 17 that includes such familiar veteran actors as Mason Adams, Joan Copeland, Penny Fuller and Larry Keith. The play opens Wednesday and runs through Sept. 3 (631) 725-9500.</p>
        <p>Namuth Portraits</p>
        <p>The success the late Hans Namuth achieved taking more than 500 ''action'' photographs of Jackson Pollock at work in his studio lead the photographer to a new artistic direction. He began snapping portraits of other visual artists, composers and writers of his era. Seventy-five of these go on display Saturday in ''Hans Namuth: Portraits'' at the Heckscher Museum of Art, Prime Avenue in Huntington. In addition to several of the Pollock photos, these include such icons as the novelists John Steinbeck and John O'Hara, the architects Philip Johnson and Miles Van Der Rohe and the composers Oscar Hammerstein, Richard Rodgers and Stephen Sondheim. Organized by the National Portrait Gallery of the Smithsonian Institute, the show runs through Oct. 29. It is accompanied by ''Pollock to Wyeth: American Masters,'' an exhibition of works by artists whom Namuth photographed, including Pollock, Andrew Wyeth, Isamu Noguchi, Willem de Koning and Roy Lichtenstein (631) 351-3250.</p>
        <p>From the Chambers</p>
        <p>Returning to the East End for the fifth time, seven musicians from the New World Symphony, America's Orchestral Academy, conclude their visit from Miami Beach with two performances this week: today at 4 p.m. they play works by Beethoven, Brahms and Mozart at the Mulford Barn in East Hampton (631) 324-6850, and on Wednesday, it will be music by Brahms, Foote and Shostakovich at 6:30 p.m. at the Wolffer Estate Vineyard in Sagaponack (631) 537-5106.</p>
        <p>In Bridgehampton, the Bridgehampton Chamber Music Festival goes into its final week today at 6:30 p.m. with ''Myths and Mood Swings'' featuring Audra MacDonald singing the songs of Adam Guettel; ''Playing Favorites'' and ''Crazy Quilt'' at 8 p.m. Wednesday and Saturday, respectively; and a children's concert, ''Feet Got the Beat,'' at 5 p.m. Thursday. The season ends next Sunday with ''East Wind'' at 6:30 p.m. It all takes place at the Presbyterian Church. (631) 537-6368.</p>
        <p>Barbara Delatiner</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
