<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Setting Inspired by Cartography</title>
    <meta content="13DINE$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mappamondo Ristorante (Bedford Hills, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5D61F3CF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Setting Inspired by Cartography</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <dateline>BEDFORD HILLS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Mappamondo Ristorante in Bedford Hills, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS winsome farmhouse, atop a Bedford hill, has discarded the French lace curtain look it has worn for the last decade. Bright yellow, brick red and strong blue provide the background for the new occupant's eclectic assemblage of maps and other chartings of land and water.</p>
        <p>The world appears on walls, on tabletops, on plates, in a stylized Mercator projection on the ceiling, in globes of all sorts -- including one in the shape of a cookie jar. Although diners can view all the world here, the menu is inspired by that country of great cartographers, Italy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS winsome farmhouse, atop a Bedford hill, has discarded the French lace curtain look it has worn for the last decade. Bright yellow, brick red and strong blue provide the background for the new occupant's eclectic assemblage of maps and other chartings of land and water.</p>
        <p>The world appears on walls, on tabletops, on plates, in a stylized Mercator projection on the ceiling, in globes of all sorts -- including one in the shape of a cookie jar. Although diners can view all the world here, the menu is inspired by that country of great cartographers, Italy.</p>
        <p>Fresh focaccia and a saucer of herbed olive oil for dipping took the edge off keen appetites on one crowded evening, when kitchen and service couldn't keep up with demand. At four months the restaurant is still young, however, and a little more experience should smooth out the snags, service among them. The menu, too, needs reorganization; categories and offerings should be rethought. Meanwhile, Mappamondo is a fun place: the patio lovely, the decor, entertaining -- a distraction that makes up for competently executed but occasionally dull food.</p>
        <p>Most appetizers were hefty enough to serve as entrees. Spinach flan topped with chopped tomato and fontina sauce was delectable, as was a dish of sauteed shrimps, mushrooms and tomato with good white beans. A couple of slabs of polenta with slippery grilled portobello along with slices of mozzarella, tomatoes and sweet roasted peppers were standard efforts. But considerably less appealing were tortino di mozzarella -- a sour, ground, unidentifiable lump topped with mozzarella -- and, equally mysterious, vegetable patties (polpettine di verdure).</p>
        <p>From a variety of salads, grilled chicken with ultra-creamy goat cheese won high marks, and spinach with Gorgonzola was almost as tasty.</p>
        <p>Except for deliciously floppy, tender spinach ravioli (a special), glossy under a lick of fresh-tasting tomato sauce, and extremely hearty and filling penne with strongly herbed lamb sausage, pastas managed to be lackluster: farfalle with smoked salmon in cream sauce, penne with tomato and mozzarella, ravioli with vodka sauce -- all lacked pizzaz.</p>
        <p>Nicely pink at center, slices of sirloin arrived fanned around a high  mound of arugula, and plump, moist salmon Mediterraneo was all that it should be, the tomato and caper garnish a mere bagatelle. Chicken proved juicy and properly timed: a generous portion came sauteed with fennel and mushrooms (another special). But a slab of tuna was cut too thin and arrived dry and flavorless.</p>
        <p>Accompanying vegetables were fine. But with some entrees, as with some of the pasta dishes, cooking was standard, missing the dash and excitement that would have raised it beyond the ordinary.</p>
        <p>Tiramisu was almost molten with creaminess, and while it was not the  usual version, it was luscious. The pious will be pleased with a goblet of cut fresh fruit, perhaps berries and melon. The top crust of creme brulee arrived overly burned, but cheesecake was as good as anywhere. Coffee on all our visits was splendid.</p>
        <p>A three-course dinner averages $34 without drinks, tax and tip.</p>
        <p>Mappamondo is at Hill Street just east of the Saw Mill River Parkway.</p>
        <p>Mappamondo  352 North Bedford Road, Bedford Hills.  (914) 244-0300.</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- A map motif decorates the charming if tight dining areas and separate bar. High noise level and strained but willing service at peak times. Outdoor dining, weather permitting, on a large, shaded patio with umbrellas and flickering candles.</p>
        <p>SMOKING -- At the bar.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Spinach flan with cheese sauce, sauteed shrimps with white beans, chicken salad with goat cheese, penne with lamb sausage, spinach ravioli, sliced sirloin with arugula, salmon Mediterraneo, tiramisu, fresh fruit.</p>
        <p>PRICES -- Lunch, main dishes, $7.50 to $18. Dinner, main dishes, $15 to $24; $11 to $14.50 for pasta.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Major cards accepted.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Lunch, every day, noon to 4 P.M. Dinner, Sundays through Thursdays, 4 to 10 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays, 4 to 11 P.M.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Necessary on weekends; always a good idea.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Not accessible.</p>
        <p>THE RATINGS -- Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Poor.</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
