<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Never Forget Lautenberg? Heck, They Never Knew Him</title>
    <meta content="13POL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eagleton Institute</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mansnerus, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEEDA173FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Never Forget Lautenberg? Heck, They Never Knew Him</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laura Mansnerus</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mansnerus, Laura</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laura Mansnerus On Politics column on recent Eagleton Institute poll showing that many voters surveyed do not know who their Senators and political candidates are (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Set aside for now the particulars of the United States Senate candidates' positions on the earned-income tax credit or the normalization of trade relations with Cuba. For half the voters in New Jersey, the more immediate task is to find out which senator is leaving and which one is staying. Some people may need to start by learning their names.</p>
        <p>The problem is apparent in a poll made public last week by the Eagleton Institute at Rutgers. Asked to list the issues they wanted the candidates to address, the respondents, all registered voters, were asked if they could identify the senator who is retiring this year. They were given three choices: Frank Lautenberg, Robert G. Torricelli and Don't Know.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Set aside for now the particulars of the United States Senate candidates' positions on the earned-income tax credit or the normalization of trade relations with Cuba. For half the voters in New Jersey, the more immediate task is to find out which senator is leaving and which one is staying. Some people may need to start by learning their names.</p>
        <p>The problem is apparent in a poll made public last week by the Eagleton Institute at Rutgers. Asked to list the issues they wanted the candidates to address, the respondents, all registered voters, were asked if they could identify the senator who is retiring this year. They were given three choices: Frank Lautenberg, Robert G. Torricelli and Don't Know.</p>
        <p>The correct answer was given by 56 percent. And among those, any number could have been guessing.</p>
        <p>This could give Senator Lautenberg the impression that he has not made much of an impression during his 18 years of service in Washington, and he would be right. But he would not be alone, either. The better explanation, political experts say, is that New Jerseyans do not know much about anyone they elect.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's distinction, said Cliff Zukin, director of polling at Rutgers, is ''our impoverished media climate.''</p>
        <p>More specifically, as campaign managers have complained for years, we are squished between two giant media markets that do not care much about New Jersey. That's especially true for television, and television is the source of more and more of the voters information.</p>
        <p>To make matters worse, news coverage of candidates -- for whatever it adds to the store of knowledge -- barely counts in total television time. When the Alliance for Better Campaigns surveyed evening news programs during the last two weeks of the Senate primary campaign, it found that New Jersey viewers were 10 times more likely to see a campaign ad than a campaign story.</p>
        <p>Ingrid Reed, the director of the Eagleton New Jersey Project, which sponsored the Rutgers poll, sounded envious when she mentioned that in Minnesota, ''the candidates for governor debated 11 times, and they were all on television.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Reed is understanding about the 44 percent of voters in this state who admitted they did not know which senator was retiring or replied that it was Mr. Torricelli. (The poll was taken in June, before Mr. Torricelli said anything about running for governor.)</p>
        <p>''Given what you know about how busy people's lives are, how many new people are in the state, and that most people don't read newspapers for political news, I actually saw this as a case where the glass was half full,'' Ms. Reed said.</p>
        <p>Another generous assessment came from Tom Shea, Jon S. Corzine's campaign manager. (Mr. Corzine is the Democrat running for Mr. Lautenbergs seat; as recently as March, three in four Democrats said they did not know enough to have an opinion of him.) ''It may be just a question of people not having focused on this year's race,'' Mr. Shea said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zukin, on the other hand, gave the title ''Duh and Dumber'' to a report on a 1998 survey of New Jerseyans' general political knowledge. In that poll, 69 percent could not name either of their United States senators, and only 29 percent could identify Governor Whitman's opponent in the election that had taken place three months earlier.</p>
        <p>It is hard to know whether New Jerseyans are in fact dumber, at least about politics, than people in other states.</p>
        <p>Eric Rademacher, the co-director of the Ohio Poll at the University of Cincinnati, said, sympathetically, ''You folks are being so inundated with New York.'' Mr. Rademacher added that even in his state, where political coverage is all Ohio almost all the time, when registered voters are asked to rate a United States Senator about one-third say they do not know enough to have an opinion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zukin said that in addition to its media difficulties, New Jersey produced few political candidates who were well known to voters because there was only one statewide elective office -- the governorship -- and thus no stepping-stone jobs that would give lesser lights campaign experience and media time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zukin ticked off a list of candidates who were, name-recognition-wise, from nowhere: The first is Christine Todd Whitman, Somerset County Freeholder, who suddenly ran for a United States Senate seat in 1990. ''People didn't know much about Byrne or Florio,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There's an argument to be made that this is a media-rich state, and Carl Golden, who served as press secretary to Governor Kean and Governor Whitman, makes it: ''In New Jersey there's a big media culture,'' Mr. Golden said. In addition to the 28 daily newspapers, he said, ''if you want those New York and Philadelphia stations, you're in the right place.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Reed said that while that exposure might make New Jersey more visible in other states, it did not tell New Jersey voters much. By the way, the priorities for the voters in the Eagleton poll were tax policy, Social Security and the federal budget surplus. Campaign finance reform drew almost no interest.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reed said those answers were fairly reliable. Whatever they do or do not know, she said, ''people know what they're interested in.''</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS Laura Mansnerus reports from Trenton for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Laura Mansnerus reports from Trenton for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
