<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Koreans, Divided by War, Await Loved Ones' Return</title>
    <meta content="13KORE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1222383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strom, Stephanie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Jong Il</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Dae Jung</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E7DD133FF930A2575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2406" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Koreans, Divided by War, Await Loved Ones' Return</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE STROM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strom, Stephanie</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, Aug. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>North and South Koreans involved in family reunions that will bring 100 North Koreans south and take 100 southerners north, are at forefront of effort to rebuild single Korean nation by first mending hearts broken long ago; exchange of family members separated by Korean War was given top priority at historic summit meeting in June between South Korean president, Kim Dae Jung, and North Korean leader, Kim Jong Il; meetings are regarded as strongest evidence to date that Kim Jong Il is committed to rapprochement; information is tightly controlled in North Korea; Kim is taking big gamble by allowing North Koreans even tiny glimpse into lives of their more affluent relatives in South Korea; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the chaos that was the first few months of the Korean War in 1950, Kim Hyun Suk, age 14, went off to school one morning in Seoul  -- and never came back.</p>
        <p>His family could only speculate on his fate until, in 1964, they received word from a neighbor in their hometown of a letter from North Korea via Japan, indicating that the boy who had vanished was in the hermetically sealed Communist North.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the chaos that was the first few months of the Korean War in 1950, Kim Hyun Suk, age 14, went off to school one morning in Seoul  -- and never came back.</p>
        <p>His family could only speculate on his fate until, in 1964, they received word from a neighbor in their hometown of a letter from North Korea via Japan, indicating that the boy who had vanished was in the hermetically sealed Communist North.</p>
        <p>That ought to have been good news, but it carried its own woe, for in the dictatorial South Korea of the time, any hint of contact with the North spelled peril.</p>
        <p>The neighbor, who had received the letter on behalf of the family, was so excited that he gossiped about it. So the mailman who had delivered the letter came and confiscated it, unopened, before Kim Hyun Suk's father could get back to his hometown to retrieve it.</p>
        <p>A year later, in 1965, the post office notified the family that a similar letter had arrived -- but refused to hand it over.</p>
        <p>With South Korean suspicions aroused, Kim Hyun Suk's younger brother, now 59, suddenly found himself unemployed, and he had to get by picking up jobs as he could. His father, who had owned a photography studio, was forced to close shop and do various jobs, hiring out a car for use as a cab and traveling for work.</p>
        <p>''We suspected my brother was in North Korea, but we couldn't tell even our friends that a family member was living there,'' said the brother, Kim Hyun Ki. ''That would have caused a lot of trouble.''</p>
        <p>With that history in mind, the family did not even apply to participate in the reunions that in coming days will bring 100 North Koreans south, and take 100 southerners north, reassembling remnants of families separated in a war that has never officially ended, despite an uneasy truce across the 38th parallel since 1953.</p>
        <p>But Kim Hyun Suk did apply to join the reunions -- and his South Korean family was stunned when the Red Cross called to tell them their son and brother wanted to come to see them.</p>
        <p>''I recently realized that a person I thought was dead is going to meet me, and I'm overjoyed,'' said Kim Nam Shik, Kim Hyun Suk's father.</p>
        <p>Back in 1950, the school told Kim Nam Shik that his son had gone on a school trip. ''A war had just broken out, and no one had any time to look for a lost student,'' the father said. ''We had no one to turn to. It's hard for me to say that we ever gave up looking for him, but there was no place to get any information and the war was intensifying.''</p>
        <p>Even when they got word of the mysterious letters that came via Japan, the idea that his son was still alive had a whiff of unreality. ''We heard about these letters through a third party and at times I even doubted they existed,'' Kim Nam Shik said. ''I had lived until then having given up on ever seeing my son again.''</p>
        <p>His wife was more hopeful. ''Every day until she died last year, my mother placed a bowl of clear water in the garden and prayed for my brother's return,'' said Kim Hyun Ki, Kim Nam Shik's second son.</p>
        <p>They cannot imagine what their reaction to the reunion will be and sometimes still speak of the meeting as if it might not occur. ''So much time has gone by that if I see him, I don't even know if I'll have any tears,'' Kim Hyun Ki said.</p>
        <p>His memories of his brother are those of a 9-year-old envious of an older sibling. ''I was the ugly duckling,'' Kim Hyun Ki said. ''He was better looking, very smart, and he was the one who got the most attention and love.''</p>
        <p>His father is so overwhelmed that he does not know what he will say to his oldest son at Tuesday's planned reunion. ''It's just unreal that we are meeting, and that in itself is enough,'' he said. ''I don't know how much longer I will be alive or whether we can ever live together for a brief period.''</p>
        <p>''I don't want to have any hope,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The Koreans involved in the reunions are at the forefront of the effort to rebuild a single Korean nation by first mending hearts broken long ago.</p>
        <p>''Reuniting the separated families is the most important part of the efforts toward eventual reunification,'' said Lee Sang Man, a professor at Chung-Ang University who is advising the government on unification. ''Without a solution to this humanitarian issue, we cannot achieve anything else.''</p>
        <p>The exchange of family members separated by the war was given top priority at the historic summit meeting in June between the South Korean president, Kim Dae Jung, and the North Korean leader, Kim Jong Il.</p>
        <p>There was a similar, albeit smaller, reunion in 1985, but it was an isolated event. This reunion is intended to be the critical first step in bringing the two nations together. As the two leaders acknowledged, without restoring the human bonds torn by the war, there would be little hope of cultivating the economic cooperation and reduction in military tension that would form the foundation for eventual reunification.</p>
        <p>''This is not just a symbolic event,'' Professor Lee said. ''The government strongly believes that it is a prerequisite to everything to follow.''</p>
        <p>The meetings are regarded as the strongest evidence to date that Kim Jong Il, until the summit meeting a mysterious recluse who ruled his country with the totalitarian power established by his father, Kim Il Sung, is committed to rapprochement. Information is tightly controlled in North Korea, the last bastion of hard-core Stalinism in the world.</p>
        <p>Thus, by allowing North Koreans a tiny glimpse into the lives of their more affluent relatives in the South, Kim Jong Il is taking perhaps the biggest gamble since his father's death in 1994.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the meetings have been carefully scripted. The reunions will take place in the tightly sealed environments of hotels in Pyongyang and Seoul.</p>
        <p>The North Koreans visiting Seoul will not even be able to go to the graves of family members who died during the separation, a restriction that is regarded by many in this Confucian society as more troubling than being unable to stay in their families' homes for the three-day reunion.</p>
        <p>Despite all the control, nothing can dim the excitement and tension surrounding the lucky Koreans chosen for the meetings.</p>
        <p>Kim Joon Sup, now 66, left what was then his home in Pyongyang on July 9, 1950, and headed for his graduation. He was 15 at the time, and he had no idea that he would not see his home again.</p>
        <p>Just two weeks earlier, the North Korean Army began the Korean War, marching south across the 38th parallel. The army needed recruits, including Kim Joon Sup and his graduating classmates.</p>
        <p>''My mother had to go to the church that day and couldn't attend the ceremony, and my father was working for the railroad and couldn't come,'' recalled Kim Joon Sup, who eventually became a prisoner of war in South Korea and stayed on to make his life here. ''So I told my parents goodbye, intending to return after the ceremony, but 50 years later, I still haven't gone home.''</p>
        <p>Immediately after graduation, Kim Joon Sup's class was herded onto the school's soccer field and enlisted. ''We never even touched our diplomas,'' he said.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Kim Joon Sup will go home.</p>
        <p>''I remember playing with my siblings on the banks of the Taedong River,'' he said. ''We would pan for gold, and in those days, if you did it all day long, you'd come up with a couple of flecks.''</p>
        <p>He will meet his younger brother, Kim Chang Hyup, and his sister, Kim Kyung Sup. ''She was only 6 years old when I was taken away, and I remember that she was really pretty,'' Kim Joon Sup said. ''But who doesn't think that about their baby sister?''</p>
        <p>Kim Joon Sup, like the other South Koreans traveling north, is an ordinary citizen. Most of those coming south, however, are believed to be North Korean loyalists, with high-level ties to the Communist Party, and from academia and the arts.</p>
        <p>They will have only limited time to meet with their South Korean family members, and they will see Seoul only from the buses that will take them to various sites, including Lotte World, a shopping mall and amusement park complex, and Changdok Palace, the historic home of Korea's emperors. Oddly, North Korea is rumored to have requested that the palace be included on the itinerary. ''There is absolutely zero risk for defection,'' Professor Lee said.</p>
        <p>The Unification Ministry put a priority on older people like Kim Nam Shik but used a computer in an effort to make the selection process as neutral as possible. Priority was given to separated spouses, then parents separated from children and then siblings.</p>
        <p>There were inevitable tragedies. Chang I Yun, 71, had been told his 109-year-old mother was alive in the North, only to get news that she had died. And one 90-year-old woman died shortly after receiving word that her son might be selected to visit Seoul.</p>
        <p>Even Kim Joon Sup, who was kidnapped into the North Korean Army, was rushed to the emergency room with acute indigestion after hearing that he was to be reunited with his siblings.</p>
        <p>Moon Kyung Ja, a life insurance broker whose sister is in the North, considered herself such a long shot for the reunion that, like Kim Nam Shik, she did not apply.</p>
        <p>''I turned on the TV and saw my sister's name on the screen,'' Mrs. Moon said. ''I kept calling the Red Cross but I couldn't get through. Finally I did get through, and just after I hung up the phone, a television station called and said they were coming over with a camera crew. I was out of my mind -- and I have to watch my high blood pressure.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Moon's memory of her sister is rooted in a childhood turned upside down when the war erupted, when Mrs. Moon was 10. Her father, a wealthy industrialist with interests in coal mining, fled to a remote family cottage, and then disappeared.</p>
        <p>Her mother, faced with the alternative of being labeled a capitalist by the Communists who were fast marching down the peninsula, went to work for them, doing various odd jobs and making sure she always had one of her children with her so the troops would leave her alone. ''We all had to work to support the North Korean troops,'' Mrs. Moon recalled, humming a tune the soldiers taught her to sing to keep up their morale. ''My older sister worked in the canteen and sneaked rice to us.''</p>
        <p>When the tide turned against the North Korean troops, the work Mrs. Moon's mother had done for the Communists landed her in jail. Relatives refused to help her or her children. ''My uncle, who was in the army, moved into our house and refused to give us any food, even though we begged him to just give us a little something for my baby brother,'' Mrs. Moon recalled.</p>
        <p>The essentially orphaned children found themselves begging for food from their former servants, who scorned them. Realizing that they would die on their own in Seoul, Mrs. Moon's oldest sister, Moon Yang Ok, took Mrs. Moon and her younger sister to live with relatives in the town of Chi Rae in the south.</p>
        <p>Moon Yang Ok returned to Seoul, and then disappeared along with Mrs. Moon's second-oldest sister and her brother. Mrs. Moon's mother had also vanished.</p>
        <p>''We were too scared to talk about them because until the 1970's, any word that you had worked for the North Koreans and you were severely punished,'' said Mrs. Moon, who is now 59. ''But we were desperate for news. We spent a fortune on famous fortune tellers, and any time we had even the vaguest word that they were sighted somewhere, we would head off for that city or town, only to be disappointed.''</p>
        <p>She suspected her sister was in the North but did not know what to do. Her younger sister, Moon Jong Oh, moved to Los Angeles, and Mrs. Moon has not heard from her in two years. ''I am alone,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But then the Red Cross called her and brought a passport-sized photo of a sad-faced woman bearing a remarkable resemblance to Mrs. Moon. ''It was like seeing someone from another country,'' she said. ''It felt very strange. I could tell she went through a lot of hard times, but the man from the Red Cross, he told me she's one of the better-off ones.''</p>
        <p>She suspects her sister, one of the seven or eight women who will come from the North, is married to a high-ranking North Korean official, but those politics do not bother her a bit. ''I'm happy about that,'' she said. ''It means she's had a good life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
