<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMPENSATION SET ON ATTICA UPRISING</title>
    <meta content="29ATTI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Attica State Prison (NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Telesca, Michael A (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0D61E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMPENSATION SET ON ATTICA UPRISING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>ROCHESTER, Aug. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Judge Michael A Telesca, declaring that inmates beaten in 1971 Attica prison uprising were treated 'like garbage,' divides $8 million settlement to compensate more than 500 inmates and relatives for abuse that prisoners suffered at hands of state police; allotment of landmark settlement caps one of longest and most ignominious chapters in American criminal justice history, fleshing out deal reached in January between New York State lawyers representing 1,281 former inmates, who will receive between $6,500 and $125,000 in compensation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Declaring that inmates beaten in the 1971 Attica prison uprising were treated ''like garbage,'' a federal judge divided an $8 million settlement today to compensate more than 500 inmates and relatives for the abuse that the prisoners suffered.</p>
        <p>The allotment of the landmark settlement caps one of the longest and most ignominious chapters in American criminal justice history, fleshing out a deal reached in January between New York State and lawyers representing 1,281 former inmates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Declaring that inmates beaten in the 1971 Attica prison uprising were treated ''like garbage,'' a federal judge divided an $8 million settlement today to compensate more than 500 inmates and relatives for the abuse that the prisoners suffered.</p>
        <p>The allotment of the landmark settlement caps one of the longest and most ignominious chapters in American criminal justice history, fleshing out a deal reached in January between New York State and lawyers representing 1,281 former inmates.</p>
        <p>At more than 200 pages, the settlement filed today also functions as a harrowing encyclopedia of personal anecdotes, incorporating months of testimony from nearly 200 former inmates who stood before Judge Michael A. Telesca of Federal District Court here and recounted how the uprising and siege at the prison in western New York left 43 people dead, 80 wounded and countless more psychologically scarred.</p>
        <p>And now, after almost three decades of waiting and legal maneuvering, the former inmates are scheduled to receive their shares by October, barring an appeal by any inmate.</p>
        <p>Yet this was far from the lottery. Most of the awards -- from $6,500 to $125,000 per former inmate -- were modest sums, Judge Telesca wrote in his decision. And many of the plaintiffs and their lawyers agreed, adding that no amount of money could compensate them or resolve an episode that has become a symbol of prison life and state-sanctioned brutality.</p>
        <p>''Just because it is history does not mean it is all in the past,'' Judge Telesca wrote. ''Indeed, Attica is the ghost that has never stopped haunting its survivors -- both the inmates and the families of the deceased guards and prison personnel. But at least the settlement of this case provides the basis for the former inmates to close the book on the past and to focus on the future.''</p>
        <p>With that in mind, the judge devoted the bulk of his decision to short but powerful summaries of each inmate's experience.</p>
        <p>For Frank B. B. Smith, for instance, Attica was about being stripped naked, pelted with hot and spent shell casings and being threatened with castration. He was awarded $125,000, the highest amount.</p>
        <p>For George Nieves, Attica was primarily a nightmare of the mind. Like so many others, he was punched, beaten and forced to crawl in the mud. But what still unsettles him is the memory of a guard drawing a giant ''X'' on his back as if marking him as a target. He received $6,500, the lowest amount.</p>
        <p>''They really made me paranoid,'' Mr. Nieves said in a telephone interview from Mount Vernon, N.Y., where he is social worker. ''Attica always continues.''</p>
        <p>For Josh Melville, Attica was simply the haunted place where his father, Samuel, was fatally shot. He traveled from Florida to Rochester to introduce a forensic ballistic report and photographs to bolster his claim that his father was murdered. He was awarded $25,000.</p>
        <p>And on it went, story after cathartic story, littered with ''brutal beatings and acts of torture'' and unlimited racial epithets, Judge Telesca wrote.</p>
        <p>So it was understandable, perhaps, that there was no celebration after today's settlement order, no high-fives or elated grins. The case was a maddeningly slow one, outlasting hundreds of inmates who have died since the uprising.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith of Queens, in fact, was the only former inmate who attended a news conference organized by lawyers for several of the former inmates, and that is because he now works as a paralegal with Elizabeth M. Fink, the principal lawyer, on prisoners' rights cases.</p>
        <p>''I hope what I say will have some kind of bridge to the rest of the plaintiffs,'' he said. ''It's not about the money; money would not compensate if it was $125 million. I want everybody to concentrate, everybody, on what happened at Attica and how we can prevent that.''</p>
        <p>The uprising began on Sept. 9, 1971, when inmates at the Attica Correctional Facility, about 30 miles east of Buffalo, took several guards hostage, seized control of parts of the prison and demanded improvements in prison conditions. When negotiations stalled, Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller ordered the retaking of Prison Yard D and authorized state troopers to storm the prison.</p>
        <p>The troopers used helicopters, dropped tear gas and fired indiscriminately into a crowd of 1,281 prisoners. Then, after regaining control, prison guards and law enforcement officials forced inmates to crawl naked over broken glass and denied them rudimentary medical care.</p>
        <p>By the end of the five-day siege, 11 guards and 32 prisoners had died.</p>
        <p>For years, though, all efforts to exact an official apology, much less legal redress, achieved little. The widows of some guards killed during the melee sued, with varied results. A class-action suit against the state, filed on behalf of the 1,281 inmates, languished for 18 years before going to a liability trial, and an additional 5 to reach the damages phase.</p>
        <p>In 1997, Mr. Smith won a $4 million jury verdict in Buffalo, while David Brosig, another inmate who had been in D Yard, won $75,000. But a federal appellate court reversed those verdicts last year, saying that the trial judge, John T. Elfvin, had mishandled the case. As a result, the case wound up with Judge Telesca.</p>
        <p>In January, a deal materialized: the state agreed to set aside $12 million, the biggest ever in a prisoners' rights case, with $8 million for the former inmates and $4 million for lawyers' fees. As is routine in settlements, the defendants admitted neither wrongdoing nor liability.</p>
        <p>To divide up the $8 million, Judge Telesca asked the plaintiffs to tell their stories in open court. From May to August, almost 200 did, in what turned out to be an emotional and often wrenching experience, Ms. Fink said.</p>
        <p>One former inmate, Charles L. Williams, told the judge that the beatings to his right leg were so severe that his leg had to be amputated below the knee in 1998. He has suffered from post-traumatic stress disorder, alcohol abuse and nightmares. He was eventually awarded $125,000.</p>
        <p>Another, David Felder of the Bronx, filed a claim that he had been shot in his calf, hit on the head by a state trooper with a club and subjected to guards playing Russian roulette with him. He was awarded $31,000, but he died several days after he filed his claim, Ms. Fink said, so the money will go to his family.</p>
        <p>There were also former inmates who testified before Judge Telesca knowing that they would not receive any compensation, but who were determined to corroborate the testimony of others. One such former inmate, Gene Hitchens, said that he had witnessed many of the atrocities from his cell in Cell Block C, and that he had difficulty absorbing what had happened.</p>
        <p>''I'm leaving Attica here today, Your Honor,'' Mr. Hitchens said. ''I don't want to talk about it. I don't want to live it again.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Judge Telesca approved 502 claims and divided the awards into five categories based on the severity of the injuries: $6,500, $10,000, $31,000 and $125,000 for the inmates, and $25,000 for the relatives of inmates who died during the uprising. More than half fell into the $6,500 category; only 15 qualified for $125,000.</p>
        <p>The payments could still be delayed should one of the plaintiffs decide to appeal, said Ellen Yacknin, one of the plaintiffs' lawyers. But she and the other lawyers said that, even with appeals, they were optimistic that the awards would be disbursed by next spring.</p>
        <p>In the next few days, the plaintiffs will receive a letter from the judge outlining his decision. But those who heard about their fate today through reporters said that while they were disappointed, there was very little choice, this late in the process. Many said that they did not know what they would do with the money, other than pay some bills and debts.</p>
        <p>And while the money, presumably, will eventually go away, the memories will not.</p>
        <p>''It's never going to go away,'' said George Alexander Shorts Jr. of Brooklyn, whose toes were broken during the uprising. He was awarded $31,000. ''I had blocked a lot of things out, but going before the judge, a lot of this stuff came back, and a lot of it hurt. Thank God it's over.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
