<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>X-Rays From Afar Bolster Theory Of a Whirlpool in Empty Space</title>
    <meta content="29GRAV$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000911T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rossi X-ray Timing Explorer (Satellite)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">X-Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Neutron Stars</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glanz, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Einstein, Albert (1879-1955)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">X-Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DD1E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>X-Rays From Afar Bolster Theory Of a Whirlpool in Empty Space</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLANZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glanz, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rossi X-ray Timing Explorer, NASA satellite designed to measure X-ray sources, detects previously unknown, oscillating X-ray signals from three dense chunks of matter called neutron stars; ringing signals may be generated by space being spun in circle, lending support to prediction of Einstein's theory of relativity that gravity of spinning object should tug slightly on surrounding space and slowly drag it around in circles; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Can empty space be stirred like pancake batter? According to Einstein's theory of relativity, the gravity of a spinning object should tug slightly on the surrounding space and slowly drag it around in circles. Any matter would be pulled along, even though ordinary gravity can only attract matter, not push it sideways.</p>
        <p>Observational astronomers have remained skeptical of that supremely bizarre prediction, since they have never found clear, direct proof that the phenomenon exists. But with the discovery of a strange new signal by the Rossi X-ray Timing Explorer, a NASA satellite designed to measure X-ray sources in deep space, a few more astronomers may be ready to get on board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Can empty space be stirred like pancake batter? According to Einstein's theory of relativity, the gravity of a spinning object should tug slightly on the surrounding space and slowly drag it around in circles. Any matter would be pulled along, even though ordinary gravity can only attract matter, not push it sideways.</p>
        <p>Observational astronomers have remained skeptical of that supremely bizarre prediction, since they have never found clear, direct proof that the phenomenon exists. But with the discovery of a strange new signal by the Rossi X-ray Timing Explorer, a NASA satellite designed to measure X-ray sources in deep space, a few more astronomers may be ready to get on board.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michiel van der Klis of the University of Amsterdam and two colleagues will report in the Sept. 1 issue of Astrophysical Journal Letters that the satellite has detected previously unknown, oscillating X-ray signals from three superdense chunks of matter called neutron stars. The powerful gravity of those stars is what theorists say is required to produce the effect, and the ringing signals may be generated by space being spun in a circle.</p>
        <p>Dr. van der Klis said that the observations were ''not a definitive proof'' of the phenomenon but were just what astronomers expected if it were happening around the stars. ''Because there is a large amount of matter spinning around there,'' he said, ''general relativity predicts that space-time will be dragged around a little bit.''</p>
        <p>The neutron stars, which are essentially the cinders that remain after a star explodes, are probably each in a close orbit around an ordinary star whose outer, gaseous layers are being torn away by the powerful gravity of their companions.</p>
        <p>As the gas spirals violently into the neutron star and becomes agitated and hot enough to emit X-rays, it begins to rock and shake with some of the rhythms of the star system, like a cup of coffee resting on the hood of an idling car -- the faster the engine idles, the faster the coffee jiggles. Astrophysicists expect one of those jiggles to be the rate at which the strong gravity of the spinning neutron star stirs the emptiness of space, and as the gas is pulled along it may be emitting X-rays at the frequency observed by the satellite.</p>
        <p>How can empty space be stirred?  In Einstein's general theory of relativity, gravity and space are not separate concepts but work hand in glove. Gravity twists and warps space, and it can also pull it along as if it were a real substance rather than emptiness.</p>
        <p>Imagine riding a merry-go-round in space. Ordinarily, a rider would feel centrifugal force only when the distant stars appeared to be spinning around. Both the centrifugal force and the apparently spinning stars would be indications that the merry-go-round is, in fact, turning on its axis.</p>
        <p>Under the influence of a massive rotating object, like a neutron star, Einstein's theory says that space itself begins swirling, though not as fast as the star -- gravity is an imperfect stirring spoon. So if a merry-go-round is turning at the same rate as space, the centrifugal force vanishes, even though the stars still seem to be spinning around. Matter outside a neutron star can be swept up in this swirling space like sticks in a whirlpool.</p>
        <p>But many of those notions have not yet been tested observationally where gravity is very strong, and they lead to the most bizarre consequences -- perhaps those seen by Rossi.</p>
        <p>Probing those consequences where the geometry is highly twisted and malleable, said Dr. Frederick K. Lamb, a physicist at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, ''is one of the major problems of modern physics and astrophysics, and it's a regime in which we have had very little or no information.''</p>
        <p>The spinning of emptiness, or ''frame dragging,'' is one of the most bizarre of all those consequences of relativity. Scientists are still debating whether that explanation for the new buzz from the neutron stars is correct. But Dr. Mario Vietri, an astrophysicist at the University of Rome, said that X-ray emissions from those extreme environments were ''the one way that we know to test general relativity in the strong-field regime.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Mitchell Begelman, an astrophysicist at the University of Colorado, Boulder, said that the X-ray emission signals would yield even more information about the gas and its behavior if scientists could only interpret them. ''I would say that Rossi has provided an amazingly rich data set that far outstrips our ability to understand it yet,'' Dr. Begelman said.</p>
        <p>The star systems in question are among the most exotic and violent in the galaxy, said Dr. van der Klis, who did his work with Peter G. Jonker of the University of Amsterdam and Dr. Mariano Mendez of Amsterdam and the National University of La Plata in Argentina.</p>
        <p>The systems probably come about when one star much heavier than the sun and one lighter than the sun are born side by side or drift near each other. The two stars are fated to have much different lives, since heavy stars use up their nuclear fuel rapidly and can explode as supernovas after just millions of years -- an eye blink in cosmic terms -- while lighter stars burn steadily for billions of years.</p>
        <p>When the heavy star explodes, it leaves behind a neutron star, a superdense cinder of collapsed matter with the density of an atomic nucleus. Just 10 to 15 miles across, it still weighs more than the sun. (Extremely massive stars can create objects called black holes that collapse even further.) Eventually, this dark star and its rather ordinary companion can settle into an orbit so tight that both would fit inside a sphere the size of the sun.</p>
        <p>At those close distances, the powerful gravity of the fast-living neutron star begins to rip gaseous material from the outer layers of its companion. The material does not fall straight onto the neutron star's surface, but instead spirals downward, like a satellite whose orbit gradually decays. The material probably gathers into a flattened disk reminiscent of the rings of Jupiter, called an accretion disk, before plunging at speeds as high as half the speed of light onto the neutron star's murky surface.</p>
        <p>Because of friction among the gases in the accretion disk and the violence of the collision at the surface, Dr. van der Klis said, ''the end result of the whole process is that an enormous amount of X-rays is emitted.''</p>
        <p>Called low-mass X-ray binaries, about 100 such systems are known in the galaxy, he said. Because the binaries are dim, distant and small in size, astronomers regard their copious emission of X-rays as more than a curiosity. Without the emission, the dark cinder ''is a dead star,'' Dr. van der Klis said. The emission ''is the basic reason that we are able to see this star at all.''</p>
        <p>The small, parsimonious companion is generally not bright enough to be of much help. So for decades, astronomers have launched X-ray satellites to study these sources and other high-energy displays in the heavens. Since X-rays do not penetrate very deeply into the atmosphere, astronomers must study them from space.</p>
        <p>NASA launched the Rossi X-ray Timing Explorer in late 1995 with a highly sensitive detector that is able to pick up high-frequency variations, often faster than a thousand times a second, in the output of X-ray sources in space. Astronomers wanted such a detector partly because they hoped to see not just a steady X-ray glow, but also a direct signature of the dynamic, whirling motion of the gases around the neutron star.</p>
        <p>The satellite cannot see anything but a flickering point of X-ray emission. But from the rate of those flickers -- their frequency -- astronomers can piece together what is happening around the star.</p>
        <p>For example, the frequency with which a clump of X-ray-emitting gas disappears behind the star and emerges again tells astronomers how fast it is moving in its orbit. The faster the speed, the smaller the orbit. Since neutron stars have little atmosphere, and gas can orbit very close to its surface, that frequency says something about the size of the star. The relevant frequencies can be higher than a thousand times a second.</p>
        <p>''If you're going to measure things that are happening near the surface of the neutron star, then you're going to have to resolve that kind of time scale,'' said Dr. Jean Swank, an astronomer at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center who is Rossi's project scientist. The satellite's detectors are up to the job, Dr. Swank said.</p>
        <p>The information is particularly precious, since the exact size of neutron stars for a given mass is a major point of contention among theorists who try to understand how nuclear matter behaves under tremendous pressures, a relation described mathematically by the ''equation of state.''</p>
        <p>''How big a star is for a given density depends basically on the equation of state -- how compressible the matter is,'' said Dr. Tod Strohmayer, an astronomer at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center. The orbital frequency, Dr. Strohmayer said, ''gives information about the mass and radius of the star.''</p>
        <p>But that is not the only telltale frequency that astronomers had a chance to see in the Rossi satellite data. Like the wavering ''beat frequency'' that is heard when two tuning forks with different tones are struck at the same time, the rotation frequency of the neutron star could modulate the first signal through a complex physical process at the star, creating more tones for Rossi.</p>
        <p>Finally, there is the possible frame-dragging effect. If a spinning neutron star's equator is not in the same plane as the accretion disk, this dragging might cause the disk to wobble with yet another frequency that the satellite could detect.</p>
        <p>Almost immediately after Rossi was launched in late 1995, teams led by Dr. Strohmayer and Dr. van der Klis detected two definite frequencies from neutron star binaries. They were identified with the orbiting gas and the spinning star, although theorists have later come up with alternative explanations.</p>
        <p>That debate continues, although Dr. Strohmayer said the data have already yielded information about the possible sizes and densities of the stars. The Sept. 1 paper by Dr. van der Klis and his colleagues announces the discovery of a new oscillation in three X-ray binaries. Some theorists, including Dr. Vietri of the University of Rome and Dr. Luigi Stella of the Astronomical Observatory of Rome, believe the new data are evidence of frame dragging.</p>
        <p>Others, including Dr. Lamb and his colleague Dr. Draza Markovic of the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, believe that the frame-dragging wobble that is theoretically expected for neutron stars falls well short of the observations, indicating that the new oscillation is probably be caused by something else.</p>
        <p>''I personally think it's not settled yet,'' Dr. Swank said. ''It seems to me likely that that kind of thing might occur there,'' she said, referring to frame dragging. But Dr. Swank said the issue probably would not be settled until other features of the oscillations were known, like how they change as the star's output brightens and dims.</p>
        <p>The debate could also eventually be influenced by a long-planned NASA mission called Gravity Probe B, which is expected to look for the tiny amount of frame dragging produced by Earth's relatively paltry gravitational pull.</p>
        <p>Dr. Begelman of Colorado cautioned that some entirely different effect could yet be behind the new discovery around neutron stars, like wave motions that relativity theory predicts should also exist in the accretion disk. Future X-ray missions with names like Constellation X and Maxim will probably have something to say about resolving those mysteries. Meanwhile, the Rossi satellite goes on making news.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 11, 2000, Monday  An illustration in Science Times on Aug. 29 with an article about space swirling around a neutron star carried an incomplete credit. It was based on an illustration by Joe Bergeron for Sky &amp; Telescope.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 11, 2000, Monday</p>
        <p>An illustration in Science Times on Aug. 29 with an article about space swirling around a neutron star carried an incomplete credit. It was based on an illustration by Joe Bergeron for Sky &amp; Telescope.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
