<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Start in Fashion? Easier to Go Through the Eye of a Needle</title>
    <meta content="29DRES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226124"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horyn, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adrover, Miguel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roi, Alice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DC1E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1442" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Start in Fashion? Easier to Go Through the Eye of a Needle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Miguel Adrover, Alice Roi and other young fashion designers in New York City; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Being a young designer in New York -- and the city seems flush with new talent now -- hardly means that one will survive to be an old designer in New York. The fashion business here, especially, functions with a kind of Darwinian magnanimity. Which is to say, either you're good or you're gone.</p>
        <p>And talent alone doesn't ensure survival, as Isaac Mizrahi found out. Nor is financial success the only measure of fashion greatness. Can anyone really say that Ralph Lauren is a better designer than Stephen Burrows?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Being a young designer in New York -- and the city seems flush with new talent now -- hardly means that one will survive to be an old designer in New York. The fashion business here, especially, functions with a kind of Darwinian magnanimity. Which is to say, either you're good or you're gone.</p>
        <p>And talent alone doesn't ensure survival, as Isaac Mizrahi found out. Nor is financial success the only measure of fashion greatness. Can anyone really say that Ralph Lauren is a better designer than Stephen Burrows?</p>
        <p>At first glance, the designers who have risen in Mr. Mizrahi's wake seem to possess neither his exciting talent nor his old-fashioned skills of self-promotion. They are often shy, inarticulate, vague to the point of appearing self-consciously cool, and even when they become stars, as Miguel Adrover did this year, there is something so reticent in their demeanor as to make one wonder if the very notion of the designer as a personality isn't dead. ''I would like to hide myself,'' Mr. Adrover said last Thursday in his new workroom on the Bowery. ''But in the United States, that is impossible.''</p>
        <p>Yet, in a way, the era of personality has ended. Ten or 15 years ago, when designers like Donna Karan and Michael Kors were building their businesses, and Todd Oldham, Marc Jacobs and Mr. Mizrahi were emerging, it was assumed that they would seek the same tried-and-true laurels. The cover of Vogue. The limousine lines of store executives and editors stretching outside their shows. The distinction, so American, of being hailed by their first names.</p>
        <p>And, in ways that fulfill the ideal of the self-made, individualistic designer, they did aspire to those things. But it is also true that in the last few years, as these designers have dropped out or taken their companies public, or merged them into larger companies, the story has shifted from personality and toward business. It is a comment, if not on this change then on the way the industry is responding, that for all the attention being paid to fashion, and for all the names filling next month's show calendar in New York, no single new designer has stood out. It isn't even clear that the brightest star wants to. As Mr. Adrover said: ''I don't feel that connected to the glamour of the fashion world. I hang out with my friends.''</p>
        <p>There used to be cachet attached to young designers -- or poets or musical artists -- whose work bubbled to the surface through some underground channel of discontent or outrage. One thinks immediately of Vivienne Westwood and her punk consort Malcolm McLaren changing the name of their London shop five times to reflect each new subtle wave of style. Or of Rudi Gernreich, who was a rebel in his own way in California in the 1960's. Yet, because of the speed with which change occurs, the underground doesn't mean what it once did.</p>
        <p>''It's harder for something to remain underground now because there's so much more information telling you where the underground is,'' Julie Gilhart, a vice president of Barneys, said. Like a lot of store buyers, Ms. Gilhart scans indie magazines like Dutch, I. D. and Purple for the names of new designers. It was in one of those magazines that she first came across the label United Bamboo, a sportswear line designed in New York by Miho Aoki and Thuy Pham. ''Their clothes are adorable and very nicely made,'' she said. ''They're serious but also funny in that polished/unpolished way that you see on girls in Japan.'' Barneys is carrying United Bamboo for fall.</p>
        <p>In the absence of a true underground -- and the avant-garde has never gained much lasting credibility here -- many young designers who have something inventive to say find themselves struggling in the margins. Among those who are worth watching are Alice Roi, whose shapely suits and neck-tie blouses play up some of the feminine cliches (secretarial glam, librarian frumpiness) that were first explored by Susan Cianciolo; Sonja Rubin and Kip Chapelle, who combine strict tailoring with fluid hand-knits that often defy you to guess how they're made; and Bruce, which is designed by Daphne Gutierrez and Nicole Noselli, and has consistently been in the vanguard of a cerebral, slightly helter-skelter femininity.</p>
        <p>About a year ago, when a reporter phoned Ms. Noselli to make an appointment, with the intention of including Bruce in an article about designers preparing for the collections, her response said a great deal about how her generation thinks. She said, ''Frankly, you'd just be in the way.''</p>
        <p>Well, it was endearing. The two Bruce designers were up to their eyeballs in work, as they recalled last week in their Lower East Side apartment, which is also their studio, and what, honestly, did they need a reporter around for? How could they explain themselves, the day-to-day struggle -- no money, but above all, no time -- without the whole thing sounding like some heartwarming Andy Hardy tale? And it might be eye-opening -- but who needs it? ''People think that because we're young designers we'll do anything,'' Ms. Noselli said.</p>
        <p>Almost every day Greg Mills, a former president of Isaac Mizrahi, who owns a showroom that represents Bruce and a dozen other lines, including the men's wear label Richard Edwards, gets calls from young designers looking for help. Lack of capital is obviously a problem. So is striking a balance between artistic integrity and commercial viability.</p>
        <p>''It just keeps getting harder,'' said Ms. Cianciolo, whose fall production of only 400 pieces neither helps her bottom line nor reflects her influence.</p>
        <p>But, as Mr. Mills suggested, the real problem may be an industry that is increasingly dominated by a few brands. ''I recently got a call from an owner of a men's store who told me he basically writes three checks -- one each to LVMH, the Gucci group and Prada,'' Mr. Mills said. ''That's unhealthy.''</p>
        <p>The thing is, none of these designers want to create clothes that are novel but don't sell. ''I sometimes feel as if I'm in a race: we've got to win,'' Ms. Roi said. Her 15-month-old company, which is being financed by her mother, produced about 1,200 pieces for fall, and they are sold at Kirna Zabete and Fred Segal. ''We want people to wear the clothes, not keep them so underground.''</p>
        <p>That is Mr. Adrover's aim, too. ''I still scratch through the garbage, because that's my nature,'' he said. ''But I don't use the word 'avant-garde,' and I don't feel like a downtown designer, either. It's about showing a different view.''</p>
        <p>Of course, the fashion business -- especially in New York -- is nothing if not a prolonged search for the obvious. Two designers who will not be on the runways this fall are Ms. Aoki and Mr. Pham of United Bamboo, though not because they are shy or too cool but rather because, for now, they think it's better to focus on developing their business. Mr. Pham, who several years ago was part of a maverick but short-lived design company called Bernadette Corp., said that after a while ''designers start to find that it's their business, doing shows.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''I would like to consider doing something like A.P.C. or Polo, more of a lifestyle kind of business where the design doesn't change every season.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Aoki, who happened to be wearing a red-striped little boy's shirt from Ralph Lauren with one of her charming wraparound skirts, looked at Mr. Pham doubtfully. ''That might get boring,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pham smiled slightly. ''I don't think so,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
