<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton to Herald a New Era of Ties on Colombia Trip</title>
    <meta content="Y29COL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colombia-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heroin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Colombia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cartagena (Colombia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia/Cartagena</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heroin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EFDF1F31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1186" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton to Herald a New Era of Ties on Colombia Trip</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>CARTAGENA, Colombia, Aug. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton will initiate new era in US-Colombia relations with visit to Cartagena on August 30; some highlights of visit described; visit comes at time when government has been weakened politically, and peace negotiations with guerrillas have stalled; for US officials, visit will highlight for American public importance of helping South America's second-largest country to fight drug trade that produces 90 percent of cocaine and about quarter of heroin entering US (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton is about to raise the curtain on a new era in United States-Colombia relations with a visit to this Caribbean port on Wednesday, and the acts that follow will probably include shooting at Marxist guerrillas by American-supplied helicopters.</p>
        <p>The visit is all the more important because it comes at a time when the government here has been weakened politically, and peace negotiations with guerrilla groups have stalled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton is about to raise the curtain on a new era in United States-Colombia relations with a visit to this Caribbean port on Wednesday, and the acts that follow will probably include shooting at Marxist guerrillas by American-supplied helicopters.</p>
        <p>The visit is all the more important because it comes at a time when the government here has been weakened politically, and peace negotiations with guerrilla groups have stalled.</p>
        <p>In Cartagena, Mr. Clinton will visit a new United States-financed community justice center, walk the stone streets of the walled colonial center to greet pedestrians, give encouraging handshakes to Colombian customs officials and offer condolences to the widows of policemen who have died in combat with the rebels who make money off the drug trade.</p>
        <p>The series of burnished photo opportunities, along with a private meeting with President Andres Pastrana, will symbolize a dramatic departure from a relationship with Colombia that has been cool, if not hostile, in recent years. Only three years ago, the previous Colombian president could not get a United States visa because there was evidence that he received a campaign contribution from the Cali drug cartel.</p>
        <p>Such embarrassing official ties to the cocaine and heroin trade were a major reason why no United States president has set foot on Colombian soil in nearly 11 years. But Mr. Clinton will break that spell with his eight-hour stop here, along with the House speaker, Dennis Hastert, a Republican, and other senior members of Congress from both parties.</p>
        <p>''Colombia has become a first-tier foreign policy issue, and this trip will show that,'' said Arturo Valenzuela, the top Latin America analyst for the National Security Council. ''The president wants to make sure that the bipartisan consensus on Colombia that has developed in the last months of his administration continues on after he leaves office.''</p>
        <p>Despite the trip's brevity, Colombian officials are placing great symbolic importance on the event since it is the kickoff of their $7.5 billion ''Plan Colombia.'' The plan is intended to strengthen the central government's presence throughout the provinces with better courts, aid to peasants displaced by fighting and alternative development projects for farmers dependent on growing coca. The government has lost control of nearly half of its territory to guerrillas and drug traffickers.</p>
        <p>The United States part of the plan is a $1.3 billion aid program recently approved by Congress. It includes 60 military helicopters and training for a new anti-narcotics army brigade to support police efforts in eradicating coca fields. Last Tuesday, Mr. Clinton waived several human rights conditions put on the aid program by Congress, declaring Colombia a national security priority.</p>
        <p>''It's a moment to display our new alliance,'' Colombia's foreign minister, Guillermo Fernandez de Soto, said in an interview last week. ''This visit will show that we have passed from one era in which the United States did not recognize the dimensions of Colombia's problems into another in which the United States is ready to put teeth into an effort that we must make together.''</p>
        <p>Colombian officials have told the White House that Mr. Pastrana would like a strong endorsement from Mr. Clinton for the stalled efforts to negotiate a settlement with two guerrilla groups. He will also press for special trade agreements to help Colombia's ailing textile industry and an exception for Cartagena in the State Department's warning that it is dangerous for American tourists to travel in Colombia.</p>
        <p>For United States officials, the visit will highlight for the American public the importance of helping South America's second-largest country to fight a drug trade that produces 90 percent of the cocaine and about a quarter of the heroin that enter the United States. And American officials hope to underscore that Mr. Pastrana, a Conservative Party leader who took office two years ago, is making a strong effort to break with past corruption.</p>
        <p>The United States has steadily increased its anti-narcotics assistance to Colombia during Mr. Clinton's second term, to $300 million this year from $65 million in 1996. But even though aerial spraying to kill coca crops has increased, coca cultivation mushroomed by 20 percent in 1999, after a 28 percent increase in 1998, says a State Department report.</p>
        <p>Success in the so-called war on drugs is often fleeting, and the deepening United States role in Colombia is not without risks, especially if the guerrillas decide to shoot at the United States-supplied helicopters.</p>
        <p>In fact, the Clinton administration's experience in Colombia so far is that any escalation is bound to have unpredictable consequences. After the Drug Enforcement Administration and the C.I.A. helped the Colombian police break up the Cali drug cartel in the mid 1990's with arrests of its top leaders, smaller trafficking organizations took its place. Those smaller organizations sought the protection of the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia,  the country's largest rebel group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton will press Mr. Pastrana to complement the new military anti-narcotics offensive against those groups in the south with civilian aid programs to avert a refugee problem that could add fighters to the guerrilla ranks and spread the conflict to neighboring countries. American officials say Mr. Clinton will emphasize the importance of holding local elections in the southern provinces, improving the human rights record of the armed forces, providing jobs for refugees and promoting alternative development projects for peasants who currently grow coca.</p>
        <p>''President Clinton wants to put his arm around President Pastrana's shoulder and demonstrate our support,'' said Peter Romero, acting assistant secretary of state for inter-American affairs, ''but also our expectations that a lot of work needs to be done.''</p>
        <p>The Colombian government has a large security presence in Cartagena to protect the two presidents and their large delegations. Colombia police officials say that at least 5,500 troops and police officers will be here, and army units will guard the periphery of the city.</p>
        <p>Colombia has 4 navy frigates and 18 patrol boats in the waters surrounding Cartagena, and 6 military helicopters will patrol the skies over the Clinton delegation. Undercover police officers are patrolling the streets, and electronic cameras and high-powered microphones have been placed atop buildings for surveillance.</p>
        <p>The Army of National Liberation,  Colombia's second-largest rebel group, said it would step up attacks on highway transportation in response to the Clinton visit. The larger rebel group has promised not to interfere with the visit, even while sharply criticizing the growing American role here.</p>
        <p>Alfonso Cano, a senior commander of the group, told Colombian reporters that Mr. Clinton ''will carry suitcases full of the dollars necessary for Colombians to continue killing each other indefinitely.'' He added, ''That's why he is not welcome.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
