<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cerebral Ardor in Affairs of the Mind and the Heart</title>
    <meta content="29KAKU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldstein, Rebecca</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Properties of Light (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFDF1E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cerebral Ardor in Affairs of the Mind and the Heart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews Properties of Light: A Novel of Love, Betrayal and Quantum Physics by Rebecca Goldstein; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PROPERTIES OF LIGHT  A Novel of Love, Betrayal and Quantum Physics  By Rebecca Goldstein  244 pages. Houghton Mifflin. $23.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Goldstein's characters are descendants of Ingmar Bergman's chilly intellectuals and Nathaniel Hawthorne's coldhearted curmudgeons. They want to subordinate the heart to the head, the spirit to the word; they dream of perfectly controlled worlds where messy emotions are subjugated to the ordering dictates of reason.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PROPERTIES OF LIGHT  A Novel of Love, Betrayal and Quantum Physics  By Rebecca Goldstein  244 pages. Houghton Mifflin. $23.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Goldstein's characters are descendants of Ingmar Bergman's chilly intellectuals and Nathaniel Hawthorne's coldhearted curmudgeons. They want to subordinate the heart to the head, the spirit to the word; they dream of perfectly controlled worlds where messy emotions are subjugated to the ordering dictates of reason.</p>
        <p>Justin Childs, the narrator of Ms. Goldstein's lumpy new novel, ''Properties of Light,'' is no exception. Like Eva in ''The Late-Summer Passion of a Woman of Mind'' and Hedda in ''The Dark Sister,'' Justin lives inside his head, and he has equipped himself with forbidding intellectual armor. Even as a child he was an absolutist, reciting the law of the excluded middle. (''Every statement is either true or false, and no statement is both!'') Now, as a physicist at a well-known university, he devotes his days and nights to trying to decipher the hidden rules of the universe.</p>
        <p>Justin's affair with a beautiful young woman named Dana -- who just happens to be the daughter of an eminent physicist named Mallach, revered by Justin for his unorthodox theories -- tests his rationalist view of the world and gives Ms. Goldstein a chance to explore her perennial themes about the dichotomies between mind and body, intellect and passion, logos and eros.</p>
        <p>It is Ms. Goldstein's achievement in this volume that she has managed that very difficult task of making palpable the sort of cerebral ardor possessed by scientists and thinkers working at the very height of their powers. She communicates the almost erotic power that ideas can impart, ''the bliss'' experienced by Justin and his colleagues when they make a breakthrough in their work, lifting ''a bit of the heavy veil the material world wears across her face'' to catch ''a feature of a feature never quite so glimpsed before.''</p>
        <p>In doing this, however, she spends an enormous amount of time trying to convey to the reader the intricacies of Justin's work in quantum mechanics, a feat she never manages to pull off. There are pages and pages of ponderous and -- to the lay reader, at least -- perplexing discussions of matters like ''wave function,'' something that is ''Lorentz invariant'' and ''backwards causation.'' Worse, the novel's characters are given to saying things like: ''Nonlocality is merely the expression of quantum entanglement.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Goldstein, who once taught philosophy at Barnard College, is interested in using Justin and Mallach's theories about ''a realistic model of nonrelativistic quantum mechanics'' to explore the relationship between reality and theory, and the role that randomness and chance may play in the cosmos, concepts that also serve as metaphors for her characters' personal dilemmas. Unfortunately her descriptions of their work feel so contrived, not to mention impenetrable, that the reader's attention soon begins to wander.</p>
        <p>Her depictions of her characters' emotional lives can be equally heavy-handed. Justin comes across as a parody of the arrogant, unfeeling scientist. He's the sort of fellow who seasons his childhood reminiscences with Latinisms and who cannot comprehend the notion that there are sensations ''that lay deeper down than reason.''</p>
        <p>He grows irritated with Dana for adoring her dead mother, because he regards her mother as a clownish drunk with silly New Age beliefs. And he's so possessive of Dana that he resents her for having an inner life inaccessible to him: ''It was a torment to need so desperately to know the contents of her mind, the hidden variables behind her words and silences and laughter, the varieties of intent behind her murmured mmm's.''</p>
        <p>Dana herself emerges as a sort of variation on Rappaccini's daughter, depicted in the Hawthorne story of that name. She has devoted her life to her brilliant, eccentric father, and her devotion alters the course of her life. She is a strange, dreamy girl, described as being ''mind-proud'' the way ''other women are house- or husband-proud.''</p>
        <p>As for her father, Professor Mallach, he is portrayed as a sort of alter ego to Justin -- another enormously gifted but fatally self-absorbed physicist with a similar proclivity to anger. Years ago, we're told, Mallach formulated a groundbreaking theory that was ignored by the academic establishment, and that experience, coupled with his wife's betrayal, has driven him to the brink of madness.</p>
        <p>He has more or less put aside the practice of physics until Justin appears on the scene and proposes that they -- along with Dana -- collaborate on finding a way to reconcile quantum mechanics and relativity, ''the two monumental theories of 20th-century physics.'' It is a hubristic proposal that reawakens not only Mallach's long-buried scientific gifts but also his fury at being marginalized and betrayed.</p>
        <p>Though it's impossible not to admire Ms. Goldstein's efforts to write a Gothic suspense story that's also a novel of ideas, her characters remain too two-dimensional and her storytelling too ponderous for the reader to ever become fully engaged. There are some brilliant glimpses of scientists' passion for their work and some well-observed depictions of life in the hothouse world of academe, but in the end, sadly, they're not enough for either a thriller or a philosophic novel.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
