<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A new campaign for Courvoisier, brandy of Napoleon, looks for younger, hipper customers.</title>
    <meta content="Y29ADC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cognac</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courvoisier</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Allied Domecq Spirits</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Drush (Ad Agency)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DeBartolomeo, Stephanie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stamler, Bernard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cognac</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brandy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EFDB1E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A new campaign for Courvoisier, brandy of Napoleon, looks for younger, hipper customers.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bernard Stamler</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stamler, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephanie DeBartolomeo of Allied Domecq Spirits aims advertising for Courvoisier at young, urban adults, mostly blacks, who drink twice as much Cognac as anyone else; ad photo; dRush LLC is running hip-hop style campaign (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT may still be the self-proclaimed Cognac de Napoleon, but Courvoisier is definitely not just the emperor's brandy anymore.</p>
        <p>Sure, it is still the favorite of some dinner-jacketed gentlemen in wood- paneled rooms. But Courvoisier's future lies with a different, more vibrant constituency, according to Stephanie DeBartolomeo, marketing director for the brand at Allied Domecq Spirits USA in Westport, Conn. And it is to these people -- ''young, urban adults who subscribe to hip-hop culture, the vast majority of whom are African-American'' -- that the company, a unit of Allied Domecq of London, has now decided to appeal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT may still be the self-proclaimed Cognac de Napoleon, but Courvoisier is definitely not just the emperor's brandy anymore.</p>
        <p>Sure, it is still the favorite of some dinner-jacketed gentlemen in wood- paneled rooms. But Courvoisier's future lies with a different, more vibrant constituency, according to Stephanie DeBartolomeo, marketing director for the brand at Allied Domecq Spirits USA in Westport, Conn. And it is to these people -- ''young, urban adults who subscribe to hip-hop culture, the vast majority of whom are African-American'' -- that the company, a unit of Allied Domecq of London, has now decided to appeal.</p>
        <p>These consumers are different, she said. For one thing, ''they drink twice as much Cognac as anyone else.'' For another, they believe that Courvoisier is uniquely a ''symbol of stature and class.'' That is because it is ''the only cognac that resonates as French to them,'' even though all true Cognac must, by definition, hail from western France. Consequently, Courvoisier is ''the only liqueur that urban young adults actually call a fashion accessory,'' Ms. DeBartolomeo said.</p>
        <p>Because the group's taste in music is said to define its taste in other things, too, for its marketing efforts Courvoisier has decided to go to the source: dRush L.L.C. of New York, the joint venture between Donny Deutsch, chairman of Deutsch Inc., and Russell Simmons, the music and entertainment executive. Mr. Simmons's Rush Communications group includes Def Jam Records, which helped kick off rap music and hip hop, as well as Phat Pharm, the clothing company, which sells the look in its own outlets and in department stores nationwide.</p>
        <p>And dRush has just introduced a campaign titled House of Courvoisier, intended to make Courvoisier appeal to ''urban influential trend setters,'' the company says.</p>
        <p>The campaign, which will also feature event sponsorships and billboards, will run to ''considerably more than $5 million'' in print and broadcast by year's end, Ms. DeBartolomeo said. It is set to break next week with a four-page spread in the September issue of Vogue and to continue through the autumn in magazines like Essence, Vibe, Elle, GQ and XXL.</p>
        <p>The ads represent quite a departure from those in Courvoisier's previous ''welcome to the state of Courvoisier'' campaign by Weiss Stagliano Partners, which did not directly challenge notions of Cognac as an after-dinner drink, and which featured unexplained, puzzling photographs, like one that showed people running up a hill toward a giant rock.</p>
        <p>That has all been changed. For example, two of the four pages running in Vogue feature images of low-cut dresses and high-heeled, zip-up boots emblazoned with tiny silhouettes of Napoleon. They also feature pictures of cocktail glasses and suggest flat out that Courvoisier should be drunk with ice or mixed with pineapple and orange juice, an idea that might alarm Cognac purists but one that is apparently in keeping with the way young consumers actually drink the liqueur.</p>
        <p>They also suggest that the drink should henceforth be called by the nickname CV. The reason: Courvoisier has become more than a brandy; now it is also ''a badge,'' according to Ms. DeBartolomeo.</p>
        <p>Such a description might astonish the Emperor Bonaparte were he around to hear it, especially because the CV the ads promote is actually Courvoisier XO, which contains 25-  to 30-year-old Cognac, and is among the brand's most expensive products, retailing at $100 a bottle or more. But it makes perfect sense to Mr. Simmons, who calls the images in his ads ''aspirational and decadent.''</p>
        <p>''Courvoisier has already got a certain kind of image, a certain kind of attitude and integrity,'' he said. ''Our goal is to build a strong base in the young community, and to market it without cheapening it down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Simmons has already attempted similar feats for other clients like ESPN, HBO and Coca-Cola, for whom he created spots featuring the rapper and actor L. L. Cool J, a Def Jam Records artist. But there are those who think he faces a more formidable challenge this time with Courvoisier, which sold 440,000 cases last year but lags far behind the category leader Hennessy, which sold 1.38 million cases, according to the Adams Handbook Advance, an industry publication.</p>
        <p>''Courvoisier is an old brand and, over the years, it has fallen back in the pack,'' said Tom Pirko, president of Bevmark, a beverage consultant in Santa Barbara, Calif. ''It has also been a black brand of preference for a long, long time.''</p>
        <p>''If they can find a way to integrate it to the spread of hip hop, that could be really something,'' he continued. But while Essence and Vibe ''are a much better match, I don't know how many of your consumers you're going to find reading Vogue.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Simmons insists that Courvoisier's target consumers are ''very into the American dream,'' and that they do read Vogue. He said that he expected his campaign to catch on and to ignite an enormous growth in Courvoisier.  And he says he believes that the results will be immediately measurable.</p>
        <p>''If they can't count their money,'' he said, ''then I haven't done my job.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
