<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When It Was a Game in Black-and-White, Called by a Redhead</title>
    <meta content="29SAND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fox Sports</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Dodgers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E1DF1F31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When It Was a Game in Black-and-White, Called by a Redhead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Sandomir TV Sports column praises Fox Sports for televising Los Angeles Dodgers-Chicago Cubs game and showing how baseball production has changed since first game was televised in 1939 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since its birth in 1994, Fox Sports has led a full-throttle charge into using advanced technological and graphics tools in its broadcasts.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, the toys enhance the telecasts, sometimes they overwhelm them. They have even angered fans; remember the glowing hockey puck with the red comet tail?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since its birth in 1994, Fox Sports has led a full-throttle charge into using advanced technological and graphics tools in its broadcasts.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, the toys enhance the telecasts, sometimes they overwhelm them. They have even angered fans; remember the glowing hockey puck with the red comet tail?</p>
        <p>On Saturday, though, Fox reversed gears, heading back in time with the Dodgers-Cubs game to show how baseball production has changed since the first televised game was called by Red Barber on station W2XBS, between Brooklyn and Cincinnati, from Ebbets Field in 1939.</p>
        <p>There was Fox's Joe Buck, jokingly dubbed the ''old redhead,'' calling the early innings solo, heard through muffled audio, calling a game in grainy black-and-white. Back then, two cameras followed the action, one behind home plate, one behind the third-base line. There were no close-ups. Buck called the game as if on radio.</p>
        <p>With each half-inning, the era changed, and the scratchy black-and-white gradually turned crystal clear. Then muddy color turned brilliant. Graphics, at first nonexistent, were then seen mounted by hand on an easel. Eventually, they came out electronically, then by computer.</p>
        <p>Tim McCarver did not join Buck until the third inning, designated to look like 1957, when players-turned-analysts became common.</p>
        <p>The first replay -- at full speed, from one angle -- popped up in the bottom of the third, or ''1961.''</p>
        <p>By the sixth, everything was contemporary, and the game lacked inherent interest. Until then, Fox created a television gem, a nostalgic road trip for some, an educational foray for others. The producer Mike Weisman lovingly recreated the look of games he grew up watching and others he later produced for NBC.</p>
        <p>''I had several flashbacks,'' Weisman said. ''This took me back to watching Yankee games in the 1960's, and when I started in baseball at NBC in 1972, I remember it was my hand that was caught on camera fixing graphics. I had flashbacks of working with Vin Scully and Joe Garagiola and Curt Gowdy.''</p>
        <p>The production was also a tribute to Harry Coyle, the late NBC Sports director who created the way viewers watched baseball. The Hall of Fame has declined to add Coyle to its broadcasters' wing because he was not an on-air announcer. Yet he was as influential as many of those already in Cooperstown.</p>
        <p>In Fox's production truck on Saturday, a photograph of Coyle was tacked to a wall next to Bill Webb, the game's director. Written on a piece of paper above the photo was: ''The world's best television director -- living or dead.''</p>
        <p>Fox ended up surrendering to modern production techniques earlier than it had intended a few weeks ago.</p>
        <p>''Unlike doing a documentary, where you can time things out and spend a planned amount of time on each inning, we had the burden of not only doing history, but we had a game to cover,'' Weisman said. ''We didn't know how long the top of the first would go. It ended up going scary fast, but the bottom could have gone on for 40 minutes. We could have done the whole inning like it was 1939, but to me, if you leave a telecast or a movie wanting more, you've been successful.''</p>
        <p>Weisman said his major fear was a story developing in the early innings when he was not using color or replays. Fortunately, Fox was also producing a shadow 2000-era game, using all modern equipment.</p>
        <p>''If Sammy Sosa was injured, whether we were in 1939 or 1944, I was going to break out, and show the highlights in slow motion, in color, and explain what was going on,'' Weisman said.</p>
        <p>The only serious drawback was the use of Steve Lyons as Keith Olbermann's co-star in the pregame studio newsreel and at breaks between innings. The excellent archival work of those productions were nearly undermined by Lyons's presence as a ninny for all eras. Someone at Fox loves Lyons or has mistaken him for Ernie Kovacs. He is not a comic actor.</p>
        <p>Airwaves</p>
        <p>The rain delay at the NEC Invitational on Sunday hindered CBS's ability to capitalize on Tiger Woods's 11-stroke victory. The 5.3 overnight rating from 2-7 p.m. fell from a 5.5 last year. When play resumed at 5:15 p.m., the rating jumped to a 7.2 before CBS handed coverage in the Eastern and Central time zones to TNN at 7 o'clock. The tournament stayed on CBS in the Mountain and Pacific zones, where it recorded a 4.3 from 7 to 8:45 p.m. An overnight rating point equals 659,000 television homes.</p>
        <p>ESPN's ''The Season,'' a two-part documentary made by NYT Television, a division of The New York Times Company, takes an engrossing look at North Penn High School's 1999 football team. The documentary, which concludes tonight at 8 p.m., uses extraordinary access to a season of Pennsylvania high school football to create balanced, riveting portraits of a grim coach, who must face his father's better team in two crucial games, and several of his players.</p>
        <p>The Fox network's film, ''Ali: An American Hero'' (Thursday at 8 p.m.), is a decent biographical treatment of Muhammad Ali, with few apparent distortions of the man's life. David Ramsey is a reasonable facsimile of Ali.</p>
        <p>Houston's 79-73 victory over the Liberty to win the Women's National Basketball Association title Saturday generated a 2.1 overnight rating on NBC, up 24 percent from 1999.</p>
        <p>Futbol de Primera, which is partly owned by the soccer announcer Andres Cantor, has acquired the United States Spanish-language radio rights to the 2002 and 2006 World Cups. The rights will eventually be resold.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
