<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Investors May Now Eye Costs of Stock Options</title>
    <meta content="Y29PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morgenson, Gretchen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6D81E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Investors May Now Eye Costs of Stock Options</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN MORGENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Morgenson, Gretchen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Market Place column on stock options as major secret expense that does not show up on earnings reports of corporations; sideways slide of stock market in recent days may inspire investors to take more notice of what option programs are really costing them in way of lower earnings; list (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is one of the prettiest lies in corporate America. Stock options dispensed to executives and workers are not accounted for as an employee expense, even though they clearly are. So companies that reward their employees with stock options do not include the costs of those programs in their overall expenses, giving their earnings a boost.</p>
        <p>As long as the stock market rose, few investors seemed to care that corporate earnings were overstated. But now with the stock market mostly moving sideways, perhaps they will begin to notice what option programs really cost them in the way of lower earnings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is one of the prettiest lies in corporate America. Stock options dispensed to executives and workers are not accounted for as an employee expense, even though they clearly are. So companies that reward their employees with stock options do not include the costs of those programs in their overall expenses, giving their earnings a boost.</p>
        <p>As long as the stock market rose, few investors seemed to care that corporate earnings were overstated. But now with the stock market mostly moving sideways, perhaps they will begin to notice what option programs really cost them in the way of lower earnings.</p>
        <p>Pat McConnell, a senior managing director and head of the accounting and tax group in equity research at Bear, Stearns, has completed a comprehensive study examining how earnings at the companies in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index would fare if employee stock option grants were accounted for as an expense.</p>
        <p>Given that option mania has swept the country, it is not surprising that Ms. McConnell finds that options had a bigger and more negative impact on corporate earnings last year than ever. Net income at the S.&amp; P. 500 companies, which totaled $51.68 a share in 1999, would have been 6 percent lower if options were accounted for as an expense, she said. This compares with a 4 percent reduction in 1998 and a 3 percent hit in 1997.</p>
        <p>One reason for the big jump is that last year was the first year in which company financial statements reflected the full impact of some stock option programs. The Financial Accounting Standards Board requires companies to include in the footnotes to their financial statements the effects of options granted in fiscal years beginning after Dec. 15, 1994. Because many companies' plans allow employees' options to vest in five years or less, last year was the first in which the full effect of some of those plans appeared.</p>
        <p>Accounting rule makers recommend that companies charge the fair value of options granted to employees as a compensation expense, but they do not require it. If companies do not run the costs of options through their profit and loss statements, they must disclose in a footnote in their annual reports what net income and per-share earnings would have been had the cost of stock options been charged.</p>
        <p>Most companies choose the latter approach. In fact, Ms. McConnell identified only 2 of the 500 companies in the S.&amp; P. index that account for options as a cost: Boeing and Winn-Dixie.</p>
        <p>Naturally, the larger the option grants, the bigger the hit to a company's earnings. Ms. McConnell found four industry groups in the S.&amp; P. 500 whose earnings would have declined 10 percent or more in each of the last three years if option grants were counted as an expense. Companies in the business of health care services would have shown a 38 percent decline in earnings last year; computer networking concerns, 24 percent; commercial and consumer services companies, 21 percent; and communications equipment makers, 19 percent.</p>
        <p>Earnings at 122 companies -- almost one-quarter of the stocks in the index -- declined more than 10 percent last year when stock options were accounted for as an expense. That compares with 79 companies showing such declines in 1998 and 61 companies in 1997, Ms. McConnell said.</p>
        <p>But earnings at 21 companies fell by more than half when adjusted for stock options. These included McDermott International, an oil services company; Yahoo, the Internet company; Autodesk, a computer software designer; Polaroid; and Palm.</p>
        <p>Even more compelling, 12 companies that had an operating profit in 1999 would have had an operating loss if stock options were considered an expense. For instance, the $6 million in operating income that Micron Technology made last year would have been an operating loss of $120 million. Grant Jones, a Micron spokesman, said, ''We treat options in accordance with generally accepted accounting principles.''</p>
        <p>The overall effect of stock options on corporate earnings is decidedly negative. According to Ms. McConnell's study, the S.&amp; P.'s three-year compound annual earnings growth rate dwindles from 11 percent to 9 percent when options are considered a cost. And the compound annual growth in operating income for the S.&amp; P. slows from a three-year rate of 12 percent to 10 percent when the favorable accounting treatment for options is eliminated.</p>
        <p>Ms. McConnell expects the impact of options on earnings to continue to grow in coming years. Will accounting rules ever change to reflect the true cost of options? ''I think in three to five years, if standard setters outside the U.S. adopt a fair-value approach for employee stock options, then I think the U.S. will have to take another look at this,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, she said she was relieved to find that the overall impact of stock options on S.&amp; P. earnings remained below 10 percent and that she believed that investors were fully aware of the problem that stock option mania posed among technology companies. Nevertheless, she added: ''I think it essential that investors look at this information in making comparisons. If you want to buy the best company in an industry, you have to take this into consideration or you may be misled.''</p>
        <p>And investors need more information, she suggested. ''While the footnote information allows you to dig in,'' she said, ''it's not a substitute for doing the accounting correctly in the financial statements themselves. In addition, this footnote is only provided annually. Investors need this information more often and sooner.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
