<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Questions Raised by a Political Period Piece</title>
    <meta content="29CRAD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jean Cocteau Repertory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blitzstein, Marc (1905-1964)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuller, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cradle Will Rock, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DD1E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1009" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Questions Raised by a Political Period Piece</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews Jean Cocteau Repertory Co revival of Marc Blitzstein's The Cradle Will Rock, directed by David Fuller; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marc Blitzstein's musical position paper in defense of labor unions, ''The Cradle Will Rock,'' is a period piece that begs an understanding of its period: the later years of the Depression when unions were exercising fresh muscles and being ferociously opposed by industrialists.</p>
        <p>That a class war was imminent and apt to be kindled by Blitzstein's proud agitprop was the evident fear of the federal government, which had financed the show under the auspices of a New Deal agency, the Federal Theater Project, but withdrew its support at the last moment, shuttering the theater on opening night, June 16, 1937.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marc Blitzstein's musical position paper in defense of labor unions, ''The Cradle Will Rock,'' is a period piece that begs an understanding of its period: the later years of the Depression when unions were exercising fresh muscles and being ferociously opposed by industrialists.</p>
        <p>That a class war was imminent and apt to be kindled by Blitzstein's proud agitprop was the evident fear of the federal government, which had financed the show under the auspices of a New Deal agency, the Federal Theater Project, but withdrew its support at the last moment, shuttering the theater on opening night, June 16, 1937.</p>
        <p>Thus was engendered one of theater history's most legendary show-must-go-on stories: the audience and the cast, led by the director, Orson Welles, and the producer, John Houseman, walked to another theater and performed the show anyway, with Blitzstein at the piano and the actors, forbidden by their unions to appear onstage, defiantly singing and reciting their lines from their seats in the auditorium.</p>
        <p>This is all so melodramatic that it would seem to be unfathomable by today's theatergoers -- well, at least until a mayor threatens to shut down an art museum. But that aside, the times, the economy and the workplace obviously look different; our hot buttons are not the same. Art frightens some people now for other reasons; communism looms to almost no one as either threat or panacea. And no matter what you think of Nafta or how outraged by American companies exploiting foreign workers, the issue of labor versus management has evolved to be considerably cloudier than Blitzstein's good-versus-evil presentation.</p>
        <p>In ''Cradle'' you're either fer us or agin us. And at a time when Al Gore is casting himself as a populist, the paradigms have obviously taken on some ambiguity.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the new Off Broadway production of ''Cradle'' by the Jean Cocteau Repertory Company at the Bouwerie Lane Theater is steadfast in its championing of the original. The director, David Fuller, has imbued the show with an earnest nostalgia, even recalling the famous opening night with several scenes staged in the aisles of the tiny house, and having actors, on occasion, make their entrances through a side door from the street.</p>
        <p>It all results in a production that is high-minded, energetic and amusingly quaint. Blitzstein's play is a story set in Steeltown, U.S.A., that pits a noble union organizer, Larry Foreman, against the powerful Mr. Mister, who owns the steel mill and holds the town's religious and civic leaders in his thrall. It consists of a series of scenes in which everyone who does not adamantly oppose Mr. Mister as corrupt -- the press, the clergy, the artists who fawn on his wife, Mrs. Mister, for her patronage -- are prostitutes, in the show's leading metaphor, except the woman who actually does sell her body because her virtue is sacrificed to need. She does it for food.</p>
        <p>This is unsubtle stuff; its power comes from its righteous gall but the best this production musters is a sincere mimicking of a passion that was heartily felt long ago. Part of this has to do, perhaps, with the small theater; Blitzstein's grandiosity is necessarily writ small here. And perhaps it has to do with many in the cast (members of the Cocteau company, including a few interns), not being old enough to remember Ho Chi Minh, not to mention Mussolini.</p>
        <p>The performers here understand well enough that Blitzstein intended acrid satire. But with a couple of exceptions (notably two longstanding company members, Elise Stone as Moll, the prostitute, whose performance has a lovely, plaintive quality, and Craig Smith as Mr. Mister, whose potency has just the slightest suggestion of puncturablility), the performances come across as glib. Their largely conventional sense of hyperbole feels on the one hand like guesswork at issue-driven passions that no longer make headlines. On the other hand they're not hyperbolic enough as if a post-modern irony has made the actors fearful of the show's bald display. Most notably, as Foreman, Jason Crowl sings well, but there's more contrived bluster than stage-holding heart about him.</p>
        <p>Blitzstein's score, with its echoes of Weill and dissonant variations on popular forms, had a novel punch in its day, something that the Tim Robbins film of last year, ''Cradle Will Rock,'' for all its show-biz romanticizing of the events leading up to the show's famous opening, satisfyingly preserved. Here, played behind the show's thin convictions by an onstage pianist, Charles Berigan, it has been robbed of its acerbic bite -- it doesn't help that not all the singers land consistently on Blitzstein's melodic astringencies -- leaving it feeling rather humorlessly fervent.</p>
        <p>The humor, instead, is of another sort; in some furiously rendered interludes, Mr. Berigan takes on the aspect of a player behind a screened silent film, cranking up the tension when little Nell is tied to the railroad track.</p>
        <p>In the end, it all feels terribly ardent, even entertainingly so, but with a whimsy that's probably unintended. It leaves the audience chuckling with the memory of how serious everything used to be.</p>
        <p>THE CRADLE WILL ROCK</p>
        <p>Book, music and lyrics by Marc Blitzstein; directed by David Fuller; musical direction by Charles Berigan; choreography by Barbara Brandt; sets by Mark Fitzgibbons; lighting by Izzy Einsidler; costumes by Irene V. Hatch. Presented by the Jean Cocteau Repertory, Mr. Fuller, producing artistic director. At the Bouwerie Lane Theater, 330 Bowery, East Village.</p>
        <p>WITH: Elise Stone (Moll and Ella Hammer), Christopher Black (President Prexy, Junior Mister and Gus), Tim Deak (Editor Daily and Professor Mamie), Angela Madden (Mrs. Mister), Craig Smith (Mr. Mister), Jason Crowl (Larry Foreman) and Jennifer Herzog (Dick, Sister Mister, Sadie and Reporter One).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
