<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mine to Close, as Tribes Prevail Over Fashion Fad</title>
    <meta content="Y29MIN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pumice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strip Mining</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arizona Tufflite (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sierra Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milloy, Ross E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock and Stone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D81E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mine to Close, as Tribes Prevail Over Fashion Fad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSS E. MILLOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Milloy, Ross E</byline>
      <dateline>FLAGSTAFF, Ariz., Aug. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal government and Phoenix, Ariz, mining company Arizona Tufflite reach agreement under which White Vulcan pumice strip mine on Sugarloaf Mountain near Flagstaff will close within six months; agreement is reached after years of struggle by Sierra Club and 13 American Indian tribes to limit company's mining, saying it damages environment of peaks, which Indians believe are sacred ground; pumice from mine was used in production of stonewashed denim; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a long way from the catwalks of Paris to the craggy forests of the San Francisco Peaks, but the two have been linked for more than a decade by the demand for stonewashed denim: new jeans made to look old by laundering them with pieces of volcanic pumice.</p>
        <p>The Right Bank provided the styles, but much of the pumice came from a strip mine on Sugarloaf Mountain, one of the Peaks, twelve miles northeast of here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a long way from the catwalks of Paris to the craggy forests of the San Francisco Peaks, but the two have been linked for more than a decade by the demand for stonewashed denim: new jeans made to look old by laundering them with pieces of volcanic pumice.</p>
        <p>The Right Bank provided the styles, but much of the pumice came from a strip mine on Sugarloaf Mountain, one of the Peaks, twelve miles northeast of here.</p>
        <p>''We were rated as the No. 1 supplier to the industry back in the mid-1990's,'' said Ed Morgan, vice president of Arizona Tufflite, the Phoenix company that owns the mine. Mr. Morgan estimated sales by his company at $25 million to $30 million over the last 10 years.</p>
        <p>''Our pumice-washed jeans went all over the world,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But for just as many years, the Sierra Club and 13 American Indian tribes have been trying to limit the company's mining, saying that it damages the environment of the Peaks, which the Indians believe are sacred ground.</p>
        <p>Today, they succeeded.</p>
        <p>On a rocky outcrop overlooking Tufflite's 100-foot-deep White Vulcan pumice mine, federal officials and the company signed an agreement to close the 90-acre site within six months.</p>
        <p>That was welcome news for the Hopi tribe, which believes that the Peaks are the home of kachina spirits who live part of the year as clouds in the mountains, and bring rain. ''Our people have believed these things for thousands of years,'' said Wayne Taylor, chairman of the Hopi tribe.</p>
        <p>For the Navajo, the mountains are one of four borders of their universe.</p>
        <p>Just as galling as the desecration of the land, Indian representatives said, was the purpose of the mining. ''Further destruction of the countryside in this sacred area just so the fashion-conscious can wear jeans which make them seem to have spent time outside, is to us, ludicrous,'' a tribal leader wrote to the government.</p>
        <p>''You should have to work to get that look,'' said Andrew Bessler, an organizer for the Sierra Club who runs the group's ''Save The Peaks'' effort linking the Indian tribes with environmentalists. ''Besides, stonewashing takes two years out of the life of the jeans, and that's why the industry likes it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>When Tufflite applied for a permit to expand its operations in 1998, the campaign by the Indians and the Sierra Club went into overdrive with concerts, demonstrations at the mine site, and relentless pressuring of local, state and federal officials.</p>
        <p>All 13 tribes passed resolutions opposing the mine, as did the city of Flagstaff and Coconino County, where the mine is located. Of 6,000 public comments received by the Forest Service on the expansion project, only four favored it.</p>
        <p>''I'm pleased that this mine is being shut down and this long controversy is ending,'' Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt said in a statement. ''It's time to restore the Peaks to their natural splendor.''</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, the government will pay Tufflite $1 million and drop a lawsuit that demanded $300,000 in unpaid royalties for previous sales of the pumice. In return, the company will shut down the mine, which has just four employees, but will be able to sell extracted pumice for the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>''This is a great victory,'' Mr. Bessler said. ''It will protect a key cultural and archaeological site from the continued desecration of the land.''</p>
        <p>To Mr. Morgan, the mine closure is a relief. ''After all these years of fighting, we decided that the government was going to make it harder and harder to do business,'' Mr. Morgan said. ''We were paying our lawyers, plus paying our taxes which paid the government's lawyers, and in the end it just didn't make sense to keep going.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Morgan said the best years of using pumice to stonewash denim are behind Tufflite anyway. ''They've got new techniques now that use enzymes that are biodegradable and cheaper,'' he said. ''Our market was declining.''</p>
        <p>As for the Indians, at least one tribal chairman saw significance in an unusual event in these drought-stricken mountains just minutes after the agreement was signed.</p>
        <p>It rained.</p>
        <p>''That's the spirits' way of thanking us,'' Mr. Taylor said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
