<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Changing of the Guard for a Vast Empire; After Whirlwind Expansion, the Met's New Chairman of Asian Art Takes His Time</title>
    <meta content="29COLL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Museum of Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotter, Holland</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fong, Wen C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E6DD1E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2230" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Changing of the Guard for a Vast Empire; After Whirlwind Expansion, the Met's New Chairman of Asian Art Takes His Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOLLAND COTTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotter, Holland</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Wen C Fong, who is retiring as head of Metropolitan Museum of Art's Asian art department, which he has transformed into the world's largest and most comprehensive collection of Asian art under one roof; Asian art occupied a marginal place at museum when he joined it in 1971; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thirty years ago Asian art led a marginal life at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. In 1970 the only Chinese works on view were in a room of early Buddhist sculpture and some cases of ceramics. As late as 1990 Indian art meant an assortment of objects crammed into dimly lighted vitrines on the Great Hall balcony.</p>
        <p>Things have changed. The museum now has more than 50 permanent galleries devoted to the largest and most comprehensive collection of Asian art under one roof. These days the Met is fond of calling itself a ''museum of Asian art within a museum,'' and it is justified in doing so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thirty years ago Asian art led a marginal life at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. In 1970 the only Chinese works on view were in a room of early Buddhist sculpture and some cases of ceramics. As late as 1990 Indian art meant an assortment of objects crammed into dimly lighted vitrines on the Great Hall balcony.</p>
        <p>Things have changed. The museum now has more than 50 permanent galleries devoted to the largest and most comprehensive collection of Asian art under one roof. These days the Met is fond of calling itself a ''museum of Asian art within a museum,'' and it is justified in doing so.</p>
        <p>What went right? Several things. The international market in Asian art opened up. (Trade relations with China were renewed in 1972, and tons -- literally -- of Southeast Asian material found its way to the West in the wake of the Vietnam War.) In addition a number of fine American private collections were ripe for institutional picking. And the Met went into a global expansion mode.</p>
        <p>The catalytic agent, though, was the arrival at the museum in 1971 of Wen C. Fong, a highly esteemed art historian at Princeton University, as special consultant for Far Eastern affairs.</p>
        <p>It was, technically, a part-time job. Mr. Fong's contract required him to be at the museum only one day a week. But over the next three decades he wooed collectors, engineered acquisitions, beefed up the curatorial staff, campaigned for gallery space and transformed an institution that had come to collecting Asian material very late in the game -- great American collections of Asian art like those at the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston were put together nearly a century ago -- into a major international contender.</p>
        <p>On his watch some superb collections came into the museum, and permanent Asian galleries gradually materialized, many carved out of space once reserved for blockbuster shows. The Astor Court garden and the Douglas Dillon galleries for Chinese painting and calligraphy opened in 1981. Next came Japanese galleries in 1987, South and Southeast Asian galleries in 1994, new Chinese painting and decorative arts galleries in 1997 and finally a Korean gallery in 1998.</p>
        <p>This summer Mr. Fong, 69, announced his retirement from the museum, where he has long been consultative chairman of the Asian art department. His position has been taken by another Met veteran, James C. Y. Watt, 63, a curator at the museum for 15 years. Both men were born in China. Both are respected scholars with similar worries about directions the field is taking. Both are, through force of personality and simply by being at the Met, part of a high-profile moment for Asian art in the West.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fong was born in Shanghai in 1930 and was given a traditional at-home education. ''I was taught by an old scholar, which meant that I studied old things,'' he said in an interview. ''But there was family pressure on me to take up engineering, so I escaped to this country to study art.''</p>
        <p>After finishing graduate work in Chinese art at Princeton, he taught there almost without break until his retirement from the faculty last year. He established the first American doctoral program in Chinese art history there in 1964; many leading curators and teachers now at work across the country are his former students. He was chairman of the executive committee of the Art Museum at Princeton when the Met called.</p>
        <p>''I was hired as an outside consultant, which I always remained,'' Mr. Fong said. ''Thomas Hoving was the museum's director at the time, but the man behind the Asian initiative was Douglas Dillon, the president of the board of trustees. He wanted to buy gobs and gobs of art.''</p>
        <p>And buy the museum did, beginning with 500 Japanese objects that it took five years to pay for. In 1973 the Met acquired a group of Chinese paintings from the collector C. C. Wang, beginning a long association.</p>
        <p>''Collecting opportunities are still plentiful,'' Mr. Fong said, ''but the market is so treacherous now in terms of forgeries.'' One of the Met's Wang purchases, the colossal scroll titled ''The Riverbank'' and attributed by the museum to the near-mythical 10th-century painter Dong Yuan,  has been pegged as a 20th-century fake by several leading scholars. Mr. Fong stands by its authenticity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fong's path wasn't always smooth. He said that when in 1971 he proposed mounting an exhibition of calligraphy, the art form revered above all others by the Chinese, one museum official wanted to put the show in the ceramics cases on the Great Hall balcony. ''It's just like postage stamps, isn't it?'' the official said.</p>
        <p>This fall, the museum will present the largest Chinese calligraphy survey ever mounted in the United States. Titled ''The Embodied Image: Chinese Calligraphy From the John B. Elliott Collection,'' it will open on Sept. 15 and fill all 13 of the Chinese painting galleries.</p>
        <p>Does Mr. Fong perceive an increased awareness of Asian art in the United States over the last few years? Yes and no. He acknowledges that for museums across the country ''Asian art is where the action is,'' with collections and exhibition space growing. But public reception is another story.</p>
        <p>The response to blockbusters is strong. The Met's 1996 traveling exhibition ''Splendors of Imperial China: Treasures From the National Palace Museum, Taipei'' drew a total of 800,000 visitors and had the largest average daily attendance for any show in the world that year. But, says Mr. Fong, ''when I give a lecture at the Met today, I see the same faces in the front row that I saw 30 years ago. The young people don't seem interested.''</p>
        <p>He's leery of the kind of attention that the field is getting in academe today. At a panel on the future of Asian art museums in the United States, held at the Japan Society in the spring, Mr. Fong spoke impatiently of the ''questions of European Orientalism'' and ''identity politics that bedevil our analysis and interpretation of Asian art.'' And he said  the trend of emphasizing social theory over connoisseurship, teaching from books and slides rather than objects, was a mistake.</p>
        <p>''Young people are very stressed out now,'' he said. ''They're under pressure to do the latest thing. But I'm an optimist. Everything will get sorted out eventually.''</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Fong's future projects for the Met, where he is now Douglas Dillon curator emeritus of Asian art, is a show that will bring social history and connoisseurship together. Scheduled to open in January, it will be an exhibition of 19th- and 20th-century Chinese painting selected from nearly 500 examples given to the Met by the collector Robert H. Ellsworth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fong, who knew several of the artists personally, is preparing the catalog. ''It's hard to imagine how one can write about noble failures,'' he said. ''But as long as there's nobility, it's worth it.'' He is quick to note that his interest is less in the political details of the Communist era than in the broader theme of ''a tradition being uprooted.'' As to the era that ends with own his own departure from the Met, his view is upbeat, not to say Churchillian: ''Now we are at the end of the beginning.''</p>
        <p>The energy Mr. Fong brought to his work was Herculean, as his successor is the first to acknowledge. Mr. Watt was easing into semiretirement when the Met asked him to take over the department. ''Recently, I've had the great leisure of being able to read for two hours every morning,'' he said. ''Now I'll have to forgo that again for a while.''</p>
        <p>Where Mr. Fong's demeanor is outgoing and voluble, Mr. Watt's is low-key and reticent, qualities reflected in his views of the immediate direction Asian art at the Met will take. ''We need to quiet down a bit,'' Mr. Watt said. ''We've been rushing headlong since I've been here, 15 years, with new galleries. Now that we've filled up every possible space we've been allotted, it's time to stand back and take stock.''</p>
        <p>But at least one ambitious Chinese exhibition -- ''Early Chinese Empire: The First Millennium, Han Through Tang'' -- is very much in the works. Scheduled for 2003, it will be primarily an archaeological show, though unlike those recently at the Guggenheim Museum in Manhattan and the National Gallery in Washington, this one will be ''a focused exhibition of a certain period rather than just a random display of masterpieces,'' Mr. Watt said.</p>
        <p>Even within that definition, the time frame is vast, from the collapse of the Han dynasty in A.D. 220 and into the Tang, which began in 618. This was a complex transitional period that produced what Mr. Watt called ''a totally new culture for China.'' The plan is for all or most of the material to be loans from China itself. ''I'm hoping we'll have some of the best Buddhist sculptures and, if it can be done, wall paintings,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also wants to include examples of decorative art -- his own academic specialty -- like Central Asian gold and ancient Persian glass of the kind imported into China at a time of massive migrations and fluid cultural exchange. ''China was never a monolithic culture,'' he said. ''When we look at things we think of as most 'Chinese,' in fact, most of them are of non-Chinese origin.''</p>
        <p>His own background adheres to some degree to this transcultural model. He grew up in Hong Kong and, like Mr. Fong, had a classical education at home with a scholar-teacher before going to Oxford. He then returned to Hong Kong, where he studied at the Chinese University and worked at the City Museum.</p>
        <p>''There was a concentration of great scholars in the city in the 1950's and 60's,'' he said, ''the last of a generation with an approach going all the way back to the Song dynasty.'' His own family background included a lineage of scholars, ''rather an obscure one.'' The last of them to come into public prominence was a Ming-period writer who became a monk to escape persecution for resisting Manchu rule during China's last dynasty, the Qing.</p>
        <p>Under Manchu rule, which ended in 1912, Mr. Watt's family retreated from public life. ''They were forbidden to do anything,'' he said. ''But they had their libraries.''</p>
        <p>They also had access to private art collections, which they were able both to enjoy and study intensively. Mr. Watt said that museums in the West served a similar function on a popular level, and for this reason he wanted to make programming a priority in the years ahead.</p>
        <p>''We need to create installations and small-scale shows that will help people to better understand Asian art,'' he said. ''Somehow familiarity will make the difference.'' Along these lines he said that it was essential to introduce the study of Asian art, using the Met as a teaching resource, into school curriculums at a very early stage, something, he said, that was not yet happening.</p>
        <p>He regularly monitors his audience by spending time in the Asian galleries to watch people looking at art. The Chinese painting galleries attract the most visitors, in part because, for reasons of conservation, the works have to be rotated roughly every four months, with the rotation usually taking the form of a thematic show. ''It's my impression that these galleries actually have a constituency,'' Mr. Watt said. ''I see people looking quite seriously. And you can easily tell if they are or if they're just wandering through.''</p>
        <p>As for the teaching of art history to a future generation of scholars, he shares Mr. Fong's misgivings about the movement away from physical engagement in favor of theory-based interpretation. ''Being able to handle an object is so important,'' he said. ''That's why some people feel not all art should be behind glass. But students today don't have that primary experience.''</p>
        <p>It is an experience that he was given by his first scholar-teacher in Hong Kong, with whom he practiced calligraphy, seal carving and music, disciplines, long associated with a true education, that can only be taught one-on-one. Noting that China has adopted a Western-style university system, Mr. Watt observed: ''The good thing is that the opportunity to study is now open to all. At the same time something gets lost.''</p>
        <p>The accomplishments that formed the basis of his approach to scholarship are no longer taught in China, and their spirit will be, he said, increasingly difficult to convey to young art historians of the future. ''But somehow,'' Mr. Watt added, ''they must become familiar with the tradition of passing on tradition.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
