<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="29PUBL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lyme Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zoos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WBBR-AM (New York)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Zoo</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koch, Edward I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'Amato, Alfonse M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seeger, Pete</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ehmke, Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Lyme Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lyme Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DA1E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column notes that former New York City Mayor Edward I Koch and Sen Alfonse D'Amato will discuss political issues during five-minute segments starting Sept 9 on WBBR-AM; also notes that folk singer Pete Seeger has Lyme disease, and comments on Minnesota Zoo's new director Lee Ehmke; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No Dead Air Here: D'Amato vs. Koch</p>
        <p>Two of New York's most outspoken, out-of-office politicians are getting themselves a second soapbox. EDWARD I. KOCH and ALFONSE M. D'AMATO plan to go face to face on the radio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No Dead Air Here: D'Amato vs. Koch</p>
        <p>Two of New York's most outspoken, out-of-office politicians are getting themselves a second soapbox. EDWARD I. KOCH and ALFONSE M. D'AMATO plan to go face to face on the radio.</p>
        <p>That is perhaps an Osgoodian way of describing what could turn out to be a more Limbaughian type of encounter beneath the ''on air'' sign.  ''Al and I are good friends, but we often disagree on candidates and issues,'' said Mr. Koch, who was mayor from 1978 to 1989. ''We disagree civilly and with good humor -- so what if on occasion I make him cry?'' For his part, Mr. D'Amato, the former senator, said, ''There's nothing I love more than duking it out with my good friend Ed Koch.''</p>
        <p>The five-minute segments on Saturdays starting Sept. 9 on WBBR-AM (1130) are not their only collaboration. Since March, they have been preparing a twice-a-month column -- these columnists do not write, they talk into a tape recorder -- for New York magazine titled ''I'm Right, You're Wrong.''</p>
        <p>So what advice does MAER ROSHAN, the deputy editor of New York magazine and coordinator of their column, have for ANTHEA RAYMOND, who will be the moderator of their radio chats?</p>
        <p>''Interrupt them frequently and feed them lots of cosmopolitans,'' Mr. Roshan said, referring to what he called Mr. D'Amato's drink of choice.</p>
        <p>Pete Seeger Has Lyme Disease</p>
        <p>First it was a missing banjo, which was returned last week, a couple of weeks after it disappeared (a self-employed painter had noticed the folk singer PETE SEEGER'S name on the case when he found the instrument, but said ''it was just another name to me'').</p>
        <p>Now comes word that Mr. Seeger, 81, has Lyme disease.</p>
        <p>His wife, TOSHI, told The Associated Press that he had received the diagnosis after feeling sick lately.</p>
        <p>''We have ticks in the area'' near their house in Beacon, N.Y., she said. There was no answer at the house last night; she told The A.P. that Mr. Seeger did not plan to cancel any performances.</p>
        <p>Bronx Gorilla Man To Minnesota Zoo</p>
        <p>On the Minnesota Zoo's automated telephone directory, one of those systems with a mechanized voice that instructs a caller to spell out the name of the person he or she wants to reach using the keys on the telephone, punching ''Ehmke'' yesterday set off a message that said those letters ''do not spell a recognized name.''</p>
        <p>It was only LEE EHMKE'S first day as director.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ehmke moved to the Midwest after overseeing the $50 million Congo Gorilla Forest exhibition at the Bronx Zoo, an African rain forest habitat populated by 19 gorillas and other jungle creatures. He turned down a promotion to assistant director (''flattering and tempting,'' he said yesterday) to take over a 22-year-old zoo in Apple Valley, Minn., that he said ''needs some refreshing.''</p>
        <p>''I couldn't agree more that we need exhibits with a bit more wow appeal,'' Mr. Ehmke said. The Minnesota Zoo has room to grow, what with more than 100 acres that could be developed, making it what he called ''one of the most beautiful palettes a zoo designer could ever think of working with.''</p>
        <p>But yesterday was only his first day on the job. ''I feel like I've parachuted in,'' he said. ''I'm still waiting for my furniture and clothes to arrive.''</p>
        <p>He said that he had arrived in Minnesota 10 days ago, planning to settle in before starting the new job. ''I've been able to get a driver's license and a car that my New York existence didn't require,'' he said.</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
