<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Finally Get to Share the View at the Top</title>
    <meta content="29METS$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Houston Astros</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDE1F31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Finally Get to Share the View at the Top</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets beat Houston Astros, 4-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There has been one poison pitcher for the Mets lately, and Glendon Rusch knows he has been the one. Rusch began the Mets' sprint to first place, which they reached last night when they beat the Houston Astros, 4-2, to pull even with the Atlanta Braves atop the National League East. But any time the Mets stumbled on the way, it seemed as if Rusch put down the tripwire.</p>
        <p>The Mets have won 25 of 34 games since July 25, picking up six games on the Braves. Rusch started that string with a victory over Montreal, and he won again last night with seven tough innings. In between, the Mets were 1-4 in games Rusch started, 22-5 when another pitcher took the mound.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There has been one poison pitcher for the Mets lately, and Glendon Rusch knows he has been the one. Rusch began the Mets' sprint to first place, which they reached last night when they beat the Houston Astros, 4-2, to pull even with the Atlanta Braves atop the National League East. But any time the Mets stumbled on the way, it seemed as if Rusch put down the tripwire.</p>
        <p>The Mets have won 25 of 34 games since July 25, picking up six games on the Braves. Rusch started that string with a victory over Montreal, and he won again last night with seven tough innings. In between, the Mets were 1-4 in games Rusch started, 22-5 when another pitcher took the mound.</p>
        <p>''That was very tough,'' Rusch said. ''That weighed on me a little bit. As good as the other four starters are, you don't want to have them go out and pitch great ballgames and then kind of detour our momentum when I go out there on my day.''</p>
        <p>While he was pitching last night at Shea Stadium, Rusch said, he did not notice that the Braves were losing to Cincinnati. Nor, probably, did he see that the Arizona Diamondbacks had fallen to the Expos, increasing the Mets' lead in the wild-card race to six and a half games. These are heady days for the Mets, and Rusch is glad to be a part of it again.</p>
        <p>''It's exciting for me to get in the middle of the whole momentum our team's building,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Astros' only runs came on bases-empty homers, by Roger Cedeno to lead off the game and by Richard Hidalgo in the third. But they clogged the bases the rest of the time against Rusch, and it was hard to tell if Rusch would make an early lead stand up.</p>
        <p>In the first inning, after two singles to open the game, the Mets got a three-run homer from Edgardo Alfonzo to take a 3-1 lead. But Rusch gave up a double to lead off the second, and a single and a walk loaded the bases with two outs. He threw a changeup to Julio Lugo, who flied softly to center to end the inning.</p>
        <p>Rusch had run up high pitch counts in recent starts, out of character for a control pitcher. He said he had just gotten through a ''dead period,'' but despite an extra day of rest, he threw 82 pitches through four innings last night.</p>
        <p>That fourth inning was troublesome. Chris Truby hit a leadoff triple, and Rusch and catcher Todd Pratt tried to pitch inside more often. With runners at the corners and two outs, Lugo tapped a changeup to second to end the inning, and Rusch was on his way. Only two more Astros reached base over his last three innings, and then he turned things over to Turk Wendell, who worked two innings for his first save.</p>
        <p>For Rusch, who has the lowest run support of any National League starter, the hard-earned decision improved his record to 9-10.</p>
        <p>''The breaks haven't gone his way,'' Pratt said. ''We haven't scored for him all year, and he's been pitching tough games all year. I don't think he's had a breather yet. Today, he was a little out of control early, but he adjusted.''</p>
        <p>Rusch's counterpart, Brian Powell, missed his spots continually. The right-handed Powell, who beat the Mets earlier this month for his first victory in the majors in two years, walked six in five innings and threw more than half his pitches for balls. The Mets could not capitalize on that wildness, but Alfonzo's blow was enough.</p>
        <p>The homer was the 17th for the second baseman, who supplied the power for the Mets on a night that Mike Piazza had off.</p>
        <p>''He threw me two sliders or cutters,'' Alfonzo said of Powell. ''He missed with his first pitch, and his second pitch was in a good place to hit. I got a good swing on it and hit it on a good part of my bat.''</p>
        <p>Benny Agbayani and Derek Bell had singled to set up Alfonzo's heroics. Agbayani is hot, with a .344 average, 5 homers and 20 runs batted in during the Mets' 34-game charge. But Bell entered the game in a 5-for-58 skid, and he was hitless in 21 at-bats before the single.</p>
        <p>Bell's single sustained what became the winning rally and made General Manager Steve Phillips look prophetic. When asked before the game if he worried when Bell slumped, Phillips noted that Bell always pulls himself out.</p>
        <p>''We've got him right where we want him right now,'' Phillips said.</p>
        <p>If Bell starts hitting and Rusch stays strong, the Mets could get used to first place.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Mets reliever JOHN FRANCO, who has been bothered by soreness in his left pectoral muscle for a week, said he hoped to be available to pitch by the weekend. Franco, who said the condition felt as if a thumb were being pressed into his armpit, threw in the outfield during batting practice and will continue the light throwing today. Franco said the Mets' position in the standing gives him the luxury of being safe. ''We're not going to push it and go out and hurt it and be out for the season,'' said Franco, who was injured in his last game, at San Diego last Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Partly because of Franco's status, the Mets called up the Class AA Binghamton right-hander JERROD RIGGAN, who could be replaced the by Class AAA Norfolk right-hander ERIC CAMMACK as soon as Cammack can get to New York. The infielder/outfielder JOE McEWING was sent to Norfolk, but he can still be put on the postseason roster because the Mets have one position player, REY ORDONEZ, on the disabled list.</p>
        <p>If the Mets' first-round draft choice, the left-handed pitcher BILLY TRABER, attends a class today at Loyola Marymount University, the Mets will essentially lose their chances of signing him. The Mets believe Traber could have a serious elbow injury, and they have drastically reduced their bonus offer. Only three other teams -- Anaheim, Cincinnati and Colorado -- have not signed their first-round draft picks this year, and the Mets have failed to do so only once in their history, in 1970. ''We have many differences on this player,'' said ADAM KATZ, one of the agents advising Traber.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
