<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping the Lines Open, Receiver Gets His Big Shot</title>
    <meta content="29GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: GIANTS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Thabiti</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E5D71E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping the Lines Open, Receiver Gets His Big Shot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Giants wide receiver Thabiti Davis; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A year ago, at a cubicle inside a telephone company's customer service center in Charlotte, N.C., Thabiti Davis dispensed plan-pricing information, routed technical questions and offered general assistance.</p>
        <p>When answering calls, he would resist the urge to say: ''I'm not really an operator. I'm a football player.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A year ago, at a cubicle inside a telephone company's customer service center in Charlotte, N.C., Thabiti Davis dispensed plan-pricing information, routed technical questions and offered general assistance.</p>
        <p>When answering calls, he would resist the urge to say: ''I'm not really an operator. I'm a football player.''</p>
        <p>His colleagues knew that the 6-foot-2-inch, 205-pound man in the headset at the next desk had an ambition to play wide receiver in the National Football League. Most days, his supervisor even bent the work schedule to allow Davis to work out.</p>
        <p>''There was a lot of support,'' Davis said. ''I think they knew this was a transition period for me.''</p>
        <p>But not an easy one.</p>
        <p>After graduating from Wake Forest in 1998, Davis lasted about two weeks in the training camp of the Carolina Panthers. Several months later, he was in Barcelona, Spain, playing in the National Football League's European league.</p>
        <p>After returning home, he next went to training camp with Jacksonville. The Jaguars soon became the second N.F.L. team to cut him. So it was back to Europe, except Barcelona had traded him to Berlin.</p>
        <p>When that season ended, Davis came home to North Carolina, once again without a team. Then, just days before this summer's N.F.L. training camps opened, the Giants invited him to their site in Albany.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to think it was my last shot,'' Davis said. ''But I figured it might be.''</p>
        <p>Sunday, on the last day N.F.L. rosters were trimmed, the 25-year-old Davis came to Giants Stadium to find out if he would be cut again. Inside the locker room, his teammates greeted him with congratulations. The Giants had released a former third-round draft pick, Brian Alford, and kept Davis, who will earn $193,000 this season.</p>
        <p>''It started out nerve-racking,'' Davis said. ''But then it was exciting.''</p>
        <p>Davis called his parents with the news. His father, James, a wide receiver who three decades ago had unsuccessfully tried out with three N.F.L. teams and played in the Canadian Football League, wanted to drive from North Carolina to New Jersey immediately.</p>
        <p>''They both wanted to help me move things into an apartment and those kinds of things,'' Davis said. ''They were excited, too. Everybody kept saying, 'We're so happy for you.' ''</p>
        <p>As the Giants' fifth receiver, Davis will not be featured in many passing plays in the team's season-opening game Sunday against the Arizona Cardinals. His biggest contribution will be on special teams.</p>
        <p>During the preseason, Davis led the Giants with four tackles on special teams. Indeed, he made the team, Coach Jim Fassel said, because he played well on special teams while Alford did not.</p>
        <p>Davis can credit his experience as an all-state high school linebacker for his tackling skills. But as good a high school linebacker as Davis was, he did not want to be one in college. He wanted to play wide receiver. The decision is one that may have delayed his entry into the N.F.L. since several major college football programs -- such as Notre Dame and North Carolina State -- recruited him at linebacker.</p>
        <p>''My heart was set on playing wide receiver,'' Davis said.</p>
        <p>Only Wake Forest agreed to play him there.</p>
        <p>''I've thought whether choosing to wide receiver hurt my football career,'' Davis said. ''But I have no regrets. As my body has developed, I think I would have had to gain too much weight.''</p>
        <p>Davis isn't a pure speed receiver, but he is quick, has good hands and can use his considerable size to get open. He led the Giants with 11 receptions in the preseason.</p>
        <p>''It took me a little while to get to this point,'' Davis said.</p>
        <p>Then, speaking like someone who was happy to be beginning a new career, he added, ''Now the real work starts.''</p>
        <p>Uniform Unveiling</p>
        <p>The Giants will wear their new white jersey uniforms for Sunday's game at Giants Stadium, even though this design and color scheme will be used as a road uniform for the rest of the season.</p>
        <p>''They look a little different,'' Jim Fassel said, explaining why he wanted the team to wear white at home. ''They look nice. And if it's a hot day, it'll be cooler.''</p>
        <p>The white uniforms have red numbers and are worn with the same gray pants worn with the newly designed blue jerseys.</p>
        <p>Blunder? What Blunder?</p>
        <p>The rookie linebacker Jack Golden survived the cut despite his infamous play at the end of the Giants' preseason game against the Jaguars. Golden tackled teammate Fred Lewis and caused a fumble that lost the game for the Giants.</p>
        <p>''I told Jack to keep track of what uniforms we have on week to week,'' Fassel said. ''I said, 'The object is to tackle the guy with the ball -- in the right uniform.' ''</p>
        <p>The Giants aren't deep in linebackers after some training camp injuries so Golden was never in any real danger of being cut.</p>
        <p>Cards to Start Jones</p>
        <p>Arizona Coach Vince Tobin announced today that the rookie running back Thomas Jones would start against the Giants.</p>
        <p>Jones, the seventh pick of this spring's draft, rushed for 100 yards on 31 carries in the preseason. He also caught 6 passes for 40 yards.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: GIANTS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
