<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chief of MP3.com Testifies in Music Copyright Hearing</title>
    <meta content="Y29MUS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Universal Music Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mp3.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robertson, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copyrights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E5D91E31F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chief of MP3.com Testifies in Music Copyright Hearing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Robertson tells federal court in New York that he believed he was acting legally when he created MP3.com, database of thousands of copyrighted record albums; damage phase of trial begins after failure of negotiations with Universal Music Group (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his Internet music start-up facing potentially hundreds of millions of dollars in damages for copyright violations, the head of MP3.com told a federal judge in Manhattan yesterday that he believed he was acting legally when he created an online database of thousands of copyrighted record albums.</p>
        <p>The testimony from Michael Robertson, MP3.com's chief executive, came at the first day of hearings in a trial pitting his company, a San Diego-based start-up, against the Seagram Company's Universal Music Group, the world's largest record company. The trial began after negotiations over the weekend failed to produce a settlement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his Internet music start-up facing potentially hundreds of millions of dollars in damages for copyright violations, the head of MP3.com told a federal judge in Manhattan yesterday that he believed he was acting legally when he created an online database of thousands of copyrighted record albums.</p>
        <p>The testimony from Michael Robertson, MP3.com's chief executive, came at the first day of hearings in a trial pitting his company, a San Diego-based start-up, against the Seagram Company's Universal Music Group, the world's largest record company. The trial began after negotiations over the weekend failed to produce a settlement.</p>
        <p>The judge in the case has already ruled that MP3.com infringed upon Universal's copyrights, but the size of the damages in the case will depend on whether the court determines the action was ''willful.''</p>
        <p>Universal and four other major record company sued MP3.com in January, but the other companies have since settled. In the original suit, filed in January, the companies asserted that MP3.com violated their copyrights with the creation of the service called My.MP3.com.</p>
        <p>The service created an ''online locker,'' permitting users to store their music albums centrally on MP3.com's computers, then get access to them through various digital devices, like computers or portable music players.</p>
        <p>To make the service easy to use, MP3.com did not require users to load their own music into the virtual lockers. Rather, a user had merely to insert a copy of the music into the CD-ROM drive of a computer, at which point, MP3.com would verify that the person had possession of a CD, then the company would automatically put a copy of the music into the person's virtual locker.</p>
        <p>MP3.com amassed 65,000 albums to create the database from which it drew its music. However, the record companies, in their lawsuit, asserted that the company had violated their copyrights by creating the digital database of albums to which they held the copyrights. In April, Federal District Judge Jed S. Rakoff found in favor of the record companies, ruling that MP3.com had infringed upon the companies' copyrights.</p>
        <p>In the ensuing months, MP3.com reached settlements with four of the major record companies, including Sony Music, Time Warner, the EMI Group and Bertelsmann A.G. Details of the settlements were not made public, but analysts estimated that MP3.com paid $20 million to each company. Eric Scheier, an industry analyst with Forrester Research, speculated that Universal had not yet settled for one or both of two reasons: because as the biggest record company it wants a larger settlement; or because it has intentions to start a competing service with My.MP3.com and does not want to license its content to MP3.com, a provision that has been a component of the settlements with the other record companies.</p>
        <p>Universal may not want to license music to ''MP3.com or more generally to anybody they don't feel they can control or express a lot of authority over about what kind of business models are going to be used,'' Mr. Scheier said. A spokesman for Universal Music Group declined to comment. Universal is an investor in MusicBank, a company that has said it plans to start a virtual locker business sometime in the fall.</p>
        <p>At yesterday's hearing, Mr. Robertson told the court that he believed the My.MP3.com service was respectful of the record companies' copyrights. ''Nothing I had looked at suggested this was illegal use or a copyright violation,'' he said, according to a report by the Dow Jones news service.</p>
        <p>The hearing, which is scheduled to continue through Thursday, will provide the basis for Judge Rakoff to assess damages against MP3.com. People close to the trial said that if the judge decided the action was willful, MP3.com could face damage payments of $750 to $150,000 for each album infringement. If the judge finds the conduct not willful, the damages could range from $750 to $30,000. People familiar with the case said that MP3.com's database included roughly 10,000 albums that are the copyrighted works of Universal.</p>
        <p>MP3.com in May suspended the My.MP3.com service, which it said had roughly 500,000 participants.</p>
        <p>The hearing comes as the music industry continues to fight on other legal fronts, notably in its battle against Napster, a popular service that permits individual users to exchange music files online. It is a practice the music industry asserts amounts to theft. The industry's case against Napster is being handled in federal court in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
