<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The 'Women's Disease' That Also Strikes Men</title>
    <meta content="29BONE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Osteoporosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bones</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tarkan, Laurie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Osteoporosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFDD1131F93AA1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The 'Women's Disease' That Also Strikes Men</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE TARKAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tarkan, Laurie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Strong link between osteoporosis and women causes many doctors to overlook disease in men, who account for only 20 percent of 10 million Americans with osteoporosis or low bone mass; lack of awareness among doctors and men has led to delays in diagnosis and treatment; disease manifests itself later in life in men than women, with fractures starting to increase around age 60 in women and between 65 and 70 in men; doctors treat men with therapies that have proven effective in women, but not yet in men; table of secondary causes of disease in men; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Richards of Anderson, Calif., goes for his physical every year, and his doctor jots down his height and weight. The doctor does not react to the fact that each year Mr. Richards is shorter.</p>
        <p>Maybe he never looks back over Mr. Richards' file to compare, or if he does notice the change, he does not think twice about it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Richards of Anderson, Calif., goes for his physical every year, and his doctor jots down his height and weight. The doctor does not react to the fact that each year Mr. Richards is shorter.</p>
        <p>Maybe he never looks back over Mr. Richards' file to compare, or if he does notice the change, he does not think twice about it.</p>
        <p>After all, although losing height is a symptom of osteoporosis, a disease of weakening bones, most doctors do not associate the disease with men.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richards had also been complaining of back pain since he was in his 40's, but he dismissed it as a part of getting old, and his doctors simply dismissed it, even though men with osteoporosis are susceptible to microfractures of the spine, and therefore back pain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richards also broke his left arm in three places when he was 46, but the accident stemmed from an accident, so again nobody suspected a more insidious bone problem.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Richards thinks it was just luck that his H.M.O. switched him to a female doctor who was more aware of women's disorders.</p>
        <p>When he went for his physical examination at age 52, the new doctor reviewed his charts and ordered a bone mineral density test. The test revealed that he had severe osteoporosis, meaning that his bones had become so porous that they were 10 times as likely to break as those of other men of his age.</p>
        <p>Now 57, and almost four inches shorter than his peak height of 5 feet 11 inches tall, Mr. Richards has to avoid activities that involve a risk of falling or injury, and he can no longer partake in the ranching activities he has done all his life.</p>
        <p>When his daughter went in for a physical recently and told her doctor that her father had osteoporosis, the doctor tried to correct her, saying, ''you mean your mother has osteoporosis.''</p>
        <p>When a disease is more common in one sex, it is not unusual for the less-affected sex to get overlooked.</p>
        <p>It happened with heart disease. Because men get it at a younger age than women, it was deemed a man's disease, and for years women were neither included in the clinical studies nor educated about their risks.</p>
        <p>And it has happened with osteoporosis, which is considered a disease of postmenopausal women, or more familiarly, a little old ladies' disease. Of the 10 million people in this country with osteoporosis and the 18 million with low bone mass, 80 percent are women.</p>
        <p>''It's clear that the burden of osteoporosis and fractures is greater in women, and what has happened is that has overshadowed a smaller but very significant problem in men,'' said Dr. Eric Orwoll, professor of medicine at Oregon Health Sciences University.</p>
        <p>The lifetime risk for a man's having a fracture of the hip, the spine or the forearm, the most troubling consequence of osteoporosis, is 13 percent or about 1 in 8. That is also the same risk for prostate cancer and about the same as a woman's risk of getting breast cancer.</p>
        <p>Osteoporosis can be a debilitating and fatal disease. Fractures of the spine lead to stooped posture, loss of height, chronic pain and can cause compression of the lungs and stomach.</p>
        <p>And, one-third of men who suffer hip fractures will die within a year.</p>
        <p>Though the disease does manifest itself later in life in men than women, it is not much later.</p>
        <p>Fractures start to increase around age 60 in women; in men, they increase between 65 and 70, said Dr. L. Joseph Melton, an epidemiologist at the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minn. Osteoporosis-related fractures can occur earlier in men and women.</p>
        <p>The lack of awareness among physicians and men has led to delays in diagnosis and treatment. Osteoporosis, known as the ''silent disease,'' often has no symptoms until the bones are so compromised that a minor trauma causes a fracture.</p>
        <p>Because there are no early warning signs, awareness of the risk factors and the use of bone density tests are critical to catching it early and preventing further bone loss.</p>
        <p>As awareness of osteoporosis in postmenopausal women has grown, it has become more common for them to get routine bone density tests, though many experts say it is not common enough.</p>
        <p>Men, though, are rarely given bone density tests, unless they have severe symptoms like spine or hip fractures. And even when an older man breaks a lesser bone or loses height due to bone loss, two red flags in postmenopausal women, many physicians still do not consider that he may have osteoporosis.</p>
        <p>''It is more likely to be thought of as due to a trauma or bad luck, even when the trauma that caused the break is relatively minor,'' Dr. Orwoll said.</p>
        <p>Often men are sent home without receiving bone density tests and without hearing any prevention strategies, even though they may be at risk for further bone loss and fractures, he said.</p>
        <p>Treatment of osteoporosis in men has also lagged behind that for women.</p>
        <p>''Until the last few years, there haven't been data that actually demonstrate the usefulness of therapies for prevention or treatment of osteoporosis in men,'' Dr. Orwoll said.</p>
        <p>Doctors treat men with therapies that have been proven effective in women, but not yet in men. The two drugs that doctors typically prescribe, alendronate (brand name, Fosamax) and risedronate (Actonel), have been approved only for postmenopausal women or in a subgroup of men with osteoporosis that induced by steroids, which have a direct effect on bones and which reduce bone formation and testosterone levels.</p>
        <p>Doctors are legally allowed to prescribe the treatment to men in what is called off-label use, but studies are needed to test the safety, effectiveness and dosing of these drugs in men.</p>
        <p>Research, though, is beginning to emerge, as is a clearer understanding of how bone growth and bone loss differ between men and women. During adolescence, boys grow longer and thicker bones than girls, making their skeletons more robust and less prone to fractures.</p>
        <p>Men and women reach their peak bone mass in their late 20's. All the while, bone is continually replenishing itself as old bone is broken down or resorbed and new bone tissue is formed. In the 30's, bone resorption begins to outpace bone formation, causing a gradual loss of bone density.</p>
        <p>Estrogen and testosterone are believed to block bone resorption, so as women reach menopause and their estrogen level drops, resorption speeds up, leading to rapid bone loss for the next five to seven years.</p>
        <p>This period is largely responsible for the higher rates of osteoporosis in women.</p>
        <p>But by the age of 65 or 70, the rate of bone loss is roughly equal in both sexes because of several age-related factors including declining levels of sex hormones, among them testosterone; a change in the ability to absorb and use calcium; and a more sedentary lifestyle.</p>
        <p>In about 60 percent to 65 percent of men (and about half of women) with osteoporosis, the disease is linked to other causes. The three leading causes in men are alcoholism; hypogonadism, in which they produce low levels of testosterone; and the long-term use of glucocorticoids, which are steroids taken for asthma, arthritis and other inflammatory diseases.</p>
        <p>''There is a long list of conditions and medications that can adversely affect bone, and these are the situations in which you would want to get a bone density test and take action earlier in life,'' said Dr. Orwoll, who will conduct a study of osteoporosis in men at universities across the country.</p>
        <p>Men who may be at greatest risk for osteoporosis are those who do not reach optimal bone mass during childhood and adolescence.</p>
        <p>By the time men reach age 25, bone density can vary as much as 30 percent. Dr. Orwoll said that ''later in life we think that makes a big difference in fracture risk.''</p>
        <p>Experts are shifting their focus on osteoporosis to skew it more toward prevention.</p>
        <p>A recent consensus conference on osteoporosis at the National Institutes of Health has elevated the importance of building peak bone mass to the level of preventing bone loss.</p>
        <p>Peak bone density is largely determined by genetics, but daily habits and practices do influence how close a man is able to get to achieving his peak.</p>
        <p>Among normally nourished children and adolescents, getting enough calcium and vitamin D can make a 5 percent difference in the density of their bones. But only an estimated 25 percent of boys (and 10 percent of girls) ages 9 to 17 get the recommended intake of 1,300 milligrams of calcium a day.</p>
        <p>''The issue for boys is that bone health is not part of their thinking, nor their parents', and often not their pediatricians','' said Dr. Anne Klibanski, professor of medicine at Harvard Medical School and chairwoman of the institutes' consensus conference.</p>
        <p>''For girls, calcium intake is associated with high amounts of dairy intake and fat and that becomes an impediment for having enough calcium in the diet,'' she added. Other factors that hamper bone building are smoking and drinking alcohol excessively (more than two drinks a day).</p>
        <p>Getting enough calcium later in life can also help to prevent bone loss. In adults over 50, only 60 percent of men (and 50 percent of women) meet the recommended intake of calcium.</p>
        <p>''Men are closer to the goal line than women, but still not that close,'' said Dr. Bess Dawson-Hughes, chief of the calcium and bone laboratory at the Department of Agriculture's Nutrition Center on Aging at Tufts University.</p>
        <p>Doctors recommend increasing dietary sources of calcium and vitamin D, and if that does not provide enough, adults should take calcium supplements, Dr. Dawson-Hughes said.</p>
        <p>Weight-bearing exercises -- including walking, running and strength-training -- appear to be as important as calcium in reaching peak bone mass and maintaining bone density.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
