<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Mets Won't Celebrate Wild Card</title>
    <meta content="27ANDE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/sports/27ANDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DB103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Mets Won't Celebrate Wild Card</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column discusses New York Mets reaction to clinching National League wild card with one more victory; Mets say celebration will be muted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Mets had a Hamlet dilemma last night: to be or not to be celebrating.</p>
        <p>Despite last night's 7-1 loss to the now division champion Braves, if the Mets can win tonight's game at Shea, they will clinch the wild-card berth in the National League playoffs for the second straight season. But don't expect them to rush to the mound in celebration.</p>
        <p>''We're not celebrating,'' Steve Phillips, the Mets' general manager, said. ''Our goal was to win the division. The wild card is a fallback.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Mets had a Hamlet dilemma last night: to be or not to be celebrating.</p>
        <p>Despite last night's 7-1 loss to the now division champion Braves, if the Mets can win tonight's game at Shea, they will clinch the wild-card berth in the National League playoffs for the second straight season. But don't expect them to rush to the mound in celebration.</p>
        <p>''We're not celebrating,'' Steve Phillips, the Mets' general manager, said. ''Our goal was to win the division. The wild card is a fallback.''</p>
        <p>The Mets would be allowed to smile. ''And they can hug each other,'' Phillips said.</p>
        <p>After all, they would be in the playoffs, looking forward to opposing either the San Francisco Giants or the St. Louis Cardinals in a N.L. divisional series next week.</p>
        <p>Even if the Mets lose tonight, they will back into the wild card if the Los Angeles Dodgers also lose tonight.</p>
        <p>''Tomorrow,'' Phillips had joked with a sarcastic smile, ''we'll show up before the game and have tea and crumpets.''</p>
        <p>But Champagne sprays in the clubhouse; they don't deserve any. Not for the wild card. And that's as it should be.</p>
        <p>If you're on a wild-card team, it would be embarrassing to even wave two fingers, as if to say, ''We're No. 2.''</p>
        <p>That's all a wild card is: the second-place team with the best record. It's even incorrect to say that any team has ''won'' the wild card because the team hasn't really won anything. All it has done is ''earn'' the wild card. Even a divisional champion hasn't really won anything to celebrate. The Braves understand that. When they clinched their ninth consecutive divisional title last night, they hardly whooped.</p>
        <p>The wild card is baseball's consolation prize. You don't celebrate a consolation prize. You just accept it. Say thank you and try to win the big prize, the World Series.</p>
        <p>Those in favor of a wild-card celebration remember how the Mets celebrated their wild card a year ago, but that was a different scenario. More emotional. More unexpected.</p>
        <p>Entering that final weekend, the Mets thought they had no chance. But when they won their last three regular-season games against the Pittsburgh Pirates at Shea and the Reds collapsed in Milwaukee, the Mets were suddenly in Cincinnati for a one-game playoff that Al Leiter won with a two-hit shutout.</p>
        <p>That sudden success deserved to be celebrated, but still with some restraint because those Mets hadn't really won anything yet.</p>
        <p>Although those Mets ambushed the Arizona Diamondbacks in the divisional series, they still hadn't really won anything. And when they lost the N.L.C.S. to the Braves in six games, they definitely had not won anything.</p>
        <p>By itself, the wild card is just a steppingstone across the raging river that is baseball's postseason.</p>
        <p>In 1997 the Florida Marlins used that steppingstone, then knocked the first-place Braves out of the N.L. playoffs and went on to win the World Series, the only wild-card team to get to the other side of that raging river.</p>
        <p>So these Mets know it can be done because it has been done.</p>
        <p>The wild card, as popular as it is these days in the American League's five-team dogfight (Seattle or Oakland, Cleveland, Toronto and Boston), also has a weakness: the lack of urgency for a team to try to finish in first place if it is comfortably ahead in the wild-card race, as the Mets were even before their three-game series in Atlanta a week ago.</p>
        <p>Knowing they were virtually certain to retain the wild card, the Mets seemed to shrug off losing the first two games in Atlanta a week ago.</p>
        <p>Once upon a time, a baseball team had to finish first in its league or in its division to qualify for the postseason. The wild card was introduced in 1994, although a wild-card team was never determined that year when the final two months of the regular season and the entire postseason, even the World Series, were canceled by a labor dispute.</p>
        <p>Baseball purists still wish the wild card did not exist. Major League Baseball has postponed serious discussion of a proposal to split 32 teams into eight divisions of four teams each, with only the eight first-place teams qualifying for the playoffs. Maybe someday that proposal will be adopted. If it is, there won't be a wild card.</p>
        <p>And there won't be a reason to wonder if a team should celebrate or not celebrate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
