<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accord Likely on Measure Allowing Drug Imports</title>
    <meta content="27DRUG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/politics/27DRUG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarez, Lizette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armey, Dick (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jeffords, James M (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E4DE103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accord Likely on Measure Allowing Drug Imports</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZETTE ALVAREZ and ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alvarez, Lizette; Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Dick Armey says House Republican leaders will approve Senate-passed version of Sen James M Jeffords bill to allow re-imports of American-made prescription drugs from nations where they are sold at far lower prices; bill is backed by Pres Clinton and opposed by drug industry; bill's impact on drug prices will be delayed for about two years, while Food and Drug Administration writes rules to implement law; bill includes safeguards to protect consumers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A proposal to allow imports of low-priced prescription drugs won support from House Republican leaders today, making it all but certain that Congress and President Clinton could eventually agree on the legislation.</p>
        <p>Although the pharmaceutical industry has lobbied furiously against the measure, the House Republican leaders announced that they would approve the Senate-passed version of the bill, which Mr. Clinton also supports. Their decision to make the bill a priority, just six weeks before the elections, suggests how potent the cost of prescription drugs has become as a political issue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A proposal to allow imports of low-priced prescription drugs won support from House Republican leaders today, making it all but certain that Congress and President Clinton could eventually agree on the legislation.</p>
        <p>Although the pharmaceutical industry has lobbied furiously against the measure, the House Republican leaders announced that they would approve the Senate-passed version of the bill, which Mr. Clinton also supports. Their decision to make the bill a priority, just six weeks before the elections, suggests how potent the cost of prescription drugs has become as a political issue.</p>
        <p>''We are comfortable with the Senate bill,'' Representative Dick Armey of Texas, the majority leader, said today.</p>
        <p>The White House spokesman, Jake Siewert, said the bill ''may well emerge from the rubble,'' and added, ''if they want to do the Senate bill, it's fine with us.''</p>
        <p>The measure, drafted by Senator James M. Jeffords, Republican of Vermont, addresses the disparities that force American consumers to pay two or three times as much for some American-made drugs as do people in Canada, Mexico and some other countries. Prices for many prescription drugs are often lower in other countries because foreign governments regulate the prices.</p>
        <p>The measure would allow pharmacies and wholesale distributors to buy prescription drugs abroad, reimport them and then sell them to consumers at a lower cost. Although the measure is designed to reduce drug prices in a roundabout way, it is not likely to do so for about two years. That is how long it is expected to take for the Food and Drug Administration to write regulations that would govern this new business. Experts say it is too early to know with any accuracy what volume of sales may flow through such a route.</p>
        <p>The Senate bill, approved on July 19 by a vote of 74 to 21, also includes safeguards to protect consumers, something the F.D.A. said was necessary. It would require the importer to provide large amounts of data to the agency to ensure that the drugs were authentic and complied with federal standards. Tests would be conducted by the pharmacist, the wholesaler or the manufacturer.</p>
        <p>Somewhat different proposals to relax restrictions on the import of prescription drugs were approved by the House with overwhelming support on July 10.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore supports the bill, and Gov. George W. Bush has not taken a position.</p>
        <p>''We think there is something that should be done there,'' said Senator Trent Lott of Mississippi, the majority leader. ''We do want to make sure about the safety aspects, and that's one of the things that concerned the industry. The potential for fraud is very strong, and you want to make sure that our people are not being duped.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lott said Congress might want to tighten up the safety provisions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton today praised the Republican leadership for agreeing ''in the face of the drug companies' opposition, to give Americans access to prescription drugs that are cheaper in other countries.''</p>
        <p>At an event celebrating the economic expansion, he added, ''I think it's wrong when drug companies sell the same drugs for a much higher price at home than they do overseas, even when those drugs are manufactured right here in America.''</p>
        <p>Despite today's accord, the bill's path to the president's desk remains somewhat rocky. The measure is now attached to an agriculture spending bill, which is tangled up in a dispute over legislation to weaken the United States economic embargo against Cuba. That conflict must be resolved before the bill can be voted on in the House or the Senate.</p>
        <p>Still, at some point, Congress must pass a bill to finance the Department of Agriculture, and if all goes as expected, the measure would be tucked inside. ''If it's not done, it's as close to done as anything can be,'' said Senator Byron L. Dorgan, Democrat of North Dakota, a co-sponsor of the legislation.</p>
        <p>John P. Feehery, a spokesman for Speaker J. Dennis Hastert, said the Senate language might be ''tweaked'' a bit, but should not pose an obstacle.</p>
        <p>By pushing the prescription drug reimportation bill, over protests of the pharmaceutical industry, Republicans hope to inoculate themselves against Democratic charges that they have done nothing to make prescription drugs more affordable for the elderly.</p>
        <p>Drug manufacturers have lobbied vigorously to kill the drug reimportation measure in recent weeks, running expensive television advertisements to get their message out.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hastert and Mr. Lott sent a letter to Mr. Clinton this week indicating their desire to act on the drug reimportation bill, among other things. They said time was running out for action on broader legislation to establish prescription drug benefits for the elderly under Medicare.</p>
        <p>While Democrats said they were pleased with today's developments, they made it clear they would not back down from the goal of securing drug coverage through Medicare.</p>
        <p>The provisions of the Senate bill would take effect only if the secretary of health and human services certified to Congress that the measure would ''pose no risk to the public's health and safety,'' and that it would produce ''a significant reduction in the cost'' of prescription drugs to American consumers.</p>
        <p>Ronald J. Streck, president of the National Wholesale Druggists' Association, said, ''The demand for imported prescription drugs could be quite high because importers will advertise low-price imported medicines in newspapers and magazines, on television and over the Internet.''</p>
        <p>The White House said the F.D.A. would need $23 million to develop a new system of regulating imported drugs. House Republicans said they were willing to provide that amount.</p>
        <p>Under the Senate bill, importers would have to provide large amounts of data to the F.D.A. to show, for example, that a statistically valid sample of all drug shipments had been tested to ensure compliance with federal standards.</p>
        <p>Imported drugs would have to have the same color, formulation, labeling and dosage as products approved for domestic sale. Importers would have to maintain records showing the ''chain of custody'' of the drugs. They would have to inform the F.D.A. of the ''points of origin and destination'' for imported drugs; the wholesale and retail prices, and ''the manufacturer's lot or control number'' for each shipment.</p>
        <p>Under existing law, a prescription drug made in the United States and exported to another country may not be reimported, in large quantities, except by the manufacturer. The law, adopted in 1988 as a consumer protection measure, sought to choke off a ''gray market'' for drugs that were counterfeit, adulterated or too old to be used safely.</p>
        <p>The National Wholesale Druggists' Association opposed the legislation. Mr. Streck, the president of the association, said ''wholesalers do not have the experience, equipment or personnel'' to sample, test, re-label and track imported drugs.</p>
        <p>Wholesalers also expressed concern that they could incur costly new legal liability for the imported drugs, and they said they would have to pass on such costs to consumers.</p>
        <p>It is not clear whether drug companies would cooperate in efforts to import low-price versions of their products. ''Why would manufacturers produce additional product in Canada, or export additional product from the United States to Canada, so it could be sold at a lower price in this country?'' Mr. Streck asked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Streck said he feared that low-price counterfeit drugs would flow into the United States to meet the demand not met by manufacturers.</p>
        <p>John C. Rother, chief lobbyist for AARP, formerly known as the American Association of Retired Persons, said: ''This legislation should not be viewed as a substitute for insurance coverage. We still need Medicare drug benefits.''</p>
        <p>Alan F. Holmer, president of the Pharmaceutical Research and Manufacturers of America, said drug companies opposed the legislation because ''it would put American patients at risk by making it easier for counterfeit, adulterated or subpotent medicines to enter the country.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
