<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rocker's Arm, Not Mouth, Is Doing the Talking Now</title>
    <meta content="27CHAS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/sports/27CHAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rocker, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1DC103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rocker's Arm, Not Mouth, Is Doing the Talking Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Baseball column discusses late season success of Atlanta Braves pitcher John Rocker; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Rocker paused for a moment after the question was asked. Now right there was a sign of maturity, thinking before opening mouth.</p>
        <p>''No,'' he finally said. Again, a wise move, declining the opportunity to speak with reporters before the Atlanta Braves opened a three-game series with the Mets at Shea Stadium last night. If one does not entertain questions from people who would dutifully record the answers for posterity and today's morning newspapers, one does not wind up requiring orthopedic surgery to have foot extracted from mouth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Rocker paused for a moment after the question was asked. Now right there was a sign of maturity, thinking before opening mouth.</p>
        <p>''No,'' he finally said. Again, a wise move, declining the opportunity to speak with reporters before the Atlanta Braves opened a three-game series with the Mets at Shea Stadium last night. If one does not entertain questions from people who would dutifully record the answers for posterity and today's morning newspapers, one does not wind up requiring orthopedic surgery to have foot extracted from mouth.</p>
        <p>So there stood Rocker, as silent as the attention paid him on this, his second visit to New York this season. Did anybody even know Rocker was here?</p>
        <p>If they didn't earlier in the day, they did by the end of it because the Braves' closer was on the mound when the Braves wrapped up their ninth consecutive division championship.</p>
        <p>They did it with a 7-1 victory, and Rocker recorded the final four outs, retiring Robin Ventura on a fly to center field with two on in the eighth inning, then putting down three batters with two on in the ninth.</p>
        <p>''If he hadn't gotten that guy,'' Manager Bobby Cox said, referring to Todd Pratt, who grounded into the final out, ''I was going to jerk him out because he had 30-some pitches already. He threw good, though. He got them out.''</p>
        <p>Was it fitting that Rocker was in the game at the end, considering the problems he had created for the organization last winter with ill-advised comments about a variety of people?</p>
        <p>''That was nothing intended to be in anybody's face at all,'' Cox said. ''It was just the way we wanted to work it tonight.''</p>
        <p>When Rocker was summoned by Cox in the eighth, he ran from the left field bullpen to the mound to the accompaniment of boisterous boos. A beer bottle landed on the grass not far away as he arrived at his work station. A fan had tossed it out of the stands behind first base. The fans' reaction at that moment might not have been different, but just about everything else about this visit to New York was different for the 25-year-old left-hander.</p>
        <p>When the Braves arrived at their midtown Manhattan hotel about 8:30 Monday evening, not a fan was there to shout obscenities at Rocker. No phalanx of police officers paved the way from the team bus to the hotel entrance. Nary an officer was on hand to make sure some rowdy New Yorker didn't extend Rocker a physically exuberant welcome. No barricades forced pedestrians to cross the street, not just to get to the other side. No paddy wagons stood at the ready to transport miscreants to barred facilities for transgressions against a visitor in the city on business.</p>
        <p>Fans, the police, barricades, paddy wagons were all part of the scene when the Braves came to New York at the end of June for their first appearance in the city since last October's playoffs, when the treatment Rocker received from fans prompted him to spew venom in a subsequent magazine interview.</p>
        <p>The highlight -- or lowlight -- of Rocker's presence in June was the obsessive concern over whether he would carry through on his stated intention to take the subway to the game. Whether or not he was ever serious, others prevailed on him not to try such a foolhardy stunt. He didn't. He was transported from the hotel to Shea in a police vehicle.</p>
        <p>No subway ride this time either. Nor a police escort. Shortly after 4 p.m., Rocker emerged from the hotel alone, signed a few autographs and got into a cab for the ride to Shea. The pitcher who ran to the mound six hours later had changed from earlier in the season.</p>
        <p>Unable to throw enough strikes, Rocker lost his closer's job and, worse, was demoted to the minor leagues briefly. But he recently went through a stretch in which he didn't walk a batter in nine games covering nine and a third innings, and he had not allowed a run in his 10 appearances before the Mets series.</p>
        <p>Leo Mazzone, the Braves' notable pitching coach, said it was a search through videotapes five or six weeks ago that led to the return of the 1999 Rocker. The difference, Mazzone said, was the way he took the ball from his glove before pitching it, doing it now in a more relaxed way than before.</p>
        <p>In personality and pitching, Rocker has returned to the point where his teammates no longer shun him and actually have confidence in him again.</p>
        <p>''I think we feel good when he comes into a game,'' said Tom Glavine, the Braves' 20-game winner. ''If he's off target from the get-go, you get a little concerned. But if he's banging strikes, guys feel good about it. But even when he's come in and not been real sharp on the first batter, he's made adjustments and done a good job on the other guys, and that's a good sign.''</p>
        <p>It's apparently a good sign for the Braves' internal health that Rocker is not a pariah in the clubhouse anymore. In spring training and earlier in the season, his teammates for the most part wanted nothing to do with him.</p>
        <p>''For a while,'' Glavine said, ''guys were trying to keep their distance, guilt by association. Guys were trying to steer clear of that until it died down and they got a sense for what was happening.''</p>
        <p>Does Rocker have friends in the clubhouse? ''Yeah, probably,'' Glavine said. ''I don't know who they are. I don't really pay attention. I see him hanging around with people, having a beer or eating dinner. I hear guys talking about stuff that they've gone out and done. So I'm assuming he does.''</p>
        <p>Glavine said that the controversy Rocker created last winter lurks somewhere in the background but hasn't surfaced for some time now. ''It's a lot better,'' he said. ''It's been pretty quiet. It's been more about baseball and what this team has been doing, what it needs to do, not so much about what's going on with John.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
