<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; The High Cost of Making Headlines</title>
    <meta content="27RHOD$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/sports/27RHOD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1DE133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; The High Cost of Making Headlines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY entered the room holding hands. Marion Jones, one of the world's greatest sprinters, and her husband, C. J. Hunter, who was coming off as one of the world's biggest head cases.</p>
        <p>The hastily arranged news conference was put together in the wake of news media reports that Hunter, a world-class shot- putter, had tested positive for performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY entered the room holding hands. Marion Jones, one of the world's greatest sprinters, and her husband, C. J. Hunter, who was coming off as one of the world's biggest head cases.</p>
        <p>The hastily arranged news conference was put together in the wake of news media reports that Hunter, a world-class shot- putter, had tested positive for performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
        <p>After a series of Team Nike meetings it had been decided: Hunter would go out front and face the music. As one Nike official put it: ''You define the situation. Don't allow the situation to define you.''</p>
        <p>Marion did not wear a Nike Swoosh yesterday. No warm-ups. Yesterday she was a partner in marriage. There are times when one partner gives 90 percent. This was one of those times.</p>
        <p>''As you all know, this has been very difficult, the past couple of days for C. J. and I,'' Jones began. ''I am here pretty much to show my complete support for my husband. Aside from him being an athlete and me being an athlete, he's my husband and I'm here to show support for him. I believe that the legal system will do what's needed to be done to clear his name.''</p>
        <p>Jones is attempting to accomplish the feat of her life here, one of the greatest feats in Olympic history. She is attempting to win five gold medals. She has already won the 100 meters with ease and was preparing to begin her quest for the 200.</p>
        <p>Yesterday she appealed to the news media for understanding. ''I hope that all of you would respect the fact that I am competing here in the Sydney Games,'' Jones said. ''I have four more events to do. So if we cannot get any more phone calls to our hotel, we would really, really appreciate that.''</p>
        <p>With that Jones stood up, kissed Hunter and left. Next to Jones, who is natural, charismatic, bright and jubilant, Hunter looked as he often looks: uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>For the next 15 minutes Hunter explained and re-explained his position. ''I may not be the most agreeable person and I might be downright mean at times, but nobody on the planet can say that I don't love my wife and I don't love my kids,'' Hunter said through tears. ''I would never, ever do anything to jeopardize her opinion of me. Track and field has never been that important to me where I'd do something like this.''</p>
        <p>The veil of suspicion is so thick, so all encompassing and, in Hunter's case, so unforgiving. One reporter pointedly asked Hunter: Whether you were taking the steroid or not, does that excuse the fact that you had a level in your system that exceeded what was allowed? Everyone knew, including Hunter, the reporter said, that you can't have that stuff in your blood.</p>
        <p>''If you had listened to anything that was said, if it was in a supplement, how would I know it was in the supplement?'' Hunter responded. ''Nothing says calcium and nandrolone, it's calcium.''</p>
        <p>''So am I reasonably expected to take every supplement I buy, find someone to test it and then take it?'' Hunter asked rhetorically. ''Is that what I'm expected to do?''</p>
        <p>The answer is yes, if it keeps your wife, Marion Jones, focused on the greatest event of her life. In hindsight, Hunter should have left the sport in this Olympic year while his wife competed. He should have taken a year off to become her full-time Rock of Gibraltar. He told me last summer that he did the shot because he was good at it, not because he loved it.</p>
        <p>''The only reason I do this, the reason I come,'' he said yesterday, ''is to be able to fly for free.''</p>
        <p>They have earned enough for Hunter to pay his own air fare. If Jones wins the five gold medals, they won't have to pay for a flight from now till kingdom come.</p>
        <p>Yesterday he was asked how long he had carried the news of his positive drug test. Hunter balked. ''One of the things that we're not going to do is get into any questions that are going to cause conflict with the I.O.C., the I.A.A.F. or the U.S.O.C.,'' he said, referring to the world and American governing bodies of the Olympics and track and field.</p>
        <p>''We're going to take the information we have. We're going to take it through the proper channels.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to defend myself vigorously, we've put together a great team. And I'm quite positive that when everything is said and done I'll be exonerated. And your opinions will be totally different.''</p>
        <p>C. J. Hunter and his camp knew in July about the positive tests. Jones did not find out until two days ago when the news leaked from the International Olympic Committee here in Australia. A Nike official confirmed that Hunter knew about this in July.</p>
        <p>Through back-and-forth conversations with the I.A.A.F., members of the Jones camp were confident that the matter would not surface until the Games ended. They miscalculated. Hunter cried yesterday. Intentionally or not, he had compromised his wife, put his family in an awkward and embarrassing position.</p>
        <p>The end result is that for Jones's competitors, the playing field just became level. For Marion Jones, the phrase in her wedding vows -- ''For better or for worse'' -- has assumed a whole new meaning.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
