<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Corzine Buys More Airtime in Senate Race, Franks Takes Attack to Street</title>
    <meta content="27CORZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/politics/27CORZ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Bob (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DF103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Corzine Buys More Airtime in Senate Race, Franks Takes Attack to Street</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Repr Bob Franks opens puckish line of attack in New Jersey Senate campaign, sending few dozen supporters to picket in front of lower Manhattan headquarters of Goldman Sachs Group, formerly headed by opponent Jon Corzine; photo; signs call on investment house to allow Corzine to make his tax returns public; Corzine reportedly has now spent close to $50 million (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Bob Franks opened up a puckish line of attack in his campaign for the United States Senate today, sending a few dozen supporters across the Hudson to picket in front of the Lower Manhattan headquarters of Goldman Sachs Group, the investment house formerly headed by his Democratic opponent, Jon S. Corzine.</p>
        <p>Holding hand-painted signs with messages like ''What is Jon hiding?'' and chanting, ''New Jersey voters need to know, where Jon Corzine got his dough,'' more than 30 New Jerseyans and at least one New Yorker called on Goldman Sachs to let Mr. Corzine make his tax returns public.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Bob Franks opened up a puckish line of attack in his campaign for the United States Senate today, sending a few dozen supporters across the Hudson to picket in front of the Lower Manhattan headquarters of Goldman Sachs Group, the investment house formerly headed by his Democratic opponent, Jon S. Corzine.</p>
        <p>Holding hand-painted signs with messages like ''What is Jon hiding?'' and chanting, ''New Jersey voters need to know, where Jon Corzine got his dough,'' more than 30 New Jerseyans and at least one New Yorker called on Goldman Sachs to let Mr. Corzine make his tax returns public.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks, a Republican, who did not attend, contends that since Mr. Corzine is mainly using his own money to pay for his Senate campaign, he should disclose his tax returns to comply with the spirit of the campaign finance laws. Mr. Corzine says he is prevented from doing so by a confidentiality agreement he signed when he was co-chairman of Goldman Sachs.</p>
        <p>The issue of Mr. Corzine's finances remains salient largely because he continues to spend at an unprecedented pace. After breaking the record for a Senate race by paying out $35 million in the primary, Mr. Corzine has nearly reached the $50 million mark already, The Associated Press reported today.</p>
        <p>An A.P. analysis of public records at six television network affiliates in New York and Philadelphia showed that Mr. Corzine has bought or reserved $12 million in TV commercial time for the nine-week fall campaign. Included were more than $60,000 each for 30-second commercials that were broadcast during the opening ceremonies of the Olympics, and $320,000 for 90 commercials to be shown on Nov. 6, the day before Election Day.</p>
        <p>Viewers who are starting to think that Mr. Corzine's image is omnipresent may have reason to: in just the first three weeks of the fall campaign, the A.P. reported, Mr. Corzine bought more than 1,500 spots on ABC, NBC and CBS affiliates -- or roughly 12 hours of all-Corzine programming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's spokesman, Tom Shea, said again today that the candidate would ''spend what it takes to get his message out.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks, who does not have the money to counter with his own paid TV ads, is resorting to tactics intended to capture news media attention.  At the lunchtime rally today, his supporters circled in a light rain outside Goldman Sachs's headquarters at 85 Broad Street, handing out yellow fliers headlined ''Free Jon Corzine!'' to dozens of passers-by and shouting, ''Goldman Sachs let Jon go, Corzine's secrets we must know.''</p>
        <p>Michael James, 42, a financial analyst for Prudential who lives in New York, joined the pickets briefly. ''I'm just an independent person who thinks he should release his tax return,'' he said. ''It's unfair. All the other candidates have to do it.''</p>
        <p>The demonstrators included several retirees and a few children. The only one in a business suit was Joseph Paone, a New Brunswick, N.J., lawyer who held a sign saying, ''Free Jon -- Force Him to Be Honest.''</p>
        <p>''It's appalling that a man who is running for office would put his partners at Goldman Sachs ahead of the people of New Jersey,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Edward Flynn, 14, who demonstrated with his mother and sister, said he lived four blocks from Mr. Corzine in Summit, N.J. Asked whether he would vote for Mr. Franks if he could, he replied, ''Well, my parents are Republican.'' His mother, Barbara Flynn, piped up, ''He's a strong Franks supporter.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea, Mr. Corzine's spokesman, had little response to the demonstration. ''I think it's been made very clear that Bob Franks has the market cornered on sophomorics in this campaign,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, meanwhile, campaigned today with Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut in Union County, Mr. Franks's base, focusing on Vice President Al Gore's proposal for prescription drug benefits under Medicare.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shea noted today that Republican leaders in Washington had signaled their support for a measure to allow the reimportation of American-made prescription drugs that are sold cheaper abroad. He said that Mr. Franks had recently voted  against a measure that would have stopped the government from discouraging the purchase of drugs from Canada or elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Citing Mr. Franks's receipt of more than $100,000 in donations from drug companies' political action committees during his four terms in Congress, Mr. Shea said, ''When the time came to stand up for our seniors and against the special interests, Bob Franks buckled at the knees.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Franks's spokesman, Peter DeMarco, said Mr. Franks voted against the bill only because it failed to ensure the safety of reimported drugs. The compromise version now being considered requires that the Food and Drug Administration certify that reimported drugs are safe and effective.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
