<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Course of Justice</title>
    <meta content="27WED1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/opinion/27WED1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1DC133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Course of Justice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial in series on key issues in presidential race focuses on importance of two or more Supreme Court appointments that the next president may make; notes even one new justice could be enough to alter court's course on some major issues; cites Gov George W Bush's identification of court's strongest conservatives as his favorite justices and Gore's admiration for liberal jurists of earlier era; notes appointments to lower federal courts will also have major influence on course of justice; urges more attention be paid to issue</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court's influence in American life was underscored in June with a burst of term-ending decisions on contentious social and political issues like abortion, school prayer, public aid to parochial schools, the rights of criminal suspects and the civil rights of gay people. The narrow margins in some of these cases reflected the continuing turmoil over certain fundamental questions of constitutional law that defines the Rehnquist court. It also served as a reminder that the coming presidential election could have a profound impact on the court's future direction.</p>
        <p>The advanced age of several justices -- Justice John Paul Stevens is 80, Chief Justice William Rehnquist is nearly 76, and Justice Sandra Day O'Connor is 70 -- means that the next president may well find himself in a position to name two or more replacements. Even one new face might be enough to alter the court's present course on abortion and gay rights, church-state separation, racial justice, federal power over state governments and environmental protection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court's influence in American life was underscored in June with a burst of term-ending decisions on contentious social and political issues like abortion, school prayer, public aid to parochial schools, the rights of criminal suspects and the civil rights of gay people. The narrow margins in some of these cases reflected the continuing turmoil over certain fundamental questions of constitutional law that defines the Rehnquist court. It also served as a reminder that the coming presidential election could have a profound impact on the court's future direction.</p>
        <p>The advanced age of several justices -- Justice John Paul Stevens is 80, Chief Justice William Rehnquist is nearly 76, and Justice Sandra Day O'Connor is 70 -- means that the next president may well find himself in a position to name two or more replacements. Even one new face might be enough to alter the court's present course on abortion and gay rights, church-state separation, racial justice, federal power over state governments and environmental protection.</p>
        <p>Consider, for example, the string of 5-to-4 decisions in which a determined conservative majority has begun to weaken Congress's power to protect basic civil rights. In the name of states' rights, it has struck down portions of one law barring age discrimination in employment and another allowing rape victims to sue their attackers. In June, the court correctly overturned bans on so-called partial birth abortion worded to water down abortion rights generally, but the one-vote margin did not bode well for future cases. Similarly, just one vote made the difference when the court, departing from its traditional analysis in discrimination cases, ruled in favor of the Boy Scouts' right to exclude gay members.</p>
        <p>So far, the presidential candidates have given the court little attention on the campaign trail in comparison with issues like taxes and prescription drugs. Nevertheless, many voters regard the court as the campaign's central issue, and there are few issues on which the differences between the two candidates are so clear. Moreover, even though justices cannot always be counted on to side with the presidents who pick them, chief executives  determined to change the court's ideological direction generally succeed. For that reason, voters should ask themselves which candidate's broad vision for the court and its role in protecting constitutional freedoms most closely matches their own.</p>
        <p>Asked to identify his favorite justices, George W. Bush names Antonin Scalia and Clarence Thomas, the court's strongest conservatives. Justices Scalia and Thomas were the only dissenters last term when the court, in a decision written by their usual ally, Chief Justice Rehnquist, upheld the longstanding Miranda rule requiring that suspects be read their rights before a formal interrogation. They were also the only justices to dissent when the court, by a surprisingly wide 7-to-2 margin, voted last January to preserve the ability of citizens to bring lawsuits to enforce anti-pollution laws, a valuable tool for protecting the environment.</p>
        <p>By citing Justices Scalia and Thomas as his favorites, Mr. Bush suggests that he would fill vacancies with conservative nominees who could be expected to support organized school prayer, tuition vouchers and further curbs on the reach of the federal government in the spheres of civil rights, criminal justice and environmental regulation. Mr. Bush would be under fearsome pressure from interest groups within his party to follow through on that implicit pledge. As to abortion, he insists that a  potential justice's views on the issue will not be a ''litmus test,'' but he continues to support his party's platform plank calling for the appointment of anti-abortion judges.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore says he will make it a point to name justices who respect women's reproductive freedom. Though he names two liberal jurists from an earlier era, Thurgood Marshall and William Brennan, as the justices he most admires, his nominees are likely to be judicial moderates in the mold of President Clinton's two appointees, Justices Ruth Bader Ginsburg and Stephen Breyer. They are generally supportive of civil rights and civil liberties, and offended by the Rehnquist court's troubling trend of elevating states' rights over federal authority, in the process substituting the court's own judgment of what national laws are needed for that of Congress.</p>
        <p>Apart from whatever Supreme Court vacancies may arise, the next president will have the chance to fill numerous vacancies in the lower federal courts. These appointments, especially to the federal courts of appeals, will also have a profound influence on the course of justice. That is another good reason that both candidates should be asked to explain more fully their thinking about judicial nominations whose impact will far outlast the winner's tenure as president.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
