<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. Senator's Challenger Has a Recognition Problem</title>
    <meta content="Y27PEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/politics/27PENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE PENNSYLVANIA RACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klink, Ron (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santorum, Rick (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E4DE103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1025" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. Senator's Challenger Has a Recognition Problem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>HARRISBURG, Pa., Sept. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rep Ron Klink, Democrat who won divisive primary, is having trouble raising television money he needs to gain name recognition in eastern Pennsylvania for his challenge to Republican Sen Rick Santorum; Santorum's well-funded campaign has been running television advertisements all over state; Senate Democrats who find Santorum personally abrasive have begun lending Klink fund-raising hand; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Democrats' high-priority targeting of Senator Rick Santorum for defeat this year is proving to be an uphill struggle so far for his challenger, Representative Ron Klink.</p>
        <p>After a divisive primary fight, Mr. Klink has had trouble raising the television money he needs for the expensive Philadelphia and eastern Pennsylvania state markets. These are Democratic strongholds, yet polls show two-thirds of the voters do not recognize the name of Mr. Klink, a Democrat from western Pennsylvania. But the congressman insists he will soon have the traction for a homestretch victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Democrats' high-priority targeting of Senator Rick Santorum for defeat this year is proving to be an uphill struggle so far for his challenger, Representative Ron Klink.</p>
        <p>After a divisive primary fight, Mr. Klink has had trouble raising the television money he needs for the expensive Philadelphia and eastern Pennsylvania state markets. These are Democratic strongholds, yet polls show two-thirds of the voters do not recognize the name of Mr. Klink, a Democrat from western Pennsylvania. But the congressman insists he will soon have the traction for a homestretch victory.</p>
        <p>In contrast, Senator Santorum, with at least eight times the war chest of his challenger, has taken to the tube with ease all over the state for much of this month. His mellow, family-man ads of the ''pop up'' sort seen on music cable channels are designed to take the bite off his early political image as a House iconoclast and Newt Gingrich acolyte.</p>
        <p>''He's got this multimillion-dollar fog machine out there making him look like a Kennedy Democrat,'' complains Mr. Klink, a four-term House member from the steel mill region near Pittsburgh who has struggled to heal the wounds from his primary victory. ''The most frustrating thing for me is the money,'' he admits while buoyed that Senate Democrats who find Mr. Santorum personally abrasive have begun lending a fund-raising hand in the hope of cutting the Republicans' 54-to-46 advantage in the Senate.</p>
        <p>Citing a roll of 30,000 donors, Mr. Santorum is busy raising even more  television money as a campaign ''imperative'' now that his double-digit polling lead shows some possible wavering. His treasury exceeded $10 million even as Mr. Klink, a former television news reporter, labored for his first $1 million after taking a mortgage on his home to win the primary.</p>
        <p>''Ron Klink is running the Democrats' prepackaged campaign that we're all right-wing Gingrich nuts,'' Mr. Santorum complained, insisting he has spent the past six years proving otherwise in a mix of intense constituent services and carefully chosen causes like his prominent sponsorship of a welfare overhaul.</p>
        <p>''There's more Rick Santorum in that legislation than anybody else in the House or Senate,'' said the 42-year-old senator, who had a former welfare mother introduce him at a Republican dinner here and tell of her new career as a teacher.</p>
        <p>For all the underdog hobbles of the 49-year-old Mr. Klink, his spirits are rising after a parched summer of fund-raising. His perceived statewide strength is that like Senator Santorum he is anti-abortion and anti-gun control. But this has not served him well in seeking the donations of liberal Democrats.</p>
        <p>But an emergency infusion of $800,000 from the Senate Democratic campaign committee in Washington is buying him his first two weeks of television commercial time, with more aid likely. ''The odds are shortening,'' a Senate Democratic worker insisted.</p>
        <p>Democrats hope Vice President Al Gore's rise in popularity will energize the Democrats' 500,000-voter edge in state registration and propel Mr. Klink toward an upset. But, as a House member, Mr. Santorum showed strong resistance to the coat-tail effect in 1992 when his heavily Democratic district voted only 30 percent for President George Bush while Mr. Santorum was re-elected by 61 percent.</p>
        <p>Emboldened by Mr. Gore's surge in this swing state, Mr. Klink maintains he will win because his party has the more popular positions on the most urgent issues. But state analysts say there is no sign yet that Mr. Klink is scoring significantly with his opposition to Mr. Santorum's proposals to privatize some Social Security investment and to use health maintenance organizations in dealing with the prescription drug problem.</p>
        <p>''The Democrats grossly underestimated what a good politician Rick Santorum is,'' said Jennifer Duffy, the Senate editor for the Cook Political Report, a Washington newsletter that tracks campaigns. ''He's taken a solid step toward the center,'' said Ms. Duffy, referring to what Democrats denounce as Santorum wiles.</p>
        <p>These include the senator's slight moderation on gun control in accepting trigger locks, despite his 100 percent rating from the National Rifle Association. Democrats also underline as cynical the quiet demeanor of Mr. Santorum, in contrast to his signature brashness, when President Clinton's impeachment trial proved unpopular with the public.</p>
        <p>In their first debate, Mr. Klink pressed the fact that Mr. Santorum once voted for a resolution that included raising the retirement age to 70. The senator said this was part of a larger omnibus package to control entitlement programs and that he had since opposed any age change.</p>
        <p>''Klink is running as a little Gore and his message is getting sharper, more populist,'' said G. Terry Madonna, the political science chairman at Millersville University in Lancaster who conducts the Keystone Poll.  ''The polls have been tightening but Klink still needs to get his name recognition much higher.''</p>
        <p>The congressman accuses the senator of having tried to head off this contest by letting three of his top staff aides work for the Republican challenger two years ago in Mr. Klink's re-election campaign for the House. The senator scoffs at this as routine politicking and questions whether ''there's some personal vendetta'' driving the congressman.</p>
        <p>There seems no love lost between the two politicians and both are proven battlers who upset incumbents with aggressive campaigns in their first campaigns for House seats.</p>
        <p>''This has been a productive six years and has given me a lot of pride and confidence,'' Mr. Santorum said, sounding far from the vulnerable incumbent at the top of the Democrats' target list. ''We've earned another six years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Klink sounds no less confident. ''People are focusing now on the issues and we're in this ballgame,'' he maintains with his old anchorman timbre. ''Santorum has taken extremely conservative, far-out positions and he cannot run away from his record.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE PENNSYLVANIA RACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
