<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buying the Rings for Leverage</title>
    <meta content="27SPON$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234051"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Olympic Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E1DD133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buying the Rings for Leverage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sports Business column discusses corporate sponsorship of Olympics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Samsung Electronics believes in the Olympics, in the brand, the logo and the prestige it expects to receive from investing heavily in them. The South Korean company is paying $55 million as one of the International Olympic Committee's 11 worldwide sponsors and is convinced that the connection will help propel its cellular phone business into world leadership.</p>
        <p>At the Sydney Olympics, Samsung is the newest of what the I.O.C. calls the Olympic Partners in the current quadrennium. Needing to elevate its profile beyond Asia, Samsung created a tented pavilion out of a garage both as a showcase for its future products and as a meeting place for athletes and their families.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Samsung Electronics believes in the Olympics, in the brand, the logo and the prestige it expects to receive from investing heavily in them. The South Korean company is paying $55 million as one of the International Olympic Committee's 11 worldwide sponsors and is convinced that the connection will help propel its cellular phone business into world leadership.</p>
        <p>At the Sydney Olympics, Samsung is the newest of what the I.O.C. calls the Olympic Partners in the current quadrennium. Needing to elevate its profile beyond Asia, Samsung created a tented pavilion out of a garage both as a showcase for its future products and as a meeting place for athletes and their families.</p>
        <p>The pavilion, visible from Sydney Olympic Park, contains a giant TV screen for fans to watch the Games and an indoor theater with a regular show by Cirque de Soleil acrobats.</p>
        <p>It's a very different presence from better-known, veteran sponsors like McDonald's with its seven restaurants, or Visa with its automated teller machines (yes, it's true, you can't charge anything on the Olympic grounds with any other card), or I.B.M. with its information technology.</p>
        <p>''We have second-tier brand awareness, which is why we're utilizing the Olympics to make people more aware of us,'' said Il Hyung Chang, a vice president of Samsung, whose chairman, Kun Hee Lee, is an I.O.C. member. ''Being a sponsor means we're world-class.''</p>
        <p>Like bottles of Coke, Big Macs and Kodak film, Samsung's cellular phones are nearly ubiquitous here. Twenty-five thousand of them are in use by Olympic officials and reporters, among others, a strategy that Samsung hopes will energize its cell phone challenge to Nokia, Ericsson and Motorola, the top three leaders in the field.</p>
        <p>The look of the Sydney Olympics is different from that of the 1996 Summer Games, when downtown Atlanta was a carnival of tacky vendors, tasteless sponsor displays and ambush marketing.</p>
        <p>Here at Olympic Park, the sponsors are visible, but not overwhelming. Downtown, there are Olympic banners and sponsor names wrapped around buses and the city's monorail, but the impact is more tasteful than grotesque.</p>
        <p>''The people from Sydney came to Atlanta and saw what could go wrong,'' said Dick Pound, the I.O.C.'s first vice president, who negotiates its television and marketing deals. ''In Atlanta, the city authorities actively worked against the Olympic committee, even ambushing it.''</p>
        <p>These are the first Games since the Salt Lake City Olympic corruption scandal, which led to the firing or resignation of 10 I.O.C. members and the passage of reforms that await the test of time, if not temptation. Except for John Hancock Financial Services, the sponsor partners quietly waited out the storm to find from I.O.C. surveys and their own research that their investment had not been tainted.</p>
        <p>''It surprised us,'' said Chang, ''but it showed the scandal had nothing to do with the athletes or the Games.'' Rosemary Windsor, vice president for Olympic and corporate events for United Parcel Service, said: ''Large companies recognize that there are scandals. You can't go unscathed.''</p>
        <p>The studies emboldened the I.O.C. to raise its sponsorship fees for the next four years. ''It's the most underpriced marketing program in the world,'' Pound said. ''We remind the sponsors of that very often.''</p>
        <p>The I.O.C. never acknowledges what it charges, but Lesa Ukman, the publisher of IEG Sponsorship Report, a monitoring publication for corporate clients, said the new deals would cost sponsors $65 million for the 2002 Winter and 2004 Summer Games, up from the current $55 million, which is payable in cash, equipment or services.</p>
        <p>Depending on how actively a sponsor wants to make use of its I.O.C. deal -- the Olympics can be marketed in 200 countries -- the cost of advertising, promotion and public relations could be three or four times the I.O.C.'s fee. Samsung said its Olympic program would cost it $200 million.</p>
        <p>Is it worth it? How do sponsors determine how their association with the Olympics delivers for them?</p>
        <p>The group is unlikely to have precise data showing that an upswing in sales is directly linked to the Olympic sponsorships. Most of the sponsors describe the connection as one that can open the door to future business, persuade consumers to sample a product, or establish a warm feeling that the company and the customer are both passionate supporters of the same Olympic cause.</p>
        <p>And if that persuades someone to send an overnight letter via U.P.S. rather than Fedex, or buy a Panasonic big-screen TV and not one from Sony, well, that's why sponsors enlist with the I.O.C.</p>
        <p>''If you're looking for a world platform, it's either the Olympics or the World Cup,'' Ukman said, noting that the advantage of World Cup sponsorship is stadiums with on-field signs, which are barred in the Olympics. ''Samsung needs it for brand awareness; Coke and McDonald's need it to keep people excited about buying Coke or going into a McDonald's. Visa's done the most; it can measure its business at banks, restaurants and stores, and how many people use the cards.''</p>
        <p>Although I.B.M. did not renew its sponsorship beyond Sydney (the Sema Group, a French-British technology services company, will take over), it still deployed an infrastructure that was larger and more complex ''than the moon shot'' to deliver results and information by computer, said Eli Primrose-Smith, I.B.M.'s vice president for worldwide Olympic sponsorship.</p>
        <p>She said that I.B.M. measures the value of its I.O.C. deal by the potential business it can develop by showing customers how it integrates its hardware and software. ''This showcases our technology and the expertise of our people in a high-visibility way,'' Primrose-Smith said.</p>
        <p>Tom Shepard, a senior vice president of Visa International, said his company has developed programs that use the Olympics to drive up card usage, and has noticed a 23 percent jump in Australian card volume since it began working with Australian and Sydney tourist associations.</p>
        <p>''But it's impossible to separate the Olympics from the other marketing programs we have,'' he said. ''They're all integrated into our overall marketing mix. We're not able to clearly differentiate the difference in sales volume specifically because of our Olympic expenditure.''</p>
        <p>And of course, such expenditures keep competitors out. Not every major sponsor will define its involvement as a defensive measure. But wouldn't American Express like to be the only card accepted throughout an Olympic site visited by tens of thousand of people daily for 17 days?</p>
        <p>For other companies, it is a way to provide incentives to employees; Hancock, for example, paid for its sponsorship with increased premium revenues produced by its top salespeople. And U.P.S., like Samsung with its cell phones, wants its package delivery system to become better known outside its domestic turf.</p>
        <p>''It's very hard to say if it's increasing our business,'' U.P.S.'s Windsor said. ''It's not like selling cheeseburgers or another consumer product.'' But as an official sponsor, U.P.S. hopes it can enlarge its business at least with other sponsors, licensees and Olympic organizations.</p>
        <p>The I.O.C. has renewed nine sponsors for its fifth Olympic partners program, covering the 2002 Winter and 2004 Summer Games, at a pace faster than ever before. With I.B.M. gone, U.P.S. is the only other sponsor not yet committed to re-enlisting.</p>
        <p>If U.P.S. declines, the I.O.C. will surely find a replacement, assuming companies still believe in the gospel of associating themselves with the Olympics. And the Olympic committee will also open a 12th sponsor category -- all to make still more money.</p>
        <p>SPORTS BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
