<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Go On. Turn His Head. He Can Take It.</title>
    <meta content="27SALA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/arts/27SALA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eastwood, Clint</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Masters (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Go On. Turn His Head. He Can Take It.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews American Masters production Clint Eastwood: Out of the Shadows; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On tonight's ''American Masters,'' Clint Eastwood's mother explains everything. ''He was the biggest baby born in St. Francis Hospital in San Francisco,'' she brags with fond good humor. ''They took him all around to show the other ladies what they might have done.''</p>
        <p>No wonder Mr. Eastwood became a movie star simply by being. As the director Sergio Leone once said, comparing Mr. Eastwood and Robert De Niro: ''Bobby suffers; Clint yawns.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On tonight's ''American Masters,'' Clint Eastwood's mother explains everything. ''He was the biggest baby born in St. Francis Hospital in San Francisco,'' she brags with fond good humor. ''They took him all around to show the other ladies what they might have done.''</p>
        <p>No wonder Mr. Eastwood became a movie star simply by being. As the director Sergio Leone once said, comparing Mr. Eastwood and Robert De Niro: ''Bobby suffers; Clint yawns.''</p>
        <p>Of course, that was back when Mr. Eastwood was merely an action hero and simplicity was permissible. In the last 20 years, however, he has gained recognition from aesthetic guardians like the Museum of Modern Art in Manhattan and the Cinematheque in Paris, and from the Hollywood establishment, finally winning an Academy Award in 1993, as best director, for ''Unforgiven,'' which won for best picture. Now he's a cultural icon and, apparently, requires more reverence.</p>
        <p>''He remains a complex, contradictory and essential figure in American culture,'' intones the actor Morgan Freeman, narrator of ''Clint Eastwood: Out of the Shadows,'' an awestruck but enjoyable appraisal of Mr. Eastwood's career. Respect is deserved, but does it have to be delivered in such a sober package -- especially when homage is being paid to a studiously unpretentious man who seemed happy playing straight man to an orangutan not once but twice (in ''Every Which Way but Loose'' and its sequel)?</p>
        <p>The documentary affectionately chronicles the construction of a busy, impressive career, one that didn't explode from an early success but was built carefully over time. Mr. Eastwood began acting in 1955, doing journeyman roles in forgettable pictures, as a pretty Hollywood contract player. He did television, and then, in 1964, he became the Man With No Name in Sergio Leone's spaghetti westerns, the modern era's nihilistic answer to John Wayne. (He was hired, for $15,000, because Mr. Leone's first choice, James Coburn, wanted $25,000.)  In 1971 he began to direct, but wasn't taken seriously because that year he also began playing Dirty Harry, the vigilante cop.</p>
        <p>In 1974, for example, reviewing ''Magnum Force'' in The New Yorker, Pauline Kael declared: ''Clint Eastwood isn't offensive; he isn't an actor, so one could hardly call him a bad actor. He'd have to do something before we could consider him bad at it.'' But now, and especially in this documentary, critics can't be lofty enough as they assess Mr. Eastwood's place in the cinematic pantheon (though Ms. Kael's reservations are noted).</p>
        <p>The biography refrains from impolite poking around in Mr. Eastwood's personal life, except to provide some explanatory material from his childhood and showing pictures of him as a beautiful little boy. His parents weren't dirt-poor, but he was raised in the Depression so they had to scramble. They moved all over California as his father chased work. Mr. Eastwood, an optimistic type, saw this as a kind of advantage, allowing him to develop his imaginary play, especially when the family lived in the country without neighbors.</p>
        <p>Besides bestowing her son with the physical size and self-confidence that would become the essence of his heroic image, Mr. Eastwood's mother did something else that would greatly influence his professional development. When Fats Waller died, she brought home an armload of the musician's records, spurring Mr. Eastwood's lifelong obsession with jazz, which eventually led him to direct ''Bird,'' his moody and musically smart biography of the saxophonist Charlie Parker.</p>
        <p>Mainly focusing on Mr. Eastwood's work, the documentary's swooning commentary is kept in check by revealing observations and anecdotes. Don Siegel, who was Mr. Eastwood's mentor and directed many of his films, is succinct in an old filmed interview: ''The hardest thing in the world is to do nothing, and he does it very well. He gives the impression that all the other actors are overacting.''</p>
        <p>Meryl Streep -- not a graduate of the do-nothing school of acting -- recalls that when filming a scene for ''Bridges of Madison County,'' Mr. Eastwood began to cry. Instead of turning this spontaneous outburst toward the camera for full effect, as most actors would, he turned away.</p>
        <p>Later she asked him why he relinquished the opportunity, and he explained plainly: ''People don't want to see me cry.'' Yet this cool assessment shouldn't be mistaken for iconic vanity. In recent films like ''In the Line of Fire'' and ''Space Cowboys,'' Mr. Eastwood has flaunted his wrinkles and allowed his on-screen impassivity to show cracks, too.</p>
        <p>Throughout the documentary, looking improbably fit but not falsely youthful, Mr. Eastwood takes a similarly matter-of-fact view of his career, leaving the frills to other commentators. ''Doing television is great schooling,'' he says of the seven years he spent as Rowdy Yates on ''Rawhide'' 40 years ago. Of his signature line from the Dirty Harry movies -- ''Go ahead, make my day'' -- he says, not quite ruefully, ''I guess it's better to have said it than to not have.''</p>
        <p>He's so comfortable in his leathery skin that he makes the others in these 90 minutes, even the nonactors, look as if they are overdoing it.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MASTERS  Clint Eastwood: Out of the Shadows  PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 8)</p>
        <p>Written by David Kehr and directed by Bruce Ricker. Kate Hirson, editor. Thirteen/WNET New York, Rhapsody Films and the BBC, producers. Susan Lacy, series executive producer.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
