<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bold Themes in a Lynne Cheney Novel</title>
    <meta content="Y27LYN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/politics/27LYNN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE-PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE'S WIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Carey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Lynne V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Showalter, Elaine (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EEDE103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bold Themes in a Lynne Cheney Novel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREY GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Carey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lynne Cheney, conservative wife of vice presidential candidate Dick Cheney, published three novels in addition to two books listed in campaign biography; Prof Elaine Showalter reviews 1981 novel, Old West romance replete with whorehouses, lesbian affairs and attempted rapes, in scholarly review, holding it shows knowledge of work of several feminist historian; Mrs Cheney comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Elaine Showalter, an English professor at Princeton University, was browsing a used-book stall in Paris in the early 1990's when she came upon an astonishing find: an Old West romance, replete with whorehouses, lesbian affairs and attempted rapes, written by an author whose name was all too familiar to academics in the humanities.</p>
        <p>Dr. Showalter had stumbled across an old and obscure novel by Lynne Cheney, who until recently was known mainly for her tenure as the conservative chair of the National Endowment of the Humanities and as a crusader against American educational decline, multiculturalism and relativism. These days, she is best known for being married to the Republican vice-presidential candidate, Dick Cheney.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Elaine Showalter, an English professor at Princeton University, was browsing a used-book stall in Paris in the early 1990's when she came upon an astonishing find: an Old West romance, replete with whorehouses, lesbian affairs and attempted rapes, written by an author whose name was all too familiar to academics in the humanities.</p>
        <p>Dr. Showalter had stumbled across an old and obscure novel by Lynne Cheney, who until recently was known mainly for her tenure as the conservative chair of the National Endowment of the Humanities and as a crusader against American educational decline, multiculturalism and relativism. These days, she is best known for being married to the Republican vice-presidential candidate, Dick Cheney.</p>
        <p>The book, entitled ''Sisters,'' was  printed in 1981 only in a Signet Canadian paperback, Dr. Showalter said, and is now extremely hard to find.</p>
        <p>In the typically hyperbolic language of romance novels, the book's jacket promises the tale of Sophie Dymond, a beautiful, strong-willed widow who leaves New York to investigate her sister's death in Wyoming, and finds herself in a world ''where wives were led to despise the marriage act and prostitutes pandered to husbands' hungers . . . where the relationship between women and men became a kind of guerrilla warfare in which women were forced to band together for the strength they needed and at times for the love they wanted.''</p>
        <p>This week, in a scholarly review published in the Chronicle of Higher Education, Dr. Showalter discussed what she considered some of the more surprising aspects of ''Sisters,'' from its open-minded attitudes toward feminism --  penned by an outspoken opponent of women's studies programs -- to its deliciously Gothic plot elements.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Cheney's brief biography on the official Bush campaign Web site lists only two books to her credit: a history of the House of Representatives she wrote with her husband, and ''Telling the Truth,'' which argues that political correctness is breaking down America's morality.</p>
        <p>She has also written two other novels, ''Executive Privilege'' in 1979 and ''The Body Politic,'' which was written with Victor Gold in 1988 and concerns the wife of a dead vice president.</p>
        <p>But it is ''Sisters'' that dominates Dr. Showalter's review; she said the book struck her in part because of the use it made of work by several feminist historians. It showed knowledge of their work, and also sympathy for 19th-century women's advocates, she said.</p>
        <p>In an interview this week, Mrs. Cheney said she wrote the book while her husband was running for  Congress and said her goal was ''to write a thriller set in the 19th-century West.''</p>
        <p>But she had another goal too. ''In the 1970's feminists did important work recovering women's history,'' she said. ''I tried to do some of that myself.''</p>
        <p>In the book, Sophie Dymond is described as a successful magazine publisher so savvy and strong-minded she carries about a little lacquer box of contraceptives. She goes to Cheyenne, Wyo., in 1886 to find out how her sister Helen had died. As Dr. Showalter writes, Sophie comes upon a group of women who are convinced of female moral superiority and the value of powerful woman-to-woman bonds of friendship, and she comes to understand their grievances even as she rejects their ''lesbian ardor.''</p>
        <p>In one passage Dr. Showalter pointed out, Sophie watches two women embrace in a wagon. ''She  saw that the women in the cart had a passionate, loving intimacy forever closed to her. How strong it made them. What comfort it gave.''</p>
        <p>What really struck her, Dr. Showalter said, was that Mrs. Cheney ''approaches these issues in a very open-minded way, and a way very sympathetic to the women and very sympathetic to the feminist arguments.''</p>
        <p>But those qualities apparently did not appeal much to the book buyers of the early 80's.</p>
        <p>''I think 'Sisters' sold about 500 copies,'' Mrs. Cheney said. ''I hope the renewed interest in it will send it flying off the shelves.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE-PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE'S WIFE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
