<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's New? Braves Win the Division Again. Mets Don't.</title>
    <meta content="SUBMET$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/sports/27METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E4DB103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1302" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's New? Braves Win the Division Again. Mets Don't.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atlanta Braves defeat New York Mets, 7-1, to clinch National League Eastern Division championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stands were speckled by the eighth inning, more empty than filled. There was no reason to stay at Shea Stadium on a raw night when the Mets played dead and their rival, the Atlanta Braves, buried their hopes for a division championship.</p>
        <p>The Braves clinched the National League East title last night with a 7-1 victory over the Mets, who are still being pursued by Los Angeles for the wild card. It would be the second season in a row in which the Mets captured the wild card, but the Braves, as usual, did better: they have now won nine consecutive division crowns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stands were speckled by the eighth inning, more empty than filled. There was no reason to stay at Shea Stadium on a raw night when the Mets played dead and their rival, the Atlanta Braves, buried their hopes for a division championship.</p>
        <p>The Braves clinched the National League East title last night with a 7-1 victory over the Mets, who are still being pursued by Los Angeles for the wild card. It would be the second season in a row in which the Mets captured the wild card, but the Braves, as usual, did better: they have now won nine consecutive division crowns.</p>
        <p>The Mets put up a meager showing, losing for the third time this season to John Burkett, the Braves' No. 5 starter, and making two errors, leading to a pair of unearned runs. The final indignity for the Mets -- and the bundled-up fans who remained -- came in the eighth inning, when John Rocker bolted in from the bullpen and closed out the game.</p>
        <p>If the Braves (94-63) lose the rest of their games and the Mets (89-68) win theirs, the teams will be tied for first. But the Braves will be awarded the division championship because they won the tie breaker last night with their seventh victory against the Mets this year, ensuring them of winning the season series.</p>
        <p>Even if the Braves and Mets end the season tied, there will be no playoff for the division title because both teams will have already qualified for postseason play. ''That's the constant hurdle we're trying to get over,'' Mets catcher Mike Piazza said of the Braves. ''I don't think by any means we're feeling sorry for ourselves. But we just have to play better to beat a quality team, and they're a quality team.''</p>
        <p>The Braves have defined quality for a decade, reaching the last eight National League Championship Series to ensure that no team gets to the World Series without getting through them. When Todd Pratt grounded to Chipper Jones, who tagged Bubba Trammell at third for the final out, Rocker pumped a fist and then lined up with the rest of his teammates, as he would for a routine victory. The clinching party was confined to the clubhouse.</p>
        <p>''We didn't want to do that out there,'' Braves Manager Bobby Cox said. ''It's not the World Series, it's the playoffs, the division. We didn't want to show anybody up, and we didn't.''</p>
        <p>They didn't have to. The Mets did not need to see a celebration to know that the Braves still own them, and will unless the Mets beat them if the teams meet in the National League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>''It's something that is a little upsetting, because I think that we're a good team that matches up fairly well,'' said Al Leiter, who stumbled in the fifth and sixth innings last night and was the losing pitcher.</p>
        <p>''You hope to have a good record against the team I believe you have to eventually go through. You want to at least have some kind of confidence that if we make the playoffs and get through the first round and somehow meet them, the regular-season record is somewhat O.K.''</p>
        <p>The Mets have overcome substantial deficits to beat the Braves; they trailed, 8-1, in the eighth inning on June 30 before mounting a 10-run rally to win. But Rocker was unavailable for that game, and the controversial left-hander confounds the Mets.</p>
        <p>Rocker, whose presence again necessitated several hundred police officers at the park, relieved Kerry Ligtenberg with two out and two on in the eighth. As he reached the mound, a beer bottle landed a few feet behind the mound; Gary Cederstrom, the first-base umpire, pointed out the fan who threw it.</p>
        <p>The fan, Raymond Maniaci, 22, of Wyckoff, N.J., was ejected and was arrested on a charge of reckless endangerment. A friend of his, Brian Peterson, 22, also of Wyckoff, was charged with obstructing governmental administration and disorderly conduct. Peterson pleaded guilty in 1998 to manslaughter, along with his girlfriend, in the death of their newborn son at a motel in Delaware.</p>
        <p>Rocker's first pitch was high, well out of the strike zone. But he recovered and got Robin Ventura to fly to center, ending the inning. In the ninth, the Mets singled twice off Rocker, but he retired the next three Mets to finish the game. Rocker has pitched three and two-thirds scoreless innings against the Mets this year.</p>
        <p>Burkett (10-6) allowed three hits and one run in six innings and benefited from outstanding plays by Andruw Jones in center. Burkett came into the game with the highest earned run average in the Braves' rotation, but he is at his best against the Mets.</p>
        <p>''He was throwing strikes and working fast,'' Piazza said. ''Unfortunately, we just weren't able to get into the game.''</p>
        <p>Burkett's bat brought in the first Braves run last night, after Leiter appeared to have escaped trouble in the fifth.</p>
        <p>With one out, Reggie Sanders doubled for his second hit. Sanders, who entered September batting under .200, has made a remarkable turnaround, with a .343 average for the month after his double. Still, Leiter seemingly had to worry only about Walt Weiss because Burkett hit next.</p>
        <p>Leiter fanned Weiss for the second out. But he left a fastball up to Burkett, who punched it into right field for a single. Sanders is fast and scored easily, and Leiter knew it.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I let Burkett's hit and the run scored in the fifth bother me enough to let me get a little bit off rhythm,'' Leiter said. ''It didn't help that the first batter of the next inning, in Chipper, hits a home run.''</p>
        <p>Chipper Jones ripped a curveball over the wall in left center to lead off the sixth, increasing the Braves' lead to 2-0, and Andres Galarraga followed with a hard-hit groundout to Edgardo Alfonzo, ranging close to second base to field it.</p>
        <p>Javy Lopez doubled to left past a diving Ventura, and Leiter walked Brian Jordan. Dave Wallace, the pitching coach, visited the mound, but Leiter, after getting ahead of Sanders, issued another walk to load the bases. Weiss chopped a ball softly, between third and short, a troublesome area.</p>
        <p>Ventura charged it on an angle and threw home as he turned his body toward the plate. It was a hurried, awkward throw, rare from a Gold Glove winner like Ventura, and it was so wild that a diving Piazza could not get a glove on it. Lopez and Jordan scored, Sanders and Weiss took extra bases, and Leiter left the game trailing, 4-0.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes you just have to take a chance and see what happens,'' said Ventura, who did not slip on the play. ''I made an error on that one. But I don't think any of us are going out there to play scared.''</p>
        <p>But they will go out for the season's final five games knowing that one goal eluded them this year. No matter what happens in the postseason, the Braves proved over six months that they are still the class of the N.L. East.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
