<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arafat's Visit to Barak's Place Broke the Ice, Both Sides Say</title>
    <meta content="Y27MIDE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/world/27MIDE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Center for Middle East Peace and Economic Cooperation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abraham, S Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DB133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arafat's Visit to Barak's Place Broke the Ice, Both Sides Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>RAMALLAH, West Bank, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Ehud Barak and aide to Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat hail Arafat's visit for late-night supper at Barak's home, holding it provided fresh momentum to peace talks; Arafat aide says meeting was engineered by S Daniel Abraham, American businessman who backs peace efforts through Center for Middle East Peace and Economic Cooperation, which he co-founded (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was just a little suburban dinner party, nothing fancy. The host and his guest of honor cracked jokes. They strolled in the garden for an intimate chat. And then the host kissed his guest goodbye, walked him to a waiting Israeli military helicopter and waved as the guest, wearing his trademark kaffiyeh, flew back to Gaza City.</p>
        <p>A senior adviser to Yasir Arafat said the late-night supper, at Prime Minister Ehud Barak's private home in Kochav Yair on Monday, was the single best meeting ever between the Palestinian and Israeli leaders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was just a little suburban dinner party, nothing fancy. The host and his guest of honor cracked jokes. They strolled in the garden for an intimate chat. And then the host kissed his guest goodbye, walked him to a waiting Israeli military helicopter and waved as the guest, wearing his trademark kaffiyeh, flew back to Gaza City.</p>
        <p>A senior adviser to Yasir Arafat said the late-night supper, at Prime Minister Ehud Barak's private home in Kochav Yair on Monday, was the single best meeting ever between the Palestinian and Israeli leaders.</p>
        <p>The adviser, Nabil Shaath, said today that it had been ''very cordial,'' even congenial. He noted that the two men had walked together to the balcony twice -- ''and both came back.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Barak said the evening had been ''warm and open.''</p>
        <p>How did the two leaders move from tense, strained relations to hugs in a single evening? Only their advisers know. Has improved chemistry shortened the distance from a deadlock to a permanent peace treaty? Probably not.</p>
        <p>Nothing substantive was discussed, the advisers said.</p>
        <p>But today both sides were willing to declare fresh momentum and, as their negotiators were landing in the United States, to move forward once more into yet another ''decisive'' phase of peacemaking.</p>
        <p>''Yesterday, in my home in Kochav Yair,'' Mr. Barak said today, ''we met with Arafat and the entire Palestinian leadership for a warm, open meeting that I believe will help us in our efforts to renew the negotiations. I would say that we are at the entrance to a very intensive effort and, in a way, to the last effort in this round to reach a breakthrough.''</p>
        <p>Such an intimate meeting between Mr. Arafat, once Israel's mortal enemy, and an Israeli leader would have been unthinkable just years ago. Mr. Arafat only made one previous visit to an Israeli prime minister's home, and that was to pay condolences to the family of Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin after he was assassinated in 1995.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shaath said the Kochav Yair meeting had been engineered by an American Jewish businessman, S. Daniel Abraham. Mr. Abraham, founder of the Slim-Fast Food Companies, is a leading contributor to the Democratic Party's election campaigns this year and a backer of Israeli-Arab peace efforts through the Washington-based Center for Middle East Peace and Economic Cooperation, which he co-founded.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat made an effort at developing a relationship last fall and earlier this year, they never clicked. Since the Camp David peace talks ended two months ago, they have not communicated directly, though they did shake hands at a United Nations gathering of world leaders earlier this month.</p>
        <p>The 15-day meeting at Camp David, presided over by President Clinton, did not produce a permanent peace accord to end 52 years of bitter conflict, as planned. But it provoked substantive debate on all of the issues and something close to a meeting of the minds on the key issues of territorial division, water resources and security cooperation.</p>
        <p>After Camp David, though, both sides say the momentum evaporated and they lost ground on those issues. In a rare news conference by a senior Palestinian official today, Mr. Shaath, the minister of planning and international cooperation, blamed the Israelis for focusing too much on the most difficult issue, the future status of the holy site known to Jews as the Temple Mount and to Muslims as Haram al Sharif.</p>
        <p>''We can live without turning our feuds into religious issues,'' he said. ''And the stalemate cannot be broken if we just concentrate on Haram al Sharif. It wouldn't be at all bad if instead, where we are close we made things closer. Trust would be created if on five to seven issues we could measure some progress.''</p>
        <p>In Washington, Israeli and Palestinian negotiators are to meet separately with American mediators to review a bridging proposal that seeks to reconcile conflicting demands on all of the key issues on the negotiating table.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shaath said President Clinton first reviewed a final copy of the document on Friday and suggested summoning the parties to review it rather than making it public, to the risk of provoking further discord.</p>
        <p>''The man is agonizing over it,'' Mr. Shaath said, referring to Mr. Clinton, ''because he doesn't want another failure.''</p>
        <p>The Palestinians do not feel the same sense of urgency as Mr. Barak, who will face a possible dissolution of his minority government when the Israeli Parliament reconvenes at the end of October.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shaath said Mr. Barak could find a way to reconstitute his coalition. He also said the Palestinians thought there were advantages to dealing with a ''lame duck'' American president after the November elections.</p>
        <p>''The Israelis are trying to create a mental picture of Palestinians like croupiers at a casino pocketing all the chips and not giving anything in return,'' Mr. Shaath said. ''I think the giving has already happened.</p>
        <p>''Israel has had a great two years'' because of Israeli-Palestinian security cooperation that has reduced terrorism, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
