<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns; In Nassau, Hard to Leave A Gilded Past</title>
    <meta content="27TOWN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/nyregion/27TOWN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gulotta, Thomas S (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E0DD103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns; In Nassau, Hard to Leave A Gilded Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew</byline>
      <dateline>MINEOLA, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Our Towns column reports that Nassau County, New York's, long-running financial nightmare is reaching climax as bumbling band of officials prepare to take weed whackers to their beloved bureaucracy, and then probably raise taxes; County Exec Thomas Gulotta, his back to wall, wants to lay off 350 employees, mostly lower-level workers who clear the snow, run recreation programs and generally keep suburbs running (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE good news is that Nassau County's long-running financial nightmare is reaching a climax. Within weeks, the bumbling band of county officials will take their weed whackers to their beloved bureaucracy, and then they will likely raise taxes (by $100 a household, at most). If not, state officials will take over and do it. And just like that, the greatest municipal finance crisis in one of the state's richest counties will be on the mend.</p>
        <p>Solving the problem requires Nassau's leaders to wrench themselves from their  dysfunctional past of big paternal government, a gold-plated police department and extreme tax aversion -- a maneuver that is becoming painful to watch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE good news is that Nassau County's long-running financial nightmare is reaching a climax. Within weeks, the bumbling band of county officials will take their weed whackers to their beloved bureaucracy, and then they will likely raise taxes (by $100 a household, at most). If not, state officials will take over and do it. And just like that, the greatest municipal finance crisis in one of the state's richest counties will be on the mend.</p>
        <p>Solving the problem requires Nassau's leaders to wrench themselves from their  dysfunctional past of big paternal government, a gold-plated police department and extreme tax aversion -- a maneuver that is becoming painful to watch.</p>
        <p>County Executive Thomas S. Gulotta, the undisputed master of the grainy ''grip and grin'' weekly newspaper photo, has tried to portray his efforts as a Marshall Plan for Nassau. But he's come off more like the discount clothier than the general.</p>
        <p>Every constituent is a consumer to Mr. Gulotta. He's fiercely proud of resisting raising county taxes for nine years. But his back is to the wall. He wants to lay off 350 employees, mostly lower-level people who clear the snow and run health and recreation programs and make the suburbs the suburbs. His big concession is a proposed $33-per-household property tax increase, pocket change in a county where the average house sells for $254,500.</p>
        <p>Nor is Mr. Gulotta forgetting a favorite constituency, the county police. He hammered out a proposed contract with the police, whose $90,000-a-year veterans are among the highest paid in the nation. The police agreed to forfeit the Flag Day holiday and other pricey baubles that Mr. Gulotta said would save tens of millions of dollars. In exchange, Mr. Gulotta agreed to increase their pay 22 percent over five years.</p>
        <p>As a reality check, Police Commissioner William Willett was asked Monday what he thought of a big raise during a financial crisis. No reality found. ''I really haven't given it that much thought,'' he said, blithely.</p>
        <p>Political thought in Nassau County has historically hewed to the Republican Party gospel of low taxes, ample patronage, stellar services and a barrier against the evils of New York City.</p>
        <p>The enforcement mechanism behind the gospel was laid out in 1996 testimony by a Nassau County detective, Melvin Boone, in a voting rights case in the Town of Hempstead. ''There was never a written or spoken directive,'' Mr. Boone said, speaking about patrolling the Queens-Nassau line. ''However, you would come to know if there were people coming over the border, good people of Nassau County didn't want that, so you were to make sure they had business and that they would do their business and then go back where they belong.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boone's party affiliation?</p>
        <p>''I was applying for a job as a police officer in Nassau County,'' he said, ''and I was instructed that I ought to register Republican if I was going to get that job.''</p>
        <p>POLITICAL reality has changed, though. Now, Republican leaders are desperate for any victory at the polls and eager to hoist all blame for the county's problems on their former ally, Mr. Gulotta. Population shifts have altered Nassau's racial and political complexion. And Nassau's stacking-doll system of towns and villages and school boards and fire districts and sewer districts -- most with independent taxing authority -- has produced steady increases in local taxes, even as the county held its own taxes down.</p>
        <p>But the setting for the budget debate, like the debate itself, seems stuck in time. The county legislative chamber resembles a 1960's suburban den with wood paneling, linoleum flooring and fluorescent fixtures.</p>
        <p>For months, Peter J. Schmitt, the Republican legislative leader, has been saying the same thing. ''We provide the Cadillac of services,'' he said Monday. ''You have to streamline.'' Where? Child care. Services for the mentally ill. How about tax increases? ''I have neighbors who live on 60-by-100 lots and are paying $6,000 to $8,000 in taxes,'' he said. ''They say that's enough.''</p>
        <p>This is the suburbs, and Judith A. Jacobs, leader of the Legislature's year-old Democratic majority, has neighbors, too. Hers are incredulous when she tells them that a $100-per-household annual tax increase could solve much of the county's fiscal problems without deep layoffs that would hurt services people like. ''When people find out the amount of money we're talking about they think we're crazy,'' she said. ''$78! $100!''</p>
        <p>Besides, easing the crisis would free Mrs. Jacobs from what has become a full-time legislative job, allowing her to resume work at her husband's real estate firm.</p>
        <p>''He'd pay $200 to have me back.''</p>
        <p>$250, anyone?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
