<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOD CHAIN</title>
    <meta content="27CHAI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/living/27CHAI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6DF133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOD CHAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELISSA CLARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Instant Coffee, Three Ways</p>
        <p>Q. How is instant coffee manufactured? And when the label reads ''agglomerated coffee,'' what does that mean?</p>
        <p>A. Instant coffee is manufactured in two ways. The most widespread method is spray-drying, in which high heat is used to extract all the liquid from a coffee concentrate, leaving crumbly, hollow crystals. Unfortunately, the heat damages the coffee's natural flavor and aroma.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Instant Coffee, Three Ways</p>
        <p>Q. How is instant coffee manufactured? And when the label reads ''agglomerated coffee,'' what does that mean?</p>
        <p>A. Instant coffee is manufactured in two ways. The most widespread method is spray-drying, in which high heat is used to extract all the liquid from a coffee concentrate, leaving crumbly, hollow crystals. Unfortunately, the heat damages the coffee's natural flavor and aroma.</p>
        <p>A better but more expensive method is freeze-drying. Vats of already brewed coffee are frozen and cut into slabs, and the ice crystals are drawn off in a vacuum. Since the brew is dehydrated without intense heat, the flavor molecules are not as greatly damaged, and the reconstituted coffee is richer and tastier than the spray-dried kind.</p>
        <p>Agglomerated instant coffee consists of spray-dried granules artificially made to clump so that they vaguely resemble freshly ground coffee beans. This process does not affect what is left of the coffee's flavor.</p>
        <p>Low-Calorie Coconut Milk</p>
        <p>Q. Is there a way to reduce the calories and fat in coconut milk without losing the taste?</p>
        <p>A. Reduced-fat coconut milk, with about a third as many calories, is usually sold alongside the regular kind, but you can make your own.  One way is to chill a can of regular coconut milk at least two hours so that the fat rises to the surface and can be skimmed off. The milk that is left is fine for savory dishes, but you might miss the richness in desserts like coconut flan.</p>
        <p>You can also puree a cup of shredded coconut with a cup of boiling water or heated skim milk, let it infuse for five minutes, then strain the mixture, pressing down hard on the solids. Chill this milk, then skim the fat off the top.</p>
        <p>Honey's Changing State</p>
        <p>Q. Why does honey solidify after an opened jar has been stored at room temperature for a while? How can it be liquefied? Can this solidification be avoided altogether?</p>
        <p>A. Honey is a combination of sugars, water, gum and lesser quantities of pollen, wax, acids, proteins, minerals, vitamins, enzymes and pigments. Its final composition results from the flowers visited by the bees that produced it and the evaporation in the honeycombs. When bees sip from flowers, the enzymes in their saliva cause the sucrose in the nectar to break down into two simple sugars: fructose and glucose. Over time, honey inevitably begins to crystallize, as the simple sugars revert back to sucrose.</p>
        <p>Crystallization can be discouraged by storing the honey in airtight containers, which keeps dampness out and prevents loss of moisture, either of which can lead to crystallization. In theory, storing honey below 52 degrees also helps, but refrigeration will actually make honey crystallize faster because of the high moisture level in a refrigerator.</p>
        <p>Returning honey to its liquid state is easy. Simply heat it in the jar, either on low in the microwave or in a pan of very hot water. Heat causes the sucrose to break down again, recreating the syrupy texture.</p>
        <p>MELISSA CLARK</p>
        <p>Questions about food and cooking can be sent to Food Chain, the Dining section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York 10036-3959, or by e-mail to dining@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Questions about food and cooking can be sent to Food Chain, the Dining section, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York 10036-3959, or by e-mail to dining@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
