<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="27FSUM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEFDC103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1260" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Opposition Claims Victory; Milosevic Seeks Runoff  Yugoslavia's government-controlled election commission said President Slobodan Milosevic trailed his challenger, Vojislav Kostunica, but rejected Mr. Kostunica's claim to outright victory, and it set a runoff for Oct. 8. Opposition leaders called the tally fraudulent and said they would not take part in a runoff.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Opposition Claims Victory; Milosevic Seeks Runoff  Yugoslavia's government-controlled election commission said President Slobodan Milosevic trailed his challenger, Vojislav Kostunica, but rejected Mr. Kostunica's claim to outright victory, and it set a runoff for Oct. 8. Opposition leaders called the tally fraudulent and said they would not take part in a runoff.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Clinton praised the Yugoslav people for choosing change and sought to embolden them by offering to lift economic sanctions if they prevailed. But he warned that Mr. Milosevic might try to cling to power.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Pan Am Flight 103 Bomb Trial  The Libyan double agent considered the most crucial witness in the Lockerbie trial in the Netherlands testified that the two defendants brought a suitcase to Malta like the one believed to contain the bomb that destroyed the airliner. But he did not say he saw a bomb put in the suitcase or the suitcase put on a plane.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Ferry Sinks Off Greece  At least 28 people died and more than 50 were missing after a Greek ferry with 511 aboard ran aground and sank off the Aegean island of Paros, the merchant marine ministry said. Officials said that more than 350 people had been rescued.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Blair Takes Responsibility  Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain, speaking at the Labor Party's annual convention in Brighton, took responsibility for government actions that sent the party's poll ratings plummeting this month. But he also urged the party to have confidence that it would win a second term in the next elections.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Split in French Politics Widens  Supporters of France's two leaders, President Jacques Chirac and Prime Minister Lionel Jospin, hurled accusations of corruption and political manipulation at each other in the growing scandal springing from a videotaped confession that accuses Mr. Chirac with misconduct.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>China Lashes Out at Vatican  China stepped up its attacks on the Vatican for its plans to canonize 120 Catholics killed in China between 1648 and 1930. Though the Vatican considers them martyrs for their faith, a Chinese government spokesman accused the Vatican of glorifying Western imperialism.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Unrest at Global Finance Talks  Protesters throwing stones and attacking the police with gas bombs tried to shut down the global finance meeting in Prague, but the talks continued under heavy security.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Peruvian Protested in Panama  Protesters took to the streets to denounce the presence of Vladimiro Montesinos, Peru's disgraced intelligence chief, who arrived on Sunday and is seeking asylum. In Peru, a prosecutor said she was closing the bribery case against him.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-21</p>
        <p>Effort to Cut Drug Costs Wins House G.O.P. Backing  Senate legislation that would allow imports of low-priced prescription drugs won support from House Republican leaders, increasing prospects that Congress would approve it and President Clinton would sign it into law. The measure, opposed by the pharmaceutical industry, would let pharmacies and wholesale distributors buy prescription drugs cheaply abroad and sell them to consumers at low prices.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Assessing Secrets Case  Attorney General Janet Reno and F.B.I Director Louis J. Freeh defended their handling of the Wen Ho Lee case, asserting at a Senate hearing that Mr. Lee had committed a serious crime when he removed what they called a portable library of atomic secrets from Los Alamos.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Incomes Up, Poverty Down  The Census Bureau said that median household income topped $40,000 for the first time last year and that the percentage of households living in poverty dropped to the lowest point in more than two decades.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>The State of the Military  Senior military commanders intend to warn Congress today that the armed services are struggling with aging equipment, shortages of parts and shortfalls in training that will need billions in new spending.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Gore Takes Campaign to MTV  Vice President Al Gore participated in an MTV forum in which, among other topics, he explained his support for civil unions between homosexuals, his opposition to the legalization of medical marijuana and his distaste for misogynistic music.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Year-Round School Plan  A New York City Board of Education task force is set to recommend that new high schools operate all year, with student vacations scattered throughout the year.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>U.S. Sues Harvard Advisers  Federal prosecutors filed a civil suit accusing two Harvard advisers who helped mold Russia's economic reforms in the mid-1990's of misusing their government-financed positions in pursuit of personal gain. The men denied any wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>District Drops Support For Scouts Over Gay Policy  Manhattan's Community School District 2 joined some other groups across the nation by withdrawing support for the Boy Scouts, citing the exclusion of gays. The board, whose area includes Hell's Kitchen, Chelsea, TriBeCa, Battery Park City, Chinatown and the East Side from 14th Street to 96th Street, urged the city's other districts and the Board of Education to follow its lead.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Limiting Some Ads for Children  Hillary Rodham Clinton called on the government to ban commercials aimed at preschool children and to prohibit advertising inside public elementary schools.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Spanish All-News Radio  WNNY-AM (1380), formerly WDKM, makes its debut today as the New York region's first all-news, all-the-time Spanish-language station.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Gene Link to Adult Diabetes  A novel gene associated with development of Type 2, or adult-onset, diabetes has been identified. If confirmed, it would be the first discovery of a gene involved in the most common kind of Type 2 diabetes.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>'R' Movies and Children  The Motion Picture Association of America announced steps to restrict the marketing of R-rated films to children. Movie industry documents show that some Hollywood companies routinely recruited teenagers and children as young as 9 to help evaluate R-rated movie projects.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000</p>
        <p>S1-8</p>
        <p>Gold for U.S. Softball  The United States beat Japan, 2-1, in an eight-inning Olympics final.</p>
        <p>S1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Court Takes Golf Cart Case  The Supreme Court will decide whether Casey Martin, who has a circulatory disorder, has a legal right to use a cart in PGA Tour events.</p>
        <p>D5</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-32</p>
        <p>A Round for Microsoft  The Supreme Court rejected a government effort to have the court hear Microsoft's antitrust appeal without its first being heard by an appeals court. The appeals court has been more receptive to Microsoft's legal defenses than the trial judge.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Direct From Drug Maker  Bayer, unable to make enough of a new hemophilia drug, has taken the unusual step of asking patients to apply for the drug, Kogenate FS, through a corporate program rather than getting it from a pharmacy or distributor. Bayer said it wanted avoid having stocks of the drug sitting unused in pharmacies.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Kodak's Warning to Investors  Eastman Kodak, citing a broad decline in sales, said third-quarter earnings would be as much as 25 cents a share below expectations, and that fourth-quarter earnings might disappoint, as well.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>The Dow dropped 176.83 points, or 1.6 percent, to 10,631.32; the S.&amp; P. 500 fell 11.82 points, to 1,427.21; and the Nasdaq fell 52.12 points, or 1.4 percent, to 3,689.10.</p>
        <p>C20</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: The course of justice; Peru's spy chief in exile; topics.  Columns: Paul Krugman, Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E9  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E10  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
