<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With a Little Luck, U.S. Keeps Its Hold on the Gold Medal</title>
    <meta content="27SOFT$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: SOFTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Softball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Softball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Softball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DD133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With a Little Luck, U.S. Keeps Its Hold on the Gold Medal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>BLACKTOWN, Australia, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US wins gold medal in softball at Sydney Olympics; Japan wins silver medal and Australia wins bronze; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Laura Berg saw the ball sailing, and the Japanese left fielder, Shiori Koseki, straining. Halfway down the first-base line, Berg realized Koseki would be there, in position. She watched the glove go up, and the catch being made. And then Koseki was falling, the ball dislodging, with Koseki landing on her back.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, Jennifer McFalls was in full stride off second, and Berg was watching the moment unfold, the gold medal moment. She wanted to feel it, freeze it, because traumatic experience has taught her that, ''You never know what comes from one moment to another.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Laura Berg saw the ball sailing, and the Japanese left fielder, Shiori Koseki, straining. Halfway down the first-base line, Berg realized Koseki would be there, in position. She watched the glove go up, and the catch being made. And then Koseki was falling, the ball dislodging, with Koseki landing on her back.</p>
        <p>Suddenly, Jennifer McFalls was in full stride off second, and Berg was watching the moment unfold, the gold medal moment. She wanted to feel it, freeze it, because traumatic experience has taught her that, ''You never know what comes from one moment to another.''</p>
        <p>It was that way for the United States softball team here at the Olympics, favored to defend its Atlanta gold medal, but having to live on the edge, game to game, inning to inning. When the Americans finally defeated Japan by 2-1 tonight, they did it with only one hit and the decisive play came in -- what else? -- an extra inning, the eighth.</p>
        <p>It was another tense duel that featured Lisa Fernandez, the iron lady, and how many pitchers get the ball with the title up for grabs on 21 hours' rest? After shutting out Australia in the semifinal the previous night, after exorcising home run demons named Peta Edebone and Joanne Brown on the final two outs, Fernandez knew she would not have her A game. Her coach, Ralph Raymond, still told her, ''It's yours to win or lose.''</p>
        <p>''And that's why Lisa Fernandez is who she is,'' Fernandez's catcher, Stacey Nuveman, would say after Fernandez's three-hitter.</p>
        <p>Most of the Japanese, who finished first in the preliminary round, listed their employment in the tournament media guide as ''office clerk,'' and they played with a neat and orderly efficiency. They didn't surprise Raymond, the native of Worcester, Mass., who looks weathered enough to have managed the Red Sox.</p>
        <p>''I said back in June Japan would be the sleeper,'' he said. ''They've been getting better and better.''</p>
        <p>Their starting pitcher, 20-year-old Mariko Masubuchi, didn't throw as hard as Fernandez, but mixed her pitches well. Her fielders made the plays. And the Japanese coaches, who know Fernandez well from the years she has played professionally in Japan, may have been stealing the early innings signals from Nuveman.</p>
        <p>The American side became suspicious when Reika Utsugi led off the visitors' fourth inning by sitting on a Fernandez changeup and clocking a rising liner to deep center field. Berg, one of the team's shorter players at 5 feet 7 inches, went back to time her leap. The ball sailed on her, though, over the fence.</p>
        <p>''I felt I should have had it, and that I owed Lisa one,'' she said.</p>
        <p>After winning 112 straight games, the Americans suffered through a numbing scoring drought against the three other teams that would make the medal round. They dropped three straight last week for the first time in 35 years of international play. They were demoralized by the time Edebone's two-run homer cleared the left-field fence and gave Australia a 2-1 victory over Fernandez after Australian hitters had been struck out 25 times over 12 2/3 innings.</p>
        <p>Berg was one of the vocal players who snapped them out of it. A 25-year-old assistant coach at Fresno State, she had played on the 1996 team, when winning and losing was life and death. A year ago, in August, she found out differently. She was home in Fresno, and had just been dropped off after a movie by her fiance of two years, Eric Kidd.</p>
        <p>The dreaded phone call soon came. Kidd had gone to a friend's birthday party. He got involved in some horseplay, a wrestling match. He stumbled, hitting his head as he fell backward. He broke his C-4 and C-5 vertebrae and was paralyzed from the chest down.</p>
        <p>They have remained engaged, but only after Berg insisted.</p>
        <p>''He thinks it's not fair for me to have to take care of him,'' she said. ''It's a natural feeling for him to have but it doesn't matter. We have our good days and our bad days but I love him unconditionally.''</p>
        <p>She awoke yesterday, believing it would be one of the best days. Back in Las Vegas, where Kidd lives, it was still Sept. 25, his 33rd birthday. They have not seen each other since Valentine's Day because of Berg's Olympic commitments. They spoke by phone, and he told her to bring home the gold.</p>
        <p>That plan looked endangered with the United States being no-hit into the fifth. With one out, Michele Smith was hit by a pitch and took second on a groundout. Up came Nuveman, who had hit the ball cleanly into right field her first time up, only to be thrown out at first. This time, she compensated for her catcher's speed, lacing the ball into the right-center gap, all the way to the fence. She lumbered no farther than first but the game was tied.</p>
        <p>By the home eighth, with Fernandez in a groove, the Japanese had changed pitchers, bringing in Juri Takayama, who was unscored on in the tournament.</p>
        <p>It was raining now, and the ball was slick and the grass was wet. Takayama walked Nuveman on a close 3-2 pitch. With one out, she also walked Dot Richardson, sending McFalls, the pinch-runner for Nuveman, to second.</p>
        <p>With the winning run in scoring position, the outfield had to play shallow. A lefty contact hitter, Berg was told by Raymond to go ahead, take her healthiest cut. She lofted the twisting fly that would fall into and out of Koseki's glove. Koseki would tearfully explain that she misjudged the ball. Hit? Error?</p>
        <p>Officially, it would be the latter, but to Berg, to the Americans, the scoring of the play was lost in celebration, in the rain that washed away last week's failure and put them on the gold medal stand again.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: SOFTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
