<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Insiders Get A Sturdy Tool To Rake In Stock Gains</title>
    <meta content="Y27INS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/business/27INSI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000930T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MANAGEMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insider Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Geanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insider Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DA133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Insiders Get A Sturdy Tool To Rake In Stock Gains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEANNE ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenberg, Geanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Securities and Exchange Commission rule that will go into effect in October should make it easier for company executives to sell their companies' stock without running afoul of insider-trading law; will allow insiders and other investors, like top executives, board members or key advisers, to buy or sell stock in their companies no matter how much inside information they have; trades must be made under plans created before investors knew about developments that could push up or drag down the stock; new provision's biggest impact will be on senior managers eager to unlock wealth of their stock-and-options riches without veering into legal trouble; graphs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The crests and troughs in the AVT Corporation's stock price are enough to bring on a bad case of sea sickness.</p>
        <p>That complicates life for Roger Fukai, the company's interim chief executive, whose fortunes have been tied to AVT, a maker of communications software in Kirkland, Wash., ever since he left the safety of a large corporation in 1988 for ''plenty of risk'' and a boatload of stock options.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The crests and troughs in the AVT Corporation's stock price are enough to bring on a bad case of sea sickness.</p>
        <p>That complicates life for Roger Fukai, the company's interim chief executive, whose fortunes have been tied to AVT, a maker of communications software in Kirkland, Wash., ever since he left the safety of a large corporation in 1988 for ''plenty of risk'' and a boatload of stock options.</p>
        <p>Like many corporate insiders at small high-technology companies, Mr. Fukai, AVT's longtime chief financial officer, eventually found himself with most of his wealth in his company's securities but with many restriction on how and when he could turn them into cash.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fukai was only allowed to trade during ''window periods'' that lasted just a few weeks after the release of quarterly financial results, and only when no major market-affecting news like an acquisition was on the horizon. Trading before such knowledge becomes public can violate federal insider trading law.</p>
        <p>Now, a little-noticed Securities and Exchange Commission rule that will go into effect next month should make it easier for Mr. Fukai and others like him to sell their companies' stock without running afoul of insider-trading law. The rule will allow insiders and other investors, like top executives, board members or key advisers, to buy or sell stock in their companies no matter how much inside information they have.</p>
        <p>The catch: the trades must be made under plans created before the investors knew about developments that could push up or drag down the stock.</p>
        <p>While the new provision could theoretically affect many of the estimated 16 million Americans who own shares in the companies they work for, its biggest impact will be on senior managers eager to unlock the wealth of their stock-and-options riches without veering into legal trouble.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fukai, for one, welcomes the change. ''Insiders will be able to spend their time managing their business rather than explaining normal wealth-diversification trades to outside investors,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And the investing public should gain, too, securities law experts say, because illegal insider trading should be easier to prosecute. ''The new rule lets the commission go after the people who really do have evil in their hearts,'' said John F. Olson, a senior partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Gibson, Dunn &amp; Crutcher.</p>
        <p>The plan must either specify the number of shares to be bought or sold on specified dates, or else provide a written formula or computer program for future trading. An insider can also relinquish control over trading decisions to someone who does not have inside information.</p>
        <p>For example, an executive could put in writing his intention to sell 100 shares of company stock the first trading day of every month to pay for his children's college educations. Then, even if he later learned of merger negotiations that could make the stock soar, or of possible accounting irregularities that could pummel it, the sales would be legal.</p>
        <p>The new rule was approved by the S.E.C. in August as an addition to the regulations that fall under the Securities Exchange Act of 1934. It is the first S.E.C. rule that specifically addresses illegal insider trading. Until now, the agency has relied upon a more general rule on securities fraud coupled with case law, said Meyer Eisenberg, the S.E.C.'s deputy general counsel.</p>
        <p>Christian J. Mixter, a former chief litigation counsel for the S.E.C.'s enforcement division, said of the new rule, ''If you comply, you're O.K.''</p>
        <p>The trading plans could allow corporate insiders to bolster their chances of getting more cash for their securities over time by providing for the sale of more shares when prices are higher and fewer when prices are lower, said David Furbush, a lawyer with Brobeck, Phleger &amp; Harrison in Palo Alto, Calif.</p>
        <p>Corporate lawyers, company compliance officers and others are only now beginning to consider the ramifications. At the Intel Corporation, management intends to look at the alternatives under the new rule ''and decide whether they'll be willing to let people take advantage of them,'' said spokeswoman Cary I. Klafter. Securities firms are also studying the potential applications.</p>
        <p>The interest is perhaps strongest in Silicon Valley, where overnight Internet millionaires are especially eager to cash out some of their holdings. ''We've had a lot of interest in selling plans by management and founders of companies,'' said Mr. Furbush of Brobeck, Phleger.</p>
        <p>''I absolutely see it as giving birth to an industry,'' said David Priebe, a partner at Wilson Sonsini Goodrich &amp; Rosati, also in Palo Alto.</p>
        <p>The rule has not received much attention partly because it was overshadowed by a related provision that banned companies from giving important information and specific guidance on future developments to analysts and professional investors before releasing it to the public.</p>
        <p>The S.E.C.'s new stipulations for trading plans could inspire companies to release executives and other employees from the ''window of opportunity'' approach that many adopted to avoid even the appearance of illegal insider trading. (Some executives have previously given up control of their trading through trusts and other legal devices to avoid facing insider charges, but could never be sure that the arrangements would give them 100 percent legal protection.)</p>
        <p>Now, as long as selling plans are set up properly, the window ''becomes irrelevant and people ought to be able to sell on a regular basis throughout the year,'' Mr. Furbush said.</p>
        <p>But it is not just senior managers who stand to benefit from the new rule, which takes effect on Oct. 23. In the more relaxed atmosphere of many high-technology companies these days, it sometimes seems that practically everybody working at them knows what research breakthroughs or corporate deals are in the works.</p>
        <p>Pia Chon, director of product marketing at RadView Software in Burlington, Mass., for example, said that virtually all employees ''are privy to future technology, future acquisitions and revenue'' and other important company information. The company has an insider trading policy for all employees, she noted.</p>
        <p>As more and more lower-level people own stock in their companies, they, too, are subject to insider-trading rules. To escape any suspicion, experts said, they too might want to consider setting up an S.E.C.-approved selling plan.</p>
        <p>Selling plans that meet the new S.E.C. specifications could also have the effect of reassuring shareholders, analysts say. Currently, the publicly announced sale of a large stake by a senior executive is often viewed as a management bailout, whatever the real motive, they say, while a pattern of selling according to a prearranged formula would be more likely to be viewed as a diversification strategy.</p>
        <p>The trading plans being authorized by the S.E.C. hold another potential benefit: ridding the market of any doubt about whether an executive who sells his company's stock knows more than he is letting on about his company's prospects. No matter how honest senior executives are, said Bob Gabele, director of insider research at First Call/Thomson Financial, they certainly have a keener understanding than the public does of their companies' general outlook. And, he believes, illegal trading in which insiders have more specific inside information about an important company development is not all that uncommon.</p>
        <p>''There are a large number of insider actions that cross the line, and I'm not surprised when I see them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There is a loophole in the new rule for those who set up plans and then watch in horror as their company's stock price tanks, but it comes at a  price. They can cancel a trade without breaking the law, said John C. Coffee, a professor and securities law expert at Columbia, but they would then be unable to hide behind their trading plan in the future.</p>
        <p>The new rule has elicited little controversy, though some securities  lawyers have complained that it is vague and exceeds the S.E.C.'s authority. Others believe the rule will help the S.E.C. fortify its enforcement powers while giving insiders some guidance on how to comply with the law.</p>
        <p>Some have long argued that untrammeled insider trading would more quickly lead to stock prices that accurately reflect companies' intrinsic value.</p>
        <p>Others, including the S.E.C., have long contended that lax insider restrictions would create an unfair playing field that would damage the integrity of the public markets.</p>
        <p>But over the last few years, the S.E.C. has been losing legal ground in court battles against illegal insider trading. The new rule is a response of sorts.</p>
        <p>''They are essentially adopting this rule to reverse a couple of court of appeals decisions,'' Professor Coffee said. ''I think it's going to place us back to where we were three or four years ago, while providing insiders the ability to sell more.''</p>
        <p>MANAGEMENT  Correction:  September 30, 2000, Saturday  Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day on Wednesday about a new Securities and Exchange Commission rule that will let corporate insiders make preset trades of company stock referred incorrectly to an executive of the Intel Corporation who said the company intended to look at alternatives under the rule. The official, Cary I. Klafter, is a man; his title is director of corporate affairs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 30, 2000, Saturday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day on Wednesday about a new Securities and Exchange Commission rule that will let corporate insiders make preset trades of company stock referred incorrectly to an executive of the Intel Corporation who said the company intended to look at alternatives under the rule. The official, Cary I. Klafter, is a man; his title is director of corporate affairs.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
