<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How the Studios Used Children To Test-Market Violent Films</title>
    <meta content="27VIOL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/national/27VIOL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Motion Picture Assn of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Organizations/Motion Picture Association of America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DE103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How the Studios Used Children To Test-Market Violent Films</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marketing documents submitted by movie studios in Federal Trade Commission probe of marketing of violent entertainment to children and teenagers show some companies routinely recruit scores of children as young as 9 to evaluate story concepts, commercials, theatrical trailers and rough cuts for R-rated movies; Motion Picture Assn of American responds with plan to curb marketing of R-rated films to under-age children that includes pledge not to use children under 17 in test screenings unless they are accompanied by adult; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before the Hollywood Pictures unit of Disney released the R-rated Sylvester Stallone movie  ''Judge Dredd,'' about urban anarchy and street war, the studio tested the film before a focus group that included more than 100 youths ages 13 to 16.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before the Hollywood Pictures unit of Disney released the R-rated Sylvester Stallone movie  ''Judge Dredd,'' about urban anarchy and street war, the studio tested the film before a focus group that included more than 100 youths ages 13 to 16.</p>
        <p>MGM/United Artists tested commercials for ''Disturbing Behavior,'' an R-rated horror thriller about troublemaking teenagers transformed into upstanding citizens, before more than 400  12- to 20-year-olds. A survey reported that they felt the ''standout scene'' was one of a blonde bashing her head into a mirror.</p>
        <p>Columbia Tristar's researchers interviewed 50 children ages 9 to 11 to evaluate concepts for the sequel to ''I Know What You Did Last Summer,'' a tale of a serial slasher equipped with an outsized ice hook.</p>
        <p>''There is evidence to indicate that attendance in the original movie dipped down to the age of 10,'' explained a memorandum from the National Research Group, the dominant market research organization for major studios. ''Therefore, it seems to make sense to interview 10- to 11-year-olds.''</p>
        <p>These incidents and others are recorded in confidential marketing documents submitted by nine movie studios to the government commission that investigated the marketing of violent entertainment to children and teenagers, who are frequent moviegoers. Those documents show that some of the biggest companies in Hollywood routinely recruited scores of teenagers and children as young as 9 to evaluate story concepts, commercials, theatrical trailers and rough cuts for R-rated movies.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the movie industry's trade association, the Motion Picture Association of America, announced steps to restrict  its marketing of R-rated films to under-age children. Among them is a pledge not to use children under 17 in test screenings unless they are accompanied by an adult. An R-rated movie requires that anyone under 17 be accompanied by an adult because of explicit violent or sexual content. The rating, like all movie ratings, is the industry's own standard,  subject only to its own policing.</p>
        <p>Jack Valenti, the trade association's chairman, said a report by the Federal Trade Commission has prompted studios to take ''a fresh new look at the way we market films.''</p>
        <p>The industry's program is the latest reaction to the commission's sharply critical report of marketing practices in the movie, music and video-game industries. Citing regulations prohibiting it from releasing trade secrets, the  report did not reveal the names of the entertainment companies involved or the details of the marketing campaigns. Those are contained in the supporting documents, which were obtained by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>Eight movie studio executives are scheduled to testify today before the Senate Commerce Committee about their policies. At the first committee hearing, two weeks ago, Mr. Valenti conceded that perhaps marketing people ''stepped over the line'' but argued that the location of that line was ''ill lit, hazily observed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Valenti maintained that ''we are not dealing with Euclid's geometry where the equations are pristine and explicit.''</p>
        <p>When asked about the confidential marketing reports yesterday, Mr. Valenti said, ''I didn't know it was happening.'' He added that the ''practice of going to 10- and 12-year-olds is really not acceptable.''</p>
        <p>In their own marketing plans submitted to the trade commission, the major movie studios offered a window into practices that can begin almost as soon as a movie is conceived. Preliminary test screenings are conducted months before films appear in theaters.</p>
        <p>Recruiters hunt for moviegoers in movie lines or malls offering free tickets to people who match the age and ethnic profile set by the studios. And the results ultimately can shape promotions, advertising and decisions for a movie sequel.</p>
        <p>In some of the memorandums describing marketing strategy, movie studios and video-game makers acknowledged that while they have publicly identified 18- to 34-year-olds as their primary audience for restricted movies and games, they needed the support of young teenagers. Toy tie-ins to PG-13 movies, which caution that violent material may be ''inappropriate'' for children under 13, broaden the promotion of those films to children as young as 4.</p>
        <p>The main company that gathers marketing information for major movie studios is National Research Group of Los Angeles. Joseph Farrell, the company's co-chairman, said that information is gathered in a variety of ways that includes telephone surveys and test screenings of movies, commercials and trailers.</p>
        <p>''All of the specifications that we carry out, including the methodology involving focus groups, are prescribed by the studios,'' said Mr. Farrell, who said no one under 14 is ''approached or interviewed or involved in discussions without a parent's permission.''</p>
        <p>For test screenings, younger people are accompanied by parents, Mr. Farrell said, although those 15 and older are not required to. He described the process of gathering information from focus groups of younger children as unusual.</p>
        <p>In its report, the Federal Trade Commission examined 44 R-rated films and 20 violent PG-13 films distributed by the nine major studios over a four-year period ending in 1999. Thirty-three of the 44 R-rated films or advertisements for them were screened for under-age teenagers and children as young as 9.</p>
        <p>''I don't know anything about that,'' Mr. Farrell said.</p>
        <p>In the aftermath of the commission report, Disney announced earlier this month that it would not show R-rated films from any of its units to focus groups with participants under 17 and would urge theaters to more strictly enforce age limits.</p>
        <p>In the past, that was not the case. Marketing plans from the company's units, Touchstone and Hollywood Pictures, show that the studio has turned to younger children for market research on R-rated films.</p>
        <p>In the case of ''Judge Dredd,'' Hollywood Pictures tested the film with a broad group that included a subset of 13- to 16-year-olds. The participants were asked to rate everything from the movie's music and action to its ending and its hero, played by Mr. Stallone. Participants also rated every movie scene, including a robot ripping off a man's arms and a plane crashing into a prison.</p>
        <p>Later, the company's researchers tested the movie's five commercials before 1,800 people, who included participants as young as 12. And those surveys, along with the earlier movie ratings, detected a clear pattern of enthusiasm among one age group: young teenagers, particularly males.</p>
        <p>In 1998, Disney's Touchstone Pictures also turned to younger viewers to test the appeal of trailers for an R-rated thriller, ''Enemy of the State,'' which starred Will Smith. One focus group of 300 people included participants 12 to 14, according to a research report. The company gathered a second group, of 300 African-Americans, which also included participants as young as 12. The aim of the survey was to test the power of the movie's trailers. That information would then provide critical insight about which people were most likely to go to the movie.</p>
        <p>John Dreyer, a spokesman for the Disney Company, said he could not explain why Disney had used younger people for marketing research.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't really privy to the decision-making,'' he said, adding, ''I think there were probably exceptions or aberrations, that clearly there were mistakes made, and there's a commitment not to do it again.''</p>
        <p>Marketing plans for other films show the meticulous efforts of major studios to gauge the tastes of younger, often under-age moviegoers.</p>
        <p>When Columbia Tristar tested concepts for the 1998 teenage slasher sequel, ''I Still Know What You Did Last Summer,'' it commissioned research from a sampling of people  who had seen the original.</p>
        <p>The sampling was made up of 500 people 12 to 24. Of those, 100 were 9 to 11. In addition, researchers interviewed a group of 150 Latinos and African-Americans ages 12 to 24, and 50 more ages 9 to 11.</p>
        <p>The goal, as outlined in a memorandum from National Research Group, was plain: ''to determine who are the most intense fans of the movie by age, gender, ethnicity, et cetera, and what drives their zeal. The results will help define the primary and secondary targets and what about the movie most appeals to them. It will also provide information on the key aspects of the original movie most liked and guidance for direction of the second movie.''</p>
        <p>Columbia was even more aggressive about focusing on a younger audience for the futuristic science-fiction thriller ''The Fifth Element,'' a PG-13 film that starred Bruce Willis as a 23rd century ex-soldier and cabdriver turned galactic hero.</p>
        <p>The studio sought to advertise the movie on the children's network Nickelodeon. MTV Networks, which oversees Nickelodeon, refused to allow an advertisement because it considered the movie inappropriate for its viewers, who are mostly under 12.</p>
        <p>''There are several gun battles, a couple of fight sequences and some devastating bomb blasts,'' an MTV executive wrote to representatives of Columbia. ''Finally the sexual situations are well removed from Nickelodeon's sphere -- the talk show host performing cunnilingus on a female singer.''</p>
        <p>The studio unsuccessfully appealed the ban, arguing in part that the science-fiction genre required a suspension of belief and that the violence would be suspect to ''the children of today who are more sophisticated.''</p>
        <p>The quest for the under-17 market reflects certain realities of moviegoing habits. Studies from the Motion Picture Association of America indicate, for example, that the group ages 12 to 17 accounts for 17 percent of movie audiences, a figure disproportionate to their actual share of the population, which is 10 percent.</p>
        <p>When MGM/United Artists was preparing to release its R-rated film ''Disturbing Behavior,'' researchers started tracking the interest and awareness among a sampling of 331  10- to 20-year-olds and a broader group of 400 12- to 59-year-olds.</p>
        <p>Later, the studio screened two 30-second commercials among 438 moviegoers 12 to 20. In a scene-by-scene rating of the commercials, viewers evaluated such fleeting moments as a ''needle toward clamped eye'' and a girl bashing her head into a mirror.</p>
        <p>''The stand-out scenes continue to be the blonde hitting her head in the mirror,'' the researchers reported. ''Also enjoyed are scenes of Holmes in confrontation with a strange man being menaced. All of these factors lead to stronger performance of the commercials among 15- to 17-year-olds. Those 18 to 24 remain hesitant about the horror focus of the story.''</p>
        <p>A year ago, Universal Studios outlined its preparations to promote the PG-13 movie ''The Mummy,'' which includes elements of suggested violence, like a knifing murder in the shadows and the mummy's theft of the eyeballs and tongue of a hapless victim.</p>
        <p>The movie's target audience consisted of two groups: heavy moviegoers 12 to 34 and male fans of action films 10 to 24. To reach the ''tweens,'' as the memorandum labeled the younger set, the company created a plan to advertise on television shows that attract extremely young viewers, like ''Pokemon,'' ''Power Rangers'' and ''Spiderman.''</p>
        <p>The target market for Universal's ''Mummy'' merchandising program was even younger: boys 4 to 14. The company developed plans to distribute 6-inch action figures and 12-inch collector mummies at Toys ''R'' Us, Kmart and Target.</p>
        <p>To cap the marketing blitz, Universal Studios in Florida built a haunted house maze for Halloween last year that included a mummy character. The marketing report noted the potential impact: ''250,000 kids expected.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most blunt and candid appraisal of the youthful audience for violent entertainment comes in two marketing memorandums for restricted video games called Turok and Duke Nukem Zero Hour, which features a foul-mouthed alien-annihilator who, according to promotional material, is notable for ''spitting more one-liners than Rodney Dangerfield while building the body count.'' Both carry an M rating, which bars their sale to children under 17. Like movie ratings, video ratings are the industry's own, not regulated by law.</p>
        <p>Advertising recommendations for the Duke from GT Interactive Software's 1998 marketing plan observe that because of the restricted M rating for the video the target audience is identified as males 17 to 34. ''The true target is males 9 to 34,'' the report adds.</p>
        <p>A year after the memorandum was prepared, GT Interactive was acquired by Infogrames Inc., a French company with offices in San Jose, Calif.</p>
        <p>''That's not the way we approach the marketing of mature games,'' said Tom Richardson, a spokesman for Infogrames. ''That doesn't reflect our philosophy. We make every effort to market mature themes to mature audiences 17 and over.''</p>
        <p>In another marketing plan, Acclaim Entertainment, the makers of the M-rated Turok series, explains why the primary audience for the video remains males 12 to 17, even though these consumers cannot buy the material by themselves. The Turok series has sold more than 3 million units on the strength of weapons features like the ''all-powerful Chest-Burster.''</p>
        <p>''Turok has an M rating, which may discourage parents from buying the game and hinder clearance of a commercial airing in shows primarily for children under 12,'' observed the marketing report. ''However, the younger the audience, the more likely they are to be influenced by TV advertising. Adults are more likely to evaluate software purchases based on more extensive research.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
