<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="27DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6DD103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Microsoft Antitrust Case Is Sent to Appeals Court  The Supreme Court handed a tactical victory to Microsoft when it summarily rejected the government's plea to immediately hear the appeal of its landmark antitrust case and instead returned the proceeding to the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia.</p>
        <p>The decision gives Microsoft greater breathing room to pursue its appeals, relieves the company of any pressure to return to the bargaining table in the near future and, in the absence of a settlement, could prolong a final court judgment by a year or longer. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Microsoft Antitrust Case Is Sent to Appeals Court  The Supreme Court handed a tactical victory to Microsoft when it summarily rejected the government's plea to immediately hear the appeal of its landmark antitrust case and instead returned the proceeding to the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia.</p>
        <p>The decision gives Microsoft greater breathing room to pursue its appeals, relieves the company of any pressure to return to the bargaining table in the near future and, in the absence of a settlement, could prolong a final court judgment by a year or longer. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Steps Taken on Bioengineered Corn  Moving to address safety concerns, agribusiness companies took steps to limit the chances that bioengineered corn unapproved for human consumption could end up in food. [C2.]</p>
        <p>3Com Loss Is Less Than Forecast  3Com reported a smaller-than-expected first-quarter loss, citing a revamping that included its exit from the analog modem and network router businesses in the previous quarter. Before 3Com reported its results, its shares closed at $13.94, down 6 cents. In after-hours trading, however, 3Com rose more than 15 percent, climbing as high as $16.06. [C11.]</p>
        <p>Document on Ford Rollover Tests  Ford told its tire suppliers a decade ago not to conduct without Ford's approval a driving test of the rollover tendencies of sport utility vehicles and other light trucks, an internal Ford document shows. But there is disagreement between Ford and its critics over how the document should be interpreted. [C20.]</p>
        <p>OPEC Prepares for Summit Meeting  With oil prices at their highest level in a decade and the United States and other industrial countries calling for relief, heads of state and oil ministers from the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries are to begin a two-day summit meeting here today. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Slump on Kodak Warning  Stocks fell sharply after an earnings warning from Eastman Kodak worried investors. The Dow Jones industrial average dropped 176.83 points, or 1.6 percent, to 10,631.32. The Nasdaq composite index was down 52.12 points, or 1.4 percent, to 3,689.10, and the Standard and Poor's 500-stock index fell 11.82 points, or 0.8 percent, to 1,427.21. [C20.]</p>
        <p>For the Love of the Games  Mark Jacobstein has been enthralled with games for much of his life. He created his first fantasy baseball game on a mainframe computer when he was in middle school and was a standout high school athlete in upstate New York. Now, he is the chief executive of Small World, a Manhattan company that develops online games. The Boss. [C10.]</p>
        <p>Christie's Approves Settlement  Christie's approved a $256 million settlement of civil claims that, along with its archrival, Sotheby's, it cheated buyers and sellers as far back as 1992. Sotheby's had already approved its half of the $512 million settlement. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Corning Seen in Deal for Pirelli Unit  Corning, the leading supplier of glass fiber, is expected to announce that it has agreed to acquire the fiber optic telecommunications business of Pirelli, the Italian tire and cable maker, for about $3 billion. [C31.]</p>
        <p>Fast Train May Not Rival Air Travel  Amtrak is about to roll out its long-delayed $1.7 billion Acela Express high-speed rail service between New York City and Boston. But it may not be as competitive with airlines as was first thought. Joe Sharkey: Business Travel. [C12.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
