<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Photography Centers Join To Form a Vast Collection</title>
    <meta content="27PHOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/arts/27PHOT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eastman, George, House (Rochester, NY)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Center of Photography (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohlen, Celestine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4DE133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Photography Centers Join To Form a Vast Collection</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bohlen, Celestine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two major photography institutions--George Eastman House in Rochester and International Center of Photography in New York City--enter an alliance that will give New Yorkers more access to one of world's greatest collections of photographs and motion pictures; alliance, which is not a merger, will result in series of operations--from joint cataloguing to a Web site--to benefit both institutions and public (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two major photography institutions -- the George Eastman House in Rochester and the International Center of Photography in New York City -- have entered an alliance that will give New Yorkers more access to one of the world's greatest collections of photographs and motion pictures.</p>
        <p>''One organization has the advantage of location,'' said Willis Hartshorn, director of the International Center of Photography,  which has galleries on 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at West 43rd  Street (reopening on Nov. 3 after renovations), and 1130 Fifth Avenue, at 94th Street (which is closing after June), and runs New York's largest photography school. ''The other has the advantage of an extraordinary collection. In terms of the public, the benefit is mostly access.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two major photography institutions -- the George Eastman House in Rochester and the International Center of Photography in New York City -- have entered an alliance that will give New Yorkers more access to one of the world's greatest collections of photographs and motion pictures.</p>
        <p>''One organization has the advantage of location,'' said Willis Hartshorn, director of the International Center of Photography,  which has galleries on 1133 Avenue of the Americas, at West 43rd  Street (reopening on Nov. 3 after renovations), and 1130 Fifth Avenue, at 94th Street (which is closing after June), and runs New York's largest photography school. ''The other has the advantage of an extraordinary collection. In terms of the public, the benefit is mostly access.''</p>
        <p>Ronald H. Fielding, board chairman at the George Eastman House, said that the alliance, which is not a merger, would result in a series of operations -- from joint cataloging to a Web site -- to benefit both institutions and the public.</p>
        <p>''The educational programs are very complementary,'' he said.  ''The I.C.P. is very strong in degree programs for photographic creation, whereas the strong point at Eastman House is preservation and conservation.''</p>
        <p>With more than five million objects related to photography and film in its 50-year-old collection, the Eastman museum owns 400,000 photographs by 8,000 photographers going back to the art form's earliest years. Its collection of 25,000 motion pictures is a rival to that of the Cinematheque in Paris and its library of photographic books and journals is one of the world's most encyclopedic.</p>
        <p>The International Center of Photography's collection concentrates on the 1950's through the 70's, with special emphasis on photojournalism. There will be a regular exchange of exhibitions. The first program in an eight-part series called ''New Histories of  Photography'' is to open on Nov. 3 at the center's expanded gallery space on the Avenue of the Americas. The show, called ''Daguerreotypmania!,'' will feature rare artifacts connected with the early years of photography.</p>
        <p>A show of photographs by Alfred Stieglitz donated to the Eastman House by Georgia O'Keeffe and now on tour in Cologne, Germany, will also come to the International Center of Photography.</p>
        <p>''Obviously a purpose of a nonprofit museum is to make its collection available to the public,'' Mr. Fielding said. ''The Web does that, but in terms of physical access, New York has a zillion more people visiting museums as well as more funding resources.''</p>
        <p>Although it is one of the top tourist attractions in Rochester,  the Eastman museum, named after the founder of the Eastman Kodak Company, who produced the first mass market amateur camera, has been stretched thin financially as it struggled to maintain its vast collection. After a proposal to transfer the collection to the Smithsonian Institution in Washington was quashed by  local protests, an endowment drive began that collected $35 million, helping to build a modern archive building next to the original George Eastman mansion.</p>
        <p>By teaming up with the Center for Photography, the Eastman museum seeks to strengthen its fund-raising, exchange information and staff, and expand the opportunity for scholarly research. Filing jointly for their first shared grant, the two institutions have already received $120,000 from the National Endowment for the Arts.</p>
        <p>For the center's 5,000 students, most of them enrolled in continuing education classes, the arrangement will provide a wealth of material for research. The Web site, to be running next spring, will include 10,000 images from the museums' collections as well as material on the history of photography.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
