<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inscriptions Add a Personal Note to City College Plaza</title>
    <meta content="27COLL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/nyregion/27COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lewisohn Stadium (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">City College (Ccny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brozan, Nadine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1DD103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inscriptions Add a Personal Note to City College Plaza</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NADINE BROZAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brozan, Nadine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>CCNY dedicates Lewisohn Plaza of Honor, concouse of bricks and concrete bearing inscriptions by graduates, faculty members and other donors; site is new much-loved Lewisohn Stadium, which was demolished in 1973 (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a city where the names of generous benefactors are affixed to everything from hospitals to bookshelves, a college is putting its own spin on a fund-raising theme: let donors put their tributes to professors, relatives, friends and to the school itself underfoot.</p>
        <p>A soft rain fell yesterday as City College dedicated the Lewisohn Plaza of Honor, a concourse of bricks and granite slabs bearing inscriptions written by graduates, faculty members and supporters. More than 350 people attended the ceremony at the college's Shepard Hall, near where Lewisohn Stadium, once the epicenter of the city's summer cultural scene and the college's athletic field, had stood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a city where the names of generous benefactors are affixed to everything from hospitals to bookshelves, a college is putting its own spin on a fund-raising theme: let donors put their tributes to professors, relatives, friends and to the school itself underfoot.</p>
        <p>A soft rain fell yesterday as City College dedicated the Lewisohn Plaza of Honor, a concourse of bricks and granite slabs bearing inscriptions written by graduates, faculty members and supporters. More than 350 people attended the ceremony at the college's Shepard Hall, near where Lewisohn Stadium, once the epicenter of the city's summer cultural scene and the college's athletic field, had stood.</p>
        <p>Though it was demolished in 1973, the stadium was never forgotten by people of a certain age who paid 25 or 50 cents to sit under the stars on summer nights and listen to great orchestras and performers. There, Ella Fitzgerald sang with the Metropolitan Opera; Marian Anderson and Eugene Ormandy gave their first concerts; George Gershwin played his ''Rhapsody in Blue'' for the first time. Performers ranged from Jascha Heifetz and Yehudi Menuhin to Leontyne Price, Pete Seeger and Jack Benny.</p>
        <p>The Doric-colonnaded amphitheater, between Amsterdam and Convent Avenues from 136th to 138th Street, was built in 1915 with a gift from Adolph Lewisohn, an investment broker and art collector. It was razed to make way for the $125 million North Academic Center.</p>
        <p>More than 2,000 people gave money for the 800 bricks and stones set in concentric circles around the college seal. Proceeds, $300,000 so far, will go to scholarships and academic programs. Bricks and granite are still available for $150 to $800.</p>
        <p>The commemorative plaza, designed by Joseph Fuller, an architect, was proposed five years ago by Patricia Black, a former superintendent of high schools in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''The idea came to me after I bought a memorial line on Ellis Island for my husband's parents,'' said Ms. Black, class of '65, who also earned a master's degree at the college. ''I thought it would be wonderful for those of us who remember Lewisohn Stadium, the source of cheap dates.''</p>
        <p>Leonard Kleinrock, an Internet technology pioneer who transmitted the first precursor of e-mail, a message between two computers in different locales (it read ''login''), put something more permanent into his slab on the plaza: ''CCNY gave me a world class free education and a bridge to success when I had no other options,'' he wrote. ''Thank you! Leonard Kleinrock, '57, inventor of internet technology.''</p>
        <p>Professor Kleinrock is chief executive of Nomadix, a start-up computer technology company, and a member of the faculty at the University of California at Los Angeles. ''A few years before I entered college, my father got very ill and couldn't afford the $12-a-semester tuition,'' he said. ''I couldn't stop working to help support my family so I went to school in the evenings. The fact that there was an evening session for someone like me was so important.''</p>
        <p>Martin Balter, who received degrees in chemical engineering in 1934 and 1935, decided to disclose a little-known fact about himself on his slab. ''After college I joined the Lincoln Brigade in the Spanish Civil War, and when I returned home I was hounded by the F.B.I. and rejected for jobs in many industries,'' he said. ''So I changed my last name to my wife's.''</p>
        <p>His inscription is signed, ''Martin Balter, previously Morris Kornblum.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
