<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Move Toward Schools Open Year-Round</title>
    <meta content="27SCHO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/nyregion/27SCHO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Board of Education (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomson, Terri</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4DF103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Move Toward Schools Open Year-Round</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Board of Education task force will recommend that newly-built high schools operate on year-round schedule, with student vacations scattered throughout the year; aim is to ease overcrowding, especially in Queens, where high schools are operating at 128 percent of capacity; graph; proposal will need state approval; student and teacher participation would be voluntary since only those at new schools would be affected; board member Terri Thomson explains (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aiming to ease overcrowding, a City Board of Education task force has decided to recommend that newly constructed high schools that are opened over the next few years operate on a year-round schedule, with student vacations scattered throughout the year instead of being confined to the summer months.</p>
        <p>The proposal, which would be the first broad attempt to operate year-round schools in New York City, appears likely to win support from a majority of the board's seven members when it is presented at a meeting next Wednesday, education officials said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Aiming to ease overcrowding, a City Board of Education task force has decided to recommend that newly constructed high schools that are opened over the next few years operate on a year-round schedule, with student vacations scattered throughout the year instead of being confined to the summer months.</p>
        <p>The proposal, which would be the first broad attempt to operate year-round schools in New York City, appears likely to win support from a majority of the board's seven members when it is presented at a meeting next Wednesday, education officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Unlike previous plans for year-round schooling, which sought to eliminate the long summer break that seemingly sweeps clean the minds of some students, the new proposal's primary aim is to relieve overcrowding, particularly in Queens, where high schools now operate at 128 percent of their planned capacity. A staggered schedule of vacations would allow a school to squeeze more students into its classrooms.</p>
        <p>In addition to the board's approval, the proposal will need legislative help from Albany, because state law now prohibits compulsory education in July and August. But Gov. George E. Pataki supported a plan to put a year-round school schedule into effect two years ago, and Democratic legislators say a similar proposal received broad support when it was first discussed in Albany last spring.</p>
        <p>Several years ago, Los Angeles began operating some of its high schools on a year-round basis with students on staggered vacation schedules. But while many other large-city districts have talked of the idea, few have gained the support of teachers' unions and parents needed to implement a year-round schooling plan.</p>
        <p>Student participation in the year-round program would be voluntary, because only those who apply and are accepted to the new high schools would be on the new schedule. Teachers, too, would have the option of applying to teach at the new high schools, an idea favored by the teachers' union.</p>
        <p>The proposal, as drafted, would apply to the 13 new high schools that, according to the Board of Education's current capital plan, are scheduled to be opened over three years beginning in the fall of 2003.</p>
        <p>Several of those schools, which would add approximately 10,000 new seats to the city's high school districts, are designated to be themed schools that focus on professions like teaching, communications and law enforcement. Ten of them are to be in Queens, two in the Bronx and one in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>The proposal for year-round operation would not extend the school year beyond its current 182 days; rather, it would lengthen the school day and reduce the number of total days a student is in school, keeping total instructional time the same but allowing for the staggering of multiple student vacation schedules.</p>
        <p>By using schools that might otherwise sit empty during the summer months, year-round schooling would create 6,000 more seats without requiring any more money to build new schools, said Terri Thomson, the board member representing Queens who headed the task force.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Ms. Thomson said she believes the current proposal will succeed where previous plans for year-round schooling have failed, in part because the task force included representatives from parent groups across the city.</p>
        <p>''If you look at the situation today, the overcrowding is unacceptable,'' Ms. Thomson said. The plan will allow more flexibility for students to schedule remedial help or to take extra courses, she said.</p>
        <p>In addition, she said, the task force will recommend working with local businesses to create year-round rather than summer jobs.</p>
        <p>The most strenuous objections to previous Board of Education plans for year-round schooling -- which date to at least the early 1980's -- came from parents, particularly in Queens, who balked at the idea of having some children in school while others were on vacation and who said their children deserved new schools rather than having to give up their summers.</p>
        <p>Jacquelyn Kamin, who represented the Chancellor's Parent Advisory Council on the task force, said the current recommendations addressed many of those concerns. The plan would be limited to high school students, whose schedules are generally more flexible than those of elementary and junior high school students and who can stay home on their own if their parents work; to schools that students choose to attend; and to schools where the new schedules are known before the doors ever open.</p>
        <p>A majority of the board appears prepared to vote in favor of the task force's proposal. William C. Thompson Jr., president of the board and a member of the task force, and Sandra E. Lerner, the board's Bronx representative, said in interviews yesterday that they support the recommendations. And Ninfa Segarra, a mayoral appointee to the board, said she supports the concept, although she has some questions about the specifics of the proposal.</p>
        <p>Some legislative leaders also appear to be leaning in favor of such a proposal.</p>
        <p>Steven Sanders, a Democrat from Manhattan who heads the State Assembly's Education Committee, said he believes the proposal will eventually win support, although it might take several weeks of discussion to address legislators' concerns.</p>
        <p>''Given the fact that for a century we have operated with this type of September-to-June schedule, I think it will take a little discussion to get used to the idea that it's time to do things differently and to deal with some of the concerns about overcrowding,'' Mr. Sanders said.</p>
        <p>Board of Education officials say there is little doubt that the city needs more high schools. High schools in each of the city's five boroughs operate at or above capacity, the most crowded being those in Queens, at 128 percent of capacity, and the Bronx, at 119 percent.</p>
        <p>According to projections by the board's division of school facilities, by 2004 the Bronx will be at 131 percent of capacity and Queens at 122 percent, even with the scheduled school additions.</p>
        <p>The task force limited its recommendations to new schools in part because they will be equipped with air-conditioning, something that new schools will have but that many schools now lack.</p>
        <p>In Queens, some high school students take fewer periods of instruction each day than are mandated by the State Education Department because the schools are too crowded to accommodate them. Claire Shulman, borough president of Queens, said she believes parents in her borough will therefore support the proposal for year-round schooling, if they understand that it is a voluntary pilot program, limited to a few schools.</p>
        <p>''I think people would opt to do that,'' she said, if students ''could have a full day of instruction rather than be forced to sit on the radiator in a cramped classroom.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
