<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Aides Question Inquiry Into Stolen Debate Material</title>
    <meta content="METMOLE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/politics/27MOLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Bureau of Investigation</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Maverick Media</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lozano, Yvette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6DB103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Aides Question Inquiry Into Stolen Debate Material</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush's campaign, responding to report that Federal Bureau of Investigation focuses probe into stolen debate materials on Yvette Lozano, employee of Maverick Media, which produces Bush's campaign commercials, questions fairness of probe; defends Lozano; suspects Clinton administration tampers with probe to boost Vice Pres Al Gore (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The campaign of Gov. George W. Bush asserted today that leaked information about a Federal investigation into stolen debate materials had raised questions about whether the inquiry was proceeding in an fair manner.</p>
        <p>The campaign issued its complaint today in response to a story on the Web site of The Dallas Morning News saying that the Federal Bureau of Investigation was focusing its inquiry on an employee of Maverick Media, an Austin, Tex.-based firm that is producing Mr. Bush's campaign commercials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The campaign of Gov. George W. Bush asserted today that leaked information about a Federal investigation into stolen debate materials had raised questions about whether the inquiry was proceeding in an fair manner.</p>
        <p>The campaign issued its complaint today in response to a story on the Web site of The Dallas Morning News saying that the Federal Bureau of Investigation was focusing its inquiry on an employee of Maverick Media, an Austin, Tex.-based firm that is producing Mr. Bush's campaign commercials.</p>
        <p>Tonight, Karen P. Hughes, Mr. Bush's communications director, said the campaign was convinced the employee, Yvette Lozano, was innocent, and she asserted that the release of confidential information about the investigation had raised questions about political tampering by the Clinton administration to help Vice President Al Gore's campaign.</p>
        <p>''This raises questions about whether the investigators are being allowed to conduct an objective investigation,'' Mrs. Hughes said. She added that the campaign manager, Joe Allbaugh, had raised similar concerns in a telephone conversation this afternoon with the F.B.I. director, Louis Freeh.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, an spokesman for the bureau refused to say whether or not agents had interviewed Ms. Lozano. ''All I can say is we have initiated a preliminary investigation,'' said the spokesman, Paul Bresson. ''At this point, we can't even determine if any federal laws have been violated.''</p>
        <p>Kym Spell, a spokeswoman for the Gore campaign said tonight, ''We have a great deal of faith in the F.B.I. investigators who are on the scene.''</p>
        <p>She added, ''For Karen Hughes to suggest otherwise is not just an attack on the Gore campaign. It's an attack on the F.B.I. And it raises question about why the Bush campaign doesn't want the F.B.I. to get to the bottom of this.''</p>
        <p>The bureau opened its investigation after former Representative Thomas Downey, who has assisted Mr. Gore in debate preparations, turned over a package he received on Sept. 13 containing a video of a mock debate between Mr. Bush and Senator Judd Gregg, Republican of New Hampshire, as well as some briefing books. The package carried an Austin postmark.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Gore campaign suspended a 28-year-old campaign worker who had bragged to a friend that the Democrats might have a ''mole'' inside the Bush campaign. Mr. Gore's aides said the suspended worker, Michael Doyne, had made the story up.</p>
        <p>Today, Mrs. Hughes complained that the F.B.I. did not seem to be taking Mr. Doyne's case seriously enough. ''I hope the F.B.I. and the federal law enforcement agencies would follow up on that boast by looking at computer hard drives to determine whether in fact there is any substance to those comments,'' she told reporters.</p>
        <p>She also rejected out of hand assertions by Molly Beth Malcolm, chairwoman of the Texas Democratic Party, that the pilfered debate materials had actually been sent to Mr. Downey by Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's chief political consultant. Democrats contend that Mr. Rove bugged his own campaign office during the 1986 gubernatorial campaign in order to cast aspersions on the Democrats.</p>
        <p>The Dallas Morning News reported that Ms. Lozano could be seen on a Postal Service surveillance videotape mailing a package on Sept. 11. Ms. Lozano told the paper today that she was returning a pair of $19 Gap khaki pants for her boss. To back her story up, Mr. McKinnon produced the pants Gap had sent him in exchange for the returned pair.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
