<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Call Off All Bets</title>
    <meta content="27CALH$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/opinion/27CALH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nevada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Calhoun, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nevada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3DC133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Call Off All Bets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jim Calhoun</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Calhoun, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>STORRS, Conn.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>University of Connecticut basketball coach Jim Calhoun Op-Ed article urges Congress to approve bill ending Nevada's exemption from federal ban on gambling on amateur sporting events; holds increased legal wagering leads to increased illegal pressure on college athletes from gambling interests; scores opposition from Republican leaders that has blocked floor votes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Casinos are dotted across America, but there is only one state where customers can bet legally on college sports events. When gambling on amateur sporting events was banned by a 1992 federal law, an exemption was given to Nevada.</p>
        <p>A bill now pending in Congress would close the Nevada loophole, stopping all legal betting on college athletics. I stand with my fellow coaches of National Collegiate Athletic Association Division I teams in endorsing this legislation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Casinos are dotted across America, but there is only one state where customers can bet legally on college sports events. When gambling on amateur sporting events was banned by a 1992 federal law, an exemption was given to Nevada.</p>
        <p>A bill now pending in Congress would close the Nevada loophole, stopping all legal betting on college athletics. I stand with my fellow coaches of National Collegiate Athletic Association Division I teams in endorsing this legislation.</p>
        <p>As coaches from across the country know, student athletes can encounter a multitude of gambling pressures during a playing season: people may approach them for inside information or try to pay them to miss a few shots or to in some way influence the outcome of a game. Each season I coach my players on how to handle such situations, but they shouldn't have to be put in that position. As the amount of money legally wagered on these kids escalates, so do the pressures on them -- and on the integrity of college sports.</p>
        <p>Nevada officials know this; the state prohibits casino betting on its own teams even as it provides a home for betting on others.</p>
        <p>Yet the leadership of the Republican-controlled Congresss has stymied efforts to close the Nevada loophole. The Senate bill has 21 cosponsors and was was adopted unanimously by the Commerce Committee in April. Leaders from both parties agree that it would be adopted overwhelmingly if it were to be considered on the Senate floor. But numerous attempts by the sponsors, Republican Senators John McCain of Arizona and Sam Brownback of Kansas, to bring it to a vote have failed.</p>
        <p>In the House, where the bill has 80 co-sponsors and has been approved by the Judiciary Committee, Republican Lindsey Graham of South Carolina and Democrat Tim Roemer of Indiana, the main sponsors, say they are optimistic that a floor vote can be scheduled over the objections of the leadership.</p>
        <p>Why don't the leaders of Congress want this bill on the calendar? Some, like Tom DeLay of Texas, the House majority whip, say it's a states' rights issue. Well, it's true that Nevada doesn't want this legislation. But what about the rights of other states not to have their sports programs tainted by Nevada's exemption? When the N.C.A.A. sent a letter to the Nevada Gaming Control Board asking that the state allow the same protections from gambling for colleges and universities in other states that it provides to those at home, it was rebuffed. N.C.A.A. schools asked to be allowed to petition the board to have a particular university removed from the sports betting boards. The response was no. This issue is clearly about an exception to federal law that hasn't worked, not states' rights.</p>
        <p>Some opponents of closing the loophole argue that it won't ease the problem of college sports gambling because curbing legal gambling only fuels illegal betting. But the evidence is to the contrary. Many college coaches have said publicly that recent point-shaving scandals would not have happened if not for the presence of Nevada's betting.</p>
        <p>The gambling industry has made generous contributions to both parties, and these may be having an effect. The legislation to close the loophole is being held up even though the National Gambling Impact Study Commission, a bipartisan group selected by Congress and the White House, recommended it. This position has wide support from sports and educational groups. What unites them is a belief that betting endangers the future -- and tarnishes the integrity -- of college sports.</p>
        <p>Jim Calhoun is the University of Connecticut's head basketball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jim Calhoun is the University of Connecticut's head basketball coach.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
