<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S., Losing to Spain, Still Dreams of Medal</title>
    <meta content="27SOCC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFDE133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S., Losing to Spain, Still Dreams of Medal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Spain defeats US, 3-1, in semifinal's of men's soccer tournament at Sydney Olympics; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The unimagined has now become almost a necessity. Having lost to Spain, 3-1, in the semifinals tonight, the United States wants to bring back a medal from the Olympic soccer competition.</p>
        <p>''It would be disappointing if we didn't win one,'' said Josh Wolff, the forward from the Chicago Fire, after the Americans were stunned early by the offensive aggression of the Spaniards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The unimagined has now become almost a necessity. Having lost to Spain, 3-1, in the semifinals tonight, the United States wants to bring back a medal from the Olympic soccer competition.</p>
        <p>''It would be disappointing if we didn't win one,'' said Josh Wolff, the forward from the Chicago Fire, after the Americans were stunned early by the offensive aggression of the Spaniards.</p>
        <p>Needing a medal to feel good about this excursion was hardly a position the Yanks could afford to take when they arrived here early in the month. They raised expectations by winning their group and then beating Japan in the quarterfinal round, already the farthest any American men's team has ever gone in the Summer Games.</p>
        <p>Now they must play Chile, a very tough squad that lost, 2-1, on a questionable penalty call against Cameroon tonight in Melbourne. The Americans and Chile will play here Friday night. On Thursday evening, the American women will defend their Olympic championship against their traditional rival, Norway, also here. Cameroon and Spain will meet for the gold Saturday night in Olympic Stadium.</p>
        <p>Tonight the Americans were outclassed early.</p>
        <p>''We were a yard off,'' said Clive Charles, the United States coach who played at the top level in his native England and totally understands just how big a yard is in soccer.</p>
        <p>Spain came out smoking, sparked by Jose Mari Romero, a 6-foot, 21-year-old forward who was sold by Atletico Madrid to AC Milan last December.</p>
        <p>In the 17th minute tonight, Romero bolted down the right sideline, turned the corner and fired a perfect low cross which Raul Tamudo of Espanyol Barcelona guided home with a sliding shot.</p>
        <p>Eight minutes later, Romero was the key man in a second Spanish goal. The defender, Ivan Amaya of Atletico Madrid, lofted a ball from the right side. Romero went up for it while his marker, Dan Califf of the Los Angeles Galaxy, slipped on the wet grass. Romero controlled the ball near the biceps of his right arm -- a hand-ball foul if the referee had seen it -- and the ball plopped down neatly at his feet. He flicked a pass to Miguel Angulo of Valencia, who had no problem tapping the ball past Brad Friedel, the reserve goalkeeper from Liverpool.</p>
        <p>Admiring Romero's offense was Wolff, who is more opportunistic than most American forwards.</p>
        <p>''You realize the stage you're on,'' Wolff said later. ''You only get two or three scoring chances a game, and you have to convert them. They're good at that. They are so talented, and they interact. They're all on the same page.''</p>
        <p>The Spaniards had a 2-0 lead because they showed a sense of privilege. At the 31st minute, Chris Albright of D.C. United, could not pull the trigger on a centering pass from Wolff. Eight minutes later, Charles removed Albright and Ramiro Corrales of the MetroStars to get more offense.</p>
        <p>''You show the other team what your tactics are before halftime, which gives them time to adjust,'' Charles said. ''But we had to do something.''</p>
        <p>The move paid off, as many of Charles's moves have. In the 41st minute, Frankie Hejduk of Bayer Leverkusen in Germany collided with Angulo in the penalty box. It was the kind of foul a referee might not call in a tie game, but here he called it. Peter Vagenas, the self-designated penalty kicker from the Galaxy, calmly whacked the ball into the corner, and the margin was cut in half.</p>
        <p>But in the second half, Spain played more conservatively than some of its World Cup teams have done with a lead. The United States threw some elbows but not to much avail.</p>
        <p>In the 87th minute, Friedel made a two-handed punch save, only to have Romero lurking in the goal mouth for the easy rebound and the 3-1 margin.</p>
        <p>At very least, the Americans were not pushed around the field the way the 1990 and 1998 World Cup squads were in Europe.</p>
        <p>''We've closed the gap,'' Charles said. ''We've played European teams. We've played everybody. The gap is closed.''</p>
        <p>''The United States is making good progress,'' Inaki Saez Ruiz, the Spanish coach, said.</p>
        <p>For the moment, progress is not good enough.</p>
        <p>''We've never won a medal,'' said Chad McCarty of D.C. United, the defender with the red goatee. ''Every one of us wants to win one. It's been great so far. Every game, more and more people back in the States are paying attention.''</p>
        <p>After the respective gold and bronze medal games, the players from these two squads will return to their teams, the Spanish players to major European teams, the Americans mostly to Major League Soccer.</p>
        <p>''We'd be all right without a medal,'' said Wolff, whose Chicago team is about to begin a playoff series with the MetroStars. ''But a medal would be a tangible to take back with us.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
