<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Researchers Find Gene for Type 2 Diabetes</title>
    <meta content="Y27DIA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/science/27DIAB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deoxyribonucleic Acid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Starr County (Tex)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Chicago</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Texas</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Nicholas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diabetes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDE103AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Researchers Find Gene for Type 2 Diabetes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Nicholas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>University of Chicago and University of Texas researchers find novel gene associated with development of Type 2, or adult-onset, diabetes in study of Mexican-Americans in Starr County, Tex, population unusually burdened with disease; gene, whose role is obscure, is not known to have anything to do with sugar metabolism, which is disturbed in diabetes; gene is first identified in multigenetic disease by systematically scanning whole genome; has also been found at lower frequency in other ethnic groups; study involved comparing DNA of patients and their siblings unaffected by disease (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A novel gene associated with development of Type 2, or adult-onset, diabetes, a major and growing public health problem, has been identified from study of Mexican-Americans in Starr County, Tex., a population with an unusually heavy burden of the disease.</p>
        <p>The finding, if confirmed, will be the first discovery of a gene involved in the most common kind of Type 2 diabetes. Although some 5 percent of cases of the disease are caused by defects in single genes, which are relatively easy to find, the most common kind of Type 2 diabetes is thought to be caused by several contributing genes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A novel gene associated with development of Type 2, or adult-onset, diabetes, a major and growing public health problem, has been identified from study of Mexican-Americans in Starr County, Tex., a population with an unusually heavy burden of the disease.</p>
        <p>The finding, if confirmed, will be the first discovery of a gene involved in the most common kind of Type 2 diabetes. Although some 5 percent of cases of the disease are caused by defects in single genes, which are relatively easy to find, the most common kind of Type 2 diabetes is thought to be caused by several contributing genes.</p>
        <p>In multigenic diseases, which include many of the most common afflictions like Alzheimer's, asthma, diabetes, heart disease and schizophrenia, the contribution from every gene is so small that each is hard to identify.</p>
        <p>To their surprise, the researchers at the University of Chicago and the University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston found the gene is one not known to have anything to do with sugar metabolism, which is disturbed in diabetes. Its role is obscure, they said, but once it is understood, it should reveal a new biochemical pathway involved in diabetes.</p>
        <p>The diabetes finding has a broader significance in that the gene is the first in a multigenic disease to have been identified by scanning the whole genome -- the full complement of human DNA -- in a systematic way.</p>
        <p>Though a few such genes have come to light through guesswork, genomewide scans are the most promising method for uncovering the roots of multigenic disease. The diabetes work was done mostly before the human genome sequence became available, and such studies should be much easier in the future.</p>
        <p>''This is the first published account of tracking down a DNA sequence variation that appears to account for a multigenic character'' by scanning the whole genome, said Dr. Francis Collins, director of the National Human Genome Research Institute. ''It is a pathway we hope to travel frequently, so it's a relief to see someone has actually done it, albeit at great effort.''</p>
        <p>The Type 2 diabetes gene has been discovered through an eight-year effort which involved comparing the DNA of patients and their siblings unaffected by the disease.</p>
        <p>The gene has been named calpain-10 after a family of known genes it resembles. Calpain-10 and other genes involved in its pathway may provide new targets for drugs.</p>
        <p>The gene variations associated with diabetes were discovered first among the Mexican-American families of Starr County, in South Texas. They have since also been found, though at lower frequency, in other ethnic groups, including the Pima Indians of Arizona, who have the highest known incidence of Type 2 diabetes, and Europeans from the Botnia region of Finland.</p>
        <p>The team of researchers who brought the gene variations to light include Dr. Graeme I. Bell of the University of Chicago, who directed the genetic analysis; his colleague, Nancy J. Cox, who devised the statistical tests to pinpoint the causative DNA variations; and Dr. Craig L. Hanis, of the University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston, who led the clinical analysis of the Starr County patients. Their findings are published in today's issue of the journal Nature Genetics.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hanis, who has been collecting diabetes-related samples for 19 years, said that in 1992 he had joined with Dr. Bell and colleagues at two other universities to map the genomes of the diabetic subjects.</p>
        <p>By 1996 Dr. Bell's group had found a strong association between diabetes and genetic variations that lay at the end of the long arm of chromosome 2, the second largest of the 23 pairs of chromosomes in every human cell.</p>
        <p>Though physically too small to be visible, chromosomes are very large structures for anyone trying to analyze their genes and other features.  The DNA variations associated with diabetes spanned a region 1.7 million DNA units in length. The region contained 7 known genes and 15 suspected genes. No one analyzing a complex disease had ever been able to take the next step, that of identifying a specific gene within the general chromosomal region identified by genetic mapping.</p>
        <p>It fell to Dr. Cox, a statistical geneticist, to thread a way through the maze. Though there are many sites of DNA variation along the 1.7 million-unit stretch, all had about the same strength of association with the disease. Dr. Cox eventually found a way to rank the various sites and narrowed the search to the novel calpain-10 gene.</p>
        <p>She said there were ''lots of uneasy moments'' because the team never knew what they were looking for or how they would know when they found it.</p>
        <p>It turned out there are three single-unit DNA variations associated with diabetes, and each falls in a different portion, known as an intron, of the calpain-10 gene. Different combinations of the three mutations correlate with different degrees of susceptibility to diabetes, the researchers found.</p>
        <p>Genetic regions on DNA are divided into alternating sections known as exons and introns. After a gene is copied, the introns are spliced out and the exons joined together in the blueprint for a particular protein. Almost all known harmful mutations are in exons and cause disease by directing a misformed protein.</p>
        <p>A mere handful of significant mutations in introns were known up to this point. The mutations in the calpain-10 introns cannot affect its protein structure but may influence the way the gene is regulated, in other words the timing and amount of calpain-10 protein that is made.</p>
        <p>The location of the mutations in introns complicated acceptance of the researchers' findings and was one reason their article was held up for roughly 19 months while reviewers pored over it.</p>
        <p>''I think the editors should have taken a chance and it should have been published 2 years ago,'' Dr. Bell said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hanis paid tribute to Dr. Bell's drive to locate the gene. ''Graeme didn't give up, he worked incredibly hard and ignored the naysayers because we were convinced that, come hell or high water, he was going to scour that region and see whether or not there was a gene there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
