<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Quiet Support On Polarizing Topics</title>
    <meta content="Y27CONS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/politics/27CONS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CONSERVATIVE ORGANIZATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christian Coalition</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1D7133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1196" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Quiet Support On Polarizing Topics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush, in latest sign that he seeks to avoid being pegged as too conservative by moderate voters, will skip Christian Coalition convention, Washington, DC; stance is not stopping coalition and other conservative groups from stepping up behind-the-scenes efforts on his behalf; groups, which are spending heavily on pro-Bush phone banks, commercials and voter drives, are hammering away on issues Bush avoids in campaign speeches (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the latest example of how Gov. George W. Bush is going out of his way to avoid being pegged as too conservative by moderate voters, he has decided to skip what for the last two Republican presidential nominees was a must-stop on the election circuit: the Christian Coalition convention that opens here on Friday.</p>
        <p>But the lack of attention is not stopping the coalition and other conservative organizations -- from anti-abortion groups to the National Rifle Association -- from intensifying behind-the-scenes efforts on his behalf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the latest example of how Gov. George W. Bush is going out of his way to avoid being pegged as too conservative by moderate voters, he has decided to skip what for the last two Republican presidential nominees was a must-stop on the election circuit: the Christian Coalition convention that opens here on Friday.</p>
        <p>But the lack of attention is not stopping the coalition and other conservative organizations -- from anti-abortion groups to the National Rifle Association -- from intensifying behind-the-scenes efforts on his behalf.</p>
        <p>They are pouring millions of dollars into phone banks, commercials and voter drives to help elect Mr. Bush. And they are hammering away on issues that Mr. Bush is not addressing in his campaign speeches, from abortion to guns to Vice President Al Gore's character.</p>
        <p>Pat Robertson, the Christian Coalition chairman and founder, said that his group would be far more active in aiding the presidential ticket than it had been four years ago. In a letter to supporters this month, he wrote, ''Our naysayers are in for a big shock this November!''</p>
        <p>Another organization, the Conservative Leadership Political Action Committee, sent out more than a million letters in the past several days to raise money and mobilize voters in battleground states.</p>
        <p>In the mailing, Lyn Nofziger, a former aide to President Ronald Reagan, wrote: ''The reason we formed this emergency committee is that George W. Bush and the Republican Party cannot talk clearly and plainly about Al Gore's record of corruption and scandal without being accused of negative campaigning. But we can. And we are.''</p>
        <p>Still another group, the American Conservative Union, said it was distributing more than three million copies of a book it published that raises doubts about Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>''You know the liberal media will not tell America about Al Gore's far-left socialist vision for America,'' David Keene, the group's chairman, said in a letter to supporters.</p>
        <p>Some of the same groups that helped Mr. Bush win the South Carolina primary after his defeat in New Hampshire have re-emerged.</p>
        <p>The Republican Ideas Political Committee has been running a TV commercial in Kansas City, Mo., urging support of Republicans. It features a woman saying she took her son out of public schools partly because there was ''a bit more diversity than he could handle.'' The group has ties to Grover Norquist, head of Americans for Tax Reform, which financed commercials to help Mr. Bush during the primaries.</p>
        <p>In past campaigns, conservative groups did not hesitate to savage Republican candidates -- even at the risk of damaging the party's prospects -- who were not viewed as sufficiently outspoken on their causes. But conservatives have been notably quiet this year and resisted criticizing Mr. Bush because they felt he had a clear shot at winning.</p>
        <p>Even as the polls have tightened, and Mr. Bush is not viewed as much as a sure bet, many conservatives said they were sticking with him.</p>
        <p>Still, while they seek to galvanize their supporters, some prominent conservatives said they had misgivings lately about the Bush campaign. Some complained that Mr. Bush had allowed Mr. Gore to seize the issue of Hollywood and morality. Other said Mr. Bush should have made more of the Supreme Court ruling supporting the Boy Scouts' right to expel a gay assistant scoutmaster. And some said they felt the campaign had marginalized them.</p>
        <p>The most striking comments came from Mr. Robertson, who has been quite supportive of Mr. Bush. For the first time, he raised warnings about the Republican nominee's strategy, saying that by declining to address the convention he was neglecting conservatives at his own peril.</p>
        <p>''It's very risky,'' he said. ''It takes a lot of energy and effort to get out and work precincts and lick envelopes and go to churches. If you want the troops to go out and fall on their swords for you, it doesn't hurt for the general to stand up and say, 'I need your help.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Robertson also said that Mr. Gore's running mate, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut, who has been outspoken on the subjects of values and religion, could eat into Mr. Bush's support. ''With Lieberman, there's going to be some defection on moral issues,'' he said, ''and they have to be aware of that.''</p>
        <p>Asked about Mr. Bush's prospects, Mr. Robertson said, ''They're very iffy. They've lost the commanding lead they had. Republicans have a marvelous facility for snatching defeat from the jaws of victory.''</p>
        <p>Gary Bauer, who took on Mr. Bush in the primaries and now leads the conservative Campaign for Working Families, said he had no major objections, but thought social issues should be better emphasized. ''The party could still do more on a variety of values issues where the division between Gore and Bush remains substantial,'' he said, ''everything from the Boy Scouts issue to Hollywood.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is benefiting from aggressive grass-roots campaigns as well. The A.F.L.-C.I.O. and the National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League this week announced huge television campaigns to help the Democratic ticket. But it is quite unusual that so many conservative groups have gone along with efforts by the Bush campaign to keep a distance -- at least publicly.</p>
        <p>The N.R.A., aware that it could be damaging if Mr. Bush is closely identified with the group, has tentatively decided not to endorse him. But the association is spending millions of dollars to help him and to discredit Mr. Gore. Mr. Bush himself this month endorsed a group connected to the N.R.A., but with a name not apt to stoke controversy: the Law Enforcement Alliance of America.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's disinclination to promote his opposition to abortion was evident at a town hall meeting in Albuquerque about two weeks ago, when an abortion foe looked for assurance on his stand. The governor gave it, but only as he said that good people could disagree on the subject.</p>
        <p>Such caution does not seem to bother abortion opponents like David N. O'Steen, executive director of the National Right to Life Committee. He said he would not press Mr. Bush to raise the abortion issue next week during his first debate with Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Steen's organization is not so timid, having sent thousands of flyers to Republicans around the country castigating Mr. Gore for his stand on abortion. The flyer quotes a letter in 1997 from Cardinal Roger Mahony, the archbishop of Los Angeles, who said he was ''appalled'' by the vice president's remarks.</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, a campaign spokesman, said Mr. Bush would not attend the Christian Coalition event because it would ''conflict with our debate preparations this weekend.''</p>
        <p>Despite his decision not to attend -- coalition officials said Mr. Bush's running mate, Dick Cheney, also declined -- Mr. Bush has generally drawn better treatment from religious conservatives than Bob Dole, the Republican nominee in 1996, did.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole spoke at the coalition's convention, but Mr. Robertson was hardly supportive, telling the crowd Mr. Dole would probably lose. ''On my personal opinion,'' he said at that time, ''there has got to be a miracle from Almighty God to pull it out.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CONSERVATIVE ORGANIZATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
