<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Australian Poised to Give U.S. Dose of Its Own Medicine</title>
    <meta content="27BASK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Lauren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFD6123AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Australian Poised to Give U.S. Dose of Its Own Medicine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE WISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wise, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lauren Jackson, center on Australian women's basketball team, is one of best young prospects in world and could be playing in WNBA next season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lauren Jackson ran upcourt after a brief altercation under the basket with the frustrated United States player.</p>
        <p>This happened two weeks ago in Melbourne when the lithe, 6-foot-5-inch 19-year-old from the Australian national team was bumped by center Lisa Leslie -- who had come to the aid of her United States teammate Sheryl Swoopes -- raising the emotional ante in a tense exhibition game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lauren Jackson ran upcourt after a brief altercation under the basket with the frustrated United States player.</p>
        <p>This happened two weeks ago in Melbourne when the lithe, 6-foot-5-inch 19-year-old from the Australian national team was bumped by center Lisa Leslie -- who had come to the aid of her United States teammate Sheryl Swoopes -- raising the emotional ante in a tense exhibition game.</p>
        <p>''Well, she chested me,'' Jackson said recently. ''I wasn't sure what she did at first, but then I went back at her, like, 'You want a piece of me?' -- as the Americans like to do.</p>
        <p>''She's a very good player, but I don't think she outplayed me,'' Jackson said of Leslie. ''She got a lot of her points at the end of the game, when it was over.''</p>
        <p>In the exhibition, Team USA's depth eventually wore down the Opals, the nickname for the Australian national women's team. After another uprising from the peasants, order was again restored to the United States women's basketball universe.</p>
        <p>But for how long? As Jackson keeps maturing, as she transforms herself into the most dangerous inside-outside threat the women's game has known, while Nike plasters her image across the globe, America's gold medal reign is no longer a given.</p>
        <p>Yes, the Americans are 5-0 here entering their quarterfinal with Slovakia Wednesday evening, but so is Team Australia, which takes on Poland in the afternoon game. The two teams have a decent shot of facing off in the gold medal match on Saturday at the Super Dome in Olympic Park. Beyond the drama of the host nation trying to knock off Goliath, the world will be treated to a glimpse of the evolution of a superstar.</p>
        <p>''After we played the Yanks, I felt so good after the game even though we lost,'' Jackson said of the exhibition loss. ''I feel we've got a real good chance of beating them.''</p>
        <p>Cocksure and quirky, Jackson is the daughter of the former Australian national team players Gary and Maree Jackson. Her father used to show her tapes of Wilt Chamberlain as a youngster, and Lauren cried when she heard that the Hall of Fame center had died. Along with the basketball pedigree, she possesses a crossover appeal crucial to her sport's growth.</p>
        <p>''She could be the Michael Jordan that women's basketball hasn't yet had,'' said Michele Timms, a guard for Australia and a member of the Phoenix Mercury in the Women's National Basketball Association.</p>
        <p>In a way, Jackson is like any other 19-year-old, tugged at by images and people competing for her time and attention. She listens to the gothic rocker Marilyn Manson more than to her elders, and to accompany the lightning bolt on her hip she had her country's flag tattooed on her left arm.</p>
        <p>''I'm not a dark person, contrary to some of the music I listen to,'' she said, smiling. ''So please don't paint me that way. I'm actually quite fun and upbeat about life. But I am a bit different, I suppose.''</p>
        <p>On the court, she sets herself apart. Relentless inside, Jackson leads the Opals in scoring and rebounding in the Olympic tournament, using her quickness and skill to dominate. She has one more season to fulfill a contractual obligation for her professional team in Canberra, where she averaged 23.4 points last season. She could be playing in the W.N.B.A. as early as next summer, dropping in soft running jump shots in the key, spotting up from behind the arc or maneuvering her sinewy frame along the baseline for a reverse layup.</p>
        <p>''I can't really go to my left and my defense is shocking, but I am picking up many things about the game,'' she said last week.</p>
        <p>Leslie, the 27-year-old All-Star of the Los Angeles Sparks, has called Jackson ''a future W.N.B.A. star, an awesome player.'' But she bristles at the notion that a rivalry between the two exists. And she disputes Jackson's account of their confrontation in Melbourne, which carried over to the other end when Leslie made a strong baseline drive only to have her shot sent to the floor by a leaping Jackson.</p>
        <p>''Maybe I misunderstood her,'' Leslie said, playing down the encounter. ''Maybe our languages are different. I didn't hear that at all.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''There is no rivalry until we play them. That's when it matters.''</p>
        <p>Swoopes said: ''She's very competitive for her age, a great player. But she also needs to understand, you're playing against players who are better than you are and who could teach you something. She shouldn't forget that.''</p>
        <p>She forgets when the teenager within often gives way to the ultracompetitive professional. ''There is one side to her that still loves to be a kid and another that won't back down from anyone at anytime,'' said Kristi Harrower, the Opals' point guard.</p>
        <p>''She'll be one of the best players the world has ever seen,'' Australian forward Michelle Griffiths said. ''She hasn't even found her stripes yet. She hasn't even got the complete game yet. I don't think the world has even touched the surface for Lauren Jackson.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
