<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Son of Microwave: Fast and Crisp</title>
    <meta content="27KITC$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/27/living/27KITC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TEST KITCHEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ovens and Stoves</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Microwaves</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabricant, Florence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Microwaves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E0DF133AF934A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Son of Microwave: Fast and Crisp</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabricant, Florence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florence Fabricant reports on new generation of ovens that can cook as fast as microwave but deliver crisp, well-browned results of conventional oven; new generation of ovens is arriving on market with considerable fanfare and endorsement of some top chefs; makers of these ovens--which combine microwave technology with other heating systems--boast that rack of lamb will be done in as little as 7 minutes, and perfect crisp-skinned roast chicken in only 20; photos; table shows new generation of ovens and their features (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT sounds impossible: an oven that can cook as fast as a microwave but delivers the crisped, well-browned results of a conventional oven.</p>
        <p>Yet, that is exactly the claim behind a new generation of ovens now arriving on the market with considerable fanfare and the endorsement of some top chefs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT sounds impossible: an oven that can cook as fast as a microwave but delivers the crisped, well-browned results of a conventional oven.</p>
        <p>Yet, that is exactly the claim behind a new generation of ovens now arriving on the market with considerable fanfare and the endorsement of some top chefs.</p>
        <p>The makers of these ovens -- which combine microwave technology with other heating systems -- boast that a rack of lamb will be done in as little as 7 minutes, and a perfect crisp-skinned roast chicken in only 20.</p>
        <p>Four companies are now manufacturing seven of the ovens, which are engineered to cut cooking times by up to 80 percent through a combination of conventional heating, convection blowers, microwaves, broiling elements or even super-hot halogen or quartz bulbs. The microwaves, which cook the interior of foods by vibrating water molecules within them, also enhance the penetration of other heating elements, which brown the surface.</p>
        <p>I tested three of the fastest ovens on the market:</p>
        <p>* General Electric's Advantium, which was introduced early last year and uses halogen light bulbs and microwaves.</p>
        <p>* Maytag's Jenn-Air Accellis 5XP, which uses microwaves and high-intensity convection heating.</p>
        <p>* Thermador's CJ, which combines high-intensity convection heating and microwaves.</p>
        <p>I prepared an array of foods in each of them, including rack of lamb, roast chicken, salmon fillets, baked potatoes and lemon poundcake. The results were often nothing short of amazing. In fact, roast chicken and salmon were better in the Thermador CJ and the Jenn-Air than in a conventional oven. Some foods, like rack of lamb and poundcake, actually cooked more evenly in one oven, the Advantium, than in either of the two others or a conventional oven.</p>
        <p>I'm not alone in my amazement.</p>
        <p>''It blew my mind,'' said Dean Fearing, the chef at the Mansion on Turtle Creek in Dallas, who recently tried Jenn-Air's Accellis 5XP wall oven as part of a television appearance. ''I was skeptical until I saw it in action and it made the best chicken I ever had, and in about 11 minutes.''</p>
        <p>Combination microwave and convection ovens have been around for years, but rely on microwaves as the source of heat -- not high-speed convection or halogen lamps. The new generation of high-speed models bring to home cooks technology once available only in professional kitchens.</p>
        <p>The manufacturers say these high-speed ovens, which start at $1,300 and, for a two-oven unit, go to $5,200, succeed where microwaves failed because of the combined technology. ''When the microwave oven was introduced 30 or so years ago it was supposed to be the savior,'' said Bill Deter, the vice president and general manager for cooking products at Maytag. ''But it only had speed, not the quality of the cooking. People were not willing to compromise.''</p>
        <p>Other major manufacturers are moving into the technology as well, including Whirlpool and KitchenAid.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deter said Maytag sees speed as the overriding concern for consumers, which is why it is investing in this electric technology even though 40 percent of all ovens in the United States run on gas. ''People want dinner in half an hour,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The ovens also function as regular microwave ovens. The Advantium can be used without preheating. All cook in a fifth to a quarter of the time of a regular oven.</p>
        <p>But there are drawbacks. The ovens are quite small -- forget about a 20-pound turkey. The Advantium must be used with a turntable, like a microwave oven, which further limits the space for food. As with regular microwave ovens, the number of items being cooked can slow things down in the Jenn-Air and the Advantium. Only the Thermador does not require microwave-safe glass or ceramic cookware. Conventional metal baking sheets, cake tins and casseroles cannot be used during speed cooking in the others, which come with special broiling and crisping pans.</p>
        <p>All the ovens have control panels for entering details like the type of cooking function (speed cooking, microwave or convection), the kind of food to be cooked and, often, its size. As a result of surveys of what people usually cook, the manufacturers have programmed the time and temperature for many standard dishes, like chicken, baked potatoes and brownies. But there can be problems with a dish that has not been programmed, like poundcake in a loaf pan. The user must consult a manual, find a similar dish and hope for the best.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, the cooking can be interrupted to check the food. With the Thermador CJ, once the food category has been selected, only the conventional cooking time has to be entered; the oven automatically converts it to the speed-cooking equivalent. The Jenn-Air also provides automatic conversion, and it has a warning beeper so the food can be checked shortly before the cooking cycle ends, to help avoid overcooking. (A minute or two can make a big difference.)</p>
        <p>With the Advantium, separate settings are needed for the upper and lower heating elements and the microwave function. Recipes from the manual are preprogrammed.</p>
        <p>I had the best overall results with the Jenn-Air and the Thermador CJ. Ordinary three-pound supermarket chickens emerged after 20 minutes with the skin beautifully crisped, yet with the breast meat exceptionally juicy. Salmon fillets on a bed of leeks, cooked in 3 minutes to an internal temperature of 120 degrees, or medium rare, were excellent in these ovens. Even when the fish was left in long enough to register about 140 degrees, as ovens were programmed for, it was still delectably moist, especially in the Jenn-Air.</p>
        <p>Not everything turned out as good as the chicken and salmon. A rack of lamb cooked in the Thermador CJ was perfectly done inside but tasted more steamed than roasted, and its crumb and mustard crust was not sufficiently browned. A souffle cooked in the same oven was too rubbery. On the other hand, this oven did a great job with beef short ribs braised in a covered metal casserole. And baked potatoes turned out fine, while a poundcake was delicious, browned, yet with perfect texture.</p>
        <p>With the Jenn-Air, timing a poundcake turned out to be somewhat hit-or-miss, and the skin of baked potatoes remained soft. I did not try the souffle or short ribs in this oven.</p>
        <p>For comparison's sake, I also tried the $1,300 Maytag 2X, a free-standing range with a full-size oven, which combines conventional cooking with microwaves, cutting normal cooking time in half. Most of the food cooked somewhat unevenly and was a trifle dry, especially the poundcake, the chicken and the salmon when it was not medium-rare. Thermador also has a full-size, slower model, the CM, which was not available for testing.</p>
        <p>As for the Advantium, though the crust on the rack of lamb was underbrowned, the meat was excellent. This oven also did the best job with baked potatoes, though they had to be turned once during baking. The chicken and salmon were not as moist as in the other ovens. The poundcake was a trifle dry; as with the Jenn-Air, the timing was a guesstimate.</p>
        <p>In a well-equipped kitchen, the ovens would best be auxiliaries to a full-size oven.</p>
        <p>The technology evolved from commercial equipment. For example, the speed of the Jenn-Air oven depends on a concentrated forced-air convection system that is similar to the one used in the company's Blodgett line for restaurant kitchens, but not so powerful. Developed by Turbo Chef, it can cook in a tenth of the time a conventional oven takes. But at that speed it's too noisy for a home kitchen. Mr. Deter said that in adapting the technology for home use the company also added features like self-cleaning.</p>
        <p>The halogen system in the Advantium was first developed in the early 1990's in California and used in pizza ovens. Called Flashbake, it is still sold commercially but has also been licensed to Vulcan-Hart, a manufacturer of professional equipment, and to General Electric for residential use. Brad Blackburn, the vice president of marketing for Vulcan-Hart, said that halogen bulbs produce a broad spectrum of light, which both browns and penetrates the food to heat it.</p>
        <p>This month, Whirlpool will introduce KitchenAid's Ultima Cook, as well as a similar Whirlpool version. It had no demonstration models available, so I was unable to test either. The company said both ovens combine microwave, convection, broiling and quartz heat but have slightly different designs. For many foods, there will be special instructions, like one requiring that the cook dust a chicken with flour and put it in a crisper bag.</p>
        <p>When microwave ovens first appeared, cooks were often in the dark about how to use them. This time around, the oven companies are lining up professional chefs to help promote and explain the products. Jenn-Air has a contract with Charlie Trotter, and is holding a cooking contest for chefs at the Culinary Institute of America at Greystone in the Napa Valley next month. Thermador's ovens have been in use at the French Culinary Institute in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>General Electric, which is advertising the Advantium heavily during the Olympics, has arranged with Nestle to have Advantium cooking instructions included with its line of Stouffer's Oven Sensations frozen meals. ''The microwave oven finally took off when appliance companies and food companies began to work together,'' Ms. Wood said. ''That's why we went with it right away.''</p>
        <p>The company has also hired Marcus Samuelsson of Aquavit, who plans to use the oven in his new Scandinavia House restaurant, where there will not be a full kitchen.</p>
        <p>I am not giving up on my regular oven just yet, but one of these would be great to have. And I'd use it for more than just 20-minute chicken.</p>
        <p>TEST KITCHEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
