<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks in a Somber Mood After Hearing About Mourning</title>
    <meta content="17KNIC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/sports/17KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mourning, Alonzo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EED61F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks in a Somber Mood After Hearing About Mourning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knickerbocker players are in no mood to discuss their enhanced position in Eastern Conference after learning that Alonzo Mourning, Miami Heat's All-Star center, will miss season with kidney disorder (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Knicks were in no mood today to discuss their enhanced position in the Eastern Conference after learning that Alonzo Mourning, the Miami Heat's All-Star center, would miss the season with a kidney disorder.</p>
        <p>''I feel so badly for Alonzo, and I'm just really thinking right now about his health and his recovery,'' Knicks Coach Jeff Van Gundy said tonight before the Knicks' 95-90 victory over the Washington Wizards at the Hartford Civic Center. ''Right now is not a time to discuss how his absence affects basketball when there are so many greater issues out there. I feel badly for him and his family and, secondarily, for their organization.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Knicks were in no mood today to discuss their enhanced position in the Eastern Conference after learning that Alonzo Mourning, the Miami Heat's All-Star center, would miss the season with a kidney disorder.</p>
        <p>''I feel so badly for Alonzo, and I'm just really thinking right now about his health and his recovery,'' Knicks Coach Jeff Van Gundy said tonight before the Knicks' 95-90 victory over the Washington Wizards at the Hartford Civic Center. ''Right now is not a time to discuss how his absence affects basketball when there are so many greater issues out there. I feel badly for him and his family and, secondarily, for their organization.</p>
        <p>''We've gone through it with Patrick Ewing being injured, but in a different way. It certainly never was anything that could be considered life threatening with Pat, but whenever you lose your best player, it's traumatic.''</p>
        <p>While Mourning's health is the primary concern of the league's players, coaches and officials, his absence in the lineup will shift the balance of power in the East. With him, the Heat, which added Eddie Jones, Anthony Mason and Brian Grant during the off-season, was the overwhelming favorite to win the conference.</p>
        <p>Now, the Knicks, who will play the Heat in a regular-season game on Nov. 29, and several other teams, including the Indiana Pacers, Toronto Raptors, Charlotte Hornets, Milwaukee Bucks, Orlando Magic and Philadelphia 76ers, will be considered potential National Basketball Association finalists.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty much wide open,'' said Marcus Camby, who led the Knicks with 16 points and 11 rebounds.. ''It was wide open before, even if he wasn't sick. But it's sad. I don't even want to speculate on the season.''</p>
        <p>With Mourning sidelined, the East is devoid of dominant centers, a development that should help the Knicks after the Ewing trade.</p>
        <p>After moving Ewing in September, the Knicks became somewhat desperate for a top-flight center and have had several conversations with the Hawks about Dikembe Mutombo. But with Mourning and Indiana's Rik Smits, who retired, off the floor, the Knicks may be more likely to stand pat and make a play for Sacramento's Chris Webber next summer.</p>
        <p>The top three front lines in the conference now belong to Charlotte (Elden Campbell, P. J. Brown, Derrick Coleman and Jamal Mashburn), Toronto (Kevin Willis, Antonio Davis and Charles Oakley) and Philadelphia (Theo Ratliff, Tyrone Hill, Matt Geiger and George Lynch). Van Gundy said those clubs will present a great challenge for the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''Charlotte is huge,'' Van Gundy said. ''They're the one team that has great size in our conference. You don't have to be huge huge, but size does matter, particularly in a playoff series.''</p>
        <p>Latrell Sprewell said the East's lack of dynamic big men should make for a faster, more exciting style of play. But he knows how difficult it will be for Mourning to miss a season.</p>
        <p>''I've had to do that under different circumstances so I know how hard it is to be sitting there and having to watch and wanting to participate,'' Sprewell said.</p>
        <p>Sprewell, however, does not think that Mourning's absence will diminish the fierceness of the Knicks' rivalry with the Heat.</p>
        <p>''I think we're still going to compete and play,'' Sprewell said. ''It's going to be very intense. I don't think it matters at this point who you put on the floor. They want to beat us and we want to beat them.''</p>
        <p>But Camby admitted that it would not be the same playing Miami without its ferocious center.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be tough playing those guys knowing that he's not there and that if he was there, the game would be a whole lot different,'' Camby said. ''It's still going to be intense, but without Alonzo, it's taking a little something away from the game for both teams.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>MARCUS CAMBY bought tickets for 600 school children from the Sand and Clark Elementary Schools, both of which he attended while growing up in Hartford. Over the summer, Camby was criticized by an official from Sand after relocating his ''March With Marcus,'' in which he walked hundreds of children to school on the opening day of classes, from Hartford to Harlem. ''That's how I get treated down here,'' Camby said. ''My thing is it's not like I didn't do the march or overslept and just didn't do it. I was still doing something for kids. That's the part I really don't understand. As long as I'm helping somebody people should be happy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
