<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; A Mariner Struggles at the Plate, but All Is Still Calm in Seattle</title>
    <meta content="17VECS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/sports/17VECS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Mariners</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilson, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2D61F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; A Mariner Struggles at the Plate, but All Is Still Calm in Seattle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column discusses Seattle Mariners catcher Dan Wilson's poor batting record in postseason play; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF ever there was an example of the difference between frantic New York and undemonstrative Seattle, consider the case of Dan Wilson, the catcher for the Seattle Mariners.</p>
        <p>The Mariners will be trying to tie their series with the Yankees tonight with a player who hasn't had a hit since 1995 -- in the postseason, that is to say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF ever there was an example of the difference between frantic New York and undemonstrative Seattle, consider the case of Dan Wilson, the catcher for the Seattle Mariners.</p>
        <p>The Mariners will be trying to tie their series with the Yankees tonight with a player who hasn't had a hit since 1995 -- in the postseason, that is to say.</p>
        <p>Wilson had two hits against the Yankees in that epic division series and hasn't had one since, for a total of 40 straight official at-bats, one of the great futility streaks in the  history of baseball, postseason or otherwise. His career postseason average is .035, which somehow seems far worse than the .000 he carries for this year, the one that shows up on the scoreboard. After all, he could be 0 for 0.</p>
        <p>For all the outs, nobody in Seattle is pushing the panic button, or even paying much attention to Wilson's predicament, presumably because it's not polite to dwell on such things.</p>
        <p>In the Bronx part of the world, if a Yankee were having such a postseason slump, the tabloid headlines  would be blaring vicious insults.</p>
        <p>However, the back-page taunts against a hometown player would be nothing compared to the blithering of the owner himself, who would be accusing said player of spitting the bit, taking money under false pretenses, choking up, or other such offenses.</p>
        <p>Back in cloudy and calm Seattle, there is not even an outpouring of civic grief or the formation of support groups. Wilson himself seems to be holding up under the slump with no visible tics or neurosis.</p>
        <p>''It's been a long stretch,'' Wilson admitted, after going 0 for 3 in Sunday's marathon victory. ''But you just have to keep going.''</p>
        <p>Wilson said there is no anxiety hanging over his life. Friends are not clustering around his front door, leaving flowers or clucking with sympathy as he goes past.</p>
        <p>Maybe nobody knows. Maybe it's the kind of thing nobody discusses in public. Maybe it's bad manners to bring up such matters.</p>
        <p>By contrast, consider the outpouring for Gil Hodges back in Brooklyn in 1952, when that Dodger idol finished the World Series 0 for 21.</p>
        <p>Not only that, but this was one of those Subway Series we keep hearing about. The Dodgers were playing the hated Yankees. And in the Borough of Churches, people were saying prayers, lighting candles, throwing coins into fountains, anything to try to get Hodges's bat untracked.</p>
        <p>Nothing like that is happening in Wilson's life, or so he insists with major blandness. ''People are concerned with the team,'' Wilson said. ''Everybody's goal is to win games.''</p>
        <p>He helps win games as a useful defensive player with the build of somebody who ought to be able to smite the ball into open spaces. He is 6 feet 3 inches, weighs 202 pounds, and played high school quarterback and hockey goalie before concentrating on baseball at the University of Minnesota. Lou Piniella saw him in the Cincinnati system in the early 1990's and was happy when the Mariners got him in 1994.</p>
        <p>Wilson isn't even that bad a hitter during the regular season, with a career average of .262 and 66 homers. But in the postseason, he was 2 for 17 against the Yankees in 1995 and has been 0 for everybody since. Zero for 16 against Cleveland in the 1995 American League Championship Series. Zero for 13 against Baltimore in the 1997 division series. Zero for 3 against the White Sox in this year's division series. Zero for 8 against the Yankees, and counting.</p>
        <p>Piniella, who surely would have snapped if he had ever gone even a week without a hit, has a theory why many hitters, whether Barry Bonds or Dan Wilson, suddenly veer southward in the postseason: ''You're playing better teams. You're facing better pitchers.''</p>
        <p>Wilson says he tries not to let the streak hurt his defense.</p>
        <p>''It's frustrating,'' he said. ''A couple of times, I could have driven in a run.''</p>
        <p>All catchers, whether great defensive players like Johnny Bench or more average catchers like Mike Piazza, have to learn not to take their offensive troubles, however temporary, behind home plate.</p>
        <p>''You have to separate the two,'' Wilson said Sunday, when he started because Joe Oliver, with whom Wilson platoons at catcher, had a strained quadriceps. ''There are two sides to baseball, and it's even more so for catchers.''</p>
        <p>Wilson actually stroked a booming fly ball his first time up Sunday, but it was easily caught by Bernie Williams near the warning track. Wilson had two infield grounders and a walk, his second in the series. He also has one run batted, a sacrifice fly against Chicago. He did drive in a run against the Yankees in 1995, a long time ago. Maybe he is due.</p>
        <p>At any rate, back home in Seattle, there was no civic gnashing of teeth, nor any great outcry of fear and trembling, nor any maudlin standing ovations.</p>
        <p>Yankee fans will make up for this yawning lack of awareness. Being such considerate souls, more than a few of the denizens of the Stadium are sure to console Wilson over his troubles before the night is out.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
