<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mixed Prospects of Indonesia</title>
    <meta content="17INDO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="W" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/business/17INDO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Timor (Indonesia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consultative Group on Indonesia</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Bank for Reconstruction and Development</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Monetary Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Wayne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DE1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mixed Prospects of Indonesia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE ARNOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Wayne</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia, Oct. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indonesian government is rebuffing criticism from international donors even as it approaches them for $4.8 billion in assistance; meeting with Consultative Group on Indonesia comes against backdrop of further decline in Indonesian political stability that has unnerved investors further and left many wondering if government is able to salvage what has become worst-performing economy in region; questions from International Monetary Fund and World Bank about government plan to take over country's largest corporate debtor have provoked angry remarks from Indonesian officials, who accuse international lenders of favoritism and interference; Japanese finance ministry officials repeatedly favor keeping noneconomic issues out of discussions; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Indonesian government, which presides over the weakest of Southeast Asia's economies, is rebuffing criticism from international donors even as it approaches them for $4.8 billion in assistance.</p>
        <p>The Consultative Group on Indonesia, an umbrella organization headed by the World Bank and including roughly 30 foreign governments, will meet Indonesian officials in Tokyo this week to decide how much the group will lend to Indonesia and under what conditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Indonesian government, which presides over the weakest of Southeast Asia's economies, is rebuffing criticism from international donors even as it approaches them for $4.8 billion in assistance.</p>
        <p>The Consultative Group on Indonesia, an umbrella organization headed by the World Bank and including roughly 30 foreign governments, will meet Indonesian officials in Tokyo this week to decide how much the group will lend to Indonesia and under what conditions.</p>
        <p>The meeting, which begins on Tuesday, comes against the backdrop of further decline in Indonesian political stability. President Abdurrahman Wahid, hobbled by two strokes and blindness in one eye, has largely failed to contain ethnic violence in far-flung areas or to prevent attacks on aid workers in West Timor. A series of bombings, most notably a blast last month under the Jakarta Stock Exchange, has unnerved investors further and left many wondering if the government is able to salvage what has become the worst-performing economy in the region.</p>
        <p>At the same time, questions from the International Monetary Fund and the World Bank about a government plan to take over the country's largest corporate debtor have provoked angry remarks from Indonesian officials, who accuse the international lenders of favoritism and interference. Jakarta officials have also rebuffed some United Nations demands on West Timor despite warnings from Britain and the United States that lending could be held up over this matter.</p>
        <p>The nation's chief economics minister, Rizal Ramli, was in Tokyo last week to seek assurances from Japan, Indonesia's biggest lender, that it would not let political issues stand in the way of aid. Japanese finance ministry officials reportedly favor keeping noneconomic issues out of the discussions.</p>
        <p>The consultative group's pledges are an important gauge of international support for economic recovery, and any sign that support is wavering could batter Indonesia's already fragile financial markets.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, some economists and analysts say that the group has lost much of its leverage over Indonesian policy because members have too much riding on economic recovery to deny the country further funds.</p>
        <p>''Indonesia at the end of the day has a very big strategic importance in the region,'' said Vincent Low, first vice president for fixed-income research and strategy at Merrill Lynch in Singapore. ''From a geopolitical point of view, it's too big to fail.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, Indonesia's government owes the rest of the world more than $60 billion, so much of the donor group's pledges go toward servicing existing debt. Indonesian annual foreign debt payments are the equivalent of about two-thirds of the group's pledge, said David G. Fernandez, a J. P. Morgan economist.</p>
        <p>Indonesia is counting on the international loans to offset roughly 40 percent of its expected budget deficit next year. High prices for Indonesian oil, however, may reduce the country's need for some of the aid. The proposed budget prices crude oil at $22 a barrel, while oil is now trading around $35 a barrel. Conservative estimates of that sort enabled Indonesia to finance its budget deficit this year without drawing on the credit line from the consultative group's lenders.</p>
        <p>And despite continued separatist violence, religious strife and political instability, Indonesia's economic recovery still appears to be on track. Many economists predict growth of at least 4 percent in 2001, with the World Bank noting that wages, adjusted for inflation, are rising, and demand for cars, electricity and building materials like cement are increasing, as well.</p>
        <p>That is good news to Indonesian creditors, especially Japan. Lenders there account for more than 30 percent of the Indonesian government's foreign debt, according to the World Bank, and Japan is offering to contribute more than $1.5 billion of the group's total pledge this week.</p>
        <p>Indonesia's bargaining position in Tokyo may, therefore, seem strong, but economists warn that its financial situation is still precarious. ''Financial markets remain unconvinced by developments in the real economy,'' said the World Bank's regional vice president, Jemaluddin Kassum, who will preside at the meeting in Tokyo. Indonesia's currency, the rupiah, has fallen about 20 percent since the start of the year and stock prices, down 40 percent in local-currency terms, are at their lowest level in a year and a half.</p>
        <p>Unlike in the United States, though, falling markets here have little impact on consumer confidence; most Indonesians do not own stocks. But such developments make it harder for Indonesia to hold up its end of financing the budget deficit.</p>
        <p>The country's bank restructuring agency, which controls assets equivalent to more than half the economy, is also responsible for plugging roughly half the budget deficit by selling some of those assets. The agency recently postponed plans to sell one of its most highly prized assets, Bank Central Asia, citing poor market conditions.</p>
        <p>The delay upset the I.M.F., which had set the bank's sale this year as one of the terms for its own, separate $5 billion assistance program. The I.M.F. and foreign investors say the orderly sale of the agency's repossessed assets is important in reviving investor interest in Indonesia. But concerns that foreigners would be able to purchase national assets at fire-sale prices arouse nationalist furor here.</p>
        <p>The latest source of disillusionment among investors was a deal late last month by the bank restructuring agency to take over a textile and engineering company, Texmaco, to recover $2.7 billion in debts the company owes it. Because the deal eventually puts the company's politically connected management back in charge, critics are calling it a bailout.</p>
        <p>The Texmaco controversy opened a rift between the government and the World Bank and I.M.F., after the leak of a letter to Mr. Ramli from the two organizations urging Indonesia to obtain a second opinion. Mr. Ramli, who before his appointment as economics minister this year was a prominent critic of the I.M.F., accused it and the World Bank of discriminating against President Wahid's government.</p>
        <p>Many Indonesian politicians suspect that other conglomerates were given unduly favorable treatment under the administration of Mr. Wahid's predecessor, B. J. Habibie, when the bank restructuring agency had a much closer relationship with the I.M.F. and Western financial advisers.</p>
        <p>Despite the rancor, the World Bank has taken pains to emphasize Indonesia's progress and explain the country's turmoil as an inevitable side effect of its newly minted democracy. Analysts here say that with so much at stake, little rebuke in practical terms is to be expected from the donors' meeting in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>''Nobody's going to sink Indonesia's first democratic government in 50 years,'' a Western banking official said. ''Not in its first year.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
