<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boo.com, Online Fashion Flop, Is Ready to Rise From Ashes</title>
    <meta content="Y17BOO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/technology/17BOO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boo.com</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fashionmall.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kapner, Suzanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DC1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boo.com, Online Fashion Flop, Is Ready to Rise From Ashes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE KAPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kapner, Suzanne</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boo.com, one of online fashion's first victims, is preparing for its reappearance on Oct 30; is now owned by Fashionmall.com (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like the pointy-toed cowboy boots last seen in the 1980's and now making a comeback with a vengeance, fashion thrives on an endless cycle of reinvention.</p>
        <p>Boo.com, one of online fashion's first victims, is banking on that maxim as it prepares for its reappearance on Oct. 30. Beginning this week, the new Boo is introducing itself with billboard posters and print ads in London and New York that are unabashedly self-deprecating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like the pointy-toed cowboy boots last seen in the 1980's and now making a comeback with a vengeance, fashion thrives on an endless cycle of reinvention.</p>
        <p>Boo.com, one of online fashion's first victims, is banking on that maxim as it prepares for its reappearance on Oct. 30. Beginning this week, the new Boo is introducing itself with billboard posters and print ads in London and New York that are unabashedly self-deprecating.</p>
        <p>In the campy vein of an old horror-movie bill, one poster introduces ''Boo.com, the sequel'' as ''the site you've been waiting and waiting and waiting for'' -- alluding to the technical glitches that prevented the original Boo from appearing on time. In a nod toward Boo's new owner, Fashionmall.com, which bought the Boo trademarks when the original liquidated last spring after it ran out of cash, the poster promises: ''A brand new production! All new cast! All new direction!''</p>
        <p>For all the tongue-in-cheekiness, reviving a name associated with one of the Internet's most spectacular failures carries its share of risk, said Richard Hyman, chairman of Verdict, a consulting group in London. ''To a lot of people, Boo carries a negative connotation. They say, 'Oh, I know Boo, it's the company that went bust.' ''</p>
        <p>Even though retailers ranging from Sears to Gucci have repositioned themselves with panache, Boo's battle to win back customers is singular in that its first incarnation was so short-lived.</p>
        <p>''We're not talking about a company that's done a great job for 10 years and now wants to reposition itself,'' Mr. Hyman said. ''We're talking about a company that's made a promise to customers -- that's taken money from people -- and hasn't delivered. There is repositioning. And there's bringing back from the dead.''</p>
        <p>Boo.com's new president, Catherine Buggeln, is mindful of the mistakes made by her predecessors, and is quick to point out the differences between the old Boo and the new. ''The original Boo was a victim of overpromise and underdelivery,'' Ms. Buggeln said. The new Boo, the implication is, will be the opposite.</p>
        <p>Unlike her predecessors, whose youth and glamour masked their limited retailing experience, Ms. Buggeln, 39, has spent 17 years working for the likes of Bergdorf Goodman, Barney's and Gucci. ''It's the  first time my age has been an asset,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The new Boo is being introduced on a $1 million budget, a veritable shoestring compared with the $44 million spent the first time around. Ms. Buggeln concedes that the huge customer awareness generated by her predecessors has eliminated the need for an all-out media blitz. ''I am doing this on their backs,'' she said.</p>
        <p>So there will be no expensive stylists coiffing Ms. Boo's digital hair, no high-powered marketing firms buffing Boo's image.</p>
        <p>Instead, Balet &amp; Albert, a boutique Manhattan firm, designed the ads, which will run mostly in the trade press until they are replaced by a broader consumer campaign early next year.</p>
        <p>Even Ms. Boo, the computerized arbiter of cool, has suffered a humbling dressing down. Now that she has squandered all her money, she has to work for a living, is on a strict budget and meets regularly with a financial adviser, according to a story line posted on Boo's Web site.</p>
        <p>''We thought what would she be like if she really lost her job and her company went bust,'' Ms. Buggeln said. ''Wouldn't she be a bit less self-assured?''</p>
        <p>Many of the changes are more than skin deep, and try to address what some considered the root of the original Boo's problems. Unlike the old Boo, which bought merchandise that it resold to customers, the new Boo is not bearing the risk of owning inventory. As a portal, it will feature some 250 of fashion's most coveted items -- ferreted out by a loose network of scouts, who scour the Internet for what is cool and are paid by the find. There will be products from Skim, for instance, a German company that imprints customers' e-mail addresses on their clothing. Rather than getting bogged down in the taking of orders and shipping of goods, Boo will direct customers who wish to make a purchase to the Web sites that sell the merchandise.</p>
        <p>In one respect the new Boo wants to resemble the original: courting a European customer base. The Manhattan-based Fashionmall bought the rights to Boo, which counted about 75 percent of its customers from outside the United States, as an entree to the European market.</p>
        <p>For all its problems, the old Boo managed to attract 558,000 visitors in  April, compared with 208,000 for Fashionmall.com, according to Media Metrix. Indeed, Ms. Buggeln said, she became convinced that sticking with the Boo name was the right choice when she learned that 35,000 people visit Boo.com each week even though it has been inactive since spring.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
