<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="17MBRF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/nyregion/17MBRF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7DC163EF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: ABSTINENCE BILL ADVANCES  A committee of the New Jersey State Assembly yesterday approved legislation that would require schools to teach abstinence as a form of birth control. By a vote of 5 to 1, with one abstention, the Assembly education committee sent the measure to the full Assembly. Different versions of the bill have been defeated in other sessions. Separately, the Assembly judicial committee heard public testimony on whether to require parents to be notified before minors could seek an abortion. Proponents said notification would strengthen families; opponents said in cases of incest or abuse, getting such approval would be difficult or impossible.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>TRENTON: ABSTINENCE BILL ADVANCES  A committee of the New Jersey State Assembly yesterday approved legislation that would require schools to teach abstinence as a form of birth control. By a vote of 5 to 1, with one abstention, the Assembly education committee sent the measure to the full Assembly. Different versions of the bill have been defeated in other sessions. Separately, the Assembly judicial committee heard public testimony on whether to require parents to be notified before minors could seek an abortion. Proponents said notification would strengthen families; opponents said in cases of incest or abuse, getting such approval would be difficult or impossible.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>ENGLEWOOD: ELECTED SCHOOL BOARD OPPOSED  Opposition appeared to be growing against a November ballot measure that would change the Englewood school board to an elected board from one appointed by the mayor. A group calling itself the Englewood Citizens for Education announced yesterday it would work with Mayor Paul T. Fader against the measure. The parents' group said it would try to convince voters that an appointed board helps maintain diverse ethnic and economic representation. Earlier, another parents' group forced the city to put the measure on the ballot because it believed an elected board would help raise some of the lowest test scores in Bergen County.</p>
        <p>Maria Newman (NYT)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: STATE TO COMBAT INTERNET HATE  The New Jersey Commission on Holocaust Education, a state-sponsored agency, yesterday announced a curriculum guide to help teachers combat expressions of hate, especially on the Internet. The guide, which will be sent to teachers in grades 6 to 12 by January, includes material that helps identify hate speech, said Paul B. Winkler, the commission's executive director.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>ALBANY: STATE REVENUE UP BY $400 MILLION  The state took in just under $400 million more in revenues during the first six months of the current fiscal year than its financial plan had anticipated, State Comptroller H. Carl McCall said yesterday. The bulk of the greater-than-expected revenues -- $299.5 million -- came through strong collections of the state's personal income tax, Mr. McCall said. Business tax collections also exceeded expectations by $84.6 million, and total spending by the state was $67.3 million lower than projected. During the period from April 1 to Sept. 30, the first half of the state's fiscal year, personal income tax withholding grew by 12.2 percent to $8.9 billion over the previous fiscal year.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: BLACK HISTORIC DISTRICT APPROVED  The City Council has given final approval to a new historic district in western Harlem, which will be known as the Hamilton Heights/Sugar Hill Historic District. The new district, approved by a unanimous vote Thursday, contains about 185 buildings from the north side of 145th Street to the south side of 149th Street, along jagged east-west borders from Convent to Edgecombe Avenues. It is part of a plan to designate an even larger swath of western Harlem up to 155th Street as a historic district, commemorating the social, cultural and architectural history of the neighborhood, which contains many turn-of-the-century row houses.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: DEVELOPMENT OF BROOKLYN WATERFRONT  In a bid to help increase freight-handling business on long-dormant sections of Brooklyn's waterfront, the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey is holding a forum today on how to expand the use of rail cars that would be carried on barges from the New Jersey docks to Brooklyn. The forum, to be held at the World Trade Center, will also look at how to expand use of other underused freight routes that come into the borough from the north and east. Chris Ward, chief of strategic planning for the authority, said establishing that there is a demand for such freight operations -- which would not worsen truck traffic on narrow streets -- would help spur development on Brooklyn's waterfront.  Ronald Smothers (NYT)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>WATERBURY: JURY MISTAKEN IN MURDER TRIAL  An apparent mistake on a jury form yesterday resulted in confusion over the sentence to be given to a man convicted of killing his girlfriend's 2-year-old daughter. The jury sent in a form that would have required a judge to sentence the defendant, Ivo Colon, to life in prison. But jurors said they meant to recommend a death sentence for Mr. Colon. Defense lawyers argued that the original form, in which jurors indicated that mitigating factors outweighed aggravating factors, was signed and valid. The trial judge ordered more testimony.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>SHELTON: SCATTERED PUMPKIN SHORTAGES  The cool, wet weather last summer has led to a pumpkin shortage in some parts of southwestern Connecticut. Last year, the pumpkin crop throughout New England suffered because of hot, dry conditions, said Hugh Wiberg, the president of the New England Pumpkin Growers Association. But this year, the southwestern corner of Connecticut got more rain than farmers needed, he said. Farther north, growing conditions were better.</p>
        <p>David M. Herszenhorn (NYT)</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
        <p>Today</p>
        <p>HADDAM POWER PLANT HEARING  The Nuclear Regulatory Commission plans to hear public testimony on plans to clean up and dismantle the closed Haddam Neck nuclear power plant. Haddam-Killingworth High School, 95 Little City Road, Higganum, Conn., 6 p.m. Information: (610) 337-5330.</p>
        <p>REVIEW OF BROOKLYN MUSEUM PROJECT  The Landmarks Preservation Commission is scheduled to review the Brooklyn Museum's $55 million plan to transform its entrance into a major civic plaza. It will also consider the proposed demolition of ''The Wall,'' a 1973 sculptural relief in SoHo that artists seek to preserve. Public hearing room, 100 Old Slip, Manhattan, 9 a.m. Information: (212) 487-6782.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
