<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hezbollah on the Kidnapping: It's a Cloak-and-Dagger Tale</title>
    <meta content="Y17LEB$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/world/17LEBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHOSE HOLY LAND? LEBANON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beirut (Lebanon)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hezbollah</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mossad (Israeli Secret Service)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kifner, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nasrallah, Hassan (Sheik)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tannenbaum, Elhanan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon/Beirut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DD163EF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hezbollah on the Kidnapping: It's a Cloak-and-Dagger Tale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kifner, John</byline>
      <dateline>BEIRUT, Lebanon, Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sheik Hassan Nasrallah, leader of Hezbollah, asserts that Israeli taken captive by group was spy who was lured to Beirut and captured in elaborate cloak-and-dagger operation; identifies him as Israeli colonel working with Mossad, Israeli secret service, who flew to Beirut on forged passport pretending to be operative of unidentified foreign intelligence service in belief that he would meet with top Hezbollah official; Israel identifies missing citizen as Elhanan Tannenbaum, who it says was businessman working in Europe; says he is lieutenant colonel in air force reserve who worked for consulting firm linked to two of Israel's arms companies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hezbollah's leader asserted today that an Israeli taken captive by the group was a spy who had been lured to Beirut and captured in an elaborate cloak-and-dagger operation.</p>
        <p>Sheik Hassan Nasrallah, the Hezbollah leader, said an Israeli colonel working with the Mossad, the Israeli secret service, had been betrayed by a Lebanese double agent in Europe. As a result, Sheik Nasrallah said, the Israeli flew here on a forged passport pretending to be an operative of an unidentified foreign intelligence service in the belief that he would meet with a top Hezbollah official.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hezbollah's leader asserted today that an Israeli taken captive by the group was a spy who had been lured to Beirut and captured in an elaborate cloak-and-dagger operation.</p>
        <p>Sheik Hassan Nasrallah, the Hezbollah leader, said an Israeli colonel working with the Mossad, the Israeli secret service, had been betrayed by a Lebanese double agent in Europe. As a result, Sheik Nasrallah said, the Israeli flew here on a forged passport pretending to be an operative of an unidentified foreign intelligence service in the belief that he would meet with a top Hezbollah official.</p>
        <p>''Under security surveillance, with a smooth plan, we lured him to Lebanon and he walked in on his own feet,'' a smiling Sheik Nasrallah said today at a news conference, making a walking motion with two fingers of his right hand.</p>
        <p>Hezbollah, a Lebanese militia of Shiite Muslims, announced on Sunday that it had captured an Israeli operative. Israel identified its missing citizen as Elhanan Tannenbaum, who it said was a businessman working in Europe.</p>
        <p>He was later identifed in Israel as a 54-year-old lieutenant colonel in the air force reserve who worked for a consulting firm linked to two of Israel's arms companies. They are Tadrian, which manufacures tactical communications systems used by a number of armies, and the state-owned Rafael, which specializes in missiles as well as communications.</p>
        <p>The Israeli Supreme Court has since imposed a highly unusual ban on publishing information about the affair in response to the Shin Bet, another Israeli secret service, which contended that information in the press could endanger the lives of many other Israelis. The missing man's family was forbidden to talk to reporters.</p>
        <p>Hezbollah's announcement that it had captured the Israeli, issued on Sunday at a conference of Arab and Islamic nationalists, appeared to be another coup for the Shiite guerrillas, who are seeking to encourage the Palestinian uprising against Israel.</p>
        <p>A week ago Hezbollah abducted three Israeli Army sergeants along the border. And while Hezbollah, whose name means the Party of God, has long sought to free 19 Lebanese held in Israeli prisons, Sheik Nasrallah appeared to up the ante today.</p>
        <p>Any information on the three sergeants, he said, would require a prisoner exchange -- and Hezbollah now is pressing for the release of all Lebanese and Palestinian prisoners.</p>
        <p>According to Sheik Nasrallah's version of events, the Israeli colonel met with a Lebanese contact in Europe. Claiming to be an intelligence agent for another country, he began asking questions about Hezbollah. The Lebanese then informed Hezbollah security officials here.</p>
        <p>''After a period of continuous surveillance, the resistance found out the truth, because of the questions he asked and the information he was seeking,'' Sheik Nasrallah said. ''We wanted to establish trust between him and the intermediary, so we provided him with information about Hezbollah that would not hurt the resistance.''</p>
        <p>Enticed by that information, the Israeli then pressed his Lebanese go-between to set up a meeting with a ranking Hezbollah official outside Lebanon in a nearby European country, Sheik Nasrallah said.</p>
        <p>''We refused, and threatened to cut the relationship through the intermediary,'' the sheik said, ''but at the same time we kept providing him with security information.''</p>
        <p>Thus intrigued, according to this version, the Israeli was finally persuaded to fly to Beirut. ''After several tries, we were able to convince this foreign intelligence agent to come to Lebanon,'' the sheik said. ''He was convinced because he was supposedly not Israeli, so there was no problem in coming to Lebanon.</p>
        <p>''And in fact, he came to Lebanon from Brussels. He came in legally to Lebanon holding a foreign passport. We discovered afterward and based on his confession, that this passport was forged.''</p>
        <p>''We were convinced and we made sure he was a colonel in the Israeli military and he was working on the behalf of Mossad, after several interrogations and procedures,'' the sheik said. ''So we arrested and imprisoned him in Lebanon.''</p>
        <p>The news conference was conducted in Arabic, and at that point in the sheik's account, a number of the Lebanese journalists burst into applause.</p>
        <p>''So it is not a kidnapping from any country in this world,'' Sheik Nasrallah said. ''For a long time he has been trying to infiltrate Hezbollah at the highest levels. When he is in Lebanon, on our land, a colonel in the Israeli military, and we are sure of this, it is our right as the resistance to arrest him -- the end.''</p>
        <p>Sheik Nasrallah said that the capture of the Israeli had been the ''sole responsibility'' of Hezbollah and that neither Iran, which has close ties to Hezbollah, nor Syria, which dominates Lebanon, was involved.</p>
        <p>He said the timing of the announcement was intended ''to give moral support to the Palestinians, cause confusion to the Israelis and assurance to the detainees.''</p>
        <p>WHOSE HOLY LAND? LEBANON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
