<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Meola, Almost a Jet, Now an M.L.S. Star</title>
    <meta content="17SOCC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/sports/17SOCCER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kansas City Wizards</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E3DB163EF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Meola, Almost a Jet, Now an M.L.S. Star</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Soccer Notebook column discusses Kansas City Wizards winning Major League Soccer championship (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tony Meola once tried out as a place-kicker for the Jets, but the gods of American football probably could not abide the ponytail he audaciously wore at the time. So Meola, a native of Kearny, N.J., tucked the oval pigskin back into the closet and again grabbed the round football. The Kansas City Wizards, the new Major League Soccer champions, are glad he did.</p>
        <p>Meola was spectacular in goal on Sunday when he stopped 22 shots, several in the game's final minutes, to lead the Wizards to a 1-0 victory over Chicago in the M.L.S. Cup in Washington. Meola was selected the game's most valuable player. The championship capped Meola's long road back from injuries and could ultimately lead to his reclaiming the starting spot in goal for the United States national team as it tries to qualify for the 2002 World Cup. (He played at the University of Virginia for the current national team coach, Bruce Arena.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tony Meola once tried out as a place-kicker for the Jets, but the gods of American football probably could not abide the ponytail he audaciously wore at the time. So Meola, a native of Kearny, N.J., tucked the oval pigskin back into the closet and again grabbed the round football. The Kansas City Wizards, the new Major League Soccer champions, are glad he did.</p>
        <p>Meola was spectacular in goal on Sunday when he stopped 22 shots, several in the game's final minutes, to lead the Wizards to a 1-0 victory over Chicago in the M.L.S. Cup in Washington. Meola was selected the game's most valuable player. The championship capped Meola's long road back from injuries and could ultimately lead to his reclaiming the starting spot in goal for the United States national team as it tries to qualify for the 2002 World Cup. (He played at the University of Virginia for the current national team coach, Bruce Arena.)</p>
        <p>After missing five months in 1999 because of a series of knee injuries, Meola set a regular-season league record for shutouts (16) and had a 681-minute scoreless streak that stretched over eight games. For his play during the regular season, Meola was named the league's M.V.P., the goalkeeper of the year and the comeback player of the year.</p>
        <p>After the final, three Kansas City players -- Miklos Molnar (the goal scorer), Mo Johnston and Alex Bunbury -- announced their retirements.</p>
        <p>With the victory, Kansas City earned the right to represent the United States in the Concacaf club championship in August.</p>
        <p>Lamar Hunt, the Wizards' owner and operator and a longtime supporter of soccer in the United States (he also owned the Dallas franchise in the defunct North American Soccer League), attended the match. He also is the owner of the Kansas City Chiefs of the National Football League and missed a Chiefs game on Sunday for only the 13th time in the 41 years he has owned the team.</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer announced its All-Star team for the 2000 season: forwards Mamadou Diallo (Tampa Bay) and Clint Mathis (MetroStars); midfielders Hristo Stoitchkov (Chicago), Peter Nowak (Chicago), Chris Armas (Chicago), Steve Ralston (Tampa Bay) and Carlos Valderrama (Tampa Bay); defenders Peter Vermes (Kansas City), Robin Fraser (Los Angeles) and Greg Vanney (Los Angeles); and goalkeeper Tony Meola (Kansas City).</p>
        <p>England</p>
        <p>While Manchester United and Arsenal again battle for supremacy in the English Premier League, the spotlight has momentarily shifted to the First Division, where Fulham is closing in on the league record of 14 consecutive victories to start a season after Sunday's 2-1 victory over Blackburn Rovers.</p>
        <p>Fulham is owned by the Egyptian businessman Mohamed al-Fayed, the owner of Harrods department store in London. And he is the father of Dodi al-Fayed, who died with Diana, Princess of Wales, in an automobile accident in Paris in 1997.</p>
        <p>The goal of getting Fulham promoted to the Premier League has obsessed Fayed. The club, which makes its home at Craven Cottage on the banks of the Thames River, was mired in the nether reaches of English soccer when he bought the team in 1997.</p>
        <p>Fulham now sits atop the First Division with a perfect record after 10 matches for 30 points. The club has outscored the opposition by a staggering margin, 28-5, under the direction of the former French international player Jean Tigana. The relationship between Fayed and Tigana took a step into a commercial realm this month when Harrods Food Hall introduced a new white wine that bears Tigana's name -- Domaine La Dona Tigana. It is produced on Tigana's estate in France.</p>
        <p>The wine, like the team Fayed has assembled, is hardly plonk. Tigana's most important signing was the French striker Louis Saha from Metz, along with the additions of John Collins (Everton) and Fabrice Fernandes (on loan from Rennes). The American international midfielder Eddie Lewis (who has one year remaining on his contract) has seen his playing time gradually diminish under Tigana. In Sunday's match, Lewis suffered the indignity of entering the game with only 30 seconds left.</p>
        <p>Corner Kicks</p>
        <p>The Liberian striker George Weah was released yesterday by Manchester City of the English Premier League. Weah was unsuccessful so far this season in landing a steady spot on the first team and had scored four goals in nine league and cup matches so far this season. He did not play this past weekend in City's 2-0 home victory against Bradford. ... The Liverpool striker Michael Owen was taken to a hospital on Sunday after sustaining a head injury in a collision with Derby County's Chris Riggot. Owens was carried off the field, bleeding from a head wound. ... With one game left in the Norwegian summer season, Rosenborg Trondheim clinched a record ninth straight title. Rosenborg, which has sent several of its top players to other European leagues (particularly the English Premier League), continues play tomorrow in the European Champions League with a match against Helsingborg. ... There were no games this past weekend in Greece after that country's national federation declared the domestic game totally rotten and imposed a two-week suspension of league play. The decision to suspend play came after last week's 2-0 loss to lowly Albania in a World Cup qualifying match. ... Glenn Hoddle, the former coach of the English national team, said this past weekend that England should forget about qualifying for the 2002 World Cup and instead concentrate on qualifying for the 2004 European Championships. England is without a full-time coach since Kevin Keegan resigned after a 1-0 defeat to Germany earlier this month.</p>
        <p>JACK BELL</p>
        <p>SOCCER: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
