<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Front Row</title>
    <meta content="17FRON$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/living/17FRON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellafante, Ginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Jeremy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7DC1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Front Row</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ginia Bellafante</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Front Page column discusses fashions from designer Jeremy Scott as shown in Paris; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jeremy Scott's Marine Period</p>
        <p>In fashion, where the standards for what's brilliant or ironic are considerably lower than in the rest of the world, Jeremy Scott, the Midwesterner based in Paris, passes for a very clever young man. Last season he sent brown sweatshirts down the runway appliqued with an image of the Eiffel Tower and the word ''Paris,'' and the audience shouted ''Genius!'' at his simplistic mockery of kitsch. He acts as if he were the first person to ridicule low-rent culture, and apparently there are enough people at his shows who have never seen ''The Simpsons'' to remain amused.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jeremy Scott's Marine Period</p>
        <p>In fashion, where the standards for what's brilliant or ironic are considerably lower than in the rest of the world, Jeremy Scott, the Midwesterner based in Paris, passes for a very clever young man. Last season he sent brown sweatshirts down the runway appliqued with an image of the Eiffel Tower and the word ''Paris,'' and the audience shouted ''Genius!'' at his simplistic mockery of kitsch. He acts as if he were the first person to ridicule low-rent culture, and apparently there are enough people at his shows who have never seen ''The Simpsons'' to remain amused.</p>
        <p>At his show on Friday night, which closed the spring 2001 collections here, he was up to some of the same tricks. He presented gaucho pants, shorts and jackets in a print of retro fashion illustrations, which seemed to belong in the window of a Junior Miss store, circa 1981. Sadly, that was surely his intent. At one point, Mr. Scott, who had some Phil Collins playing at his show, sent a jersey wrap dress down the runway, prompting the designer who invented it, Diane Von Furstenberg, to nudge a neighbor seated near her in the front row and point. If Mr. Scott had a real sense of humor, he would have printed the dress with Ms. Von Furstenberg's curly-haired image.</p>
        <p>At any rate, Mr. Scott pulled off a grand finale to an otherwise dull affair. It consisted of a series of one-piece bathing suits, none engineered for the high dive. Some had pillowed armbands, and they grew progressively more elaborate until they started coming out with expandable scallop shells that rose at least a foot above the models' heads. For a minute or two, Mr. Scott, whose clothes aren't available much beyond the world of Colette, the supertrendy boutique on the Rue St.-Honore here, offered what could really be construed as entertainment.</p>
        <p>Jewelry at $600 and Up</p>
        <p>Victoire de Castellane could be found one afternoon last week behind her desk off the ultrabourgeois Avenue Montaigne, wearing an outfit that appeared indigenous to a street more typical of Pigalle. Ms. de Castellane designs fine jewelry for the house of Christian Dior, one of the very few luxury fashion empires to take on the Bulgaris and Cartiers of the world. While a tight skirt, a low-cut shirt and a push-up bra merit hardly a second glance in the fashion world, Ms. de Castellane had added to that package a white French maid's apron and black stiletto lace-up boots.</p>
        <p>Ms. de Castellane, who used to design costume jewelry for Chanel (she was a muse to Karl Lagerfeld there), joined Dior two years ago to design jewelry priced from $600 to $600,000. Dior sells it at a boutique in Paris and will open a second store next Monday on East 57th Street in New York.</p>
        <p>''A lot of girls can now buy themselves jewelry,'' Ms. de Castellane said in heavily accented English. ''You are not waiting for your husband to buy it.'' Her generally baroque pieces employ colorful stones like pink diamonds and large sapphires and amethysts. A number of designs include garden motifs inspired by fruit once found in Mr. Dior's garden when he was alive.</p>
        <p>''I like to be very close to nature,'' Ms. de Castellane said.</p>
        <p>Footwear by a Man in Sharp Boots</p>
        <p>''There are 1,000 ways to do a pointy toe,'' said Francesco Russo, a footwear designer who just moved here from Milan to take a position in which he will no doubt be closely watched: designing shoes at Yves Saint Laurent under its new creative director, Tom Ford. ''For me, the feet are the sexiest part of the person.''</p>
        <p>One recent evening at a bar near the Place Vendome, Mr. Russo, whose move was so sudden he is still without a place to live, had on a pair of flat black ankle boots with a point sharp enough for roasting a marshmallow. The boots were from Miu Miu, where Mr. Russo worked designing men's and women's shoes after a stint designing accessories at Costume National.</p>
        <p>With him was his friend Andrea Pompilio, another new arrival here, who has been hired as part of a four-member team to design men's wear for Saint Laurent. Mr. Pompilio, who was on the men's wear design team at Prada, wore similarly pointy boots he had bought in London.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russo wouldn't divulge much about what the Saint Laurent shoe line will look like now that it is under his eye, but he was happy to philosophize about shoemaking in general. Almost all his energy goes into thinking about the toe and the sexy scoop of the instep, he said.</p>
        <p>''Shoes are like tables,'' he added. ''If they don't have proportion, they don't work.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
