<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nassau Plan To Raise Taxes By 10 to 20%</title>
    <meta content="17NASS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/nyregion/17NASS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239508"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baker, Al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Property Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E6D61F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nassau Plan To Raise Taxes By 10 to 20%</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AL BAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Baker, Al</byline>
      <dateline>GARDEN CITY, N.Y., Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nassau County, NY, Democrats, trying to prevent state takeover of county's finances, say that they will seek double-digit percentage increase in county portion of property tax rate next year and reject costly raises for county police officers and detectives (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trying to prevent a state takeover of Nassau County's finances, the Democrats who control the County Legislature said today that they would seek a double-digit percentage increase in the county portion of the property tax rate next year and reject costly raises for county police officers and detectives.</p>
        <p>Aides to Judith A. Jacobs, the Democrat who is the Legislature's presiding officer, said the tax increase would be 10 to 20 percent, raising property taxes an average of $105 to $200 per household. They said their 2001 budget would also scuttle a proposal by Thomas S. Gulotta, the Republican county executive, to lay off more than 300 unionized county workers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trying to prevent a state takeover of Nassau County's finances, the Democrats who control the County Legislature said today that they would seek a double-digit percentage increase in the county portion of the property tax rate next year and reject costly raises for county police officers and detectives.</p>
        <p>Aides to Judith A. Jacobs, the Democrat who is the Legislature's presiding officer, said the tax increase would be 10 to 20 percent, raising property taxes an average of $105 to $200 per household. They said their 2001 budget would also scuttle a proposal by Thomas S. Gulotta, the Republican county executive, to lay off more than 300 unionized county workers.</p>
        <p>The Democrats, who say they will pass a 2001 budget on Thursday, submitted a draft of the plan today to the Nassau Interim Finance Authority, the state board overseeing the county's efforts to pull out of its financial tailspin. And while they would not release the draft, they revealed some of its outlines.</p>
        <p>Aides to Ms. Jacobs said the tax increase proposed by Democrats did not reach 20 percent, but was well above 10 percent. Others close to the talks said the figure was above 15 percent. The aides also said the Democrats would reject tentative contracts, which Mr. Gulotta had negotiated with two police unions, that included cumulative 22 percent raises over the next five years.</p>
        <p>''With the Gulotta budgets over the years, the question always turned out to be how far short of the mark his deficit reduction proposals would fall,'' said Chuck Cutolo, counsel to the Democratic majority. ''With the budget we will now be proposing, if there are any surprises, they will likely end up being how much the surplus will be.''</p>
        <p>But many details remain sketchy and serious questions persist. The county's 2001 budget and financial plans for the following three years have to pass muster with the state oversight board, or the board could seize day-to-day fiscal powers from elected officials. And the plan has to win support from Republicans -- from Mr. Gulotta or, if he vetoes any part of the budget, from the Republicans in the Legislature, whose votes will be needed to override the veto. (An override requires 13 of 19 votes.)</p>
        <p>The adopted county budget must plug a deficit of roughly $143 million next year and a shortfall of nearly $380 million projected by 2004. And with elections fast approaching for state lawmakers, chances seemed slim today that Republican legislators, who are outnumbered 10 to 9, would join their political opponents and support a double-digit tax rise.</p>
        <p>''We are at zero,'' Robert W. Lazaro, a spokesman for Peter J. Schmitt, the Republican legislative minority leader, said of any potential agreement to raise property taxes. ''I am not going to comment on the Democrats' plan until we have seen it, touched it, sniffed it, tasted it and had a chance to digest it.''</p>
        <p>The Democrats' draft budget plans were hand-delivered to the state board today. Darren S. Bloch, chief of staff to Ms. Jacobs, said the Democrats would hear the board's reaction before committing to a final budget. Ms. Jacobs is set to brief Mr. Gulotta and Mr. Schmitt on Tuesday, Mr. Bloch said.</p>
        <p>When Gov. George E. Pataki offered a state bailout in May -- the county accepted the deal of $100 million in aid and a restructuring of the county's debt load -- he said a fiscal fix could be accomplished without a tax increase. Recently, a member of the state board, Richard M. Kessel,  said that he and other authority members felt that property tax increases should be a last resort for the otherwise wealthy county -- after all possible spending cuts and consolidations were considered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulotta said today through a spokeswoman that he had not seen the Democrats' plan, but that ''our efforts must be directed toward cutting government spending, not increasing taxes.''</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Gulotta submitted his proposed budget on Sept. 15, the Democratic and Republican lawmakers have laced into it, saying it is short on detail. The state board also rejected it for relying on $81.7 million worth of spending cuts or new revenues that, for one reason or another, may not materialize next year, and for being short on specifics for spending cuts in future years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulotta proposed a tax increase of nearly 4 percent next year that would have added $33 on average to a household's county tax bill; county property taxes make up roughly 19 percent of residents' overall property-tax bills. He also included pay increases for county police officers and detectives as part of  tentative contracts that he said would save the county tens of millions of dollars through givebacks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloch, the Democrats' chief of staff, said the proposed pacts with the Police Benevolent Association and the Detectives Association Inc. were seen as unfair and politically unfeasible. ''Right now we are going to assume a freeze in salaries until a true savings is realized that would offset any salary increases,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Still, Gary DelaRaba, the president of the 2,100-member P.B.A., criticized the decision to reject the proposed deals and said it would force him back into negotiations with Mr. Gulotta. ''They are being unrealistic, so I would bet their budget would reflect the same unrealistic projections,'' Mr. DelaRaba said of the Democrats' plans, which he had not yet seen. ''You are not going to keep blaming this entire crisis on the cops and keep beating their morale into the ground.''</p>
        <p>In his budget, Mr. Gulotta called for laying off more than 300 unionized county workers to save $11 million next year. But with roughly 800 county workers leaving because of early retirement or severance incentives -- including about 200 police officers -- Ms. Jacobs said further work force reductions would severely impair the county's ability to provide needed services, like plowing the streets, mowing lawns or keeping buildings in good repair.</p>
        <p>But the Democrats left intact Mr. Gulotta's proposal to lay off roughly 70 nonunion workers, and even added another 30 positions, Mr. Bloch said.</p>
        <p>Anthony P. Giustino, the president of Local 830 of the Civil Service Employees Association, which has 11,000 members, including 6,000 county employees, said he had been urging leaders in each party to avoid layoffs of unionized workers.</p>
        <p>''Until Thursday, I have a wait-and-see attitude,'' he said. ''I am keeping my fingers crossed and saying my prayers.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
