<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheney Presses Case for Shoring Up Military</title>
    <meta content="Y17CHE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/politics/17CHEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICAN RUNNING MATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EEDF163EF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheney Presses Case for Shoring Up Military</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>SPRINGFIELD, Mo., Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican Vice Presidential candidate Dick Cheney campaigns in Missouri, where he again presses case today for maintaining strong military even in times of peace; invokes some current and past crises to make point (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Cheney continued to press his case today for maintaining a strong military even in times of peace, invoking not only last week's attack on the destroyer Cole but also the hostage crisis in Iran and President Jimmy Carter's ill-fated effort to rescue the 52 American captives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential nominee, has been campaigning hard on the issue of military readiness. Today he drew an analogy to the 1980 presidential election, when, against a backdrop of national anguish over the fate of the American hostages being held in Teheran and the seeming inability of the American military to do anything about it, Ronald Reagan made calls for a strong Pentagon a centerpiece of his campaign against the incumbent, Mr. Carter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Cheney continued to press his case today for maintaining a strong military even in times of peace, invoking not only last week's attack on the destroyer Cole but also the hostage crisis in Iran and President Jimmy Carter's ill-fated effort to rescue the 52 American captives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential nominee, has been campaigning hard on the issue of military readiness. Today he drew an analogy to the 1980 presidential election, when, against a backdrop of national anguish over the fate of the American hostages being held in Teheran and the seeming inability of the American military to do anything about it, Ronald Reagan made calls for a strong Pentagon a centerpiece of his campaign against the incumbent, Mr. Carter.</p>
        <p>''Our opponents in this campaign, Al Gore and Joe Lieberman, have sometimes argued when I raise issues about the status of the U.S. military today, they sometimes argue that you shouldn't talk about it, that somehow it's unpatriotic to have this conversation,'' Mr. Cheney, a former defense secretary, told a rally at Evangel University here. ''Well, I think they're dead wrong. I can't think of a more important time to have this conversation.''</p>
        <p>In recent days, both campaigns have cautiously sought to use the attack on the Cole and the crisis in the Middle East to support their positions. The Bush campaign has seen it as a validation of its calls for a stronger military and more domestic oil production, while the Gore campaign has sought to remind voters that Vice President Al Gore has far more foreign policy experience than Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>Today, though, Mr. Cheney reached back two decades to find another example.</p>
        <p>''I remember another presidential campaign 20 years ago, when a man named Ronald Reagan was running for president,'' Mr. Cheney said. ''And we had a little issue of capabilities and the status of the U.S. military in that year. We had a large number of Americans being held hostage in our embassy in Teheran.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney then recounted the failed military effort to rescue the 52 hostages, which ended in disaster when a helicopter collided with a C-130 transport plane at the staging area for the mission in the Iranian desert about 200 miles southwest of Teheran; eight servicemen died.</p>
        <p>''And Ronald Reagan went around the country and campaigned and talked about the fact that the U.S. military had fallen on hard times. That it wasn't receiving the kind of support that it needed. And he was right, absolutely dead on.''</p>
        <p>''Ultimately, of course, the American people voted, they elected him president of the United States, and the day he was sworn in as president, the hostages were released,'' Mr. Cheney said.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign accused the Bush campaign today of trying to score political points off a crisis.</p>
        <p>''The Bush campaign's attempt to take advantage of the Middle East situation for Bush's own selfish political benefit will be rejected by the American people,'' said Kym Spell, a Gore campaign spokeswoman .</p>
        <p>Juleanna Glover Weiss, a spokeswoman for Mr. Cheney, responded: ''For the Gore campaign to purposefully misunderstand Cheney's point that our troops don't have what they need is typical of the dissembling and distortions that the American people have come to expect from Al Gore.''</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign noted that Mr. Gorewas proposing to spend more than twice as much money on national defense as the Bush campaign; Ms. Glover Weiss said she thought the Gore campaign's numbers were ''suspect.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE REPUBLICAN RUNNING MATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
