<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pulse, Dreams And Reserve Of the East</title>
    <meta content="17CARN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/arts/17CARN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Composers Orchestra</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffiths, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davies, Dennis Russell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oppens, Ursula</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E3DD1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pulse, Dreams And Reserve Of the East</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL GRIFFITHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Griffiths, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Griffiths reviews concert of Asian-American composers by American Composers Orchestra, conducted by Dennis Russell Davies, at Carnegie Hall; photo of pianist Ursula Oppens (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By presenting in succession three works by Asian-American composers, ''Pacifica,'' a concert by the American Composers Orchestra conducted by Dennis Russell Davies at Carnegie Hall on Sunday, invited its enthusiastic audience to listen for traces of ethnic origin. And the evidence came in plenty: in modal flavors, most of all, but also in rushing rhythms on percussion and a precise realization of form.</p>
        <p>Equally abundant, though, were the differences. The Cambodia of Chinary Ung's ''Inner Voices'' was all gently rolling landscape; the Vietnam of P. Q. Phan's ''When the Worlds Mixed and Times Merged'' all traffic, bright lights and noise on city streets. There was, too, a cautionary note sounded after the intermission by Lou Harrison's Piano Concerto, which, though the work of an American who has spent almost his whole life on the West Coast, was the most Asian-sounding piece on the entire program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By presenting in succession three works by Asian-American composers, ''Pacifica,'' a concert by the American Composers Orchestra conducted by Dennis Russell Davies at Carnegie Hall on Sunday, invited its enthusiastic audience to listen for traces of ethnic origin. And the evidence came in plenty: in modal flavors, most of all, but also in rushing rhythms on percussion and a precise realization of form.</p>
        <p>Equally abundant, though, were the differences. The Cambodia of Chinary Ung's ''Inner Voices'' was all gently rolling landscape; the Vietnam of P. Q. Phan's ''When the Worlds Mixed and Times Merged'' all traffic, bright lights and noise on city streets. There was, too, a cautionary note sounded after the intermission by Lou Harrison's Piano Concerto, which, though the work of an American who has spent almost his whole life on the West Coast, was the most Asian-sounding piece on the entire program.</p>
        <p>It stood apart in its affection for its source material. Affection is different from the high-spirited excitement of Hong-Kong-born Melissa Hui's ''Common Ground,'' the concert's punchy, pulse-driven overture, moving from accelerations on cymbals through diverse, quick little patterns to end with a spray of glitter at the top of the piano. Affection is different, too, from the sophisticated reverie of Mr. Ung's music or the mania of Mr. Phan's. Affection does, though, take its time, and there was some relief in finding the four movements of Mr. Harrison's concerto getting progressively shorter.</p>
        <p>The soloist, Ursula Oppens, always such an engaging player, responded to the mood by being eager and lustrous, enjoying the opportunities of an unusual tuning to bring out the piano's resonances, and carrying off with complete aplomb the zoom from Brahms's D minor Piano Concerto to Chinese-style melody right at the start. The orchestra did not sound thoroughly prepared, but there were charming moments. James Preiss kept his cool on drum kit in the second and fourth movements, rattling off contrary rhythms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Phan's piece, commissioned for the concert, was a noisy, seething mass almost from beginning to end. Occasionally something would emerge: an infantile trumpet march, a hoedown and finally some energetic Bernstein-type stuff on brass and percussion. But the careering of miscellaneous events and the lack of care were as disappointing here as in the mixed quartet by this composer that was included in a related and generally regrettable chamber concert at the Japan Society on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
