<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-U.S. Envoy Testifies Against Salvadorans in 4 Women's Deaths</title>
    <meta content="Y17SAL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/world/17SALV.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239541"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">El Salvador</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Robert E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garcia, Jose Guillermo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vides Casanova, Carlos Eugenio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarke, Maura</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kazel, Dorothy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, Ita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donovan, Jean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/El Salvador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/El Salvador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6DD163EF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-U.S. Envoy Testifies Against Salvadorans in 4 Women's Deaths</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WEST PALM BEACH, Fla., Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert E White, former US ambassador to El Salvador, testifies in suit, Federal District Court, West Palm Beach, against two retired Salvadoran military officials living in Florida; says he believes men helped cover up killings of four American churchwomen in 1980; says former defense minister Gen Jose Guillermo Garcia and former chief of national guard Carlos Eugenio Vides Casanova did not properly investigate slayings and contributed to government cover-up (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former United States ambassador to El Salvador, testifying today in a suit against two retired Salvadoran military officials who are living in Florida, said he believed that the men helped cover up the kllings of four American churchwomen in El Salvador 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>Robert E. White, the envoy in 1980, when the women were killed, said the defendants did not properly investigate the slayings and contributed to a government cover-up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former United States ambassador to El Salvador, testifying today in a suit against two retired Salvadoran military officials who are living in Florida, said he believed that the men helped cover up the kllings of four American churchwomen in El Salvador 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>Robert E. White, the envoy in 1980, when the women were killed, said the defendants did not properly investigate the slayings and contributed to a government cover-up.</p>
        <p>The trial of Gen. Jose Guillermo Garcia, who was defense minister, and Carlos Eugenio Vides Casanova, who was a colonel and a former director of the National Guard, began here in federal district court last week. Lawyers for the victims' families said they were beginning a long-awaited ''quest for the truth.''</p>
        <p>The trial is generally expected to continue for two more weeks before Judge Daniel T. K. Hurley.</p>
        <p>The killings caused an international controversy over responsibility in the case. The bodies of three nuns -- Maura Clarke, Dorothy Kazel and Ita C. Ford -- and a lay worker, Jean Donovan, were found beaten, raped and bullet ridden, buried in a ditch along a country road.</p>
        <p>''The Salvadoran military killed these women,'' Mr. White told the court today. ''We knew pretty well what had happened. We knew from the first day.''</p>
        <p>Some family members dabbed their eyes. They filed their wrongful-death suit under the federal Torture Victim Protection Act against Mr. Garcia, 67, and Mr. Vides Casanova, 62, last year after having learned that the two had been living in Florida since 1989. The families are seeking unspecified damages.</p>
        <p>In his opening statement, a lawyer for the plaintiffs, Robert Montgomery, told the 10-member jury that Mr. Garcia and Mr. Vides Casanova knew of civilian killings by their soldiers, failed to end the bloodshed and should be held responsible for the deaths.</p>
        <p>''They were murdered and raped by national guardsman under the command responsibility of these persons here,'' Mr. Montgomery said. ''Persons who had the ability to stop it didn't do so.''</p>
        <p>The lawyer for the former generals, Kurt Klaus Jr., put off his statement until after the family had completed its side of the case. Mr. Garcia and Mr. Vides Casanova have denied any involvement in the killings or a possible cover-up.</p>
        <p>But a United Nations report in 1993 found that Mr. Vides Casanova had been involved in covering up the killings and that Mr. Garcia had failed to investigate them. In 1984, four members of the National Guard who killed the women and the men's immediate superior were convicted of the murders and sentenced to 30 years in prison. In 1998, however, the four enlisted men ended their silence and said they had been acting on their superiors' orders.</p>
        <p>At the start of his testimony, Mr. White testified that the killings were part of a pattern in El Salvador and that its military leaders at the time did nothing to end it. ''I became convinced that the minister of defense had no intention of rooting out of the military those men who were notorious, even in El Salvador, for savagery,'' Mr. White said.</p>
        <p>As Mr. White read from declassified cables written to the Secretary of State in 1980 that were used as evidence, he said Mr. Garcia admitted to him and another American official in March 1980 that ''he knew security forces were participating in death squads.''</p>
        <p>Today, when Mr. Klaus suggested in cross-examination that the American government might bear partial blame for the killings, Mr. White defended the role of the United States. ''We worked very hard,'' he said. ''It was the Salvadorans on vacation. They're the ones with the obligation to solve their crime.''</p>
        <p>The women were slain, Mr. Montgomery told the court last week, at a time the Salvadoran security forces and death squads were involved in a long-running campaign of torture and killings against sympathizers of left-wing guerrilla groups. The victims included religious leaders like nuns, priests and an archbishop.</p>
        <p>Mr. Montgomery contended that allthough the military forces that held power insisted that they were putting down a Communist insurrection, they were actually trying to protect the economic power of the so-called 14 families that owned and effectively ran the country.</p>
        <p>The 12-year civil war began in 1979 and left more than 75,000 people dead.</p>
        <p>Some experts say they believe that the women were a target because the military worried that they were aiding peasants who did not support the government.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
