<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finally, Good News For Rutgers Squad</title>
    <meta content="PL030714" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PLUS: COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dicker, Ron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sherrod, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DB163EF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="437" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finally, Good News For Rutgers Squad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Sherrod, promising freshman guard for the Rutgers basketball team, is declared eligible (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Sherrod, a promising freshman guard for the Rutgers basketball team, was declared eligible just minutes before Coach Kevin Bannon took the dais yesterday at the Scarlet Knights' media day in Piscataway, N.J.</p>
        <p>It was a rare piece of good news for Rutgers since it ended last season with a 15-16 record. Dahntay Jones, the team's leading scorer, has transferred to Duke. Guard Luis Flores has transferred to Manhattan. Herve Lamizana, a 6-foot-10-inch forward from St. Patrick's in Elizabeth, N.J., did not qualify academically and will sit out the season. Eddie Starks, a former New York City prep star, was denied admission into school and is now enrolled at Iona. And Kaspars Cipruss, a Latvian who was expected to start for Rutgers, signed a contract with the Italian pro league after a letter-of-intent problem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Sherrod, a promising freshman guard for the Rutgers basketball team, was declared eligible just minutes before Coach Kevin Bannon took the dais yesterday at the Scarlet Knights' media day in Piscataway, N.J.</p>
        <p>It was a rare piece of good news for Rutgers since it ended last season with a 15-16 record. Dahntay Jones, the team's leading scorer, has transferred to Duke. Guard Luis Flores has transferred to Manhattan. Herve Lamizana, a 6-foot-10-inch forward from St. Patrick's in Elizabeth, N.J., did not qualify academically and will sit out the season. Eddie Starks, a former New York City prep star, was denied admission into school and is now enrolled at Iona. And Kaspars Cipruss, a Latvian who was expected to start for Rutgers, signed a contract with the Italian pro league after a letter-of-intent problem.</p>
        <p>No wonder Bannon told his team that it must overachieve.</p>
        <p>''We know we don't have the numbers that we all wish we had,'' said Bannon, who also had to replace three-fourths of his coaching staff, filling the remaining spot yesterday with the former Rutgers player Geoff Billet. ''We're certainly relying on the improvement of our four returning starters.''</p>
        <p>Bannon said guard Todd Billet (who averaged 12.8 points and 4.2 assists a game) is now the undisputed floor leader.</p>
        <p>Billet will be joined in the lineup by the swingman Jeff Greer (11.9 points), forward Rashod Kent (8.9 points, 6.9 rebounds), center Eugene Dabney (3.7 points, 3.3 rebounds) and perhaps Sherrod, from Paul Robeson High School in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>RON DICKER</p>
        <p>AL McGUIRE HONORED: Marquette University's new athletic facility will be named after the former men's basketball coach Al McGuire, university officials said.</p>
        <p>McGuire, who is ill with leukemia, said in a statement that he is honored and is looking forward to taking the first shot in the new building, which will house practice facilities for men's and women's basketball, an academic center for student-athletes and a Marquette athletic hall of fame.</p>
        <p>The 72-year-old McGuire became as famous off the court as on during his 13 years leading the team to 259 victories. His career culminated in 1977 when Marquette won the National Collegiate Athletic Association championship shortly after he announced his retirement.</p>
        <p>McGuire also led the Warriors to the 1970 National Invitation Tournament title.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>PLUS: COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
