<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Planning for Strategic Home Reserves</title>
    <meta content="Y17HOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/business/17HOME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating Oil</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Banerjee, Neela</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E1DC1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="498" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Planning for Strategic Home Reserves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEELA BANERJEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Banerjee, Neela</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Homeowners can take steps to prevent heating oil bills from rising drastically this winter (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cold weather may have already crept in, but homeowners still have time to take steps that could prevent heating oil bills from rising drastically this winter.</p>
        <p>Most homeowners usually buy their heating oil ahead of time, often in the summer or early fall, or they are on a monthly payment plan that keeps monthly bills steady, fuel dealers said. In any case, dealers recommend that homeowners avoid waiting until their tank runs down to buy heating oil, which leaves them extremely vulnerable to price spikes and possible shortages when the weather is particularly cold and demand particularly high.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cold weather may have already crept in, but homeowners still have time to take steps that could prevent heating oil bills from rising drastically this winter.</p>
        <p>Most homeowners usually buy their heating oil ahead of time, often in the summer or early fall, or they are on a monthly payment plan that keeps monthly bills steady, fuel dealers said. In any case, dealers recommend that homeowners avoid waiting until their tank runs down to buy heating oil, which leaves them extremely vulnerable to price spikes and possible shortages when the weather is particularly cold and demand particularly high.</p>
        <p>While the price of heating oil has been rising, many New York area dealers have capped prices to regular customers at about $1.50 a gallon. The retail price of heating oil, while lower nationally, averages about $1.65 in New York City. ''The safest thing you can do right now is get under a capped program with a supplier,'' said Jim Pierson, owner of the J. W. Pierson Company of East Orange, N.J.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pierson also urged consumers to check out their heating oil dealers carefully, since the industry is splintered into many small operations. During a cold snap last winter that drove prices up overnight, some companies reneged on their contracts because they had not hedged against price volatility.</p>
        <p>''Ask them if they can back up their commitment to capped prices and regular delivery with futures contracts for real barrels of heating oil,'' he said. ''Ask them how long they have been in business and check them out with the Better Business Bureau.''</p>
        <p>Recently, some homeowners have been tempted by offers of so-called home heating oil insurance offered by a heating oil dealer who promises a capped price for the fuel, if consumers pay a premium upfront. But industry experts point out that consumers can arrange capped prices without paying extra for the service. A recent heating oil insurance advertisement promised to cap prices at $1.39 a gallon for a one-time premium of $145. But if the premium is factored into the price of the fuel, consumers who need, say, 1,000 gallons in winter, would actually end up paying almost $1.54 a gallon.</p>
        <p>At home, consumers can turn down their thermostats. For every degree, homeowners can save about 3 percent on heating oil bills, Mr. Pierson said. Consumers can also get a heating system ''tune-up,'' in which a heating oil company technician sets the oil burner so that it functions at peak efficiency. Such a visit, which could save another 2 percent to 10 percent on heating bills, typically costs under $100.</p>
        <p>Over the long term, of course, homeowners can make sure they have storm windows, proper insulation and efficient oil burners.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
