<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Day for Families and Farrakhan in a Capital Gathering</title>
    <meta content="Y17MARC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/national/17MARC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nation of Islam</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farrakhan, Louis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2D81F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Day for Families and Farrakhan in a Capital Gathering</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tens of thousands of people heed call of Nation of Islam leader Louis Farrakhan and converge on national Mall in Washington, DC, in daylong commitment to renewing family solidarity as force in American life; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Heeding the call of Minister Louis Farrakhan, tens of thousands of people converged on the national Mall today in a daylong commitment to renewing family solidarity as a force in American life.</p>
        <p>''If all this is is a march for feeling good, then this is vanity,'' said Mr. Farrakhan who dominated the day with a two-hour speech, a mass renewal of wedding vows and a proposal to create an ''economic development bank'' primed by $100 contributions from families across the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Heeding the call of Minister Louis Farrakhan, tens of thousands of people converged on the national Mall today in a daylong commitment to renewing family solidarity as a force in American life.</p>
        <p>''If all this is is a march for feeling good, then this is vanity,'' said Mr. Farrakhan who dominated the day with a two-hour speech, a mass renewal of wedding vows and a proposal to create an ''economic development bank'' primed by $100 contributions from families across the nation.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Farrakhan, the leader of the Nation of Islam, extended an invitation to families of all ethnic and religious backgrounds, the vast majority of participants were African-Americans enjoying a sunny day given over to the happy display of thousands of family circles. Babies and youngsters slept, crawled or cried while their parents listened to dozens of speakers endorse a raft of causes, from ending the death penalty to granting amnesty to illegal immigrants.</p>
        <p>''This won't happen for another 20 years,'' said John Lone, a black father who watched the proceedings with his wife, Joanne, and their four children.</p>
        <p>''I want the kids to see black people coming together in a spirit of family and fun so they'll be able to pass it on to their kids,'' he said, emphasizing that he was less interested in the sometimes controversial views of Mr. Farrakhan, whom critics denounce as a race-baiter and anti-Semite.</p>
        <p>The day's proclaimed Million Family March fell well short of that total and clearly seemed less than half the estimated 400,000 people who attended Mr. Farrakhan's highly successful Million Man March five years ago. People tended to gather in clusters around separate giant television screens along the Mall rather than in a single flowing throng.</p>
        <p>''We're so spread out, we can't meet people from other places,'' said 27-year-old Deborah Kirk who drove from Charlotte, N.C., with her two children and husband. ''In family, you're supposed to be connected, but it's not happening here,'' she complained, saying that the 1997 Million Woman March was far more energized and interactive.</p>
        <p>Further down the Mall, Richard Oben, the 48-year-old director of facilities at The Washington Times, said that the day was well worth it for him, his family and a group of schoolchildren he shepherded from Landover, Md. Like other whites in the crowd, Mr. Oben said he was a follower of the Rev. Sun Myung Moon, the leader of the Unification Church and founder of the company that publishes The Washington Times.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Farrakhan is going in a more universal direction,'' Mr. Oben said of past controversy as he emphasized the day's larger message of family strength and solidarity.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Farrakhan was far more playful than controversial in his typically rambling, exuberant speech. The day seemed designed around him as much as the idea of family. His speech was preceded by a video biography worthy of a political convention, replete with orchestral crescendos and encomiums about his ''life, character and strength.''</p>
        <p>Speakers praised him as a visionary and ''the most courageous man in America today,'' in the words of Representative Bobby L. Rush, Democrat of Illinois.</p>
        <p>With the Capitol as his backdrop, Mr. Farrakhan delighted much of the crowd by describing the coming election as ''almost like a choice between Beelzebub and the Devil -- you lose with either one.''</p>
        <p>The crowd responded with a chant: ''Farrakhan for President!'' And the audience laughed when he instantly responded, ''I'm not a politician; I like to be able to speak the truth.''</p>
        <p>Like other speakers, Mr. Farrakhan called for an end to economic embargoes of Cuba and Iraq. He called for ''justice for the Palestinians'' among other troubled groups, but he avoided the accusations of other speakers that Israel was largely to blame for the renewal of Middle East violence.</p>
        <p>He warned women against abortion: ''Choice? Choose well the man you're giving yourself to,'' he advised to the applause of the crowd. And he warned men against rap lyrics that denigrate women: ''Don't call your woman a 'ho!' '' he angrily advised to cheers. ''Pick up a hoe -- H-O-E -- and start cultivating.''</p>
        <p>No less did he denounce the government and Congress as being preoccupied with the middle class over the poor. ''Help me clean up that gangsta-rap!'' he shouted to the crowed's laughter and applause.</p>
        <p>The day's speakers included  Ayanna Muhammad, an articulate, crowd-stirring, 11-year-old (''Power concedes nothing without demand!'') and Daniel Ortega, Nicaragua's former Sandinista president (''You are giving an example to the world.'').</p>
        <p>With obvious pleasure, Mr. Farrakhan greeted an assortment of religious and foreign political figures, including a contingent of Jews from the Neturei Karta International in Monsey, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''We've had discussions with Minister Farrakhan and find him to be a very warm person,'' said Yisroel Dovid Weiss, an associate rabbi with the group, which denounces atheistic ''Zionists in the Holy Land'' for the renewed fighting there. Asked about Mr. Farrakhan's past denunciations of Jews, Rabbi Weiss said that those comments ''clearly were taken out of context.''</p>
        <p>The day ended with the television screens flashing the contribution address for Mr. Farrakhan's proposed economic development bank to create neighborhood businesses. He said that he hoped for as much as $1 billion from families, which he pledged to protect and use to seek matching funds from government and the private sector.</p>
        <p>''Corporate America is buying your political leaders,'' he told the crowd. ''Who will balance the greed of corporate America?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
