<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Melancholy, Wit and Glitter in a Civilized Way? But of Course</title>
    <meta content="17DAM.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/arts/17DAM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holland, Bernard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">van Dam, Jose</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E4DD1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Melancholy, Wit and Glitter in a Civilized Way? But of Course</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD HOLLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holland, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bernard Holland reviews recitals by Jose van Dam at Alice Tully Hall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>France's uneasy and occasionally loud confrontations with the world tend to obscure a national personality deeply private and peculiarly ardent in its veiled and melancholic way. The music of Henri Dutilleux reminds us that global pressures have not quite erased the elusive, retreating quality of French musical art, but to experience it with clarity we do best to retreat a century. There we find Debussy's ''Pelleas et Melisande'' and around it the art songs so strikingly set forth by Jose van Dam in two recitals at Alice Tully Hall last week.</p>
        <p>The Belgian bass-baritone, just finished with a run of Debussy's great work at the Metropolitan Opera across the plaza at Lincoln Center, began both his programs with Duparc: five songs on Thursday evening, seven on Sunday afternoon. These 12 make up the essence and almost the whole of his work. ''L'Invitation au Voyage'' and ''La Vie Anterieure,'' the constant companions of any song lover, express a characteristic loneliness and dignity with extraordinary sophistication of harmony and originality of melodic writing. Next to them on Thursday were four songs by Duparc's less-known contemporary Guy Ropartz, whose ''Four Poems in the Style of Heinrich Heine's 'Intermezzo' '' reflect the same isolation and love of harmonic surprise but without perhaps Duparc's magical economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>France's uneasy and occasionally loud confrontations with the world tend to obscure a national personality deeply private and peculiarly ardent in its veiled and melancholic way. The music of Henri Dutilleux reminds us that global pressures have not quite erased the elusive, retreating quality of French musical art, but to experience it with clarity we do best to retreat a century. There we find Debussy's ''Pelleas et Melisande'' and around it the art songs so strikingly set forth by Jose van Dam in two recitals at Alice Tully Hall last week.</p>
        <p>The Belgian bass-baritone, just finished with a run of Debussy's great work at the Metropolitan Opera across the plaza at Lincoln Center, began both his programs with Duparc: five songs on Thursday evening, seven on Sunday afternoon. These 12 make up the essence and almost the whole of his work. ''L'Invitation au Voyage'' and ''La Vie Anterieure,'' the constant companions of any song lover, express a characteristic loneliness and dignity with extraordinary sophistication of harmony and originality of melodic writing. Next to them on Thursday were four songs by Duparc's less-known contemporary Guy Ropartz, whose ''Four Poems in the Style of Heinrich Heine's 'Intermezzo' '' reflect the same isolation and love of harmonic surprise but without perhaps Duparc's magical economy.</p>
        <p>Mr. van Dam and his splendid pianist Maciej Pikulski had several other things to say about French taste. One was its compulsive returns to childhood, where wit, absurdity, awe and innocence hold sway. Poulenc's ''Chansons Gaillardes'' and ''Le Bestiaire'' catalogued the animal kingdom, the attractions of booze and the vagaries of romance. Startling shortness is Poulenc's technique of choice.</p>
        <p>Ravel's ''Don Quichotte a Dulcinee'' on Thursday indulged France's occasional weakness for glitter and at the same time acknowledged its love of all things Spanish. The three songs are Ravel in his glitter mode: self-conscious elegance that teeters between clever good taste and clever bad taste. Ibert addressed the same subject with less flash but equal charm on Sunday in his four ''Chansons de Don Quichotte.'' The rhythms and the modal melody are authentic, but they have been cleaned up, neatly dressed, carefully posed and in general civilized. The French would have it no other way.</p>
        <p>Berlioz's eccentricities (four songs from ''Les Nuits d'Ete'') seemed to rise above national characteristics on Sunday, but the quietness of French art marked both events. Five of Faure's favorites flowed with great elegance on Thursday. The ''Fetes Galantes II'' of in 1904, sung on Sunday, are an introduction to late Debussy: spare, suggestive. They are silent in tone; they pass swiftly by; but the listener who truly listens will find in them some of the last century's greatest music.</p>
        <p>Mr. van Dam's singing, presented to two sophisticated and dedicated audiences, will be remembered for a long while. Conversational in delivery and yet wrapped in the most gorgeous sound imaginable, this is a voice and an understanding made to sing French repertory. In Duparc's ''Chanson Triste'' languid melody melted into dance rhythm without either element being obscured. Mr. Pikulski is a rare piano virtuoso who applies powerful technique to relatively simple music and finds the proper scale. In the piano part of ''Extase'' (again Duparc) singular tension and power never raised its musical voice above a stage whisper.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
