<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Baseball; From Wild Card to World Series</title>
    <meta content="17CHAS$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/sports/17CHAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Francisco Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E7DB163EF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Baseball; From Wild Card to World Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Baseball column discusses New York Mets winning National Leage championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The only team that knows it will play the opening game of the 2000 World Series on Saturday night is -- blast the trumpets, beat the drums, clang the cymbals -- the New York Metropolitans.</p>
        <p>The Atlanta Braves, their archnemeses and winners of nine consecutive division championships, will not be in the World Series this year. The San Francisco Giants, the team with the best record in the major leagues, will not be in the World Series this year. The Yankees, winners of the last two World Series and three of the last four, may be in it again this year, but they are not there yet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The only team that knows it will play the opening game of the 2000 World Series on Saturday night is -- blast the trumpets, beat the drums, clang the cymbals -- the New York Metropolitans.</p>
        <p>The Atlanta Braves, their archnemeses and winners of nine consecutive division championships, will not be in the World Series this year. The San Francisco Giants, the team with the best record in the major leagues, will not be in the World Series this year. The Yankees, winners of the last two World Series and three of the last four, may be in it again this year, but they are not there yet.</p>
        <p>No longer lovable losers but revered winners, the Mets boarded their Subway Series-bound train at Shea Stadium last night by thumping the St. Louis Cardinals once more with feeling, 7-0, to win the National League Championship Series, four games to one. Mike Hampton pitched a three-hitter and was named most valuable player of the series.</p>
        <p>Unlike a year ago, when they fell two games short of the ultimate series, the Mets stormed into Saturday's opener by dispatching the team that had done their dirty work for them. The Cardinals vanquished the Braves in the division series, knocking out the team that has served as the Mets' personal bogeyman.</p>
        <p>The Braves prevented the Mets from reaching the playoffs two years ago by sweeping a season-ending three-game series. They blocked the Mets' path to the World Series last year by winning the N.L.C.S. And they finished ahead of the Mets yet again during the regular season this year and threatened to frustrate them once more at this stage of the postseason.</p>
        <p>But the Braves stumbled in three straight games against the Cardinals and forfeited their chance to play the wild-card Mets. Yes, the w-i-l-d c-a-r-d Mets. They cannot topple the Braves from their perennial first-place perch, but they have parlayed the league's best second-place record into a ticket on the train to the Bronx or on the plane to Seattle.</p>
        <p>The only other team to reach the World Series as the wild card in the six years the also-ran pass has been in use was the 1997 Florida Marlins, and they won it.</p>
        <p>As the manager of the wild-card Mets, Bobby Valentine has never taken a team to a division championship, but now he is a pennant-winning manager, a designation that may make people forget he has managed the second highest number of major league games without finishing first.</p>
        <p>Valentine, who has alienated most other managers by his need to remind people that he is a smarter field general than the others, has done a good job maneuvering his troops in this postseason. He is generally credited with having outmanaged both Dusty Baker of the Giants and Tony La Russa of the Cardinals. In fact, he received pregame praise last night from none other than  La Russa, one of those managers with whom he has had a less than cordial relationship.</p>
        <p>La Russa, unsolicited, said Valentine's use of Timo Perez as the Mets' leadoff hitter was ''a hell of a move that really did a lot for their club and has helped them be up, 3-1.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, who would have ever conceived of a series where a pestiferous Mighty Mouse of a leadoff hitter named Timo (don't call me Timoniel) Perez would make a greater impact than a Man Mountain of a home run hitter named Mark McGwire?</p>
        <p>La Russa was limited in his use of McGwire, who has a right knee wracked with tendinitis. He could use him as a pinch-hitter once a game, but in the five games, McGwire appeared only three times. He was walked intentionally and hit a bases-loaded fly for the third out. And last night, when the Cardinals needed a seven-run home run, McGwire batted in the ninth with no one on and grounded out to second base.</p>
        <p>Valentine, on the other hand, got plenty of use out of Perez, a 23-year-old Dominican who learned his baseball playing four seasons in Japan. The Mets signed him as a free agent last March; he joined them for the last month of the season and played his way onto the postseason roster.</p>
        <p>''I thought he was a good player, a table-setter,'' said Omar Minaya, the senior assistant general manager,  ''He has a lot of feel for the game. What I found attractive was he played a style of baseball that was played in the 50's, 60's, 70's, like the Pirates, the Dodgers, the Giants. Those are the kind of guys that I am attracted to.''</p>
        <p>Minaya told his boss, Steve Phillips, here was a youngster worth signing, even though he was small, not even measuring the 5 feet 9 inches the Mets say he is.</p>
        <p>''I told Steve he's a little guy, but he knows how to play,'' Minaya said. ''I told him I thought he was close to the major leagues.''</p>
        <p>Minaya was right on that count and right about Perez as table-setter.</p>
        <p>In the Mets' decisive victories in Games 4 and 5, Perez was the first batter to reach base in five of the seven innings they scored. He triggered their first three scoring spurts Sunday night in the first, second and fourth innings. Last night he replicated that performance by igniting a pair of three-run flurries in the first and fourth innings.</p>
        <p>Perez opened the first inning by grounding a single up the middle, then stole second, continued to third on the throw into center field and scored when Edgardo Alfonzo singled. With one out in the fourth, Perez singled off the foot of St. Louis starter Pat Hentgen and subsequently scored when Todd Zeile lashed a bases-loaded double against the right-center-field fence.</p>
        <p>For the five-game series, Perez was the first batter on base in 8 of the 15 innings the Mets scored. The Mets, who lacked a genuine leadoff hitter for most of the season, could not have designed a better catalyst.</p>
        <p>But Perez was also a finisher. He caught the last out in Sunday's game and at 11:39 p.m. last night, he caught the final out as the Mets' final step to the World Series.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
