<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revelations About Greed, as Seen Through 160 Years of Dust</title>
    <meta content="17MONE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/arts/17MONE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001019T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bulwer-Lytton, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davies, John S</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Money (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDF1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revelations About Greed, as Seen Through 160 Years of Dust</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews Edward Bulwer-Lytton play Money, presented at Studio Theater; John S Davies directs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Edward Bulwer-Lytton, a prolific Victorian playwright and novelist as well as a politician, was the author, most notably of  ''The Last Days of Pompeii,'' but he lives on more formidably in anonymity by virtue of lines that have become familiar aphorisms. In his play ''Richelieu'' he coined ''The pen is mightier than the sword,'' and he began his novel ''Paul Clifford'' with a line so embedded in the popular mind that it was frequently appropriated by Snoopy: ''It was a dark and stormy night.''</p>
        <p>''Money,'' a popular social satire in its day, has the feel of a play that was funny and pertinent when it was first produced, in 1840, when it would have functioned as a mirror to a caste-obsessed upper-class audience. Today it's more than a little stale, not because it's written in the Victorian mode, with all the pretentious-sounding formal locutions of the day and with a complicated plot that untangles according to a neat and instructive moral lesson. Rather, the dustiness of the play has more to do with its cheery sense of revelation of a human foible -- greed -- that most of us have by now examined at some pretty complex depth. Did you know that money, though it makes life more comfortable, is no substitute for love?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Edward Bulwer-Lytton, a prolific Victorian playwright and novelist as well as a politician, was the author, most notably of  ''The Last Days of Pompeii,'' but he lives on more formidably in anonymity by virtue of lines that have become familiar aphorisms. In his play ''Richelieu'' he coined ''The pen is mightier than the sword,'' and he began his novel ''Paul Clifford'' with a line so embedded in the popular mind that it was frequently appropriated by Snoopy: ''It was a dark and stormy night.''</p>
        <p>''Money,'' a popular social satire in its day, has the feel of a play that was funny and pertinent when it was first produced, in 1840, when it would have functioned as a mirror to a caste-obsessed upper-class audience. Today it's more than a little stale, not because it's written in the Victorian mode, with all the pretentious-sounding formal locutions of the day and with a complicated plot that untangles according to a neat and instructive moral lesson. Rather, the dustiness of the play has more to do with its cheery sense of revelation of a human foible -- greed -- that most of us have by now examined at some pretty complex depth. Did you know that money, though it makes life more comfortable, is no substitute for love?</p>
        <p>The new production of the play at the Studio Theater on West 46th Street, by the Storm Theater, a three-year-old Off Off Broadway troupe, makes an effort to point out that such a sentiment remains legitimate social commentary. In blackouts between scenes, as the actors move the props around, they chant lyrics from songs like the Beatles' ''Can't Buy Me Love'' and Cyndi Lauper's ''Money Changes Everything.'' But in the end this is a play that says what it says, and in the earnest and straightforward rendition it is given here, directed by John S. Davies -- the first production ever in this country, the company claims -- the obvious is rather egregiously belabored.</p>
        <p>The story concerns a collection of wealth-hungry social climbers who expect to inherit the fortune of a man to whom they are all distantly related. Their hopes are dashed when it turns out he was well aware that their fawning over him had an ulterior motive; instead, he leaves virtually everything to a poor scholar, Alfred Evelyn, who is immediately elevated in the eyes of the other characters to the status of a great man. Evelyn has had a marriage proposal rebuffed by a worthy but penniless young woman, Clara Douglas, because she had seen what poverty had done to her own parents, and once his fortunes are reversed both of them are too proud to revisit their former affections and they begin to pursue other attachments. The main action of the play involves Evelyn's plot to unveil the hypocrisy of the greedy, which in the end, of course, delivers him to the love he deserved in the first place.</p>
        <p>With handsome period costumes by E. Shura Pollatsek and a set by Mary Houston that employs panels and minimal furniture, the production makes able if unsurprising use of a small budget, and the actors, too, generally display a comfort and competence with the Victorian mode of behavior and diction.</p>
        <p>Stephen Logan Day, as Sir John Vesey, a conniving estate owner who hopes to marry off his pleasant if dim daughter to Evelyn, does a nicely understated job in a role that would be deadly if played for pomposity. And as Clara, Elizabeth Roby manages to be charming even with her character's insufferably inflexible conscience. Colleen Crawford, as Sir John's sensibly wry sister, and Laurence Drozd as Evelyn's friend Sir Henry Graves, whose palpably insincere grief at his wife's long ago death is one of the play's running jokes, both find a nice balance between the elements of caricature and credibility in their roles. As the foppish Sir Frederick Blount, Clara's other suitor, Brett Hemmerling is less successful, but he's less fortunate; his character, who can't pronounce the letter R -- Sir Fwedwick, he calls himself -- is written for pure silliness.</p>
        <p>Over all the problem is that the production is so, well, faithful to the playwright. There's not an arch moment in it; the humor is the playwright's own, and though there are flashes of wit in the dialogue -- the scene in which the will is read is the play's best -- Bulwer-Lytton's perspective is worn as can be. This is most evident in the performance of Peter Dobbins, the company's artistic director, as Evelyn, whose morally stiff spine and know-it-all righteousness are played at an overwrought high pitch that makes you wish someone would just pull his pants down. Evelyn gets everything he wants, after all. It probably never occurred to the playwright -- but it should have, to the company -- that a century and a half later, we'd expect him to be a little bit embarrassed about that.</p>
        <p>MONEY</p>
        <p>By Edward Bulwer-Lytton; directed by John S. Davies; producing artistic director, Peter Dobbins; associate artistic director, John Regis; associate producer, John Aherne; stage manager, Jean Klepka; production manager, Jason Decremer; sets by Mary Houston; costumes by E. Shura Pollatsek; lighting by Charles Cameron; choreography by Maryanne Chaney; assistant stage manager, Colleen Beakey. Presented by the Storm Theater, in association with East End Productions. At the Studio Theater, 145 West 46th Street, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Stephen Logan Day (Sir John Vesey), Colleen Crawford (Georgina Vesey), Suzanna Geraghty (Lady Franklin), Elizabeth Roby (Clara Douglas), Peter Dobbins (Alfred Evelyn), Laurence Drozd (Sir Henry Graves, MacFinch) and Brett Hemmerling (Sir Frederick Blount).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW  Correction:  October 19, 2000, Thursday  A theater review on Tuesday about ''Money,'' at the Studio Theater in Manhattan, misidentified the actress who plays Lady Franklin, the sister of Sir John Vesey, a conniving estate owner. As shown in the cast listing, the role is played by Suzanna Geraghty; Colleen Crawford plays Georgina Vesey, Sir John's daughter.</p>
        <p>The review also included an erroneous reference from the company to the play's production history. It was staged in New York in 1979; this is not its first American production.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 19, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>A theater review on Tuesday about ''Money,'' at the Studio Theater in Manhattan, misidentified the actress who plays Lady Franklin, the sister of Sir John Vesey, a conniving estate owner. As shown in the cast listing, the role is played by Suzanna Geraghty; Colleen Crawford plays Georgina Vesey, Sir John's daughter.</p>
        <p>The review also included an erroneous reference from the company to the play's production history. It was staged in New York in 1979; this is not its first American production.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
