<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man's Fate, Through Dry but Sorrowful Irish Eyes</title>
    <meta content="17KAKU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/arts/17KAKU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trevor, William</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hill Bachelors, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E4DF1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man's Fate, Through Dry but Sorrowful Irish Eyes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews William Trevor book The Hill Bachelors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE HILL BACHELORS  By William Trevor  245 pages. Viking $22.95.</p>
        <p>''He was out of touch, and often felt it,'' writes William Trevor of one of his heroes, ''out of touch with the times and what was happening in them, out of touch with two generations of change, with his own country and what it had become.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE HILL BACHELORS  By William Trevor  245 pages. Viking $22.95.</p>
        <p>''He was out of touch, and often felt it,'' writes William Trevor of one of his heroes, ''out of touch with the times and what was happening in them, out of touch with two generations of change, with his own country and what it had become.''</p>
        <p>Though this description refers to a clergyman in a remote parish in rural Ireland, it could just as well apply to all of Mr. Trevor's characters in this elegiac collection. They are all outsiders of sorts, marginalized by temperament, history or bad luck -- perpetual visitors, as one puts it, consigned to live in an emotional exile that goes unbroken save for nervous exchanges with others just as disaffected or isolated as they are.</p>
        <p>The Protestant clergyman Mr. Trevor portrays in ''Of the Cloth'' realizes he shares a bond with a visiting Catholic priest who has come to pay his respects after the parish gardener -- a Catholic, who has nonetheless tended the clergyman's grounds for 28 years -- abruptly dies. A high-strung woman who killed her disabled sister many years ago carries on an uneasy flirtation with the man who once provided her with an alibi. And a stoic widower meets a solitary female traveler in a local restaurant and allows himself to envision a future together, only to find himself made the butt of a cruel swindle.</p>
        <p>Though the weaker tales in this volume highlight Mr. Trevor's penchant for manipulating his characters' fates to lend his story lines neat ironic twists, he always manages to give the reader a sense of the entire arc of their lives, compressing years, even decades, into a few sharply observed lines. His people, who live in rural Ireland for the most part,  tend to lead highly circumscribed existences, doing what their parents and grandparents did before them. One man must choose between his sense of religious vocation -- the Virgin has appeared to him and told him to enter a monastery -- and his duty to preserve the family farm. Another must choose between his love for a woman and his obligations to his widowed mother.</p>
        <p>Like so many earlier Trevor characters, these people often find their experiences dividing, alarmingly, into a before and after, a then and now. In ''The Telephone Game'' a young woman discovers on the eve of her wedding that her fiance, who has concocted an elaborate practical joke to play on a complete stranger, has a callous, cynical streak. And in ''A Friend in the Trade'' a couple who for 25 years have allowed their eccentric friend Michingthorpe to treat their home as his own decide to move to the country, where the carless Michingthorpe is unlikely to visit.</p>
        <p>In other cases it's the intrusion of the public into the private -- a conjunction between the Irish troubles and troubles of a more personal nature -- that determines the course of a life. One of Mr. Trevor's characters loses his wife and daughter when a bomb is planted in their car in error, their vehicle ''similar in make and color to the would-be victim's, the registration number varying by only a single digit.'' Another man, an impoverished Irish immigrant in London, is recruited as a bomber by militants intent on finding someone to redo a hit job gone tragically awry; they appeal to his rage against a cruel, exploitative boss and to his dreams of heroism and distinction.</p>
        <p>In fact, in story after story Mr. Trevor points up the disparity between his characters' romantic fantasies and the deadening reality of their daily lives. Whether it's a man losing his dream of true love in the wake of a sordid one-night stand or a professor learning what the world really thinks of him when his obituary is prematurely published, a sense of disappointment hovers about these people, giving way in most cases to a resignation bordering on acceptance.</p>
        <p>These, of course, are perennial themes for Mr. Trevor, themes excavated and examined in earlier collections like ''After Rain'' (1996) and ''Family Sins'' (1990) as well as novels like ''Felicia's Journey'' (1995). But if he fails to reconnoiter new territory in these stories, Mr. Trevor nonetheless manages to work masterful variations on these familiar melodies, demonstrating once again his authority and poise as a storyteller, his Chekhovian understanding of missed connections and misplaced hopes.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
