<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="17OBSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/science/17OBSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Salt</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mississippi River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Antarctic Regions</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Salt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7DD1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study finds that earthquake in New Madrid Fault, 100-mile stretch along Mississippi River, could occur much sooner than 1,000 years previously thought; new report by California Dept of Conservation says that about 70,000 acres of open space was lost to urban and suburban sprawl over two-year period ending in 1998--25 percent increase over previous two years; comment on research into origin of salts in Dry Valleys of Antarctica (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Earthquake Threat</p>
        <p>Residents of the Central Mississippi Valley are on something of a roller coaster ride -- a slow roller coaster ride -- when it comes to the threat of large earthquakes.</p>
        <p>The New Madrid fault zone, a 100-mile stretch along the Mississippi River from Missouri to Arkansas, has been the site of several large earthquakes over the past 1,500 years, including three powerful ones in 1811-1812 when, fortunately, there were comparatively few people around. The question has been whether the area, which now includes St. Louis and Memphis, can expect another strong earthquake anytime soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Earthquake Threat</p>
        <p>Residents of the Central Mississippi Valley are on something of a roller coaster ride -- a slow roller coaster ride -- when it comes to the threat of large earthquakes.</p>
        <p>The New Madrid fault zone, a 100-mile stretch along the Mississippi River from Missouri to Arkansas, has been the site of several large earthquakes over the past 1,500 years, including three powerful ones in 1811-1812 when, fortunately, there were comparatively few people around. The question has been whether the area, which now includes St. Louis and Memphis, can expect another strong earthquake anytime soon.</p>
        <p>The issue appeared to have been resolved last year, when a study by a Northwestern University geologist showed almost no ground movement in the fault zone, suggesting that it would take at least 1,000 years, and possibly much longer, for enough strain to build up for a devastating earthquake to occur.</p>
        <p>But a new study in the journal Science by researchers at the California Institute of Technology and Stanford suggests that a quake could occur much sooner. The surface may not be moving much, these researchers say, but stress is building up below.</p>
        <p>The researchers say that the earlier study applied the ground-movement data to a fault model similar to that found at the edges of tectonic plates, while the New Madrid zone is in the middle of one. The scientists developed a new model for such a region, called an intraplate zone, suggesting that strain builds up in a weak area below the surface and eventually shifts to the surface, where it causes a rupture in the fault.</p>
        <p>The scientists put the time between such ruptures at 250 to 4,000 years, meaning a strong quake could occur as early as the middle of this century.</p>
        <p>Land of Sprawl</p>
        <p>Earthquakes are more certain in California, and the joke has been that someday half the state will slide into the ocean. But California is already losing land in a different way.</p>
        <p>A new report by the state's Department of Conservation says about 70,000 acres of open space was lost to urban and suburban sprawl over a two-year period ending in 1998 -- a 25 percent increase over the previous two years. The state's booming economy and population growth are to blame, officials said.</p>
        <p>Southern California, the region that put sprawl on the map, lost the most open space, nearly half the state total, followed by the San Joaquin Valley and the San Francisco Bay area.</p>
        <p>Of the acreage lost (an area about five times the size of Manhattan), about 60 percent was farmland. Since California now supplies more than 50 percent of the country's fruits and vegetables, loss of farmland is cause for some concern nationally. The report did, however, show an increase in the amount of irrigated farmland in some areas. But this was mostly in form of vineyards.</p>
        <p>Salt of Antarctica</p>
        <p>There is still plenty of open space in Antarctica, including the Dry Valleys, landforms curiously devoid of the ice and snow that smothers the rest of continent.</p>
        <p>In addition to being dry, the valleys, which are near McMurdo Sound, are very salty. Researchers have long debated where the salts, including sulfates, came from. Some believe it was sea salt blown from the oceans; others hold it was the legacy of an ancient sea that covered the region.</p>
        <p>A report in Nature offers convincing evidence that the salt does originate in the oceans around Antarctica, but not largely from sea salt. Instead, by examining the composition of oxygen isotopes in the sulfates, researchers from the University of California at San Diego discovered that they come from sulfur-belching marine algae. The sulfur gas is oxidized in the atmosphere and deposited as sulfates in the valleys.</p>
        <p>Since the Dry Valleys are about the closest thing to Mars on Earth, the researchers say their findings could have implications for the search for signs of life on Mars, to see how similar phenomena may have occurred there.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
