<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Business Briefing</title>
    <meta content="17BBRF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/nyregion/17BBRF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E4DD163EF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Business Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CASINO RIVALS MEET  Political leaders in Monticello, N.Y., say that the two rival developers of an Indian casino project may be close to a deal that would finally bring gambling to the Catskills.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the stock price of Alpha Hospitality, a gambling company that is involved in the casino effort, has jumped nearly 80 percent in unusually heavy trading since last Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CASINO RIVALS MEET  Political leaders in Monticello, N.Y., say that the two rival developers of an Indian casino project may be close to a deal that would finally bring gambling to the Catskills.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the stock price of Alpha Hospitality, a gambling company that is involved in the casino effort, has jumped nearly 80 percent in unusually heavy trading since last Thursday.</p>
        <p>Word began circulating in Monticello last week that Alpha Hospitality and its partners at Catskill Development were negotiating with Park Place Entertainment, the largest casino company in the world, said Rusty Pomeroy, chairman of the Sullivan County Legislature. According to three people who have been briefed on the talks, Park Place would buy out Catskill Development for about $300 million and build a casino with the St. Regis Mohawks at the Monticello Raceway.</p>
        <p>''It's encouraging,'' Mr. Pomeroy said yesterday.</p>
        <p>An adviser to the Mohawks confirmed that the two sides had been meeting. But Tom Aro, an Alpha executive, declined to comment, and Park Place did not return calls requesting comment.</p>
        <p>But one executive cautioned that the deal may have come undone yesterday, after Park Place failed to sign a contract and wire a down payment to Catskill Development.</p>
        <p>Joseph Bernstein, a partner in Catskill Development, said, ''There is no deal.'' But he refused to say whether negotiations continued.</p>
        <p>Investors remain convinced that a breakthrough in the long stalled project is imminent.</p>
        <p>''Alpha's stock is singing,'' said Richard Wexler, who heads Wexler Kronen Capital Associates, a money management firm with a stake in the company. ''I think a resolution is at hand.''</p>
        <p>Charles V. Bagli (NYT)</p>
        <p>WIZARD RECALLED  A federal judge in Manhattan issued a temporary restraining order yesterday that bars a leading costume manufacturer from selling Halloween costumes, one of which is called the ''Crimson Wizard,'' that appear to be based on the Harry Potter character.</p>
        <p>The judge, Louis L. Stanton of Federal District Court, also ordered the manufacturer, Disguise Inc., to recall all such costumes that have already been shipped.</p>
        <p>Ads for the costume on the company's Web site show a boy wearing black-framed glasses and a yellow and maroon striped jersey, the lawsuit said.</p>
        <p>Time Warner Entertainment Company, which owns the licensing rights to the popular children's book series and had sued Disguise, will ''very aggressively protect'' the Harry Potter property, said one of its lawyers, Dale M. Cendali.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for Disguise had no comment. Earlier, it had told Time Warner that it believed the costume it showed on its Web site was ''sufficiently dissimilar'' to any depiction of the Harry Potter character in the artwork on the books.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Weiser (NYT)</p>
        <p>SHOE RETAILER SOLD  Joan and David Helpern Inc., a family-owned shoe retailer whose Joan &amp; David stores are found in many upscale shopping malls, has been sold for $16.8 million and the assumption of certain liabilities, the company's financial advisers said yesterday. After experiencing financial difficulties for the past five years, the New York-based company sought bankruptcy protection in March.</p>
        <p>The Helperns, who used to sell their Joan &amp; David shoes in Ann Taylor stores, severed their ties with the clothing retailer a decade ago and began to expand rapidly. By the time of the bankruptcy filing, they had 67 Joan &amp; David boutiques, shops within major department stores and outlet stores.</p>
        <p>Since March, the company has closed 12 stores, including one Manhattan store at 104 Fifth Ave., said Robert L. Pressman, a senior partner at Newmark Retail Financial Advisers, which assisted the company with its restructuring. Joan &amp; David has another store in Manhattan at 816 Madison Avenue.</p>
        <p>The shoe retailer was acquired Thursday by Maxwell Shoe Company, of Readville, Mass., whose product lines include Sam &amp; Libby and Anne Klein 2. As part of the sale agreement, the Helperns will no longer be associated with Joan &amp; David. Executives at Maxwell did not respond to requests for comment.</p>
        <p>Terry Pristin (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
