<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; An Ode to Pork</title>
    <meta content="17COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/opinion/17COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EEDC1F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; An Ode to Pork</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed column says Congress is racing toward adjournment and nobody, not even the 60-odd representatives who are unopposed, wants to go home to campaign without some pork-barrel project; several projects noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a truth universally acknowledged that a town in possession of a congressman running for re-election must be in want of a new parking lot.</p>
        <p>Congress -- remember Congress? -- is racing toward adjournment. Nobody, even the 60-odd representatives who are unopposed, wants to go home to campaign without a stack of bacon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a truth universally acknowledged that a town in possession of a congressman running for re-election must be in want of a new parking lot.</p>
        <p>Congress -- remember Congress? -- is racing toward adjournment. Nobody, even the 60-odd representatives who are unopposed, wants to go home to campaign without a stack of bacon.</p>
        <p>''The Republicans are running on pork!'' moaned Kevin Hassett, a resident scholar at the American Enterprise Institute. ''Do you hear anybody saying 'Elect me and I'll get George W. Bush's tax cut through'? Noooo. They say, 'Elect me and I'll deliver the National Monument for Slate Manufacturing.' Or whatever.''</p>
        <p>This is the time of year when you realize how many different kinds of museums and monuments this lucky nation has been blessed with, and how all of them are in need of constant infusions of federal aid to stay afloat. The monument to the god Vulcan in Birmingham, Ala., is getting a $2 million refurbishing, and the Museum of the First Ladies in Canton, Ohio, is getting $300,000, much to the chagrin of Citizens Against Government Waste, which says the museum ''frequently has a drag queen dress up like Helen Taft and give tours to senior citizens.''</p>
        <p>Already we have an unfair attack. The person dressing up like Helen Taft is actually the museum's in-house historian. ''He does portrayals of 11 different first ladies,'' a spokeswoman said proudly.</p>
        <p>If you were in Canton, with the birthplace of Ida McKinley hanging heavy on your hands, you'd probably want to turn it into a museum too. Mrs. McKinley was not one of our more charismatic first ladies, but she happens to be the only president's wife who was born in a city represented by a senior Republican on the House Appropriations Committee.</p>
        <p>I've got to admit I have a soft spot for this sort of stuff. Sure, there's a big new hotel in Savannah that's getting subsidized water taxi service with the help of a Congressman with a seat on Appropriations. But if the Democrats take over the House of Representatives in November, the congressman in my neighborhood becomes chairman of the Ways and Means Committee, and we are fully expecting water taxis all around.</p>
        <p>Our theme today is going to be: Things could be worse. Spending $400,000 to improve a parking lot in the town of Talkeetna, Alaska, population about 330, may not be on your agenda, even after the office of Ted Stevens, the Senate Appropriations Committee chairman, explains to you that Talkeetna gets a lot of tourists in the summer. But look at it this way: President Clinton scrapped an entire plan for the nation's antiballistic-missile defense because it didn't cover a couple of sparsely inhabited islands that Mr. Stevens represents. Just be grateful he didn't want to give Talkeetna its own MIRV.</p>
        <p>This has been a strange time in Washington. Senator Jesse Helms has bonded with the Irish rocker Bono. Dennis Hastert, the House speaker, has bonded with Bill Clinton. ''Hastert's a reasonable sort of guy, and he's willing to cut deals,'' said Mr. Hassett, the budget hawk. ''The moral is -- it's better when they all hate each other.''</p>
        <p>The Transportation Committee chairman, Bud Shuster, got a break when the crack House Ethics Committee ruled it was not illegal for him to take gifts from Ann Eppard, a lobbyist. Mr. Shuster celebrated by producing an extra-chunky road-building program. Then, in a demonstration of his deep interest in alternate forms of transportation, he got involved in a controversy over whether CBS news had caught him lying down in the back seat of Ms. Eppard's car as it left her garage.</p>
        <p>In the Senate, Orrin Hatch, the Judiciary chairman, managed to paste a measure expanding the prosecution of illegal Internet wine sales to a bill combating domestic violence and sex trafficking. In one extremely efficient stroke, the upper chamber has helped the spousal-abuse hot lines, declared war on the importation of sex slaves and made the lobbyists for liquor wholesalers very, very happy.</p>
        <p>''It could have been worse,'' said one Democrat. ''For a while they were trying to attach the bankruptcy legislation to it too.''</p>
        <p>Only the boutique wineries in California and their Internet customers were unhappy. Maybe somebody could build them a nice museum in Napa Valley.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
