<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Westchester County Frets Over What the Loss of Texaco Would Mean to the Region</title>
    <meta content="Y17TEXA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/business/17TEXA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Texaco Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chevron Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chevron Texaco Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Worth, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6D71F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Westchester County Frets Over What the Loss of Texaco Would Mean to the Region</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT WORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Worth, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>HARRISON, N.Y., Oct. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Local officials and businesspeople in Harrison, NY, are concerned about loss of Texaco Inc headquarters in wake of Chevron's acquisition of Texaco and Chevron's decision to consolidate merged company in San Francisco; officials fear loss of jobs as well as substantial reduction in tax revenue (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Texaco's corporate headquarters, on a vast rolling campus just outside White Plains, has been an important source of employment and a strong philanthropic presence in Westchester County since the company moved here in 1977.</p>
        <p>But after Chevron announced on Sunday that it would acquire Texaco and consolidate the headquarters staff in San Francisco, where Chevron is based, a number of local officials and businesspeople expressed concern about how the move would affect the community.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Texaco's corporate headquarters, on a vast rolling campus just outside White Plains, has been an important source of employment and a strong philanthropic presence in Westchester County since the company moved here in 1977.</p>
        <p>But after Chevron announced on Sunday that it would acquire Texaco and consolidate the headquarters staff in San Francisco, where Chevron is based, a number of local officials and businesspeople expressed concern about how the move would affect the community.</p>
        <p>''They've been a very good corporate citizen,'' said Harold Vogt, president of the Westchester County Chamber of Commerce. ''If Texaco were to depart from the county entirely, it would certainly have an impact.''</p>
        <p>The company has not determined how many of the 800 employees based here will be laid off, said Andy Norman, a spokesman for Texaco. The new company, to be called Chevron Texaco, plans to eliminate 4,000 positions out of its combined worldwide work force of 57,000, saving $1.2 billion a year.</p>
        <p>The company would not allow reporters to speak to employees about potential moves or layoffs, Mr. Norman said. There were no visible signs of distress at the Texaco headquarters, a low-lying stone and glass structure surrounded by lush lawns.</p>
        <p>The loss in taxes alone will be significant if the company moves out entirely, said Ronald Bianchi, the Harrison town supervisor. This year Texaco has paid $1,756,000 in school taxes, $410,800 to the town and $866,000 to the county, said Nancy Masi, the Harrison town receiver.</p>
        <p>But losing Texaco entirely would not be a devastating blow, said Sal Carrera, the county's director of economic development and real estate. The loss in taxes could easily be regained if another company moved into Texaco's Harrison headquarters. A number of corporations have moved into the county or expanded their operations here in the last year, and those gains have more than offset the losses from other companies that have left or announced plans to leave, like International Paper. Altogether, the county has gained 3,000 employees, and the vacancy rate has dropped from 30 percent to 13 percent in the last 18 months, he said.</p>
        <p>In addition, a number of local people said the company's philanthropic impact has been more important than its employment base. Westchester, after all, has suffered the departure or downsizing of a number of corporate giants, starting with I.B.M. in 1993. Texaco has been gradually reducing its Harrison work force since 1983, when it reached a peak of 1,800, said Keelin Molloy, a spokeswoman. The company, which once occupied all of its 770,000-square-foot headquarters, now uses about 650,000. Last spring it rented 120,000 to Atlas Air, an air cargo carrier.</p>
        <p>The company has, however, been a strong philanthropic presence here, contributing to a number of schools and nonprofit organizations.</p>
        <p>''I would hate to see them go,'' said Donald Howard, superintendent of schools in Harrison. ''They've been a very good neighbor.''</p>
        <p>Texaco has contributed materials and services worth more than $200,000 a year, Mr. Howard said. They help publish the school newspaper; provide annual grants for technology, the sciences, and multicultural activities; and helped finance a variety of special programs.</p>
        <p>Texaco provides similar services for the neighboring Port Chester school district, said the superintendent, Dr. Charles Coletti, including a mentoring program to which Texaco employees have contributed some 15,000 hours of volunteering time.</p>
        <p>''It will be a great loss to the community; I can't quite imagine it,'' said Laura Calzolari, executive director of the Music Conservatory of Westchester, based in White Plains.</p>
        <p>Over the last decade, Texaco has provided a number of grants to the conservatory, including a recent three-year grant for $75,000, she said.</p>
        <p>Texaco has been calling all the organizations to which it has contributed and reassuring them that it will honor its commitments regardless of what happens to its operations in Westchester, said Anne Dowling, president of the Texaco Foundation and director of corporate contributions and community relations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
