<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tranquillity Elusive for Famed Jeweler's Heir</title>
    <meta content="17PROF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/17/nyregion/17PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business and Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Ronald Winston</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wadler, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winston, Ronald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5D61F3FF934A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tranquillity Elusive for Famed Jeweler's Heir</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE WADLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wadler, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column profiles career of jeweler Ronald Winston; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Dresden Green diamond, a 40.70-carat stone never before seen in this country, spent a day in New York en route to the Smithsonian Institution last week, thanks to the efforts of Ronald Winston, who runs what used to be Dad's store, Harry Winston.</p>
        <p>Photographers and television crews were invited to shoot the diamond at the Fifth Avenue jewelry store, and to meet the directors of the museum in Dresden, Germany, that has lent the diamond to the Smithsonian for three months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Dresden Green diamond, a 40.70-carat stone never before seen in this country, spent a day in New York en route to the Smithsonian Institution last week, thanks to the efforts of Ronald Winston, who runs what used to be Dad's store, Harry Winston.</p>
        <p>Photographers and television crews were invited to shoot the diamond at the Fifth Avenue jewelry store, and to meet the directors of the museum in Dresden, Germany, that has lent the diamond to the Smithsonian for three months.</p>
        <p>But getting Mr. Winston's mug was out of the question. So camera-shy was he, he stayed in another room, occasionally poking his head through a curtain. It was the balding head of a conservative businessman of 59; looking at that head, you would  never guess this was a man who tried LSD as a chemistry student at Harvard, trained for the Olympic 100-yard dash at age 47, and had a Japanese teahouse in the garden of his Upper East Side brownstone.</p>
        <p>What's the deal with the photo ban?</p>
        <p>''It's been part of the Lloyd's of London policy ever since two members of the Bulgari family got kidnapped and put in a closet for six weeks,'' says Mr. Winston a few days later, showing a good memory about a 16-year-old crime. ''And that was a less dangerous time.''</p>
        <p>He is a courteous man with a dry sense of humor who chats armchair to armchair in an office filled with antiques and plays his wealth nonchalantly. ''Why don't you put those puppies to bed?'' he tells one of his people when it's time to put away a pair of 50-carat, canary-yellow diamond earrings worth $6 million.</p>
        <p>His tranquillity is the sort one finds in a New York guy who has embraced an Eastern culture, in this case, Japanese. A ''polite, sensitive culture,'' Mr. Winston says. That tranquillity is threatened when a photographer arrives. He insists, with some urgency, that one of his people be present.</p>
        <p>He is also reluctant to discuss his 12-year legal battle with his younger brother, Bruce Winston, 56, for control of the company. It was a vicious fight, with Ronald, Harry Winston's favored son, sometimes portrayed as ruthless and Bruce, a college dropout, as an unambitious dreamer. ''I have two sons,'' Harry Winston reportedly told his sister-in-law, Lillian Winston, who repeated the comment to The Wall Street Journal. ''One is a genius and one is a moron.''</p>
        <p>This summer, a settlement was reached in Surrogate's Court in White Plains, with Ronald buying out Bruce for $54.1 million. The brothers shooks hands before Judge Albert J. Emanuelli.</p>
        <p>WHAT is the relationship between the brothers three months later?</p>
        <p>''I don't know, I really don't know,'' Mr. Winston says. ''We did shake hands, but we haven't talked since.''</p>
        <p>There was that remark from the aunt -- ''Yeah, my Aunt Lillian, a very nice lady,'' interrupts Mr. Winston with a wry smile, clearly plagued by the comment.</p>
        <p>Did the remark accurately reflect their father's feelings?</p>
        <p>''I think my father was very frustrated with my brother, who early in life decided he was not going to work, just to enjoy life,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Time for a rebuttal from Edward Wohl, a lawyer for Bruce Winston.</p>
        <p>''My understanding is, that's not true,'' he says. ''Bruce was active in the business for some time, certainly in the 60's, even in the early 70's.''</p>
        <p>The legend of Harry Winston: he made his first million by age 21, acquired the Hope diamond in 1949, and presented it as a gift to the Smithsonian in 1958.</p>
        <p>Ronald Winston was brought up in luxury in Westchester and New York. He saw his first diamonds as a boy, when his dad brought them home. The younger Mr. Winston's interests, nonetheless, were in science; after graduating from Harvard, he worked for a few years in rocket research at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. He went into the diamond business in his late 20's, only because his father asked.</p>
        <p>Today, he is married to a film producer and maintains a home in California, a brownstone in New York and another home in Westchester. But his interests, Mr. Winston insists, include quiet pursuits. He works on his poems, he gardens.</p>
        <p>A rendezvous is arranged for later in the day at the Japanese teahouse. Mr. Winston unlocks the door of the town house, which has the stale air of a dwelling that is not much inhabited. A living room looks out on a Japanese garden and the teahouse beyond.</p>
        <p>It is a lovely teahouse, with the traditional low door. Inside hangs a long scroll, painted to reflect the changing seasons. Only, as Mr. Winston points out, the flower on the scroll is wisteria, a May flower; it's been months since he's been in the teahouse. The tatami mats are scattered with dead moths.</p>
        <p>Mr. Winston finds a broom, sweeps out the moths, removes his shoes, and sits down. In his business suit, he gives the impression of being the wrong look, the wrong size, for his teahouse, but no matter. Are there any impressions, after all his press coverage, he might like to correct?</p>
        <p>''Well, I think people think of me as this very highfalutin person,'' Mr. Winston begins. ''I run a glamorous business, so people think I'm unapproachable. I'm really a very simple guy. I do a lot of things myself, I swept out the moths.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
