<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burlington</title>
    <meta content="BURL.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BURLINGTON (VT)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURROS, MARIAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont/Burlington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2DC163CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burlington</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARIAN BURROS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BURROS, MARIAN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What's Doing In column offers suggestions on events, sightseeing, lodging and restaurants in Burlington, Vt; photos; chart; maps (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudyard Kipling, a short-time resident of Vermont, said Lake Champlain was one of the finest places in the world to view a sunset. But for decades, outdoor enthusiasts on their way to Vermont's renowned mountains passed within a few miles of the lake and never knew what they were missing. They lingered at the Burlington airport only long enough to pick up their luggage.</p>
        <p>For decades there was not much reason to visit Burlington despite its setting on Lake Champlain. The once-wealthy mercantile city, a center for lumber barons, fur traders and shipping magnates, who built brick mansions on the hill overlooking the lake, had become another New England wasteland, the grand homes turned into dormitories for University of Vermont students.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rudyard Kipling, a short-time resident of Vermont, said Lake Champlain was one of the finest places in the world to view a sunset. But for decades, outdoor enthusiasts on their way to Vermont's renowned mountains passed within a few miles of the lake and never knew what they were missing. They lingered at the Burlington airport only long enough to pick up their luggage.</p>
        <p>For decades there was not much reason to visit Burlington despite its setting on Lake Champlain. The once-wealthy mercantile city, a center for lumber barons, fur traders and shipping magnates, who built brick mansions on the hill overlooking the lake, had become another New England wasteland, the grand homes turned into dormitories for University of Vermont students.</p>
        <p>A key part of the city's comeback was the creation in 1981 of the Church Street Marketplace downtown. Today the four-block pedestrian mall, a short walk from the restored waterfront, is lined with shops in Victorian and Art Deco buildings along brick-paved streets. In nice weather, the sidewalk cafes are filled with people all day and into the night, and there is a constant parade of concerts, dancing and jugglers.</p>
        <p>In 1990 plans took shape to turn the underutilized parcel of land along the lake shore into Waterfront Park. Today many of the town's festivals are held there, with views of the Adirondacks across the lake. A free trolley runs up College Street from the waterfront past the Marketplace.</p>
        <p>Burlington is a lively college town, but more than that, it combines a year-round cultural and intellectual community with a relaxed, friendly small-town atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>The Discover Jazz Festival, in its 17th year, includes about 200 performances from June 6 to 11 in locations all over town. The most expensive ticket is $26, but many concerts are free. Some of this year's performers include the Dave Douglas Sextet and Chucho Valdes Quintet with Claudio Roditi. Information: (802) 863-7992; tickets: (802) 863-5966; www.discoverjazz.com.</p>
        <p>Professional actors' equity summer theater is featured at the McCarthy Arts Center at St. Michael's Playhouse, Route 15, off Interstate 89, (802) 654-2281; academics.smcvt .edu/playhouse. This year's productions are ''Grease'' from June 20 to July 1; ''Barefoot in the Park'' July 5 to 15; ''Communicating Doors'' July 18 to 29; ''Cirque du Souffle'' Aug. 1 to 12. Tickets range from $15 to $22.</p>
        <p>Over three weeks, from July 16 to Aug. 6, the Vermont Mozart Festival will present nine concerts in the Burlington area, including five outdoors at Shelburne Farms, overlooking Lake Champlain. Preconcert picnics are encouraged. Tickets, $20 to $25; (800) 639-9097; www.vtmozart.com.</p>
        <p>The Green Mountain Chew Chew food festival, June 23 to 25, features samplings from 40 restaurants and caterers at Waterfront Park, (802) 864-6674, everything from pulled pork sandwiches to gazpacho. Free admission; nine food tokens cost $5. Friday and Saturday 11 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Sunday 11 a.m. to 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>Originally bred for the Hapsburg Empire, majestic white Royal Lipizzan stallions perform amazing feats four times a week from July 6 to Aug. 20 at their summer home at Herrmann Farm, Route 2, in North Hero, 35 miles north of Burlington, (802) 372-5683. Admission is $8 to $15.</p>
        <p>Nostalgia for the over-40 set, something new for the rest: The Sunset Drive-In, Porter's Point Road off Route 127, Colchester (10 minutes from downtown), (802) 862-1800, shows double features on four screens from April to mid-September. Admission $7 for adults, free for those under 12.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>The Ethan Allen Homestead, (802) 865-4556, the 18th-century farmhouse of the Revolutionary War hero and flamboyant founder of the Green Mountain Boys, is set on the banks of the Winooski River. The timber house, gardens and an interactive archaeology exhibit are open to visitors. It's a grand spot for picnicking. Take Route 127 north to the first exit, then the first right. From mid-May to mid-June, 1 to 5 p.m. daily; mid-June to mid-October, Monday to Saturday 10 a.m. to 5 p.m., Sunday 1 to 5 p.m. Adults $4; www.ethanallen.together .com.</p>
        <p>There are several ways to take to the lake, including Lake Champlain Shoreline Cruises (choose a cruise without a meal), (802) 862-8300;  Lake Champlain Transportation, which runs ferries to New York, (802) 864-9804; sailing with Winds of Ireland, (800) 458-9301; kayaks, canoes and motorboats from Waterfront Boat Rentals, (802) 864-4858; and sailing cruises and charters from Whistling Man Schooner Company, (802) 862-7245.</p>
        <p>Certified scuba divers can visit Lake Champlain's Underwater Historic Preserve System, where they can see seven 19th-century sunken shipwrecks. The Waterfront Diving Center, (802) 865-2771 or (800) 283-7282, rents equipment and offers instruction.</p>
        <p>Shelburne Farms, about seven miles south of Burlington on 1611 Harbor Road, off Route 7, (802) 985-8686, is a working 1,400-acre farm with buildings from the late 19th and early 20th century. Depending on the time of day they visit, children can milk a cow, make butter, collect eggs and see cheese being made. Adults $5; guided property tours are $5 extra. Open daily 9 to 5 from mid-May through mid-October.</p>
        <p>The Shelburne Museum, Route 7 in Shelburne; (802) 985-3346, is an extraordinary eclectic collection of  more than 100,000 pieces of folk art, Americana and French Impressionist paintings assembled by Electra Havemeyer Webb. The museum, which opened in 1947, encompasses 37 buildings on 45 acres. Open 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. daily through Oct. 15; shorter hours in spring and fall. Closed January through March. Adults, $17.50 (a consecutive second day is free); www.shelburnemuseum .org.</p>
        <p>Watch and sample some of the best chocolate in the country as it is made at Lake Champlain Chocolates, 750 Pine Street, (802) 864-1808. Tours are given hourly from 9 a.m. to 2 p.m. Monday to Friday. Seconds are sold, from $9 to $12 a pound.</p>
        <p>Some of the most interesting parts of the city -- the lake shore, the Ethan Allen Homestead and the Hill section with its vintage mansions -- are easily accessible by bike. Touring bikes are $18 a day, in-line skates $14 at the Ski Rack, 85 Main Street, (802) 658-3313 or (800) 882-4530.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Heart of the Village Inn, 5347 Shelburne Street, (802) 985-2800; fax (802) 985-2870, is a bed-and-breakfast in a charming 1886 clapboard Queen Anne Victorian home in Shelburne. There are nine rooms, five in the main house and four in the converted carriage barn, all with private baths and furnished with period pieces. A hearty breakfast and afternoon tea are part of the package. Doubles are $95 to $205 year round; www .heartofthevillage.com.</p>
        <p>If you want to sleep like a Gilded Age millionaire, the grandest lodging is the Inn at Shelburne Farms, 1611 Harbor Road, Shelburne, (802) 985-8498, fax (802) 985-1233, a restored Queen Anne Revival country manor house on 4,000 acres with 24 guest rooms, 17 with private baths, on a point overlooking Lake Champlain, which was built by a member of the Vanderbilt family. Doubles, $100 to $310. Breakfast costs around $6 to $10 a person. Open mid-May through mid-October. The restaurant, which serves dinner, was expensive and erratic on my last visit.</p>
        <p>If you'd rather sleep like a bank president, book a room at the Willard Street Inn, 349 South Willard Street, (802) 651-8710; fax (802) 651-8714. This handsome Queen Anne/Colonial Georgian Revival style brick mansion, with a turret, was built in 1881 in the historic Hill district within walking distance of downtown. There are 14 rooms, done up in Victorian splendor, with private baths. A lavish breakfast is served in the solarium with a view of the lake and the English gardens. Doubles, $115 to $225 year round, including breakfast; www.willardstreetinn.com.</p>
        <p>Around half the 256 rooms overlook the waterfront and the lake at the Radisson Hotel Burlington, 60 Battery Street, (802) 658-6500, fax (802) 658-4659. The hotel has modern amenities and two restaurants, indoor pool and workout room. Doubles are priced from $179 to $199; www .radisson.com/burlingtonvt.</p>
        <p>The Anchorage Inn, 108 Dorset Street, off Route I-89, South Burlington, (800) 336-1869, fax (802) 658-3351, has 89 motel-style rooms, a heated indoor pool, whirlpool and sauna; doubles, $57 to $87, including coffee, juice and doughnuts at breakfast.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>At Smokejacks, 156 Church Street, (802) 658-1119, two grand chandeliers hang over a long wooden bar from the 1930's in a modern room with touches of Art Deco. The delicious contemporary food includes spicy hot corn soup and rare tuna with black sesame seeds on a bed of thinly sliced and julienned cucumbers with flying fish roe. On the intriguing list of cheeses, many are local. Dinner for two with a bottle of wine, around $70. Dinner nightly, lunch weekdays, brunch weekends.</p>
        <p>The Village Pump House Restaurant on Falls Road in Shelburne, (802) 985-3728, seats only 35, 40 if you count the bar, so reservations are a good idea, and essential on weekends. The Victorian house is decorated with old photographs on the walls and vintage furnishings. You might try succulent lamb shank; bean cake with a delicious salsa, and a fine lemon tart. Entrees, including soup and salad, are $21 to $26; desserts, $4.50. Wines start at $25 a bottle. Dinner Tuesday through Saturday.</p>
        <p>Slightly away from downtown, in the gentrified old North End, Scrumptious, 139 North Champlain Street, (802) 864-9220, in a bright and cheerful Victorian building, serves bold American food: cold cucumber soup, excellent hummus, a savory bean salad and a good spinach quiche. Handy for lunch when you are visiting the Ethan Allen Homestead, it's worth a trip at breakfast  for buttery almond croissants and the best cinnamon buns within 100 miles. Breakfast costs $3.50 to $5.50 a person, lunch $4.50 to $6.50. No alcoholic beverages are served. Open 6:45 a.m. to 3 p.m. Monday through Saturday.</p>
        <p>You can stop at Myer's Bagels, 377 Pine Street, (802) 863-5013, any time of day for the genuine article, crusty and dense. You can sit at Formica-topped tables and watch the bagels being baked in a wood-burning oven. A dozen plain bagels are $4.99; a bagel with smoked salmon and cream cheese, $4.25; with brisket and salad, $3.99. Open seven days, 4 a.m. to 4 p.m.</p>
        <p>Materials salvaged from Ireland were brought to the Marketplace, tile by tile and beam by beam, and set up last year as RiRa, an Irish pub, at 123 Church Street, (802) 860-9401. The name translates as ''a place where exuberance and revelry prevail.'' The food is simple and generally well prepared, particularly the mussels in white wine and beef and Guiness pie. Lunch is about $9; a two-course dinner runs $16; pints of beer start at $2.75, and desserts are around $5. Open daily from before noon to after midnight.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN MARIAN BURROS, a food columnist for The New York Times, spends part of each year in Burlington.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">MARIAN BURROS, a food columnist for The New York Times, spends part of each year in Burlington.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
