<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Memo; For Corzine and Florio, Money Bags vs. Baggage</title>
    <meta content="04JERS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204848"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Florio, James J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DA1F3CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Memo; For Corzine and Florio, Money Bags vs. Baggage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>political memo: for corz</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The state's newspapers are falling in behind Jim Florio. The party establishment is squarely backing Jon S. Corzine. The airwaves are full of nasty commercials about each of the Senate candidates. So what is a Democratic voter to do?</p>
        <p>The New Jersey primary season, which culminates in Tuesday's election, has been the most competitive in a generation. The retirement of Frank R. Lautenberg left a Senate seat open for the first time in decades. And though the Republican primary drew four reasonably experienced but little-known contenders, the Democratic contest between Mr. Florio, the former governor, and Mr. Corzine, who spent tens of millions to gain name recognition, gave rise to a rarity in state politics -- a match between two household names.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The state's newspapers are falling in behind Jim Florio. The party establishment is squarely backing Jon S. Corzine. The airwaves are full of nasty commercials about each of the Senate candidates. So what is a Democratic voter to do?</p>
        <p>The New Jersey primary season, which culminates in Tuesday's election, has been the most competitive in a generation. The retirement of Frank R. Lautenberg left a Senate seat open for the first time in decades. And though the Republican primary drew four reasonably experienced but little-known contenders, the Democratic contest between Mr. Florio, the former governor, and Mr. Corzine, who spent tens of millions to gain name recognition, gave rise to a rarity in state politics -- a match between two household names.</p>
        <p>''This is a singular story in New Jersey,'' said Clifford Zukin, a longtime political observer and director of The Star-Ledger/Eagleton Poll. ''We've never had a marquee matchup like this between two people universally known by the citizenry.''</p>
        <p>Because the race has been so hard fought and so well publicized, it has confronted voters with an unusual number of important questions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine, the former co-chairman of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, arose as the answer to a search by Democratic officials for an anyone-but-Florio candidate. Even though Mr. Florio remains popular with many rank-and-file Democrats, he  was considered by party leaders to be unelectable in November because of the memory of a $2.8 billion tax increase he pushed through the Legislature as governor in 1990.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's appeal to voters, not surprisingly, has been framed as a choice between an unhappy memory, embodied by Mr. Florio, and Mr. Corzine's own idealized vision for the future, with strict gun controls and ambitious new programs for health care, education and long-term care for the elderly and disabled. But to judge from the attack commercials Mr. Corzine has been running for more than a month, it remains, at its root, a not-Florio campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio, too, has naturally cast the race in terms that suit him. For months, he described the primary as a choice between his 30 years of experience in government and Mr. Corzine's naivete.</p>
        <p>More recently, Mr. Florio has seized upon Mr. Corzine's unprecedented campaign spending, asking voters whether they cared to let Mr. Corzine buy the election.</p>
        <p>Voters can seize on a few issues on which the men hold opposing views. Mr. Corzine opposes the death penalty, and Mr. Florio favors it, for example. And Mr. Corzine supports a limited investment of the Social Security trust fund in the stock market, to extend the fund's solvency, a position Mr. Florio has vilified in the starkest terms. But the sharp line between the men on this subject was blurred when it was reported that Mr. Florio's and Mr. Corzine's positions were identical as recently as a year ago.</p>
        <p>There are more subtle questions, too. A vote for Mr. Corzine's platform, for example -- with its hard-line support for abortion rights, gay rights, affirmative action, gun control and big government programs -- would seem to represent an embrace of the kind of liberalism that has been out of fashion for decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio, meanwhile, has in many ways made his own campaign a referendum on the nation's economic boom, warning voters that the fantastic wealth created by the new economy has momentarily obscured looming problems on issues like Social Security and pension financing.  Mr. Florio has hammered away at Mr. Corzine on trade policy, corporate mergers and government borrowing. In doing so, he has employed the kind of class-based attacks Democrats often aim at Republicans.</p>
        <p>If there is one watchword in the primary, however, it is electability. On the Republican side, voters must pick a contender for November from a field of four relatively unknown candidates: William L. Gormley, a veteran state senator from the south; Robert D. Franks, a four-term congressman from New Jersey's prosperous midsection; James W. Treffinger, a county executive in predominantly Democratic Essex County; and Murray Sabrin, a former Libertarian candidate for governor. In this race, where turnout is expected to be light, party endorsements are likely to play a heavy role.</p>
        <p>On the Democratic side, every attack that Mr. Florio and Mr. Corzine employ can be reduced to the idea that only one of them has a reasonable chance to prevail in November. To Mr. Florio, his foe is too left-wing, too soft. To Mr. Corzine, Mr. Florio is too combative to win over even the most moderate Republicans.</p>
        <p>''Democratic voters have to ask themselves whether they're selecting a candidate, be it Florio or Corzine, who can win,'' said Gerald M. Pomper, a political science professor at Rutgers University. ''Primaries are about such practical calculations. After all, you're selecting somebody to carry the party's banner, not just somebody you like.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
