<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Refinancing a Car Loan, It's Driver Beware</title>
    <meta content="04REFI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000611T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kravetz, Stacy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDD113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1299" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Refinancing a Car Loan, It's Driver Beware</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STACY KRAVETZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kravetz, Stacy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tracking every twitch in interest rates is developing into a national obsession; homeowners have become quite willing to refinance mortgages to capture favorable rates, but some are now also refinancing car loans; it is possible to save money by making larger payments for a shorter period, but many auto refinancings do the opposite, lowering monthly payments by stretching out loan term; some lenders will allow customers to borrow more than they owe on old loan, or even more than car is worth; while homes tend to appreciate or at least hold their value, new cars depreciate sharply, and borrowers are 'upside down' in loan, owing more than car is worth, when they drive off lot; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Gerald Jutting drove his 1997 Oldsmobile Bravada home from the dealership, he thought he had found a good deal. The interest rate on the loan the dealer secured for him from a local bank was 8.75 percent, better even than the employee rate at the bank where he works.</p>
        <p>Soon, though, he began seeing even more attractive rates advertised on the Internet. One Saturday Mr. Jutting, 51, typed an online application at the PeopleFirst.com Web site and was approved almost instantly. He refinanced his car.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Gerald Jutting drove his 1997 Oldsmobile Bravada home from the dealership, he thought he had found a good deal. The interest rate on the loan the dealer secured for him from a local bank was 8.75 percent, better even than the employee rate at the bank where he works.</p>
        <p>Soon, though, he began seeing even more attractive rates advertised on the Internet. One Saturday Mr. Jutting, 51, typed an online application at the PeopleFirst.com Web site and was approved almost instantly. He refinanced his car.</p>
        <p>The tracking of every twitch in interest rates has been developing into a bit of a national obsession for a while, and consumers have become quite willing to refinance home mortgages when rates bounce favorably. Playing hopscotch with car loans is a newer phenomenon, fraught with pitfalls for the incautious.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jutting's case illustrates the kind of situation in which refinancing makes sense. He refinanced the $20,000 balance he owed on his car at 7.49 percent for five years. His original note was for six years, so his new monthly payment is actually $25 larger, but he will make fewer payments; all told, he will save $800.</p>
        <p>But many auto refinancings do the opposite, lowering monthly payments by stretching out the term, and thus greatly increasing the total to be repaid. Some refinance lenders will let consumers borrow more than they owe on their old loan, or even more than the car is worth -- giving borrowers extra cash to use as they wish, but leaving them deeper in debt than before.</p>
        <p>Refinancing of car loans is growing rapidly, with much of the action online, and lenders are stepping up marketing efforts. Reasons for the tactic's rising popularity can be found at both ends of the consumer sophistication spectrum. Relatively savvy car buyers, like Mr. Jutting, who for one reason or another have gotten stuck with high-rate loans are eager to replace them with lower rates; others with less financial acumen may respond to the siren song of lenders' advertising -- and mistake lower payments for less debt.</p>
        <p>SAVING the consumer money is the heart of the lender's pitch, of course, a pitch often directed to the names in commercial databases of recent car-loan borrowers. One recent mailing from Auto-refi Financial Services says ''save up to $40+ per month'' in eye-catching type. A company spokeswoman said its officials were not ready to discuss its offer, which she called a prototype, with a reporter.</p>
        <p>In general, auto refinancings work the way home refinancings do. The new lender pays off an existing loan in full and replaces it with a new loan on different terms -- a longer or shorter term, a higher or lower interest rate.</p>
        <p>But there is a crucial difference. Homes tend to rise in value over time, or at least hold their value. But new cars depreciate sharply, especially in the early going, when  they are often worth far less than what is owed on them. That condition is called being upside down.</p>
        <p>''If you paid sticker price with a low down payment, you're upside down in your loan when you drive off the lot,'' said Tamela Rich, director of auto development at LendingTree, a Web site that helps arrange loans.</p>
        <p>Consider a year-old BMW 528i sedan that sold new for $40,000. If the owner put down $2,000 and borrowed at 10 percent for five years, the $11,684 paid so far still leaves a balance of $38,736 on the loan. That is because, like a home mortgage, a car loan's early payments are mostly interest, not principal. But the Kelley Blue Book trade-in value of the car has fallen by now to $33,005.</p>
        <p>This is a financially dangerous time for the car owner; neither a sale nor an accident that totals the car will yield enough to repay the loan. A refinancing that extends the term or increases the amount borrowed, as many do, will make matters worse, prolonging the upside-down period.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, though, a refinancing is just what is needed to correct a borrowing mistake. ''So many customers go into the dealership and haggle over the price of the car until they get to where they can see the light at the end of the tunnel -- and then lose their guard a bit when it comes to financing,'' said Bob Ferber, an auto finance executive at eloan.com, an Internet-based lender. Eloan says that about one-quarter of visitors to its Web site want to refinance car loans.</p>
        <p>The very low promotional interest rates automakers have long offered on some models are beginning to dry up -- DaimlerChrysler said last week it would almost entirely stop offering them -- and the run-of-the-mill loan rates available through dealers are usually a bit higher than can be obtained directly from banks or credit unions.</p>
        <p>BORROWERS with stained or strained credit can also benefit. Making even a few timely payments on the kind of high-interest loan offered to a ''subprime'' borrower may qualify the consumer to refinance at a lower rate.</p>
        <p>Given the Federal Reserve's recent efforts to head off incipient inflation by increasing interest rates, general declines in consumer rates are probably not in the immediate offing. And if they were, they would be more likely to show up in mortgage rates, which are more volatile than auto loan rates.</p>
        <p>There are many loan provisions to pay attention to besides the rate and term. The old loan agreement may have features like gap insurance, warranties, and credit life and disability insurance that may be missing from a refinance offer.</p>
        <p>And timing is important. Lenders prefer to refinance vehicles that are less than six months old, when they still may be worth 80 percent or more of the purchase price. Cars much more than a year old may be rejected as having too little collateral value. Lenders rarely advance more than 130 percent of the car's value.</p>
        <p>Still, the annual percentage rate is ''the one number a customer should focus on,'' said Doug Lebda, chief executive officer of LendingTree.com, because lenders are required by law to calculate it in a way that allows apples-to-apples comparisons.</p>
        <p>Things to Ponder in Reassessing Debt</p>
        <p>A KNEE-BUCKLING car payment may have you thinking refinance, but unless you are sorely strapped for immediate cash, a new loan that lowers the payment by stretching the term may do more long-term harm than short-term good. Here are some points to keep in mind when considering an auto loan refinancing.</p>
        <p>* Home equity beats car equity. Rates on home equity loans are often lower than car loans, with an added bonus: the interest is usually tax deductible. ''If you own a home and have equity, nearly 100 percent of the time the right solution is to refinance your house,'' not your car, said Doug Lebda of LendingTree.com, a Web site where borrowers can solicit loan offers from lenders.</p>
        <p>* Apply selectively. The Internet makes applying for loans almost too easy. According to Bankrate.com, the banking industry data firm, many consumers do not realize that a flurry of applications in a short time, including inquiries to services like LendingTree, can damage their credit rating before they have borrowed a penny.</p>
        <p>* Know where you stand in lenders' eyes. Making even a single timely payment on a high-rate car loan can improve your credit score enough to qualify for a new loan at a lower rate for the same term -- just the situation where a refinancing makes the most sense.</p>
        <p>STACY KRAVETZ</p>
        <p>PERSONAL BUSINESS  Correction:  June 11, 2000, Sunday  An article last Sunday about refinancing car loans misstated some aspects of a five-year, $38,000 loan at 10 percent interest. After making payments for one year, the borrower would owe $31,833 principal on the loan, not $38,736. An average of 39 percent of the first-year payment amount, not a majority, is applied to interest on such a loan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 11, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about refinancing car loans misstated some aspects of a five-year, $38,000 loan at 10 percent interest. After making payments for one year, the borrower would owe $31,833 principal on the loan, not $38,736. An average of 39 percent of the first-year payment amount, not a majority, is applied to interest on such a loan.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
