<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Room at the Top</title>
    <meta content="04BARC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barcott, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">True Summit (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5DE123DF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Room at the Top</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bruce Barcott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barcott, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Barcott reviews book True Summit: What Really Happened on the Legendary Ascent of Annapurna by David Roberts; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>True Summit</p>
        <p>What Really Happened on the</p>
        <p>Legendary Ascent of Annapurna.</p>
        <p>By David Roberts.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 239 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>True Summit</p>
        <p>What Really Happened on the</p>
        <p>Legendary Ascent of Annapurna.</p>
        <p>By David Roberts.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 239 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $24.</p>
        <p>Readers of Jon Krakauers best-selling chronicle of the 1996 Mount Everest disaster may be surprised to learn that ''Into Thin Air is not the most popular mountaineering book of all time. The reigning champ, with 11 million copies sold, is Maurice Herzogs ''Annapurna, the story of the French mountaineers who in 1950 reached the summit of Annapurna, the first of the worlds 14 peaks above 26,000 feet to be scaled. Herzogs harrowing adventure, with its Gallic sense of drama, romance and camaraderie, concludes with a stirring final line -- There are other Annapurnas in the lives of men -- that still inspires adventurers to answer the challenge of the mountains.</p>
        <p>On the occasion of the 50th anniversary of the Annapurna ascent, which was yesterday, the American author and climber David Roberts revisits that historic expedition in ''True Summit and finds troubling new meaning in Herzogs famous phrase. ''Other Annapurnas, it turns out, did exist -- in the memories of the authors own climbing mates. In order to preserve the legend of Frances greatest climb, and perhaps his own reputation as well, Herzog suppressed competing versions of the Annapurna climb for nearly 50 years.</p>
        <p>The trouble began before the expedition left Paris. When the climbers were about to board their plane, Herzog, the expedition leader, surprised his comrades with a contract that forbade them from publishing anything about the climb for five years. Thus Herzog assured himself the first word on Annapurna and denied his fellow climbers the chance to earn a little coin for their work. Herzog was a successful Parisian businessman, but his principal climbers were three mountain guides from Chamonix -- Louis Lachenal, Lionel Terray and Gaston Rebuffat -- who sacrificed their lucrative summer season for the unpaid chance at Annapurna. While Herzogs audience later read that the climbers ''only motive was a great ideal, his teammates silently gnashed their teeth. (In fairness, Roberts points out that the profits from ''Annapurna went to the French Mountain Federation, not to Herzog.)</p>
        <p>On June 3, 1950, Herzog and Lachenal set out for the top, without supplemental oxygen, clad in thin leather boots. As he felt his feet go numb with frostbite, Lachenal initiated one of the most famous exchanges in climbing:</p>
        <p>''If I go back, he asked Herzog, ''what will you do?</p>
        <p>''I should go on by myself, Herzog replied.</p>
        <p>Continuing on meant the loss of Lachenals toes; turning back meant the loss of Herzogs life. ''Then Ill follow you, the gallant montagnard said.</p>
        <p>The exchange becomes all the more moving in light of the aftermath laid out in ''True Summit. Lachenal, toeless, melted into obscurity as Herzog, fingerless, became a national hero on the order of Jacques Cousteau. Paris Match magazine celebrated Herzog in a cover story that failed to mention Lachenal at all and, incredibly, referred to the camera ''that accompanied him to the summit and captured the famous image of Herzog holding the French tricolor aloft.</p>
        <p>''It was as if the camera had been Herzogs only teammate on the summit, and the photo had taken itself, Roberts writes.</p>
        <p>Lachenals erasure continued even after his death in 1955. His Annapurna diary, which often conflicted with Herzogs narrative and exposed the expeditions infighting and tedium, fell under the posthumous guardianship of an editor who prepared a published version cleansed of all passages that might tarnish the legend. The editor? Maurice Herzog.</p>
        <p>The Annapurna myth began to crack when Lachenals unexpurgated diaries and a biography of Rebuffat were published in 1996. Roberts uses those books and more recent interviews to give us a balanced overview of the Annapurna expedition, but ''True Summit isnt merely a better-sourced retelling of a 50-year-old story. Roberts uses the new revelations to deliver a long delayed glory to Louis Lachenal and to explore the tension between the demands of narrative, the duty of historical accuracy and the fallibility of memory.</p>
        <p>Through a triumph of irony, Herzog alone among the climbers survives to commemorate the expeditions 50th anniversary. When Roberts interviewed him in 1999, Herzog offered no apologies. He had considered having each expedition member write one chapter in the book, he explained, but that would have sold 1,000 copies at most. Herzog then asked Roberts rhetorically why the book had sold millions of copies, and provided his own answer: '' 'Annapurna is a sort of novel. Its a novel, but a true novel.</p>
        <p>The thing about novels is they come neatly wrapped -- action is consistent with character, and events have meaning. Real life, especially at 26,000 feet, tends to fray with inconsistency and chance. In the case of Herzog, Roberts concludes, his constant burnishing of the Annapurna legend wasnt necessarily cynical. It was more likely ''the fruit of memorys seizing again and again on disturbing, pivotal events, reshaping them with each rehearsal, trying to find meaning where there was only happenstance. That, and the preservation of a fantastic story.</p>
        <p>Bruce Barcott is a contributing editor at Outside magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bruce Barcott is a contributing editor at Outside magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
