<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fortune Telling For Profit And Policy</title>
    <meta content="04VIEW$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic View</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E3DC113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fortune Telling For Profit And Policy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Economic View column predicts Federal Reserve will raise interest rates once or twice by end of summer and will then call a time out; predicts upcoming federal budget surplus projections will rise substantially (M),</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS column has been lent a crystal ball for one week. Reception is a bit fuzzy, but here goes.</p>
        <p>The Federal Reserve will raise interest rates once or twice by the end of the summer, and then will call a time out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS column has been lent a crystal ball for one week. Reception is a bit fuzzy, but here goes.</p>
        <p>The Federal Reserve will raise interest rates once or twice by the end of the summer, and then will call a time out.</p>
        <p>Six rate increases in less than a year, to little obvious effect, have left economists and analysts fretting that monetary policy has lost its punch. But now there are at least tentative signs that the rip-roaring economy is slowing. Moreover, the Fed still has faith in its tools, and after tightening by another quarter-point at the end of this month, and perhaps again in August if its hawks insist, it will pause to reassess the outlook.</p>
        <p>It is clear that technology and globalization have changed the economy in ways that even Alan Greenspan does not fully understand, and slowing its growth may require a bigger dose of interest-rate medicine than in business cycles past.</p>
        <p>But monetary policy seems to be working much the way it always has. Long-term interest rates on corporate debt have risen substantially, and companies are turning away from bond issuance and toward bank loans and commercial paper to avoid being locked into high-cost long-term debt.</p>
        <p>At some point, the cost of borrowing short-term will rise so much that companies will choose to defer plans to expand or modernize -- or they will absorb the higher interest costs in the form of diminished profits. Either way, business activity and the economy will slow.</p>
        <p>Consumer mortgage rates have jumped and the housing market is cooling. Retail spending may have peaked. Stocks are volatile but no longer rising relentlessly.</p>
        <p>Unemployment is still so low, and consumer confidence so high, that Mr. Greenspan and his colleagues are not comfortable holstering their weapons quite yet. But unless the stock market takes off again or unambiguous acceleration in growth and inflation appear, the Fed will show great patience later this year.</p>
        <p>The federal budget surplus will again prove larger than expected, with implications for the presidential race and the bond market.</p>
        <p>Congress and the White House will update their long-term surplus projections over the summer; both will rise substantially, reflecting the strength of tax receipts this year and the spreading consensus that the economy is capable of higher rates of noninflationary growth than in the past. The economy has been so strong that economists now expect a fiscal-2000 surplus of at least $200 billion and perhaps $225 billion; in January the Congressional Budget Office was estimating $176 billion.</p>
        <p>Even if growth slows substantially, the economy will still be bigger than had been forecast, yielding more tax revenue, and the budget office has gradually been raising its estimates of growth potential.</p>
        <p>Economists at Goldman, Sachs recently raised the possibility that this summer's new surplus numbers could allow the federal government to pay off the entire $3.5 trillion national debt held by the public as soon as 2007, six years ahead of the Clinton administration's current schedule.</p>
        <p>More money on the table would give George W. Bush an opportunity to argue that the nation can afford both his big tax cut plan and his proposal to create private investment accounts within Social Security. Vice President Al Gore would get a chance to call both for accelerated reduction of the national debt and for additional spending on Democratic priorities like adding prescription drug coverage to Medicare.</p>
        <p>Defining and nurturing the new economy will emerge as a major political issue.</p>
        <p>In Congress -- especially in the House -- the two parties will continue falling all over each other to prove that they are au courant with the wired world (and happy to receive its campaign contributions).</p>
        <p>Republicans will push through a bill to extend for five years the current moratorium on Internet taxation, and the two parties will reach agreement on granting more visas to skilled workers from abroad to meet demand from technology companies.</p>
        <p>The whole topic of the government's role in the new economy will take center stage when the federal judge presiding over the Microsoft antitrust case orders, perhaps this week, that the company be broken up.</p>
        <p>But even as they maneuver for political advantage, politicians will continue trying to decipher what these issues mean to voters. A recent poll by the centrist Democratic Leadership Council found voters to be optimistic about the new economy's prospects, dubious that it should be regulated like any other industry and willing to endure more frequent job changes but insistent that government support job training and education.</p>
        <p>Full disclosure: This crystal ball appears to be a prototype, and carries no warranty. Check back in a few months to determine its accuracy.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
