<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Footlights</title>
    <meta content="04FOOT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westchester Chamber Orchestra</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershenson, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E7DE133CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Footlights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershenson, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Westchester Chamber Orchestra unveils plans for fifth annual Summer Jazz Institute for Homeless Children at Westhab Family Center in Elmsford, NY; summer activities will include free public concert by students and orchestra members at St Gabriel's Church in New Rochelle (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Youngsters Take Their Bows</p>
        <p>It's the season for young artists to take their bows, not just in public and private schools but also at performances of community after-school programs.</p>
        <p>Barry Charles Hoffman, founder and artistic director of the Westchester Chamber Orchestra, keeps finding new ways to help disadvantaged children make music. His intensive Summer Jazz Institute for Homeless Children at the Westhab Family Center in Elmsford, now in its fifth year, will immerse 36 youngsters in three weeks of daily music theory, ear training, jazz history and their choice of lessons on the trumpet, alto sax or double bass. This year's program, to take place in August, will also include children from the Coachman in White Plains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Youngsters Take Their Bows</p>
        <p>It's the season for young artists to take their bows, not just in public and private schools but also at performances of community after-school programs.</p>
        <p>Barry Charles Hoffman, founder and artistic director of the Westchester Chamber Orchestra, keeps finding new ways to help disadvantaged children make music. His intensive Summer Jazz Institute for Homeless Children at the Westhab Family Center in Elmsford, now in its fifth year, will immerse 36 youngsters in three weeks of daily music theory, ear training, jazz history and their choice of lessons on the trumpet, alto sax or double bass. This year's program, to take place in August, will also include children from the Coachman in White Plains.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoffman has commissioned a three-minute piece called ''Peanut Butter and Jelly'' for a group of second through sixth graders who take after-school classes at Songcatchers, a volunteer arts organization based in New Rochelle. The idea is for the 30 children, playing instruments on which they have had group lessons, to alternate in the call and response pattern of the piece with members of the chamber orchestra.</p>
        <p>Students and orchestra members will spend time getting to know one another at a lecture-demonstration, rehearsal and dinner. Then they will perform for and with one another in a free concert open to the public. The time is June 16 at 8 p.m., and the place is St. Gabriel's Church in New Rochelle.</p>
        <p>A Musical for Teenage Talent</p>
        <p>Theater-savvy teenagers at the Amadeus Conservatory of Music in Chappaqua, meanwhile, are sweating out the chords and rhythms of a contemporary musical, ''RumpelStiltSkin,'' written by Adam David Cohen and Kevin Laub. Deborah Molodofsky, Amadeus's violin-playing director, seems to have stumbled on her own Pied Piper in Mr. Cohen, who serves as the school's musical theater director. She hired him, she said, and ''the next thing I knew, the teenagers started knocking on our door.''</p>
        <p>Why? ''These kids love to sing,'' she said. ''It's a real passion for them.''</p>
        <p>But not just any songs. Not just ''Pippin,'' ''Joseph and the Amazing Technicolor Dreamcoat'' or Rodgers and Hammerstein.</p>
        <p>Cohen, like Sondheim, is not always hummable, Ms. Molodofsky said. ''These kids are handling material that would be tough for professionals,'' she said. ''We're stretching them.'' Dates for the show are next Friday (8 p.m.) and Saturday (3 and 8 p.m.) in the Whippoorwill Theater of the North Castle Public Library. Tickets are $14 at the door and $12 if ordered in advance (238-0388).</p>
        <p>Youthful Recital of Dance Forms</p>
        <p>Andrew Vereen has been part of Youth Theater Interactions for 22 of his 30 years. Now he's the full-time paid office manager of the Yonkers program, but his involvement began like many other 8-year-olds in his community: taking African dance, mime and drum lessons after school. ''It kept me off the streets,'' he said, adding that many of the group's graduates go on to college and success in the arts or business. Youth Theater's acting troupe tours schools and summer camps with plays on AIDS and violence prevention as well as skits about the do's and don'ts of a job interview.</p>
        <p>On most afternoons, the place is packed with 125 children 9 through 19, and there is a perpetual waiting list. Next Sunday from 1:30 to 4:30 p.m., the group will present its 27th annual recital of dance, percussion, hip hop, jazz, ballet, Haitian folklore and steel band at the Fox Fire School in Yonkers.  Proceeds from the requested donation of $12  ($6 for students and those over 65) will go toward a scholarship fund.</p>
        <p>Theft of Musical Instruments</p>
        <p>Musical instruments have suddenly become literally hot items for some Westchester teenagers. A possibly related rash of thefts of school band instruments broke out last month in Scarsdale and Eastchester, where police are working together to find the thieves and recover the instruments. In all, 14 instruments were stolen in Scarsdale, and four in Eastchester.</p>
        <p>Two Scarsdale High School students were arrested on felony charges for stealing trumpets, saxophones, clarinets and other instruments from the middle and high school band rooms and trying to sell them over the Internet. Lt. Bryant Clark said that six of the instruments had been recovered, including a trombone, which a student had already replaced for $2,500. The arrests were made, Lieutenant Clark said, after police, acting on tips, scanned various auction sites on the Web. He said that the investigation was continuing.</p>
        <p>Detective Sgt. Mario Astarita of the Eastchester Police Department said two saxophones valued at $695 each, a $450 flute and a clarinet had been reported missing from the middle-high school band room. None of the instruments have been recovered.  ''Right now we can't tie the thefts together with Scarsdale's, but we're working closely on it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>ROBERTA HERSHENSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
