<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Mall Proposal Unfolds, Residents Fear More Cars</title>
    <meta content="04MALL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: ELMHURST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Queens Center Mall (Nyc)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Macerich Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'grady, Jim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4DB113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="460" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Mall Proposal Unfolds, Residents Fear More Cars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM O'GRADY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'grady, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Plans released by Macerich Co, which is managing redevelopment of Queens Center Mall in Elmhurst, NYC, draw mixed reaction from local residents and elected officials; latest plan calls for further expansion by spring 2003; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The glamour quotient at the Queens Center Mall may be small to nonexistent, but its sales-per-square-foot numbers are huge. So the Macerich Company, which is managing the redevelopment of the somewhat nondescript mall, plans to expand it by spring 2003.</p>
        <p>But some of the just-released details of the expansion have drawn a mixed reaction from local residents and elected officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The glamour quotient at the Queens Center Mall may be small to nonexistent, but its sales-per-square-foot numbers are huge. So the Macerich Company, which is managing the redevelopment of the somewhat nondescript mall, plans to expand it by spring 2003.</p>
        <p>But some of the just-released details of the expansion have drawn a mixed reaction from local residents and elected officials.</p>
        <p>Members of Community Board 4, Borough president Claire Shulman and the City Planning Commission have already approved the company's plan to add 420,000 square feet of retail space and 800 new parking spaces to the mall. But new renderings of the site have left Councilwoman Helen Marshall, for one, worried about gridlock in her district, especially on congested Queens Boulevard. The City Council has until early July to vote on the plan.</p>
        <p>''I think the expansion will probably bring it up to date as a modern mall,'' she said. ''But I'm not satisfied that we will not be stampeded by cars, especially on holidays.''</p>
        <p>John Genovese, a spokesman for Macerich, said traffic circulation around the mall would be improved by new entrances on Queens Boulevard and on 57th Avenue that would have drop-off and pick-up lanes, and by four new car bridges that would connect an existing parking garage to a new seven-story garage. He added that a pedestrian bridge over 92nd Street would link the mall to a new building with stores that would rise on what is now a city parking lot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Genovese claimed that these modifications would allow cars and people, once they arrived at the mall, to move around it without using local roads, as is now the case.</p>
        <p>The district manager of Community Board 4, Rose Rothschild, said that few residents had expressed opposition to the mall expansion. But she said that when a Queens developer announced its plan for a multiplex theater on 57th Avenue with 300 new parking spots, she took calls from residents who worried that the two projects combined would attract a glut of cars to the area.</p>
        <p>She added that the parking squeeze is worsened by commuters who park in the mall and catch a bus or subway to Manhattan. She said  the board asked Macerich not to sell long-term permits for the new spots.</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: ELMHURST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
