<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Memphis-on-Hudson?</title>
    <meta content="04COLU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTY LINES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Applebome, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EFD9153CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Memphis-on-Hudson?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Applebome, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Applebome column on plethora of New Yorkers living in Westchester County suggests that, with some qualifying prohibitions, people from America's heartland be imported; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I DON'T want to be rude, but after moving back to New York a few years ago, I've come to realize what's wrong with New York, something I hadn't expected. It's full of New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Now, I don't have anything in particular against New Yorkers. I was born here. My parents were born here. Some of my best friends are New Yorkers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I DON'T want to be rude, but after moving back to New York a few years ago, I've come to realize what's wrong with New York, something I hadn't expected. It's full of New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Now, I don't have anything in particular against New Yorkers. I was born here. My parents were born here. Some of my best friends are New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>But when I moved to Westchester after two decades in Dallas, Houston and Atlanta, I expected to find the best and the brightest, or at least the pushiest and most ambitious, from around the country. After all, in Dallas, Houston and Atlanta, you almost never meet a native. Everyone is from someplace else.</p>
        <p>Instead, I've come to realize that whenever anyone moves in anywhere near me, they're either lawyers and financial types from Manhattan or people who make a lot of money selling something in Brooklyn or the Bronx. (No one from Queens moves to Westchester, and as far as I can tell no one has ever lived on Staten Island.)</p>
        <p>Of course, there are exceptions. There's a new couple across town from us who come from Arkansas via Washington and drive in elaborate motorcades. Westchester has high-end pockets of French, German and Australian expatriates and areas with low-income Mexicans and Salvadorans. But mostly we're all New Yorkers on this bus.</p>
        <p>Maybe this shouldn't be a problem. Paris is full of Parisians, Arkansas of Arkansans. It's not all that astonishing that Westchester is full of New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Still, in the interests of diversity, and a kinder, gentler Westchester I have a modest proposal. Why not import people, the way countries in Europe import workers, not just to fill jobs but to spice things up and perhaps encourage the natives to chill out?</p>
        <p>We'd get a few more non-Type A's, some restaurateurs who don't think that a couple of tacos, rice and beans have to cost $12.95, and parents who don't assume their little genius has to go to Harvard. It would be nice to run into more people who went to Ohio State, who know what a meat and three is, who don't need to be told that the rest of us on the train don't want to listen to your stupid cell phone conversation with your lawyer all the way from Grand Central to White Plains.</p>
        <p>There are two ways to do this. The first, the random dispersal model, would recruit heartlanders and sprinkle them randomly across Westchester. Finding the immigrants should not be hard -- you could just set up booths at shopping malls across America. But I'm worried that the housing allowance -- hundreds of thousands of dollars to allow them to approximate their current housing at exorbitant Westchester prices -- is something that only the geniuses who ran Nassau County into the ground could deem prudent.</p>
        <p>An alternative would be the targeted relocation model, which would call for turning various Westchester locales into little outposts of Americana in exile. A community of South Carolinians with colorful spats over the Confederate battle flag here, a pod of mellow Californians there, a gaggle of earnest Nebraskans someplace else.</p>
        <p>The tricky part, of course, is which local communities to repopulate. As the Ur, high-end Westchester suburbs, Scarsdale and Bronxville get to stay the way they are. It's hard to imagine Yonkers as full of anything other than New Yorkers or Sleepy Hollow full of Cajuns from Louisiana.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Pleasantville clearly wants to be full of perky, polite Midwesterners. Dobbs Ferry has the unpretentious sound of some town along the Chattahoochee in Georgia. Jefferson Valley could easily be in Virginia. And whatever locales are selected, Westchester would benefit from semiautonomous duchies with modest country music dives and people who wait patiently in line, say ''Y'all come back,'' and expect to sell their fancy houses for $250,000 or so.</p>
        <p>Sure there could be problems. You couldn't allow towns to impose the death penalty, like back home. Maybe we don't need a bunch of helmet-head televangelists and bass fishing shows on Channel 12. The first football game between the lads from Rye or Larchmont and the behemoths from Texas and Oklahoma would not be pretty.</p>
        <p>And, to make it clear there are some minimal standards, here's my bottom line: No NASCAR tracks. And no matter how many Hoosiers move to Harrison, we're not taking Bobby Knight.</p>
        <p>COUNTY LINES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
