<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italian Standards and American Classics</title>
    <meta content="04DINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Il Giglio (Locust Valley, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DE153CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italian Standards and American Classics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Il Giglio restaurant in Locust Valley, Long Island, NY (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR nearly four years, the building at the corner of Birch Hill and Buckram Roads in Locust Valley, the former home of Caminari's, was empty. Its diamond-paned windows were dark. Now, Il Giglio is pumping life into this landmark.</p>
        <p>Well-heeled Gold Coasters will feel right at home here. Il Giglio is understated, subdued and quietly elegant. Comfortable chairs, well-spaced tables, thick carpeting and soft lighting create a haven where diners want to linger. It's a place where quiet table conversation is easy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR nearly four years, the building at the corner of Birch Hill and Buckram Roads in Locust Valley, the former home of Caminari's, was empty. Its diamond-paned windows were dark. Now, Il Giglio is pumping life into this landmark.</p>
        <p>Well-heeled Gold Coasters will feel right at home here. Il Giglio is understated, subdued and quietly elegant. Comfortable chairs, well-spaced tables, thick carpeting and soft lighting create a haven where diners want to linger. It's a place where quiet table conversation is easy.</p>
        <p>The lovely dining room subtly works its charm. There are roses on the tables and the creamy napery is echoed in the diaphanous drapes at the windows. Shaded sconces cast a warm glow on wood-paneled walls.</p>
        <p>The menu is also comforting, familiar and nonthreatening. Italian standards are joined by American classics like rack of lamb, grilled salmon and shrimp cocktail. There are also Continental favorites rarely encountered nowadays outside country club dining rooms: chateaubriand, duck a l'orange and filet mignon Rossini topped with truffles and pate de foie gras. Unfortunately, or thankfully (depending on one's cholesterol count and point of view), the pate was absent from the steak we sampled. The waiter who delivered the dish made no mention of the missing ingredient.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to service: it seems better than it is. Waiters are gracious, numerous and ever-present, replacing used silver, decrumbing the table and refilling water glasses. But one evening, when half our party arrived 15 minutes late, the crew was thrown into a tailspin. We never received the complimentary olives and cheese every other table had, an empty butter dish stayed that way and servers were spinning their wheels, never quite sure who ordered which dish.</p>
        <p>The food is also mixed. We enjoyed a red snapper filet, lightly turned out with a tasty topper of black olives and garlic chunks, that was in the ''best ever'' category. We also had a disappointing, overcooked Dover sole napped with a thick, overpowering orange sauce.</p>
        <p>The rest of the dishes ranged between these two, with underseasoning being the biggest flaw. This was certainly true of a creamy risotto Milanese that was utterly tasteless, as were pasta triangles filled with artichokes in a fresh tomato sauce. The lackluster Caesar salad and the nothing-special capricciosa salad of mixed greens with tomatoes and peppers also needed flavor boosts.</p>
        <p>Openers that made the grade were the tiny, tender clams oreganato, lightly sprinkled with bread crumbs; the super shrimp cocktail with four jumbos and a sit-up-and-take-notice cocktail sauce, and the crabmeat cocktail enfolded in a lush Louis sauce.</p>
        <p>Entrees were generally better. A roast duck special with crisp skin and a tangy orange sauce was a hit, as were the quartet of baby lamb chops in a balsamic sauce and the simple yet simply delicious grilled salmon. Also getting high marks were the pounded and breaded veal chop topped with salad and tomatoes and the delicate veal scaloppine crowned with slices of tomato and a glaze of melted mozzarella. But a special lobster tail in a fra diavolo sauce set over linguine lacked verve.</p>
        <p>Desserts are ordinary. The tiramisu was not nearly creamy enough, and the chocolate mousse was grainy. The best bets are the poached pear mated with a scoop of vanilla ice cream and the yummy citrus-flavored cheesecake.</p>
        <p>Il Giglio  One Buckram Road, Locust Valley, (516) 609-2999.</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Sedate, elegant dining room.  SERVICE -- Gracious, attentive but still needs work.  SOUND LEVEL -- Civilized.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Shrimp cocktail, crabmeat cocktail, clams oreganato, red snapper, salmon, duck a l'orange, scaloppine with tomato and mozzarella, breaded veal chop, lamb chops, poached pear, cheesecake.  WINE LIST -- Pricey, diverse list of nearly 100 selections, with prices starting in the mid-$20's.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch, entrees $9.75 to $13.75. At dinner, appetizers $5 to $10.50; entrees $18.50 to $29.75.  CREDIT CARDS -- All the majors.  HOURS -- Lunch, noon to 2:30 p.m. Monday through Friday. Dinner, 5:30 to 10:30 p.m. Monday through Thursday, till 11:30 p.m. Friday and Saturday, and 4 to 9 p.m. Sunday.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- A dozen steps at main entrance but none at side door on Birch Hill Road.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
