<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Showing Off The Profusion Of a Culture</title>
    <meta content="04ROHT$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204530"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E3DD143CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Showing Off The Profusion Of a Culture</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>SAO PAULO, Brazil</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Larry Rohter reviews Rediscovery Show: Brazil+500, which opened in last April with 15,000 objects on display in 13 modules in four buildings in Sao Paulo, largest and most ambitious display of Brazilian visual arts ever assembled; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOTHING is ever done on a small scale here in the largest city in Latin America's largest country. So when cultural and business leaders gathered a few years back to plan how to commemorate the 500th anniversary of the Portuguese colonization of Brazil, it was preordained that they would want to make a bold, sweeping statement about the state of the arts in Brazil.</p>
        <p>Even so, the dimensions of the mega-exhibition that opened here in late April exceed all expectations. With nearly 15,000 objects on display in 13 separate ''modules'' in four buildings that have a combined area larger than the Louvre, ''The Rediscovery Show: Brazil+500'' is, quite simply, the largest and most ambitious display of Brazilian visual arts ever assembled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOTHING is ever done on a small scale here in the largest city in Latin America's largest country. So when cultural and business leaders gathered a few years back to plan how to commemorate the 500th anniversary of the Portuguese colonization of Brazil, it was preordained that they would want to make a bold, sweeping statement about the state of the arts in Brazil.</p>
        <p>Even so, the dimensions of the mega-exhibition that opened here in late April exceed all expectations. With nearly 15,000 objects on display in 13 separate ''modules'' in four buildings that have a combined area larger than the Louvre, ''The Rediscovery Show: Brazil+500'' is, quite simply, the largest and most ambitious display of Brazilian visual arts ever assembled.</p>
        <p>''We are not partisans here of the notion that less is more,'' Nelson Aguilar, the exhibition's chief curator, said dryly. As a result, the exhibition, which has a $25 million budget, ranges from the Stone Age to the 21st century, with lingering stops along the way to examine and admire the fusion of European, African and Amerindian components that is the main characteristic of Brazil's complicated cultural mix.</p>
        <p>''Things didn't start out that way, but we would find one important piece, which would lead us to another, and before we knew it, the project had taken on a life of its own,'' explained Edemar Cid Ferreira, a prominent Sao Paulo banker who is president of the exhibition's organizing committee. ''So what we ended up with is a panorama of Brazil that says to both Brazilians and the rest of the world that this country has a cultural density that few others can match.''</p>
        <p>The section that may most surprise the average visitor is the one devoted to what is designated as ''Popular Art.'' Brazilians have often looked upon the folk and ''primitive'' art produced around them with marked disdain, reserving their admiration for more formal manifestations of high art, but this section of the show, which is perhaps the largest, is likely to force a reassessment.</p>
        <p>Wood engravings and earthenware figures from Pernambuco, carved figureheads for boats sailing the Sao Francisco River, ex-votos from the churches of the Northeast, papier mache masks from carnival and folk festivals, even homemade rudimentary toys: all have found their way into the exhibition, mounted with respect and affection. Indeed, the sheer volume and variety of the pieces is a powerful demonstration of the remarkable fecundity of the popular imagination.</p>
        <p>''You have to look at this art as something that is ours, ours in the sense that it is not linked to any canon except our own,'' said Emanoel Araujo, the exhibition's curator. ''This is art that comes from the very core of our being, and the objective is precisely to show that these artists are profound in their own way, that they are not beings from some other planet but from this earth, expressing the strengths of this people.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Araujo is also the driving force behind ''Black in Body and Soul,'' a unit that displays art both by and about blacks. It includes objects that have little to do with Brazil -- photographs by Robert Mapplethorpe, French colonial postcards of quotidian scenes in West Africa in the 1930's -- as well as chains and other ''instruments of punishment'' from the days of slavery. But Mr. Araujo said the message he wanted to convey was as much political as aesthetic.</p>
        <p>''The racial question is always one and the same, with the same ancestry, no matter where in the black diaspora you happen to be, and that is what this exhibit is addressing,'' he said. ''I want a positive construction of the black image, so this is not an exposition of Afro-Brazilian art, but an exposition about black people and how they express themselves.''</p>
        <p>In an exhibition whose scope is so vast, the principal underlying concepts are obviously diversity and variety. Yet it is possible to discern some common threads that link apparently unrelated works from different periods, such as, for example, the glossy feathered cape of a Tupinamba Indian chief sent to Europe in the 1630's and the ''Tupinamba Cloak,'' a mixed-media construction created by Lygia Pape just this year.</p>
        <p>''There is a sense of continuity in Brazilian art that is very dramatic to me, and it has to do with humor and playfulness and a sensuality that is expressed in rhythms that are visual as well as musical,'' said Edward J. Sullivan, chairman of the Department of Fine Arts at New York University and an expert on Brazilian art. ''High seriousness with an undercurrent of irony is a constant feature of Brazilian art, literature, cinema and even music.''</p>
        <p>The distance Brazil has had to travel in creating its own exuberant aesthetic is perhaps best demonstrated in the weakest of the exhibitions, that devoted to the 19th century. The paintings and sculptures displayed are frankly imitative of conventional French salon art of the same period, with little to identify the works as Brazilian except for the tropical landscape.</p>
        <p>Yet a module called ''The Distant View,'' which examines the ways in which foreigners have portrayed Brazil, makes clear that Brazil has also influenced Europe. The unit begins with the landscapes painted by the Dutch artist Frans Post in the 1630's and concludes with Anselm Kiefer's 1998 mixed-media series based on photographs of the Sao Paulo skyline, with constant references along the way to Brazil's extravagant flora and fauna and resplendent natural light.</p>
        <p>In an effort to make the exhibition attractive to a mass public that does not ordinarily frequent museums, the organizers have taken the unusual step of asking prominent stage designers from the Brazilian theater to mount each section. That has led to a startling diversity in ways of presenting works of art -- and to most of the complaints about the exhibition, aside from the $5.75 admission fee, which some find too steep.</p>
        <p>The ''Indigenous Art'' section, for instance, is strikingly simple and stark, with feather headdresses, masks, baskets and fetishes suspended in glass cases with no further adornment and sometimes even without a label, leaving the objects to speak for themselves. The ''Baroque Art'' unit, in contrast, is a bizarre and darkly lighted fantasy of purple and yellow paper flowers that recalls nothing so much as the set of ''The Wizard of Oz'' and never ceases to be distracting.</p>
        <p>To their credit, the organizers have also devoted a great deal of attention to the exhibition's catalogs. There are a dozen of them, totaling more than 3,000 pages, with gorgeous photographic reproductions and thoughtful essays that explain, in both Portuguese and English, the historical and social context in which the artworks were produced and their creators lived.</p>
        <p>''Taken as a whole, we envisioned these catalogs as a huge encyclopedia, a vade mecum of Brazilian civilization,'' Mr. Ferreira said. ''Brazil is a country that is not in the habit of looking back, and so it never gets to know itself as it really is. We wanted to remedy that both with the exhibition and the catalogs.''</p>
        <p>THE catalogs are available in CD-ROM form as well, and some of the works on display can also be viewed at a bilingual Web site that will continue to function even after the show closes here on Sept. 7: www.br500anos.com.br.</p>
        <p>After visits to other Brazilian cities later this year, parts of the exhibition will begin a long overseas tour, including stops next year in Washington and at the Museo del Barrio in New York City.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Guggenheim Museum will be selecting a few of the works being shown here for a separate show that is to run from Sept. 23, 2001, through Jan. 20, 2002. ''There will surely be some overlap in terms of objects, but the two enterprises are completely independent in terms of organization,'' said Lisa Dennison, the Guggenheim's chief curator and deputy director. ''Our project is highly selective, with probably 250 objects, and will focus on the relationship between the Baroque and modernism.''</p>
        <p>Both of those periods are of course effectively represented in the ''Rediscovery'' show, earning displays and catalogs of their own. Modernist painters like Tarsila do Amaral and Anita Malfatti and contemporary sculptors like Helio Oititica and Lygia Clark are among the 20th-century standouts, while the Baroque module focuses on polychrome woodcarvings and terra cotta works of 18th-century masters like Aleijadinho and Francisco Xavier de Brito.</p>
        <p>This was one of the most extraordinary flowerings of painting, sculpture, architecture and decorative arts ever seen in the Americas, and very different from the Spanish sense of melancholy you see in the Mexican or Peruvian art of this period,'' Dr. Sullivan said. ''In general, it contains a sense of lightness and optimism carried out in color and architectonic form that have a high degree of theatricality, like constantly being involved in a rococo opera.''</p>
        <p>It was an exhibition of modern art here in 1922 that set Brazil's cultural agenda for the rest of the 20th century, producing a manifesto arguing that the basis for all Brazilian culture was a ''philosophy of anthropophagy,'' or appropriation, amalgamation and regurgitation. With that concept now enshrined as part of the national orthodoxy, ''The Rediscovery Show'' is making a conscious effort to promote an updated agenda for the new century.</p>
        <p>''What we are doing is opening the doors and leaving them open,'' Mr. Aguilar explained. ''By doing that, we can break taboos, destroy myths and completely change the perspective that people have of themselves. It is a scandal that an exhibition like this was not mounted 20 or 40 years ago, but important that it is finally being done now.''</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Larry Rohter is the New York Times correspondent in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Larry Rohter is the New York Times correspondent in Rio de Janeiro.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
