<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Craving Solitude but Needing Community</title>
    <meta content="04TACT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="URBAN TACTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Other Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lofts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berger, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lofts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3D7103CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1205" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Craving Solitude but Needing Community</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE BERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berger, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on dearth of affordable office space available to writers in New York City; budding and younger writers tend to share loft space with others and work communal-style while settled ones, loath to give up single life, seek out rent-regulated bachelor apartments; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WENDY PARIS, a travel writer, bikes across Lower Manhattan to get to work at an office loft shared among a dozen writers, editors and graphic artists. Ms. Paris, who also contributes to women's magazines, sought out the ersatz newsroom at 72 Madison Avenue to beat back the sense of anonymity she felt when working at home. For $315 a month she gets not only a desk with fax, phone and computer lines, but a conference room, cafe and camaraderie.</p>
        <p>''Working at home I felt like I was invisible, like I didn't exist,'' Ms. Paris said. ''I felt like I could wear the same clothes every day and nobody would even notice. Now, when I sleep over at some guy's house and come in wearing the same sweater, everyone knows and I find that very comforting.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WENDY PARIS, a travel writer, bikes across Lower Manhattan to get to work at an office loft shared among a dozen writers, editors and graphic artists. Ms. Paris, who also contributes to women's magazines, sought out the ersatz newsroom at 72 Madison Avenue to beat back the sense of anonymity she felt when working at home. For $315 a month she gets not only a desk with fax, phone and computer lines, but a conference room, cafe and camaraderie.</p>
        <p>''Working at home I felt like I was invisible, like I didn't exist,'' Ms. Paris said. ''I felt like I could wear the same clothes every day and nobody would even notice. Now, when I sleep over at some guy's house and come in wearing the same sweater, everyone knows and I find that very comforting.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Paris's work space was borne of the city's crushing real-estate market. For years, during recessions, it was possible to find a cheap little hideaway apart from home. Patricia Bosworth, a biographer, fondly recalls one she took over from a nudist-magazine publisher that cost her less than $100 a month, 20 years ago. Many writers were also able to grab a spot at the Frederick Lewis Allen Room at the New York Public Library, or in the privately established Writers Room, a nonprofit loft with 35 desks that started in 1978 and remains at 10 Astor Place.</p>
        <p>Today, the writer's paradox of craving solitude but needing community, too, is still there but it's subsumed by the crasser calling of cash. Commercial office space commands as much as $50 a square foot and library spots are pretty much spoken for. The Writers Room -- which charges $185 every three months -- has a two-year waiting list of 250 names, said Donna Brodie, the executive director.</p>
        <p>''When I fund-raise now,'' Ms. Brodie said, ''I point to the real-estate crisis and to the fact that, particularly for emerging writers who tend to be young and living doubled and tripled up, writers' rooms and places like them are absolutely essential.''</p>
        <p>Some writers manage to work in circumstances that evoke prerevolutionary Russia. Before he quit his day job in publishing, Nicholas Weinstock would write from 5 a.m. till 8 a.m. (HarperCollins is to release his first novel, ''The Assistant,'' next year). He toiled just four feet from his girlfriend's bed, behind a purple curtain, in an apartment he estimates was 200 square feet. Now married and expecting their first child, Mr. Weinstock and Amanda Beesley, an essayist, both write from their new home in a two-bedroom apartment, only Ms. Beesley's office, which was a bedroom, has become the nursery. The author of ''Something New,'' her reflections on the beginnings of marriage, she works from a secretary in their living room.</p>
        <p>''If you have 8.5 by 11 inches free, you can pretty much do it,'' Mr. Weinstock said. ''Only in New York, it might be called a one-bedroom.''</p>
        <p>The issue is so pressing that the Authors Guild Foundation sponsored a panel discussion last fall called Writers and Their Work Spaces. Several hundred writers attended, said the foundation's president, Sidney Offit.  He said the idea for the evening was inspired partly by the many letters of recommendation he had been writing lately for writing spaces. ''It used to be for grad school,'' he said. ''Now it's for Yaddo and the Writers' Room.''</p>
        <p>The Authors Guild president, Letty Cottin Pogrebin, is sharing office space with five other women as she works on a novel. Ms. Pogrebin said she writes nonfiction from a study at home, but felt she needed a ''zone for fiction.'' She pays about $250 a month for part of a suite on West 57th Street.</p>
        <p>''The space is the novel,'' she said. ''I open the door and the characters are all there. There are no plants to water, no bills to pay, no maps to study for summer vacation.''</p>
        <p>The bigger, slightly rowdier writers' commune where Ms. Paris goes each day apparently works because of mutual respect, staggered routines and the gentle but firm oversight of the magazine consultants Basia Hellwig and Anne Mollegen Smith. ''Every once in a while I'll put out a note saying, 'Please put your coffee cups directly in the dishwasher as opposed to the sink or your desk or whatever,' '' Ms. Smith said.</p>
        <p>Former magazine editors, Ms. Hellwig and Ms. Smith rented the renovated loft, on Madison between 27th and 28th Streets, after they formed their own company. The atmosphere is casual yet professional, enhanced by lots of natural light.</p>
        <p>For settled writers loath to completely give up the single life, rent-regulated bachelor apartments have become a popular form of office space. ''My husband had his place 25 years, and when we got married he had all these excuses for why he had to keep it,'' said Susan Shapiro, a journalist who teaches at New York University and the New School University. Her husband, a screenwriter who shuns publicity, works out of his old apartment for $700 a month.</p>
        <p>Susan Cheever also wrote for a while from her old singles place, one of a series of small apartments she rented in the same Upper East Side neighborhood in an endless quest for privacy after she was married and had children. At one point, Ms. Cheever would run between her office and home to nurse her infant son; her nanny learned to recognize the baby's hunger cries and would summon her as needed. Later, she invited another nanny to live in the apartment she was using as an office, an arrangement meant to eliminate the Filipina emigre's commute and have her nearby.</p>
        <p>''I forgot it takes a lot more space to live than it takes to work,'' Ms. Cheever recalled. ''Slowly that apartment became like the home to many Filipinos passing through New York and a kind of gathering place for my baby sitter and her friends, the way my home does. It became less and less a place where I could work. I had to laugh at my own pretensions.''</p>
        <p>Single again and writing from home, Ms. Cheever said she had concluded that where and how one works is as individual as the writer. She noted that her father, John Cheever, wrote in a guest bedroom, a railroad station and a tent, among other places.</p>
        <p>''Writing is very mysterious,'' Ms. Cheever said. ''Nobody really knows what the best conditions are for writing. Writing doesn't happen in real time. It doesn't happen the way anything else happens, thank  goodness. The hardest part of being a writer is understanding that and finding your own rhythm.''</p>
        <p>URBAN TACTICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
