<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Special Teams Hold Off The Stars</title>
    <meta content="04HOCK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY: STANLEY CUP FINALS -- DEVILS VS. STARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1D81F3CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Special Teams Hold Off The Stars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, June 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils coach Larry Robinson credits special teams, especially penalty killers, in Devils' victory over Dallas Stars in Game 3 of Stanley Cup finals (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jason Arnott and Petr Sykora rebounded by scoring last night, but goalie Martin Brodeur and the Devils' special teams, particularly the penalty killers, were the keys in New Jersey's 2-1 victory over the Dallas Stars in Game 3 of the Stanley Cup finals.</p>
        <p>''Our penalty killers won us the game,'' Coach Larry Robinson said after the Devils killed four of the Stars' five manpower advantages, including a 49-second, 2-man edge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jason Arnott and Petr Sykora rebounded by scoring last night, but goalie Martin Brodeur and the Devils' special teams, particularly the penalty killers, were the keys in New Jersey's 2-1 victory over the Dallas Stars in Game 3 of the Stanley Cup finals.</p>
        <p>''Our penalty killers won us the game,'' Coach Larry Robinson said after the Devils killed four of the Stars' five manpower advantages, including a 49-second, 2-man edge.</p>
        <p>Brodeur played perhaps his best game of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes your best penalty killer is the guy between the pipes,'' Robinson said, referring to Brodeur, ''and he made a couple of good saves sliding across.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur made 22 saves and was simply superb, especially in the closing minutes. The Devils had to kill a delay-of-game penalty to Brodeur when his clearing attempt sailed over the glass in his zone. Brodeur and the Devils responded in grand fashion despite severe pressure from the Stars.</p>
        <p>''We got ourselves in a jam there toward the end and we had to come through,'' Brodeur said.</p>
        <p>Arnott and Sykora have combined with Patrik Elias to form the Devils' premier line all season. They carried the Devils in the regular season with 82 goals and have combined for 23 goals in the playoffs, including four in the Devils' 7-3 victory in Game 1. Sykora is the leader with nine and Arnott and Elias have seven each.</p>
        <p>But the threesome, especially Sykora and Elias, played so poorly in the 2-1 loss in Game 2 that Robinson contemplated benching one of them. Robinson decided not to break up the three, and he said the next day that he kicked himself for not benching one of them.</p>
        <p>The poor performance was forgotten after tonight's game.</p>
        <p>''I was very proud of all of them,'' Robinson said.</p>
        <p>Arnott said: ''We realized after that game that we had to get our act together and do the job. We had to produce, but the reason we're here today was our penalty killing.''</p>
        <p>The most impressive penalty killed by the Devils came shortly after Sylvain Cote's second goal of the playoffs opened the scoring. The  goal looked huge for the Stars because they have won 11 of the 12 games in which they had scored first.</p>
        <p>The Devils could have collapsed shortly after Cote's goal, 13 minutes 8 seconds into the game, when they found themselves two men down for 49 seconds after an interference penalty by Vladimir Malakhov and a cross-checking penalty by Claude Lemieux.</p>
        <p>When they escaped unscathed from the two-man disadvantage, the Devils seemed inspired and tied the score on Arnott's seventh goal of the playoffs with 1:54 left before the first intermission.</p>
        <p>Arnott displayed a great deal of tenacity by fighting off Derian Hatcher and Dave Manson, the two Dallas defensemen, before beating goalie Ed Belfour while falling to the ice after being sandwiched by the two defensemen.</p>
        <p>Sykora's goal came with 7:33 left in the second period, when he took a pass from Arnott and beat Belfour with a blistering shot from just inside the blue line. Belfour got his glove on Sykora's shot, but it had so much velocity it bounced off his glove and into the goal for Sykora's ninth of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>After taking no penalties in the previous game and just three minors in the opening game, it was uncharacteristic of the Devils to take three penalties before the first intermission of this game.</p>
        <p>They paid the price just 22 seconds after Sergei Nemchinov took the first penalty and Scott Stevens failed to clear the puck with authority after Brodeur had knocked down a shot by Jere Lehtinen from the left side.</p>
        <p>Stevens redeemed himself by leading the Devils' penalty killers, who have been the best in the playoffs after finishing first in the regular season. Cote's power-play goal was only the fourth the Devils allowed in 54 attempts against them.</p>
        <p>''The guys did a great job on the penalty kill,'' Lemieux said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY: STANLEY CUP FINALS -- DEVILS VS. STARS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
