<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where I Seem to Find the Happiness I Seek</title>
    <meta content="04WASS$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Porter, Cole (1892-1964)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gershwin, George (1898-1937)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berlin, Irving (1888-1989)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wasserman, Wendy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Branagh, Kenneth</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Love's Labour's Lost (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1DC143CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where I Seem to Find the Happiness I Seek</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WENDY WASSERSTEIN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wendy Wasserman article waxes nostalgic about old movie musicals, where tuxedo-clad men and ball-gowned women danced and sang to Cole Porter, George Gershwin and Irving Berlin standards; focuses on resurgence of movie musical genre, including Kenneth Branagh's version of Love's Labour's Lost, which is about to open; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STANDING in front of 200 earnest female faces and a smattering of sympathetic men at a recent Harvard Hillel conference on ''superwomen,'' I realized my customary ironic autobiographical anecdotes were falling flat. This audience expected substance, a concrete point of view on ''having it all'' -- plus relevant thought on the future of feminism, not to mention Judaism. And I was offering my best stories about my mother.</p>
        <p>But five minutes into what I feared could become a debacle, a movie musical began. My nephew Ben, a freshman, strode into the room with six young men, all in black tie. As they climbed the steps to the back row of the lecture hall, I pictured them breaking into an updated version of the Cole Porter classic ''Anything Goes!'' I was especially pleased that in my movie-musical fantasy, a Yale man was providing the melody and lyrics for a Harvard musical.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STANDING in front of 200 earnest female faces and a smattering of sympathetic men at a recent Harvard Hillel conference on ''superwomen,'' I realized my customary ironic autobiographical anecdotes were falling flat. This audience expected substance, a concrete point of view on ''having it all'' -- plus relevant thought on the future of feminism, not to mention Judaism. And I was offering my best stories about my mother.</p>
        <p>But five minutes into what I feared could become a debacle, a movie musical began. My nephew Ben, a freshman, strode into the room with six young men, all in black tie. As they climbed the steps to the back row of the lecture hall, I pictured them breaking into an updated version of the Cole Porter classic ''Anything Goes!'' I was especially pleased that in my movie-musical fantasy, a Yale man was providing the melody and lyrics for a Harvard musical.</p>
        <p>The mere thought of them elegantly tapping up the stairs amidst the young women peering at me completely lifted my spirits. Of course, my nephew and his associates were only stopping by on their way to the freshman prom, an event my own generation would have vehemently protested. But once I pictured my nephew singing and dancing, I relaxed and quite enjoyed the conference. In fact, I even worked out what I thought was a very nice little exit for the tuxedo-clad six. A woman asks towards the end of my talk, ''Where do you think men are going?'' I answer, ''To the prom!'' Then the boys break into a refrain from ''Varsity Drag'' and get the entire room up singing and dancing. All that's missing is June Allyson.</p>
        <p>Although most likely you wouldn't cast June Allyson as a Harvard Hillel superwoman.</p>
        <p>For me, the great movie musicals defined romance and American exuberance. But while in recent, more ''edgy'' decades, these Technicolor feasts were dismissed as kitschy, campy or just ridiculously sentimental, a resurgence seems to be in the air. The Lars von Trier film that won the Golden Palm at Cannes is a musical, and so are the forthcoming films from Baz Luhrmann and the Coen Brothers. Jerome Robbins's choreography for ''West Side Story'' has been revived as a retro-hip Gap ad. And Kenneth Branagh, the director of ''Henry V,''  ''Much Ado About Nothing'' and ''Hamlet,'' offers a new, musicalized Shakespeare.</p>
        <p>My musical apparition featuring my nephew and company is not far from the spirit of Mr. Branagh's version of ''Love's Labour's Lost,'' opening Friday. The three young gentlemen-scholars who take an oath with the King of Navarre to seek the purity of intellectual pursuit and renounce women are constantly breaking into Cole Porter, George Gershwin and Irving Berlin standards. When the Princess of France and her three lovely ladies-in-waiting propitiously camp out by their Academy, the King and his court can only express their excitement by singing and dancing.</p>
        <p>PERSONALLY, I believe no situation is either so tense or so romantic that it can't be just slightly heightened by a good old-fashioned movie-musical number. I have always secretly hoped that economic summit meetings erupted behind closed doors into ''Big Spender'' and that Margaret Thatcher crooned ''Begin the Beguine'' as she told the cabinet her plans for the Falklands. Wouldn't any commuter's trip to Darien be immeasurably enhanced by a chorus of eager returning spouses harmonizing ''I Married an Angel'' a cappella? Finally, the playwright Christopher Durang and I have always thought that the tragedy ''Medea'' would be much improved if she forgot about revenge and sang and danced, ''Forget your troubles, c'mon get happy,'' with the Greek chorus instead. Think Ann Miller tap dancing on a drum.</p>
        <p>Watching ''Love's Labour's Lost,'' I thought perhaps Mr. Branagh shares with me a desire to musicalize even the classics simply because movie musicals are among the top 10 reasons to live. In fact, ''The Band Wagon,'' the movie musical by Betty Comden and Adolph Green about the transformation of a Broadway show from a pretentious version of ''Faust'' into a delightful musical souffle, is definitely in the top five.</p>
        <p>In ''The Band Wagon,'' Fred Astaire plays a Broadway song-and-dance man who is making a comeback. He is, however, partnered with Cyd Charisse, a formally trained ballerina. Their relationship on stage and off is -- to say the least -- tortured, until he takes her for a carriage ride in Central Park after a particularly dreadful run-through. They stop at the most ideal version of a fountain and suddenly all their artistic and personal disputes fade away as they dance together in graceful harmony. When they sit back in the carriage on the final note of ''Dancing in the Dark,'' the New York skyline is shimmering behind them and all is suddenly, romantically, perfect in the world.</p>
        <p>Kenneth Branagh in ''Love's Labour's Lost'' seems to assume that the majority of the movie audience is already familiar with standards such as ''I Won't Dance,''  ''The Way You Look Tonight'' and ''Cheek to Cheek.'' In fact, many of the numbers in Mr. Branagh's film are homages to the great Fred Astaire and Ginger Rogers movie musicals. However, the most striking difference between the Branagh film and the movies it tries to emulate, according to quotations from the choreographer Stuart Hopps in the production notes, is that the new film is ''actor-led as opposed to dancer-led.''</p>
        <p>The ''Cheek to Cheek'' sequence in ''Love's Labour's Lost'' has the young scholars literally flying upward on cables as soon as the opening lyric, ''Heaven, I'm in heaven,'' is heard. Both the words and the musical-comedy style are being ''sent up,'' literally. Personally, I'm still a sucker for Mr. Astaire, ascending to heaven on his feet. Even the great ballet choreographer George Balanchine was a Fred Astaire fan. ''The male dancer I like to watch is an American,'' he once said, ''Fred Astaire. He is the most interesting, the most inventive, the most elegant dancer of our times.''</p>
        <p>''Love's Labour's Lost'' doesn't tip its hat only to Fred and Ginger. There's a sly nod to every kind of movie-musical extravaganza, from a splashy Esther Williams-style water ballet with a bevy of bathing beauties to a rousing rendition of ''There's No Business Like Show Business'' led by Nathan Lane, one of the few remaining crossover film and stage musical-comedy stars.</p>
        <p>But except for the film's final, bittersweet ''They Can't Take That Away From Me,'' the numbers in this musical ''Love's Labour's Lost'' are always performed with an arched eyebrow. And when the eyebrow becomes too arched, we can't help but suspend our suspension of disbelief and wonder why anyone's singing to begin with.</p>
        <p>In a classic movie musical like ''Singin' in the Rain,'' Gene Kelly is never self-conscious. He simply can't wait to get wet and sing and dance his heart out. Even in a more ironic situation, as when Fred sings ''The Way You Look Tonight'' to Ginger while she has cold cream all over her face, there is a naive sweetness. Not surprisingly, Adrian Lester, the song-and-dance man who was the lead in Sam Mendes's London stage production of ''Company'' and who plays the scholar Dumaine in ''Love's Labour's Lost,'' captures in a contemporary way some of Kelly's energy and Astaire's elegance. Still, dancing tongue-in-cheek is hardly as difficult or inspiring as cheek-to-cheek.</p>
        <p>I hope Kenneth Branagh's musicalized version of ''Love's Labour's Lost'' will introduce a new generation of moviegoers to one of the best romantic comedies and some of the best songs ever written. But I would wish that after all the Harvard superwomen had seen this film, they would rush to the nearest video store to rent the real thing. Just as you can't know the genius of Jerome Robbins's choreography if you've only seen it in a Gap ad, you can't know the possibilities of a filmed dance number without at least one viewing of Fred Astaire literally dancing up the walls.</p>
        <p>I am still afraid I can't predict if the Harvard women will or won't have it all. But I do know that if I'm watching Fred and Ginger dancing in ''The Gay Divorcee,'' I have it all.</p>
        <p>FILM Wendy Wasserstein is writing a Broadway version of the film ''An American in Paris.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Wendy Wasserstein is writing a Broadway version of the film ''An American in Paris.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
