<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doing God's Work Where Hope Is Rare</title>
    <meta content="04COLM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Part of the Solution (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Amira</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E7DA133CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doing God's Work Where Hope Is Rare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICIA R. LEE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Felicia Lee Coping column on Amira Hernandez's search for God in Bedford Park section of Bronx, NYC; Hernandez, college graduate volunteering with nonprofit group called Part of the Solution, is somewhat disillusioned by rampant poverty but grateful to people she has tried to help; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW do you find God in a place of faded glory, far from home? The question haunts Amira Hernandez. Ms. Hernandez, who recently graduated from college, works in Bedford Park, the Bronx, near the part of the Grand Concourse that is no longer grand, with its drug-dealing side streets and ground-down life stories.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hernandez, 23, came to New York last summer from Spartanburg, S.C., to volunteer with a nonprofit group called Part of the Solution, which provides poor people with food, housing and legal services. Ms. Hernandez's spiritual faith made her want to change the world, and her idealism has not faded. But her search for God in the Bronx has been far harder than she ever imagined.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW do you find God in a place of faded glory, far from home? The question haunts Amira Hernandez. Ms. Hernandez, who recently graduated from college, works in Bedford Park, the Bronx, near the part of the Grand Concourse that is no longer grand, with its drug-dealing side streets and ground-down life stories.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hernandez, 23, came to New York last summer from Spartanburg, S.C., to volunteer with a nonprofit group called Part of the Solution, which provides poor people with food, housing and legal services. Ms. Hernandez's spiritual faith made her want to change the world, and her idealism has not faded. But her search for God in the Bronx has been far harder than she ever imagined.</p>
        <p>''Something's out of sync when you've got so many women and children and men being abused and neglected in some way in a world that should be able to feed everyone,'' she said, explaining her mission. ''I didn't want to participate in the injustice. ''</p>
        <p>But justice can be a mighty big concept to wrestle down to human size and parcel out.  Ms. Hernandez would organize meetings so people could deal with the bad things in their lives, like dilapidated housing, but often they would not show up. Sometimes it was because of a long wait at a clinic to treat a sick baby. Sometimes it was because of too many drinks the night before.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hernandez, a thin woman with a curtain of bright red hair, also felt the heartbreak of seeing suffering up close, day in and day out. Homelessness. Unemployment. Addiction.</p>
        <p>''You come in with these great, idealistic intentions,'' she said. ''Grass roots all the way. Work from the bottom up. On a practical level, sometimes it's hard to get everybody to go to a meeting they're supposed to go to.''</p>
        <p>''It's a challenge to remain respectful and at the same time try to demonstrate the importance of follow-through,'' Ms. Hernandez said. ''There are days that I am so frustrated, I'm not convinced this is the level on which I'm supposed to be working. The flight response is huge.''</p>
        <p>''I am angry not just about the disproportion of wealth but also the simplicity of what people ask for,'' she said. ''Some days, all they want is someone to talk to.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hernandez is part of an effort called the Jesuit Volunteer Corps, a Roman Catholic organization that sends recent college graduates to volunteer in poor communities. They work in exchange for food, board and a small stipend. In New York City, the volunteers are in every borough, working at organizations like New York State Tenants and Neighbors Coalition and the Urban Justice Center. They are teachers, counselors and health workers, among other vocations.</p>
        <p>Like the other volunteers, Ms. Hernandez was recruited from college. She is a 1999 graduate of Sweet Briar College, which has a 3,600-acre campus in Sweet Briar, Va. She was not especially keen on coming to New York, she said, but was attracted to Part of the Solution because it offered so many services and seemed so engaged with the community. She was heartened when she found that many people in the neighborhood were eager to share their lives with her.</p>
        <p>Many of the smells and sounds of the neighborhood were familiar, Ms. Hernandez said, from the trips she took to Colombia with her father, a college professor who is a native of that country. She speaks Spanish.</p>
        <p>''I guess the greatest surprise has been how much of their lives they want to share with you,'' she said. ''In detail many of us out of fear of embarrassment or judgment would not divulge to anyone. The honesty is beautiful and humbling. There's not a lot of surface you have to go through to get to the real person. That's the greatest gift.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hernandez lives in a long, narrow house with five other volunteers. White and well-scrubbed, they do not exactly resemble their neighbors, who are mostly poor black and Latin people.</p>
        <p>If nothing else, the volunteers seem well intentioned, and no one in the neighborhood bothers them. Sharing the same values for the most part, they support one another through those dark nights of the soul.</p>
        <p>''A lot of my personal anguish this year has been over women,'' Ms. Hernandez said. ''The cycles of abuse they seem to be stuck in or the presence of drugs and alcohol in their lives.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day, someone will say let's go and have a beer, and I flip out. I can't hear it without seeing the face of someone here and seeing the loss of life and the loss of independence because of alcohol.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hernandez's tour of duty ends early in August. She is not certain what she will do next. But even if her search for faith in the Bronx has been met with silence sometimes, she has seen a God with a different face, the face of the people she has tried to help. They have endured in the absence of answers.</p>
        <p>''They're homeless and they're housed,'' Ms. Hernandez said. ''They're addicted and they're clean. They're men and they're women.</p>
        <p>''I'm grateful to them. If it wasn't for them, I don't know if I would have survived.''</p>
        <p>COPING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
