<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High-Tech Philanthropy in a Low-Tech Guatemalan Village</title>
    <meta content="04GUAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Pedro La Laguna (Guatemala)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Guatemala</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ebay Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellin, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stahl, Karin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Guatemala</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Guatemala</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E0DD1E3CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2114" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High-Tech Philanthropy in a Low-Tech Guatemalan Village</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY ELLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ellin, Abby</byline>
      <dateline>SAN PEDRO LA LAGUNA, Guatemala</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Since 1998, eBay has donated 15 computers and two printers to Colegio Bethel, a private school in rural Guatemalan town of San Pedro La Laguna, population 12,000; school was founded 11 years ago by Emilio and Esther Battz; about 350 students, in kindergarten through 9th grade, pay 25 quetzales ($3.25) a month tuition, and 40 quetzales ($5.20) a month for junior high; modest tuition is struggle for many families, but parents hope education will give children a chance to better themselves; eBay's Karin Stahl, the force behind company's involvement with school, hopes computers and Internet will expose students to wider world; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is early evening on a hazy spring night, and a group of children are gathered on the shores of Lake Atitlan, eagerly awaiting the visit from Karin Stahl. Her boat has just pulled in to this tiny Mayan village 90 miles west of Guatemala City, and it is as if a celebrity has arrived.</p>
        <p>''Karina!'' they cry, rushing toward the docks. ''Bienvenidos, Karina!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is early evening on a hazy spring night, and a group of children are gathered on the shores of Lake Atitlan, eagerly awaiting the visit from Karin Stahl. Her boat has just pulled in to this tiny Mayan village 90 miles west of Guatemala City, and it is as if a celebrity has arrived.</p>
        <p>''Karina!'' they cry, rushing toward the docks. ''Bienvenidos, Karina!''</p>
        <p>Ms. Stahl grins and hugs each child, doling out kisses like chocolates, asking questions in flawless Spanish. She has been coming to this village of 12,000 since 1997, and everywhere she goes people call out to her. Three families have even named their newborns Karina.</p>
        <p>''Isn't she beautiful?'' Ms. Stahl asks a companion, cradling one of her namesakes.</p>
        <p>Two young boys offer to help with Ms. Stahl's bags, but they give up when they discover how heavy the bags are. Inside, amid the heap of clothing, are four gleaming new Compaq Presario laptop computers, complete with DVD's. There is also a server, a monitor and Spanish/English translation software -- all courtesy of eBay, the online auction house, where the 34-year-old Ms. Stahl works.</p>
        <p>Since 1998, eBay has donated 15 computers and two printers to Colegio Bethel, a private school here in San Pedro. The school was founded 11 years ago by Emilio Battz, a local pastor, and his wife, Ester, who live in a modest home on the premises with their three children.</p>
        <p>About 350 students, in kindergarten through 9th grade, attend. Their parents pay 25 quetzales ($3.25) a month for the elementary school and 40 quetzales ($5.20) for junior high. And while these rates sound nominal, families struggle to make the payments. Many live in adobe or bamboo huts, four or more to a bed, with no running water, no telephones, and limited electricity. They share outhouses with neighboring families and bathe in the lake.</p>
        <p>But five days a week their children come to Bethel, where, in addition to studying traditional subjects like math and history, they are learning to use computers.</p>
        <p>The region is known for its unique handicrafts, with brightly patterned designs and intricate embroidery. One goal is for students to sell these wares -- woven and beaded place mats, napkins, hats and scarves -- on eBay.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stahl, the force behind the San Pedro project and, separately, the director of the eBay Foundation, the company's philanthropic arm, said she would like to provide scholarships or loans for the children to continue their higher education outside the village. They would repay the loans by returning to Bethel to work as interns for a year, helping students learn the e-commerce process, she said.</p>
        <p>''So many of us at eBay have made so much money,'' Ms. Stahl said. ''We want to help kids do something with their lives other than selling fruit. The point is to give them some means to get out, to give them a vision of what they can do with their lives.''</p>
        <p>GENERALLY, women here earn about 5 quetzales (65 cents) if they sell their goods to a third party; the wholesaler then typically resells the items for 10 times that price. Some local men make the handicrafts, too, though most work in the fields, growing coffee, corn and cotton, for 20 quetzales a day. If families here could cut out the middlemen, the theory goes, their options would expand.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, the rate of economic growth in Guatemala rose to 5.1 percent -- the highest level in the 1990's, when the economy expanded at a yearly average of 4.1 percent. But last year, the growth rate slumped to 3.5 percent, according to Bank of Guatemala estimates. And, in any event, ''to have an impact on poverty reduction and to accommodate the population explosion, the economy should be growing by 6 percent,'' said Maurico Valdes, the Central America coordinator for the United Nations Development Program. ''Computers may help.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Stahl met Mr. Battz in July 1997 while traveling and working in Guatemala for Compassion International, a United States relief organization. When she joined eBay as an account manager in October of that year, she wondered how she could continue helping the village. She mentioned San Pedro in conversations with colleagues, and her enthusiasm spread throughout the company. A year later, she returned here with the first round of computers.</p>
        <p>''Karin is passionate about the project,'' said Meg Whitman, the chief executive of eBay. ''All 1,200 of our employees know about the school; it's part of our culture now. We have a bulletin board with the children's photographs on them.''</p>
        <p>Last August, nearly 30 eBay employees and relatives, including Ms. Whitman's 15-year-old son, joined Ms. Stahl on a trip to San Pedro, where they trained teachers on computers. Another group is heading out this summer.</p>
        <p>On this spring trip, though, there is just Ms. Stahl and Ron Sackman, 34, a friend and a consultant for Lucent Technologies, the communications equipment maker. Mr. Sackman is linking the new computers to the Internet. This is not an easy task; the dial-up connection is extremely slow, and the school only has one phone line -- in Mr. Battz's home. Web access is costly -- about $60 to open an account and $10 a month after that, not including local and long-distance telephone charges, in an area where incomes average about $900 a year.</p>
        <p>To curb costs, Mr. Sackman runs a 200-foot cable from Mr. Battz's home phone into the main server in the school. ''I'm hoping to do it so the kids can write e-mails during the day, and then late at night, when the rates are lower, the e-mail will automatically send,'' he explained.</p>
        <p>While he fiddles with the cable, Juan Cruz, Bethel's computer teacher, sets up the new machines. ''Hay mas mouse pads?'' (''Are there any more mouse pads?'') he asks. He flips through a manual he has put together, a 100-page curriculum that includes the history of technology and a step-by-step guide to Windows and other programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cruz, 25, learned computers in Guatemala City, then returned to San Pedro, his native village, to teach. ''These kids never saw a computer before, but now it's like no big deal to them,'' he said. ''They're so happy to take classes; otherwise they have to go to Guatemala City, and it's very expensive.''</p>
        <p>The Internet is not especially new to Guatemala; there are cybercafes in the capital and in tourist towns. But it is a novelty in this village, which did not have electricity until the mid-90's. The school has had power for just two years; before that, teachers would dangle an extension cord out a window and ''borrow'' a neighbor's.</p>
        <p>Now, while there is Web access in San Pedro, there is little pavement -- just dirt and stones. Dogs and chickens roam freely. Few tourists visit, except for some travelers who are generally understood to come for the marijuana, which grows abundantly in the hills. And though there are six other schools in the village -- three private and three public -- Bethel is the only one with computers.</p>
        <p>''It's very unusual for schoolchildren in a rural area like San Pedro La Laguna to have Internet access,'' said Mr. Valdes of the United Nations. ''In the more elitist private schools in the larger cities, it might be more common, but even basic things like electricity and telephone lines aren't always there to make computer technology work.''</p>
        <p>The computers are ''a giant step,'' agreed Mr. Battz, 47. ''Our kids are getting three years of computer training. It's excellent.'' A byproduct is that the computers have enhanced the children's self-esteem. ''I'm a Mayan, and we're typically very timid and think we're less important than those people with blue eyes and blond hair. Now that the children are learning new skills, they are seeing their own value.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, he wants to also train parents on the machines -- a necessity if the villagers are to sell their wares on eBay, since children aren't supposed to use the auction site on their own. That will be a formidable challenge, as most of the adults are illiterate and speak only Tz'utuhil, the indigenous language.</p>
        <p>THE parents seem thrilled with their children's education. ''I like that she studies,'' said Diego Pop, 60, whose daughter, Vila, is an eighth grader at Bethel. A widower, Mr. Pop works in the fields and supplements his income by embroidering clothing. He earns about 85 quetzales, or $11, for a pair of pants that takes about three weeks to complete. ''I don't want her to be like me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Lidia Gonzalez, the mother of 14-year-old Norma, cannot read or write; she earns her living selling pots and pans in the local market. ''It's important that she doesn't suffer like me,'' said Ms. Gonzalez, 29. ''I want her to study in the capital so she'll get a good job.''</p>
        <p>Computer skills certainly can't hurt. ''If students acquired programming skills or were able to do word processing or spreadsheets or knew how to surf the Web, that would increase their job prospects tremendously,'' said Susan Peacock, senior associate at the Washington Office on Latin America, a human rights organization.</p>
        <p>Alas, realities often fly in the face of these dreams. Vila Pop, for example, is the youngest of six children, and she has been saddled with the responsibilities of cooking and cleaning for her father and brothers since her mother died three years ago.</p>
        <p>Although she plans to further her education, it's not uncommon for students to drop out of school. According to a 1999 United Nations Development Program report on Guatemala, only about 56 percent of the Guatemalan population had attended school through the 9th grade.</p>
        <p>That number is only an estimate, Mr. Valdes said. ''A lot of people are migrant workers, and they migrate with their whole family during the harvest of sugar cane, so the children leave school to go with them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>How much time will the villagers actually have to devote to the Net? Would they be better off with clothes and food instead of computers, as some critics suggest?</p>
        <p>''A lot of people think computers are a luxury, but we can't say that rural areas only need water and sanitation and basic health,'' Mr. Valdes said.</p>
        <p>''We can't let the technological gap go on, but you have to devise a way to make it economically self-sustaining,'' Mr. Valdes added. ''In poor, rural, isolated areas, you can't just have computer access at a school. It has to become an information center for the community, because otherwise it's too expensive. There are local merchants and professionals who can benefit from a connection and, with time, be able to pay something for it. But these issues have to be discussed at the local level, in the villages, and not by people in New York.''</p>
        <p>MS. STAHL said she would like to integrate into the junior high curriculum instructions for selling online, including shipping preparation and accounting. ''The village is slowly growing in tourism, so this program will provide students the business and people skills to successfully help their community grow,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Right now, there are more pressing issues. Back in the computer lab, Mr. Sackman has managed to get online, though it takes nearly 15 minutes to download a page. The students hover around him excitedly.</p>
        <p>He checks his own e-mail account and prints out a few pages to show the students. Ms. Stahl also goes online -- only to learn that she did not win a bidding war for a house she had hoped to buy back home in San Jose, Calif.</p>
        <p>''I bid $100,000 over the asking price, and I was still outbid,'' she said. She glanced at the children clicking away at the computers and sighed. ''As if it really matters.''</p>
        <p>PERSONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
