<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; 2 Elections On an Island. So Close, So Far Apart.</title>
    <meta content="04GONZ$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Haiti</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dominican Republic</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Dominican Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D9113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; 2 Elections On an Island. So Close, So Far Apart.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gonzalez, David</byline>
      <dateline>PORT-AU-PRINCE, Haiti</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Haiti and Dominican Republic share island of Hispaniola and also history of dictatorship, violence and US intervention, and both have held elections in the last month; in Haiti, five years of US-led occupation have failed to restore peace, and 15 people died in politically motivated violence prior to election; in Dominican Republic, voters who felt excluded from recent prosperity peacefully turned out ruling party, which conceded defeat for the good of the country; Haiti, once the more pr prosperous of the two, has been undone by destructive dictators, while Dominican Republic has been built up by more constructive, if no less cruel, dictators (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILDA SEVERE carried the future in her mind and body as she waited to cast her ballot last month in Haiti's legislative elections. Though five months pregnant, she stood for hours on a slowly moving line, hoping that her vote would usher in a better life for her baby.</p>
        <p>''I want the conditions of the country to change,'' she said. ''The conditions are not good for anybody right now. People suffer and there is no work. And there is insecurity. The country is still not at peace.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILDA SEVERE carried the future in her mind and body as she waited to cast her ballot last month in Haiti's legislative elections. Though five months pregnant, she stood for hours on a slowly moving line, hoping that her vote would usher in a better life for her baby.</p>
        <p>''I want the conditions of the country to change,'' she said. ''The conditions are not good for anybody right now. People suffer and there is no work. And there is insecurity. The country is still not at peace.''</p>
        <p>More than five years after a United States-led military occupation restored democratic rule in Haiti, the civil serenity that she and many Haitians hoped for remains elusive. In the weeks before the elections, politically motivated violence had left 15 people dead, and in the slums the sense of poverty only deepened.</p>
        <p>When the last American troops left Haiti this year, some policy makers saw it as the end of a successful mission to restore democracy. But the fact that the  elections (in which former President Jean-Bertrand Aristide's party did well) found so many Haitians still pining for peace and progress belies any boast. It raises questions about why Haiti seems to stagger from crisis to crisis as it tries to embark on the path to democracy.</p>
        <p>Part of an answer lies just a short flight away in the Dominican Republic -- a nation that shares not just the island of Hispaniola with Haiti, but also a history of dictatorship, violence and American intervention. It too has had an election in the last month.</p>
        <p>But there, just over the border, the economy is expanding rapidly. New roads, modernized government agencies and investment have transformed the capital. Though many of the poorest Dominicans felt excluded from the boom times, they peacefully voiced their dissatisfaction at the polls, where a near majority  elected Hipolito Mejia president on May 16. And then the ruling party abandoned its quest for a runoff and conceded defeat for the good of the country.</p>
        <p>Like the border that separates the two countries -- where the lush green landscape of the Dominican Republic gives way to the barren, deforested soil of Haiti -- the contrast in political and social fortunes is sharp. Considering that Haiti was once the more prosperous and cosmopolitan of the two countries, and that the violence of Gen. Rafael Trujillo's dictatorship in the Dominican Republic 35 years ago ago rivaled if not exceeded that of the Duvalier family here, why do the two nations seem headed in opposite directions?</p>
        <p>''A big part of the answer can be summed up in two words: 30 years,'' said Michele Wucker, author of ''Why The Cocks Fight,'' a book exploring the relationship between the two nations. ''Haiti is now where the Dominican Republic was not too long after the United States invasion in 1965.''</p>
        <p>Even within the shared experience of military intervention, however, there are differences. After the 1965 intervention, when Joaquin Balaguer came to power and ushered in years of repressive rule, the United States essentially kept a hands-off policy in the Dominican Republic, Ms. Wucker said. In Haiti, the United States restored President Aristide to power in 1994, but placed narrow constraints on the exercise of his power. Mr. Wucker said that the United States also contradicted itself, pressing for elections while cutting aid to help finance them. ''They talk in pretty terms about democracy,'' Ms. said. ''But deep down they are reluctant to let Haiti muddle its own way in that direction.''</p>
        <p>The legacy of dictatorship also played out differently. While some Dominicans still bear scars -- physical and psychological -- from Mr. Balaguer's early years, just as many recall benefiting from jobs, homes and other favors. So strong are those memories that nearly a quarter of the votes went to Mr. Balaguer, even though he is 93, blind and infirm. In Haiti, the experience of a former president running again is relatively rare, since most have gone into exile after enriching themselves.  ''They had Balaguer, we had Duvalier, but the histories are very different,'' said Raoul Denis, a record store owner in Port-au-Prince. ''On our side, Duvalier destroyed the institutions and everything.''</p>
        <p>Those institutions, like the courts and the police, still struggle to maintain a semblance of law and order in Haiti. At the same time, other forces that could help bring pressure to bear lack sufficient experience to prove effective. In the Dominican Republic, public-interest advocates have played an important role in calling for clean elections and good government. Business owners, aware that tourists and factory jobs can flee unless there is social and political stability, also had a stake in the future and supported it with investment.</p>
        <p>''Our problem is we in Haiti do not have an authentic bourgeoisie that has invested in Haiti,'' said Patrick Pierre-Louis, a law school professor. ''All their money goes to the United States.''</p>
        <p>Dominican business leaders were a major force for their country's stability, said a diplomat who has worked there and in Haiti. When the United States worried about elections in the mid-1990's, such leaders were vulnerable to friendly pressure, since business owners wanted trade parity with the United States.</p>
        <p>''In Haiti there isn't much tourism,'' said the diplomat, who spoke on condition of anonymity. ''The assembly sector is still not large. They weathered the embargo and other bad situations. I'm not sure the levers we had in the Dominican Republic could work here.''</p>
        <p>While Haiti's elections are the first step toward achieving a normal government, bigger obstacles remain in a country where winner-take-all has been a rule applied literally by victorious candidates. Haiti's political leaders have yet to understand that the power of the vote extends beyond election day.</p>
        <p>''Dominican interests are the interests of their country,'' said Georges Sassine, a factory owner active in civic groups. ''Here, you have people who come here, get rich and leave. We are still a colony of ourselves.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
