<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind Geography Whiz Stood a Patient Teacher</title>
    <meta content="04GEOG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Geography Bee</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Geographic Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boyle, Alix</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russo, Lou</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peng, Felix</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E0D6123CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind Geography Whiz Stood a Patient Teacher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALIX BOYLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boyle, Alix</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lou Russo, social studies teacher at Elisabeth Adams Middle School in Guilford, Conn, describes mentoring Felix Peng, 13, who has won National Geography Bee; sample questions; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Felix Peng of Guilford won the National Geographic Bee last month, it was the culmination of years of drilling and studying, not only for the 13-year-old history and geography lover, but also for his teacher.</p>
        <p>''I almost did one of those moves you see at hockey games where you raise your hands, but I stopped myself,'' said Lou Russo, a social studies teacher at Elisabeth Adams Middle School in Guilford and Felix's mentor. ''Felix really brought a 30-year career to its height. I can't say enough how proud I am of him.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Felix Peng of Guilford won the National Geographic Bee last month, it was the culmination of years of drilling and studying, not only for the 13-year-old history and geography lover, but also for his teacher.</p>
        <p>''I almost did one of those moves you see at hockey games where you raise your hands, but I stopped myself,'' said Lou Russo, a social studies teacher at Elisabeth Adams Middle School in Guilford and Felix's mentor. ''Felix really brought a 30-year career to its height. I can't say enough how proud I am of him.''</p>
        <p>Although Felix, an eighth-grader at Adams, has had a lifelong interest in geography, he said Mr. Russo's coaching was essential in helping him win. He took home the grand prize of $25,000 in scholarship money from the bee held in Washington on May 24.</p>
        <p>''He helped me with time management and he bought all these tapes,'' Felix explained in an interview at his school. ''If I didn't have the time management, I kind of rushed my answers. It made a difference.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Russo believes that Felix could have won the contest by himself, but that their relationship enhanced the learning experience.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes that's the reason people learn in the first place,'' Mr. Russo said of the student-teacher relationship. ''I hope I gave him the confidence that helped push him through.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Russo bought tapes of previous geography bees to use the questions for practice and he rehearsed with Felix before school, after school, in the hall between classes and while waiting for the bus. Sometimes, for motivation, Mr. Russo would bet Felix his favorite candy, Charleston Chews, if he could answer a question correctly. He usually did.</p>
        <p>The two spent up to 90 minutes a day with Felix answering a variety of questions. ''I worked on his timing,'' Mr. Russo said. ''At this age, kids tend to be a little impulsive.'' Although Felix had 12 seconds to answer the questions at the contest, Mr. Russo urged him to wait about eight seconds before speaking.</p>
        <p>Finalists are allowed to get one wrong answer; on the second one they're out. Felix did get one wrong at the bee. (Name the term geographers use to describe the reflection of sunlight off a certain place on earth. The answer: an albedo.) But his opponent missed two, and Felix was declared the winner.</p>
        <p>Felix has loved geography ''since before he could talk,'' said his father, Richard Peng, a dentist. When Felix was about 18 months old, his parents bought a globe and showed him Taiwan, their birthplace, and Connecticut, his birthplace. The Pengs played a game of spinning the globe and asking Felix to find either place. He always did.</p>
        <p>As he grew, Felix loved learning about not only the land formations but also the culture and the people who live there. On a trip to Washington several years ago, Felix got information about the geography bee at the National Geographic headquarters, ''his shrine,'' Dr. Peng said. In fifth grade at the time, he persistently asked his principal to enter the school in the state geography bee. Felix has competed since then.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russo had Felix as a student in his seventh grade social studies class last year, making it easy for the two to get together. Felix won the Connecticut state championship in 1999 and entered the national bee but did not win. Prevailing at this year's contest is a culmination of four years of work.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Russo's work, Dr. Peng also helped his son study for the test, and, of course, drove him to all the competitions. Once, stuck in traffic, Felix and his Dad were forced to run down the highway and hitchhike to make it to a state championship. A Coors beer truck picked them up and deposited them near the site.</p>
        <p>The National Geographic Society started the bee about 12 years ago because it was concerned that Americans knew too little about geography. A 1988 Gallup poll showed that 20 percent of Americans aged 18 to 24 had trouble finding the United States on a map without labels.</p>
        <p>Teachers say that students know less geography than their grandparents because schools stopped teaching it as its own subject in the late 1950's. Instead, geography is folded into the history and social studies curriculum.</p>
        <p>The geography bee starts with about 5 million students across the country who take written geography tests. The winners of the local competitions go to a state championship, and, finally, representatives from the 50 states and five territories go on to compete in the nationals.</p>
        <p>The 55 are whittled down to 10 finalists, then to two for the championship round. The bee has been hosted by Alex Trebek of the ''Jeopardy!'' TV show.</p>
        <p>An only child, Felix lives with his mother and father and also plays tennis and cello. He also likes to spend time online, he said. One of the people he most admires is Chen Shui-bian, the president of Taiwan, and he hopes to work in the biotechnology or genetics field someday. He speaks fluent Mandarin.</p>
        <p>Catherine Walker, principal at Adams Middle School, said she was particularly pleased that Felix found a mentor in Mr. Russo.</p>
        <p>''The mentor/mentee relationship is the essence of teaching,'' Ms. Walker said. ''I wish we could identify and support more kinds of experiences like this in which individual teachers could serve as mentors to individuals or small groups of students, rather than the factory model of education.''</p>
        <p>Name the Place</p>
        <p>Following are some sample geography questions taken from previous National Geographic Bee competitions and the research of Lou Russo, a social studies teacher at Elisabeth Adams Middle School in Guilford.</p>
        <p>1. An instrument made from the jaw bone of a pike and horsehair is the national instrument of what Nordic country north of Estonia?</p>
        <p>2. Many klongs or canals in the most populous city in the Indonesian peninsula have been filled in and replaced by streets. Name the city.</p>
        <p>3. Malawi, Mozambique and what other country border Lake Malawi?</p>
        <p>4. Name the world's largest salt water lake that has traditionally been a major source of sturgeon for caviar.</p>
        <p>5. What English-speaking Central American country was previously known as British Honduras?</p>
        <p>The answers: 1. Finland. 2. Bangkok. 3. Tanzania. 4. The Caspian Sea. 5. Belize.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
