<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Growing Club of Left-Leaning Leaders Strains to Find a Focus</title>
    <meta content="04GERM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE1DD1F3CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Growing Club of Left-Leaning Leaders Strains to Find a Focus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, June 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton and 12 other left-of-center presidents and prime ministers who year ago branded themselves as leaders of new 'Third Way' meet for summit in Berlin; banish concept in favor of new mantra of 'Progressive Governance' but are unable to define its meaning; seemingly agree that they stand for new brand of social-democratic leaders who support free trade and globalization yet are determined to soften their harsher aspects through strong government support for social justice (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When they met in Italy one year ago, they were leaders of a ''Third Way'' and their founding members were President Clinton and Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain.</p>
        <p>Today, as Mr. Clinton joined 12 other left-of-center presidents and prime ministers here, the Third Way was banished in favor of ''Progressive Governance.'' And Mr. Blair, pleading the need to help his wife care for their newborn, stayed home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When they met in Italy one year ago, they were leaders of a ''Third Way'' and their founding members were President Clinton and Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain.</p>
        <p>Today, as Mr. Clinton joined 12 other left-of-center presidents and prime ministers here, the Third Way was banished in favor of ''Progressive Governance.'' And Mr. Blair, pleading the need to help his wife care for their newborn, stayed home.</p>
        <p>The upshot was that although the meetings were unshakably friendly -- the main agenda was ''dialogue,'' interspersed with a few good meals -- leaders found themselves struggling for words.</p>
        <p>Everybody agreed that they stood for a new brand of social-democratic leaders who support free trade and globalization yet are determined to soften their harsher effects through strong government support for social justice, education and public health.</p>
        <p>But perhaps inevitably, most of the conclusions beyond that were murky.</p>
        <p>Even before today, the Third Way had brought German Chancellor Gerhard Schroder political heartburn. In a move he later admitted was a mistake, Mr. Schroder infuriated left-wing traditionalists in his Social Democratic Party last year when he signed a ''Third Way'' declaration with Mr. Blair praising economic deregulation and greater support for business.</p>
        <p>The new mantra of Progressive Governance appears to have several virtues. It implies modernization and a focus on the future, key themes for  Europe's new generation of pragmatic social-democratic leaders. At the same time, the word ''progressive'' carries echoes of more traditional Socialist goals like income redistribution and strong government.</p>
        <p>Werner Perger, an editor of the German news weekly Die Zeit and a German delegate to today's meeting, said that echoes were enough to set themselves apart rhetorically from center-right leaders like President Jacques Chirac of France. Mr. Chirac, who is neither Third Way nor Progressive, was not invited. But Prime Minister Lionel Jospin of France, one of Europe's most traditional Socialist leaders, is a charter member of the group.</p>
        <p>In sharp contrast to the enthusiastic pro-business views of Mr. Blair, the leaders here rarely if ever mentioned the word ''reform.'' Mr. Perger said that may have reflected a recognition that, in Europe at least, ''reform'' has become largely synonymous with deregulation and reduced government spending.</p>
        <p>President Clinton, who helped coin the phrase Third Way and wanted to make the new club of like-minded leaders a part of his legacy, admitted he was disappointed. ''I like the Third Way because it is sort of easy to remember,'' he said wistfully.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Jean Chretien of Canada had his own proposal for a new label: ''I am the radical center,'' he remarked.</p>
        <p>In their concluding communique, the leaders praised the so-called New Economy and said they accepted economic globalization but were duty-bound to temper the harsher effects of reliance on unfettered market competition.</p>
        <p>''We are leaders who are aware of the opportunities of globalization, without denying the dangers,'' the communique said. ''Globalization must lead to higher living standards for all and not a destructive race to the bottom at the expense of environmental and worker protections.''</p>
        <p>The conference was the first time that the former Third Way club has invited leaders from Latin America and South Africa. The newest members were President Ricardo Lagos of Chile, President Fernando de la Rua of Argentina, President Henrique Cardoso of Brazil and President Thabo Mbeki of South Africa.</p>
        <p>The expanded group made it more difficult to identify the criteria for membership. It does not, for example, include the social-democratic president of Finland, one of the Europe Union's fastest-growing countries. Nor does the group include Jose Maria Aznar, the center-right prime minister of Spain who is arguably closer in mind-set to the Progressives than he is to Spain's own Socialist Party.</p>
        <p>There was enormous speculation about whether Mr. Blair is now trying to distance himself from the group because it has tilted too much toward the likes of Mr. Jospin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schroder of Germany made a special point of denying such rumors, saying Mr. Blair stayed in London purely because he wanted to help his wife, Cherie, with their baby.</p>
        <p>There were political reasons to believe those claims: Mr. Blair has come under a fair amount of political razzing in Britain because he refused his wife's request to take time off from work for paternal leave.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, with a grin, jumped in with assurances. ''The Third Way and Progressive Governance are pro-family,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
