<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Now for the Beaches?; Court Tells Towns to Allow Access, but Old Ways Die Hard Along the State's Coastline</title>
    <meta content="04BEAC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenwich (Conn)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenwich Point Park (Greenwich, Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woodside, Christine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EED6123CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Now for the Beaches?; Court Tells Towns to Allow Access, but Old Ways Die Hard Along the State's Coastline</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTINE WOODSIDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woodside, Christine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article explores possible fate that awaits Connecticut's municipal beaches in aftermath of State Appellate Court ruling that it is illegal for town of Greenwich to block outsiders from Greenwich Point Park; state's 217-mile-long coastline has 85 miles of sandy beaches, only 13 of which are open to general public for swimming; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE residents-only tradition at many of Connecticut's municipal beaches will stand this summer, but it's a tradition that may not be around by next summer after it was toppled by a State Appellate Court last month.</p>
        <p>Three judges declared on May 17 that it was illegal for the town of Greenwich to block outsiders from Greenwich Point Park, and although the ruling focuses on Greenwich, if it stands it will affect just about every town in the state, especially those along the 217-mile-long coastline that restrict access to their beaches. The state has 85 miles of sandy beaches along the coast, and considering that only 13 are open to the general public for swimming, the ruling could have an immense impact.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE residents-only tradition at many of Connecticut's municipal beaches will stand this summer, but it's a tradition that may not be around by next summer after it was toppled by a State Appellate Court last month.</p>
        <p>Three judges declared on May 17 that it was illegal for the town of Greenwich to block outsiders from Greenwich Point Park, and although the ruling focuses on Greenwich, if it stands it will affect just about every town in the state, especially those along the 217-mile-long coastline that restrict access to their beaches. The state has 85 miles of sandy beaches along the coast, and considering that only 13 are open to the general public for swimming, the ruling could have an immense impact.</p>
        <p>Initially, not much will change. Greenwich is appealing, and until there is a final decision, coastal towns said they have no plans to alter the various ways they restrict outsiders from their beaches. From Greenwich to East Lyme, town officials said they intend to continue favoring residents, whose taxes help care for their beaches. The rules at municipal beaches range from higher parking fees charged to nonresidents, an issue the ruling doesn't address, to strict prohibitions against their entry.</p>
        <p>''There is a saturation point for use of that resource without destroying those fragile parts of it,'' said Waterford First Selectman Paul B. Eccard, referring to Waterford Beach Park, a beach open only to residents who buy seasonal passes for $10. ''Historically, from the very beginning, the citizens of Waterford have regarded it as a fragile and treasured resource.''</p>
        <p>Other towns feel the same way. In Madison, which is famous for its Surf Club, only town residents and their guests are admitted.</p>
        <p>First Selectman David LaFemina said it's going to stay that way for now. ''We're not changing our policy,'' he said. ''We're going to wait for the appeal in Greenwich to be heard.''.</p>
        <p>He said Madison leaders wonder how to admit its residents -- who pay $20 each for the season -- let alone outsiders. ''Our town is growing leaps and bounds,'' he said. ''On a hot day, you can't find a parking space at our beach.''</p>
        <p>Stamford Mayor Daniel P. Malloy said that city admits nonresidents to its municipal beach because they believe laws require it. But, he admitted the city blocks their admission on weekends and the rest of the time charges them much more to park: they pay $15 per day (compared to the residents' fees of $10 for the season).</p>
        <p>''Quite frankly, I'm not advertising for outsiders,'' Mr. Malloy said. ''Parking is the premium. The community feels the obligation to provide parking for their residents. On weekends, we fill our lots with Stamford residents.''</p>
        <p>Westport charges higher parking fees for nonresidents at its Compo and Burying Hill beaches and will continue that practice, said First Selectwoman Diane Goss Farrell. For example, at Compo Beach, nonresidents pay $30 a day on the weekend, $15 a day on weekdays, or $375 a season, compared to the residents' rate of $25 for the season.</p>
        <p>Ms. Farrell said she does not think it would be fair to charge the same parking rates to residents and outsiders because residents taxes pay for lifeguards and maintenance.</p>
        <p>''When you want to equalize costs you would have to factor property taxes into it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Farrell said the town is proud that it welcomes anyone to walk onto its beaches. She said some people take the train and a taxi to spend a day sunbathing in Westport. She said when she campaigned at the beach three years ago, it seemed as if every other towel belonged to someone from places like Redding or Ridgefield.</p>
        <p>In East Lyme, the beach at McCook Point Park will remain restricted to its residents, who pay $20 for their passes, said First Selectman Wayne L. Fraser. In Old Lyme, only residents may buy the $10 passes to its White Sands Beach, said First Selectman Timothy Griswold.</p>
        <p>The Appellate Court ruling, if it stands, would not stop towns from charging more to nonresidents. It only states that nonresidents be admitted. Brenden P. Leydon, the Stamford lawyer who filed the suit against Greenwich, said he would take up that battle later.</p>
        <p>Penny Venetis, a lawyer who has filed public access lawsuits in New Jersey, said more and more, courts are ruling against restricted access to municipal parks.</p>
        <p>''A lot of municipalities have blinders on, but we now have two well-respected appellate courts in the span of a year coming to the same conclusion,'' said Ms. Venetis, who runs the Constitutional Litigation Clinic at Rutgers School of Law in Newark. She referred to the Connecticut Appellate Court and the New Jersey Appellate Court, which ruled last fall that the public has the right to reach waterfront walkways.</p>
        <p>In the region, beach access is granted or denied in different ways. In Massachusetts and New York, many beaches are restricted. In Rhode Island, most towns sell passes to the general public for their beaches to raise revenue. In New Jersey, a series of court cases between the 1950's and 1980's established a practice of municipal beaches opening to everyone, with fees that do not vary. In Connecticut, where less than half of its coastline is sandy beach to begin with, many believe that access is especially difficult.</p>
        <p>Last year, the State Department of Environmental Protection published a map that shows people how to get to the water, legally. The great majority of the access points are boat launches, though a few of them are town beaches that, for a fee or if you don't have a car, will let nonresidents in.</p>
        <p>Public access is not a clear-cut issue, and the agency holds no official opinion of what towns should do, said Jane Stahl, the department's deputy commissioner for air, waste, and water.</p>
        <p>''We have not intervened in the Greenwich case, and in large part it's because we recognize the limitations associated with the utilization of the beach,'' she said. The agency wants the public to get to the water, she said, but ''we need to recognize the physical limitations associated with many of our beaches.''</p>
        <p>In the Greenwich ruling, the Appellate Court judges agreed with the claim of Mr. Leydon that the Public Trust Doctrine in Connecticut entitles any resident of the state to visit any town park, including a beach, ''regardless of the fact that he is not a resident of the town.''</p>
        <p>The judges also said the town's prohibition of outsiders in its parks ordinance went beyond what the state meant to allow when it passed a special act creating the town park.</p>
        <p>''The town will vigorously oppose this attempt,'' said Lolly Prince, the Greenwich First Selectwoman. ''We believe the Connecticut Supreme Court is the proper venue, in light of the magnitude of the Appellate Court ruling.''</p>
        <p>Greenwich officials have appealed the ruling to the State Supreme Court, which is expected to decide in July whether it will hear the case. Ralph Elliot, a lawyer for the town, said that until any new court ruling, Greenwich will continue to admit only residents and their guests to the beach, as it has been doing between April and October since the 1940's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon said he has asked the Appellate Court to make its decision binding immediately. He said he wants the town to change its ways now, even if the case reopens in the Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>''I think it's just a question of fairness in general, and what it means to live in a free country,'' Mr. Leydon said. ''I think it's obscene that you can be stopped while walking into a public park and asked for an ID card.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Leydon, a former student of Ms. Venetis, used a case about access to a park in Haledon, N.J., as his inspiration when he decided to challenge Greenwich. Even though the New Jersey case was decided on constitutional grounds, rather than on the Public Trust Doctrine, Ms. Venetis, who was Mr. Leydon's professor at the time, said that doctrine was part of their argument and that it applies more clearly in the case of beaches.</p>
        <p>The reason, she said, is that the Public Trust Doctrine ''makes very, very clear that waterways are a protected area for the public.''</p>
        <p>Greenwich has made the case that the road leading to Greenwich Point Park can't be open to the general public because it goes through a private neighborhood, which has granted the town an easement. Ms. Venetis said that does not alter the public's rights.</p>
        <p>''Waterways are for everybody,'' she said. ''If they're blocking it in some way, they have to create a sort of easement. If the residents of the private road don't want people accessing it through this private road, the municipality has to create another access route.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
