<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where 'No Parking' Is Merely A Suggestion, Not a Command</title>
    <meta content="04PARK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: LITTLE ITALY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macfarquhar, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DB113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where 'No Parking' Is Merely A Suggestion, Not a Command</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macfarquhar, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on group of mostly retired residents of Sullivan Street in New York City's Little Italy section who pass time outdoors every Monday and Thursday from 11 AM to 2 PM waiting to park their cars legally; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In some neighborhoods, a ''No Parking'' sign clearly remains a matter of interpretation.</p>
        <p>It's hard to spend much time around Little Italy, for example, without noticing the occasional glistening sedan slithering in alongside a fire hydrant as if the thing wasn't there. Sometimes a chauffeur stands guard, sometimes not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In some neighborhoods, a ''No Parking'' sign clearly remains a matter of interpretation.</p>
        <p>It's hard to spend much time around Little Italy, for example, without noticing the occasional glistening sedan slithering in alongside a fire hydrant as if the thing wasn't there. Sometimes a chauffeur stands guard, sometimes not.</p>
        <p>But when you have neither the impunity to ignore regulations nor the resources to hire a driver, the law can also prove somewhat flexible. That is the attitude among a group of mostly retired denizens of Sullivan Street, who have transformed its twice-weekly no-parking times into a social hour.</p>
        <p>They chat. They read the paper. They sketch. They pay their bills. They do crossword puzzles. They eat lunch. They nap.  They do almost anything they can think of to fill the hours every Monday and Thursday from 11 a.m. to 2 p.m., when the city says parking is forbidden.</p>
        <p>The key to the strategy is never letting the car be out of reach.</p>
        <p>''How do I pass the time?'' said Carmine Auletta, who has been parking his car, currently a midnight blue Mercury Topaz, on the same stretch of street for 20 years. ''I watch the car. I clean the car. I watch the car some more.''</p>
        <p>The basic principle is to remain off the west side of the street when the cleaning machine trundles through, which happens during the first hour. Basically, these men all park on the street's east side until that happens, then shift west but stick to the car lest the parking police roll through, dispensing tickets.</p>
        <p>There are several schools of thought as to whether leaving the car is ever safe. Most advise against it. Take going to the bathroom.</p>
        <p>''That would be taking a chance, I'm not kidding,'' said Jimmy Iannacone, who has lived all of his 84 years on the street. During ''No Parking'' hours, he either sits behind the wheel of his aquamarine Ford Taurus or right beside it. ''I make sure I go to the bathroom before I come down.''</p>
        <p>A few restaurant owners don't bother sitting on the street all day, either. Instead, they put large cardboard signs in the windshields of their cars that point to their establishments. The device seems to ward off tickets. (Mr. Iannacone wonders if food enters the bargain.)</p>
        <p>Aside from the street's regulars, there are periodic guest parkers. Margaret Strucic was sitting in her husband's truck paying her bills while her husband was inside one of the buildings on a construction job. The couple usually show up at a building site at 6:30 a.m., and she stays in the truck.</p>
        <p>Compared to some places where she has sat all day, she found Sullivan Street welcoming.</p>
        <p>''The people here are very nice,'' Mrs. Strucic said. ''It feels like an old-fashioned neighborhood. Those people on Park Avenue, they are a little different up there.''</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: LITTLE ITALY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
