<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Race in America</title>
    <meta content="04SUN1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204775"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7DF1E3CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Race in America</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial introduces series of a dozen or so articles on state of race relations in US, to be published over next six weeks, the culmination of year-long investigation of Americans' private attitudes toward racial issues; notes aim of series is not to provide analysis or policy solutions, but to simply report on actual interplay of white and blacks on a daily basis</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A generation ago, after riots in several major cities, the Kerner Commission warned that the United States was in danger of becoming two nations, one black and one white. That has not happened. America is now an inescapably multiracial society from which there is no turning back for whites or blacks -- in its schools, its workplaces, its churches, its military and its cultural institutions. Yet divisions and frustrations persist on both sides, in minds and hearts if not in the laws of the land.</p>
        <p>For various reasons, however, most Americans, especially white Americans, do not like to share their personal feelings on race. In 1997, President Clinton proposed a national ''conversation'' about race. A committee was appointed and town meetings were duly organized across the country. Most of those who showed up were civic activists interested in public policy. Almost no one dared to discuss private attitudes, a more subtle and potentially divisive subject. Yet these attitudes lie at the heart of the racial question because it is attitudes and feelings that determine how we actually interact with one another, and whether we get along.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A generation ago, after riots in several major cities, the Kerner Commission warned that the United States was in danger of becoming two nations, one black and one white. That has not happened. America is now an inescapably multiracial society from which there is no turning back for whites or blacks -- in its schools, its workplaces, its churches, its military and its cultural institutions. Yet divisions and frustrations persist on both sides, in minds and hearts if not in the laws of the land.</p>
        <p>For various reasons, however, most Americans, especially white Americans, do not like to share their personal feelings on race. In 1997, President Clinton proposed a national ''conversation'' about race. A committee was appointed and town meetings were duly organized across the country. Most of those who showed up were civic activists interested in public policy. Almost no one dared to discuss private attitudes, a more subtle and potentially divisive subject. Yet these attitudes lie at the heart of the racial question because it is attitudes and feelings that determine how we actually interact with one another, and whether we get along.</p>
        <p>Partly with that in mind, the editors of The New York Times's news department decided over a year ago to investigate the state of race relations in the United States, not with an eye to providing analysis or policy solutions, but simply to report in detail on the actual interplay of whites and blacks on a daily basis. The result was a series of a dozen or so articles that will be published over the next six weeks. The reporters who wrote these pieces spent as much as a year on their projects, returning again and again to the people who eventually came to inhabit their narratives, learning a bit more each time about their fears and frustrations and hopes.</p>
        <p>In nearly every case, African-Americans were far more willing to talk about race, in large part because they have endured America's long history of discrimination and live with its consequences every single day. Yet in the end whites began to open up as well, sharing their thoughts about a subject that many would just as soon avoid and others do not think about at all. The fact that whites and blacks, as well as Latinos and Asian-Americans, were eventually able to address painful issues with great candor is one of the series' great reportorial accomplishments.</p>
        <p>The first article appears today. It examines what happens in a Pentecostal church in Georgia when blacks begin to join an all-white congregation. In broadest terms, the piece is an examination of the struggle of two races to coexist in a world neither wants to leave, of the compromises accepted by both sides, of the narrowness of some parishioners and the bigheartedness of others. The struggle to coexist, in fact, defines most of the pieces in this series.</p>
        <p>An article later this week, for example, will explore the daily tensions among white and black soldiers in the United States Army, an institution where the work force is fully and officially integrated and where racial resentments are usually thought to be a thing of the past. Another details the extraordinarily complex, painfully edgy relationship between the black producer and white writer who together created HBO's extraordinary documentary on Baltimore's drug culture.</p>
        <p>In some cases there is evidence of progress, moments of growth and reconciliation, small epiphanies when one side comes to understand the motivations of the other and both come to understand that they need each other. In others, the divisions seem too great to bridge. The lifelong friendship between two Cubans, one white, the other black, loses its intimacy under the centrifugal strains of racial isolation in their adopted home of Miami. Whites, blacks, Mexicans and American Indians competing for rock-bottom wages on the factory floor simply cannot connect when racial animosities are sharpened by economic fears. White and black boys and girls, fast friends in a suburban elementary school, are tugged apart by seemingly irresistible cultural and academic forces by the time they begin high school.</p>
        <p>Whether they chronicle success, failure or just plain inertia, these are stories that report race relations as they actually exist on a human scale in America. In a way, without deliberately trying to, the people who populate these stories provide the uncomfortably candid conversation about race that Mr. Clinton sought but never got. The stories hardly depict a perfect world, but they do depict a country in which citizens bring strong feelings, deep thought and, in a heartening number of cases, resilient spirits to one of the abiding issues of American life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
