<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lives; Clicking the Habit</title>
    <meta content="04LIVEST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="106" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, Lynne Sharon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE6DC173CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lives; Clicking the Habit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lynne Sharon Schwartz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwartz, Lynne Sharon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lynne Sharon Schwartz Lives art</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that my habit is history, I don't mind going public. Sharing, that is. Sure, I miss the high. I'll miss it every day for the rest of my life. But I know I'm better off clean.</p>
        <p>The war on drugs drags on, A.A. meetings are S.R.O. but no one breathes a word about the addiction that's become the writer's occupational disease: computer solitaire. Maybe that's because it leaves no visible signs: no needle tracks or dilated pupils, no staggering gait or slurred speech. And it's more or less harmless: no highway wrecks or liver failure or ghastly teen mayhem. The only problem is that we don't get any work done. But maybe we really don't want to get any work done.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that my habit is history, I don't mind going public. Sharing, that is. Sure, I miss the high. I'll miss it every day for the rest of my life. But I know I'm better off clean.</p>
        <p>The war on drugs drags on, A.A. meetings are S.R.O. but no one breathes a word about the addiction that's become the writer's occupational disease: computer solitaire. Maybe that's because it leaves no visible signs: no needle tracks or dilated pupils, no staggering gait or slurred speech. And it's more or less harmless: no highway wrecks or liver failure or ghastly teen mayhem. The only problem is that we don't get any work done. But maybe we really don't want to get any work done.</p>
        <p>It is no secret that writers, in fact freelancers in general, will use any delaying tactic to avoid starting work. In that sense, solitaire (so aptly named for our condition) is the diabolic answer to our prayers. It even feels almost like work -- after all, we're poised at the computer, able if not quite willing.</p>
        <p>I used to think I was the only one. My shameful little secret. I'd go to my desk full of good intentions, but before I could glance at the waiting work, the husky voice of temptation would murmur, How about a quick game of solitaire (or maybe hearts) for starters? Five minutes, no big deal. There went the first half-hour in captivated oblivion. Sated, I'd turn to the task at hand and concentrate for an hour or so, if I was lucky. Then out of nowhere came a faint gnawing in the gut -- the need for another hit. Next, as night follows day, the familiar debate between the stern disciplinarian and the libertine who share my head. Forget it. Before they could warm to the subject, my fingers, apparently with a will of their own, were clicking on the game keys. On it went, from work to play and back again, into the fading light of another lost afternoon.</p>
        <p>Hearts, in particular, led me into pockets of the past better left unvisited. In each game I needed to give names to my three adversaries. Sometimes I chose the names of childhood friends I hadn't seen in decades and found myself re-enacting nasty pre-pubescent squabbles. Let's get Sue, I'd mutter to Judy -- she always thinks she's so special. Or while passing the dread queen of spades to Ronnie -- there, that's for the time you snitched about the homework. In more vindictive moods, I'd choose the names of long-lost boyfriends or teachers who hadn't appreciated me enough. As a way of settling old scores, this was pretty pathetic, and besides, I usually lost. Finally it dawned on me that I was playing against a programmed machine, and the program, by whatever name, was smarter than I was.</p>
        <p>With some trepidation, I confided my obsession to a few friends. Imagine my surprise! All over the country, my colleagues, in their monkish solitude, were mesmerized at the screen, escaping the rigors of le mot juste. (One luminary confessed to 9,700 games of solitaire. Others raved about Tetris, a trance-inducing game luckily unknown to me.) Add in all the consultant types working from home nowadays, the graduate students huddled in the library, plus retirees charmed by their new toys, and it's clear that we're faced with an epidemic.</p>
        <p>Once I caught on, I did what every addict does. Rationalize. I can lick this if I figure out what's driving me. Analyze the urge and master it. O.K., it wasn't the games themselves. I could go for years without shuffling a real deck. It was watching those virtual cards jump around on the screen at the flick of my finger. Magical. Hypnotic. Irresistible. The sheer distracting nonsense of it. There were deeper reasons, too. The perennial frustration of writing, aggravated by the corporate takeover of publishing, the decimation of independent bookstores, the fact that editors no longer return phone calls. I was avoiding not only the blank screen but also all its ramifications.</p>
        <p>Still, addiction is addiction. The truth did not set me free.</p>
        <p>At this rate, my professional future was doomed. Did I want to spend my life playing solitaire or writing books? The choice was simple; I knew what I had to do. Banish the program files. But oh, that moment of truth when the screen flashed its ultimate challenge: ''Are you sure you want to delete this program permanently? You will not be able to access it again. . . . '' My finger trembled over Enter. Life would never be the same. Gone that rapt oblivion; gone the thrill of watching the cards leap and pirouette at my whim. Never again to see those delicious words -- You win! -- alongside the tiny red and black hearts logo. I took a deep breath, recalled my once-purposeful life and clicked solitaire, et al., into limbo.</p>
        <p>It was one of the hardest things I've ever done, but I'm glad. It was a matter of life or death, professionally speaking. Choose life, they say, and I did.</p>
        <p>But they also say nothing's truly lost in the digital world. Can anyone tell me how to get them back? I've learned my lesson. I'd only do it 10 minutes a day, I swear.</p>
        <p>Lynne Sharon Schwartz is the author of ''Face to Face,'' a collection of essays, and ''In the Family Way: An Urban Comedy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lynne Sharon Schwartz is the author of ''Face to Face,'' a collection of essays, and ''In the Family Way: An Urban Comedy.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
