<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Floats! It Speeds! It's a Train!</title>
    <meta content="04MAGL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magnetism and Magnets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">High-Speed Rail Projects</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brookhaven National Laboratory</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Danby, Gordon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotsalas, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E6DA153CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Floats! It Speeds! It's a Train!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE COTSALAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cotsalas, Valerie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on maglev, high-speed train concept developed three decades ago by Brookhaven National Laboratory scientists James Powell and Gordon Danby; two recently received Benjamin Franklin Medal in Engineering and held demonstrations and symposiums in Philadelphia; photos; diagram; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was a dark and stormy night, as James Powell likes to tell it, when he got stuck in a traffic jam on the Throgs Neck Bridge in the early 1960's, heading for Boston. The five long hours he spent in that jam gave Dr. Powell, a Brookhaven National Laboratory scientist, a lot of time to think.</p>
        <p>Imagine a train, he thought, that could ''fly'' above the ground at 300 miles an hour without ever touching its rails. Imagine zipping down to Florida for the weekend, then unloading your car from the train and driving off into the sunset.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was a dark and stormy night, as James Powell likes to tell it, when he got stuck in a traffic jam on the Throgs Neck Bridge in the early 1960's, heading for Boston. The five long hours he spent in that jam gave Dr. Powell, a Brookhaven National Laboratory scientist, a lot of time to think.</p>
        <p>Imagine a train, he thought, that could ''fly'' above the ground at 300 miles an hour without ever touching its rails. Imagine zipping down to Florida for the weekend, then unloading your car from the train and driving off into the sunset.</p>
        <p>When the young scientist returned from his weekend trip to Boston, he proposed the idea to his friend and Brookhaven colleague Gordon Danby. Using their expertise in superconducting magnets and engineering, and working in their spare time, they developed a high-speed train they called the maglev.</p>
        <p>For that invention, the two scientists received the Benjamin Franklin Medal in Engineering last May, more than three decades after they published their first findings. During a week of symposiums in Philadelphia, the inventors presented their design and a demonstration model to about 100 enthusiastic listeners.</p>
        <p>''When we say it's a 300-mile-per-hour train that floats above the rails, that's something that people can understand,'' said William Dickhart, who presented the medals. ''It grabs your imagination.'' Mr. Dickhart is a retired manager of the technical center of the Budd Company, which once made trains, and is a consultant to Trans Rapid International, a German company involved in maglevs.</p>
        <p>The idea behind the maglev (for magnetic levitation) is that when current runs through a wire, called a conductor, a magnetic field is created. The stronger the current, the stronger the field. If you use a superconductor, a metal that can conduct current with close to zero resistance at extremely cold temperatures, the field is so strong that it can support even a train.</p>
        <p>Once the train is levitated, there is little friction to slow it down. Add some electrical power for propulsion, and soon the train is zipping along at 300 m.p.h.</p>
        <p>''You could go anyplace in the country with this, practically,'' said Dr. Powell, who is 67. ''In addition, there would be lower-speed feeder lines, let's say along the Long Island Rail Road. You could take a vehicle at 150 miles per hour, get into New York in half an hour, then take another vehicle probably to go to Miami, or wherever, on the system.''</p>
        <p>But what has happened to the American maglev, which promised to solve the passenger and freight transportation problems of a nation? The answer is that the maglev has been researched, developed and refined and is now being built as a high-speed train between two major cities. The cities are Tokyo and Osaka, and the country that took the Americans' design and proved it could be done is Japan.</p>
        <p>''The Japanese picked right up on the fact that our electrodynamic maglev really worked, and they proceeded to develop it,'' said Dr. Danby, who is 70. ''It didn't do us much good, but it certainly started a worldwide movement.''</p>
        <p>That movement started out at a good clip in the United States in the 1960's after the scientists, now retired, published papers describing just how to build a maglev train system. Officials at the Department of Transportation called Dr. Powell a short time later to report they had received 50 proposals.</p>
        <p>But the maglev party ended in the early 1970's, the scientists said, after President Richard M. Nixon ordered a review of the potential for high-speed ground transport and the Department of Transportation concluded that airplanes and automobiles would meet all America's needs for the foreseeable future. ''It was a little frustrating,'' Dr. Powell said, ''but both of us have a lot of other things we do.''</p>
        <p>Each man holds more than a dozen patents, including the original maglev patent and several others for modifications. Dr. Powell has developed lightweight nuclear power-generating systems and has been involved in studies of high-level nuclear waste. Dr. Danby has worked on accelerator design technology and was the chief designer of the magnet for the first open M.R.I. machine -- faster and friendlier than the tunnel variety -- which uses magnets to create images of the human body.</p>
        <p>The maglev was never an official project at Brookhaven. Beginning the day Dr. Powell returned from his slow trip to Boston until they published their first paper in 1963, the scientists wrote out their calculations and discussed the design in the house they shared in East Patchogue. Even after Dr. Danby married and moved out, the two scientists spent free time developing a stable and efficient system.</p>
        <p>''In those days, Brookhaven was much more like a university than what it is today,'' said Dr. Powell, who now lives in Shoreham. ''The lab was a great place for having other interests, and at about the time that we got interested in maglev, I was working on ways of making an improved electrical generator out of a reactor -- taking hot gas from a reactor and running it through a magnetic field to make power.''</p>
        <p>In more recent times, Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, the New York Democrat, has tried to drum up congressional support to start building an American maglev system.</p>
        <p>Since Japanese scientists have already proved that the maglev can handle extreme weather conditions, earthquakes and the stresses of trains passing each other at 300 miles an hour, Dr. Danby said, the outlook for the train is rosier today.</p>
        <p>At a projected cost of $10 million a mile to build a system, comparable to the cost of building the Interstate highway system, Dr. Powell said, the maglev would pay for itself in two years, carrying both freight and passengers. And because the system's rails only operate when the train and its magnets are passing by, there is less energy consumption than in conventional trains.</p>
        <p>''The motor requires a modest amount of power to push the magnets forward, but the inductive suspension basically requires nothing on the ground but shaped loops of metal,'' Dr. Danby said.</p>
        <p>In 1998, after a report by a task force of the Senate Energy and Public Works Committee that was headed by Dr. Danby and Dr. Powell, Congress appropriated $60 million for seven maglev projects in six states.</p>
        <p>Design work began in 1999 and is continuing, each project hoping to be selected for further financing.</p>
        <p>Dr. Danby and Dr. Powell have formed their own company and are working on one of the seven contending projects, in Florida, both there and from a hangar at Brookhaven Airport. The Florida train, if it is built, would ferry tourists between the Titusville airport, the Cape Canaveral seaport and the Kennedy Space Center.</p>
        <p>''We recognized that if we tried to build from here to New York, it would be wonderful, but it would cost a lot more money than this project,'' Dr. Danby said. ''If there was an enormous amount of government money available, anything's possible, but we had to assume that that's unlikely to happen.''</p>
        <p>Sitting at the dining room table at Dr. Danby's 18th-century home in Wading River, the two scientists imagined what daily life on Long Island would be like with a national network of maglev trains.</p>
        <p>''You would see a lot less traffic congestion and cheaper goods,'' Dr. Powell said. ''And there's a more subtle benefit which isn't usually appreciated, which is that the maglev system is weather-independent and more than that, it's nonsaturable. Because you can carry so many people on a given guideway, you could never saturate it like you saturate airports or like you saturate highways.''</p>
        <p>The two scientists envision a lower-speed maglev in places like Long Island that would feed into a high-speed interstate system. But the L.I.R.R. is planning a less revolutionary upgrade, using more than $2 billion recently approved by New York State for new electric cars and to renew older cars, tracks and signal systems. The trains currently travel at a top speed of 80 m.p.h.</p>
        <p>''Maglev is a very promising technology for inter-city high-speed rail,'' said Brian Dolan, an L.I.R.R. spokesman, ''as opposed to the close proximity of our stations from one another.''</p>
        <p>Now that there is modest financing to develop the maglev after nearly 40 years of starts and stops, the scientists hope the maglev will have its chance to be the choice transportation mode of this century. Another $950 million has been authorized by Congress for maglev development, but the money has still not been appropriated and if recent history is any measure, that support is not a sure thing.</p>
        <p>''Somebody pointed out a few years ago that in this country, nobody wants to be first, but nobody wants to be second either,'' Dr. Powell said, mulling the psychology behind getting financial support. ''Once a real system is in operation, everybody will want it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
