<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</title>
    <meta content="T02PHI0AA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4DB153CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIES: CRITIC'S CHOICE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anita Gates discusses several movies that will be shown on television during current week; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SONGLIAN is 19 and has just left her parents' home to become the fourth wife of a rich man in Zhang Yimou's wise, hauntingly beautiful drama RAISE THE RED LANTERN (1991), set in 1920's China. The master is so weathly, in fact, that each of his wives has a house of her own. (And the servants light the red lanterns each evening at the house in which he plans to spend that night.) Mistress No. 2 is warm and welcoming, but she may be hiding a vicious side. Mistress No. 3, a former opera singer, is glamorous, jealous and a little too friendly with the family doctor. As Mistress No. 4, Songlian (the gorgeous Gong Li, whose every subtle facial expression is a life lesson) learns fast about the politics of power. And as she learns, she does a great deal of damage - Sunday at 2 p.m. and Sunday/Early Monday at 3:30 a.m. on Bravo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SONGLIAN is 19 and has just left her parents' home to become the fourth wife of a rich man in Zhang Yimou's wise, hauntingly beautiful drama RAISE THE RED LANTERN (1991), set in 1920's China. The master is so weathly, in fact, that each of his wives has a house of her own. (And the servants light the red lanterns each evening at the house in which he plans to spend that night.) Mistress No. 2 is warm and welcoming, but she may be hiding a vicious side. Mistress No. 3, a former opera singer, is glamorous, jealous and a little too friendly with the family doctor. As Mistress No. 4, Songlian (the gorgeous Gong Li, whose every subtle facial expression is a life lesson) learns fast about the politics of power. And as she learns, she does a great deal of damage - Sunday at 2 p.m. and Sunday/Early Monday at 3:30 a.m. on Bravo.</p>
        <p>Woody Allen stepped back and let John Cusack play his alter ego in BULLETS OVER BROADWAY (1994), a wickedly funny backstage film about amibition, rehearsals and rewrites. Mr. Cusack plays a young playwright who isn't nearly as talented as he thinks he is. Luckily, or unluckily for him, a mobster named Cheech (Chazz Palminteri), who is hanging around the theater as an actress's bodyguard, is a natural theatrical genius. Dianne Wiest won the best supporting actress Oscar for her role as a Broadway prima donna whose signature line, ''Don't speak,'' gets better every time she says it - Saturday at 3 p.m. on Channel 11.</p>
        <p>Robert Downey Jr. had made movies in his extreme youth, but we didn't know he was a genius until he was 27 and starred in CHAPLIN (1992). The film, directed by Richard Attenborough, is too slow-paced and more appreciative than insightful, but Mr. Downey's portrayal of the silent screen's most brilliant comedian - from London poverty to Hollwyood superfame - makes it more than worthwhile. The casting is fun too: Dan Aykroyd plays Mack Sennett, Kevin Kline portrays Douglas Fairbanks, and Geraldine Chaplin is outstanding as her own grandmother - Saturday at 8 p.m on Channel 55.</p>
        <p>What if Albert Einstein had a beautiful, brilliant, unmarried blond niece? And what if an auto mechanic fell in love with her? Who would be smart enough to see that she should break her engagement to a deadly dull intellectual and follow her heart? Walter Mathau, Meg Ryan and Tim Robbins are the stars of I.Q. (1994), a bright romantic comedy that makes 1950's Princeton, N.J., look like a paradise. Fred Schepisi directed - Saturday at 8 p.m. on Channel 4.</p>
        <p>Viewers might tune in to see IT (1927) just for the novelty. After all, this was the silent film that gave the young Clara Bow her lifelong nickname, the It Girl. But the movie, directed by Clarence Badger, has considerably period charm (even if it does include a scene in which the author Elinor Glyn drops by to explain the concept of It, a totally un-self-conscious sex appeal, to the characters). Bow plays a poor but perky shopgirl with a crush on her new boss, the department store owner's son (Antonio Moreno). Things go well between them until there's a little misunderstanding about a newspaper story and a baby. When Bow sees her new boss for the first time, her dialogue title reads ''Sweet Santa Claus, give me him'' - Sunday at midnight on TCM.</p>
        <p>- Anita Gates</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
