<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cache</title>
    <meta content="04GATEST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanchez, Thomas</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Day of the Bees (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D6153DF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cache</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anita Gates</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gates, Anita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aita Gates reviews book Day of the Bees by Thomas Sanchez (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAY OF THE BEES</p>
        <p>By Thomas Sanchez.</p>
        <p>305 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAY OF THE BEES</p>
        <p>By Thomas Sanchez.</p>
        <p>305 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $24.</p>
        <p>THE painter Francisco Zermano rose to fame in an era when artists were giants. And he had a great love affair that ended mysteriously. Louise Collard, his mistress, disappeared from Ville Rouge, their favorite spot in Provence, in the early days of World War II. Zermano went on to prosper, marry and procreate in Mallorca, but eventually, in 1969, he too dropped out of sight. Some people believe that he's dead, perhaps murdered.</p>
        <p>As Thomas Sanchez' fourth novel begins, the world has just learned Louise's fate. An elderly recluse, she has died having ''lived out her life unrecognized in the medieval hilltop village of Reigne, far across the valley from Ville Rouge.'' There is to be an auction of her belongings (the catalog is titled ''Louise Collard: The Muse Exposed''), and the book's narrator, an unnamed art professor from California, heads for Reigne to see what he can see. A man from the New York gallery that represents Zermano lets him into Collard's house and tells him he can have Louise's seemingly worthless old knitting baskets. And what should be underneath the false bottoms of those baskets but bundles of letters from Francisco to Louise, as well as unsent replies from Louise to her lover. Of course, the letters tell everything.</p>
        <p>This is a gorgeous, tantalizing premise for a romantic novel, but one that ''Day of the Bees'' fails completely to realize. The most obvious problem is that Sanchez -- whose earlier works, ''Rabbit Boss,'' ''Mile Zero'' and ''Zoot-Suit Murders,'' dealt with American Indians, burned-out 60's activists in Key West and the Los Angeles barrio in the 1940's -- has no command of the epistolary form. Or no respect for it.</p>
        <p>''I don't think any woman was ever seduced by a man the way I was seduced by you,'' Louise writes to her lover. ''I had gone to a gallery opening in Paris. The gallery was not displaying your work, but the paintings of another artist.'' Francisco needs to be told how they met? The novel's exposition never gets any more convincing, or any less clumsy.</p>
        <p>Sanchez plays writer's games with embarrassing obviousness. He can't toss out a clue without calling attention to it: ''I saw you hobbling on your cane, your knees still not healed from what happened last summer,'' writes Louise. And elsewhere: ''Perhaps if I had not intervened, and you had smashed the Officer with the tire iron, then what happened later with the bees would never have occurred and we would not now be separated.'' Sometimes the clue-planting is just cheap, as when Francisco writes, referring to his Stutz Bearcat, ''In its trunk you will find something I have left for you, something you must know in the event of my death.''</p>
        <p>When Sanchez grows tired of playing detective novelist, he still tends toward the overblown. ''We climbed out of the Bearcat, wanting each other again,'' Louise writes. ''For lovers, between desire and the end of the world, there is only desire. There is only the eternal instant of now.''</p>
        <p>Occasionally, to Sanchez' credit, his language comes close to real effect. ''Their bodies exude a dusty scent of pollen, the sweet smell of lavender, the pungent crush of wild thyme and rosemary,'' Louise writes of the landing of thousands of bees on her body. ''Honey and death. Honey and venom. Pollen and sperm. Wings brushing kisses.'' This is the kind of intense bipolar sensuality that David Lynch evokes so well in his films. Most of the time, however, Sanchez is just telegraphing plot revelations left and right.</p>
        <p>And there is indeed a plot behind all this blowsy language. The events and consequences of a particular ''hot summer day in the cherry orchard'' involve a German officer, a beekeeper, a pregnancy and what may have been a crucifixion. Later, Louise delivers messages for the Resistance, but only because the local postmaster demands her cooperation in return for surrendering her letters from Francisco. We also learn a good deal about Louise and Francisco's sexual relationship (which involves bondage and a ''Story of O'' element) and about Francisco's fascination with a 13th-century mystic whose married lover was stricken with breast cancer. But the revelations are anticlimactic, undercut by the florid narration that precedes them.</p>
        <p>So what could have been a touching denouement feels instead like inept melodrama. As the novel winds down, there's even a seven-page soliloquy in a ninth-century fortress guarded by Buddhist monks. Wouldn't you know it?</p>
        <p>Anita Gates contributes articles about the arts to The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Anita Gates contributes articles about the arts to The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
