<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: Kindler, Gentler; A Newt-less Revolution With a Familiar Agenda</title>
    <meta content="04MITC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204786"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gingrich, Newt (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reagan, Ronald Wilson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DC1E3CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1128" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: Kindler, Gentler; A Newt-less Revolution With a Familiar Agenda</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican presidential candidate George W Bush has been pushing well-worn conservative agenda cloaked in more sympathetic rhetoric and symbolism; his new approach has given Republicans the kinder, gentler face they have longed for in place of steely intellectualism of former House Speaker and conservative firebrand Newt Gingrich; but substance of Bush's platform does little to challenge basic conservative tenets that have guided party at least since Ronald Reagan (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS Gov. George W. Bush rolls out policy address after policy address, Congressional Republicans are watching him do what Newt Gingrich, Trent Lott and the self-effacing J. Dennis Hastert could not: win a fresh hearing for ideas cherished by conservatives.</p>
        <p>It's the Newt-less revolution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS Gov. George W. Bush rolls out policy address after policy address, Congressional Republicans are watching him do what Newt Gingrich, Trent Lott and the self-effacing J. Dennis Hastert could not: win a fresh hearing for ideas cherished by conservatives.</p>
        <p>It's the Newt-less revolution.</p>
        <p>For all the recent talk of how Mr. Bush has moved to the center, the thrust of his campaign has been to employ more sympathetic rhetoric and symbolism to refashion a Republican policy wish list long familiar on Capitol Hill and in conservative think tanks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush does not speak in strident, angry tones of big government. Rather, he focuses on how conservative ideas can help the working poor, describing, for example, how tax incentives could help expand home ownership. Sometimes the picture alone sends a message, with Mr. Bush standing next to minority children or campaigning in the inner city.</p>
        <p>It's this sort of thing that has helped Mr. Bush give the Republicans the kinder, gentler face they have longed for in place of Mr. Gingrich's steely intellectualism.</p>
        <p>In substance, though, Mr. Bush has done little to challenge the basic conservative tenets that have defined his party at least since Ronald Reagan's presidency. Yes, he has chastised House Republicans on the budget, and told Senate Republicans not to tie the president's hands on foreign policy. But only on education has he broken fundamentally with his conservative allies by calling for the federal government to play a more forceful role in America's schools.</p>
        <p>''Free market guys like me don't see in his suggestions anything that's problematic,'' said Grover Norquist, president of Americans for Tax Reform, who had been a Gingrich adviser. ''And we welcome his much-improved tone and rhetoric -- over Barry Goldwater, let's say.''</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Bush's proposals, like diverting some Social Security payroll taxes to individual investment accounts, have drawn rave reviews from the conservative intellectuals. As the writer Ramesh Ponnuru noted in a recent National Review story, Social Security is ''symbolically what's left of the New Deal,'' and Mr. Bush is not holding it sacrosanct.</p>
        <p>Many of Mr. Bush's ideas have been incubating in Republican policy circles for years. For example: When Mr. Bush spoke on Social Security, he was picking up a ball dropped by the House Ways and Means Committee, when Republican leaders, afraid of the political risk, scuttled plans to create an individual investment plan.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Bush's support of a missile defense system with global reach has a GOP heritage stretching back to President Reagan's Strategic Defense Initiative.</p>
        <p>In advocating a $1.3 trillion tax reduction over 10 years, Mr. Bush is aligning himself with House and Senate Republicans, who pushed in 1999 for a $792 billion tax reduction, then retreated in disarray after President Clinton vetoed it.</p>
        <p>So, too, Mr. Bush's proposal for a  tax credit of up to $2,000 a family to help working people with low or moderate incomes buy health insurance is very close to proposals pushed by Representative Dick Armey, the House Majority Leader from Texas, and Senator Bill Frist, Republican of Tennessee.</p>
        <p>No wonder that Mr. Bush's advisers occasionally become impatient with comparisons of their candidate's ''compassionate conservatism'' to Mr. Clinton's ''New Democrat'' break with his own party's orthodoxy. Mr. Bush's policy agenda, one of his aides said, ''is within Republican orthodoxy but takes it to the next step.''</p>
        <p>FOR Congressional Republicans, who long regarded themselves as belonging to the party of ideas, this is vindication. This time, they feel, they have the right messenger and, as a presidential contender, he has a megaphone almost as big as the president's. Praising Mr. Bush's Social Security proposal, Mr. Armey said, ''A Republican in the House brings it up and before he can get it before the American people it gets reframed as the secret Republican plan to destroy Social Security. When Governor Bush brings it up, people first say, 'What is he talking about?' And when he brings it up it has a standing with the American people.''</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, a Bush spokesman who attended many House Republican hand-wringing sessions, noted that a lawmaker with an idea got little attention, but ''when Governor Bush gave his speech on Social Security it was carried live on CNN and Fox TV and made the front page of all the national newspapers the next day.''</p>
        <p>DEMOCRATS argue that, despite his amiability, Mr. Bush's positions are to the right of those of the great American middle.</p>
        <p>''I think he's a fairly doctrinaire conservative,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer Democrat of New York. ''I think he has done a masterful job at making himself look more moderate than the positions he has taken in the campaign, let alone his record in Texas.''</p>
        <p>So Mr. Gore and his allies have been trying to portray Mr. Bush as out of the mainstream by branding each of his proposals a ''risky scheme.'' But this has proven harder for the Democrats than four years ago -- and not just because of Mr. Bush's manner.</p>
        <p>The federal surplus has changed the political dynamics. In 1995, when Republicans wanted to balance the budget as well as grant a large tax cut, it meant they had to make unpopular reductions in other programs. By contrast, Mr. Bush has been able to propose both a large tax cut and new social spending. And Democrats, in trying to co-opt or defuse some Republican ideas, have made them harder to demonize.</p>
        <p>Take missile defense. Last year the White House dropped its veto threat against legislation calling for a national missile defense after some language was inserted committing the nation to build such a  program only when it became ''technologically possible.''</p>
        <p>That accommodation -- as well as a newly perceived threat from rogue nations -- helped shift the debate so that the battle was no longer over whether to have a missile defense, but what kind and at what cost.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Clinton's call for the government itself to invest some Social Security taxes in the stock market, coupled with his proposal to give lower income taxpayers up to $300 a year for a new type of retirement account, makes it harder for Democrats to argue against Mr. Bush's innovations.</p>
        <p>Public attitudes also change over time and over generations. The Bush campaign is betting that with nearly half of American households now owning stock, fewer Americans will so fear the market that they will insist that Social Security remain as it is.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing more powerful than an idea whose time has come,'' Mr. Armey said. The Democrats are hoping mightily that Mr. Bush's timing is off.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
