<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Its Best, A Season That Made The Leap Into Life</title>
    <meta content="04BRAN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE143CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Its Best, A Season That Made The Leap Into Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley, in view of June 4 airing of Tony Awards, assesses current Broadway theater season; drawing; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I WAS wonderin' what it was like to be you.''</p>
        <p>Things are still more or less in control when these words are spoken in the revival of Sam Shepard's ''True West,'' one of the high points in the dizzyingly uneven Broadway season that just ended. The spilled quarts of beer and sweat, the ransacked drawers, the smashed furniture and the mutilated egos all lie ahead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I WAS wonderin' what it was like to be you.''</p>
        <p>Things are still more or less in control when these words are spoken in the revival of Sam Shepard's ''True West,'' one of the high points in the dizzyingly uneven Broadway season that just ended. The spilled quarts of beer and sweat, the ransacked drawers, the smashed furniture and the mutilated egos all lie ahead.</p>
        <p>But that simple sentence, uttered with gruff shyness by one brother to another, is what really opens the doors to the ensuing chaos. You have to be careful about wondering what it's like to be someone else. It can take you into strange and slippery places. And isn't it exhilarating?</p>
        <p>Imagining yourself into another existence, and then giving physical life to those imaginings, is at the primal heart of drama. It is what makes play-acting so incredibly glamorous to children, and it is a large part of what keeps many of us hooked on live theater. Much of literature may be fueled by this empathic leap of the imagination. But what art form other than theater gives that leap such unnerving immediacy, the sense of watching a circus performer grabbing in midair for the trapeze?</p>
        <p>Books are consumed in the head, in a private dialogue between writer and reader; movies, while often experienced communally, are inevitably distanced by being confined to two dimensions. Theater, taking place in the flesh in real time, is the most public and the least lonely of the narrative arts.</p>
        <p>Even when it ponders the opacity of people, as it frequently does these days, theater pulses with its vital human connection with its audience. This may indeed be one reason that the televised Tony Awards ceremonies (this year's take place tonight) have traditionally captured so little of what makes the theater distinctive. But if the celebration that is the Tony Awards falls short of embodying what it celebrates (and limiting itself to the parochial professional village known as Broadway doesn't help matters), there is much to toast in the first New York theater season to stretch into a new century. The best offerings of the last year, at least among nonmusical productions, reached with a heady suppleness of both form and content to envision complete lives, to open human minds for public display.</p>
        <p>The director Matthew Warchus's dynamic production of ''True West,'' Mr. Shepard's portrait of diametrically different brothers who unwittingly trade roles, took on a new Pirandello-like vividness with its electric young stars, Philip Seymour Hoffman and John C. Reilly, switching the two leads in alternating cycles of different performances.</p>
        <p>To see either version is a thrill; to see both is to perceive the very essence of the play -- which is, after all, about the mutability of personality -- being both altered and confirmed by the changed casting. You become newly aware of just how much an actor is an author of any given production, and the degree to which a play reinvents itself on a nightly basis.</p>
        <p>Uptown and down, the quest to peer into the consciousness of others took varied and vigorous forms: from the avant-gardist Richard Foreman's fragmented landscape of a philosopher's mind, ''Bad Boy Nietzsche!,'' to the director and playwright Moises Kaufman's ''Laramie Project,'' in which a team of performers shaped interviews surrounding the murder of a gay student in Wyoming into a heartbreaking work of theatrical journalism.</p>
        <p>The best new plays to open on Broadway, Michael Frayn's ''Copenhagen'' and Claudia Shear's ''Dirty Blonde,'' summoned the lingering presences of long-dead real-life figures -- the movie star Mae West (''Dirty Blonde'') and the physicists Niels Bohr and Werner Heisenberg (''Copenhagen'') -- to figure out what made them run and how they shaped the world around them. They are biographical mystery plays, in a sense, in which the dramatists invite those watching to follow along as fellow detectives.</p>
        <p>Our feeling of being in on the process is achieved through the actors, too. In ''Dirty Blonde,'' staged with an astonishing fluidity by James Lapine, two characters, played by Ms. Shear and Kevin Chamberlin, actually turn into Mae West. The transformations are the engine of the play, a reflection of the characters' (and our) hunger to understand West and, most ingeniously, a means of letting us come to understand the characters.</p>
        <p>SIMILARLY, in ''Copenhagen,'' directed with canny precision by Michael Blakemore, who had previously staged it in London, it's a ravenous, frustrated curiosity that propels the drama, in which the ghosts of Bohr, his wife and Heisenberg try to pin down exactly what did happen during a tense World War II meeting among the three characters.</p>
        <p>Philip Bosco, Blair Brown and Michael Cumpsty bring a contagious fierceness to their characters' quests, and what is effectively a shifting dance of subjective points of view, that keeps the evening from drifting into the ether of abstraction. The implicit watchwords of the evening are ones we have all said from time to time: ''What were they thinking?''  ''Copenhagen'' makes the point that even the participants themselves couldn't answer the question.</p>
        <p>A spirit of wonder at the opacity of people, even those you think you know well, infuses this year's Pulitzer Prize winner for drama. That's Donald Margulies's ''Dinner With Friends,'' and like most recent Pulitzer winners, it is tellingly an Off Broadway production.</p>
        <p>As familiar in its shape, dialogue and sensibility as an episode of the television series ''thirtysomething,'' the play nonetheless has a piercing emotional eloquence that speaks directly to the baby boom audience that has made it a long-running hit. Given a top-drawer production by Daniel Sullivan, ''Dinner With Friends'' paints a portrait of two 40-ish couples, best friends, who come to realize they have never understood one another at all.</p>
        <p>It's a cold and isolating perception, yet the production emanates a continual warmth, generated by the four actors' loving embrace of characters who aren't always sympathetic. The fact that it is a live drama, staged in an intimate theater, only strengthens its connection with middle-aged audience members just beginning to confront their own mortality.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sullivan, demonstrating a directorial versatility matched this season by Mr. Blakemore (who is responsible for the triumphant revival of ''Kiss Me, Kate'' as well as ''Copenhagen''), is also the man behind the soul-stirring Broadway revival of Eugene O'Neill's ''Moon for the Misbegotten.'' The play itself is a deeply affecting example of an artist reclaiming unhappy elements from his own life and transforming them into something redemptive.</p>
        <p>''A Moon for the Misbegotten'' was O'Neill's elegy for and apology to his alcoholic brother James, whose character in the play (also named James) is granted a moment of absolution and unconditional love before dying. Yet most previous interpretations have been dominated by the actress playing Josie, the strapping farm girl who prompts James's cleansing confession. Though Josie is here ably portrayed by no less a performer than Cherry Jones, it is Gabriel Byrne's James that makes this production a milestone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Byrne has an emotional transparency that allows you to see straight to the core of James's self-lacerating guilt and to realize how it determines his every gesture. What you are witnessing is an extraordinary collaboration between a dead dramatist and a living actor, a convergence of wills to come to terms with and to redeem a given character. Mr. Byrne, turning in the richest dramatic performance of the season, gives ''A Moon for the Misbegotten'' back to James Tyrone, and there is no understating the significance of that accomplishment.</p>
        <p>A contemporary play from a young writer achieved its own transcendent transformation of autobiography. Kenneth Lonergan's ''Waverly Gallery,'' seen Off Broadway at the Promenade Theater, was inspired by the last years of his grandmother, an enduringly strong-willed woman sliding into dementia. The resulting work is both harrowing and funny, suggesting how much Beckett's absurdity is rooted in real life.</p>
        <p>What took the play to another level, however, was Eileen Heckart, the fabled octogenarian actress. Playing the grandmother, Ms. Heckart rendered senility with such limpid sharpness that even as you lamented the character's decline, you cheered the performer's triumph. A crystalline order emerged from the muddle that is life. Watching Ms. Heckart serve as its chief architect, in what she has said will be her last stage performance, was a kind of transporting privilege that only the theater affords.</p>
        <p>Other productions played directly and appealingly with a self-conscious awareness of just what the theater achieves and how it does it. The sparkling Broadway revival of ''The Real Thing,'' Tom Stoppard's keen-witted tale of a playwright in love, makes the case that certain things (love, for example) defy articulation.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, with the infinitely charming Stephen Dillane playing the playwright in this import from London, even groping in the dark acquires a glistening stylishness that is pure theater. Mr. Dillane's co-star, the radiant Jennifer Ehle, is, by the way, the daughter of an actress who gave another sublime study this season in stage-savvy artifice.</p>
        <p>That's Rosemary Harris, whose portrayal of a great lady of the British stage exiled to a retirement home was the touchstone of ''Waiting in the Wings,'' a 40-year-old play by Noel Coward that received its Broadway debut only this season. Ms. Harris slyly plied, and gently sent up, the tricks of her trade to conjure a vanished era of stagecraft, turning them into the tools by which her character dominated her fellow residents. There is after all, it seems, a practical use for the skills acquired on stage.</p>
        <p>''Waiting in the Wings'' provided the additional pleasure of presenting a host of actresses on the far side of 60, from Lauren Bacall to Helen Stenborg, working as a team with contagious delight. But the laurels for ensemble acting this season unquestionably go to the cast of August Wilson's ''Jitney.''</p>
        <p>THIS reworking of an early play by the author of contemporary masterpieces like ''Joe Turner's Come and Gone'' and ''Ma Rainey's Black Bottom'' presented a slice of life, from the streets of Pittsburgh in the 1970's, so invigoratingly fresh that you somehow felt you had lived it yourself.</p>
        <p>Many of the cast members, directed by Marion McClinton, had been together through earlier incarnations of the play, and they wore their roles with a deceptively easy-looking assurance. By the end of the performance, you had the sense that you had been listening to these people regularly for most of your life. You left the theater with the heartening illusion that it really is possible to know people thoroughly, after all.</p>
        <p>In what is becoming a dispiriting tradition, musicals did not begin to match their non-singing siblings in moments of revelation, with the merciful exceptions of two envelope-pushers: ''Contact'' and ''James Joyce's 'The Dead.' '' The season had one glorious pinnacle of a revival, Cole Porter's backstage musical ''Kiss Me, Kate,'' and a charming if imbalanced new version of Meredith Willson's all-American ''Music Man,'' courtesy of the director and choreographer Susan Stroman.</p>
        <p>Less encouragingly, the trend of reinventing, and usually flattening, movie musicals for the stage -- which seemed to have reached a nadir with the sterile ''Footloose'' -- scraped even deeper with the mechanical interpretation of ''Saturday Night Fever,'' which managed to erase every vestige of sensuality and period authenticity from the film that inspired it.</p>
        <p>An original musical from Disney, Elton John and Tim Rice's ''Aida,'' somehow felt as if it, too, had been translated from the screen -- in this case, from a Disney cartoon -- though it did have the virtue of establishing the incandescent Heather Headley, in the title role, as a bona fide Broadway star.</p>
        <p>More ambitious, and hence ultimately more disappointing, were two separate productions that adapted ''The Wild Party,'' Joseph Moncure March's cult poem of the Jazz Age, as musicals: Andrew Lippa's version for the Manhattan Theater Club and the current Broadway incarnation by George C. Wolfe and the composer Michael John LaChiusa (the latter also represented this season by the overweening ''Marie Christine'' at Lincoln Center).</p>
        <p>Following a battalion of self-destructive sybarites through one evening of dubious pleasures, both shows suffered from feelings of arrested development. The notes of shrill unhappiness and brooding restlessness were struck early and held for the musicals' remainders, imprisoning their characters and scores in a frieze of decorative decadence that never became fully animated.</p>
        <p>There were, however, two productions that bravely and successfully staked out new territory for the musical: Ms. Stroman's ''Contact'' at Lincoln Center and ''James Joyce's 'The Dead,' '' by Richard Nelson and Shaun Davey, which transferred to Broadway from Playwrights Horizons. The slew of Tony nominations heaped upon ''Contact'' has caused some grumbling in the New York theater, since the show is a dance play, with minimal dialogue and no original music.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, its three vignettes blissfully capture what has always been most seductive about the American musical: its ability to lift off from everyday reality into a music-driven empyrean, while pulling its audiences skyward with it. Boyd Gaines's portrayal in the evening's final scene, of a suicidal urbanite who finds his feet and his heart by learning to dance, became the perfect metaphor for the audience's implicit participation in the show.</p>
        <p>''The Dead,'' though less flashy, was even more innovative: a musical that dared to be quiet. In retelling Joyce's great story of mortal shadows at a Christmas party in Dublin, the show presented a group of people who appeared to be performing for one another rather than for the audience. The responses of those onstage became as important as those who were singing or dancing for them, and a whole other level of naturalistic character definition was introduced to the musical form.</p>
        <p>No musical season in New York will ever be entirely barren as long as the ''Encores!'' series of American musicals in concert continues to flourish at City Center. This year the program's peak was its final offering, a heavenly resurrection of a never-never-land, an idealized New York City of the 1950's, in ''Wonderful Town.''</p>
        <p>Overseen by the prodigiously gifted Kathleen Marshall, also the choreographer on ''Kiss Me, Kate,'' the evening provided myriad pleasures but none quite so astonishing as those offered by its star, the two-time Tony winner Donna Murphy. Hitherto most notable as a performer of somber emotional intensity (''Passion,''  ''The King and I''), Ms. Murphy turned her image on its head with a dazzling, razor-sharp comic performance.</p>
        <p>Which further confirms that really good theater artists are an enviable lot. They can, after all, turn into anyone.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
