<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dose of Sense From Viagra's Spokesman</title>
    <meta content="04SENI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SENIORITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Viagra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impotence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brock, Fred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Seniority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Viagra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Impotence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EEDE113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dose of Sense From Viagra's Spokesman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRED BROCK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brock, Fred</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Everyone expected Bob Dole to disappear from view after he lost 1996 presidential election, but he has maintained his public profile, notably as spokesman for Pfizer's impotence drug, Viagra; more significantly, he has emerged as spokesman for older Americans, regardless of their politics; they view Dole as hero who has displayed determination, courage and humor; Dole, who concedes his age, then 73, cost him votes in election, says he does not think of himself as old, and thinks some people overreact to growing old; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN SOME ways, Bob Dole is an unlikely spokesman for older Americans.</p>
        <p>After all, the former Kansas senator was one of 68 Republicans in the House who voted against the creation of Medicare in 1965, although he has since supported it. He loathes the idea of retiring and, at 76, doesn't consider himself old. His most cynical detractors say he is cashing in on his celebrity status by accepting money from Pfizer for appearing in ads urging men with erectile dysfunction to have checkups and, presumably, obtain prescriptions for Viagra, which Pfizer makes. The ads made him late-night fodder for Leno and Letterman for months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN SOME ways, Bob Dole is an unlikely spokesman for older Americans.</p>
        <p>After all, the former Kansas senator was one of 68 Republicans in the House who voted against the creation of Medicare in 1965, although he has since supported it. He loathes the idea of retiring and, at 76, doesn't consider himself old. His most cynical detractors say he is cashing in on his celebrity status by accepting money from Pfizer for appearing in ads urging men with erectile dysfunction to have checkups and, presumably, obtain prescriptions for Viagra, which Pfizer makes. The ads made him late-night fodder for Leno and Letterman for months.</p>
        <p>Despite all that, and in the wake of his unsuccessful run for the presidency in 1996, Mr. Dole has emerged as a hero to many older people, regardless of their politics. For them, he has displayed a rare combination of determination, courage and humor in the face of severe battlefield wounds suffered in World War II that left him with a withered right arm. He also has struggled with serious illnesses, including prostate cancer.</p>
        <p>''I think I'm a pretty good role model for seniors,'' he said during a recent interview in his office at Verner, Liipfert, Berhnard, McPherson &amp; Hand, the Washington law firm where he is a special counselor. ''I've had problems and worked through all of those. I'm getting older, but I've survived. Maybe by speaking out I can help people.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Mike Magee, Pfizer's senior medical adviser, who also sat in on the interview, said: ''Everyone expected Senator Dole to disappear after he lost the 1996 election. But what does he do? He goes public, and with humor and a real smart and engaging personality.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Magee was referring to Mr. Dole's 1998 appearance on CNN's ''Larry King Live,'' when he disclosed that he had taken part in clinical trials for Viagra and that it had reversed the impotency resulting from the removal of his cancerous prostate in 1991. Overnight, a hidden, stigmatizing medical condition that had received little attention exploded into the public's awareness.</p>
        <p>''My wife was a little startled,'' Mr. Dole said.</p>
        <p>At first he was a bit testy over the Viagra jokes, but has since mellowed. ''Actually, some of them were pretty funny,'' he conceded.</p>
        <p>MR. DOLE'S revelation on television led to his relationship with Pfizer. In addition to Viagra-related ads, he also helps the drug giant with a broader campaign to inform older Americans about the value of early detection and treatment of diseases.</p>
        <p>''It's not so much Viagra,'' Mr. Dole said. ''It's the underlying cause of E.D.''</p>
        <p>Early detection usually means drug therapy, which is good for companies like Pfizer. ''There is a vested interest for Pfizer or any of the pharmaceutical companies,'' Dr. Magee said. ''They are very prejudiced toward prevention.''</p>
        <p>In the two years that Pfizer has run its Viagra ads, seven million men have received the drug. For every million who asked for Viagra, it was also discovered that an estimated 30,000 had untreated diabetes, 140,000 had untreated high blood pressure and 50,000 had untreated heart disease.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole says the fact he is on Pfizer's payroll has not affected his opinions on issues, including those on health care. ''I'm still a free citizen; I've never been told I shouldn't express some opinion,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He favors a federal program to help low-income people pay for drugs, but doesn't think the government should get involved for people who can afford them on their own.</p>
        <p>He thinks the proposal by Gov. George W. Bush of Texas to partly privatize Social Security by allowing people to invest a portion of their contributions in the stock market is fine in concept. But he worries that ''the devil is in the details.''</p>
        <p>''We have to protect the people who aren't good at investing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush's proposal ''is not a radical plan,'' he said. ''It's bold, because for the first time you would change Social Security. ''</p>
        <p>HE said his proudest accomplishment in the Senate came in 1983, when he and Daniel Patrick Moynihan, the New York Democrat, helped lead bipartisan efforts to rescue Social Security. Mr. Dole suggested that he and Senator Moynihan could chair a commission Governor Bush plans to appoint to work on his Social Security proposal if he is elected president.</p>
        <p>He stresses the importance of preventive care and of remaining engaged. ''I sort of got into a slump in my 50's,'' he said. ''Then I started to realize how important it is to take care of yourself. Now I work out on a treadmill. I can't do much with my arms, but I figured I'd keep my legs strong. I want to be mobile. I've seen people I thought were old at 50. They don't take care of themselves. It's so important to stay connected and exercise your mind and body.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole, tan and trim after losing 12 pounds, hates the idea of retiring. ''Suddenly you wake up and you're 70-some years old,'' he said. ''But I've never thought of myself as old. To me, old is when you can't function. I go down to Florida. We stay about three days. I like to get a little sun and then I want to come home.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole says his age -- 73 at the time -- cost him some votes when he ran for the White House. ''But I've demonstrated I would have lived out my first term, anyway,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He said everyone had to make his or her own judgment about when to retire, but he thinks some people overreact to growing old.</p>
        <p>''I guess if you really get paranoid,  you don't buy any new shirts or shoes,'' he said. ''You think, 'Well, I'll never wear these out.' I guess when you get to be Strom's age, you worry about room service -- 'How long will it be? Thirty minutes?' ''</p>
        <p>He was referring, of course, to Senator Strom Thurmond of South Carolina, who is 97.</p>
        <p>SENIORITY Fred Brock is an editor at The Times. His column on the approach and arrival of retirement appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: fbrock@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Fred Brock is an editor at The Times. His column on the approach and arrival of retirement appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: fbrock@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
