<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Changing the World, One Endless Dance at a Time</title>
    <meta content="04BAHR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bahr, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reiss, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harrison, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerrigan, Justin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Better Living Through Circuitry (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Groove (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Human Traffic (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DD143CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Changing the World, One Endless Dance at a Time</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BAHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bahr, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Bahr article on new documentary movies Better Living Through Circuitry, directed by Jon Reiss, Groove, directed by Greg Harrison and Human Traffic, directed by Justin Kerrigan, which celebrate rave scene; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWO years ago, the director Jon Reiss could not have cared less about raves. As far as he was concerned, they involved nothing but hordes of teenagers, psychedelic drugs and mindlessly repetitive techno music.</p>
        <p>Then he went to one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWO years ago, the director Jon Reiss could not have cared less about raves. As far as he was concerned, they involved nothing but hordes of teenagers, psychedelic drugs and mindlessly repetitive techno music.</p>
        <p>Then he went to one.</p>
        <p>''It just blew me away,'' recalls Mr. Reiss, 35. ''The hair on the back of my neck was standing up. The music and collective energy brought me to this spiritual level that I had only experienced while meditating. I knew I had to learn what made it tick.''</p>
        <p>So he set out to make a documentary about the phenomenon, ''Better Living Through Circuitry,'' one of three new films, along with the recently released ''Human Traffic'' and ''Groove'' (which opens Friday), to celebrate the rave scene. As Greg Harrison, the director of ''Groove,'' says, ''Rave serves a powerful purpose in the modern Western world because those kinds of communal, cathartic experiences based on music have been factored out, or at least commodified, in our culture.''</p>
        <p>Rave itself began in England during the late 1980's, when rebellious youths took over abandoned warehouses, consumed hallucinogens and danced to live D.J.'s into the morning hours. It was not until the early 1990's that these events made it to this country, much to the dismay of narcotics enforcement officials and parents.</p>
        <p>Previously, in movies like ''Trainspotting'' (1996) and last year's ''Go,'' rave culture has been presented as little more than a backdrop for misery and death. But for this most recent crop of rave moviemakers, the films are an attempt to dispel misconceptions and portray the subculture in all its blissed-out, trippy glee. ''For the most part, raves have been unjustly vilified by the media,'' Mr. Harrison says. ''With 'Groove,' I wanted to portray the positive aspects and optimism that underlies the scene.''</p>
        <p>That optimism, vibrantly apparent in all three films, stems from ravers' faith in music and dance as regenerative, liberating forces. Unlike the aggressive and nihilistic currents that ran through the punk rock scene, rave, as the recent documentary ''Better Living Through Circuitry'' portrays it, cultivates a life-affirming attitude and socially productive spirit. In fact, for the technologically savvy and musically innovative, it provides a vast outlet: participants communicate and network over the Internet (since the locations of underground events are ever-changing), designing cutting-edge graphics and, perhaps most intriguingly, composing and generating electronic dance music. ''D.J.'s have replaced rock stars in our world,'' says Justin Kerrigan, the 25-year-old British director of ''Human Traffic'' and an outspoken rave devotee. ''The freshest tracks around come from D.J.'s and kids playing around on their bedroom computers.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Reiss, what is most impressive about rave culture are its ideals.</p>
        <p>''One of the things I found amazing is that they share the same fundamental values that I have but thought were gone,'' he says. ''And that is the notion that if society doesn't offer the avenue you want, to go out and create it yourself. Here are people with a view of the world where money isn't the be-all and end-all of everything. People are drawn into raving because of the transformative effect of the experience, not just materially, but spiritually, psychically. And there's something about that collective purpose that gives it an additional dimension, a communal energy if you will.''</p>
        <p>AS Mr. Reiss's compelling documentary shows, rave is open to anyone regardless of race, sexual orientation or age (though participants tend be well under 30), and it's that inclusiveness that attracts revelers -- many of them outsiders who feel uncomfortable at other social and athletic events. Mr. Reiss spoke with scores of D.J.'s, musicians, promoters and fans, accumulating over 200 hours of interviews before editing the film down to a richly packed 88 minutes. What emerges is a self-determined community dedicated to creative expression and personal freedom, of which drugs are not necessarily an integral part.</p>
        <p>''We learned that drugs are not important to a lot of people who have kept the culture going,'' says Stuart Swezey, who produced ''Better Living Through Circuitry'' with Brian McNelis. ''Certainly drugs can be a transporting experience, but there are many ravers that have never taken them and those who still rave that have grown out of them. And that's one of the reasons we put off addressing the issue until halfway through the film.'' Of course, Mr. Swezey does not dispute the indelible imprint of rave scene, particularly Ecstasy and LSD, something all three films boldly reflect. Indeed, both ''Human Traffic'' and ''Groove'' portray drugs with such cozy familiarity that their presence is merely taken for granted. The skimpy plot of the infectiously energetic ''Human Traffic'' involves a group of British friends living for the weekend so they can pop Ecstasy, dance and forget their problems. The more substantive and equally entertaining ''Groove'' weaves together several drug-related story lines. The central one involves an uptight writer named David (Hamish Linklater) whose first rave-Ecstasy experience teaches him a lesson in liberation. Along the way, he falls for the lost and jaded Leyla (Lola Glaudini), a perpetual party-goer unable to escape the scene. Strategically, however, no one dies in either film.</p>
        <p>''There are no overdoses or shootouts in my film,'' says Mr. Harrison, who, like Mr. Kerrigan, refused to cave in to early pressures by film company executives to inject a little death and gunfire into the plot. ''The darkness in my film is more realistic and pervasive in that it deals with getting trapped in the scene. Yes, rave can be an epiphany that changes the way you see your life.</p>
        <p>''But it can also be a trap, as it is for Leyla, sucking you into a false sense of happiness and well-being if you're unwilling to examine your life as a whole.''</p>
        <p>By acknowledging a wider range of rave experience as well as the limits of its liberation, ''Groove'' has greater emotional resonance than the frenetic, cartoonish ''Human Traffic.'' But in the end, even ''Groove'' is too much of a tidy crowd-pleaser to satisfactorily explore the various motivations behind recreational drug use.</p>
        <p>Still, what all three films do successfully convey is the passion and primal power surrounding communal dance. As Mr. McNelis notes, drugs aren't the focus of raves; collective transcendence is. ''Our film is not about telling people to attend these events to do drugs,'' he says. ''If anything, it reveals a world that encourages them to attend these events to dance, sweat, let go, and, if you want, experience some kind of enlightenment.''</p>
        <p>FILM David Bahr, a writer based in New York, writes frequently about film.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Bahr, a writer based in New York, writes frequently about film.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
