<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Doctor Fights Gender Bias</title>
    <meta content="04GEND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204602"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montefiore Medical Center (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perry-Bottinger, Lynne V (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wetzler, Cynthia Magriel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Heart Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DF133CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Doctor Fights Gender Bias</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA MAGRIEL WETZLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wetzler, Cynthia Magriel</byline>
      <dateline>THE BRONX</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Dr Lynne V Perry-Bottinger, cardiologist at Montefiore Medical Center in New York City, who is leading movement called gender-based medicine, which takes into account differences between men and women in diagnosis, treatment, medication and physiology of coronary heart disease; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR Dr. Lynne V. Perry-Bottinger, medicine is a family business. Her husband, her parents and 6 of her 10 siblings are doctors.</p>
        <p>But she has a major complaint with the medical establishment: she believes it has long treated women poorly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR Dr. Lynne V. Perry-Bottinger, medicine is a family business. Her husband, her parents and 6 of her 10 siblings are doctors.</p>
        <p>But she has a major complaint with the medical establishment: she believes it has long treated women poorly.</p>
        <p>Dr. Perry-Bottinger, a cardiologist who lives in New Rochelle, is a leader in a movement called gender-based medicine, which takes into account the differences between men and women in diagnosis, treatment, medication and basic physiology.</p>
        <p>For example, she said: ''Women have smaller hearts and smaller coronory arteries than men. Consequently, they often have different symptoms for heart disease than men.''</p>
        <p>Instead of crushing chest pains radiating to the shoulder and forearm, which are the classic symptoms of a heart attack presented by men, women may complain of jaw pain, stomach ache, fluttering in the heart, profuse sweating, shortness of breath or just plain fatigue.</p>
        <p>Women who go to their doctors with such symptoms are often not taken seriously, Dr. Perry-Bottinger said. ''They are told it's probably just anxiety or stress and are given tranquilizers,'' she said. ''To me this is frightening. Men are overtested for coronory disease and women are undertested. This is gender bias.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Perry-Bottinger, a 1982 graduate of Harvard University, received her medical degree from Yale University Medical School in 1986. In 1997 she and her husband, Dr. Erwin Bottinger, a kidney specialist, were recruited as a team to Albert Einstein Medical College.</p>
        <p>Dr. Perry-Bottinger is affiliated with both Albert Einstein and Montefiore Medical Center, which is the teaching college of Albert Einstein Medical College.</p>
        <p>''Gender-based medicine,'' she said, ''is the first thing in medicine that really got me charged.''</p>
        <p>As she sped down the corridor one day at Montefiore to prepare for a catheterization procedure, she recounted the story of a woman who called her doctor to complain of a funny feeling in her jaw while watching a Knicks game.</p>
        <p>The doctor said he didn't think it was serious and to rest. Her daughter insisted on taking her to Montefiore, where she was diagnosed with heart disease and underwent bypass surgery three days later.</p>
        <p>''These kinds of occurrences are disturbing to me as a cardiologist and as a woman. When I come to my doctor at age 65 with symptoms which may indicate coronary disease I don't want someone to blow it off and say it's all in your pretty little head.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Doris Escher, director emeritus at the cardiac catheterization laboratory at Montefiore, who has been practicing cardiology since 1946, said in a telephone conversation: ''Women patients are often dismissed. Male doctors tended, and some of them still tend, to credit women's symptoms more to indigestion rather than heart attacks.''</p>
        <p>As Dr. Perry-Bottinger stepped into the elevator after friendly greetings with almost everyone she passed, she held the door, greeted a fellow doctor passing by and conversed with him in rapid-fire Spanish. She also speaks German (her husband is Bavarian), some Yiddish and French. Russian patients who speak Yiddish are referred to her.</p>
        <p>Besides her clinical practice, Dr. Perry-Bottinger takes her crusade into the community. In December 1999, she helped organize a symposium with a fellow cardiologist, Michelle N. Johnson, titled ''Sex-Based Differences in Coronory Interventions,'' which was attended by more than 225 doctors from the New York metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>''One of the burdens of being a female physician,'' she said, ''is my responsibility to turn up the notch a little in order to educate my colleagues.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Perry-Bottinger was raised in Houston, Tex. Her father is a cardiologist and her mother is a pediatrician.</p>
        <p>''Each Friday afternoon,'' she recalled, ''all the kids sat down and my father gave a lecture on the heart, sometimes telling us his interesting cases and showing us slides.''</p>
        <p>In the anteroom to the catheterization lab where she had readied herself to perform her scheduled procedure, she chatted, dressed in green scrubs, booties over her shoes, paper shower cap and mask and glasses and a lead apron to protect against radiation from the X-ray, which is part of the procedure. She left her earrings on.</p>
        <p>She is unrelenting in her dedication to her work. ''When I was pregnant both times, I worked until delivery,'' she said. ''I just wore an extra shielding of lead where the fetus was.''</p>
        <p>As one of a handful of female cardiologists who perform balloon angioplasty between Boston and New Jersey, she has become a sort of commodity, she said.</p>
        <p>Well-informed female professionals from the New York region who are looking for objective cardiac care come to the Bronx to consult with her and Dr. Johnson.</p>
        <p>''The white, male medical establishment has had much power,'' she said. ''I'm not saying this unkindly. My husband is one.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
