<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Higher Profile for a Little-Known Foundation</title>
    <meta content="04FOUN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Foundation for Economic Education</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boudreaux, Donald J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Read, Leonard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kelly, Caitlin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DA123CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1219" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Higher Profile for a Little-Known Foundation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAITLIN KELLY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kelly, Caitlin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on little-known Foundation for Economic Education in Irvington, NY, founded in 1946 by business executive Leonard E Read; new president Donald J Boudreaux's plans include fund-raising, Web sites, remaking of monthly magazine, new educational programs and nationwide distribution of materials to high school debaters and teachers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT took a Nobel prize-winning Austrian economist to turn a New Orleans' welder's son on to the joys of free-market capitalism. But once Donald J. Boudreaux discovered the work of Freidrich von Hayek, co-winner of the Nobel prize in 1974, there was no going back. ''This is my greatest hero,'' Mr. Boudreaux said of the man whose photograph is one of several pictures of free marketers lining the mantelpiece in his office at the Foundation for Economic Education, a libertarian nonprofit educational group in Irvington.</p>
        <p>''I love his depth, his erudition, his seriousness,'' said Mr. Boudreaux, a friendly, down-to-earth 41-year-old who left a tenured professorship in economics at Clemson University in South Carolina in 1997 to take over as head of the foundation. ''A lot of people on both sides of the debate are facile, but he thought about their arguments seriously. He didn't dismiss them.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT took a Nobel prize-winning Austrian economist to turn a New Orleans' welder's son on to the joys of free-market capitalism. But once Donald J. Boudreaux discovered the work of Freidrich von Hayek, co-winner of the Nobel prize in 1974, there was no going back. ''This is my greatest hero,'' Mr. Boudreaux said of the man whose photograph is one of several pictures of free marketers lining the mantelpiece in his office at the Foundation for Economic Education, a libertarian nonprofit educational group in Irvington.</p>
        <p>''I love his depth, his erudition, his seriousness,'' said Mr. Boudreaux, a friendly, down-to-earth 41-year-old who left a tenured professorship in economics at Clemson University in South Carolina in 1997 to take over as head of the foundation. ''A lot of people on both sides of the debate are facile, but he thought about their arguments seriously. He didn't dismiss them.''</p>
        <p>For years, the group, founded in 1946 by a Westchester County business executive,  Leonard E. Read, has remained little known and low profile -- drivers whizzing south on Broadway might have noticed its small sign stuck high up on a roadside tree trunk. But the foundation never advertised, gave few seminars, was rarely quoted in the press.</p>
        <p>No more, thanks to Mr. Boudreaux, whose passion for the dismal science could illuminate the Manhattan skyline. His plans for the foundation include fund-raising, Web sites, remaking its monthly magazine, creating new educational programs and distributing their materials nationwide to high school debaters and teachers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boudreaux recently hired Nicole Gray, formerly with Steve Forbes's presidential campaign, as his development director. Ms. Gray, who has also worked for the Cato Institute, a conservative think tank in Washington, intends to create and nurture new relationships with members in one region of the country that has, historically, provided the foundation with relatively little support -- New York.</p>
        <p>One local fan is John Stossel, the ABC ''20/20'' correspondent who describes himself as ''libertarian leaning.'' Mr. Stossel discovered the foundation through its magazine. ''I had read it and found it really stupid and boring,'' he said. ''Then these new people came in. I was skeptical, as it had always been tedious, but the articles now are often original and well written. It's a jungle gym for the brain.''</p>
        <p>A longtime Westchester resident who appreciates the foundation's point of view is Sheldon Jacobs, editor and publisher of The No-Load Fund Investor, a monthly newsletter in Irvington. Mr. Jacobs admits that, even after living in Irvington for five years, with the foundation blocks away, ''I'd only heard vague references to it.'' Eventually, a colleague, a fellow investment newsletter publisher in Florida, introduced Jacobs to the group and its activities, including seminars and lectures. Those wanting more information about the foundation can visit its  Web site at www.fee.org.</p>
        <p>''My attraction to them is that they stand for smaller government,'' said Mr. Jacobs, who reads the foundation's monthly publication, attends its seminars and hopes, someday, to write for the foundation. The organization puts out a quarterly newsletter, called FEE Today and the 64-page monthly magazine, called Ideas on Liberty. ''The thing that really impressed me about them was their 50th anniversary dinner,'' he said. ''It was a huge event at the Waldorf-Astoria, with Bill Buckley as the host and Margaret Thatcher as their keynote speaker. People came from all across the country.''</p>
        <p>Herb Grossman, who teaches mathematics in Oradell, N.J., but who taught at Roosevelt High School in Yonkers from 1968 to 1985, has, for many years, handed out the foundation's literature to any student he thinks might find it useful. ''The materials they get are very inadequate,'' he said. ''I feel the period dealing with the robber barons is terribly portrayed. They were major benefactors. They also learn that the Depression was a failure of the free-enterprise system and the government bailed us out. What I object to is that the kids never hear anything to the contrary.''</p>
        <p>Only 5 percent of the foundation's 5,000 contributors are from New York, although the group has been based here since it was founded. Members, most of them older and male, traditionally come from Wisconsin and Michigan, Washington State, Texas and California because the last time the Foundation for Economic Education was on the radar screen, fund-raising was strongest in these areas, Mr. Boudreaux says.</p>
        <p>The group's annual budget of $2 million comes exclusively from private individuals and a few foundations. Given that its credo is libertarian -- ''We're skeptical of state power, no matter what its use,'' Mr. Boudreaux said -- it would never consider accepting government funds.</p>
        <p>''We're looking for local libertarians,''  Ms. Gray said. ''It's just a matter of connecting with them. They just haven't seen us lately.''</p>
        <p>The group is definitely graying and needs new blood, Mr. Boudreaux said. ''Most of our members are in their 60's. When they became interested in free markets they were in college or even in high school.'' Back then, he says, the foundation was well-known, and Mr. Hayek was a celebrity on a par with his fellow economist Milton Friedman.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Hayek's theories, popular from the 1930's through the 1950's, fell out of favor in the 1960's and the age of government expansion, Mr. Boudreaux says.</p>
        <p>He has little illusion that the group's work and ideas, filtering slowly through its small and relatively invisible network of supporters, will change the world overnight, or even in his lifetime.</p>
        <p>''What FEE does is not going to have an effect on the world tomorrow -- Cato will,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But he went on confidently to say: ''I'm out to make people more suspicious of collective political action. I do think ideas matter longterm, but our time horizon is very long. It's not a hard sell because the ideas we espouse are esoteric or out of this world. They're not weird or bizarre. But because the ideas making up an ideology are deeply rooted you can't change them easily.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boudreaux, who studied at Nicholls State University in Thibodaux, La., received his law degree at the University of Virginia and his Ph.D. at Auburn University in Alabama, enjoys his own subsidy of sorts -- he and his wife, Karol, and their 2-year-old son, Thomas, live rent free in a carriage house on the foundation's property.</p>
        <p>The foundation is currently struggling, he admitted, to define itself. Legally, it is a nonprofit educational organization, and he rejects the term think tank. Instead, he said, ''We're more abstract, and focus on the fundamentals.''</p>
        <p>The trustees, who meet twice a year, ''judge us on our inputs'' -- seminars, the monthly magazine, with a circulation of 14,000, lectures and summer programs for college and graduate students.</p>
        <p>The group does not take positions or create policy like the Cato Institute, with whom it shares trustees and information. This, Mr. Boudreaux said, has kept its profile low. When reporters call, as they often do on deadline seeking a sound bite on economic issues, Mr. Boudreaux doesn't offer them prepackaged answers.</p>
        <p>''Some headline,'' he said with a laugh. ''Economist says 'I Don't Know.' ''</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
