<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the Twilight Patrol</title>
    <meta content="04GUAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DOWN THE SURF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lifeguards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drownings</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pawling, G Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6DA133CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the Twilight Patrol</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By G. PATRICK PAWLING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pawling, G Patrick</byline>
      <dateline>OCEAN CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Officials in at least two South Jersey beach towns extend lifeguards' hours at some popular swimming beaches in light of after-hours drownings last summer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With last summer's late-evening drownings on their minds, officials in at least two South Jersey beach towns are extending the hours that lifeguards will be on some popular swimming beaches.</p>
        <p>Atlantic City, which kept lifeguards on its Kentucky Avenue beach until 8 p.m. last year after an after-hours drowning there, will again keep patrols on duty until 8 on weekends and weekdays, said the chief of the beach patrol there, Robert Levy. Normally, lifeguards leave Atlantic City Beaches at 6 p.m.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With last summer's late-evening drownings on their minds, officials in at least two South Jersey beach towns are extending the hours that lifeguards will be on some popular swimming beaches.</p>
        <p>Atlantic City, which kept lifeguards on its Kentucky Avenue beach until 8 p.m. last year after an after-hours drowning there, will again keep patrols on duty until 8 on weekends and weekdays, said the chief of the beach patrol there, Robert Levy. Normally, lifeguards leave Atlantic City Beaches at 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>In addition, other beaches will remain open later on holidays and during particularly hot spells, Mr. Levy said.</p>
        <p>''Lots of places in poorer sections don't have air-conditioning, so you want to provide a safe bathing beach,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In Ocean City, where three people drowned last year at unguarded beaches, the city will keep three of its most crowded beaches -- the 8th, 9th and 12th Streets beaches -- open on Fridays, Saturdays and Sundays until 8 p.m. starting June 30, said the assistant captain of the beach patrol here, Bud McKinley. Lifeguards there usually leave the beach at 5 p.m. on weekdays and 5:30 p.m. on weekends.</p>
        <p>Mr. McKinley said the city was also strengthening a rapid-response team for after-hours emergencies, as is the beach patrol in Cape May.</p>
        <p>However, Cape May is not extending its lifeguard hours beyond the regular quitting times -- 5 p.m. until July 1 and 5:30 p.m. for the rest of the summer -- said the supervisor of beaches there, Harry J. Mogck Jr. ''I kind of have mixed feelings about it when you open one beach,'' Mr. Mogck said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mogck said he feared that if tourists heard a beach was open late, they could misunderstand the situation and head to the nearest beach for a swim, even if was not guarded.</p>
        <p>But what concerns officials here is a repeat of last year's drownings. A review of incidents at the beach showed that 7:30 p.m. was one of the most frequent times for drownings and rescues, Mr. McKinley said.</p>
        <p>''The statistics are pretty plain,'' he said. ''That's the time these things happen.''</p>
        <p>He estimated that extending the lifeguards' hours at three of the town's beaches would cost about $10,000 in overtime.</p>
        <p>Mr. McKinley said many people were probably coming to the beach later these days because of the heightened concern over exposure to the sun, particularly during the time when the sun's rays are strongest.</p>
        <p>An informal survey of towns along the 127-mile Jersey Shore did not turn up any other beaches extending lifeguards' hours, and officials in Atlantic City and Cape May said they knew of no other towns adding hours.</p>
        <p>The assistant beach manager of  Sea Bright, David Farley said that changing life guard hours from their current 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. would require  changing a town ordinance. ''It's also an economic issue,'' he said, adding that in the event of any ''really nasty water'' such as large waves brought on by a hurricane, the city may extend the beach patrol hours to keep people out of the water.</p>
        <p>In other parts of the country, beach towns are becoming more flexible, said Don Rohrer, president of the United States Livesaving Association. Shifts vary from 8 to 24 hours a day, Mr. Rohrer said, and beach patrols are starting to realize that if they want to protect the public's safety they have to be around when people want to swim.</p>
        <p>People's lives are more flexible, Mr. Rohrer said, and that is reflected in the times they are using the beach.</p>
        <p>The presence of lifeguards is also an issue on the Delaware following the drowning of seven people last summer at unguarded sections of the Delaware Water Gap National Recreation Area, which straddles 70,000 acres in New Jersey and Pennsylvania. Over the 35-year history of the park, there was less than one drowning a year on average. However, said Bill Halainen, management assistant at the park, it was ''a very intense summer'' for crowds.</p>
        <p>The drownings have prompted the park to institute an ''aggressive'' effort to educate visitors about water safety, said Mr. Halainen. He also said that a tentative plan to develop a  guarded beach on what is known as the Depew area on the New Jersey side is getting greater attention, though there would not be lifeguards there this summer.</p>
        <p>There are two areas on the Pennsylvania side with 11 lifeguards in the summer and none on the New Jersey side. Swimming is allowed anywhere along the river.</p>
        <p>DOWN THE SURF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
