<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT REHEARSAL WITH/Arthur Aitkens; A Pianist's Circuitous Route to the Van Cliburn Competition</title>
    <meta content="04CLIB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Van Cliburn Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aitkens, Arthur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minor, E Kyle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4D6123CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT REHEARSAL WITH/Arthur Aitkens; A Pianist's Circuitous Route to the Van Cliburn Competition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Minor, E Kyle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with pianist Arthur Aitkens of Armonk, NY, who will perform at Van Cliburn Foundation's Second International Piano Competition for Outstanding Amateurs in Fort Worth, Tex; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Arthur Aitkens had a devastating horse-riding accident in 1988, he had no idea that it  would reunite him with music, his childhood passion. This week, 12 years after doctors told Mr. Aitkens that he would always be mostly paralyzed on his right side, he will perform in the Van Cliburn Foundation's Second International Piano Competition for Outstanding Amateurs.</p>
        <p>The Van Cliburn Foundation, known internationally for the piano competition it holds every four years for emerging professional pianists under 30, began an amateur competition last year. The contest features pianists from around the world over 35 who have pursued any career other than music, including doctors, librarians, homemakers, computer specialists, engineers, a massage therapist, an astrologer and a television news anchor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Arthur Aitkens had a devastating horse-riding accident in 1988, he had no idea that it  would reunite him with music, his childhood passion. This week, 12 years after doctors told Mr. Aitkens that he would always be mostly paralyzed on his right side, he will perform in the Van Cliburn Foundation's Second International Piano Competition for Outstanding Amateurs.</p>
        <p>The Van Cliburn Foundation, known internationally for the piano competition it holds every four years for emerging professional pianists under 30, began an amateur competition last year. The contest features pianists from around the world over 35 who have pursued any career other than music, including doctors, librarians, homemakers, computer specialists, engineers, a massage therapist, an astrologer and a television news anchor.</p>
        <p>Eighty-one contestants will perform in the first round tomorrow through Wednesday at Texas Christian University in Fort Worth. Eighteen semifinalists will perform on Friday with a final round of six contestants on Saturday. The top prize is $2,000 and a performance at the Hirshhorn Museum in Washington. (The foundation's Web site is www.cliburn.org.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Aitkens, who retired as associate general counsel of Mobil Corporation in 1990, is one of 15 contestants from New York State. He has attended the Juilliard School, the American Academy of Arts in Fontain bleu, France, and the TCU/Cliburn Institute. A native of New Orleans, Mr. Aitkens was an accomplished classical pianist and winner of the New Orleans Pops Contest at 13. He abandoned music long before he graduated from Tulane Law School in 1958 and for many years didn't even own a piano.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, he talked about what brought him back to music.</p>
        <p>Q. How did your accident return you to the piano?</p>
        <p>A.  About the time of my horse-riding accident, my 80-year-old aunt sent me one of her pianos. It was a Steinway grand. She just wanted to give it away, and I had not thought about playing in 40 years. After the accident, my doctors told me to squeeze a rubber ball for therapy. I tried it once. Thought that was a waste of time.</p>
        <p>Q. How is that a New Orleans native gravitates to classical rather than jazz piano?</p>
        <p>A. My aunt -- the one who gave me her piano -- was a teacher. She taught me and took me to concerts all the time. I greatly admired Rubenstein and Horowitz.</p>
        <p>Q. Why did you stop playing altogether?</p>
        <p>A. I became interested in other things, and school was very demanding. Then I was very busy, practicing law and raising a family with my wife. There were always other things to do.</p>
        <p>Q. After you resumed playing, when did it become more than just physical therapy?</p>
        <p>A. I went to Juilliard's night school and the American Academy of Arts in Fontainbleu after that. Two years ago I went to the Van Cliburn Institute, where I met three other pupils from the New York area. We get together once a month to play for each other. Two of them, Alwyn Farey-Jones, a banker from Sands Point, and Henri-Robert Delbeau, a physician from Jackson Heights, are also performing at the competition.</p>
        <p>Q. How did you audition?</p>
        <p>A.  This year the judges accepted 30-minute audition tapes. You are free to select any pieces you think will show you at your best. This, by the way, was different than last year's competition. I auditioned in person and was turned down. I recorded two Rachmaninoff preludes, a Brahms intermezzo, a Schubert impromptu and a Bach fugue.</p>
        <p>Q. What will you perform in the first round?</p>
        <p>A. Each performer is given a 12-minute slot, so I'm playing a Rachmaninoff prelude and the Schubert impromptu. The Rachmaninoff is a showy piece technically, and the Schubert is just a beautiful piece. I've always loved the romantic composers and these are two of the best.</p>
        <p>Q. How often do you rehearse?</p>
        <p>A.  Usually about two hours a day. About twice that now.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you feel much pressure with the competition so close at hand?</p>
        <p>A. Of course, there's pressure. But I love it.</p>
        <p>Q. Reflecting on your current success, do you have any regrets about not playing for so long?</p>
        <p>A. No. I had other things happen in 40 years that I enjoyed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
