<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art Versus Politics</title>
    <meta content="04ALEX$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E0DD143CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art Versus Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This excerpt has been adapted from ''Command Performance: An Actress in the Theater of Politics'' by Jane Alexander, an account of her tenure as chairman of the National Endowment for the Arts from 1993 to 1997. The book is being published this month by Public Affairs.</p>
        <p>POLITICIANS come and go. Newt Gingrich left Congress; Bill Clinton's term as president is ending. But politics as it is practiced today in the United States is entrenched, and it is deeply in trouble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This excerpt has been adapted from ''Command Performance: An Actress in the Theater of Politics'' by Jane Alexander, an account of her tenure as chairman of the National Endowment for the Arts from 1993 to 1997. The book is being published this month by Public Affairs.</p>
        <p>POLITICIANS come and go. Newt Gingrich left Congress; Bill Clinton's term as president is ending. But politics as it is practiced today in the United States is entrenched, and it is deeply in trouble.</p>
        <p>It is hard to know what a politician believes any more because he is so beholden to the special interests of those who elected him. An elected official has to pay attention to the money in his campaign chest first and foremost. Corporations spend to the limit, and special interest groups all have their own Political Action Committees ready and eager to give.</p>
        <p>If all politicians sound alike these days it is because they cannot dare to be different. If all politicians take a poll rather than take a stand, it is because they need to please as many people as possible and keep the coffers filled. The system is so corrupt it may not ever be fixed.</p>
        <p>If an organization has no money to give or insufficient money to give, it is going to be ignored. And that is exactly what happened to the National Endowment for the Arts. No wonder the 104th and 105th Congresses thought it was a shoo-in for elimination! Who was going to stand up for it? Even though the nonprofit arts in America generated more attendance than all professional sporting events combined, and there were more artists in America than there were police and corrections officers, according to Americans for the Arts.</p>
        <p>Today, a few arts organizations have begun Political Action Committees to help elect candidates who support government financing of the arts, but the real issue to be addressed is that of campaign finance reform. Until candidates stand on an equal playing field, it will be nearly impossible for politicians to support issues like the arts and humanities. It is a testament to the citizens of America who love the arts in their communities that the endowment is alive today. These citizens are a pure force in an impure world and our society needs more of them.</p>
        <p>When we teach a child to sing or play the flute, we teach her how to listen. When we teach her to draw, we teach her to see. When we teach a child to dance, we teach him about his body and about space, and when he acts on the stage, he learns about character and motivation. When we teach a child design, we reveal the geometry of the world. When we teach children about the folk and traditional arts and the great master pieces of the world, we teach them to celebrate their roots and find their own place in history.</p>
        <p>No one will remember or revere the F-22 in 100 or even 20 years, but Shakespeare is performed all over the world 400 years after he began to tell his stories.</p>
        <p>$; copyright 2000 Jane Alexander</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
