<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Telling Tales of Fear to a Wary Audience</title>
    <meta content="04FREE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION/RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Immigration and Naturalization Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freedman, Samuel G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Camerini, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robertson, Shari</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Well-Founded Fear (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E6D6173CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Telling Tales of Fear to a Wary Audience</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL G. FREEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freedman, Samuel G</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Columbia University journalism Prof Samuel G Freedman article on Well-Founded Fear, documentary directed by Michael Camerini and Shari Robertson that describes plights of eleven Chinese seeking political asylum in US; documentary, in interview form, penetrates Immigration and Naturalization Service's confidential system of granting or denying asylum to refugees; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE creased and sweaty figure of a Chinese poet named Huang Xiang appears on the screen halfway through the new documentary ''Well-Founded Fear.'' Seated in a drab and spartan apartment, his wife beside him, he begins to recall a recent medical examination. The physician had noticed a number of curious scars, evidence of the poet's plight during the Cultural Revolution.</p>
        <p>With a quaking finger, Mr. Huang traces the line of a wound across his chest. He speaks of bones shattered in his hands, palms torn apart. ''My feet,'' he continues, pulling up a trouser leg. ''The veins were broken and never stitched back.'' As he indicates his teeth, his voice breaks into wordless moans. When his wife reaches to comfort him, he shakes off her touch, covers his face with his forearms, and cries, ''I do not dare to remember my past. I do not dare!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE creased and sweaty figure of a Chinese poet named Huang Xiang appears on the screen halfway through the new documentary ''Well-Founded Fear.'' Seated in a drab and spartan apartment, his wife beside him, he begins to recall a recent medical examination. The physician had noticed a number of curious scars, evidence of the poet's plight during the Cultural Revolution.</p>
        <p>With a quaking finger, Mr. Huang traces the line of a wound across his chest. He speaks of bones shattered in his hands, palms torn apart. ''My feet,'' he continues, pulling up a trouser leg. ''The veins were broken and never stitched back.'' As he indicates his teeth, his voice breaks into wordless moans. When his wife reaches to comfort him, he shakes off her touch, covers his face with his forearms, and cries, ''I do not dare to remember my past. I do not dare!''</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Huang must remember, and remember in accurate and compelling detail, in order to gain asylum in the United States as a political refugee. The story he tells the camera is the same story he will imminently tell a bespectacled and bow-tied immigration officer named Gerald Brown, on whom the dissident's destiny rests. And in their encounter, and 10 others like it captured on camera, lies the dramatic force of the documentary directed by Michael Camerini and Shari Robertson.</p>
        <p>''Well-Founded Fear'' penetrates the Immigration and Naturalization Service's confidential system of granting or denying asylum to tens of thousands of refugees each year. (It will be broadcast at 9 p.m. tomorrow on PBS in its ''P.O.V.'' series and will be screened tonight at 9:15 in the New York International Documentary Festival at the Directors Guild of America Theater at 110 West 57th Street.) The film's title refers to the requirement that an applicant prove a ''well-founded fear of persecution based on race, religion, nationality, membership in a particular social group or political opinion.''</p>
        <p>As the two-hour documentary makes evident, what is at issue in the asylum hearings is less the objective reality of an applicant's experience than his or her ability to express it, often in imperfect English or through the imprecise channels of an interpreter or attorney. On the receiving end, the asylum officer has roughly 90 minutes per case to separate truth from falsehood, to parse all the increments of exaggeration and emphasis in between, and thus to determine which refugee receives sanctuary and which is rejected and left to fight deportation before an immigration judge. In the fiscal year that ended last September, asylum officers heard 41,377 cases, approving 13,220. The political theater surrounding the Elian Gonzalez case could hardly be more of an aberration.</p>
        <p>''People judge each other by how they seem,'' Ms. Robertson said during a recent interview at the office she and Mr. Camerini share in the Chelsea neighborhood of Manhattan, ''and that's based on appearance and performance and the luck of which officer hears your case. It's about how well you say things, how winning you can be. One sentence can make the difference in your case.'' Or as one applicant puts it: ''How can you express a life experience in a few minutes? It's one thing to tell a story about something. It's a completely different thing to live it.''</p>
        <p>The supplicants in ''Well-Founded Fear'' range from a Romanian woman claiming she was persecuted as an Anglican to a Nigerian man citing multiple arrests for opposing the military regime to a Salvadoran woman who fled after the murder of two relatives more than a decade ago to a Chinese man who says he was forcibly sterilized -- and adds inexplicably that he will be sterilized again if he is returned.</p>
        <p>Weighing those stories are a spectrum of officers, from a former immigration lawyer to a military veteran, from the solicitous to the skeptical. ''Well-Founded Fear'' offers as much empathy for the asylum officers as for the applicants, capturing their private discussions and doubts about the life-changing judgments they make daily. In one moment, Mr. Brown expresses awe at Mr. Huang's suffering, granting his application; in another, several colleagues crack wise about how many petitioners claim to have toppled the statue of the dictator in their homeland.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes you get a case where the person has pictures of dead bodies,'' says one officer, Charlene Claxton. ''And that's of course the last thing you want to look at. And they just give them to you.'' She continues: ''And we're not permitted to cry, we can't cry during interviews, it's not a good thing. You want to come up sometimes and give them a hug, but you can't, you can't do it.''</p>
        <p>Another officer, Kevin Love, instead emphasizes how guarded he has grown over the years. ''Maybe at first I was more gullible, I was more naive,'' he says. ''I felt like I wasn't a detective. And now, after seeing so many people who come in and have an identical story. They're so boilerplate, there's not even anything unique about the claims. It makes you wonder.''</p>
        <p>For the filmmakers, the asylum system provided not only dramatic material but a vehicle for fulfilling their journalistic ambitions. ''We had been struggling with how to get Americans to think about the world,'' Mr. Camerini said. ''And suddenly it was clear that here, in the asylum officers, were the Americans who dealt with the world. Here was the place where the world collided with America.''</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Camerini, who is 50, and Ms. Robertson, 46, had worked abroad extensively before embarking on this project. Their separate documentaries had covered such topics as the Khmer Rouge guerrillas, the drug war in Peru, social change in India and the Mexican artist Diego Rivera, and they began collaborating in the early 1990's with a film about girls in sub-Saharan Africa.</p>
        <p>WHAT ultimately became ''Well-Founded Fear'' had its genesis as a proposed multi-part series on immigrants and refugees in the post-cold war world. Mr. Camerini and Ms. Robertson did not even intend to focus on the American asylum system, dismissing it as too small a part of the subject. But the filmmakers were never able to raise more than a fraction of their $3 million budget, and they came to doubt the interest of domestic audiences in six hours of programming on an international topic.</p>
        <p>Stymied, they went to dinner one night in January 1996 with a member of their advisory board, Estelle Strizhak. A former specialist in refugee resettlement, Ms. Strizhak had recently been recruited to join the I.N.S. as an asylum officer. Having known Ms. Strizhak in her prior life as ''someone good at guerrilla warfare against the I.N.S.,'' as Mr. Camerini put it, the filmmakers were surprised and intrigued to hear her speak admiringly of her current colleagues in the agency. The problem, however, was the service's policy of confidentiality for all asylum cases. Even over a friendly meal, Ms. Strizhak would not divulge the name of a single officer or applicant.</p>
        <p>So the filmmakers relied on another advisory-board member, Demetrio Papademetriou, of the Carnegie Endowment for International Peace. He had previously worked in the Labor Department with Doris Meissner, who was by this time the I.N.S. commissioner, and he delivered to her a one-page proposal from Mr. Camerini and Ms. Robertson to film hearings inside any of the agency's nine asylum centers. In October 1996, Ms. Meissner essentially ordered her subordinates to cooperate with the documentary, and that same month the filmmakers became fixtures in the asylum offices in Queens, N.Y., and Lyndhurst, N.J.</p>
        <p>Before even starting to shoot, they attended 50 hearings and interviewed all 116 officers and supervisors; they parked themselves in a conference room to read volumes of I.N.S. regulations; they screened their earlier documentaries for the staff members. The efforts were enough to persuade 81 employees to agree to be filmed. The applicants proved even more amenable, hoping that a camera and sound man in the hearing room might somehow help their chances. From July 1997 to May 1998, Mr. Camerini and Ms. Robertson collected 85 hours of video and another 15 of audio tape. Of the 50 asylum cases they filmed, 11 made the final cut (material omitted from the film can be found on the documentary's Web site, www.pbs .org/pov/wellfoundedfear).</p>
        <p>Along the way, the pair watched their $500,000 budget double and their debts mount. They were $40,000 in arrears and paying their studio rent with cash advances from a credit card by the time their first large grants -- from the Ford Foundation and the Open Society Institute, among others -- arrived early in 1997. Even after that, the filmmakers had to resort to credit-card advances for the $80,000 cost of enlarging their 16-millimeter print to 35-millimeter for film festivals. A showing at Sundance last January gave ''Well-Founded Fear'' its first burst of exposure and critical acclaim.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Camerini and Ms. Robertson, though, an earlier indicator of success came when they feuded with their own editors. ''When you edit, you're working with a new person who's never seen the footage and they have this tendency to simplify the characters and the issues -- 'Oh, that person is ridiculous, that person is awful,' '' Mr. Camerini said. ''Both Shari and I were terribly defensive of all the people in the film. To run into that instinct to make archetypes sharpened our sense of goal. Which was to identify with and really like pretty much everyone in the movie. It's easier for people to fall in love with the poet than with the officers. But the officers are us.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION/RADIO Samuel G. Freedman is a professor of journalism at Columbia University and author of the forthcoming ''Jew vs. Jew: The Struggle for the Soul of American Jewry'' (Simon and Schuster).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Samuel G. Freedman is a professor of journalism at Columbia University and author of the forthcoming ''Jew vs. Jew: The Struggle for the Soul of American Jewry'' (Simon and Schuster).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
