<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Musicians Offer A Historic Perspective</title>
    <meta content="04VALE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Metz, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bach, Johann Sebastian (1685-1750)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Buxtehude, Dietrich (C1637-1707)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus (1756-91)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monteverdi, Claudio (1567-1643)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruice, Valerie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E1D6123CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Musicians Offer A Historic Perspective</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE CRUICE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cruice, Valerie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Early Music Festival director John Metz, professor of harpsichord and director of early music program at Arizona State University, comments on his job of insuring that musicians do not violate historical performance practices; this season's concerts will feature Bach, Buxtehude, Mozart and Monteverdi (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOHN METZ is a self-described style cop who as director of the Connecticut Early Music Festival, insures that none of the musicians violate historical performance practices.</p>
        <p>The festival, which opens on Friday for an 18th season, has a well-informed audience who relish authentically wrought concerts of 17th-and 18th-century music.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOHN METZ is a self-described style cop who as director of the Connecticut Early Music Festival, insures that none of the musicians violate historical performance practices.</p>
        <p>The festival, which opens on Friday for an 18th season, has a well-informed audience who relish authentically wrought concerts of 17th-and 18th-century music.</p>
        <p>Mr. Metz explained it this way:  ''It's not just having the right instrument. What you learn about the style is how to make the music more exciting.'' That translates into freedom to improvise, based on scholarly research, which is what Mr. Metz teaches at Arizona State University where he is professor of harpsichord and director of the early music program.</p>
        <p>The Connecticut Early Music Festival has a three-weekend run (Friday through June 25), presented in intimate settings with appropriate acoustics and atmosphere in and around New London. From the festival's inception, its programming has been creative and clever, performed by musicians specializing in period performance.</p>
        <p>This season, Bach, Buxtehude, Mozart and Monteverdi are among the composers whose works have been chosen. But the Bach will be done on a rarely heard five-string cello, and on a viola da gamba (which has nothing to do with the modern-day viola).</p>
        <p>The Mozart will be performed on a basset clarinet and valve-less French horn, the instruments Mozart had in mind when he put the notes on paper.</p>
        <p>And for Monteverdi's opera of power and lust, ''The Coronation of Poppea,'' Mr. Metz is importing the Lyric Opera Theater company of Arizona State University to give a fully costumed, semi-staged version. There is even a children's concert.</p>
        <p>The festival opens Friday night with a program entitled ''Baroque Virtuosi'' and features Kimberly Marshall playing the Tracker organ at St. John's Church in Niantic.</p>
        <p>The next day (at the Children's Museum of Southeastern Connecticut in Niantic and at the Science Center of Eastern Connecticut in New London), Ms. Marshall will give a children's concert and demonstration on a reproduction 17th-century German portatif organ, a portable pipe organ.</p>
        <p>On Saturday evening, at the Noank Baptist Church, audiences will hear a program titled ''The Intimate Bach: A Commemoration'' in honor of the 250th anniversary of Johann Sebastian Bach's death (he was born in 1685). Christine Gummere will play the rarely heard five-string cello in the Sixth Suite.</p>
        <p>Next Sunday evening, ''Abendmusik'' explores the Northern German music tradition from the late 17th to early 18th centuries with vocal and instrumental music by Buxtehude, Schein and Schutz. The program will be performed in Harkness Chapel at Connecticut College.</p>
        <p>On June 16, it's ''The Glory of the Gamba'' at the Lyman Allyn Art Museum in New London. Barbara Bailey, the viola da gamba artist, with Mr. Metz on the harpsichord, will present a concert of works by Marais, Couperin, J. S. Bach and C. P. E. Bach.</p>
        <p>The gamba, Ms. Bailey said, ''had its heyday in the baroque period in France.'' ''By the mid-18th century it had fallen out of favor and was overshadowed by the cello,'' she continued. ''If you look at the instrument, your first reaction is, it's a cello, but it has either six or seven strings and it's got frets. Gamba refers to the player's legs used to support the instrument.'' She also noted that the bow is held with the palm up, not  down as with a violin.</p>
        <p>''Classical Quintets,'' on June 18, celebrates chamber works by Mozart and Boccherini and features basset clarinet and natural horn.</p>
        <p>Krommer's Octet for winds in E flat (Op. 69), a great wind partita, can be heard on June 24 as part of ''Wonderful Winds.''</p>
        <p>The festival concludes with ''The Coronation of Poppea,'' continuing the tradition of including an opera in the festival. A cast of 17 singers will be accompanied by harpsichords, strings, recorders and a bass lute known as a theorbo. Mr. Metz will be at his keyboard, working his beat.</p>
        <p>Tickets for the Connecticut Early Music Festival, June 9-25 in the New London area, may be ordered by mail (Post Office Box 329, New London 06320), by phone (860-444-2419) or on line (www.CtEarly Music.org).</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
