<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World; To Win the Peace You Dance With the Devil</title>
    <meta content="04HOGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northern Ireland</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sinn Fein</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Irish Republican Army</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trimble, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2DB113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World; To Win the Peace You Dance With the Devil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ulster Unionist leader David Trimble has won praise for rescuing endangered peace process in Northern Ireland by persuading his quarrelsome, doubting rank and file to trust in Sinn Fein's promise that Irish Republican Army will disarm; his stance earned him Nobel Peace Prize in 1998 and the scorn of Protestant hardliners among whom he had been a hero; in 1972, Trimble formed hardline faction within Unionist party that played role in bringing down last effort at power-sharing in province; he still occasionally lapses back into incendiary rhetoric; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND is locked in a grim struggle to trade in tested old tribal instincts for risky new communal ones, and the qualms and tensions in that swap were on display last week in Belfast in the actions of a central figure in the peace negotiations, David Trimble.</p>
        <p>Last weekend Mr. Trimble, leader of the province's largest Protestant party, the Ulster Unionists, revived what has been a repeatedly jeopardized peace accord by persuading his quarrelsome, doubting rank and file to trust in the disarmament promises of its Catholic sworn enemies in Sinn Fein, which represents the Irish Republican Army. Supporters of the 1998 accord, which aims to end three decades of violence with the creation of power-sharing political institutions, promptly praised him for his courage and vision -- virtues infrequent in Ulster politics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND is locked in a grim struggle to trade in tested old tribal instincts for risky new communal ones, and the qualms and tensions in that swap were on display last week in Belfast in the actions of a central figure in the peace negotiations, David Trimble.</p>
        <p>Last weekend Mr. Trimble, leader of the province's largest Protestant party, the Ulster Unionists, revived what has been a repeatedly jeopardized peace accord by persuading his quarrelsome, doubting rank and file to trust in the disarmament promises of its Catholic sworn enemies in Sinn Fein, which represents the Irish Republican Army. Supporters of the 1998 accord, which aims to end three decades of violence with the creation of power-sharing political institutions, promptly praised him for his courage and vision -- virtues infrequent in Ulster politics.</p>
        <p>Then, after achieving his narrow victory, Mr. Trimble stepped out into the luminous gallery of glass-sheathed Waterfront Hall, which is itself a symbol of a brighter future for the conflicted province, and promptly reverted to an all-too-familiar name-calling.</p>
        <p>''As far as democracy is concerned,'' he said of the Sinn Fein politicians whose word he was championing moments before, ''these folk ain't house-trained yet.'' They would have to be ''brought to heel,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Calling the opposition dogs and worse is standard-issue oratory in Northern Ireland, where insult is the common currency of public dialogue. One of those consigned by Mr. Trimble to the kennel, Sinn Fein Assemblyman Alex Maskey, robustly protested the crude allusion but quickly added that it was probably something the Ulster Unionist leader felt impelled to say to keep party hard-liners on board.</p>
        <p>Out of this kind of grudging acceptance of each other's atavistic imperatives has emerged a sense of sameness between two rival communities that have spent generations fighting to maintain their differences.  It may not be the ultimate equality that reformers are seeking, but it is a kind of companion conduct that suggests consensual politics may stand a chance in Ulster.</p>
        <p>No sooner was the home rule government up and running last week than Sinn Fein dominated debate with an argument over whether its ministers would allow the British flag to fly over public buildings they now occupied. It was telling behavior for a party that has regularly mocked Protestants for devoting so little time to real issues and so much to symbolic ones like defending their right to wave banners and parade around the province in uniform.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trimble finally got his delegates' support for going into government with Sinn Fein by warning that if they voted no, they would be banishing themselves to the margins and leaving the main arena to their opponents. His point -- one that has taken time to dawn on his tradition-bound audience and produced the support of only a slight majority -- was that the only way to keep power was to share it. Continue trying to hold onto all of it, he was saying, and there's the unenviable possibility of ending up with none of it.</p>
        <p>SUMMONING his party to the center was a daring bid because it is the fringes that often are more alluring to Ulster politicians. George J. Mitchell, the former United States senator who brokered the original peace agreement, once commented that while the normal movement of politics in Western societies was toward the middle space of reconciliation, in Northern Ireland it was toward the poles of defiance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trimble has been in both places.</p>
        <p>Born in 1944 in Bangor, a seaside resort in County Down, and formerly a law professor, Mr. Trimble had his first political involvement on the clamorous right wing of the unionists, whose unionism sprang from a wish that Northern Ireland remain part of the United Kingdom. He joined the Ulster Vanguard, which was formed in 1972 to confront the more mainstream Ulster Unionists, and took an active part in the hard-line protests that helped end the Sunningdale Agreement in 1974, which was the last attempt at power-sharing in the province.</p>
        <p>A result of that agitation was to bring down the home rule government of Brian Faulkner, a Protestant moderate who occupied the same position then, premier of Northern Ireland, that Mr. Trimble does today as first minister.</p>
        <p>The Upper Bann district that he has represented in the British Parliament since 1990 includes the town of Portadown, known as the citadel of the militant Orange Order. It has been the scene of violent standoffs every summer when the black-suited ''brethren'' in their bowler hats and orange sashes have tried to take their parade commemorating centuries-old Protestant triumphs from Drumcree Church along a road that wends through Catholic neighborhoods. In 1995 Mr. Trimble attracted attention by leading the marchers into a police formation blocking their path, hurling himself against a patrolman and giving the officers a red-faced, finger-wagging lecture. When the Orangemen penetrated the police lines and reached their destination at the Portadown Orange Lodge, he danced a victory jig arm in arm with the Rev. Ian Paisley, the preacher-politician who is the best-known opponent of any accommodation with Catholics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trimble won a Nobel Peace Prize in 1998, but just years before he was making his mark by acting rude, truculent and spiteful, his occasional smiles tight, joyless and disdainful. Hardly a matinee idol today, he has mellowed into a more relaxed and broadly persuasive orator, indulging in the occasional hot-tempered flashback as a reminder that his more primitive past still lurks.</p>
        <p>These days he is denounced by Mr. Paisley as a Judas, and Mr. Trimble's picture hangs in a hut on Drumcree Hill, altered to show satanic horns protruding from his forehead. His party has traditionally been most comfortable saying no, and only 53 percent of the 862 ruling council members chose to say yes to accepting the I.R.A. pledges on disarmament and participating in government with Sinn Fein.</p>
        <p>The British and Irish governments, the two sponsors of the peace effort, both believe that Mr. Trimble is the only person on the Protestant side capable of maintaining progress in putting into place the power-sharing arrangements that have continually faltered. Sinn Fein also appreciates his fundamental value, and the biggest threat to him now comes from his own co-religionists. There will be lots of tactical maneuvering among them to try to undo what he has done, and his leadership is sure to be challenged again.</p>
        <p>To the task of dealing with this crafty enemy within, Mr. Trimble brings an important qualification. He was until recently one of them himself.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
