<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turner's Death Stuns N.F.L.'s Players</title>
    <meta content="04NFLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Raiders</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wise, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turner, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oster, Martin (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Oakland Raiders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4DA1F3CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1247" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turner's Death Stuns N.F.L.'s Players</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses death of Oakland Raiders safety Eric Turner from complications of abdominal cancer; Dr Martin Oster, oncologist at Columbia Presbyterian Medical Center, describes this type of cancer as insidious and without many symptoms; Turner is remembered as gregarious person and unselfish player; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Oakland Raiders' organization and much of the National Football League remain saddened -- and puzzled -- over the death of Raiders safety Eric Turner last Sunday from complications of abdominal cancer.</p>
        <p>Many in the league, especially his teammates and coaches, were stunned that the cancer could have so quickly struck down a top, young athlete with seemingly little warning. In a matter of months, Turner, 31, went from a Pro Bowl player who last season was a contributing member of the Raiders, to recently losing 70 pounds from his 215-pound frame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Oakland Raiders' organization and much of the National Football League remain saddened -- and puzzled -- over the death of Raiders safety Eric Turner last Sunday from complications of abdominal cancer.</p>
        <p>Many in the league, especially his teammates and coaches, were stunned that the cancer could have so quickly struck down a top, young athlete with seemingly little warning. In a matter of months, Turner, 31, went from a Pro Bowl player who last season was a contributing member of the Raiders, to recently losing 70 pounds from his 215-pound frame.</p>
        <p>Turner, who two weeks ago denied reports that he was seriously ill, died at Los Robles Hospital in Thousand Oaks, Calif. Because of privacy concerns, the Raiders and family members have released little information about his illness.</p>
        <p>Turner's death has caused some players, especially his teammates, to make themselves more aware about cancer. One agent said he had asked his clients, with the Raiders and others throughout the league, to see their team doctors for a checkup.</p>
        <p>Abdominal cancer, said Dr. Martin Oster, an oncologist at Columbia Presbyterian Medical Center, is an insidious disease that is hard to detect, and once it spreads, it kills quickly. Even the detailed physical exams administered to N.F.L. players would not have most likely detected the cancer.</p>
        <p>''This type of cancer might begin without any specific symptoms,'' Oster said. ''The patient may have vague symptoms, like stomach pain or weight loss. In a healthy young person, those symptoms do not alarm. So the cancer advances.''</p>
        <p>Such symptoms would not have most likely alerted Turner, or almost any other player. Football players are used to enduring physical discomfort. They routinely play with broken fingers, sore knees, battered ribs and other injuries. So Turner would have barely noticed a stomach ache, and any weight loss might have been attributed to workouts.</p>
        <p>''I don't know all of the details of his case of course, but there is a stage in this type of cancer, like many types of cancer, where it is early, and the cancer is curable,'' Oster said. ''But this cancer is an iceberg cancer. The symptoms can be few while the cancer grows. Then by the time it is diagnosed, it can be beyond a surgical cure.''</p>
        <p>While the details of when the stomach cancer was diagnosed are not known publicly, what is known is that last season he was playing. So the diagnosis had to have come in the past year -- it is hard to imagine a doctor diagnosing stomach cancer in Turner during the season and then Turner continuing to play -- which means the disease was most likely diagnosed after the season and in the last six months.</p>
        <p>It is not unusual for this type of cancer to spread rapidly. ''About 10 to 20 percent of the people who get this cancer may live five years or longer after the diagnosis,'' Oster said. ''But for the vast majority, about 80 to 90 percent, it is not uncommon to see death within a year.''</p>
        <p>As Turner's illness worsened, he withdrew from some teammates and friends. Terry Donahue, who coached Turner at U.C.L.A., said he had sent him a note several weeks ago after word of his illness leaked out, but he never heard back from him. Several teammates tried to contact Turner by phone, but could not reach him. ''In retrospect, he was exceedingly private in cloaking this illness in the most private of terms,'' said Art Modell, the Baltimore Ravens owner, whose Cleveland Browns drafted Turner second over all in 1991. ''It's very sad that a young man that age has to be taken that way.''</p>
        <p>Several players questioned how a young person in outstanding physical shape could lose his life so quickly.</p>
        <p>''Being in good shape and taking care of yourself never hurts, no question,'' Oster said. ''But over all, I'm afraid, it means very little. It doesn't help you fight the cancer. Why you get the cancer is a function of genetics and what you eat.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Raiders are remembering Turner as a gregarious, friendly person, as well as an unselfish player. Oakland Coach Jon Gruden said Turner was ''a great guy who will be sorely missed by a lot of people.'' Napoleon Kaufman, the Oakland running back, said: ''He was compassionate and a class act. It was truly a pleasure to have known Eric and I will miss him.''</p>
        <p>Sanders May Join Redskins</p>
        <p>A Dallas Cowboys team official said he hated the idea that cornerback Deion Sanders might end up playing for the rival Washington Redskins, but conceded it would probably happen. Sanders, who was released Friday by the Cowboys, could sign with the Redskins soon.</p>
        <p>The Cowboys believe Sanders is still a good player, but they simply could not afford to keep him on their roster. If Dallas did not cut Sanders before Friday, his contract for the next two years -- a $10 million roster bonus and $500,000 in base salary for the coming season and a $13 million salary for next season -- would have been guaranteed.</p>
        <p>Sanders has been working with a speed coach, and the Pro Bowl player believes he is in great shape. The Redskins and other teams agree. Tampa Bay and Denver are also interested in Sanders, and the Dallas owner Jerry Jones will not rule out an attempt to re-sign Sanders at a cheaper price. But look for Sanders to end up in Washington.</p>
        <p>Eagles Budgeting Well</p>
        <p>The Philadelphia Eagles are in the best position of any team to take advantage of the remaining free-agency period, since last week the team was an astounding $7 million under the $62 million salary cap. Even though the Eagles will use $4 million to sign draft picks, the remaining cash will allow them to sign one or two quality free agents.</p>
        <p>The Eagles have had a tremendous off-season so far, acquiring linebacker Carlos Emmons, fullback Stanley Pritchett and offensive lineman Jon Runyan through free agency. In the April college draft, they selected defensive tackle Corey Simon, a possible future Warren Sapp.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia is definitely a team to watch next season in a division, the N.F.C. East, that is certain to be one of the toughest in football.</p>
        <p>Young Torn Between Options</p>
        <p>According to someone close to the quarterback, Steve Young simply cannot make up his mind about his future. One day, Young will talk to friends about how he would like to finish his career in Denver playing for Coach Mike Shanahan, one of the most innovative minds in the game. Then the next day, Young says he will retire, and the next, Young expresses the desire to finish his playing career with the 49ers. Young has also expressed the desire to become a football television analyst.</p>
        <p>Young's indecision was the reason he asked San Francisco for extra time -- until June 10 -- to make a decision regarding his future. Privately, the 49ers said they would like Young to retire because they feared for his health. Young has sustained a number of concussions, and San Francisco's line next year is expected to be porous.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
