<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nymphet at the Net</title>
    <meta content="04DOWD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LIBERTIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sports Illustrated</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kournikova, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EED6113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nymphet at the Net</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column laments that Anna Kournikova has emerged as one of highest-earning players in women's tennis not by winning matches but by vamping, as she does in new issue of Sports Illustrated magazine (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Lolita of tennis may be cold on the court. Anna Kournikova flopped at the French Open in a cascade of unforced errors and double-faults.</p>
        <p>But the blond knockout, who turns 19 this week, burns up the pages of the new issue of Sports Illustrated, with bronze legs, black patent stiletto mules and a smoldering look that you usually only see after-hours on Showtime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Lolita of tennis may be cold on the court. Anna Kournikova flopped at the French Open in a cascade of unforced errors and double-faults.</p>
        <p>But the blond knockout, who turns 19 this week, burns up the pages of the new issue of Sports Illustrated, with bronze legs, black patent stiletto mules and a smoldering look that you usually only see after-hours on Showtime.</p>
        <p>Without ever having won a major tournament, Miss Kournikova is the highest-earning player in women's tennis -- and outearns most men. Only problem is, she isn't making it playing. She's making it vamping.</p>
        <p>Sports was one of the last bastions where you could still sell tickets on pure ability. Michael Jordan's flair and good looks didn't hurt, but it was his basketball moves that made him Michael Jordan.</p>
        <p>With the ascendance of Anna, eroticism trumps athleticism. ''A hot body can count as much as a good backhand,'' Sports Illustrated says, calling her the Jezebel of Sweat, the Ground Strokin' Goddess, the femme fatale of serves and curves. Linesmen only have eyes for her lines. Ball boys dive for her sweaty towels.</p>
        <p>Under a picture of her mile-high legs and inch-long skirt and a leopard-skin bra at a banquet, S.I. intones: ''To climb to the top of the tennis ladder, Kournikova will have to step up her game considerably.'' Translation: She got gams, not game.</p>
        <p>Her coach, Eric Van Harpen, admits it is hard to motivate a girl who already has a Porsche and jewels.</p>
        <p>''Men play to win,'' he says. ''Women play not to lose.''</p>
        <p>We've come a long way, baby, since Billie Jean King whupped Bobby Riggs in an exhibition game intended to pump interest in women's tennis.</p>
        <p>The Russian-born Anna will soon be featured in ads for Berlei sports bras with the slogan, ''Only the ball should bounce.'' Besides her $10 million in endorsements, she snagged a part in the new Jim Carrey movie.</p>
        <p>''Moreover,'' Frank Deford writes in S.I. about its cover girl, ''she has achieved this status at a time when we are all supposed to be so gender-enlightened, when pretty isn't supposed to matter anymore in the workplace, especially in such a meritocratic domain as sports. So here is what Kournikova proves about Homo sapiens, male division, circa 2000: Skin-deep still counts.''</p>
        <p>Skin-deep still counts?</p>
        <p>Skin-deep rules -- even where it wasn't supposed to. America is more obsessed with looks and sex appeal than ever.</p>
        <p>Once women burned their bras. Now they're lining up for bras featuring built-in silicone bags, giving you the ''natural'' implant look.</p>
        <p>Silicone-deep counts.</p>
        <p>When Arnon Milchan, the flamboyant Hollywood producer of ''Pretty Woman'' and ''L.A. Confidential,'' pledged $120 million in a nine-year deal for TV rights to the Women's Tennis Association tour two years ago, he hired designers to make sexy clothes for teen hotties like Anna, Martina Hingis and Venus Williams. This, even though some young players already wore outfits so revealing that the tennis analyst Mary Carillo likened it to ''kiddie porn'' and Martina Navratilova cracked, ''Why not just send them out there naked?''</p>
        <p>Many of Anna's fellow players can't stand her. Nathalie Tauziat, a 32-year-old French player who ranks seventh  in the world, has written a book titled ''The Hidden Side of Tennis,'' in which she asserts that the game is being ruined by babes who care more about modeling than playing.</p>
        <p>''Aesthetics and charisma are seen as more important than sporting performance,'' she writes, ''and it won't change as long as the box office puts Kournikova ahead of Lindsay Davenport just because she is prettier. . . .  For the WTA, Anna is a really powerful cash machine, a blond godsend.''</p>
        <p>She said that the women players try to teach the 15th-ranked Anna a lesson: ''They all play harder to make her realize that, on court, being the prettiest is useless.'' Anna's a diva. She expects the cattiness.</p>
        <p>I covered tennis in the 70's, a period when the most famous woman playing was a man -- Renee Richards, who had undergone a sex change and had to go to court in New York to be able to play in the U.S. Open. So maybe I have flexible ideas about female tennis stars. Or maybe I just accept that life has certain verities.</p>
        <p>As E. M. Forster wrote, ''Beauty creates its own rules of conduct.''</p>
        <p>LIBERTIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
