<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>May 28-June 3; To Be or Not to Be, Texas Style, and Bush-Lessness</title>
    <meta content="04BOXA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DC113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>May 28-June 3; To Be or Not to Be, Texas Style, and Bush-Lessness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has the distinction of presiding over more executions (131) than any governor in the country. So, on Thursday, when he granted his first 30-day reprieve to a death-row inmate, the political world took note: was it an instance of a man running as a compassionate conservative trying to advertise his charitable nature?</p>
        <p>Matters of life and death can become embroiled in the theater of politics. Eight years ago, a presidential candidate who also happened to be a governor made a special trip back to his home state of Arkansas to be on hand for an execution, an act viewed in political circles as a demonstration of a moderate Democrat's tough-on-crime credentials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush of Texas has the distinction of presiding over more executions (131) than any governor in the country. So, on Thursday, when he granted his first 30-day reprieve to a death-row inmate, the political world took note: was it an instance of a man running as a compassionate conservative trying to advertise his charitable nature?</p>
        <p>Matters of life and death can become embroiled in the theater of politics. Eight years ago, a presidential candidate who also happened to be a governor made a special trip back to his home state of Arkansas to be on hand for an execution, an act viewed in political circles as a demonstration of a moderate Democrat's tough-on-crime credentials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides insisted there was nothing political about their candidate's decision, which paved the way for DNA tests to be administered to try to clarify the condemned man's guilt or innocence in a case of rape and murder.</p>
        <p>''There's an opportunity to get more information now from that test,'' said Karen P. Hughes, a spokesman for Mr. Bush. ''So he feels it's the right thing to do.''</p>
        <p>With the candidates' daily rollout of positions on all sorts of pressing issues -- last week Mr. Bush and Vice President Al Gore offered their takes on, among other things, mental health care, cancer treatment and land conservation -- voters can be forgiven for forgetting that the politicians still hold important day jobs that can change lives.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, the ceremonial aspects of their offices meld with the oratorical requirements of their campaigns, as they did for Mr. Gore on Monday, when he addressed a Memorial Day commemoration in Pennsylvania. Noting his own military service, which included a five-month stint in Vietnam as an Army reporter, Mr. Gore said, ''I know that my service doesn't in any way match that of the heroes we honor on this day.'' One of the more unusual aspects of the speech, delivered in a week in which polls showed the presidential contest to be neck-and-neck: not a single mention of Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>PETER MARKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
