<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Brooklyn Meetings, From Sea Gate to Dumbo</title>
    <meta content="04BOAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COMMUNITY BOARDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDF113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Brooklyn Meetings, From Sea Gate to Dumbo</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DISTRICT 1: Greenpoint, Williamsburg; usually the second Tuesday of the month; but the next meeting is Tuesday, 6:30 p.m.; Swinging Sixties Senior Center, 211 Ainslee Street, corner of Manhattan Avenue, Williamsburg; Board chairman: Vincent V. Abate; District manager: Gerald Esposito; (718) 389-0009.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 2: Fort Greene, Downtown Brooklyn, Brooklyn Heights, Clinton Hill, Boerum Hill, Dumbo, Vinegar Hill, Farragut; second Wednesday of the month; next meeting June 14, 6 p.m.; Brooklyn Borough Hall, 209 Joralemon Street; Board chairman: Robert Evens; (718) 596-5410.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DISTRICT 1: Greenpoint, Williamsburg; usually the second Tuesday of the month; but the next meeting is Tuesday, 6:30 p.m.; Swinging Sixties Senior Center, 211 Ainslee Street, corner of Manhattan Avenue, Williamsburg; Board chairman: Vincent V. Abate; District manager: Gerald Esposito; (718) 389-0009.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 2: Fort Greene, Downtown Brooklyn, Brooklyn Heights, Clinton Hill, Boerum Hill, Dumbo, Vinegar Hill, Farragut; second Wednesday of the month; next meeting June 14, 6 p.m.; Brooklyn Borough Hall, 209 Joralemon Street; Board chairman: Robert Evens; (718) 596-5410.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 3: Bedford-Stuyvesant; first Monday of the month; next meeting tomorrow, 7 p.m., 1368 Fulton Street, near Verona Place (community room); Board chairman: Hardy Joe Long; District manager: Lewis A. Watkins; (718) 622-6601.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 4: Bushwick; third Wednesday of the month; next meeting June 21, 6 p.m., 195 Linden Street, near Wilson Avenue; Board chairwoman: Anna Gonzalez; District manager: Nadine Whitted LeBron; (718) 628-8400.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 5: East New York; fourth Wednesday of the month, next meeting June 28, 7:30 p.m., P.S. 13, 557 Pennsylvania Avenue, near Riverdale Avenue; Board chairman: Earl Williams; District manager: Walter Campbell; (718) 498-5711.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 6: Columbia Terrace, Gowanus, Park Slope, Carroll Gardens, Cobble Hill, Red Hook; second Wednesday of the month; next meeting June 14, 6:30 p.m., Berkeley Carroll School auditorium, 181 Lincoln Place, between Seventh and Eighth Avenues; Board chairwoman: Irene Lo Re; District manager: Craig R. Hammerman; (718) 643-3027.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 7: Sunset Park, Windsor Terrace and Greenwood; third Wednesday of the month; next meeting June 21, 6:30 p.m., Community Board 7 building, 4201 Fourth Avenue, corner of 43rd Street, Sunset Park; Board chairwoman: Sara Gonzalez; District manager: Eugene Moore; (718) 854-0003.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 8: North Crown Heights, Prospect Heights; second Thursday of the month; next meeting Thursday, 7:30 p.m.; Center for Nursing and Rehabilitation, 520 Prospect Place, corner of Classon Avenue; Board chairman: Robert Matthews; District manager: Doris Alexander; (718) 467-5574.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 9: Crown Heights, Prospect-Lefferts Gardens, Wingate; usually fourth Tuesday of the month; but the next meeting is Monday, June 26, 7  p.m.; Atwell J.H.S., 400 Empire Boulevard, corner of New York Avenue; Board chairman: Rabbi Jacob Goldstein; District manager: Pearl Miles; (718) 778-9279.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 10: Bay Ridge, Dyker Heights, Fort Hamilton; third Monday of the month, next meeting June 19, 7 p.m., Shore Hill Community Room, 9000 Shore Road, on 91st Street between Shore Road and Colonial Road; Board chairman: Kirk Tzanides; District manager: Denise Virga; (718) 745-6827.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 11: Bensonhurst, Bath Beach, Gravesend, Mapleton; usually second Thursday of the month; but the next meeting is Wednesday, 7:30 p.m., Hyam Salomon Home, 2300 Cropsey Avenue, corner of 23rd Avenue, Bensonhurst; Board chairman: William Guarinello; District manager: Howard Feuer; (718) 266-8800.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 12: Borough Park, Midwood, Kensington/Dahill; fourth Tuesday of the month; next meeting June 27, 7:30 p.m., P.S. 192, 4715 18th Avenue, corner of 47th Street, Borough Park; Board chairman: Alan J. Dubrow; District manager: Priscilla Celano; (718) 851-0800.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 13: Coney Island, Brighton Beach, Gravesend; fourth Wednesday of the month; next meeting June 28 at 7:30 p.m., Coney Island Hospital, second floor auditorium, 2601 Ocean Parkway, Board Chairman: Martin Levine; District Manager: Charles Reichenthal; (718) 266-3001.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 14: Flatbush, Midwood; second Monday of the month; next meeting June 12, 7:30 p.m., P.S. 249, Caton Avenue and Marlborough Road, Midwood; Board chairman: Alvin M. Berk; District manager: Terry Rodie (718) 859-6357.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 15: Manhattan Beach, Sheepshead Bay, Gravesend; Sheepshead Bay; last Tuesday of the month; next meeting June 27, 7 p.m., Kingsborough Community College, at Oriental Boulevard, Faculty Dining Room; Board chairman: John E. Nikas; District manager: Paula Lupka; (718) 332-3008.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 16: Brownsville, Ocean Hill; fourth Tuesday of the month; next meeting June 27, 7 p.m., at the district offices, 444 Thomas S. Boyland Street between East New York and Pitkin Avenues; Board chairman: Charles T. Hamilton; District manager: Viola D. Greene; (718) 385-0323.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 17: East Flatbush; third Wednesday of the month; next meeting June 21, 7 p.m.; Downstate Medical Center, 395 Lenox Road, near Classon Avenue,Board chairman: Albert Payne; District manager: Willie Scott; (718) 467-3536.</p>
        <p>DISTRICT 18: Canarsie, Mill Basin, Marine Park, Bergen Beach, Flatlands, Georgetown, Fraiser; third Wednesday of the month; next meeting scheduled for June 21, 8 p.m., Kings Plaza Community Room, Flatbush Avenue and Avenue V; Board chairman: Saul Needle; District manager: Dorothy Turano; (718) 241-0422.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY BOARDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
