<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Overdose Alert</title>
    <meta content="04POLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Richard (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toy, Vivian S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E4D9153CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Overdose Alert</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN S. TOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toy, Vivian S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island, NY, has become center of attention for Republican and Democratic parties in national elections; several contests have become high profile, including US Senate race between Rick Lazio and Hillary Rodham Clinton; island-wide campaign spending is likely to set new records; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIRST there was Representative Michael P. Forbes's seat, which instantly became one of the nation's most hotly contested races when Mr. Forbes incurred the wrath of the Republican Party last year by jumping ship and becoming a Democrat.</p>
        <p>And now that Representative Rick A. Lazio has become the Republican Senate candidate, his open seat also has caught the attention of the national parties, putting Long Island -- an area with a record of crossover voting to belie its reputation as a Republican redoubt -- square at the center of the national political stage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIRST there was Representative Michael P. Forbes's seat, which instantly became one of the nation's most hotly contested races when Mr. Forbes incurred the wrath of the Republican Party last year by jumping ship and becoming a Democrat.</p>
        <p>And now that Representative Rick A. Lazio has become the Republican Senate candidate, his open seat also has caught the attention of the national parties, putting Long Island -- an area with a record of crossover voting to belie its reputation as a Republican redoubt -- square at the center of the national political stage.</p>
        <p>Put aside the fact that having a South Shore native in the Senate race against Hillary Rodham Clinton automatically raises Long Island's national profile. What promise to be two extremely tight congressional races have made Long Island a crucial battleground in national politics.</p>
        <p>With the Democrats just six seats away from recapturing the House, both parties have a lot at stake in the First and Second Congressional Districts in Suffolk County. And in Nassau, some believe that Representative Carolyn McCarthy, a Democrat, may be vulnerable to a challenge as well.</p>
        <p>''Long Island is very important real estate for us,'' said Jim Wilkinson, a spokesman for the National Republican Congressional Committee. ''So much is on the line this year, if we lost Long Island, we'd lose the nation.''</p>
        <p>There may be just a hint of hyperbole in that statement, since there is also the matter of the presidential race. But it leaves no doubt as to where Long Island stands this year. For politics-watchers, it doesn't get much better.</p>
        <p>Island-wide campaign spending will likely set new records, with both parties pumping in big doses of money to supplement whatever the candidates themselves raise. More money will mean a deeper flood of political advertisements. And the local and national news media will cover the races closely.</p>
        <p>''With two or three seats in play, it's possible that the Island could determine which party controls the House,'' said Stuart Rothenberg, a Congressional analyst who publishes a political newsletter. ''So you're probably likely to have all kinds of political celebrities passing through the Island, and they can get a two-fer or a three-fer out of each trip.''</p>
        <p>Political analysts say Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush will probably not spend much time on Long Island, given that New York is considered a relatively safe state for Mr. Gore. But President Clinton already helped raise $500,000 for Mr. Forbes at a Manhattan fundraiser in April and Richard A. Gephardt, the House minority leader, made an appearance at the Suffolk County Democratic Party's annual spring dinner.</p>
        <p>More such forays are inevitable. With Long Island's new heightened profile, chances are that if local party leaders make a request, national leaders will come.</p>
        <p>''The celebrities are not just going to come to Long Island to raise money,'' Mr. Rothenberg said. ''They'll be coming to get voters excited and interested.''</p>
        <p>Making sure voters are focused on the elections will be important, he added, because what happens in the congressional races could also affect the senatorial and presidential races. The ratio of registered Republicans to Democrats is 56-44 in both the First and Second Districts, but voters have frequently split their tickets. Before Mr. Lazio, the Second District elected a Democrat, Thomas Downey, for nine consecutive terms.</p>
        <p>Of the three congressional races, no one doubts that Mr. Forbes's will be the toughest and probably most expensive battleground, with both parties preparing to spend as much as $3 million in an area where $1 million is more the norm for a contested race.</p>
        <p>The Republican Party declared Mr. Forbes public enemy No. 1 last summer when he denounced the party's leaders as ''intolerant and incapable of governing'' and became a Democrat. ''We're looking at three huge races on Long Island, but there's no question that Forbes is our No. 1 target,'' said Mr. Wilkinson, of the National Republican Congressional Committee.</p>
        <p>Bradford W. O'Hearn, a spokesman for the Democratic Party in Suffolk County, said the Forbes race would be different from the other two because Republicans see Mr. Forbes as ''a traitor to the cause and they want to set an example of him.'' Especially with the Democrats possibly regaining control of the House, he said, other Republicans may consider following Mr. Forbes's lead and the party ''wants people to know that there's a price to pay.''</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, it looked like Mr. Forbes might not even get the nomination of his new party when Democratic leaders said they would withhold their support if he also accepted the endorsement of the Right-to-Life Party. He ultimately turned down the Right-to-Life support and got the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>One key to Mr. Forbes's race, and possibly to the other races as well, will be the role that organized labor plays in the election. Mr. Forbes has long had the support of labor unions, and they have vowed to fight hard for him this time around.</p>
        <p>The New York State A.F.L.-C.I.O., which usually does not make endorsements until its convention in August, endorsed Mr. Forbes in April because his race would probably be ''the closest one in the state,'' said Suzy Ballantyne, the union's political director.</p>
        <p>''We had planned to do a full-court effort for Forbes and now we're probably going to do the same for the Lazio seat,'' she said. Hundreds of thousands of flyers will be handed out at work sites and sent directly to members' homes, and volunteers will work phone banks and go door-to-door to persuade members to vote for the union-backed candidates.</p>
        <p>With nearly 71,000 members in the First Congressional District and more than 72,000 in the Second, Ms. Ballantyne said, ''if we do our program correctly and we can persuade 70 to 75 percent of our members to vote for our candidates, we certainly could be the margin in a close race.''</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Lazio did not become a Senate candidate until Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's sudden withdrawal from the race last month, the players in the Second District race have yet to be named. Mr. Lazio's seat had been seen as an easy victory for the Republican Party, but it now becomes an opportunity for the Democratic Party to gain one more seat.</p>
        <p>Just as local Republican Party leaders united behind one candidate, Felix J. Grucci Jr., the Brookhaven town supervisor, to avoid a primary challenge before battling Mr. Forbes in the First District, Republicans are expected to rally behind one candidate to run in Mr. Lazio's place. The most likely candidate is Peter McGowan, the Islip town supervisor.</p>
        <p>The Democratic nominee, however, remains an open question. Richard H. Schaffer, the Babylon town supervisor, was lobbied hard to enter the race by national party leaders. Mr. Schaffer was widely seen as the strongest candidate, particularly because he would have eliminated the possibility of a messy primary. But Mr. Schaffer announced last week that he had decided to stay out of the race and is likely to become the county's Democratic chairman if Dominic Baranello retires in September, as expected.</p>
        <p>''Schaffer was under a lot of pressure to get in, and this race is going to get a lot of national attention because ultimately the open races will provide the key to the control of the House,'' said Amy Walter, an editor at the Cook Political Report, a Washington newsletter.</p>
        <p>Two Democrats left to battle for the nomination are the Suffolk County Legislature's minority leader, David A. Bishop, and the Huntington Town Board's majority leader, Steven J. Israel. Mr. Bishop has the support of Mr. Schaffer and the party's county committee, but Mr. Israel has proven himself an able fundraiser and formidable opponent.</p>
        <p>Ms. Walter said that while the Cook Political Report sees the First and Second District seats among the nation's 15 most competitive congressional races, the race for Ms. McCarthy's seat in the Fourth District comes in the next tier of closely watched races.</p>
        <p>''There's not as much focus from the parties on McCarthy's seat, but she was rattled by her close shave last time, and this is a race that may break later if a crack in the veneer comes through,'' she said. Ms. McCarthy's opponent, Assemblyman Gregory R. Becker, lost to her in 1998, but her 53-47 margin was close enough to give Mr. Becker's supporters hope that he can overcome Ms. McCarthy's high profile as a gun-control advocate.</p>
        <p>Jack Caffey, president of the Long Island Federation of Labor, an umbrella group for 80 unions, said the federation had long considered Ms. McCarthy's race a tough one. ''She's still a Democrat running in a Republican district, and we don't want to take things for granted,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Having to focus union efforts on not just two but three congressional races ''is going to split our forces somewhat,'' Mr. Caffey said. ''But we're still going to do whatever it takes to get our candidates elected.''</p>
        <p>While Long Island will be in the national political spotlight this year, the concentration of contested races will probably not produce any real benefits or disadvantages to either party or to any of the candidates.</p>
        <p>''Everybody thinks there's a never-ending spigot of money in New York for campaigns anyway,'' Ms. Walter said. ''And there may be some competition for attention, but in the end it's just going to mean that no matter where in New York you are, you're going to be inundated with campaigning.''</p>
        <p>Eric Smith, a spokesman for the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, said, ''It's always easier to have the big races concentrated than having them spread all over the country.''</p>
        <p>But he, too, downplayed the impact on the races themselves. ''Although I suppose it might have some political consultants a little upset,'' he added, ''because it'll mean fewer frequent-flier miles for them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
