<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shared Prayers, Mixed Blessings</title>
    <meta content="Y04RCH$77" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HOW RACE IS LIVED IN AMERICA" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentecostal Church</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1DF113CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="7919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shared Prayers, Mixed Blessings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>DECATUR, Ga.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First article in series, How Race is Lived in America, examining racial relations which still ignites political debates two generations after end of legal discrimination and is being defined less by political action than by daily experiences; examines interactions between blacks and whites in sphere of religion; focuses on Assembly of God Tabernacle, Pentecostal church in Decatur, Ga, where blacks make up almost half of congregation; Tabernacle is rare religious institution in nation where 90 percent of all congregations are at least 80 percent one race; blacks and whites mix freely and almost all aspects of church are thoroughly integrated, but even so it remains deeply conservative socially and theologically and its life is still driven by race in countless ways; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Howard Pugh, head usher, is on patrol. May the good Lord have mercy on any child, or adult for that matter, who dares to tread across the lobby of the Assembly of God Tabernacle with so much as an open Coca-Cola in his hand. Because first he will get the look, the alert glare of a hunting dog catching its first scent of game. Then he will get the wag, the slightly palsied shake of the left index finger. And then the voice, serious as a heart attack and dripping with Pensacola pinesap: ''Son, this is the Lord's house. And they just shampooed that carpet last week.''</p>
        <p>It goes without saying that Howard Pugh knows what is going on in his lobby. So when Mr. Pugh, a white man with a bulbous pink nose, spots 81-year-old Roy Denson slipping out of the sanctuary, he doesn't even have to ask. He just knows. He knows because he has seen Mr. Denson flee the 10:30 service time and again, and it is always when one of the choir's black soloists moves to center stage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Howard Pugh, head usher, is on patrol. May the good Lord have mercy on any child, or adult for that matter, who dares to tread across the lobby of the Assembly of God Tabernacle with so much as an open Coca-Cola in his hand. Because first he will get the look, the alert glare of a hunting dog catching its first scent of game. Then he will get the wag, the slightly palsied shake of the left index finger. And then the voice, serious as a heart attack and dripping with Pensacola pinesap: ''Son, this is the Lord's house. And they just shampooed that carpet last week.''</p>
        <p>It goes without saying that Howard Pugh knows what is going on in his lobby. So when Mr. Pugh, a white man with a bulbous pink nose, spots 81-year-old Roy Denson slipping out of the sanctuary, he doesn't even have to ask. He just knows. He knows because he has seen Mr. Denson flee the 10:30 service time and again, and it is always when one of the choir's black soloists moves to center stage.</p>
        <p>This time it is Robert Lawson, a soulful tenor with a fondness for canary-yellow suits. As he begins to sing, the Pentecostal faithful gradually rise. First a few black members clap and sway. Then more join in. Finally, the white members are moved to stand, and before long the 2,000-seat sanctuary is washed over with harmony. Stretching their arms toward the heavens, the congregants weave a tapestry of pinks and tans and browns.</p>
        <p>But to Mr. Denson's ears, Mr. Lawson's improvisational riffs sound like so much screeching and hollering. And so he sits there seething, thinking about how he joined this church 56 years ago, how he followed it from downtown Atlanta to the suburbs, how he hung the Sheetrock with his own hands, and how the blacks are taking over and the whites are just letting it happen.</p>
        <p>He gets angrier and angrier, listening to these boisterous black folks desecrate his music, until he simply cannot bear it. ''I ain't sitting there and listening to that,'' he mutters on his way out. ''They're not going to take over my church.''</p>
        <p>And there waiting for him is Mr. Pugh, at 65 another white man of his generation, always with the same smart-alecky question. Never mind that Mr. Pugh and his wife, Janice, have themselves become uneasy about the direction of their church, that they have been quietly contemplating a walk of their own. ''Now, Roy,'' Mr. Pugh begins, stroking his seafarer's beard, ''what are you going to do when you get to heaven? Walk out of there, too?''</p>
        <p>Back inside, the ecstatic singing has ended, the speaking in tongues has melted into a chorus of hypnotic whispers and the members of the Tabernacle have been invited to roam the sea-foam carpet, welcoming visitors and greeting one another.</p>
        <p>They embrace, the white people and the black people, with long, earnest hugs. Eletia Frasier, a Guyanese immigrant, kisses all who come her way, whether she knows them or not. Brad Jackson wraps his thick white arms around Eugene Glenn, a slender black man, and jerks him cleanly off the ground.</p>
        <p>Ruben Burch, a 6-foot-7 black man whose blue usher's blazer is a tad short in the sleeves, saunters down the aisle with an irrepressible grin. During the Sunday fellowship, Mr. Burch makes a point of approaching older whites to gauge acceptance. Will they offer hugs, or merely handshakes? Will they linger, or recoil?</p>
        <p>Halfway down the aisle, he encounters Madge Mayo, the spry 85-year-old widow of a pastor from the Tabernacle's segregated days. She stands 4-foot-9 and keeps her luminescent white hair in a tight bun.</p>
        <p>There was a time when Mrs. Mayo could never have imagined hugging a black man, and even now she is not sure she approves of the integration of her church. But she has been touched by the bigheartedness of the Tabernacle's black members. And like so many of the whites who have stayed, she reasons that all believers are going to the same heaven, so they might as well get used to one another right here on earth.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Mayo sees Mr. Burch heading her way and trots a few steps toward him in her shiny black pumps. They smile fondly, and he bends at the waist to embrace her. She pats Mr. Burch on the back and presses her cheek against his, passing his test.</p>
        <p>It is a moment that would probably chafe some of his relatives, who feel that he and his wife, Vanessa, are compromising their blackness by attending ''the white church.'' But the Burches feel blessed by the blendedness of the Tabernacle.</p>
        <p>''Man,'' Mr. Burch reflects later, ''30 or 40 years ago I would have been hung for just touching this lady.''</p>
        <p>Praying Side by Side</p>
        <p>Sixteen miles east of downtown Atlanta, a vast granite monolith known as Stone Mountain looms over DeKalb County. Up on that mountain in 1915, the 20th-century Ku Klux Klan was born. And virtually in its shadow, the Tabernacle, all brick and glass and sharp angles, sits along Interstate 285 in the thick of the Atlanta sprawl.</p>
        <p>Nearly 50 years after the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. scolded Christians for making 11 a.m. Sunday the most segregated hour of the week, the Tabernacle is the rarest of religious institutions: a truly integrated church in a nation where 90 percent of all congregations are at least 80 percent one race. It is, to many of its 800 members, a slice of heaven on earth, a church whose spirituality is magnified by its multiracial character. What better evidence of God's presence, they reason, than the sight of whites and blacks praying side by side?</p>
        <p>And yet, the Tabernacle is not some liberal church like the one nearby that took down its white stained-glass Jesus and replaced him with a black one. It is deeply conservative, socially and theologically. What draws the Pughs and the Burches and so many others is the intensity of their Pentecostal faith, which teaches that the Holy Spirit can move in the lives of all believers, regardless of background.</p>
        <p>Pastor Roger W. Brumbalow's mission statement, displayed prominently in the lobby, challenges the congregation ''to be a multiracial, multicultural maturing body of believers,'' and, indeed, the church is blended in almost every way. Fifty-five percent of the members are white, 43 percent are black and the rest are Asian or racially mixed. Perhaps a third of the blacks are foreign born, and the church flies 36 flags to honor their homelands.</p>
        <p>The Tabernacle has had trouble integrating its eight-member pastoral staff, a legacy of the Assemblies of God's history as a white denomination. Its first black associate pastor resigned last fall after two years. Over the last 13 months, Pastor Brumbalow, who is white, filled two openings with white associate pastors before finally hiring a black youth pastor last month. The board of deacons, by contrast, has been integrated since 1994 and became majority black after elections in March.</p>
        <p>The choir is thoroughly mixed, and its praise-and-worship-style music falls comfortably between the traditional country hymns of white Pentecostalism and the thumping gospel funk of the modern black church. Pastor Gary Smith, the music minister, jokes that his choir would be faultless ''if we could just get the whites to clap on time and just get the blacks to be on time.''</p>
        <p>The congregation does not mix only in the pews. Blacks and whites visit each other in the hospital, share motel rooms at retreats and attend potluck dinners at one another's homes. They come together in kitchens and living rooms, forming circles of prayer around an ailing old man or a hopeful young couple, then laying hands on the supplicants' foreheads and shoulders. Visiting one another's suburban homes, with their manicured lawns and large-screen TV's, these accountants and teachers, nurses and software consultants discover the common threads of their middle-class lives.</p>
        <p>Yet for all the utopian imagery, for all the hope and faith that the congregation has moved beyond race, the life of the church is still driven by race in countless ways.</p>
        <p>Most everyone has made accommodations of some kind. The whites, mostly native Southerners, have been forced to confront their racial assumptions and cede some control over church governance and liturgy. The blacks have ventured from the safe harbor of the African-American church and, in many cases, have suppressed lifetimes of racial resentment and distrust.</p>
        <p>The little compromises can be detected any Sunday. They show in the frustration of some black members with the regimentation of the morning service, which opens with exactly 30 minutes of singing and usually lasts precisely two hours.</p>
        <p>''There are times when we're praising God and then they just cut it off,'' complains Robert Lawson. ''You can't do that. You can't put God in a box.''</p>
        <p>Some whites, meanwhile, dart glances at black churchgoers who they feel may be worshiping too exuberantly. They search for delicate words to explain.</p>
        <p>''In a lot of cases, the blacks are really more committed,'' says John F. Kellerman, a former deacon.</p>
        <p>''More outgoing,'' agrees his wife, Grace.</p>
        <p>''Where the whites are more reserved, you know,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Behind such concerns, though, is the question at the heart of the Tabernacle's future: Is the church simply enjoying a fleeting moment of integration on the way to becoming predominantly black? With the church growing rapidly and blacks joining at twice the rate of whites, the Tabernacle could tip, like those neighborhoods where blacks move in and whites eventually flee.</p>
        <p>The Tabernacle is a work in progress. But how far is it willing to go? And how much are the Burches, the Pughs and the others willing to concede in order to realize St. Paul's declaration that ''you are all one in Christ Jesus''?</p>
        <p>Making 'Colored' Friends</p>
        <p>On a chilly Saturday afternoon in January, a racially mixed crowd gathers at Howard and Janice Pugh's house for a catfish feast. They segregate quickly, of course. The men decamp to the garage, handicapping the Super Bowl and admiring Mr. Pugh's skill with the deep-fat fryer. The women settle in the sun room, swapping tales about the cold snap and the flu bug.</p>
        <p>When the group comes together for dinner, everyone laughs knowingly at Eugene Glenn's stories about his 16-year-old daughter's interest in buying a car and lack of interest in finding a job. Before long, the joshing turns to the male love affair with the channel changer and, eventually, to Mr. Pugh's vigilance in the church lobby. The guests tease their host about how he was spotted letting the youth pastor's wife cross the carpet with an open can of soda.</p>
        <p>''You're slipping, Howard,'' taunts William Turner, a black deacon.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' he chuckles, ''I'm getting soft.''</p>
        <p>As much as anyone, the Pughs have been transformed by the church's integration. Having lived most of their lives with little exposure to blacks, and little interest in gaining any, they now count blacks from the church among their closest friends.</p>
        <p>''My feeling before I got to know them was that there really wasn't that many good blacks out there,'' Mr. Pugh explains. ''After being around them and working with them, shoot, I don't even think about them as colored anymore.''</p>
        <p>Of course, Mr. Pugh's ''colored'' friends would prefer he use a synonym. But in his mind, his choice of words marks some progress. ''Hey, I've come a long way,'' he says. ''I don't say nigger anymore.''</p>
        <p>''That's right,'' his wife chimes in, ''they should see where you've come from.''</p>
        <p>Where they both came from were country churches in the piney woods of northwest Florida. When Howard was an infant, his mother would slide him under the bench so he wouldn't get trampled while they danced in the spirit. Janice was abandoned by her parents and raised by a grandmother who enforced a strict Pentecostal code: no smoking, no drinking, no dancing, no makeup, no short pants.</p>
        <p>They found each other 21 years ago via CB radio and began courting over a cup of truck-stop coffee. Mr. Pugh, a widower, could be gruff as an Alabama trooper. But he was also giving and good-hearted and a fine provider. She was pretty and sweet and recently divorced. She kept a Christian household and had no problem letting her husband be head of it. Even today, she cooks and cleans and lays out his clothes.</p>
        <p>''All he has to do is put them on,'' she says, rolling her eyes.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' he grins, sunk into his recliner, his toy poodle, Pepe, in his lap, ''all them guys at the church comes up to me and says, 'Boy, your wife dresses you nice.' ''</p>
        <p>After working for years in pulp mills, Mr. Pugh brought his bride to Atlanta 19 years ago and started a lucrative business pouring concrete in the ever-expanding suburbs. With its sizable black middle class and political structure, the city was a shock.</p>
        <p>The Pughs had come up in a strictly segregated culture. Mr. Pugh remembers having little childhood exposure to blacks, and during the civil rights movement he couldn't figure out what all the fuss was about. As far as he could tell, blacks had the same opportunities as he and other poor whites, even if they did have their own neighborhoods and schools.</p>
        <p>''I just wanted to stay on my side of the fence and for them to stay on theirs,'' he says. ''I never abused them. But they pretty much knew that I was white and they were niggers and we just ran our own way.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Pugh, 46, says she was never taught prejudice but recalls her grandmother's warning to avoid the black side of town. Her view of black men, she says, came from movies that portrayed them ''raping a white woman or something.''</p>
        <p>In Atlanta, she had to confront her fears. ''You'd turn the TV on and it's a black mayor and a black city council,'' she says. ''I'd say: 'Howard, where did you bring me? Are there any white people here?' ''</p>
        <p>When the Pughs joined in 1992, the Tabernacle was perhaps 10 percent black. They had never worshiped with blacks before. But the black folks tended to sit on the right side of the sanctuary, separated from the whites by a demilitarized zone of empty pews. ''We came at a good time,'' Mrs. Pugh recalls. ''There weren't so many of them that it was overwhelming. We could adjust.''</p>
        <p>The Burden of Blending In</p>
        <p>Last year, Ruben and Vanessa Burch moved into a new house with an orange-brick facade in a subdivision that is perhaps a third white. Determined to raise their two daughters in an integrated setting, the Burches had been impressed while house hunting that white neighbors had waved to them, a black couple, from their lawns.</p>
        <p>A week after the Pughs' fish fry, many of the same couples gathered for a house-blessing dinner at the Burches'. To the strumming of a guitar, the crowd welcomed the Holy Spirit into the airy two-story home. ''Come in today, come in to stay,'' they harmonized, ''come into my house, Lord Jesus.''</p>
        <p>Vanessa Burch, tall, slender and poised, handed out cups of olive oil, and the blacks and whites anointed doorknobs, bedposts and televisions with slick smudges of oil. The ceremony ended when the Burch family -- Ruben, Vanessa, 12-year-old Jessica and 7-year-old Gabrielle -- huddled in the center of the living room and surrendered to the prayers of their friends. The guests gave them a wall plaque, and little Gabby haltingly read, ''May the Lord bless this home and keep you in the company of angels.'' Then spaghetti was served.</p>
        <p>Like most black Southerners of their generation, the Burches have experienced their share of racism. Mr. Burch, 46, grew up in Albany, Ga., a stronghold of resistance to the civil rights movement. His wife, 40, grew up in Blakely, a south Georgia town whose high school still has separate homecoming queens and class reunions.</p>
        <p>Both remember ''colored only'' water fountains and parental warnings not to be caught on the white side of town after dark. Mrs. Burch still recalls the indignity of hearing white children call her mother by her first name. And then there was the day, perhaps 15 years ago, when her white boss in a South Carolina bank informed her that the one thing he hated was an ''uppity, educated nigger.''</p>
        <p>''It almost knocked me to my knees,'' says Mrs. Burch, then a teller at the bank. ''I walked off and went into the restroom and cried because it hurt me so bad.''</p>
        <p>The Burches reacted to all this in different ways. Mr. Burch, happy-go-lucky and confident to a fault, says he never grew  deeply bitter. His mother shielded him from the worst affronts, and when his high school integrated, he saw it as an opportunity to date white girls, discreetly. ''You knew how far to take it,'' he says. ''I mean, you wouldn't walk down Broadway holding somebody's hand.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Burch was more defiant. When her school desegregated, her white classmates learned that anyone who tossed a racial epithet her way was liable to go home with bruises. At age 12, she dressed down a white woman who had scolded her sick mother for sitting in the white section of a doctor's waiting room. ''After that,'' she says, ''Mama didn't take me too many times to the doctor's office.''</p>
        <p>Their experiences left both Burches, though, with a strong understanding that their world would be multiracial, and that schooling, diction and personality would be important tools in getting ahead. Those lessons were reinforced in the Navy, where Mr. Burch spent 22 years as a medic.</p>
        <p>In 1996 they moved to Atlanta, where he found work inspecting commercial waste-water systems. They looked for an Assemblies of God church and found the Tabernacle, then about 30 percent black. Before long they were fully involved, he as an usher, she as a Sunday school teacher and both as scout leaders.</p>
        <p>''I liked the diversity,'' says Mrs. Burch, an administrative assistant for a computer company. ''I wanted my children to grow up with differences in a church so they could see that whenever they went to heaven it wasn't going to be all black and it wasn't going to be all white. It was going to be mixed.''</p>
        <p>A 'Walk With the Lord'</p>
        <p>When the Tabernacle was founded, in 1916, it was most definitely not mixed. And it remained that way through most of its history, moving twice to escape the migration of blacks into its neighborhood. In the 1940's it affiliated with the Assemblies of God, a historically segregationist Pentecostal denomination. But ultimately, the church could outrun neither the changing demographics of postsegregation Atlanta nor some stark fiscal realities.</p>
        <p>Shortly before the Pughs arrived, an unmanageable mortgage put the congregation in debt. To dig out, the church called as its senior pastor Coy Barker, a onetime rodeo rider, and agreed to pay him 25 percent of tithes and offerings. With a financial incentive to fill the pews, Pastor Barker tapped the most readily available market -- the middle-class blacks flocking into the area.</p>
        <p>By 1984, when the church's current building was completed, the surrounding suburbs were in the midst of a stunning transformation. In 1970 there was one black among the 11,000 residents in the church's census tract. Twenty years later, two-thirds of the residents were black.</p>
        <p>Pastor Barker, a typecast televangelist with silver hair, flashy jewelry and a black Lincoln Town Car, had a high-stepping style that mimicked the traditional black preacher. By the time he was forced out in 1993, in the throes of a messy divorce, the church was perhaps 20 percent black and on the road to financial recovery.</p>
        <p>Predictably, some whites left. Susan Carithers, a member since birth, could never quite accept integration as God's will. Her husband grew agitated, she says, because ''he just didn't want black boys sniffing up to his daughter.'' They left in 1996, shortly after a black man gave Mrs. Carithers a big hug during a Sunday service.</p>
        <p>The Pughs could also have left, but they liked Pastor Brumbalow's preaching and their son's participation in the youth group. And as they got to know black members, they found they liked them, too. A lot.</p>
        <p>The black churchgoers did not fit the Pughs' stereotypes. Mr. Pugh noticed that they did not loll around or always have their hands out like the black men who smooth his concrete, the ones he calls ''the boys.''</p>
        <p>Even today he draws distinctions between his black employees and his black church friends. Sometimes he cannot recall his workers' last names, though they have been with him for years. He says that he occasionally has to bail one out of jail, and that if he drives around a corner fast enough he will catch some lounging.</p>
        <p>But he admires the blacks at the Tabernacle. They work hard and dress well, often better than the whites, and live in two-story houses on well-tended lanes. ''As I began to be around them a lot more,'' he says, ''I saw that there was a lot more of them trying to benefit themselves.''</p>
        <p>The Pughs held cookouts and invited mixed crowds, disregarding, even slightly savoring, their white neighbors' stares. On Saturday mornings Mr. Pugh would round up a crew of church men, white and black, to go paint a widow's house or serve soup to the homeless. One Easter the Pughs took their black friends Paul and Rudine Hardy to an all-white club for dinner.</p>
        <p>''Oh, my God, it was so funny,'' Mrs. Hardy says. ''I said: 'Janice, Janice. These people are all just looking.' They had all this fancy food, and every time I chewed they was just looking.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Pugh sometimes gets weepy talking about her deep kinship with Mrs. Hardy and other black women from church. She feels connected to them spiritually and turns to them when she needs prayer.</p>
        <p>As she has learned about the bigotry they face, she has come to empathize. It isn't guilt exactly. She doesn't feel she owes black people anything. After all, her life hasn't been so easy either. But she understands, and that is something new.</p>
        <p>''When I moved to Atlanta,'' she says, ''I had never had any occasion to know what these people were going through. I'd never had anyone come up to me and say, 'I was treated this way because I was black.' When you hear someone say that, with tears in their eyes, you know they just want to be loved. And I guess I connected with them because I was the same way when I was a little girl. All I wanted was to be loved.''</p>
        <p>As she sees it, God is using the Tabernacle's integration to test ''whether you move on in your walk with the Lord.''</p>
        <p>Her husband's walk has been less steady. He remains capable of offending black friends even as he beckons them into his life. They recognize that he has come a long way, that he has a good heart. But they also suspect that he continues to use the word ''colored,'' often to their faces, to make it clear that he, not they, will define the terms of their relationships.</p>
        <p>''It's a control thing,'' Mrs. Pugh says. ''He wants people to know that he still knows the difference.''</p>
        <p>Last August, one of Mr. Pugh's black friends decided to confront him, fearing newcomers might be put off by his ways as head usher. But the man later backed down. Don't major in minor, his wife had advised him. ''I do value my friendship with Howard and Janice,'' the man reasoned, ''and if it's my friendship with them versus this, it's really very insignificant.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burch reacted much the same way at a retreat last year, when Mr. Pugh told him a joke, the one about the black guy who moved next door to the white guy:</p>
        <p>The white man was leaning over his fence as his new neighbor mowed the yard. With each pass, the black neighbor taunted the white man, ''I'm better than you are, I'm better than you are.'' Exasperated, the white man finally asked, ''What makes you so much better than me?'' And the black man replied, ''I don't have a nigger living next to me.''</p>
        <p>''Old Ruben just about fell out,'' Mr. Pugh remembers. ''He didn't have a problem with it.'' And, in fact, Mr. Burch says he didn't have much of a problem with it, though he was surprised Mr. Pugh felt comfortable enough to tell him the joke. ''That's just Howard,'' he told himself. He let the moment pass, thinking that Mr. Pugh was like an old car, sputtering down the highway: ''You just say, 'Well, this is just an old car smoking and we'll go ahead and pass it and one day it'll give out and be gone.' ''</p>
        <p>What the Relatives Say</p>
        <p>The Burches may want to make sure, as Mrs. Burch puts it, that their girls don't grow up ''in an all one-race anything.'' But when it comes to their choice of church, they have been wounded by second-guessing from their relatives, particularly Mr. Burch's sister Jacalyn Ray. It has become personal, and at times ugly.</p>
        <p>''It's a wannabe thing,'' says Mrs. Ray, who attends a black church. Her sister-in-law, she thinks, is too eager to make white friends and entertain them in her home. ''Some people don't know who they are and have to go somewhere to validate themselves. She doesn't feel comfortable being black.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Burch cannot figure out what she did to provoke Mrs. Ray, other than marry her brother. But other family members, while more tactful, do not fully reject Mrs. Ray's assessment. Mr. Burch's half-brother Frederick Caldwell has long noticed that Mr. Burch feels most comfortable in interracial settings.</p>
        <p>''I think of Rick as my white brother,'' he laughs, using a nickname. ''He has Caucasian features. Not facial features, but he has a white body type. He can't dance. He'll wear plaid pants. He played on the tennis team in school. He's a Newt Gingrich fan. I wouldn't necessarily say he wants to be white, but he has opinions not normally associated with a black man in the United States.''</p>
        <p>The relatives say they are also concerned that the Burches may be sending their daughters mixed signals. ''I do know with Jessica there's kind of a working out of who she is,'' Mr. Caldwell says. ''My concern for Gabrielle and Jessica is that they have a healthy respect for who they are.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burch concedes some concern that his daughters may be too colorblind, that a life without overt discrimination has left them with little racial identity. Someday, he fears, an act of bigotry will shatter their naivete.</p>
        <p>Still, he resents the suggestion that he and his family prefer integration because they want to be white. He is comfortable with who he is. ''I enjoy me,'' he says. ''And I feel if you don't know me you're missing out.'' As for his sister, he says: ''She's not in touch with reality. I mean, how do we want to be white? Because we want different things, want to live in different neighborhoods? No, she's totally wrong. I think it's a chemical imbalance.''</p>
        <p>Jessica, tall and outgoing like her parents and engagingly mature for her age, acknowledges inner conflict over racial identity. But it is not that she rejects her blackness or wants to be white. Rather, it is that she feels torn between her parents' insistence on living an integrated life and her black peers' suspicion of anyone who does.</p>
        <p>Her parents insist that she and her sister speak ''proper English'' and scold them gently if they slip into black slang. But her classmates tease her relentlessly for her speech and for having white friends, and sometimes she cannot resist the pressure.</p>
        <p>''I do talk improper English, or ebonics, with black friends,'' she admits. ''Maybe I think they'll pick on me if I don't.''</p>
        <p>Two years ago, she decided to drop her white friends to placate the black ones. But she felt distracted, her grades suffered and she concluded that God was not pleased.</p>
        <p>''I finally told myself that it doesn't matter what they think about me, it doesn't matter what color I hang out with,'' she says. ''I have too much respect for who I am.''</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, Vanessa Burch is annoyed by her daughter's problems and her in-laws' carping. But it has all made her think.</p>
        <p>''I think long and hard about it to see, you know, could this really be true,'' she says. ''And then I go and ask other people, 'Do you think I try to be white?' And they're like: 'What? No. You couldn't be if you wanted to.' It used to really weigh on me and I used to pray about it. 'Lord, what is it? Show me. If I'm doing something to make people see me like this, show me.' ''</p>
        <p>It hasn't come. People just don't understand, she says, that she is motivated by pragmatism, not racial treason. The reality is that her daughter will face a white world, with certain rules for getting ahead.</p>
        <p>''I know that being black is one strike against us,'' she says, ''and in the business world, where she's going to have to compete, being a woman is two against her. So I want her to have enough education that they can't resist her. I want her, when she gets up to speak, that they're like, 'Wow, who is that?' And believe me, voice and articulation get attention.''</p>
        <p>She is trying, she says, to help her daughters realize that there are no limits, that the restraints and prejudices of her own youth have been lifted. They can do anything, live anywhere, even someplace more extravagant than their new three-bedroom house.</p>
        <p>''You want to live in that house on the hill over there,'' she challenges them, ''you can live there. You have the same rights as the next person before you, beside you, behind you, around you. All of you can do the same thing. Once upon a time we couldn't. But now we can.''</p>
        <p>A Colorblindness Test</p>
        <p>There was little chance that the Burches and Pughs would miss the wedding of Dorothea Lemon and Curtis Lockridge last June. It was to be the Tabernacle's first big interracial ceremony, and as Madge Mayo explained it, ''Something is about to happen that we haven't all fully digested.''</p>
        <p>The bride, 43 and black, and the groom, 58 and white, had both recently been widowed. The two couples had been friendly at church, and Mr. Lockridge and Mrs. Lemon comforted each other through their grief. Before long, they were holding hands through the Sunday service and scribbling notes on the church bulletin.</p>
        <p>''I luv you, Curtis,'' she would write.</p>
        <p>''I'm glad,'' he would respond.</p>
        <p>It raised some eyebrows when Pastor Brumbalow announced their engagement. One elderly white lady asked if Scripture permitted mixed marriages, and he told her there was no prohibition. Blacks and whites asked if it was wrong to want their children to marry within their races. He said it wasn't, and made a point of telling the men's group that he was not encouraging interracial dating.</p>
        <p>The afternoon of the wedding, Vanessa Burch slid into a pew toward the back. ''What are these people thinking?'' she remembered wondering. ''How many are going to be in an uproar, and how many aren't going to be back?''</p>
        <p>Howard Pugh recognized that the couple were grownups and could do as they pleased. But interracial relationships just went against his upbringing.</p>
        <p>''Oh, Lord,'' he thought as the bride walked down the aisle. But by the end of the afternoon, Mr. Pugh could not help smiling. The couple looked awfully cute, and very much in love. The ceremony had been elegant, the reception lavish. ''I'll tell you the truth,'' he said. ''I haven't seen many white folks' weddings put on like that.''</p>
        <p>Still, some remained uneasy. ''The thing that worries me most,'' said Madge Mayo, ''is that this is going to turn things loose for the young people and it's going to get, I shouldn't say entangled, but I'd just say more mixed.''</p>
        <p>Sense and Sensitivity</p>
        <p>What Janice Pugh cannot understand, despite her newfound empathy, is why black folks remain obsessed with race, why they can't just let it all go. She and Rudine Hardy talk about it from time to time, sitting on a green leather couch outside the sanctuary. Mrs. Hardy will wonder why the pastoral staff is so white, and Mrs. Pugh will bristle.</p>
        <p>''You need to stop being so sensitive about all this,'' she will say.</p>
        <p>''You don't understand,'' Mrs. Hardy will respond. ''You're not black.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not black, and I never will be black,'' she will answer. ''I just think there are other issues out there that you have to be concerned about that have nothing to do with race.''</p>
        <p>She thinks about it often. The church should be about love, and love should know no color. ''If I were in their shoes,'' she says, ''I would take the attitude that the past is past. You have to go on, and the blacks now, this is the time for them. They're more accepted now.''</p>
        <p>Because the Tabernacle is an island, and a refuge, it is often hard to accept that racial tensions lie just beneath the surface, vulnerable to exposure from the slightest scratch. But the island is in the world, and in the world there is no refuge.</p>
        <p>Kathy Watson, a children's pastor, learned that lesson when she was rebuked by a black parent for referring affectionately to her toddlers as ''monkeys.'' Another youth pastor got an earful about a Bible lesson that equated the color black with sin.</p>
        <p>But those flare-ups do not rival what happened last summer with the Homebuilders, a Sunday school class for couples. Until two years ago it was led by a white couple, and attendance was predominantly white. Then Enefiok Umana, a deacon from Nigeria, and his wife, Eno, assumed the leadership, and the class became overwhelmingly black.</p>
        <p>Many blacks concluded that whites were simply unwilling to submit to black leadership. And their suspicions were stoked one August morning when two associate pastors interrupted class to introduce a white couple as leaders of a Bible study being started for younger couples. One pastor, Ray Martin, added that the Homebuilders would come under the new class's ''umbrella.''</p>
        <p>After church, the blacks huddled in the parking lot and burned up the phone lines. Some wrote in protest. The implication was clear, they felt. The church was starting a white class for those unwilling to attend the black-led class. And the bit about the umbrella really set them off.</p>
        <p>''It was like a kick in the behind to me,'' said Mrs. Hardy.</p>
        <p>Pastor Brumbalow ate lunch at William and Lula Turner's house that day. And as they told him of the discontent many blacks were feeling, the pastor started to weep and vowed that the Enemy -- meaning the Devil -- would not divide his flock. But he had to leave town the next day, and the flames raged on.</p>
        <p>The associate pastors were flabbergasted by the reaction and wounded that the blacks could think there was racial intent. ''I really thought they were a little further down the healing curve,'' Pastor Martin said. ''It let me know that we're dealing with people that still have some wounds.''</p>
        <p>In conversations with class members, Pastor Martin acknowledged that the word ''umbrella'' had left the wrong impression. What he had meant, he said, was simply that the two classes would be parallel ministries that would occasionally come together for functions.</p>
        <p>When Pastor Brumbalow returned, he took charge of damage control, delaying the new class to let emotions calm. The next night, though exhausted from his trip, he made a point of attending a Homebuilders potluck dinner.</p>
        <p>Still, when the new class finally began, it was attended mostly by whites. And when the new group held a retreat, only one Homebuilders couple chose to attend.</p>
        <p>When to Preach on Race</p>
        <p>Two Sundays after the Homebuilders incident, Pastor Brumbalow did something he had hardly ever done. He preached about race. ''I don't normally get this blunt,'' he began, slapping his hands for punctuation, ''but I will get this blunt this morning.''</p>
        <p>''I want to say to you of color and you that are white'' -- he was screeching like the brakes on a train -- ''that if you look at a person based on the color of their skin and you evaluate them right then and there, then, my friend, you have missed the purpose of the love of God.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, he said, it takes a while to catch on -- to comprehend that God is working a miracle at the Tabernacle so people might have a glimpse of heaven. ''When I look across this congregation,'' he said, ''I understand what God is doing. I understand the eternal kingdom.''</p>
        <p>Pastor Brumbalow recognizes that not everyone was brought up that way. In fact, he wasn't brought up that way. Growing up near Atlanta, he didn't really know any blacks, and he wasn't particularly godly. It was only after some wild days as a rock guitarist with a band called Completely Souled Out that he found God and his future wife, Becky, at a Pentecostal revival. He left shortly for Vietnam, where he won decorations for heroism.</p>
        <p>His previous pulpit, in suburban New Orleans, had few blacks. And yet, at 50, he has managed and accelerated the Tabernacle's integration with considerable skill. Both races trust him like a parent and admire his evenhandedness, political instincts and common touch.</p>
        <p>''He'll drink out of the same glass,'' Mr. Burch says. ''That's the kind of feeling I get from him, you know, that I'm not higher than you.''</p>
        <p>He is a gifted preacher, fashioning sermons that are neither inaccessibly erudite nor insultingly shallow. But he prefers, he says, not to preach about race. He would rather lead by example, embracing each in his flock with the same tenderness, blessing each with the same prayers, accepting dinner invitations from all.</p>
        <p>''I think the pitfall of having a blended church is when you make race the issue,'' he says. ''What we're doing here as a church is not about race, and if we make that the emphasis then we miss the bigger picture. Our main goal is to reconcile people to God.''</p>
        <p>He would never say it, and maybe doesn't even let himself think it, but there is another reason not to make race the issue. To preserve the Tabernacle's fragile balance, he must reach out to newcomers without alienating old-timers like the Pughs.</p>
        <p>The blacks at the Tabernacle were jubilant about the pastor's race sermon. And the Pughs, like many of the whites, had no real problem with its content. But that he delivered the sermon at all rubbed them the wrong way. He was playing to the crowd, they felt, or at least to part of it.</p>
        <p>From time to time, the Pughs had discussed looking at other churches. The Tabernacle was a long drive from home. Now they shared this gnawing sense that race was beginning to supplant God's love as its driving force.</p>
        <p>''What would cause me to leave,'' Mrs. Pugh said, ''is for them to constantly have a platform on the black issue, to always talk about race, and not let the Holy Spirit lead us.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, though, Pastor Brumbalow says, God just lays a message on his heart and he can't shake it loose. It happened again in February, when, voice quavering, he read Dr. King's ''I Have a Dream'' speech and prophesied that the Tabernacle would become a beacon for others.</p>
        <p>''God is saying, 'I am going to prepare you to be a light, to be an example to the city of Atlanta and to the state of Georgia,' '' he said. ''I want to tell you, God has a dream and his dream is being fulfilled in this house this morning in the name of the Lord. Hallelujah!''</p>
        <p>The Pughs would have preferred a different topic. ''He keeps bringing it up and bringing it up,'' Mr. Pugh said. ''With this race deal, once a year is adequate, not every other Sunday.''</p>
        <p>Several weeks later the Pughs visited another church.</p>
        <p>A Delicate Balance</p>
        <p>If the Burches and other black leaders at the Tabernacle have a complaint, it is with the level of diversity in the staff. They do not always protest publicly, fearing they might break the spell of racial good will. But they are always watching and counting. All you have to do, they say, is look at last year's Christmas card photograph of ''the Tabernacle team,'' 19 red-sweatered staff members, every last one of them white.</p>
        <p>And yet when positions have opened, black deacons have chosen not to lobby Pastor Brumbalow to fill them with blacks. They recognize, they say, that the task is not easy. The Assemblies of God is still virtually all white, with fewer than 400 blacks among its 32,000 licensed ministers. And because Pastor Brumbalow holds a statewide leadership position with the Assemblies, it might be considered bad form to hire from outside the denomination.</p>
        <p>Even before last month's success, he had searched assiduously for black prospects, knowing that ''it would certainly speak volumes that I pretty much practice what I preach.'' In several instances he let the congregation know that he had offered jobs to black prospects, only to be rebuffed. That seemed to satisfy his black constituents.</p>
        <p>''He interviewed black people and they turned it down, so what can you do?'' Mr. Burch said after one such search.</p>
        <p>In general, black members suspect that it may not take much to upset the racial equilibrium of the church. Ultimately, they assume, it will come down to power. If black numbers increase to where whites feel disenfranchised, whites will leave, they predict.</p>
        <p>For the moment, the pastors feel they must move incrementally. That was never clearer than in the planning of last year's Christmas pageant.</p>
        <p>Like other blacks, Ruben Burch had long noticed that blacks had never been cast as Joseph, Mary or Jesus. The whites, he assumed, would have a fit. ''Boy, if they figure out there was a black Jesus they probably wouldn't want to go to heaven,'' he joked.</p>
        <p>Pastor Smith, the music minister, badly wanted to break that color barrier. He knew that Scripture was largely silent about Jesus' appearance and that various cultures portrayed him in their own images. But he, too, was unsure if the older whites were ready for an ebony Jesus.</p>
        <p>So he devised a scheme to soft-pedal the racial transformation of Christ. He selected for the lead roles Stephen and Sobrina Smith, a light-skinned multiracial couple who happened to have a newborn son, Joshua. Mrs. Smith, born in Trinidad, is part African, Chinese, East Indian, Hispanic and South American Indian. Her husband, a New Yorker, is part Italian, Polish, black, Jewish and Native American.</p>
        <p>The pastor theorized that if he could sell the Smiths, he could cast darker-skinned blacks in future years. ''The first time it shouldn't be such a shock,'' he said. ''They're not as dark. They're sort of a medium.''</p>
        <p>The pageant went off without a hitch, down to the triumphant finale, when an adult Christ figure, adorned with a crown and scarlet cloak, rode into the sanctuary on a stocky white horse. Mrs. Smith was fetching as Mary, dressed in a blue satin robe and a white shawl, cradling Joshua as her husband knelt nearby. Mr. Burch, playing a wise man, watched on bended knee.</p>
        <p>Pastor Smith could not have been more pleased. He received lots of compliments and not a single comment about the racial makeup of the cast, which was how he wanted it. Most white members, if they noticed at all, reacted about the way the Pughs did, with a shrug.</p>
        <p>''I think the white people have been shocked so many times that it doesn't make any difference anymore,'' Mrs. Pugh said. ''They just say, 'Well, that's the way it is now.' ''</p>
        <p>Even the Smiths, told later that they had been selected for their complexion, said they didn't mind too much, so long as it helped move the church forward. And yet the whole experience made them wonder.</p>
        <p>''If we are an integrated church, as we claim to be,'' Mrs. Smith asked, ''why do we still have to go through hoops and loops to make a point and get a message across and pacify certain people and keep waves from starting? If we're still playing around with this, then maybe we're not really who we say we are.''</p>
        <p>HOW RACE IS LIVED IN AMERICA</p>
        <p>Two generations after the end of legal discrimination, race still ignites political debates -- over Civil War flags, for example, or police profiling. But the wider public discussion of race relations seems muted by a full-employment economy and by a sense, particularly among many whites, that the time of large social remedies is past. Race relations are being defined less by political action than by daily experience, in schools, in sports arenas, in pop culture and at worship, and especially in the workplace. These encounters -- race relations in the most literal, everyday sense -- make up this series of reports, the outcome of a yearlong examination by a team of Times reporters.</p>
        <p>This series will continue intermittently over the next six weeks and conclude with a special issue of The New York Times Magazine on July 16.</p>
        <p>The articles in this series can also be read at The New York Times on the Web. The site offers forums in which visitors can discuss the articles and the racial issues in their own lives and respond to a questionnaire. Photo essays, video and audio presentations -- including comments by people from around the nation -- and lesson plans from The Learning Network are also available:</p>
        <p>www.nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
