<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Americans Aren't in the Market for Freedom</title>
    <meta content="04CONT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE CONTRARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Akst, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Contrary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0DB133CF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Americans Aren't in the Market for Freedom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL AKST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Akst, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Akst, On the Contrary column, suggests American consumers, formerly known as 'people,' might be able to quit an unrewarding job and live a more fulfilling life if they would save more and perhaps live a little more modestly; finds current record-high level of personal indebtedness indicates few consumers are interested in buying financial freedom; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERYWHERE you turn nowadays, somebody is trying to sell you something. And why not? The American economy is churning out unprecedented prosperity, and consumers (the creatures formerly known as ''people'') are snapping up vacation houses, fancy cars and other nifty appurtenances of the good life.</p>
        <p>Folks are entitled to enjoy their earnings, after all. And why should anyone attend social critics who, from their tasteful vacation houses in Amagansett, berate the masses for buying his-and-hers Barcaloungers?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERYWHERE you turn nowadays, somebody is trying to sell you something. And why not? The American economy is churning out unprecedented prosperity, and consumers (the creatures formerly known as ''people'') are snapping up vacation houses, fancy cars and other nifty appurtenances of the good life.</p>
        <p>Folks are entitled to enjoy their earnings, after all. And why should anyone attend social critics who, from their tasteful vacation houses in Amagansett, berate the masses for buying his-and-hers Barcaloungers?</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the one thing nobody is insisting you rush out and buy is freedom. Ever hear of it? I don't mean freedom of speech or religion, which we enjoy in spades. I mean the freedom to do what you want -- including, if necessary, telling your boss to drop dead. For non-lottery winners,  it's the kind of freedom that comes of thrift, and maybe also self-knowledge.</p>
        <p>What I'm suggesting, in other words, is to forget that big new professional-quality range or $40,000 sport utility vehicle and buy yourself some freedom; you really can, because it's a commodity just like any other.</p>
        <p>In a two-earner household, for instance, maybe one of you can quit and go back to school, or even see the kids once in awhile. Save enough and perhaps live a little more modestly, and you might be able to ditch that lucrative but unworthy gig you've been slaving at all these years and do something you believe in -- teach school, start a business, move to the country, join the Elks. Read a book, for Pete's sake.</p>
        <p>The current boom comes at a steep price. Cell phones, pagers, e-mail and other technological tethers keep us on our toes at all hours. Those who hand out Internet freebies insist that you pay with your privacy. Even the dot-com elite find themselves bound by so-called golden handcuffs: They can't leave until their options vest, and now that investors are showing signs of coming to their senses about Internet valuations, it may all be for naught anyway.</p>
        <p>At a time when more people than ever have the opportunity to do what they want in life, many lack the imagination to do anything but accumulate possessions. Freedom is losing market share to stuff.</p>
        <p>Why? One possibility is that freedom has a marketing problem. All the other stuff is hawked day and night in commercials suggesting that a product will somehow make you more free rather than less. Yet freedom itself goes unpromoted.</p>
        <p>This woeful lack of advertising for America's very best product means relatively few people know about it, at least judging by consumer behavior. Easy credit and record-high personal indebtedness mean that, despite rising affluence, lots of people still owe their souls to what amounts to the company store. ''Money is coined liberty,'' Dostoyevski rightly observed long ago.</p>
        <p>People who make pronouncements like that are usually well-fixed in the things department; the poor regrettably don't have the option of blithely giving up some of their income to change their lives. Besides, Americans really like all the stuff they buy, even deriving a sense of identity from it. Yet many of us are so rich that we need not give up much material well-being to become a whole lot freer to do what we want to do.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Americans aren't in the market for more freedom because they already enjoy an extraordinary degree of personal liberty, by global and historical standards. It's odd that we aren't any happier, though. Maybe we have too much of some kinds of freedom and too little of others.</p>
        <p>Recognizing that money buys freedom (if not love) might change the way you look at all you make and spend. If you're smart, it will induce you to save more. It might also challenge you to think about what you're doing with your life. Then again, money has always heavily taxed the imagination. In this day of unbacked currency and electronic balances, the whole concept requires a leap of collective faith.</p>
        <p>Maybe that's the reason there's so little call for more material freedom in this country. More than anything else you buy, freedom demands that you do something with it. It's not something to tuck away in the garage or unload a few years later on ebay. When someone asks, ''Free to do what?'' the answer doesn't always come easily. But when you're lucky enough to live in a time and place like this one, perhaps that's your real job -- not making the money, but figuring out what you ought to achieve with it.</p>
        <p>ON THE CONTRARY Daniel Akst's column tilts at conventional business wisdom and appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daniel Akst's column tilts at conventional business wisdom and appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
