<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Updated Refrains of the 60's As Dissenters Hit the Streets</title>
    <meta content="Y31PRO$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219121"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE CAST AND THE CONFLICTS -- THE PROTESTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DB133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1092" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Updated Refrains of the 60's As Dissenters Hit the Streets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rich assortment of several thousand dissenters dominate eve of Republican National Convention in Philadelphia; stage orderly but at times rambunctuous demonstration in city, giving pause to Republican conventioneers intent on decorum; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Devotees of lively political protest, a fading art in recent decades, had something to cheer for and against today as an eclectic, ragtag assortment of causes snaked and howled through the heart of this city, giving pause to Republican conventioneers intent on decorum.</p>
        <p>A rich assortment of several thousand dissenters -- all of them orderly, many rambunctious -- dominated the eve of the convention as marchers consciously sought to revive some old-time 60's rhythms and jingles, but with strategic updating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Devotees of lively political protest, a fading art in recent decades, had something to cheer for and against today as an eclectic, ragtag assortment of causes snaked and howled through the heart of this city, giving pause to Republican conventioneers intent on decorum.</p>
        <p>A rich assortment of several thousand dissenters -- all of them orderly, many rambunctious -- dominated the eve of the convention as marchers consciously sought to revive some old-time 60's rhythms and jingles, but with strategic updating.</p>
        <p>''Hey, hey! Ho, ho!'' began one group, a generation removed from the old ''L.B.J.'' punch line, who bellowed a coda edited for current events: ''H.M.O. has got to go!''</p>
        <p>''What do we want?'' came one marching question. And the answer (''Freedom!'' in the old days) came back: ''Health care!''</p>
        <p>For all the altered stakes, veteran witnesses of the antiwar demonstrations of the 60's felt a pang of nostalgia. Particularly when guerrilla-theater demonstrators capered past with large papier-mache heads of piggish plutocrats and Darth Vader caricatures of politicians. Chanting denunciations of corporate wealth and the two-party system, they happily rose to the bait of a few fundamentalist Christian counterdemonstrators lobbing bullhorn taunts from the sideline.</p>
        <p>''Hey, environmentalists, get a life!'' boomed John Franklin, wielding a printed billboard that judgment day was near. ''God will take care of the trees, then he'll take care of you on the Last Day, for all the clear-cutting of babies,'' he said, mixing the abortion issue in for good measure.</p>
        <p>The marchers offered as good as they got, several offering an obscene blend of gesture and advice. Mr. Franklin, a 58-year-old veteran of varied protests of the 60's, admitted later in an interview: ''At least the kids are trying, scratching away, although they don't quite have it. It's like watching a cartoon, but it's nostalgic. They're trying.''</p>
        <p>Arms outstretched, Michelle Christedes intervened as a peaceful parade monitor between the caustic Mr. Franklin and an unshaven young man in a sundress who drew tension-tinged laughter in impishly shouting contentions about the sexuality of Jesus.</p>
        <p>But the peace was maintained. Other causes strutted by: opposition to the death penalty, to sweatshops, to the antimissile defense movement and a score more, many of them clearly pressed by crowds of galvanized young people.</p>
        <p>''I've been waiting for them a long time,'' said Ms. Christedes, a 53-year-old psychology consultant who said she felt some of the fury and swagger of her youth when she marched against the war in Vietnam as a Ph.D. candidate at the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>''The old me generation sold out,'' she said, hoping for better. Not all the evidence was encouraging. One young man, dressed melodramatically in the black garb and red bandanna of the self-styled anarchists, brandished a bottle of Gatorade and a cell phone on his way to the rhetorical ramparts.</p>
        <p>Safely beyond all sight and sound of the demonstrators, Rand S. Larson, a convention delegate, sipped a rum and diet cola at a new oasis in town, the Ritz-Carlton bar, which just opened in a palatial six-story marble bank building on Broad Street.</p>
        <p>''I've not seen any of the protest,'' said Mr. Larson, a first-time delegate from Richmond, Vt., who sported a bright ''V.I.P.'' tag atop his necklace of credentials. ''I don't really fear any trouble from the demonstrators, although my wife and 11-year-old son are coming down and I hope they have a good, safe time,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Larson savored his drink after working for days to tamp down dissension as a member of the party platform committee. ''We dealt with all the right issues in a climate of respect,'' he insisted of a platform smooth as a runway for the candidates' landing.</p>
        <p>As a man strolled past the bar with one of the day's least contentious T-shirts (''Dartmouth Fall Foliage Squash Tournament''), the Ritz's Sunday brunchers seemed all gentled out and ready to convene, far removed from the dissenting crowd on the other side of City Hall.</p>
        <p>Once outside, however, Joe Bramante, a freelance Democrat from Derry, N.H., bearded delegates with a big, bluff hello, then asked, ''So, how's the economy?'' Before Republicans could answer, Mr. Bramante spun a hand-printed sign on its stanchion: ''I am Bill Clinton's Number One Fan!'' And he told each of them about the booming economy as they sought escape.</p>
        <p>Farther east in the city, tourists approaching the Liberty Bell were distracted by a display of hundreds of pairs of shoes lined up as part of the Silent March demonstration, the empty shoes representing the thousands killed annually with handguns.  A barefoot, grandmotherly woman walked stolidly past, bearing her own printed protest: ''Too angry, too female to vote Republican.''</p>
        <p>The day's larger march of dissenters presented a gathering of various causes, from NOW to the N.A.A.C.P., from folk-singing unionists to animal rights demonstrators, under an umbrella label called Unity 2000. Some self-proclaimed student anarchists marched amiably with the larger parade, but they have hinted they may try to act up by midweek with some hit-and-run street initiatives.</p>
        <p>''So far so good,'' said Police Commissioner John F. Timoney, who has been darting between demonstrations as a member of the police bike patrol in helmet, shorts and monogrammed ''P.C.'' shirt. ''But it's early and you never get cocky,'' he said, noting that other marches potentially more troublesome begin on Monday. ''We can work out deals, even if we don't quite like the deals,'' the commissioner said in emphasizing flexibility as his chief weapon for getting through convention week.</p>
        <p>This was demonstrated on Saturday evening as the police quickly put aside confrontation and became escorts of an ad hoc march of 200 teenagers who showed up on Chestnut Street loudly devoted to the cause of virginity. ''Free sex kills!'' they warned. ''Honk if you're a virgin!'' they pleaded as restaurantgoers stared from sidewalk cafes for a passing moment before turning back to their food.</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE CAST AND THE CONFLICTS -- THE PROTESTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
