<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="31FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E4DA133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Venezuelan President Wins Expanded Powers  Venezuelans granted President Hugo Chavez, a former paratrooper, a new six-year term with enhanced powers, top officials said. Mr. Chavez has promised to use his time in power to sweep away the last remnants of the traditional political order in the nation of 23 million that in recent years has been the United States' top oil supplier.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Reprieve For Barak  It appeared that Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel would be able to keep his battered government afloat for the next three months, thanks to complex back-room maneuvering on the eve of a no-confidence vote in Parliament.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Venezuelan President Wins Expanded Powers  Venezuelans granted President Hugo Chavez, a former paratrooper, a new six-year term with enhanced powers, top officials said. Mr. Chavez has promised to use his time in power to sweep away the last remnants of the traditional political order in the nation of 23 million that in recent years has been the United States' top oil supplier.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Reprieve For Barak  It appeared that Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel would be able to keep his battered government afloat for the next three months, thanks to complex back-room maneuvering on the eve of a no-confidence vote in Parliament.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Reports from all sides say Jewish settlers living in and around Hebron will be among those left under Palestinian rule in any final peace pact. There is a powerful element of poignancy to the settlers' plight and the choice they will have to make.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Shoring Up Belgrade Opposition  American officials are reportedly putting strong pressure on the president of Montenegro and the leader of Serbia's largest opposition party to take part in Yugoslav elections. They said a united opposition could defeat President Slobodan Milosevic.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Emergency Stop for a Concorde  A British Airways Concorde flight from London to New York had to make an emergency stop in Canada after passengers complained about a smell of gasoline in the cabin, the airline said. Officials in Paris investigating the Concorde flight that crashed on Tuesday said the flames spewing out of the aircraft most likely came from a major fuel leak.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Disputed Treasure Off Greece  Greek and French divers will try to salvage what they hope is a fortune off the southwest Peloponnesus. The wealth was reputedly stripped from Jews sent to labor and death camps during World War II. But a long line of claimants is already jostling for their stakes.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Another Crisis for Japan Leader  Dealing another blow to Prime Minister Yoshiro Mori's wobbly government, Kimitaka Kuze, left, the head of the agency charged with overhauling Japan's faltering financial system, resigned in the face of a scandal over his relationship with one of Japan's largest financial institutions.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Difficult Asylum Case for U.S.  The United States delayed a decision on the request for political asylum by Zhang Hongbao, the leader of China's second-largest spiritual movement who is wanted in China for criminal activity.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Koreas to Expand Cooperation  North and South Korea agreed to reopen border liaison offices and reconnect a railway linking their capitals that has been closed for 55 years. Negotiators also agreed to hold regular high-level talks to carry out an accord reached at a historic meeting of their leaders in June.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-17</p>
        <p>Conservative Delegates Test Bush's Moderation  The majority of Republican delegates assembling in Philadelphia to nominate Gov. George W. Bush for president are notably conservative in thought and spirit, even at a time when Mr. Bush has sought to portray his party as increasingly moderate, according to a New York Times/CBS News poll of delegates. On issues from affirmative action to environmental concerns to abortion, the poll found that delegates stand significantly to the right of much of the nation, and even to the right of rank-and-file Republican voters.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney, the Republican choice for vice president, arrived in Philadelphia on the eve of the party's national convention, after trying in several television interviews to smooth the more conservative edges of his House voting record.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Senator John McCain was booed in Philadelphia by the sort of audience he usually enraptures, an uneasy assortment of the disgruntled -- critics of the campaign finance system, politics-as-usual and much else -- gathered for a ''shadow convention.'' The booing came after the senator endorsed Mr. Bush, the man he had once derided as a phony reformer unprepared for the Oval Office.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>A rich assortment of several thousand dissenters -- all of them orderly, many rambunctious -- dominated the eve of the convention as marchers consciously sought to revive some old-time 60's rhythms and jingles, but with strategic updating. A march of dissenters presented a gathering of various causes, from NOW to the N.A.A.C.P., from folk-singing unionists to animal rights demonstrators, under an umbrella label called Unity 2000.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>G.O.P. Judicial Stall Criticized  President Clinton, in a pair of speeches to trial lawyers, said the Republican majority in the Senate was purposely slowing down confirmation of his nominees to the federal appeals courts and, in some cases, blocking people solely because they are black or Hispanic.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Reform Party Turmoil  Patrick J. Buchanan has vowed to disregard a vote by leaders of the Reform Party to remove his name from the party's presidential ballot because of how he collected voters' signatures in the nominating process. The party's convention on Aug. 9 is almost certain to involve a battle between two distinct camps for control of the party and the $12.6 million in federal campaign money that will be available to the nominee.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Defeat for Treasure Hunters  A federal appeals court in Virginia recently ruled that Spain owned the remains of two warships lost off the Virginia coast two centuries ago. The ruling snatched the ships away from Ben Benson, a treasure hunter who had estimated that the shipwrecks bear more than a half billion dollars in lost coins and precious metals. But Mr. Benson, president of Sea Hunt, a salvage company, may fight the ruling.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Lobstermen Say Spraying Caused Crippling Die-Off  Scientists say there are plausible indicators, but not definitive proof, that millions of lobsters were killed last fall in western Long Island Sound by the intense pesticide spraying to fight the West Nile Virus. But as the region continues to grapple with the virus and the chemical spraying, the lobster deaths and the fate of the lobstermen put out of work suggest that the stakes can be high and the facts often elusive.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>5 Rescued in Blaze  Firefighters rescued five members of a family trapped in a bedroom after a blaze tore through an apartment in the Brownsville section of Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Treasures Rediscovered  A wealth of important finds has been unearthed as the New-York Historical Society prepares for a coming-out party on Nov. 17. That is when the institution will unveil the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture, an $11.3 million exhibition, research and storage space in its building on Central Park West at 77th Street.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Trade Talks Heat Up  The Yankees moved closer to completing a trade for the San Diego pitcher Matt Clement and the outfielder Eric Owens, according to baseball officials. In the deal that was being worked on, the Yankees would give up the top prospect Alfonso Soriano, middle reliever Jason Grimsley and the minor league pitcher Brandon Knight. But the Mets are also talking with the Padres about Clement.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Jose Angel Valente  One of the principal figures of Spanish poetry in the 20th century, he was 71. He wrote more than two dozen books and won a number of prestigious Spanish literary prizes.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>Abraham Pais  A physicist who helped build the conceptual foundations of the modern theory of elementary particles, then became a science historian and wrote one of the most acclaimed biographies of Einstein, he was 82.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18</p>
        <p>Telephone Workers May Strike  About 85,000 telephone workers on the East Coast are threatening to go on strike next weekend. The workers are facing off with Verizon Communications -- the company that Bell Atlantic formed after buying GTE -- largely because they fear the company's use of lower paid, nonunion workers will endanger the wages and benefits of unionized workers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Digital Wing for Random House  The nation's largest trade publisher will create a purely digital imprint. In January, the house will begin publishing about 20 digital books.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Suit Tests Digital Data Access  A potential landmark case about the limits of a new copyright law is awaiting the judge's verdict. The case, involving the copying of DVD movie disks, may affect the way cultural products are consumed and whether computer code deserves First Amendment protection.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Fight Over Generic Car Parts  Since losing an Illinois lawsuit, State Farm Insurance stopped requiring body shops to use lower-priced generic car parts. Now, the industry is fighting back with another suit. If it wins, the industry plans to try to undo the ruling in other states.</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Republican pleasantries; the petro-curse; turning the needy away.</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire, Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>B4  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A10</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
