<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trapped by Politics, Engaged by a Country</title>
    <meta content="31CHIE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Council on Foreign Relations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FlorCruz, Jaime</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D8123DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trapped by Politics, Engaged by a Country</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, July 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Jaime FlorCruz, outgoing Time magazine Beijing bureau chief, who is leaving China after 29 tumultuous years; he will spend year in New York on Council on Foreign Relations press fellowship; comments on his growing cynicism toward Communist Party and optimism about his adopted nation; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Standing in the late afternoon light of his near-empty apartment, Jaime FlorCruz rolls up a massive Qing Dynasty-era map of this city that for 29 years has been successively his refuge, his effective prison and his home. At long last, he is moving on.</p>
        <p>''My mother agonized about waking me up that morning,'' says Time magazine's bureau chief of the August day in 1971 when he flew from Manila to Hong Kong and then crossed by train into China for what was to have been a three-week tour. She had an inkling that something might go wrong.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Standing in the late afternoon light of his near-empty apartment, Jaime FlorCruz rolls up a massive Qing Dynasty-era map of this city that for 29 years has been successively his refuge, his effective prison and his home. At long last, he is moving on.</p>
        <p>''My mother agonized about waking me up that morning,'' says Time magazine's bureau chief of the August day in 1971 when he flew from Manila to Hong Kong and then crossed by train into China for what was to have been a three-week tour. She had an inkling that something might go wrong.</p>
        <p>Something did. The longhaired, bell-bottomed Mr. FlorCruz, a well-known student advocate during the waning days of Philippine democracy under President Ferdinand Marcos's increasingly authoritarian rule, had been invited to see China by the Chinese Friendship Association -- an illegal journey under Philippine law at the time.</p>
        <p>While Mr. FlorCruz visited Mao Zedong's revolutionary redoubt amid the caves of northern Shaanxi Province, Marcos suspended the writ of habeas corpus, allowing Philippine security forces to imprison political opponents without presenting them for trial.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of people disappeared, some never to be seen again. Mr. FlorCruz was on Marcos' list of enemies. As a result, he did not leave China again for 12 years.</p>
        <p>At first he did not dare leave. Then he could not leave. And at last, he did not want to leave, having married, had children and built a career as a journalist here. The soft-spoken Mr. FlorCruz, 49, watched the country emerge from Cultural Revolution fanaticism to the brutal pragmatism of the post-Tiananmen Square protest era and became a well-known fixture in Beijing's expatriate community.</p>
        <p>He covered the trials of Mao's widow, Jiang Qing, and the rest of the tyrannical Gang of Four, and he covered the Tiananmen Square student protests that ended in bloodshed in 1989. Under his watch, Time broke the story of Jiang Qing's suicide in 1991. He interviewed Jiang Zemin when he was Shanghai's mayor, and again after he had become the nation's president.</p>
        <p>But Mr. FlorCruz has finally had his fill. He says he has reached the point ''where I can almost write the story without doing any reporting, and so it is time to go.'' He will spend a year in New York on an Edward R. Murrow Press Fellowship at the Council on Foreign Relations.</p>
        <p>Mr. FlorCruz recounted how his early naivete gradually gave way to cynicism toward the Communist Party. But he showed, too, that he has retained a remarkable optimism about the country that became his home.</p>
        <p>''I'm conscious of the need to maintain a distance from politics, to try not to let it color my views,'' he said. ''Just about any change is an improvement from where I started.''</p>
        <p>His hosts brought him and his friends to Beijing nearly three decades ago, installing them in a small hotel near the heart of the city. His punishment was mind-numbing boredom. He did not speak Chinese and certainly did not read it. The available reading materials in English were arid editions of Chinese propaganda. He and his group soon exhausted the supply of tourist sites, and they were not otherwise allowed to leave the hotel. China is still undergoing class struggle, Mr. FlorCruz recalls being told by his minders.</p>
        <p>Still, he says his enthusiasm for the New China was undaunted. ''We blamed everything on Marcos,'' Mr. FlorCruz said, his face older, his hair shorter, but otherwise little changed in appearance from those days. ''We were still very high on China -- we had that wide-eyed, gee-whiz attitude,'' he added from behind his new, owlish eyeglasses. ''There were no flies! The cops didn't carry guns!''</p>
        <p>In fact, the group had little idea how turbulent the times were. Mao Zedong's anointed heir, Lin Biao, was in power when they arrived, but gone a month later. Mr. FlorCruz remembers being told that Mr. Lin was killed in a plane crash. (Many people today believe he was shot down while fleeing to the Soviet Union after staging an aborted coup.) Soon, Mr. FlorCruz realized that he and his friends were the only ones still toting Mao's little red book and many people had stopped wearing the Mao pins that had been so ubiquitous.</p>
        <p>The summer turned to fall and fall to winter and Mr. FlorCruz saw his first snowfall. To cure their cabin fever, the group agreed to go work in the countryside along with millions of urban Chinese following Mao's exhortation to bridge the gap between intellectuals and peasants. Mr. FlorCruz and his friends were sent to Mao's home province of Hunan, mistakenly thinking they would escape Beijing's brutal winters in a more southern clime. Instead, they traded their heated Beijing hotel for a frigid, unheated dormitory and left the hotel menu for crude peasant fare. The work was backbreaking but occupied the mind.</p>
        <p>By the time he and his friends returned to Beijing in mid-1972, Marcos had declared martial law, making their repatriation even riskier. Mr. FlorCruz's passport expired the next year, leaving him stateless in China.</p>
        <p>He worked on a Yellow Sea trawler shoveling fish, enrolled in a language school and later earned a degree in Chinese history at Beijing University. He watched the nation convulse when Mao died in 1976.</p>
        <p>In 1983 the Philippine Embassy finally issued him a new passport and he visited home. But by then he had a life in China, where he had started working as a reporter for Newsweek and later Time magazine. After the 1989 massacre, Time helped secure him a visa to the United States in case the bureau needed to be evacuated. He was made Time's bureau chief the next year.</p>
        <p>From the black vinyl sofa that is about the only furniture left in his Beijing home, Mr. FlorCruz summed up how he feels about all that has happened since his mother woke him on that morning 29 years ago: ''It's like a dream.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
