<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>L'Anse aux Meadows Journal; Newfoundland Happily Rediscovers the Vikings</title>
    <meta content="Y31CAN$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vikings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newfoundland (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Erickson, Leif</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Newfoundland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5DE133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>L'Anse aux Meadows Journal; Newfoundland Happily Rediscovers the Vikings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>L'ANSE AUX MEADOWS, Newfoundland, July 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>1,000th anniversary of Leif Ericson's landing on L'Anse Aux Meadows, establishing short-lived Viking colony on Newfoundland's northernmost tip, is re-enacted by group of Icelandic men, who sailed from Greenland aboard replica of old Viking vessel; commemmoration is part of Newfoundland's efforts to shake off label as Canada's poorest province; long isolated from rest of North America, it is well on way to meeting self-imposed goal of attracting one tourist each year for each of 540,000 residents; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Out of the cold gray mists of the North Atlantic, the small flotilla appeared, tiny boats with fierce prows, propelled by billowing sails and protected by circular shields of oak and cowhide. Arriving in this rocky cove on Friday, Icelandic-speaking men with sun-creased faces and unkempt hair strode to this unfamiliar shore, their first time on dry land since sailing south from Greenland.</p>
        <p>One thousand years ago, there was a similar scene, seen by some as a defining moment in human history, as Leif Ericson arrived here on Newfoundland's northernmost tip. Here, in the only authenticated Viking settlement in the Americas, historians believe, the first Christian rites were celebrated in the Americas and the first European child, Snorri, was born.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Out of the cold gray mists of the North Atlantic, the small flotilla appeared, tiny boats with fierce prows, propelled by billowing sails and protected by circular shields of oak and cowhide. Arriving in this rocky cove on Friday, Icelandic-speaking men with sun-creased faces and unkempt hair strode to this unfamiliar shore, their first time on dry land since sailing south from Greenland.</p>
        <p>One thousand years ago, there was a similar scene, seen by some as a defining moment in human history, as Leif Ericson arrived here on Newfoundland's northernmost tip. Here, in the only authenticated Viking settlement in the Americas, historians believe, the first Christian rites were celebrated in the Americas and the first European child, Snorri, was born.</p>
        <p>The sagas say that Indian attacks forced the Vikings to abandon their colony within a decade. Such resistance helped postpone European conquest and settlement of the Americas for 500 years.</p>
        <p>In Friday's historical vignette on this windy strait facing Labrador, where whales mingle with icebergs, modern reality quickly intruded on the magical moment. The cameras caught little girls clutching Snorri dolls, their brothers strutting in horned helmets and their parents tapping time to the rock version of a  fishing chanty, ''Your Daddy's a Sailor Who Never Comes Home.''</p>
        <p>Reflecting modern fascination with the Norse, a seafaring people whose medieval trade routes stretched from here to Baghdad, this weekend about 15,000 tourists from North America and Europe crammed into this tiny fishing village, winter population 44.</p>
        <p>Newfoundland, a craggy island nicknamed ''The Rock,'' is newly determined to shake off its label as Canada's poorest province. Long isolated from the rest of North America, it is well on its way to meeting a self-imposed goal of attracting one tourist each year for each of its 540,000 residents, a ratio long enjoyed by such tourism powers as France and Spain. This weekend, tourists driving up the ''Viking Trail'' found no-vacancy signs at the Vinland Motel, the Viking Nest Bed and Breakfast, and the Valhalla Lodge.</p>
        <p>Watson Tucker, a 59-year-old former welder and fisherman, said as he watched the festival unfold that the whole world seemed to be there. A graduate of a course in Viking culture offered by the local branch of the College of the North Atlantic, Mr. Tucker sported a thick beard, deerhide shoes, and heavy green tunic for his summer job acting the role of a Norse poet.</p>
        <p>After half a century under Canada's wing, this onetime British colony is also rediscovering its North Atlantic neighborhood. St. John's, the provincial capital, is equidistant in flying time from Toronto and Reykjavik, Iceland.</p>
        <p>''The North Atlantic is our pond,'' Brian Tobin, premier of Newfoundland and Labrador, said after buttonholing the visiting president of Icelandair about starting flights linking the two island communities.</p>
        <p>Iceland's national airline now flies three times a day to Halifax, Nova Scotia. With more and more Icelanders coming here for business and shopping, the company wants to increase flights to five a week and to add stops in St. John's. Iceland plans  an embassy in Ottawa next year.</p>
        <p>Odd Inge Skjaevesland, a visiting Norwegian newspaper reporter, noted the absence of a high-level Norwegian delegation and said that Norway, Denmark, and Sweden increasingly look east to the opportunities developing in the Baltics, rather than west toward their old North Atlantic colonies -- the Faeroe Islands, Iceland and Greenland. As a result, these islands increasingly are knitting trade ties with their Canadian neighbors.</p>
        <p>Josef Motzfeldt, Greenland's deputy prime minister, agreed, marveling in an interview that, in only three hours, he was able to fly from Nuuk, Greenland's capital, to St. John's, a modern city of 150,000, three times the population of Greenland.</p>
        <p>The Viking re-enactment, with a cruise ship bringing hundreds of Scandinavian tourists ashore to watch, is the most visible face of a burgeoning North Atlantic relationship. Half an hour down the road from where two Norwegian archaeologists, Helge Instad and Anne Stine, discovered the Norse ruins here in 1960, an Icelandic company is managing a new shrimp processing plant, providing needed employment to people laid off after the cod fishery collapsed in 1992. In Notre Dame Bay, 130 miles south of here, Jonas Kristjansson, an Iceland saga scholar, is searching this summer for more Viking ruins.</p>
        <p>In St. John's, where plans are under way to triple Newfoundland's oil production, to 500,000 barrels a day in 2005, oil executives talk easily of friendships and professional ties forged in recent years with Scottish and Norwegian engineers as Newfoundlanders learned skills for building oil platforms in the iceberg infested North Atlantic.</p>
        <p>By the end of this decade, oil royalties are expected to help end Newfoundland's dependence on aid from Ottawa. But, provincial planners are betting heavily on tourism to reduce Newfoundland's double digit unemployment rates, the highest of any state or province in North America.</p>
        <p>This year, the number of tourists is expected to hit 450,000, a 50 percent jump in five years, attributable in part to the low Canadian dollar.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to see one million visitors a year,'' Charles Furey, the provincial tourism minister, said as he strode past the sod-covered church, chieftain's hall, smithy and boat shed of Norstead, the replica Norse port that opened here two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>These living villages populated with re-enactors turn dry historical sites into family attractions. Nearby, at the ruins of the real Viking village, a Unesco World Heritage Site, attendance jumped by 50 percent, to 29,000 last year, after Parks Canada hired re-enactors.</p>
        <p>At Norstead, local actors will be rotated with groups from Britain, Denmark, Maryland, Sweden and Ontario. Belying the new, kinder image of the Norse as peaceable farmers, a group of English re-enactors on Thursday practiced throwing axes at a target wall, then engaged in mock fights -- a sword in one hand and an ax in the other.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
