<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Retirement Is Ahead For Chavez After Loss</title>
    <meta content="31FITE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219126"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arkush, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chavez, Julio Cesar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tszyu, Kostya</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DB133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Retirement Is Ahead For Chavez After Loss</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL ARKUSH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arkush, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>PHOENIX, July 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boxer Julio Cesar Chavez, following knockout loss to Kostya Tszyu in World Boxing Council superlightweight championship bout, says he plans to retire (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Moments after the end that so many had anticipated, the proud Julio Cesar Chavez did what other fighters have done in the painful aftermath of defeat. He said he was retiring.</p>
        <p>''I think it is time for me to leave,'' Chavez announced Saturday night after his title bout with the World Boxing Council superlightweight champion, Kostya Tszyu, was stopped by Referee Bobby Ferrara halfway through the sixth round.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Moments after the end that so many had anticipated, the proud Julio Cesar Chavez did what other fighters have done in the painful aftermath of defeat. He said he was retiring.</p>
        <p>''I think it is time for me to leave,'' Chavez announced Saturday night after his title bout with the World Boxing Council superlightweight champion, Kostya Tszyu, was stopped by Referee Bobby Ferrara halfway through the sixth round.</p>
        <p>While Chavez, 38, may have lasted longer in the scheduled 12-round bout at Veterans Memorial Coliseum than numerous critics had feared, he showed nothing to dispel the view of boxing experts that his once magnificent skills have clearly diminished in recent years.</p>
        <p>Though he was behind on the judges' cards, Chavez fought courageously in the early rounds. But he began to receive a lot of pounding in the fifth from the more powerful Tszyu, 30, who then knocked him to the canvas with a right hand in the sixth. Chavez managed to get up, but that only prolonged the punishment. The fight was soon over. It was his fifth defeat in a career that began in 1980 and included 103 victories, 2 draws and 6 championships in 3 weight classes.</p>
        <p>''I'm sorry to all the Latin people,'' Chavez said. The Latin people, to be sure, were sorely disappointed with the result. Wearing red headbands and waving Mexican flags, they gave Chavez a tremendous ovation when he began to make his way toward the ring. Any exchange in the contest that seemed to favor him was greeted with loud cheers. Perhaps he could, they hoped, produce one more memorable triumph.</p>
        <p>Not Saturday night, however, and when the miracle did not happen, when their longtime hero had lost, there was an understandable blend of anger and sadness among the faithful in the near capacity crowd. They might have sensed that they would never see Chavez in the ring again.</p>
        <p>Many who follow boxing felt strongly that they should not have seen him this time. Even though he had not faced a top-10 contender in over a year and had lost a 10-round decision last October to the journeyman Willy Wise, Chavez was still ranked as the World Boxing Council's top contender, which made the bout mandatory. The Tszyu bout was considered such a mismatch that the major sports books in the Las Vegas casinos would not post odds.</p>
        <p>But after there were indications that the Nevada Athletic Commission was not going to sanction the fight, originally scheduled for July 15 at the MGM Grand in Las Vegas, the three-member Arizona Boxing Commission gave its approval.</p>
        <p>Chavez, who had appealed to the Arizona commission, apparently trained pretty hard, which, by all accounts, he had not done for the Wise fight. He also talked tough, boldly predicting that he would knock out Tszyu by the eighth round.</p>
        <p>The fight, of course, never got to the eighth round. The Russian-born Tszyu, who improved his record to 25-1-1, took care of that. The future for Tszyu, who lives in Australia, looks even brighter. He earned $1.2 million for this fight and figures to make a lot more.</p>
        <p>The future for Chavez is a much different story, depending on whether he stands by what he said in the ring and retires.</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
