<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Digging for Forgotten Treasure; Museum Opens Its Vaults for New Exhibition Space</title>
    <meta content="31HIST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Luce, Henry, III Center for Study of American Culture</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Historical Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Glenn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gotbaum, Betsy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E7D9133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Digging for Forgotten Treasure; Museum Opens Its Vaults for New Exhibition Space</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Glenn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Historical Society, with some long-missing treasures that were rediscovered in vaults at museum, are preparing for Nov 17 dedication of Henry Luce III Center for Study of American Culture, $11.3 million exhibition, research and storage space that will inhabit entire fourth floor of building on Central Park West at 77th Street in Manhattan; society president Betsy Gotbaum comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here are some long-missing treasures that are soon to be revealed: a 1914 brass time capsule that was supposed to be opened on Wall Street in 1974 but wasn't, because no one could find it. A hide-covered bass drum that took two Confederate bullets at the First Battle of Bull Run. An ornate chair believed to be Napoleon's. And a fresco of Venus from Pompeii.</p>
        <p>These are just a few of the archival orphans that have been rediscovered in the vaults of the New-York Historical Society, the state's oldest museum, which has clung to existence -- and its hyphen -- since 1804.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here are some long-missing treasures that are soon to be revealed: a 1914 brass time capsule that was supposed to be opened on Wall Street in 1974 but wasn't, because no one could find it. A hide-covered bass drum that took two Confederate bullets at the First Battle of Bull Run. An ornate chair believed to be Napoleon's. And a fresco of Venus from Pompeii.</p>
        <p>These are just a few of the archival orphans that have been rediscovered in the vaults of the New-York Historical Society, the state's oldest museum, which has clung to existence -- and its hyphen -- since 1804.</p>
        <p>It's not that the artifacts were lost, exactly: the historical societies of America, which misplace things all the time, have long come up with ingenious ways to describe such rediscovered items, explaining that they were ''undercataloged'' until they ''came to light'' or were ''found during inventory.''</p>
        <p>Some artifacts were simply misfiled. Others were long mistaken for similar objects. Many more were, well, voted off: banished from public view by fickle curators, then forgotten over the dusty decades as staff members quit, retired or went to that great archive in the sky.</p>
        <p>And now, a wealth of important finds has been unearthed as the society feverishly prepares for a coming-out party on Nov. 17. That is when the institution will unveil the Henry Luce III Center for the Study of American Culture, an $11.3 million exhibition, research and storage space that will inhabit the entire fourth floor of its 1904 building on Central Park West at 77th Street.</p>
        <p>Although the society is a museum, a library and an archive, only a small scholarly coven has ever enjoyed the full wealth of its holdings. ''People would tell me it was such a wonderful collection,'' said Betsy Gotbaum, the institution's president. ''And I would ask how they knew, because it wasn't accessible.''</p>
        <p>And so, the opening of the center is a public celebration of the society's return from what can only be described as a near-death experience. Not quite expiring with the old millennium, the society spent virtually all its endowment, came close to bankruptcy, stopped mounting exhibitions and closed its museum doors to the public in 1993.</p>
        <p>Even after the museum reopened in 1995, most of its 60,000 items were stored in a warehouse on East 20th Street at a cost of $500,000 a year. Now that archive is being moved to the society's fourth floor (save for a selection of less valuable and bulky materials bound for a warehouse in Bergenfield, N.J.). ''For the first time, the museum and library collections are under one roof, together, and accessible,'' Ms. Gotbaum said.</p>
        <p>The redesigned 21,000-square-foot space, built with a grant from the Henry Luce Foundation, will hold 40,000 museum items, with 10,000 on view. The society's treasures include 435 original John James Audubon watercolors, George Washington's Army cot, the desk upon which Clement Clarke Moore wrote ''A Visit From St. Nicholas,'' and the 1904 silver Tiffany motorman's handle used to inaugurate the first subway train in New York.</p>
        <p>The new center occupies an old space that long provided storage and gallery rooms until a leaking roof forced its closing a decade ago. Ms. Gotbaum said that when she took over in 1994, ''the fourth floor looked like Berlin after the war.''</p>
        <p>Now, on the repolished original oak parquet floors, and up on a new 4,500-square-foot mezzanine, the collection will reside on maple shelves set in steel and satin-finish aluminum. The museum's 1,200 paintings will be assembled there, as well as its sculptures, home furnishings, ceramics, glass, silver, textiles, toys, dolls and firearms. Devotees of ''Antiques Roadshow'' take note: the space will also provide a showcase for the society's collection of 135 Tiffany lamps, hidden away since 1995.</p>
        <p>All storage and display areas will be visible in the space, designed by the architectural firm Beyer Blinder Belle, which oversaw the restoration of Grand Central Terminal and Ellis Island.</p>
        <p>The center will put New York at the forefront of design in ''open storage,'' a growing worldwide archival trend in which shelf after visible shelf of objects is arrayed for public viewing in so-called dense displays.</p>
        <p>The hybrid design ''was dictated by the need of the society for a multiple-use facility,'' said Norma Barbacci, a project manager for Beyer Blinder Belle. ''The old practice was to hide objects protectively in rooms, but now we want to involve visitors in the workings of the museum. This redesign allows them to see the curators, and staff, at work behind the scenes.''</p>
        <p>About 300 paintings will be on ''close view,'' behind tempered glass. The rest will be suspended in transparent cases. A regularly rotating collection of other once-hidden prizes will be arrayed on shelves.</p>
        <p>''The completion of the Luce Center is a tangible demonstration that the society is back,'' said the state attorney general, Eliot L. Spitzer. His office, which oversees the operation of nonprofit organizations, has monitored the society's finances since 1990. ''The new leadership at the society has turned things around,'' he said, referring to Ms. Gotbaum, who has announced plans to run for public advocate.</p>
        <p>When Ms. Gotbaum took charge of the society, it had an operating deficit of $2.6 million. Detractors said the society had been run for much of its existence like a private club that spurned government control and assistance. Not only did it suffer from what critics said were decades of mismanagement, but it also allowed its endowment to shrink from $16 million in 1986 to next to nothing, as a result of the 1987 stock market collapse and the use of the endowment to erase operating deficits.</p>
        <p>In 1988, articles in The New York Times revealed that dozens of the society's paintings and artifacts had been damaged by storage in a rented warehouse space in Paterson, N.J., and in a town house on the Upper West Side of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''There was a time after I'd arrived that I thought I'd made a mistake in coming here,'' said Ms. Gotbaum, 62, who was the parks commissioner under Mayor David N. Dinkins before she was recruited to head the society. ''The building was literally falling apart, the roof was leaking, the walls were leaking and the staff was dispirited,'' she recalled. Not to mention the literal black cloud that formed in 1995, when welders inadvertently ignited greasy rags in the basement, starting a smoky fire.</p>
        <p>William L. Brown III, a staff curator at the National Park Service Design Center, said: ''There was a point there where I thought that they weren't going to make it. There were serious discussions about auctioning off the whole collection.''</p>
        <p>But the society won permission from the attorney general's office to sell a selection of old master paintings donated in 1867 by an American collector, Thomas Jefferson Bryan. It also sold duplicate rare books, paperweights and other Americana. The sale, which Mr. Spitzer and Ms. Gotbaum now defend, raised the hackles of critics who opposed using the money to extract the society from a financial morass. But it also raised a much-needed $17.6 million.</p>
        <p>The society received $13.5 million from the city and state to fix the roof, clean and repair the exterior walls and modernize the heating and air-conditioning systems.</p>
        <p>With a cavalcade of new exhibitions, attendance went from zero in April 1995 to 100,000 last year, higher than the average of 80,000 in the 1980's. For the last two years, the nonprofit society has had surpluses. The library is now open five days a week, including Saturday; the museum is open every day but Monday. Meanwhile, the endowment has crept up to $25.5 million.</p>
        <p>''Assuming the trend line continues, both in visitors and in increased revenue,'' Mr. Spitzer said, ''we can imagine that we would be able to terminate the arrangement to monitor their financing.''</p>
        <p>These days, the society has to vie for visitors and donations in the city's hypercompetitive cultural environment, in the shadow of a powerhouse: the American Museum of Natural History, right across the street. The society must continually find money for its operating budget, since -- unlike its next-door neighbor and the Metropolitan Museum of Art across the park -- it is not in the Cultural Institutions Group, a 33-member consortium whose lighting, heating, maintenance and security expenses are paid by the city.</p>
        <p>As the society faces such challenges, one of the institution's most crucial tasks -- getting control of its collections -- is well under way. Thanks to the Luce Foundation, 90 percent of the museum collection has been cataloged.</p>
        <p>The cataloging nightmare has been even more daunting for the society's library staff of 32, which must keep track of 4 million items. They include 500 letters to and from George Washington, and letters between Alexander Hamilton and Aaron Burr before their duel in 1804.</p>
        <p>In 1997, the society affiliated with the Bobst Library of New York University, and the society's library is being cataloged with the help of a $5.1 million grant from the Mellon Foundation. So far the society has put descriptions of 70,000 of its library holdings on electronic databases, which are available at www.nyhistory.org, the society's Web site, and on the university's BobCatPlus computer catalog.</p>
        <p>But the most important aspect of the effort to organize the collection is the society's ''new democratization,'' said Jan Ramirez, director of the museum. ''In the past, the very knowledge of these materials was anecdotal and privileged, shared only by an elite of staff members and historians. But now everything will be available to everyone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
