<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Philadelphia, 2,000 Delegates Await the Arrival of the Star of the Republican Show</title>
    <meta content="Y31CON$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: APPROACHING THE NOMINATION -- THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EEDB133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Philadelphia, 2,000 Delegates Await the Arrival of the Star of the Republican Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Overview of 2000 Republican National Convention in Philadelphia; vice presidential candidate Dick Cheney arrives in city; appears in morning television talk shows to smooth more conservative and controversial edges of his voting record in Congress; Bush campaign's plans for conflict-free convention proceed without serious difficulty; diagram of convention hall shows seating of delegations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Cheney, the Republican choice for vice president, arrived here on the eve of the party's national convention after trying in several television interviews this morning to smooth the more conservative edges of his House voting record.</p>
        <p>In interviews on the Sunday morning talk programs, Mr. Cheney called some of the Democratic criticism of his votes ''trivial'' and ''irrelevant to the important issues of the day.'' But while he defended some of his actions, like his vote in 1986 against freedom for Nelson Mandela, he seemed to back away from his votes opposing action against ''cop-killer'' bullets and plastic guns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Cheney, the Republican choice for vice president, arrived here on the eve of the party's national convention after trying in several television interviews this morning to smooth the more conservative edges of his House voting record.</p>
        <p>In interviews on the Sunday morning talk programs, Mr. Cheney called some of the Democratic criticism of his votes ''trivial'' and ''irrelevant to the important issues of the day.'' But while he defended some of his actions, like his vote in 1986 against freedom for Nelson Mandela, he seemed to back away from his votes opposing action against ''cop-killer'' bullets and plastic guns.</p>
        <p>The Democrats, meanwhile, continued their incessant assault on Mr. Cheney's record today, releasing a television advertisement that attacked his votes against Head Start, the Clean Water Act, the school lunch program and health insurance for people who lost coverage when they lost their jobs, as well as his having praised OPEC for cutting oil production.</p>
        <p>The advertisement asked, about him and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, ''What are their plans for working families?''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Bush continued his slow march toward Philadelphia, campaigning at the replica of the historic Crosley Field in the suburbs of Cincinnati. Several thousand people withstood a driving rain to see him as he drove up in a campaign bus emblazoned with the slogan ''Renewing America's Purpose,'' the theme of his five-day tour through battleground states. He told the Republican members of Congress sharing the stage with him: ''Be patient. Help is on the way.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, who has made only a few campaign stops since being selected as Mr. Bush's running mate, made a brief appearance here this afternoon, promising ''most of all to make America proud again by giving them a president they can respect.'' He spoke for four minutes at the hotel where he will be joined by Mr. Bush on Wednesday, and he seemed overwhelmed by his reception from a crowd organized by the campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's more important task came on the morning talk programs. He defended his vote against freedom for Mr. Mandela because he believed the African National Congress was a ''terrorist'' group.</p>
        <p>He said his votes opposing action against cop-killer bullets and plastic guns that could pass metal detectors were caused by the no-amendment procedure under which they were considered. In each case, he said now that he would be ''happy to entertain'' such proposals.</p>
        <p>He said he had voted against Head Start and the Older Americans Act because they were costly. On both subjects, he said his position was different today.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney also sought to generate support, Mr. Bush's primary-season nemesis, Senator John McCain of Arizona, also made a pitch for the ticket. Appearing before the ''shadow convention,'' an event ranging from reformist to radical, he gamely asked the audience to vote for Mr. Bush and was soundly booed for his troubles. Then he went before his own delegates and formally released them from commitments to vote for him. Many groaned.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Bush camp's plans for a conflict-free convention chugged along without serious difficulty. Abortion-rights advocates insisted they were working to find the required six states to support new language in the platform acknowledging diverse views on the subject, but they had yet to find them. One minor rules squabble was shaping up -- over an effort to make all 165 members of the Republican National Committee automatic delegates at the next national convention.</p>
        <p>There was no formal convention business beyond the arrival of 2,066 delegates -- mostly middle-aged white men and generally more conservative than the voters who gave Mr. Bush the nomination -- assembled in the city where Republicans have nominated five previous candidates, from John C. Fremont in 1856 through Thomas E. Dewey in 1948.</p>
        <p>But it became increasingly clear that despite the shadow convention and occasional minor demonstrations like today's peaceful march of 7,000 for a variety of causes, the four-day show beginning Monday is all about Mr. Bush and Mr. Cheney.</p>
        <p>The party's Congressional wing gets barely an hour at center stage, yet Representative Thomas M. Davis III of Virginia, chairman of the House Republican Campaign Committee, which is striving mightily to retain control of the House, pronounced himself happy with the time given House candidates at the podium -- two segments of fifteen one-minute speeches in the daytime on Monday. Nor did the senators complain at the opportunity for six four-minute speeches around lunchtime.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis said: ''This convention is about electing George W. Bush. It's not about the House and Senate.'' He said Republican hopes of retaining the House, where they now hold only a 13-seat majority, would be aided by Mr. Bush's ''creating an updraft that our candidates can take advantage of.''</p>
        <p>It was also clear that the campaign has settled on a strategy for dealing with the problems it obviously did not anticipate from Mr. Cheney's voting record. On one television show after another, he said that the votes did not matter but that he  might vote differently today anyway.</p>
        <p>On ABC's ''This Week,'' Mr. Cheney complained of ''so much time and energy and effort devoted to this kind of trivia'' and ''the trivial aspect of the debates that rage in Washington now.''</p>
        <p>On CBS's ''Face the Nation,'' he said: ''The campaign that Governor Bush and I will run is very much oriented towards the future. It's focused on trying to restore a degree of civility in Washington, to end the kind of partisan backbiting that has been so much a part of the tone and tenor in this city for all too many years.''</p>
        <p>On NBC's ''Meet the Press,'' he said, ''I think the American people want to hear about the future, not about the past.'' That choice of phrase recalled what Bill Clinton said on Jan. 26, 1992, when he was a candidate for president, about accusations that he had conducted an affair with Gennifer Flowers. Mr. Clinton said, ''The problems are about what's going to happen to families in New Hampshire and the rest of the country in the future, not what happened to mine in the past.''</p>
        <p>On CNN's ''Late Edition,'' Mr. Cheney said: ''I hope the Democrats spend the next three months going after my voting record; I'll be happy to defend it. But in the meantime, we're going to talk about the future of the country, and we're going to win the election.''</p>
        <p>His argument about how his pro-gun votes were dictated by House procedures banning amendments was consistent from one program to the next. He put it this way on ABC:</p>
        <p>''Debate was limited. No amendments were allowed. And I often voted against measures that I thought deserved more serious coverage and debate than was permitted when the majority brought it up under the procedure.''</p>
        <p>But he gave different answers when asked what he would do now on the measure attacking bullets that can penetrate the Kevlar vests of police officers. He told Bob Schieffer of CBS, ''It would depend.'' When NBC's Tim Russert asked him, ''Would you authorize money to ban cop-killer bullets and ban plastic weapons?'' he replied, ''Ah, yes.''</p>
        <p>On ABC he offered an explanation of his 1987 vote against the Older Americans Act, which provided $1.6 billion for programs including health centers, Meals on Wheels and Alzheimer's research: ''Well, probably because I thought that it was excessive in terms of funding.'' He said, ''When we had big deficits I voted against bills that I thought either authorized or appropriated too much fund.''</p>
        <p>He was also interviewed on ''Fox News Sunday'' but was not asked about his House votes.</p>
        <p>He continued the anti-Washington theme here, saying, ''For the last five years, I've been outside Washington, I've been out in the real world where people are building companies, creating jobs, inventing new technologies that are transforming our lives.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, who has been the chairman and chief executive of Halliburton, a large oil-services company based in Dallas, said, ''When I look back at Washington, I scratch my head and ask what the hell are they doing back there?''</p>
        <p>As for the platform, Republican abortion-rights supporters said they had yet to concede defeat. They filled a ballroom at a downtown hotel, where speakers assailed the platform but argued that over the long haul, they would prevail.</p>
        <p>''I do believe that, ultimately, reason will prevail and the Republican Party will finally eliminate that anti-choice, anti-woman, and antediluvian plank from our party platform, and we will once again represent the values of personal freedom and choice,'' declared Roselyn O'Connell, a Republican and president of the National Women's Political Caucus.</p>
        <p>It was a difficult day for Mr. McCain. Ariana Huffington, the commentator who is the chief organizer of the shadow convention, focused on the overhaul of campaign financing, lingering poverty and a drug war seen as mostly simply fill up prisons, and to intervene to shush the booing crowd. When the catcalls continued, intermittently, he canceled a promised question-and-answer session.</p>
        <p>One participant, Emily Hagopian of Los Angeles, said: ''Everybody saw him as our hope for change, and then he came in here with that endorsement. He disgusted us. He betrayed us.'' Ms. Hagopian had arrived with a group called Youth Vote 2000.</p>
        <p>Tears came to Mr. McCain's eyes when he met with his own delegates. He said, ''I need every one of you to give this campaign the same amount of enthusiasm and participation you did for our primary campaign.'' He added, by way of warning, ''America doesn't like sore losers.''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: APPROACHING THE NOMINATION -- THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
