<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Republican Pleasantries</title>
    <meta content="31MON1$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE6DA133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Republican Pleasantries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial comments on upcoming Republican National Convention says it represents gear-shifting time for Gov George W Bush, who knows he will not be elected president unless he gets votes from many people who do not agree with him or with Republican Party platform (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush knows that he cannot be elected president unless he gets votes from many people who do not agree with him or the Republican Party platform on issues such as abortion, gun control, capital punishment and the privatization of Social Security. That is why today is gear-shifting day in Philadelphia. The selection of Dick Cheney as his running mate and the deliberations of the platform committee all emphasized the conservative part of Mr. Bush's background and core vote. Once the first session of the Republican National Convention opens this evening, the nation will see four nights devoted to what Frank Luntz, a Republican pollster, calls the politics of pleasantry.</p>
        <p>Somewhat paradoxically, Governor Bush has imposed what he calls an ''iron-fist rule'' to make sure that ideology does not trump his preferred themes of tolerance and inclusion. That means most of the party's hard-line orators will be kept away from the microphones inside First Union Center, site of a convention that is, in essence, a $65 million exercise in recruiting the moderate swing voter. Governor Bush's plan for this convention reflects the lessons of 1992, when his father's lax campaign team gave Pat Buchanan and other polarizing speakers prime-time roles. By way of contrast, Bill Clinton used his party's 1992 convention to play down the Democrats' liberal tradition and to emulate the Republicans' emphasis on fiscal responsibility and welfare reform. In Philadelphia, Mr. Bush will attempt to borrow the positive imagery long associated with such Democratic issues as education and the saving of Social Security and Medicare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush knows that he cannot be elected president unless he gets votes from many people who do not agree with him or the Republican Party platform on issues such as abortion, gun control, capital punishment and the privatization of Social Security. That is why today is gear-shifting day in Philadelphia. The selection of Dick Cheney as his running mate and the deliberations of the platform committee all emphasized the conservative part of Mr. Bush's background and core vote. Once the first session of the Republican National Convention opens this evening, the nation will see four nights devoted to what Frank Luntz, a Republican pollster, calls the politics of pleasantry.</p>
        <p>Somewhat paradoxically, Governor Bush has imposed what he calls an ''iron-fist rule'' to make sure that ideology does not trump his preferred themes of tolerance and inclusion. That means most of the party's hard-line orators will be kept away from the microphones inside First Union Center, site of a convention that is, in essence, a $65 million exercise in recruiting the moderate swing voter. Governor Bush's plan for this convention reflects the lessons of 1992, when his father's lax campaign team gave Pat Buchanan and other polarizing speakers prime-time roles. By way of contrast, Bill Clinton used his party's 1992 convention to play down the Democrats' liberal tradition and to emulate the Republicans' emphasis on fiscal responsibility and welfare reform. In Philadelphia, Mr. Bush will attempt to borrow the positive imagery long associated with such Democratic issues as education and the saving of Social Security and Medicare.</p>
        <p>Given the blunt, contrary language of much of the Republican platform, this will require some serious spinning and deft television imagery. The effort began yesterday with such figures as Governors Tommy Thompson and George Pataki giving the platform a decent burial by declaring it basically irrelevant to the Bush campaign. Never mind the restrictive language on abortion. According to Mr. Pataki, what matters more is Mr. Bush's vision. In fact, whereas former President George Bush stumbled over the vision thing, his son is determined to make it a central theme. His emphasis will be on positive evocative language about character, principles, leadership, faith, hope, love, rather than on the Republican policy positions that could make him appear authoritarian, elitist or hostile to the interests of women and minorities. To offset the sparse minority representation, convention planners have given starring roles to Mr. Bush's most prominent black advisers, Gen. Colin Powell and Condoleezza Rice, and included a large number of Hispanic Republicans. The prominence of entertainment figures and musical numbers also bespeaks an effort to steer this convention away from wedge issues.</p>
        <p>President Clinton, in his role of the Democrats' uber-strategist, tried to blow the whistle Friday on what he sees as Mr. Bush's desire to make this a campaign about good feelings rather than hard issues. ''That's the message, isn't it? Blur, blur, blur,'' the president complained. Such critiques are not likely to dent the faith that Mr. Bush and his advisers have in polls showing that voters prefer lofty, positive generalities to bitter partisan wrangling. Another ''iron-fist rule'' imposed by Mr. Bush is that there should be no prolonged attacks on Mr. Clinton, Vice President Al Gore or Hillary Rodham Clinton. The campaign will try to be more deft in invoking Clinton fatigue. Mr. Cheney has taken to depicting the president as a tragic figure. In a television commercial, Mr. Bush speaks of the Clinton years as bringing a budget surplus, but a deficit in values.</p>
        <p>Not all Republicans agree with these soft tactics and the gauzy approach summed up in Mr. Bush's slogan of compassionate conservatism. But suppose he succeeds this week in having undecided voters focus on his soothing, positive statements about education, health care, Social Security and taxes, rather than on the harsh and often unfair policy positions espoused by the platform and the Republican Congressional majority. Then Mr. Bush will be able to count this convention a success, and Mr. Gore can count on having his hands full this fall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
