<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tears, Cheers and Jeers as McCain Delivers His Delegates to Bush</title>
    <meta content="Y31MCC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE CAST AND THE CONFLICTS -- THE ARIZONA SENATOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennet, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDC133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1024" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tears, Cheers and Jeers as McCain Delivers His Delegates to Bush</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennet, James</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain is derided by audience at Shadow Convention in Philadelphia after endorsing Gov George W Bush, whom he once scorned as phony reformer unprepared for Oval Office; he meets with senior officials of Bush campaign to formally release delegates to governor; praises Bush for running centrist, inclusive campaign; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Poli tics as usual  with its compromises, cruelties and emotional costs -- caught up with Senator John McCain this weekend.</p>
        <p>Reporters repeatedly tested his appetite for his own words, asking, item by item, if he still believed all those nasty things he had said about his former opponent for the Republican presidential nomination, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas. Over and over, he endorsed the man he had once derided as a phony reformer unprepared for the Oval Office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Poli tics as usual  with its compromises, cruelties and emotional costs -- caught up with Senator John McCain this weekend.</p>
        <p>Reporters repeatedly tested his appetite for his own words, asking, item by item, if he still believed all those nasty things he had said about his former opponent for the Republican presidential nomination, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas. Over and over, he endorsed the man he had once derided as a phony reformer unprepared for the Oval Office.</p>
        <p>Today, one youthful audience here responded with boos, derisive laughter and cries of ''Drag him off!'' to what he insisted was his ''sincere conviction'' that ''all Americans'' should support Governor Bush. On the eve of Mr. Bush's national convention, Mr. McCain was beginning to seem downright conventional, a quality he despises in politics.</p>
        <p>This afternoon, as the senator gathered at a reception with senior officials of the Bush campaign to formally release his delegates to the governor, the moment and the message proved too much. Mr. McCain praised Mr. Bush for running a ''centrist, inclusive campaign.'' He urged his supporters to give the Bush campaign ''the same kind of enthusiasm and participation'' they had given him, that had made him believe, for a time, he might be president. Then he tried to say thanks.</p>
        <p>''I will always be grateful,'' Mr. McCain told the packed room, before stopping to harshly clear his throat. He tried again: ''I will never be able to -- I'll never be able to thank.'' He gave up, eyes shining, as the room erupted in a full minute's applause despite his repeated efforts to get back to business. At his side, his wife, Cindy, began weeping, along with some of the delegates and campaign staff, who had never seen tears from their boss.</p>
        <p>When he regained control of himself and the room and at last expressed his gratitude, Mr. McCain declared ''This is a time for celebration.'' Then, to groans and cries, he released his remaining delegates -- roughly 150 -- to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Coming before the four days of processed emotion that is a modern political convention, Mr. McCain's raw moment left some delegates shaken, even as rock music blared and confetti cannons blasted the room. ''People really believed in him,'' said Ric Barros, a lawyer from Massachusetts. ''It's like a death in the family.'' Asked if he would support Mr. Bush, Mr. Barros said: ''In time. Today, I just want to think about John McCain.''</p>
        <p>Appearing before Mr. McCain, Don Evans, the chairman of Mr. Bush's campaign, praised the senator as ''my American hero'' -- though at least one McCain aide rolled his eyes. Joe Allbaugh, the Bush campaign manager, was also present, though he did not address the crowd.</p>
        <p>The Bush camp can afford to be gracious. Trailing Senator McCain around the margins of the convention here is like watching an episode of ''Survivor'' while knowing who has been voted off the island. The only sense of suspense surrounding his appearances hangs over the question of how far he will go in endorsing Mr. Bush -- and the only surprise registered by his audiences has been over how far he has gone.</p>
        <p>For his full-throated endorsement, Mr. McCain was booed today by the sort of audience he usually enraptures, an uneasy assortment of the disgruntled -- critics of the campaign finance system, politics-as-usual and much else -- gathered for a ''shadow convention.'' Head down, Mr. McCain soldiered through his prepared speech until the noise became too loud, and he looked up. ''If you like, I do not need to continue,'' he said evenly. But a wave of applause from the generally supportive audience kept him going.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain rode his Straight Talk Express here on Saturday for what he insisted was a fun reminder of how his campaign ''caught lightning in a bottle.''</p>
        <p>It seemed more like a rolling test of his humility. Asked on his bus if he still believed Mr. Bush was a ''Pat Robertson Republican,'' Mr. McCain said quietly, ''No, no, I don't believe that.'' To another oft-repeated question, he insisted that his relationship with Mr. Bush was ''cordial'' or even ''very good.'' Repeatedly, he said that he expected to be supporting Mr. Bush's re-election in 2004 and not running himself.</p>
        <p>But the Arizona senator's self-sacrifice had its limits. He bristled when asked, for perhaps the hundredth time, whether he had checked with the Bush campaign before putting his bus back on the road. ''No,'' he shot back, ''because the last time I checked, I'm a United States senator.'' He repeatedly reminded questioners that he always promised to support his party's nominee -- a caveat that made his endorsement sound more dutiful than heartfelt. But his sense of humor stayed intact. When asked if he would accept a position in a Bush cabinet, he said, as he contended with an enormous soft-serve vanilla waffle cone, that the only job he wanted was emperor.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain still admits to differences with Mr. Bush, including over campaign finance reform. But he no longer declares that Mr. Bush should adopt his position, instead noting, as he did at the shadow convention, that ''we agree on many more issues than we disagree on.'' Mr. McCain has repeatedly acknowledged that he is walking a tightrope, trying to retain an insurgent appeal while playing by the rules of party politics. He remains extremely popular, which is why Mr. Bush and scores of congressmen are clamoring for public shows of his support.</p>
        <p>Supporters who turned out for the senator during the weekend said they understood what he was doing. ''Everybody who's reasonable knows that in order to make any change, you have to be incremental,'' said George Leslie, who stood outside the shadow convention today waiting for the senator and wearing a black T-shirt declaring ''Thank God I'm an Atheist.''</p>
        <p>''You have to support the system you're in.''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE CAST AND THE CONFLICTS -- THE ARIZONA SENATOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
