<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Offstage, an Introspective Bush Reflects on His Family and Legacy</title>
    <meta content="Y31BUS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: APPROACHING THE NOMINATION -- POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EEDD133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Offstage, an Introspective Bush Reflects on His Family and Legacy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>BLUE ASH, Ohio, July 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican presidential candidate Gov George W Bush, who is increasingly animated in public as he nears nomination, is more introspective behind the scenes, talking of his family, his history and his legacy (Political Memo); photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As he rides toward his moment of triumph, George W. Bush speaks with extra punch. He belts out his speeches now, his face flushing, arms waving. Yet once off the stage, he is unusually introspective, talking of family. History. Legacy.</p>
        <p>''I'm mindful of the Adams family factor,'' he said on his campaign plane this weekend, bringing up unprompted the last father and son in American history to both win the presidency: John Adams and John Quincy Adams, so very long ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As he rides toward his moment of triumph, George W. Bush speaks with extra punch. He belts out his speeches now, his face flushing, arms waving. Yet once off the stage, he is unusually introspective, talking of family. History. Legacy.</p>
        <p>''I'm mindful of the Adams family factor,'' he said on his campaign plane this weekend, bringing up unprompted the last father and son in American history to both win the presidency: John Adams and John Quincy Adams, so very long ago.</p>
        <p>So confident is he that he jokes fondly about his new running mate's flat campaign style, calling it with notable understatement ''a little more laid-back than mine.'' And though usually allergic to pyschobabble, Mr. Bush does not brush off questions about his relationship with his father, former President George H. W. Bush.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't all that long ago that he himself was the president of the United States, which will make the story unique and different,'' Mr. Bush mused.</p>
        <p>There is poignancy to this conversation on the plane. At his rallies, Mr. Bush speaks of his popular mother. He revels in telling the tale of his courtship of his wife, Laura. But the only acknowledgment of his father is oblique.</p>
        <p>It comes when he bellows, ''I understand that the last two presidential elections haven't gone well,'' and promises to change that for Republicans come November. Left unmentioned is that one of those defeats was his father's.</p>
        <p>Now the Bush clan is gathering once again, just as it did to watch the father's triumphant nomination by two Republican National Conventions. This time it is the eldest son who will take his moment on the stage, capping a remarkable 17-month transformation from a governor with less than two full terms in office to his party's great hope to reclaim the White House.</p>
        <p>''They'll be there, sure, I think all of my brothers and sister,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I can't think of any boycotters.''</p>
        <p>Day after day as Mr. Bush gets closer to Philadelphia, the pyrotechnics become more elaborate. Today he stole a technique from his primary rival John McCain and showed up on a campaign bus for a rally here at the replica of the historic Crosley Field. Fireworks shot into the sky to dazzle the crowd of 2,000, who had waited for hours on the open field despite several pelting rainstorms.</p>
        <p>In a blue shirt and no jacket, dancing on his heels, Mr. Bush spoke of himself in the third person. ''You got to understand about George W.,'' he said. ''I don't take polls to tell me what to think. I do what I think is right.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush seems serene, though at times emotional too. At the governor's mansion in Austin late last week, he almost choked up when he said he would recognize his wife, his daughters and his parents in his convention speech.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bush is at his side at rally after rally, beaming, as he weaves her into his stump speech by promoting her own convention speech, planned for Monday night. ''The first speaker will be the first lady of the state of Texas,'' he tells his audiences.</p>
        <p>He gives them a thumbnail history of the public school librarian from dusty Midland, Tex. ''I said, 'Would you marry me?' '' he says. ''She wasn't particularly interested in politics and politicians. She said, 'I will, except don't ever make me give a speech.' I said, 'O.K.' '' He pauses and then adds, to rising laughter from his audiences, ''It's the only political promise I've ever broken.''</p>
        <p>So the Republican convention will be about Mr. Bush and the Bush family and the Bush platform, beginning in prime time on Monday with Laura and ending Thursday night with Mr. Bush's acceptance speech. ''That puts the Bush family arms around the convention,'' said Karen P. Hughes, Mr. Bush's communications director.</p>
        <p>Many other Republican officeholders -- the ones who remind the public of the the hard-edged Gingrich years -- have been pushed offstage or to nonprime time.</p>
        <p>Not that the edge is gone completely. Revving up the drenched crowd before Mr. Bush's arrival today, Bill Cunningham, the host of a local radio talk show, asked, ''Are we going to permit an eighth of an inch of rain to keep us from scouring out the White House from the filth and degradation of Clinton-Gore?''</p>
        <p>''No!'' the audience thundered back.</p>
        <p>Representative Steve Chabot, who served on the House Judiciary Committee during the impeachment of President Clinton, wondered jokingly who would have expected to see ''Microsoft split up and the Clintons still together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's speeches by contrast have few hard edges, except for his promise to restore ''honor and dignity'' to the presidency and the dig at President Clinton that is implicit when he says Dick Cheney ''understands what the definition of 'is' is.''</p>
        <p>At the heart of the speeches is the concept of family, a soft and subtle way to appeal to his party's conservatives yet also sound right to suburban soccer moms. ''Love your children all the time,'' he croons. ''Tell them you love them.'' Or else he shouts, ''I got a kind of special feeling for moms -- if you know what I mean.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes he sounds more like a revivalist preacher than a politician. Before 5,000 people in Joplin, Mo., on Friday night, Mr. Bush thundered: ''My administration will rally what I call the armies of compassion, the decent, kindhearted souls that act not because of government, that act because they hear our call to people all across America.''</p>
        <p>And under the confetti and the balloons, and on outdoor stages, Mr. Bush throws out his arms maniacally to give oomph to the old familiar stump speech. He gets help in looking animated by way of the contrast with his new running mate.</p>
        <p>On his one day of campaigning with Mr. Bush last Friday, Mr. Cheney shook hands fast along the receiving line waiting to greet the Bush plane. Then he stood all alone at the waiting car. Mr. Bush was still working the line, grabbing a hand here, a shoulder there.</p>
        <p>''We have a different campaigning style,'' Mr. Bush said the next day. ''That's the way it is. He's going to be a great partner. He's warming up.''</p>
        <p>And if these are glory days, well, Mr. Bush says he learned something else from his father, who watched his sky-high approval ratings after the gulf war collapse, leaving him unable to stave off defeat in 1992 by a young, untested governor.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to get overconfident,'' said this year's governor of the moment. ''You know why? I know what can happen. I have seen poll numbers crumble. I have seen defeat first hand.''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: APPROACHING THE NOMINATION -- POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
