<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LEGALLY INSANE/A special report.; Voices in His Head Muted, A Killer Rejoins the World</title>
    <meta content="31SWEE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harden, Blaine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Nina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lowenstein, Allard K (1929-80)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sweeney, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E6D9133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LEGALLY INSANE/A special report.; Voices in His Head Muted, A Killer Rejoins the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BLAINE HARDEN and NINA BERNSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bernstein, Nina; Harden, Blaine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special report, Legally Insane, on release of Dennis Sweeney, who murdered former congressman Allard K Lowenstein in 1980 but was found not guilty by reason of insanity and sent to New York State mental institution; examines aspects of case, notably wholesale changes in use of insanity defense in US court cases since Lowenstein's murder; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until this month, Dennis Sweeney was the only killer in New York State who was required by law to go twice a month to a mental hospital for a six-hour sleepover.</p>
        <p>Around midnight, he drove to a state hospital in Middletown, N.Y., said hello to the duty nurse and picked out an empty bed on the third floor. He woke himself at dawn, walked out of the hospital and returned to the carefully calculated anonymity of his small-town life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until this month, Dennis Sweeney was the only killer in New York State who was required by law to go twice a month to a mental hospital for a six-hour sleepover.</p>
        <p>Around midnight, he drove to a state hospital in Middletown, N.Y., said hello to the duty nurse and picked out an empty bed on the third floor. He woke himself at dawn, walked out of the hospital and returned to the carefully calculated anonymity of his small-town life.</p>
        <p>This odd and empty ritual, which he has performed without fail for more than five years, was the endgame in a legal and psychiatric odyssey that began two decades ago when Mr. Sweeney committed a crime that dumbfounded a generation of Americans who came of age in the 1960's.</p>
        <p>On March 14, 1980, he walked into a law office in Rockefeller Plaza and shot dead Allard K. Lowenstein, the former congressman whose liberal passion helped shape a decade of civil-rights and antiwar activism. Mr. Lowenstein had been his friend and mentor. But after his arrest, Mr. Sweeney told psychiatrists that he was convinced by voices in his head that Mr. Lowenstein was part of a Jewish plot to destroy him. After a quick diagnosis of paranoid schizophrenia, Mr. Sweeney was found not guilty by reason of insanity and packed off to a state mental hospital.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Sweeney's sleepovers at the mental hospital suggest, the laws and procedures that define insanity and have ruled his life for more than a third of his 57 years are often arbitrary and sometimes useless. The process, too, has a history of being turned upside down in response to public fear, populist politics and sensational crimes like the shooting of President Reagan.</p>
        <p>The treatment of the man who killed Al Lowenstein spans an era of wholesale change in the insanity defense in America. While the very meaning of insanity was being rewritten in legislatures and reinterpreted in the courts, Mr. Sweeney was living in Middletown, about 70 miles northwest of Midtown Manhattan, and making what his psychiatrists describe as a rare and impressive recovery.</p>
        <p>The dental crowns that he gouged out of his mouth with a hacksaw blade in the early 1970's -- in an attempt to silence the voices -- have been replaced. Mr. Sweeney has said the voices disappeared more than a decade ago, and doctors at Middletown Psychiatric Center say they believe him.</p>
        <p>Hospital furloughs have allowed him to find a job as an employment counselor. He rents a house with a fine view of the Shawangunk Mountains. He is active in the Unitarian Universalist Church in Middletown and managed a Habitat for Humanity project there that built a house for a disabled couple.</p>
        <p>For about a year, court records show, he has been romantically involved with a woman who works as a counselor to the mentally ill, and he has told her about his violent past. He refused repeated requests to grant an interview for this article.</p>
        <p>Justice Brenda Soloff of State Supreme Court in Manhattan has been tracking Mr. Sweeney's progress for more than 15 years, and on June 30, she ordered a conditional release that will end his sleepovers at the mental hospital. Those visits were a legal fig leaf, she said, covering the reality that he is ''an inpatient in name only.''</p>
        <p>In her decision, the judge concluded that ''for six years, without medication, Dennis Sweeney has been building an ever more complex, satisfying and successful life in the community.''</p>
        <p>Changing Attitudes  Reagan Attack Tilted Legal Landscape</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney's recovery and return to everyday life would, in all likelihood, have been impossible had he pulled the trigger after John W. Hinckley Jr. shot President Reagan in 1981. Mr. Hinckley was later found not guilty by reason of insanity -- a decision that roiled public opinion and prodded politicians to act.</p>
        <p>In 1984, Congress sharply raised the bar for the insanity plea. It changed the test of incompetence from whether defendants appreciated their acts or could control their behavior to a more restrictive standard: Did they know right from wrong? Congress also shifted the burden of proof. Where once the prosecution had to establish reasonable doubt about an insanity plea, the defense now has to show convincing evidence to support the plea.</p>
        <p>States followed the federal lead, with two-thirds restricting the defense. Twelve states adopted a guilty but mentally ill verdict, 7 narrowed the test for insanity, 16 shifted the burden of proof, and 25 tightened release rules for those found not guilty by reason of insanity. New York State narrowed the test and shifted the burden of proof.</p>
        <p>Changes in the law followed a sea change in public attitudes, according to legal scholars, as the insanity defense generated mounting skepticism. Psychiatrists who testified as expert witnesses also retooled the way they judged the sanity of people who committed murder.</p>
        <p>''Before Hinckley, our approaches erred on the side of finding insanity,'' said Dr. Park Dietz, a psychiatrist who has been an expert witness, usually for the prosecution, in some of the most notable insanity defense cases of the past 20 years, including Mr. Hinckley's, Jeffrey Dahmer's and the Unabomber's. ''The approach launched in 1981 would, in the Sweeney case, have looked very specifically at whether he knew Lowenstein was a man who could be injured or killed by shooting, and whether he knew that the police would come and want to punish him.''</p>
        <p>By that standard, several psychiatrists said, Mr. Sweeney was sane when he killed Mr. Lowenstein. And by that standard, had he shot Mr. Lowenstein after 1984, Mr. Sweeney would have probably been found guilty of murder, sentenced to life in prison and would still be behind bars.</p>
        <p>Even for those found not guilty by reason of insanity, the notoriety of a crime itself -- irrespective of a patient's recovery from mental illness -- often governs the length of confinement in mental hospitals.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Sweeney had shot someone who was not famous, he probably would have won a conditional release from Middletown Psychiatric Center several years earlier, according to researchers who study forensic law.</p>
        <p>''These people tend to silt up in the system,'' said Henry Steadman, a sociologist who worked for the New York State Office of Mental Health for 17 years and whose specialty is assessing the risk of releasing mental patients. ''They have committed heinous offenses, the public is afraid of them and prosecutors are reluctant to release them. The political valence in these cases significantly impedes the practice of good psychiatry.''</p>
        <p>The determination that a once-homicidal patient no longer suffers from a dangerous mental illness is an art, not a science, and mental health experts agree that it is subject to error.</p>
        <p>''Predicting a harmful event such as violence is very much like predicting harmful weather -- estimates rather than guarantees are all that can be expected,'' said John Monahan, a psychologist and professor of law at the University of Virginia who specializes in risk assessment.</p>
        <p>That Mr. Sweeney is an excellent risk, as judged by mental health professionals, is of little comfort to Mr. Lowenstein's survivors.</p>
        <p>His widow and his children say they are afraid of Mr. Sweeney, as do two of his own former friends. Court records show that Mr. Sweeney has told friends about his ability to pull the wool over the eyes of psychiatrists.</p>
        <p>Asked if Mr. Sweeney might now be covering up his violent delusions, two risk assessment experts said it was highly unlikely. They said that psychiatrists tend to err on the side of caution. But they said no one, except Mr. Sweeney, could be absolutely certain.</p>
        <p>A Life Unravels  Before the Voices, Idealism and Courage</p>
        <p>Until it was ruined by the voices in his head, the life of Dennis Sweeney had been shaped by idealism and by his own considerable courage.</p>
        <p>He grew up in Portland, Ore., the only son of working-class parents who separated when he was an infant. His father, a military pilot, was later killed in Korea. Dennis grew up bookish, athletic and handsome. He won a scholarship to Stanford University.</p>
        <p>At Stanford he met the charismatic Mr. Lowenstein and became one of his disciples. When his mentor asked him to go to Mississippi in 1963 and join the civil rights movement, Mr. Sweeney went. For most of the next three years, he devoted his life to the movement. While he was working in McComb, Miss., his house was dynamited.  Mr. Sweeney made a name for himself as thoughtful, effective and quietly fearless, according to ''Dreams Die Hard,'' a book about Mr. Sweeney and Mr. Lowenstein by David Harris, a friend of both men.</p>
        <p>In 1964, the book said, he came to share the feelings of black activists in Mississippi who felt patronized by white Northern liberals like Mr. Lowenstein. The idealistic student turned against his loquacious mentor. The break was given a nudge when Mr. Sweeney, according to an account he later told several friends, was asked by Mr. Lowenstein to share his bed. It was an invitation offered to a number of Mr. Lowenstein's male acolytes, according to a friend of Mr. Lowenstein, Mr. Harris's book and other published reports,  but friends say Mr. Sweeney found it especially disturbing.</p>
        <p>As the civil rights movement gave way, for white liberals, to protests against the Vietnam War, Mr. Sweeney's life came undone. A marriage failed. His friends said he took a lot of LSD. According to prosecutors in New York, as well as Mr. Harris's book, Mr. Sweeney helped to burn an R.O.T.C. clubhouse at Stanford in February 1968, and was questioned about it by the F.B.I., though he was never charged.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, after he dropped out of college and lost touch with most of his friends, Mr. Sweeney began telling people about an electrode planted in his head. He gouged out his bridgework. He declined voluntary psychiatric treatment in Oregon. He assaulted a former friend in Boston. He confronted Mr. Lowenstein about the voices. Finally, after the death of his stepfather, for which in his delusional state he blamed Mr. Lowenstein, he applied for a permit to buy a handgun. He bought the gun in New London, Conn., and drove his pickup through a rainstorm to keep an appointment with Mr. Lowenstein in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>A Rapid Diagnosis  Spitting Out the Devil Into a Plastic Cup</p>
        <p>After Mr. Sweeney was arrested and taken to jail on Rikers Island, psychiatrists had no trouble with a diagnosis. He kept trying to ''spit out the devil'' into a plastic foam cup. Mr. Lowenstein was not really dead, he claimed, and was still out to get him.</p>
        <p>Persecutory delusions are classic symptoms of paranoid schizophrenia. Anyone with his diagnosis would today be treated with a mix of powerful pyschotropic medications, psychiatrists say.</p>
        <p>What puts Mr. Sweeney ''outside the curve'' of standard treatment, said Dr. Robert H. Berger, director of forensic psychiatry at Bellevue Hospital Center, is that for almost two decades his recovery has been without drugs.</p>
        <p>Since 1985, his recovery has been so seemingly free of the usual symptoms of schizophrenia that examining psychiatrists, including Dr. Berger, have questioned whether he was misdiagnosed. They wondered if he might have had some other mental disorder.</p>
        <p>In the end, though, two generations of doctors have concluded that everything in his history fits the pattern of schizophrenia. The chronic disease is a gradually deteriorating onset of auditory hallucinations and psychosis. Still poorly understood, it is attributed to genetic vulnerability, brain chemistry imbalances and life stresses, sometimes including the effects of drugs like LSD.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of studies of patients with schizophrenia have reported recovery rates ranging from 10 percent to 50 percent, with or without medication. The National Institute of Mental Health, however, now says no more than 20 percent of schizophrenics ever fully recover.</p>
        <p>The capacity to calmly obtain a gun permit and make an appointment for homicide does not square with popular notions of insanity, but psychiatrists say it does fit the profile of paranoid schizophrenics. They typically appear far more normal than other psychotics because, outside of delusions, most of their thinking remains intact. To protect themselves from perceived enemies, they are adept at deception.</p>
        <p>Deception has been a recurrent concern in Mr. Sweeney's case. By 1985, his treating psychiatrists said he showed no signs of illness. Describing him as ''alert, intelligent, friendly, respectful and cooperative,'' they wanted to transfer him from a maximum-security hospital to a nonsecure one.</p>
        <p>In court hearings the following year, however, evidence emerged that Mr. Sweeney was lying to his doctors. He confided to Charles Hinkle, an old friend from Oregon, that to win his release he had falsely said he no longer heard voices. By then, court records show, Mr. Hinkle was afraid of his friend. When Mr. Sweeney found out in 1986 that Mr. Hinkle had told prosecutors about the voices, he angrily broke off their friendship.</p>
        <p>Ten years later, Mr. Hinkle told a psychiatrist involved in the case that he hoped Mr. Sweeney would never be allowed back in Oregon. When Mr. Sweeney learned about this, he wrote Mr. Hinkle a furious letter calling the statement ''disgustingly shrewish.'' Mr. Hinkle, a lawyer in Portland for the American Civil Liberties Union, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Psychiatrists who specialize in murder consider Mr. Sweeney's case particularly rare.</p>
        <p>''I would have to say that his is the only case that I have personally examined where I believe there has been a spontaneous remission from schizophrenia without medication,'' said Dr. Dietz, who says he has examined thousands of murderers. He advised the court in 1993 that Mr. Sweeney would most likely be ready for release within a year.</p>
        <p>Immediately after the doctor gave his recommendation, however, he pulled aside Mr. Lowenstein's widow, a psychiatric social worker, and gave her a private warning that he routinely imparts to families of victims: No good could come of any contact between her family and Mr. Sweeney.</p>
        <p>A Troubling Encounter  Her Father's Killer Offers an Explanation</p>
        <p>Kate Lowenstein was 9 when Mr. Sweeney killed her father, but family friends say she was determined to attend a hearing this year on Mr. Sweeney's release. It was a way, somehow, to represent her father's life.</p>
        <p>In the courtroom during a recess, Mr. Sweeney looked her straight in the eye and walked over. Mr. Sweeney was ''fairly certain'' he recognized the young woman in the last row, he later told the court. Ms. Lowenstein was astonished that he knew her. At most, he had seen her once before, when she was a toddler and he was deep in his delusions.</p>
        <p>He would tell the court that he ''just felt like it was one of those situations where the silence was unbearable and I wanted to say something.'' No one else in the courtroom was watching. He started by offering an apology, according to court records.</p>
        <p>Do you know what you did to me? Ms. Lowenstein asked in reply.</p>
        <p>He said that he did not.</p>
        <p>You broke my heart, she told him.</p>
        <p>Leaning closer, he tried to explain why he had done it. She seemed frozen by distress by the time lawyers ran over to her. Outside the courtroom door, she broke down. The words of Mr. Sweeney's explanation, as she wrote them down, were: ''The only reason I did what I did was to stop something terrible from happening. You can't understand that, but I had to do it. I had to stop it.''</p>
        <p>Prosecutors have repeatedly delayed Mr. Sweeney's release, turning up information overlooked by his changing cast of therapists. ''It's not a question of whether we worked hard to keep him in,'' said Ralph Fabrizio, a prosecutor. ''We tried hard to see what was going on.''</p>
        <p>They fought to retain Mr. Sweeney's fictional inpatient status at Middletown Psychiatric, Mr. Fabrizio said, because legally it made it easier to reel him back in if he tried, for example, to contact members of the Lowenstein family.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors say they want a short enough leash on Mr. Sweeney to keep him from slipping through what they call a gap in the law. Once he is granted conditional release, he cannot be recommitted just for breaking conditions imposed by the court. A judge would have to rule that he was dangerously mentally ill.</p>
        <p>There is, though, an alternative -- a petition for involuntary civil commitment. In practice, officials at Middletown Psychiatric said, this option, which requires the signatures of two psychiatrists, is routinely used to bring in patients on conditional release who are judged to be regressing.</p>
        <p>To the prosecutors, the courtroom encounter with Ms. Lowenstein was a disturbing illustration of Mr. Sweeney's poor judgment, if not his skewed thinking. They wanted to get it on the record. But when Mr. Fabrizio told Ms. Lowenstein he might have to call her as a witness, ''she just turned ashen,'' he said.</p>
        <p>They both knew what the psychiatrist had told her mother.</p>
        <p>The Cusp of Freedom  Weaving a New Web Of Life and Love</p>
        <p>In Middletown, it took Mr. Sweeney eight years to convince psychiatrists at a maximum-security mental hospital that he was a good risk for transfer to a nonsecure facility. It took three more years for him to convince officials at Middletown Psychiatric Center that he was a good risk for unescorted furloughs.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Sweeney has had to convince people in a semirural community of 50,000 that he is not dangerous. It has not been easy.</p>
        <p>Publicity cost Mr. Sweeney his first job, counseling mentally disabled adults at an agency called Crystal Run Village, when a reporter told administrators that he was writing a story about a psychotic killer working with vulnerable people.</p>
        <p>''The handwriting was on the wall and people were running for cover,'' said Mark Lukens, then executive director at the agency. ''We told Dennis about the story and he resigned.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney started over, working as secretary, lumber-store clerk and carpenter. It took him six years to land a job he really wanted, as an employment counselor. Meanwhile, he joined a church and told its members about his illness and the killing.</p>
        <p>When the same newspaper, The Times Herald-Record, in a 1994 article about the local hospital, mentioned him in passing as a ''notorious patient,'' Mr. Sweeney complained in a letter to the editor.</p>
        <p>''It has not been my experience that people I have met over the past two and a half years bear me hostility or begrudge me a life, as long as I do not represent a potential danger to the community or anyone in it,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>He went on to accuse the newspaper of trying to sabotage his chances for work or friendship. Since then, Mr. Sweeney has been mentioned twice in the paper for his work with Habitat for Humanity. He was described only as ''a former Oregon resident.''</p>
        <p>Several psychiatrists familiar with Mr. Sweeney's life said that the best insurance that he will not slip back into dangerous mental illness is the web of work, home and love that he appears to have woven for himself in Middletown. Even psychiatrists who do not find Mr. Sweeney to be a charming person -- and there are several -- say his release is sound on medical grounds.</p>
        <p>''He is an obsessive-compulsive man who is very intellectualized, not a warm, mushy, caring person,'' said Dr. Alan J. Tuckman, one of the examining psychiatrists who recommended release. ''But that's not the standard. If somebody is going to have recurrent schizophrenic episodes, they are not going to occur every 20 years.''</p>
        <p>As part of his conditional release, the precise terms of which are still being argued in court, officials at Middletown Psychiatric say Mr. Sweeney will continue in psychotherapy and will be visited at home at least twice a year. He has been ordered to stay away from the Lowenstein family and from two former friends who fear him, Mr. Hinkle and the man he assaulted in Massachusetts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
