<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heritage of Gold Captures A Duel Amid the Puddles</title>
    <meta content="31RACI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Go for Wand Stakes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05EFDC133DF932A05754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heritage of Gold Captures A Duel Amid the Puddles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y., July 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Heritage of Gold wins Go For Wand Stakes at Saratoga (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They staggered back toward the winner's circle, splattered with mud, in a cleansing drizzle. One mare, Beautiful Pleasure, had been crowned a champion in 1999. The other, Heritage of Gold, had just run Beautiful Pleasure down to validate her intention to take that crown. The crowd rose to its feet and thundered applause for the two rivals' effort in a duel down the stretch at Saratoga which splashed drama as well as puddles all the way to the wire.</p>
        <p>The bare facts are that, for the second time this year, Heritage of Gold bested Beautiful Pleasure, ran her victory record for the year to 5 of 5 and poured $150,000 more into her owner's coffers by capturing the $250,000 Go For Wand Stakes. That, however, does not reflect the anguish that the trainer Tom Amoss and the owner Jack Garey muddled through trying to decide whether Heritage of Gold might have a chance to duel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They staggered back toward the winner's circle, splattered with mud, in a cleansing drizzle. One mare, Beautiful Pleasure, had been crowned a champion in 1999. The other, Heritage of Gold, had just run Beautiful Pleasure down to validate her intention to take that crown. The crowd rose to its feet and thundered applause for the two rivals' effort in a duel down the stretch at Saratoga which splashed drama as well as puddles all the way to the wire.</p>
        <p>The bare facts are that, for the second time this year, Heritage of Gold bested Beautiful Pleasure, ran her victory record for the year to 5 of 5 and poured $150,000 more into her owner's coffers by capturing the $250,000 Go For Wand Stakes. That, however, does not reflect the anguish that the trainer Tom Amoss and the owner Jack Garey muddled through trying to decide whether Heritage of Gold might have a chance to duel.</p>
        <p>Garey, who is from Texas, told Amoss two days ago that if the track turned sloppy by today's race, he wanted to wait to take on Beautiful Pleasure, last year's champion older filly, some other day. In 22 career races and 14 victories, Heritage of Gold, a 5-year-old daughter of Gold Legend, had run on turf and dirt, long and short, on at least seven tracks. But she never puddle-jumped on a soggy track. Amoss stalled his owner. Wait and see, he told him, for most of the afternoon. Finally after the fourth race, it was time to decide.</p>
        <p>''But there is something about Saratoga and being here,'' Amoss said. ''If he was back at home in Austin, I'm sure he wouldn't have run. He got all caught up it and said to me, 'What do you want to do?' I told him I was speaking very subjectively, but I want to take her on.''</p>
        <p>When the gates popped open on the mile-and-an-eighth race, Amoss admitted, he thought he should have listened to his boss. Beautiful Pleasure, who in winning three previous races on wet tracks looked as if she had webbed feet, torpedoed to the rail and built what appeared to be an insurmountable seven-length lead.</p>
        <p>''I thought we were in trouble,'' Amoss said. ''All of a sudden, we were back so far and you start to wonder if the race is over. I turned to my family and said, 'At least we're starting to pick her up.' ''</p>
        <p>He did not really believe it, however, until the jockey Shane Sellers hustled Heritage of Gold around the turn and subtracted four lengths from Beautiful Pleasure's lead. Sellers said he knew that he had Beautiful Pleasure in trouble when her rider, Jorge Chavez, turned back and looked him in the eye.</p>
        <p>''I saw Choppy look back,'' said Sellers, referring to the nickname the Peruvian rider has developed for his short whip strokes. ''He still had us. But my mare was moving easy and I had the momentum.''</p>
        <p>The crowd of 58,584 sensed it and bounced to its feet as Heritage of Gold collared Beautiful Pleasure, the heavily bet 1-5 favorite, at the quarter pole. Sellers and his mare ran in stride with Beautiful Pleasure for 30 yards until Heritage of Gold catapulted ahead in the middle of the track for a one-length victory that paid $7.90 for a $2 bet to win.</p>
        <p>''It was fair and square; no excuses,'' Beautiful Pleasure's trainer, John Ward, said of his mare, who has earned more than $2.2 million in purses. ''We'll get a rematch.''</p>
        <p>It will probably not come until November, however, and the Breeders' Cup Championship at Churchill Downs in Kentucky. But, for an afternoon at least, Amoss overruled his owner and got away with it. He was at once gracious and relieved.</p>
        <p>''Anyone who really appreciates horse racing, no matter who the horses were involved, saw a super race,'' Amoss said.</p>
        <p>Garey agreed but could not help beating his chest a bit.</p>
        <p>''She didn't get any respect coming into this race, and didn't get any respect from the bettors either,'' Garey said. ''We proved that we have the best dirt female in the country.''</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
