<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Egan Delivers Blunt Message For Elections</title>
    <meta content="30EGAN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/nyregion/30EGAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243272"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED81430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Egan Delivers Blunt Message For Elections</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Archbishop Edward M Egan, interjecting New York Roman Catholic Archdiocese directly into next week's elections, bluntly urges its 2.4 million parishioners to cast votes for candidates in local, state and national races who 'share our commitment to fundamental rights for unborn'; Egan's remarks are contained in letter sent to 413 parishes in diocese (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Interjecting the New York Roman Catholic Archdiocese directly into next week's elections, Archbishop Edward M. Egan yesterday bluntly urged its 2.4 million parishioners to cast votes for candidates in local, state and national races who ''share our commitment to fundamental rights for the unborn.''</p>
        <p>The archbishop's remarks were contained in a letter he sent to the 413 parishes in the diocese, instructing that it be read before Masses on Saturday night and yesterday. A rector read the letter at the start of the 10:15 a.m. Mass yesterday at St. Patrick's Cathedral, and Archbishop Egan emphasized some points during his homily.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Interjecting the New York Roman Catholic Archdiocese directly into next week's elections, Archbishop Edward M. Egan yesterday bluntly urged its 2.4 million parishioners to cast votes for candidates in local, state and national races who ''share our commitment to fundamental rights for the unborn.''</p>
        <p>The archbishop's remarks were contained in a letter he sent to the 413 parishes in the diocese, instructing that it be read before Masses on Saturday night and yesterday. A rector read the letter at the start of the 10:15 a.m. Mass yesterday at St. Patrick's Cathedral, and Archbishop Egan emphasized some points during his homily.</p>
        <p>The letter did not stake out new doctrinal ground. Both Archbishop Egan and his predecessor, Cardinal John O'Connor, routinely declared their opposition to abortion, euthanasia and racial discrimination, as well as their support for school vouchers. And the archbishop's letter reiterated his position on those issues.</p>
        <p>But it was a departure of sorts for Archbishop Egan. Since his installation four months ago, he has largely maintained a low-key profile, although he did issue a statement on Oct. 1 against the federal Food and Drug Administration's approval of the abortion pill RU-486. He shied away from direct political commentary at the recent Alfred E. Smith Memorial Dinner, an annual archdiocesan event that drew Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas. Cardinal O'Connor had often used the dinner as a platform to express his political views.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, though, the archbishop stood in the towering stone pulpit at St. Patrick's and told about 2,000 worshipers that he felt obliged to speak out on moral matters during this election season and that bold statements were expected from the New York archbishop.</p>
        <p>''One of the reasons I am so happy to come to New York is because here in New York we say just what's on our mind and we don't care,'' he said. ''Some people call it chutzpah. I call it part of our charm.''</p>
        <p>He did not mention political candidates or parties by name in either the letter or his homily. But both made clear that the archbishop expected his parishioners to take candidates' stands on abortion and euthanasia, among other matters, into account when casting ballots on Nov. 7.</p>
        <p>''All of us will have an opportunity to choose leaders for our nation, our state and our local communities who share our commitment to fundamental rights for the unborn, those advanced in age, the sick and the needy,'' the letter said. ''As you cast your ballot, I prayerfully urge you to take a stand worthy of the community of faith of which you are a member.''</p>
        <p>It is not routine in the New York Archdiocese for priests to suggest to parishioners how to vote. When on occasion Cardinal O'Connor stepped into the political arena, he sometimes evoked intense and critical responses, as in 1984, when he said at a news conference, ''I do not see how a Catholic in good conscience'' could vote for a political candidate favoring abortion. He then refused to rule out the possibility that he might excommunicate Gov. Mario M. Cuomo over the governor's support of abortion rights.</p>
        <p>The archdiocese's spokesman, Joseph G. Zwilling, said yesterday that he could not recall a time in which Cardinal O'Connor sent out a parish letter similar to the one from Archbishop Egan just before an election.</p>
        <p>But church commentators said the archbishop's remarks largely reflected a 1998 directive from the National Conference of Catholic Bishops declaring that church leaders had a pastoral duty to ''persuade, correct and admonish'' elected leaders who supported abortion rights so that they might undergo a ''change of heart.'' The conference also instructed the bishops to urge parishioners to register their opposition to abortion by speaking out and voting.</p>
        <p>''Around the country, there's a trend toward parish priests providing homilies that are more focused on the nexus between the church's moral teaching and specific political issues before the electorate,'' R. Scott Appleby, director of the Cushwa Center for the Study of American Catholicism at the University of Notre Dame, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to evaluate the impact Archbishop Egan's remarks will have on the elections. Democratic and Republican analysts yesterday questioned how much influence church directives had on contemporary New York voters, saying that those who would most likely be swayed by them generally lean toward more conservative, anti-abortion candidates anyway.</p>
        <p>In the United States Senate race in New York, Hillary Rodham Clinton and her Republican opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio, both consider themselves supporters of abortion rights, although Mr. Lazio favors some restrictions.</p>
        <p>The archbishop's letter addressed subjects other than abortion. ''In the coming election,'' he wrote, ''in addition to issues of basic human rights, there will also be addressed the questions of parents' rights to decide how their children are to be educated.''</p>
        <p>He urged Catholics to support candidates who favor allowing government money to be used to pay tuition at private or parochial schools.</p>
        <p>Again, he did not specify a particular candidate or party, which Dr. Appleby said was a common approach among Roman Catholic leaders in recent years, despite their more political tenor.</p>
        <p>''It is significant to note that the church has stopped short in most of cases of endorsing or denouncing particular candidates,'' Dr. Appleby said. ''In fact, Catholics are left with quite complicated decisions to make as to which candidates would be the true champion of the whole range of Catholic social and moral concerns.''</p>
        <p>Several worshipers at St. Patrick's yesterday said they agreed with the archbishop's comments.</p>
        <p>''It is about time the bishop spoke out,'' said Silvio D. Buccieri of Port Chester, N.Y., who attended the 10:15 Mass with his wife and mother and a friend. ''The church has more or less been silent, afraid to appear as if it is taking a position.''</p>
        <p>But others said they were disappointed. Elaine Dwyer of Liverpool, England, said she found the archbishop's remarks on abortion 'too political, too pushy.''</p>
        <p>''It is a private matter that no woman takes lightheartedly,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
