<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E-Commerce Report; To make online shopping easier and quicker, many Web sites are redesigning their home pages.</title>
    <meta content="30ECOM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/technology/30ECOMMERCE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243192"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tedeschi, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/E-Commerce</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Operations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/E-Commerce Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E5DF1430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1356" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E-Commerce Report; To make online shopping easier and quicker, many Web sites are redesigning their home pages.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bob Tedeschi</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tedeschi, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many Web sites are redesigning home pages to make online shopping easier and quicker; analysts say moves may not be enough to stave off further dot-com failures, but could presage better days for e-tailers who survive into 2001; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BUSINESS-MINDED archaeologists who pick through the rubble of the e-tailing fiasco will have little trouble piecing together what went wrong. With every new rollout of a Web store in 1998 and 1999 came declarations that the shop in question would revolutionize the buying experience by making it so much easier than shopping the traditional way.</p>
        <p>The truth, of course, is that it was too seldom truly easy. Poorly designed sites could turn the experience into one of hair-tugging frustration that was just as slow as a trip to the local store. Factor in problems with privacy, security, customer service and shipping, and it is little wonder why the revolution has been slow to arrive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BUSINESS-MINDED archaeologists who pick through the rubble of the e-tailing fiasco will have little trouble piecing together what went wrong. With every new rollout of a Web store in 1998 and 1999 came declarations that the shop in question would revolutionize the buying experience by making it so much easier than shopping the traditional way.</p>
        <p>The truth, of course, is that it was too seldom truly easy. Poorly designed sites could turn the experience into one of hair-tugging frustration that was just as slow as a trip to the local store. Factor in problems with privacy, security, customer service and shipping, and it is little wonder why the revolution has been slow to arrive.</p>
        <p>It is a bittersweet paradox that now, as the e-tailing morgue fills up, industry survivors and the nearly dead are actually starting to deliver on their promise of easy shopping. Take Web site design. Entering the holiday season, many e-commerce sites are revamping their navigation systems to help shoppers find the right products quickly, without wading through a sea of irrelevant information or wasting 10 clicks in search of a gift.</p>
        <p>Home pages, logically, are first in line for the redesign. Executives and site navigation experts say that companies are finally getting the message that simpler is better. As the year progressed, most sites grudgingly gave up on multimedia filigree they hoped would get shoppers' attention and entertain them. Now, they are giving up on home pages that overwhelm customers with too much information. Analysts said the resulting improvement in sales might not be enough to stave off further dot-com bloodshed, but it could presage better days for those e-tailers fortunate enough to make it into 2001.</p>
        <p>Amazon.com is a prime example of a site making things simpler. The company recently rolled out a newly designed welcome page that eliminated most of the so-called ''tabs'' that dominated the top margin of the page. Amazon has also deleted many of the graphics, links and promotional text that had cluttered the page.</p>
        <p>Maryam Mohit, vice president of site design for Amazon, said the design team was influenced by the book ''Why We Buy: The Science of Shopping,'' by Paco Underhill (Simon &amp; Schuster Trade, 1999 )in which the author discussed how shoppers approach traditional storefronts. ''When you come into a store, you need a soft landing where you can take a breath and orient yourself, as opposed to getting assaulted by a barrage of offers all at once,'' Ms. Mohit said. ''We wanted to create that soft landing online.''</p>
        <p>The company succeeded nicely in the eyes of many analysts. Rebecca Nidositko, an analyst with Yankee Group, lauded Amazon's redesign in a recent report, noting that it was particularly welcome, since the new navigation system ''is sure to be emulated by many other online retailers.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, when Amazon first began using tabs at the top of its pages in 1998, the idea quickly became standard fare among retailers -- even those with a more narrow range of product categories. But Ms. Nidositko said other retailers would be wise not to follow Amazon's lead blindly this time, ''since at different stages in your business, you want to do different things with your home page.''</p>
        <p>For instance, Ms. Nidositko said, new online retailers -- if any such animals exist -- could use large, simple images on their home pages to establish their brands with customers, while older sites could afford to devote more space on the home page to shopping information like sales, best-selling products and other promotions.</p>
        <p>Tracy Wan, president and chief operating officer of the Sharper Image Corporation, agreed. ''We look at Amazon all the time, just like all good retailers watch the competition.'' Still, Ms. Wan said, the companies diverge in their approach to the home page. ''We've always been a little more subtle than other companies,'' she said. ''We want to sell, but we don't want a hard sell.''</p>
        <p>Among other considerations, she said, that means using less space for the home page than other sites. On Amazon and many other sites, the home page extends two or more screens below what the user initially sees. Rather than force the customer to scroll down the page to see more information, Ms. Wan said, the Sharper Image home page fits nearly all of its content and images within one screen. ''It's just like a storefront window,'' she said. ''You've got one shot at capturing them.''</p>
        <p>In this and other regards, Internet shoppers are moving targets. According to Jakob Nielsen, a principal of the Nielsen Norman Group, which advises companies on Web site design, 90 percent of Internet users in 1994 would only look at one screen on the home page, ''because the programs people used on their computers showed everything on one page. Now, people will go to three screens before they stop scrolling.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Mr. Nielsen said he counseled sites to convey as much basic information about the site as simply as possible on the first page. ''The home page has to do three things: Tell the user whose site they're on, tell them what they can do on the site, and where to go to get what they want.''</p>
        <p>Naturally, that is more easily said than done -- as the designers of Walmart.com have found. The company rolled out a new version of its Web site in January, only to be greeted by tepid reviews. Earlier this month the company made the unusual decision of closing  down the store entirely while it prepared a new version of the site. That version is expected to open on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Erik Hagerman, creative director for Walmart.com, said the company was in a particularly thorny position, because it must determine a way to tell users how to find some 500,000 items on the site quickly and simply, without using so many graphics and so much text that the site slows down. A fast-loading first page is critically important in sending a message to users that the entire shopping experience will be fast, Mr. Hagerman and others said.</p>
        <p>As a result, he said, the site will feature no tabs, and just 12 product categories, without frills. ''We treated every 'K' as something precious,'' he said, using industry shorthand for a kilobit, the standard measure for a piece of data on the Internet.</p>
        <p>Similar attention to the user would do much to brighten the prospects of e-commerce in general, according to a recent report by Creative Good, a consulting firm. In a recent test, the company found that 43 percent of shoppers who tried to buy something online failed, because of poorly designed sites. The report further stated that e-commerce companies would lose $14 billion in holiday sales because of such design failures.</p>
        <p>Statistics like these are not lost on Paul Pappajohn, president of J. C. Penney's e-commerce division. Mr. Pappajohn said the site was on track to get roughly $300 million in sales this year, even though its current incarnation was, he said, ''cluttered and somewhat confusing.'' In mid-November, he said, a newly designed site will roll out, which, like other online merchants, will incorporate a more simplified home-page design. ''We did pretty well with the site as it is,'' he said. ''But we're going to do better.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
