<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Devils Find Goals In Strange Uniforms</title>
    <meta content="30DEVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/sports/30DEVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Penguins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4DC1430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Devils Find Goals In Strange Uniforms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils 9-0 victory over Pittsburgh Penguins discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils defeated the Penguins in Pittsburgh by 9-0 on Saturday night and were in a joking mood. They were reacting to the efforts of Randy McKay and John Madden, who combined to do something that had eluded such fearsome twosomes as Mario Lemieux and Jaromir Jagr, Mike Bossy and Bryan Trottier, and Wayne Gretzky and Mark Messier.</p>
        <p>McKay and Madden, two wings who are not linemates, scored four goals each in the victory, matching an accomplishment that had not been done by two National Hockey League teammates in 78 years, or since the Cleghorn brothers, Odie and Sprague, did it for the Montreal Canadiens in a 10-6 victory over the Hamilton Tigers on Jan. 14, 1922.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils defeated the Penguins in Pittsburgh by 9-0 on Saturday night and were in a joking mood. They were reacting to the efforts of Randy McKay and John Madden, who combined to do something that had eluded such fearsome twosomes as Mario Lemieux and Jaromir Jagr, Mike Bossy and Bryan Trottier, and Wayne Gretzky and Mark Messier.</p>
        <p>McKay and Madden, two wings who are not linemates, scored four goals each in the victory, matching an accomplishment that had not been done by two National Hockey League teammates in 78 years, or since the Cleghorn brothers, Odie and Sprague, did it for the Montreal Canadiens in a 10-6 victory over the Hamilton Tigers on Jan. 14, 1922.</p>
        <p>''Holy mackerel,'' Coach Larry Robinson said minutes after the game at Mellon Arena. ''I don't think I ever saw this even in peewee. It's just great for both guys. They worked extremely hard.''</p>
        <p>McKay and Madden, not known for their scoring prowess, became offensive wizards against a listless Pittsburgh team. They then absorbed a great deal of kidding from teammates, particularly Bobby Holik.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be tough to live with those two; luckily, we have another game soon,'' Holik said, referring to tonight's game with the Florida Panthers. ''If we had a week off, it would be a long week with these two.''</p>
        <p>McKay and Madden had earned the attention.</p>
        <p>McKay, sitting in the first seat in the dressing room, seemed taken aback when someone asked what he thought of Madden's four goals.</p>
        <p>''He said he was going for five,'' McKay said of Madden before talking about himself. ''It was just a great night. Bobby Holik was shaking his head every time I came off the ice after a goal. The funny thing is that I didn't feel good in the warm-ups after sitting around all day.''</p>
        <p>With his team playing to a 3-3 tie in Carolina a night earlier, Robinson canceled the morning skate Saturday, allowing his players to mill  around their hotel most of the day. The pace picked up at night.</p>
        <p>''It was one of those nights that when I touched the puck, it went in,'' said McKay, who leads the Devils with seven goals. ''I was in the right spot at the right time. Never scored four goals before, not at this level. I have to go back to high school for the last time I did this.''</p>
        <p>After McKay finished talking, Madden took the stage, saying he was happy to score just one goal, let alone four.</p>
        <p>''Things went our way because we played a solid game all around,'' Madden said.</p>
        <p>Turner Stevenson, who scored the first goal, joked that he was being overlooked.</p>
        <p>''You score the winning goal and you get third star,'' Stevenson said, rolling his eyes.</p>
        <p>The victory catapulted the Devils (5-2-2-0) past the Penguins (5-4-1-0) to the top of the Atlantic Division.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>A breakthrough may be imminent in the negotiations with the restricted free agents JASON ARNOTT and SCOTT NIEDERMAYER. LOU LAMORIELLO, the Devils' president and general manager, had a lengthy meeting yesterday with DON MEEHAN, the players' agent. Lamoriello and Meehan will talk by telephone again today. . . . The groin injury to PETR SYKORA will be evaluated today. . . . The shoulder injury to JAY PANDOLFO is more likely a separation than a bruise.  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
