<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Maimed Destroyer Cole Starts for Home</title>
    <meta content="Y30SHI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/world/30SHIP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cole (USS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States-International Relations-Yemen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yemen</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Yemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EFD81430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Maimed Destroyer Cole Starts for Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>ADEN, Yemen, Oct. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patched-up US destroyer USS Cole, aided by tugboats, limps away from Aden harbor in Yemen on first leg of return voyage to US almost 17 days after terrorist bombing killed 17 soldiers; will be raised onto deck of chartered Norwegian salvage ship in deeper waters offshore for five-week, 6,000-mile voyage; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With  battle ensign flying, crew on deck saluting and cheering and sound system booming songs ranging from ''The Star-Spangled Banner'' to an irreverent hit by the Detroit rapper Kid Rock, the patched-up destroyer Cole limped away from Aden harbor today with a show of unbowed pride as it cleared the moorings where 17 sailors were killed in a suicide bombing attack.</p>
        <p>Almost 17 days after the guided missile destroyer entered Aden for a refueling stop that turned into one of the most violent and humiliating moments in the Navy's peacetime history, the Cole was hitched to four yellow-nosed Yemeni tugs and moved out of the Gulf of Aden, where the harbor tugs handed it over to a deep-sea Navy tug, the Catawba.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With  battle ensign flying, crew on deck saluting and cheering and sound system booming songs ranging from ''The Star-Spangled Banner'' to an irreverent hit by the Detroit rapper Kid Rock, the patched-up destroyer Cole limped away from Aden harbor today with a show of unbowed pride as it cleared the moorings where 17 sailors were killed in a suicide bombing attack.</p>
        <p>Almost 17 days after the guided missile destroyer entered Aden for a refueling stop that turned into one of the most violent and humiliating moments in the Navy's peacetime history, the Cole was hitched to four yellow-nosed Yemeni tugs and moved out of the Gulf of Aden, where the harbor tugs handed it over to a deep-sea Navy tug, the Catawba.</p>
        <p>At first light on Monday, about 25 miles out, the Navy will begin the 36-hour task, itself risky and unprecedented, of raising the 8,600-ton ship onto the deck of a chartered Norwegian salvage ship for the five-week, 6,000-mile voyage home.</p>
        <p>The Cole's defiant exit came with the scars of the ordeal still visible in the jagged, 40-by-40-foot blast hole at the waterline and whole sections of the gunmetal-gray superstructure still rent and twisted from the attack made on Oct. 12 by two suicide bombers in an explosives-laden skiff. But the Navy, which says it intends to return the ship to service despite the costly task of rebuilding a mangled engine room and messhalls, as well as possible keel damage that will only be fully assessed in an American drydock, sent out an unmistakable message with the perky way in which it sent one of its most sophisticated warships out of the harbor.</p>
        <p>''What happened on Oct. 12 was a tragedy, it was an insult, but I think what was clear this morning as we watched the U.S.S. Cole is that it was not in any way a defeat,'' said Barbara K. Bodine, the American ambassador. Ms. Bodine has played a leading role in the large American task force sent to Aden to help in the struggle to keep the Cole from sinking, open a criminal investigation and devise ways of getting the crippled ship home.</p>
        <p>She added: ''The Cole left proudly.  She left with some help from her friends, but she left proudly.''</p>
        <p>The defiance was mixed with a bleak admission that it may be weeks, months or even longer before investigators can fulfill President Clinton's vow to track down those responsible for the attack. A week ago, after Yemeni security police officials found a string of safe houses used by the bombers, as well as an abandoned sport utility vehicle and a trailer used to launch the boat that carried the bomb, American officials said that a ''quantum leap'' had been made in the investigation. The advance reinforced the F.B.I.'s ''working theory'' that the attackers belonged to the same broad network of Afghan-trained Arabs who drove Soviet forces from Afghanistan, and  then turned in the 1990's to a ''holy war'' against the United States.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Bodine acknowledged today that no conclusive progress toward identifying the culprits had been made, and that the task ahead for the investigation ''will not be short, and it will not be easy.'' She implied that the investigation had gotten bogged down in trying to move beyond the initial breakthroughs, a problem American officials have said has been accentuated by a Yemeni security police embargo that has severely curtailed the F.B.I.'s role in the case. ''We do not have any suspects, and we do not know at this time who is behind this,'' Ms. Bodine said. ''I don't think anyone knows how long this will take.''</p>
        <p>The Cole's departure came after Navy frogmen, metal cutters, and welders and other specialists had worked around the clock for more than two weeks to get the ship seaworthy enough for a safe rendezvous with the salvage ship, the Blue Marlin, which the Navy has hired at a cost of $4.5 million to piggyback the destroyer. The salvage vessel, usually used for hoisting massive oil-drilling rigs in and out of the Persian Gulf and the North Sea, will employ an innovative technology in which it pumps water into its ballast tanks, slides under the Cole, then raises itself and the Navy ship by pumping the ballast water out again.</p>
        <p>Navy officials have acknowledged that lifting the Cole, which has to be done in waters 70 feet deep or more, is not foolproof, and that the risks are compounded by lingering uncertainties left after Navy divers inspected the Cole's hull and keel. But even those worries paled when set beside the tasks that had to be completed before the Navy could think about towing the Cole away.</p>
        <p>First, divers, metal cutters, welders and others had to recover the 17 sailors' bodies, a task that took nine days to complete. Then they had to weld new plates into the punctured hull and bulkheads, and pump out millions of gallons of seawater that had flooded the lower decks. Even late on Saturday, the welders could still be seen at work near the blast hole, sparks flying. A Navy spokesman said the repairs had left the ship ''structurally sound,'' but acknowledged that after the work here, the Cole was ''patched'' and ''cauterized'' -- in effect, a pale relic of the high-technology, cruise-missile-firing, billion-dollar ship it was.</p>
        <p>Long-term wounds to the Navy's pride may still lie ahead as admirals, senators and others, at inquiries already begun in Washington, investigate the reasons for the Pentagon's sending warships to refuel in a country called a ''safe haven for terrorists'' and then issuing orders that placed the ships at the second-lowest level of alert in the Navy's handbook. But today, at least, Cmdr. Karl S. Lippold, the Cole's captain, made sure that 200 crewmen still aboard held their heads high. As the ship cast off, the crew lined up at bow and stern to salute a giant Stars and Stripes fluttering stiffly from the mast, raised from half-mast after the mourning period for the sailors who were killed.</p>
        <p>Other red-and-yellow pennants, marking out a stay-clear warning used by mariners for centuries, signaled that the vessel was ''maneuvering with difficulty,'' under tow. Above, Navy attack helicopters prowled like hornets, and at least four picket boats with armed marines -- a precaution absent when the Cole arrived -- patrolled back and forth. But with thousands of Yemenis lining the harbor, and the crew of a rusting, Russian-built Yemeni navy patrol boat saluting, the main message was one of pride.</p>
        <p>Along with ''The Star-Spangled Banner,'' the recorded tunes blasted from the destroyer's loudspeakers included ''America the Beautiful,''  ''Anchors Aweigh,'' the Marine Hymn, and, by what the Navy said was the choice of the Cole's enlisted men, a rap identified by many American reporters as ''American Bad Ass'' by Kid Rock.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bodine, the American ambassador, described the choice of the rap song as a case of the crew's ''making a joyful noise.'' But heard from a shoreline sailors' club, it seemed encoded with defiance for violent Islamic groups, and an in-your-face exuberance at leaving Yemen.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bodine, the task force's sole spokesman for much of the last two weeks, acknowledged that little progress had been made in American attempts to reverse a Yemeni security police embargo that has sharply curtailed the F.B.I.'s role.</p>
        <p>''We are still -- negotiating is the wrong word -- we are still working with the Yemenis very closely on the modalities of how you do this,'' Ms. Bodine said. She said the United States remained confident that President Ali Abdullah Saleh would keep his commitment ''to seeing this through to the end.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
