<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sapp Pushes, and Vikings Plunge From Unbeaten Ranks</title>
    <meta content="Y30MIN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/sports/30MINN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Buccaneers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Vikings</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Minnesota Vikings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tampa Bay Buccaneers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE3DA1430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sapp Pushes, and Vikings Plunge From Unbeaten Ranks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., Oct. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tampa Bay Buccaneers defeat Minnesota Vikings, 41-13; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are few plays where Tampa Bay defensive lineman Warren Sapp does not make his presence known. His large frame, square and unwieldy, can overwhelm blockers, and his quickness is surprising.</p>
        <p>Sapp used both attributes to immediately set the tone of the game against Minnesota today, creating havoc along the Vikings' offensive line. His outburst fit perfectly with an excellent passing day by Shaun King, who teamed with Keyshawn Johnson to help beat Minnesota, the National Football League's last undefeated team, 41-13.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are few plays where Tampa Bay defensive lineman Warren Sapp does not make his presence known. His large frame, square and unwieldy, can overwhelm blockers, and his quickness is surprising.</p>
        <p>Sapp used both attributes to immediately set the tone of the game against Minnesota today, creating havoc along the Vikings' offensive line. His outburst fit perfectly with an excellent passing day by Shaun King, who teamed with Keyshawn Johnson to help beat Minnesota, the National Football League's last undefeated team, 41-13.</p>
        <p>On their game-opening possession, the Vikings were moving smoothly. On second down at the Minnesota 40-yard line, Sapp beat guard Corbin Lacina, curving around quarterback Daunte Culpepper's blind side. Lacina was one-on-one with Sapp -- never a good idea. Sapp knocked the ball out of Culpepper's hands, and it was recovered at the 14 by defensive end Marcus Jones.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay wasted little time before going to Johnson. He went in motion on second down and darted to the right side of the end zone. King, one of the most maligned quarterbacks in the league this season, threw a perfect dart to Johnson for a 9-yard touchdown.</p>
        <p>This is the Tampa Bay the N.F.L. expected coming into this season: Sapp dominating, Johnson scoring and King leading. For much of this season, the Buccaneers' offense has resembled something from the Pleistocene. Suddenly, against a familiar foe, it exploded, and caught in the supernova was Minnesota.</p>
        <p>Who let the offense out? ''Warren set the tone early,'' Johnson said, ''and then the offense followed. We opened things up on offense, and you see the results when we do that. I hope it continues. I think it will.''</p>
        <p>This is why Tampa Bay's Tony Dungy is one of the best coaches in the game. The Buccaneers, losers of four straight, never panicked, but they did go back to the drawing board in a sense. Against the Vikings, there was less of fullback Mike Alstott, who tends to slow things down, and more passing. As a result, Tampa Bay had a scoring feast.</p>
        <p>''We kind of knew how they were going to play us,'' Dungy said. ''We felt we could do a lot of three-wide stuff, they would put safety Robert Griffith up in the box, they would force us to throw the ball. They played us with a lot of seven- and eight-man fronts. We told the guys last night that the passing game is going to have to click for us.''</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay desperately needed the victory, and not just to end the losing streak. A Vikings victory would have given them a decisive lead in the National Football Conference Central. Now the Buccaneers (4-4) are again in the playoff hunt.</p>
        <p>Do not feel too sorry for Minnesota. The Vikings are still 7-1 and a possible Super Bowl team. Culpepper struggled, completing only 29 of 53 passes with 2 interceptions.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay scored on four of its first five possessions, and on the other one King went to his knee in the second quarter to run out the clock. Running back Warrick Dunn scored on a 23-yard touchdown catch to give Tampa Bay a 14-3 lead, and that was followed in the second quarter by a 20-yard touchdown pass from King to tight end Dave Moore, which made the score 21-10.</p>
        <p>The Tampa Bay defense then got into the act when Culpepper's pass was intercepted by linebacker Derrick Brooks and returned 34 yards for a score. Then Martin Gramatica connected on a 47-yard field goal.</p>
        <p>And like that, the offensively challenged Buccaneers had a 31-13 halftime lead. It tied the team record for most points in a half.</p>
        <p>King was brilliant, completing 16 of 23 passes for 267 yards and 4 touchdowns. Johnson had 6 catches for 121 yards and a score. Dunn had 11 carries for 89 yards. When those three players have those kinds of numbers, and Sapp is a one-man tropical storm (he had two tackles, one sack, one pass deflection and one forced fumble, with another strip of Culpepper reversed on replay), few teams can beat Tampa Bay.</p>
        <p>One thing that helped shake the Buccaneers from their offensive slumber was a conversation Johnson had last week with King. They met at the quarterback's house one night for more than three hours, and Johnson told King to stay in the pocket and hold the football as long as possible and Johnson would get open.</p>
        <p>''I gave him seven weeks without saying anything, and I said enough is enough,'' Johnson said. ''I had to tell him, 'We are going to do this thing together.' ''</p>
        <p>King listened.</p>
        <p>And the Buccaneers prospered.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
