<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poll Finds Little Voter Movement In Race for Senate in New York</title>
    <meta content="30POLL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times/cbs News Poll</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Connelly, Marjorie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E6D71430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poll Finds Little Voter Movement In Race for Senate in New York</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY and MARJORIE CONNELLY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam; Connelly, Marjorie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Times/CBS News Poll finds voter opinions about Hillary Rodham Clinton and Repr Rick A Lazio appear largely static as candidates enter final week of US Senate campaigns, despite three televised debates and barrage of television advertisements and attacks; finds some of Lazio's central attacks against Clinton have yet to take hold; finds voters are equally divided over which candidate would do better job of improving New York's economy; finds Clinton with 8-point, 49-41 percent lead over Lazio, statistically unchanged from September; poll's other findings discussed; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite three televised debates and a barrage of television advertisements and attacks, voter opinions about Hillary Rodham Clinton and Rick A. Lazio appear largely static as the candidates enter the final week of their contest, with Mrs. Clinton's prospects now very much dependent on the extent to which her supporters turn out to vote, according to the latest New York Times/CBS News Poll.</p>
        <p>The poll, taken Wednesday through Saturday, suggests that some of Mr. Lazio's central attacks on Mrs. Clinton in this final month of their Senate campaign have yet to take hold. Voters overwhelmingly said they believed that the first lady would do a better job at overhauling the health care system, even after a  week of attacks in which Mr. Lazio raised her failed advocacy of a national health care plan in 1994. And a slight majority said Mrs. Clinton was the stronger advocate of Israel, despite Mr. Lazio's escalating attacks on her Middle East views at a time of increasing unrest in the region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite three televised debates and a barrage of television advertisements and attacks, voter opinions about Hillary Rodham Clinton and Rick A. Lazio appear largely static as the candidates enter the final week of their contest, with Mrs. Clinton's prospects now very much dependent on the extent to which her supporters turn out to vote, according to the latest New York Times/CBS News Poll.</p>
        <p>The poll, taken Wednesday through Saturday, suggests that some of Mr. Lazio's central attacks on Mrs. Clinton in this final month of their Senate campaign have yet to take hold. Voters overwhelmingly said they believed that the first lady would do a better job at overhauling the health care system, even after a  week of attacks in which Mr. Lazio raised her failed advocacy of a national health care plan in 1994. And a slight majority said Mrs. Clinton was the stronger advocate of Israel, despite Mr. Lazio's escalating attacks on her Middle East views at a time of increasing unrest in the region.</p>
        <p>But voters were equally divided over which candidate would do a better job of improving the New York economy. Voters upstate, which is overwhelmingly Republican, gave Mr. Lazio a slight edge, despite Mrs. Clinton's persistent attempts to portray Mr. Lazio as unconcerned about upstate economic problems, most recently as she traveled across the region this weekend.  And respondents to the poll also said Mr. Lazio deserved the credit for an agreement in the race to restrict campaign contributions, even though most said it would not influence how they voted.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton now has an eight-point lead over Mr. Lazio, 49 percent to 41 percent. That is statistically unchanged from the previous Times/CBS News Poll, taken in September, when Mrs. Clinton had a nine-point lead, 48 percent to 39 percent. When the latest poll was adjusted to take into account how undecided voters said they were leaning, Mrs. Clinton led Mr. Lazio by 52 percent to 44 percent.</p>
        <p>The eight-point lead in the latest Times/CBS News Poll is relatively consistent with the findings of most public polls over the last month, and could explain both why Mr. Lazio was attacking Mrs. Clinton so intensely during the last debate, on Friday night, and the air of confidence that has settled in around Mrs. Clinton's camp in recent days.</p>
        <p>Still, even with the margin suggested by this poll -- which would be considered wide by the standard of recent New York elections -- the results suggest abundant reasons for concern by Mrs. Clinton and hope for Mr. Lazio as they enter the last eight days of their contest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's supporters seem much more likely to turn out on Election Day, driven less by an allegiance to the Republican Senate candidate and more by their dislike of Mrs. Clinton; 25 percent of Mr. Lazio's supporters cited their dislike of Mrs. Clinton in explaining their choice, compared with just 6 percent of Mrs. Clinton's supporters who said they were motivated to vote against Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>What is more, if it appears that Vice President Al Gore is going to win New York easily -- this poll suggests that he is 21 points ahead of George W. Bush in New York, 52 percent to 31 percent -- then Democrats may not bother to turn out in the numbers Mrs. Clinton needs to win the race. If the percentage of voter turnout falls near 45 percent, then Mrs. Clinton's edge in the Times/CBS News Poll shrinks to just a few percentage points.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton is clearly concerned about Democrats turning out on her behalf, and she spent much of yesterday urging supporters to be sure to vote a week from Tuesday, beginning with an appearance at two churches with predominantly black congregations in Buffalo. The poll found that Mrs. Clinton had the support of nearly 9 out of 10 black New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Most analysts also believe that a majority of the undecided voters will end up supporting Mr. Lazio, because at this point they know so much about her that there is little left that she can tell them that would sway their vote. Mr. Lazio's senior strategist, Mike Murphy, made that point last night in arguing that the findings were bad for Mrs. Clinton, notwithstanding the lead suggested in the numbers.</p>
        <p>''Upstate, not a single undecided voter is going to vote for her,'' he said. ''We're moving up every day, and our own polls show it even closer.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's pollster, Mark Penn, disputed that argument, asserting that after five months in the race and extensive spending by Mr. Lazio on television advertisements, voters were as familiar with the Republican congressman from Suffolk County as they were with Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''People know about him and who he is, and they know about her and who she is,'' Mr. Penn said. ''The undecideds are people who are still holding back from both of them, and are likely to break pretty evenly.''</p>
        <p>The poll was of 995 registered voters, of whom 871 are considered likely to vote. The poll had a margin of sampling error of plus or minus four  percentage points.</p>
        <p>The peculiarities of this particularly race aside, the poll for the most part suggests that Mr. Lazio has had difficulty in finding ways to gain traction against Mrs. Clinton. His long-planned assault on Mrs. Clinton's role in the health care legislation, which Mr. Lazio's aides have for months predicted would be devastatingly effective, has not caught on,  perhaps because the candidate chose to begin the attack in the middle of the World Series, when campaign coverage was overshadowed.</p>
        <p>One in two respondents said Mrs. Clinton's role in what she herself has acknowledged as a legislative debacle made no difference in their decision on how to vote; nearly one in four said it made them more likely to vote for her.</p>
        <p>''What she had to say at the time about health care reform made a lot of sense,'' Bruce Gronich, 41, a Democrat and an architect from Plainview, N.Y., said in a follow-up interview. ''She was trying to do the right thing.''</p>
        <p>But Donald Hoffman, 72, a sales manager from Queens, who does not identify himself with either party, echoed some of the criticism that Mr. Lazio has voiced in recent days. ''I felt she was out of line in that it was a government function, not the function of an individual, even though she is the first lady,'' he said. ''It was an unauthorized act and she should not have been doing that. I think it was a grab for power for her.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, the issue that Mr. Lazio adopted as a flagship issue a month ago -- trying to force a ban on the use of so-called soft money for commercials -- seems to have won him more good will than actual support from voters. Nearly 80 percent of respondents said the ban was a good idea, and about 40 percent said Mr. Lazio deserved the credit for it, notwithstanding Mrs. Clinton's claim that she first proposed the idea. But nearly half the respondents said that would not influence their vote at all.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's attempt to invoke Mario M. Cuomo, the Democratic governor who lost a bid for a fourth term in 1994, to discredit Mrs. Clinton also seems problematic. Statewide, only 22 percent of New Yorkers said they had an unfavorable opinion of Mr. Cuomo, who has been out of public life for six years; upstate, that figure is only 28 percent.</p>
        <p>On Israel, an issue that Mr. Lazio has made central to his campaign in an attempt to undercut Mrs. Clinton's standing among Jews, 50 percent of respondents said Mrs. Clinton would be a strong supporter of Israel in the Senate, while 44 percent said the same thing about Mr. Lazio. Seven in 10 respondents who said they were Jewish said they supported Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Since the last Times/CBS News Poll, Mr. Lazio appears to have made up some ground with suburban women, among whom he had been trailing in September. Now, he is leading her among those voters by 48 percent to 38 percent. The previous poll was taken shortly after their first debate, in which Mr. Lazio walked across the stage and demanded that Mrs. Clinton sign a pledge to ban the use of soft money, a move that several analysts suggested was too aggressive and might hurt him among female voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio is leading Mrs. Clinton in the suburbs by 51 percent to 39 percent. But he continues to have trouble in Republican upstate, which should be his stronghold: the poll found that he was ahead there 50 percent to 40 percent. Mr. Lazio probably must win at least 55 percent of the upstate vote to counteract Mrs. Clinton's advantage in New York City, where she is winning 7 of 10 votes.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton seems to be enjoying some success with the issues she has raised to date. While Mr. Lazio has sought to connect Mrs. Clinton to Mr. Cuomo, she has moved to link her opponent to Newt Gingrich, the Republican former House speaker. Mr. Gingrich is much more disliked than Mr. Cuomo: one in two New Yorkers have an unfavorable view of Mr. Gingrich.</p>
        <p>The poll also found that nearly half the respondents think that Mrs. Clinton was ''doing a better job of discussing the issues that are important to the campaign,'' compared with nearly one-third who said the same thing about Mr. Lazio. That is the kind of measure that politicians watch closely, because in recent years, candidates who are perceived as spending more time talking about the issues rather than attacking their opponents tend to do well in elections.</p>
        <p>''Personal character attacks are just a way of deflecting you from the substance of real issues,'' said Risa Dimm, 50, a business owner from Livingston, N.Y., who said she was likely to vote for Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Democrats have tried to suggest that Mr. Lazio does not have the stature to serve as a United States senator. The poll suggests that those attacks have not had much success: 56 percent said they believed that Mr. Lazio had the ''maturity and experience'' to be a senator, compared with 66 percent who said the same thing about Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Finally, in a bit of good news for Mrs. Clinton, it seems that the first lady continues to be having some success in responding to concerns about where she is from. In this poll, 61 percent of respondents -- the highest so far -- said it made no difference to them where she was born.</p>
        <p>How the Poll Was Conducted</p>
        <p>The latest New York Times/CBS News Poll of New York State is based on telephone interviews conducted Wednesday to Saturday with 1,255 adults throughout the state. Of those, 995 said they were registered to vote. Interviews were conducted in English or Spanish.</p>
        <p>The sample of telephone exchanges called was selected by a computer from a complete list of exchanges across the state. For each exchange, the telephone numbers were formed by random digits, thus permitting access to both listed and unlisted numbers. Within each household, one adult was designated by a random procedure to be the respondent for the survey.</p>
        <p>The results have been weighted to take account of household size and the number of telephone lines into the residence, and to adjust for variations in the sample relating to geographic regions of the state, race, Hispanic origin, sex, age, and education.</p>
        <p>In addition, the question about voting preferences and other aspects of the 2000 election for the United States Senate are based on the responses of likely voters, weighted to a probable electorate on the basis of intention to vote, attention to the campaign, and past voting behavior, further weighted so that those who reside in New York City make up 31 percent of the entire state, which is the city's typical share of total ballots cast on Election Day.</p>
        <p>In theory, in 19 cases out of 20 the results based on such samples will differ by no more than three percentage points in either direction from what would have been obtained by seeking out all adult residents of New York State. For smaller subgroups the potential sampling error is larger. As an example, for the 871 likely voters, weighted to a probable electorate of 667, it is plus or minus four percentage points.</p>
        <p>In addition to sampling error, the practical difficulties of conducting any survey of public opinion may introduce other sources of error into the poll. Differences in the wording and order of questions can lead to somewhat varying results.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
