<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dark Childhood Warmed by Footlights</title>
    <meta content="30WOLI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/arts/30WOLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wolitzer, Hilma</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rich, Frank</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ghost Light: A Memoir (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D61730F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dark Childhood Warmed by Footlights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HILMA WOLITZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wolitzer, Hilma</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hilma Wolitzer reviews Ghost Light: A Memoir by New York Times columnist Frank Rich; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GHOST LIGHT  A Memoir  By Frank Rich  315 pages. Random House. $24.95.</p>
        <p>''Anybody who has survived his childhood,'' Flannery O'Connor once observed, ''has enough information about life to last him the rest of his days.'' Frank Rich's wonderful coming-of-age memoir persuasively bears her out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GHOST LIGHT  A Memoir  By Frank Rich  315 pages. Random House. $24.95.</p>
        <p>''Anybody who has survived his childhood,'' Flannery O'Connor once observed, ''has enough information about life to last him the rest of his days.'' Frank Rich's wonderful coming-of-age memoir persuasively bears her out.</p>
        <p>The opening image of ''Ghost Light,'' by this former chief drama critic for The New York Times and current writer for both its Op-Ed page and magazine, is appropriately stagelike. The author's tearful young mother -- newly separated from her husband -- appears spotlighted to 7-year-old Frank as she sits atop their stacked suitcases at National Airport in Washington, after being bumped from an overbooked flight.</p>
        <p>''The light picked her out dramatically from the blurry dark background,'' he writes. ''Were this a play, it would be the Act I curtain, and the audience could look forward to a resolution of Mom's predicament, happy or tragic, in Act II.''</p>
        <p>Theatrical metaphor comes naturally to Mr. Rich, and it proves both comforting and illuminating to him during the 1950's and 60's, when his parents' troubled marriage and their subsequent divorce and remarriages disrupt and reorder his childhood.  Despite their cooling affection for each other, Helene and Frank Rich Sr. continue to share a love for the theater, and they spark their son's precocious interest with recordings of musical comedy scores, tickets to Washington tryouts of new plays and encouragement to adopt his mother's habit of Playbill collecting.</p>
        <p>Even before that, Frank and his younger sister, Polly, are seduced by the transitional fantasy world of television. The failings of their own suburban Maryland family are offset by viewing the seemingly happier, episodic lives of the Nelson, Kramden and Ricardo families.</p>
        <p>But such light entertainment increasingly becomes more than mere escape or distraction to young Frank. ''If the TV was extinguished, I decided, part of me would be too.'' He suffers from persistent insomnia and a morbid fear of darkness, ''the darkness of not knowing what was going to happen next,'' that only worsen after his mother's marriage to Joel Fisher, a loudmouthed, short-tempered Washington lawyer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fisher, who moves the family to the heart of the city, bullies everyone, from waiters to his wife, and beats his own children and his stepson with equal, brutal abandon. Helene doggedly defends his violent behavior, even after he's begun slapping her around as well. She keeps assuring her children of her husband's love for their makeshift family, citing all the worldly gifts he's brought them, and vaguely alluding to his own unhappy childhood.</p>
        <p>Frank must call upon his memory of the musical ''Carousel'' -- of how Julie Jordan sings about her love for Billy Bigelow (apparently unshaken after he hits her) -- in an effort to understand the enigma of adult affairs. But he's still reluctant to enter the master bedroom for comfort when he's wakeful, and settles for sleeping pills instead. His father's new household isn't much of a refuge either. The boy's complaints about Joel's abuse arouse some commiserating clucks but no serious action, while a newborn baby, referred to with amusing anonymity as ''your new sister,'' seems to expropriate Frank's place.</p>
        <p>Only the theater remains a dependable sanctuary. There, in the more hospitable ''velvet darkness,'' he finds himself ''alone, but not alone.'' He continues: ''I was in Washington, but not in Washington. I lived with Mom and Joel, but not right now. Not as long as the curtain was up.''</p>
        <p>Offstage events continue to take on theatrical overtones, too. About his first, ephemeral, junior-high romance, Mr. Rich writes, ''As abruptly as we had started going steady, we stopped: One day at school I found that my name had been erased from her sneakers, its place usurped by 'Duke Duke Duke Duke of Earl' Swindell's. Was this how it felt to be replaced in a Broadway show?''</p>
        <p>But the riveting real-life drama of the Kennedy years keeps impinging on Frank's inner life, as Joel secures invitations to hot political events as easily as he acquires airline and theater tickets. The boy's turbulent relationship with his stepfather is gradually tempered by gratitude and awe. Frank is especially grateful for an extended ''post-assassination Christmas'' visit to New York City, to Broadway, where he's permitted to run joyously, on his own, from theater to theater. Mr. Rich ruefully notes that, only a little more than a month after John F. Kennedy's funeral he felt ''indecently happy.''</p>
        <p>There are no absolute villains in Mr. Rich's compellingly readable story; for the most part the people in his life, like the characters in a satisfying play, are given their full, complex dimension. If Mr. Rich's father remains hazy to the reader, this probably reflects his passive presence in his son's life rather than the writer's failure to render him fairly. Even the abusive and overbearing Joel Fisher is granted redemption by Mr. Rich's evenhanded depiction of his stepfather's enthusiasm and generosity, and by the sympathetic disclosure of his tragic secret past.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most indelible figure in ''Ghost Light'' is Clayton Coots, a theater company manager the adolescent Frank encounters at his first job, as a ticket taker at the National Theater. Although there's some parental suspicion about Coots's motives, he serves steadily and unconditionally as Frank's friend, mentor and confidante. His letters, which routinely begin, ''Dear Pal Frank,'' have a Salingeresque charm. ''Don't worry too much about feeling confused about things,'' he writes. ''It's a rotten way to feel but that's what happens in this life.''</p>
        <p>He offers advice on matters of the heart and the mind, and his reliable, affectionate approval provides the perfect antidote to the imperfect fathers Mr. Rich has endured.</p>
        <p>The legitimate theater he so loves is described by Mr. Rich as ''a pileup of double-edged sensation,'' a place where sorrow and salvation exist in a continuum. ''A closing would always be followed by an opening, an empty house would always become full again.''</p>
        <p>By seamlessly blending theatrical magic with personal history, Mr. Rich corroborates Freud's principle that ''the purpose of drama is to reveal sources of pleasure and enjoyment in our own emotional life.''  ''Ghost Light'' is a poignant and darkly funny account of a boy's life shaped by difficult circumstances and the consolations of art.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES Hilma Wolitzer's new book, ''The Company of Writers,'' will be published in February.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Hilma Wolitzer's new book, ''The Company of Writers,'' will be published in February.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
