<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheney Loosens Up as G.O.P. Confidence Grows</title>
    <meta content="Y30COU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/politics/30COUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: ON THE TRAIL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henneberger, Melinda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2DC1430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheney Loosens Up as G.O.P. Confidence Grows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henneberger, Melinda</byline>
      <dateline>DAVENPORT, Iowa, Oct. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican vice presidential candidate Dick Cheney exudes more relaxed demeanor as Republicans' confidence grows that they will win White House; is beginning to enjoy himself, usually at Vice Pres Al Gore's expense; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dick Cheney is pumped. How can you tell? During a rally at the Mississippi Valley Fairgrounds here today, he underscored a point in his stump speech by raising his arm in the air. When someone in the crowd shouted encouragement, he smiled and ad-libbed a line, ''I'm going to take you with me.''</p>
        <p>He even invited reporters on his campaign plane to join him for a glass of wine. Regulars on the plane said they had never seen him like this.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dick Cheney is pumped. How can you tell? During a rally at the Mississippi Valley Fairgrounds here today, he underscored a point in his stump speech by raising his arm in the air. When someone in the crowd shouted encouragement, he smiled and ad-libbed a line, ''I'm going to take you with me.''</p>
        <p>He even invited reporters on his campaign plane to join him for a glass of wine. Regulars on the plane said they had never seen him like this.</p>
        <p>''You can feel the excitement,'' Mr. Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential nominee, told four party workers over a roast beef sandwich and fries at a local diner before the rally. ''Has Lieberman been here?'' he inquired, referring to Senator Joseph I. Lieberman of Connecticut, the Democratic vice-presidential nominee.</p>
        <p>''No, Gore,'' one of the women told him. ''It rained when he started to speak,'' she added, laughing.</p>
        <p>There are a lot of laughs just now in Bush-Cheney country, where confidence about next week's election is so high that both Republican candidates felt they could take Sunday off. The Republicans' only campaign event was remarks by satellite by Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>At a joint appearance in Wisconsin today, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the presidential nominee, seemed barely able to contain himself, mugging, morphing, making funny faces at the crowd, his antics throwing Mr. Cheney's quiet-man persona into even greater relief -- and vice versa. (''What a solid citizen!'' Mr. Bush said of his vice-presidential pick.)</p>
        <p>Still, there was no mistaking the fact that Mr. Cheney, whose grudging campaign style has been well documented, has started to enjoy himself, too -- usually at Vice President Al Gore's expense.</p>
        <p>On the stump and off, he shows an open lack of respect for the competition that Mr. Gore does not reciprocate. And watching Messrs. Gore, Bush and Cheney campaign on back-to-back days only highlights the striking difference in tone, with Mr. Gore rarely mentioning his opponents by name.</p>
        <p>Both Republicans, who are running on a platform of changing the tone in Washington, take much more personal shots, joking but seriously questioning the vice president's credibility and character all the same. And they get away with it.</p>
        <p>''He claimed he invented the Internet,'' Mr. Bush said again today, though that itself is an exaggeration of Mr. Gore's boast about his role in its development. Then he mocked Mr. Gore's statement that he is against big government. ''I knew the man was prone to exaggeration,'' Mr. Bush said, ''but not to that extent.''</p>
        <p>Later, in Davenport, Mr. Cheney was introduced by his daughter, Liz Perry, who got big applause when she said, ''My parents are from Casper, Wyo. They grew up in a place where people look you in the eye and tell you the truth -- it's a new approach.''</p>
        <p>Usually, Mr. Cheney's wife, Lynne, does the honors, often telling crowds that the couple's favorite movie is ''Love Story'' and that she once wrote a book called, ''Telling the Truth,'' which she is thinking of sending to the vice president. But Mrs. Cheney skipped this trip. ''She stayed back to get some clean laundry done,'' her husband told his audience.</p>
        <p>When he began by saying that the ''end to the Clinton-Gore era'' is around the corner, the crowd chanted: ''No More Gore! No More Gore!'' Standing behind him, Mr. Cheney's 6-year-old granddaughter, Kate Perry, waved a tiny American flag and booed at the mention of Mr. Gore's name.</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Cheney mentioned President Clinton again -- ''Al Gore, Joe Lieberman and Bill Clinton are drooling at the prospect of getting their hands'' on the surplus, he said, ''because they want to spend it.'' His audience went wild, shaking red, white and blue pompoms.</p>
        <p>Finally -- and they can taste it -- Republicans feel they are going to beat Bill Clinton. And anybody who thinks Mr. Clinton is not on the ballot this year should talk to a few voters here.</p>
        <p>Ellen Burt, for example, who came to the rally with her family, said she was enthusiastically supporting Mr. Cheney, for these reasons: ''He's honest. He's not going to lie. He's a man of integrity and a man of good morals.'' Get it?</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney told the group, ''I was intrigued when I got to Memphis'' on a recent campaign swing. ''There were Al Gore and Joe Lieberman. I thought that was his home state. They have no home state! Maybe that's why they're in Washington, D.C.''</p>
        <p>Then he said, as he had before, that in the debates, Mr. Gore changed so radically from one occasion to the next that Mr. Bush was ''up against three different guys and he beat them all.''</p>
        <p>He got a laugh when he said, ''If you've got a solar panel on your house, you get tax relief,'' though the Republicans offer a similar provision. And there were boos when he went on to say, ''But if you're a stay-at-home mom taking care of your kids, you don't get anything,'' though Mr. Gore's plan does offer financial incentives to stay-at-home parents.</p>
        <p>He ended by talking about his own favorite subject, the military. Mr. Gore disagrees with Mr. Cheney's view that the readiness of American troops has declined under the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>''Either he doesn't know the state of the U.S. military, or he knows and isn't telling the truth,'' Mr. Cheney said, and several people began shouting, ''Both!''</p>
        <p>Then the crowd was sprinkled with confetti, and left smiling, as did Mr. Cheney. When one of his luncheon companions remarked, ''It's too bad you can't be vice president and secretary of defense,'' he barely demurred.</p>
        <p>''Not enough hours in the day,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: ON THE TRAIL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
