<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Rural Life; Chaste Weather</title>
    <meta content="30MON3$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/opinion/30MON3.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EED91430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="537" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Rural Life; Chaste Weather</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VERLYN KLINKENBORG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Verlyn Klinkenborg's Rural Life column on onset of autumn (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When snow began falling on Sunday, I realized that a line from Keats -- ''until they think warm days will never cease'' -- had been running through my head for weeks. The line is from his ode ''To Autumn,'' one of the loveliest poems in the language, and ''they'' are the bees, whose clammy cells, as Keats calls their comb, have been ''o'erbrimm'd'' by summer. Jonathan Bate, author of a new book called ''The Song of the Earth,'' observes that the late summer of 1819, the season leading up to the completion of Keats's ode on Sept. 19, ''was clear and sunny on thirty-eight out of the forty-seven days from 7 August to 22 September 1819'' and that temperatures were milder in the final week of that period than they had been in three years.</p>
        <p>This was not merely a spate of beautiful weather. It was weather of a kind, Mr. Bate notes, that would actually make breath come easier for a consumptive like Keats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When snow began falling on Sunday, I realized that a line from Keats -- ''until they think warm days will never cease'' -- had been running through my head for weeks. The line is from his ode ''To Autumn,'' one of the loveliest poems in the language, and ''they'' are the bees, whose clammy cells, as Keats calls their comb, have been ''o'erbrimm'd'' by summer. Jonathan Bate, author of a new book called ''The Song of the Earth,'' observes that the late summer of 1819, the season leading up to the completion of Keats's ode on Sept. 19, ''was clear and sunny on thirty-eight out of the forty-seven days from 7 August to 22 September 1819'' and that temperatures were milder in the final week of that period than they had been in three years.</p>
        <p>This was not merely a spate of beautiful weather. It was weather of a kind, Mr. Bate notes, that would actually make breath come easier for a consumptive like Keats.</p>
        <p>There could be nothing more personal than the question of Keats's lung capacity, and yet ''To Autumn'' does not read as a personal poem. There is, it is true, something deceptively long-winded in the syntax of the first stanza, and some critics have seen a consumptive's hectic flush in the stubble plains touched with ''rosy hue.'' But Mr. Bate reminds us, too, how broad the boundaries of ''personal'' experience really are. For Keats, those boundaries include the season as a whole. The fine weather o'erbrimm'd him, and in doing so gave voice to itself.</p>
        <p>Until the past few days, it was a Keatsian autumn, full of what the poet calls, in a letter from those same weeks, ''Chaste weather -- Dian skies.'' Never mind that the leaves are now almost gone, or that the skies are now unchaste, gray and dousing us with snow showers. Somehow the brightness of the trees created the illusion that the periphery of one's awareness had expanded. When we walked the dogs, it felt as though we were all walking with eyebrows raised, though for the dogs that would be with nostrils distended.</p>
        <p>Keats personified autumn, imagining her by a cider press or fast asleep in a ''half-reap'd furrow.'' Personifying the natural world is so fundamental and so limitless that it seems sometimes like the foundation of all poetry. To some, I suppose, personifying nature appears to be an act of hubris, a refusal to accept the otherness of the world around us. But in a fall like this one -- dry after a long wet, warm after unusual coolness -- personifying nature seems only like a means of meeting nature halfway. In the ghostliness of Keats's autumn, ''sitting careless on a granary floor,'' what we really see is the way the season swells within us.</p>
        <p>VERLYN KLINKENBORG</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
