<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tall Order for a Tall Player at a Tournament</title>
    <meta content="30CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bocchi, Norberto</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD71730F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="387" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tall Order for a Tall Player at a Tournament</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott Bridge column on hand defended by Italian world champion Norberto Bocchi; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the Italian players who won the world team title last month at Maastricht, in the Netherlands, was Norberto Bocchi, who was easy to recognize. At 6 foot 6 he was the tallest player in the tournament.</p>
        <p>He made many good plays and was sometimes the victim of good plays made against him. But nothing quite matched his suffering on the diagramed deal played in April when he and his partner, Giorgio Duboin, were leading in the Politiken tournament in Denmark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the Italian players who won the world team title last month at Maastricht, in the Netherlands, was Norberto Bocchi, who was easy to recognize. At 6 foot 6 he was the tallest player in the tournament.</p>
        <p>He made many good plays and was sometimes the victim of good plays made against him. But nothing quite matched his suffering on the diagramed deal played in April when he and his partner, Giorgio Duboin, were leading in the Politiken tournament in Denmark.</p>
        <p>As East, he began with a weak two-bid and became alarmed when South's takeout double was passed for penalties by North. That contract would probably have failed by two tricks, for a penalty of 300. He tried the effect of rescuing himself into two spades, gambling that his partner had some spade length. This was a frying-pan-into-the-fire move, for two spades doubled would have failed by at least three tricks after an opening trump lead.</p>
        <p>But South chose to remove his partner's double, a dubious action. He then had to vindicate his decision by making three no-trump after the lead of the diamond jack. South was Vincent Ramondt, a young Dutchman, and he began by taking dummy's diamond winners. He then led a spade; it was West's turn to take an ace-king combination. He shifted back to diamonds, and South took his queen in this position:</p>
        <p>(Diagrams)</p>
        <p>Now came the key play. South cashed his heart ace, removing a crucial exit card from the West hand. He then led a diamond, allowing West to take two tricks in that suit. This had a double impact. West had to lead a club, giving away a trick in that suit. And the third round of clubs squeezed the unfortunate Bocchi down to a spade winner and the queen-jack of hearts, in the major suits. He could choose between allowing South to score the spade seven or dummy to win the heart 10.</p>
        <p>This effort earned Ramondt an Award from the International Bridge Press Assocation for the Best Hand of the Year.</p>
        <p>Some of the world's best bridge teams will be competing this week in the International Olympic Committee's Grand Prix to be played in in Lausanne, Switzerland. The action can be followed on the Internet at: www.e-bridgemaster.com.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
