<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patents; A few frightful ideas, but some safe ones, too, all in the spirit of Halloween.</title>
    <meta content="30PATE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/business/30PATE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Halloween</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pumpkins</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Candy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Geller, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spulveda, Jorge</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morphet, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chapman, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Gwendolyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blount, Terry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blount, Jeanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Halloween</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Candy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE4DF1430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patents; A few frightful ideas, but some safe ones, too, all in the spirit of Halloween.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many Halloween costumes, decorations, candy and even pumpkins are patented; recent patents include Andrew Geller's costume that bleeds, Jorge Sepulveda's candy bag that makes noise when opened, Deborah Morphet's Halloween backpack, Jeffrey Chapman's carvable artificial pumpkin, Gwendolyn Anderson's system of tagging candy with giver's identity and Terry and Jeanne Blount's candy that can be eaten without danger of choking (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GHOSTS and goblins, as well as Pokemon creatures and presidential candidates, will traipse the streets tomorrow night -- the culmination of weeks of preparation for Halloween. Hundreds of millions of dollars are spent on those efforts every year, and many of the costumes, decorations, candy and even pumpkins are patented.</p>
        <p>In the true spirit of Halloween, Alan Geller, who lives in Sea Cliff, N.Y., won a patent this year for a costume that bleeds. In his patent, he points out that people like Halloween and dressing up as ghosts and monsters because they ''get pleasure out of scaring or entertaining people.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GHOSTS and goblins, as well as Pokemon creatures and presidential candidates, will traipse the streets tomorrow night -- the culmination of weeks of preparation for Halloween. Hundreds of millions of dollars are spent on those efforts every year, and many of the costumes, decorations, candy and even pumpkins are patented.</p>
        <p>In the true spirit of Halloween, Alan Geller, who lives in Sea Cliff, N.Y., won a patent this year for a costume that bleeds. In his patent, he points out that people like Halloween and dressing up as ghosts and monsters because they ''get pleasure out of scaring or entertaining people.''</p>
        <p>But while there are masks on the market that make heads look bloody, wounded, deformed and otherwise gory and repulsive, Mr. Geller finds it unfortunate that there is not much to a mask once everyone has seen it. The novelty wears off fast, he says, and people get bored. So he has come up with a way to frighten people repeatedly with the same get-up.</p>
        <p>''As is well known, costumes are not limited to masks, and it is desirable to produce bleeding body parts aside from the face,'' Mr. Geller writes in his patent.</p>
        <p>He designed a mask and costume formed with two layers of material. The inner layer is opaque or decorated, and the outer skin is at least partly transparent. Tubes run through the passage between the layers. They're connected to a pump holding a red fluid. When the wearer activates the pump, the ''blood'' is forced into openings in the tubes. As it moves through the tubes, it is visible through the transparent parts of the costume. With a mask, the blood oozes from the top.</p>
        <p>''Fluid is distributed across the forehead,'' Mr. Geller explains in his patent. ''Fluid then trickles down across the skull features of mask. Because fluid is visible through transparent outer layer, it gives the appearance of blood trickling down the skull features of mask thereby creating a realistic bleeding effect.''</p>
        <p>He adds that his invention ''can be shaped to depict any object, including, but not limited to, any human, animal or monster body part.''</p>
        <p>He says his costume can be fitted into a breastplate shaped like skeleton ribs, with the blood dripping from between the bones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Geller received patent 6,093,475.</p>
        <p>To heighten the trick-or-treating experience, Jorge Sepulveda has patented a candy bag that makes noise when opened. His bag might scream, shout ''boo,'' or say ''trick or treat,'' Mr. Sepulveda writes in his patent. He says he wants to increase the holiday impact because ''children, at these times, are always seeking new ways to better their friends.''</p>
        <p>The candy bag is shaped like a shopping bag, with handles emerging from opposite sides of its opening. Mr. Sepulveda adds thin metal plates to the inside surfaces where the handles connect to the paper, and electrical contact wires on one plate, along with a sound chip with its own contact wire.</p>
        <p>When the wires touch the metal, a closed circuit is created. When the bag is opened, the circuit separates and that activates the sound chip. Mr. Sepulveda, who lives in Bridgeport, Conn., won patent 6,137,410.</p>
        <p>Deborah Morphet is an inventor in Penticton, Calif., who worries that children have too much to carry on Halloween night. In addition to their goodie bag or plastic pumpkin, many children carry safety lights. Ms. Morphet says that as the night wears on and the candy bag gets heavier, kids are apt to abandon their flashlights in favor of carrying the candy. She has removed that quandary by patenting a Halloween backpack. A hollow chute extends from the top of the backpack, over the child's shoulder, to open over the chest. The child can feed candy into the chute, or the person handing out the treats can pop them in. The pack leaves the trick-or-treaters' hands free to hang onto that flashlight. Ms. Morphet won patent 5,878,931.</p>
        <p>Pumpkin sales in this country certainly peak in the weeks before Halloween, when most people buy the only fresh pumpkins they will own all year. Nearly all of those are sold for decoration and for carving into jack-o'-lanterns. If Jeffrey Chapman has his way, that market will be wiped out by his carvable artificial pumpkin. Mr. Chapman, who lives in Scottsdale, Ariz., patented a polyurethane shell coated with an acrylic elastomer shaped like a pumpkin. The fake squash is hollow, and is formed by spraying polyurethane foam from a rotating nozzle into a pumpkin-shaped mold. The acrylic coating is applied as a liquid. The artificial pumpkin can then be carved, lighted, stored and re-used next year. Mr. Chapman received patent 5,811,160.</p>
        <p>The object of Halloween for kids is candy. Some people insist on passing out healthier treats like raisins. But everyone prefers packaged goodies, and for safety's sake it has become common to throw away anything of uncertain origin. To make children and their parents even more comfortable, Gwendolyn Anderson has patented a system of tagging the candy with the giver's identity. Ms. Anderson uses small boxes, or paper or plastic bags, with Halloween decorations on the outside and a space to fill in with the name and address of the candy-giver. She received patent 5,735,548.</p>
        <p>An inherently safer candy was on the minds of Terry and Jeanne Blount, who live in Wayne, Okla. The Blounts won a patent last spring for a hard candy they hope children or adults can eat without danger of choking. The candy has three holes bored through it so that if it gets lodged in the throat, air will continue to flow into the lungs. The Blounts received patent 6,054,152.</p>
        <p>Patents may be viewed on the Web at www.uspto.gov or may be ordered through the mail, by patent number, for $3 from the Patent and Trademark Office, Washington, D.C. 20231.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Patents may be viewed on the Web at www.uspto.gov or may be ordered through the mail, by patent number, for $3 from the Patent and Trademark Office, Washington, D.C. 20231.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
