<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Politicians March in a Racy Celebration of Gay Progress</title>
    <meta content="26PARA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210613"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gay and Lesbian Pride Parade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5DC1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Politicians March in a Racy Celebration of Gay Progress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Annual Gay and Lesbian Pride March held, New York City; scene described; Democratic Senate candidate Hillary Rodham Clinton marches while her opponent, Repr Rick A Lazio, campaigns upstate; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With pulsating music, the gyrations of scantily clad dancers and the echoing thunder of cheering spectators, hundreds of thousands of New Yorkers gathered yesterday to celebrate a year of concrete progress in the gay rights movement.</p>
        <p>The annual Gay and Lesbian Pride March is by tradition a rowdy event, sort of half Mardi Gras, half political rally by one of New York City's most vocal interest groups.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With pulsating music, the gyrations of scantily clad dancers and the echoing thunder of cheering spectators, hundreds of thousands of New Yorkers gathered yesterday to celebrate a year of concrete progress in the gay rights movement.</p>
        <p>The annual Gay and Lesbian Pride March is by tradition a rowdy event, sort of half Mardi Gras, half political rally by one of New York City's most vocal interest groups.</p>
        <p>But with the State Legislature's passage last week of a bill toughening penalties for hate crimes, including those against gays, and Vermont's recent passage of a law recognizing same-sex unions, marchers said there was an even greater incentive to celebrate. ''It's a tremendously significant year,'' said Virginia M. Apuzzo, a lesbian activist, former White House adviser and one of the grand marshals for the 31st annual parade. ''The changes have been dazzling.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday's parade illustrated the diversity in the movement, with marchers representing Polish and Brazilian groups, high school students and the elderly, teachers and firefighters, Republicans and Socialists, Jews and Buddhists.</p>
        <p>There were, of course, the typical entourages of politicians, including Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi, Speaker Peter F. Vallone of the City Council and C. Virginia Fields, the Manhattan borough president. But none of the politicians or nearly 300 other groups participating in the parade garnered anywhere near as much attention as Hillary Rodham Clinton, the Democratic candidate for the Senate.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton, who happened to be behind a group called the Radical Faeries, which featured a man on skates who wore nothing but a silver cape, a tiara and a jockstrap, was so popular the police had difficulty controlling the crowd. Some pressed against barriers to try to get close to her, and others threw confetti from fire escapes and windows. Together, thousands applauded and at times even chanted her name as she passed, smiling and waving.</p>
        <p>''That is the warmest, most extraordinary parade welcome I have ever seen,'' said Representative Barney Frank, a gay Democrat from Massachusetts, who said he had been marching in similar parades for 30 years.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's opponent, Rick A. Lazio, a Republican congressman from Long Island, was campaigning upstate in appearances that he said had been scheduled earlier. ''It is just a shame he is not here,'' Mrs. Clinton said. ''I think that anyone who would run to represent the state of New York should run to represent all New Yorkers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani came to the defense of Mr. Lazio, who replaced him in the Senate race last month after the mayor, citing his prostate cancer, dropped out. ''Schedules are very, very difficult when you run for office,'' the mayor said. The mayor himself received an unusually warm welcome. There was some occasional booing, but the marchers in the group the mayor joined -- the Log Cabin Republicans -- quickly blew whistles to mask the heckling.</p>
        <p>The mayor received a fair share of cheers as well. ''The fact that I am a Republican but still a very strong supporter of gay rights is actually in some ways more difficult than being a Democrat and a strong supporter of gay rights, and I think that people appreciate that,'' Mr. Giuliani said.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's parade started just above St. Patrick's Cathedral on Fifth Avenue, went down Fifth Avenue to Greenwich Village and then past Sheridan Square, the site of the Stonewall Inn, where a clash with the police in 1969 helped begin the modern gay rights movement.</p>
        <p>Although police said there were no major confrontations during the parade, a 17-year-old man reported that he had been sexually assaulted by another man on Christopher Street at Weehawken Street in the rowdy aftermath last night.</p>
        <p>He said the first officer he approached did not respond, an allegation like those made by several women who were groped in Central Park during the National Puerto Rican Day Parade on June 11.</p>
        <p>Sgt. Gerry Falcon, a police spokesman, said the man's allegation was under investigation.</p>
        <p>The march was led by a Cadillac convertible filled with veterans of the Stonewall uprising, dressed in drag. As in past years, there were topless women and nearly naked men, some on motorcycles. And there was float after float of dancers -- men and women -- in hot pants and platform shoes. The politicians, gay rights activists and spectators spoke of a gradual transformation of the movement's goals as gays and lesbians increasingly struggle for acceptance, instead of just tolerance, in society.</p>
        <p>''Every single day, people are recognizing that there are gay, lesbian and transgender members in their communities,'' said James Dale, 29, of Brooklyn, whose expulsion from a New Jersey Boy Scout troop 10 years ago resulted in a civil rights case that is now before the United States Supreme Court. ''When they see that they realize we are all part of the same community.''</p>
        <p>Yet there was a recognition that despite the progress of the last year, the push for rights is far from complete. ''Any civil rights movement is a marathon, not a sprint,'' Ms. Apuzzo said. ''In this year's piece of that marathon, we have done phenomenally well.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
