<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At CBS, the Lines Between News and Entertainment Grow Fuzzier</title>
    <meta content="26CBS.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Big Brother (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Early Show, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Survivor (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E5DA1530F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1164" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At CBS, the Lines Between News and Entertainment Grow Fuzzier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Chen, newscaster on CBS News program The Early Show, will host weekly prime-time interview show based on developments in new reality series Big Brother, further blurring lines between entertainment and news; will also provide voice of Big Brother on that show; Early Show is at center of CBS strategy to exploit success of Survivor series and hoped-for success of Big Brother; CBS officials defend link between shows; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every Thursday morning, the CBS News morning program, ''The Early Show,'' gives over two full segments to exploring the latest developments in the summer prime-time phenomenon, ''Survivor,'' including a half-hour panel discussion and the first interview with the latest cast member cast adrift by his or her island compatriots.</p>
        <p>Starting next week, when CBS kicks off its second reality series, ''Big Brother,'' the network's news division will take another leap in terms of opportunism and self-promotion, creating further potential for blurring the lines between entertainment and news. The newscaster on ''The Early Show,'' Julie Chen, will begin hosting a weekly prime-time interview show based on developments in ''Big Brother,'' a 90-episode exercise in voyeuristic television in which 10 people will be locked in a house full of cameras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every Thursday morning, the CBS News morning program, ''The Early Show,'' gives over two full segments to exploring the latest developments in the summer prime-time phenomenon, ''Survivor,'' including a half-hour panel discussion and the first interview with the latest cast member cast adrift by his or her island compatriots.</p>
        <p>Starting next week, when CBS kicks off its second reality series, ''Big Brother,'' the network's news division will take another leap in terms of opportunism and self-promotion, creating further potential for blurring the lines between entertainment and news. The newscaster on ''The Early Show,'' Julie Chen, will begin hosting a weekly prime-time interview show based on developments in ''Big Brother,'' a 90-episode exercise in voyeuristic television in which 10 people will be locked in a house full of cameras.</p>
        <p>More than merely interviewing participants in that show, and various sociologists and psychologists commenting on it, Ms. Chen will actually play the role of Big Brother on that show, providing the voice -- an unseen intercom voice in the manner of the classic ''Big Brother'' on George Orwell's ''1984''-- that tells one contestant the audience has voted to throw him or her out of the house.</p>
        <p>The moves are part of a strategy, being pushed aggressively by CBS's News division as well as other divisions of the network, to capitalize on the current fascination with ''Survivor'' -- and the hoped-for fascination with ''Big Brother.''</p>
        <p>Already CBS radio stations are regularly promoting developments on ''Survivor,'' even on news programs, some of which are looking for local tie-ins to contestants voted out of that tropical island competition. The all-news WCBS radio in New York, for example, included the exit of a woman from New Jersey as one of its headline stories last Thursday morning. Some CBS local television stations are doing the same thing on their news programs.</p>
        <p>But ''The Early Show'' is at the center of CBS's strategy to take advantage of the surging ratings for ''Survivor,'' especially among younger viewers. (CBS has, for years, been the oldest network in terms of median age of viewers, a status that has hurt CBS with advertisers, many of whom pay premiums to reach younger viewers.) The morning news show, which has suffered through disappointing ratings since its much heralded premiere in November, has hitched its future in significant ways to both '''Survivor'' and ''Big Brother.''</p>
        <p>Far from being concerned about blurring any lines between news and entertainment, CBS executives have expressed nothing but enthusiasm for the links being forged between ''The Early Show,'' and the two reality series from CBS's entertainment division.</p>
        <p>''It's an experiment well worth taking on,'' said Andrew Heyward, the president of CBS News.</p>
        <p>''All I can say is: Thank God for 'Survivor,' '' said Steve Friedman, the senior executive producer of ''The Early Show.'' Citing ratings increases he said are directly attributable to the show's association with ''Survivor,'' Mr. Friedman said he said he is already looking forward to the possibilities for more ratings coattails from ''Big Brother.''</p>
        <p>Beyond the heavy coverage every Thursday, ''The Early Show'' devotes another segment each Wednesday morning to a preview of that night's action on ''Survivor.''</p>
        <p>The plan for ''Big Brother'' is similar. Mr. Friedman said Ms. Chen will appear every Friday morning to discuss the previous night's decision to banish one of the housemates. (Unlike ''Survivor,'' the audience, not the participants, votes to eliminate cast members on ''Big Brother.'') Then on Monday, after a weekend of compulsory psychological counseling, the exiled cast member will come to New York for a first interview on ''The Early Show.''</p>
        <p>''We'll have four of five days when we're dealing with either 'Survivor' or 'Big Brother,' Mr. Friedman said, enthusiastically. He noted that any time a significant news story occurs, he will abandon features on the reality show. But he noted that he does not believe his program has skimped on any news story this summer.</p>
        <p>''It's not like there's been a lot of news,'' he said. ''If I see one more story on gasoline prices I'll choke.''</p>
        <p>As for the decision to use Ms. Chen as the most visible face on ''Big Brother,'' Mr. Heyward acknowledged that ''the ancillary benefit to 'The Early Show' was of course a big reason.'' He said there had been ''some discussion about it'' within CBS News. ''I understand the traditional view that says we shouldn't do something like this.'' But Mr. Heyward said, ''I'm very comfortable with it.''</p>
        <p>He included in that comfort Ms. Chen's performance as Big Brother. ''I don't have problem with it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Defending the decision to use Ms. Chen on the show, both Mr. Heyward and Mr. Friedman cited numerous examples of news correspondents from morning television who have undertaken entertainment projects, from Barbara Walters interviewing Oscar contenders to Ann Curry of ''Today'' jumping out of an airplane.</p>
        <p>Jeff Zucker, the executive producer of ''Today,'' said he ''understood why CBS is doing this, but we wouldn't allow one of our newspeople do it.'' One long-time morning news executive was more succinct: ''They're doing it because they're desperate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman acknowledged: ''The program has really been struggling. We did not do the rating we thought we were going to do.''</p>
        <p>But he is trumpeting better ratings in the last four weeks -- since ''Survivor'' went on the air -- citing especially what he called ''huge increases'' among certain younger viewers in categories like women between the ages of 18 and 49, over what the show did the same week last year.</p>
        <p>But last year's numbers were assembled by a grab bag of occasional hosts while the ''Early Show'' has since been reconstructed, at an expense of more than $30 million, around one of the biggest names in morning television, Bryant Gumbel, and a newcomer, Jayne Clayson.</p>
        <p>In terms of more recent performance, ''The Early Show'' has added about 100,000 viewers a week -- from about 2.15 million to about 2.25 million -- in the four weeks since ''Survivor'' began, over its totals for the four previous weeks. That is a modest number, but still notable because the four previous weeks were mainly within the regular television season and viewing has declined since then. ''Today,'' for example, has lost about 170,000 viewers (off a base of more than 6 million) a week since then, a typical summer development.</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman is certainly convinced that it is worth riding the ''Survivor'' wave. He said, ''When you get a show that everyone's talking about, that's nirvana. We're in television nirvana right now.''</p>
        <p>That does not mean the pressure to pull the show up to a true competitive position is any less. ''Frankly we're under more pressure,'' Mr. Friedman said. ''We have an opportunity to get viewers in to take a look at us. We better take advantage of it.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
