<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sampras Chases History With His Back as a Foe</title>
    <meta content="26WIMB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4DD1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sampras Chases History With His Back as a Foe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>WIMBLEDON, England, June 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for Wimbledon Tennis Championships; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These days, the chilly breezes that sneak through the slats in the green fences and the damp air that sticks to the same lush tennis grounds Pete Sampras adores tend to reach out and grip his tricky back like a squeeze toy.</p>
        <p>Under traditional climate conditions today, Sampras was splayed across the blades of grass next to a net post, gingerly stretching his muscles like Silly Putty after his practice session in an attempt to uncover enough elasticity to start a fortnight. Just two months shy of age 29, Sampras is beginning to experience part of longevity's attack plan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These days, the chilly breezes that sneak through the slats in the green fences and the damp air that sticks to the same lush tennis grounds Pete Sampras adores tend to reach out and grip his tricky back like a squeeze toy.</p>
        <p>Under traditional climate conditions today, Sampras was splayed across the blades of grass next to a net post, gingerly stretching his muscles like Silly Putty after his practice session in an attempt to uncover enough elasticity to start a fortnight. Just two months shy of age 29, Sampras is beginning to experience part of longevity's attack plan.</p>
        <p>Those white, baggy shorts of his have not doubled as parachutes for all of his diving volleys, for all of his leaps to put tears in the sky with his hanging overheads and for all of his lift to uncoil the torque in a serve that leaves a smoke trail. While collecting six Wimbledon titles in seven years, half of his 12 career Grand Slam victories, the spectacular has not come without wear and tear.</p>
        <p>There is no certainty to Sampras's resilience anymore. When the All England Club unlatches its gates for opening day on Monday, Sampras will step on the court for perhaps his last best chance to pass Roy Emerson for most Grand Slam victories. To break the record at Wimbledon, in front of his bride-to-be, Bridgette Wilson, could not be more special -- unless his parents were by his side, too.</p>
        <p>This is why he is trying to coax Georgia and Sam Sampras out of the small club of tennis parents who are not fighting for space in the frame during their child's photo op. Usually, Sampras's parents are nervously catching up on their son's glamorous tennis career from the television set in their living room.</p>
        <p>''I'd like to get into the last week and see if they can come over,'' Sampras said after practice for his first-round match Monday against the little known Jiri Vanek of the Czech Republic. ''It'd be nice for my parents to share this tournament with me because it's been such a big part of my career. And they've been a big part of my tennis, obviously.</p>
        <p>''They've always given me my space. They've always kept their distance. But as you get older, you want your family to be more of a part of what you do. That's my goal over the next couple of years. I'd like to have them around -- I mean, maybe not every week -- but to be more a part of everything.''</p>
        <p>From the friends box at Center Court, they could watch their son make history. Sampras has not won a Grand Slam event outside of Wimbledon since the 1997 Australian Open. This is his backyard, grass included. But is it now or never? The question has circled him for weeks, but in response, he produces a relaxed facial expression and a blanket denial of the pressure. If there are anxieties tumbling inside of him like socks in the drum of a dryer, it is not for public viewing.</p>
        <p>''I don't look at the record as something I want to get over with,'' Sampras said. ''It's something you can't take for granted. I never, ever thought I'd be in this position as a young pro.</p>
        <p>''If it happens, it'll be a good moment. It's hard to feel what I might feel if it does. If I get into that position, it'll be something special. But there is a lot of work to be done first.''</p>
        <p>Ahead of him, there are potential spoilers. If he is not too mentally hung over from his French Open title, Gustavo Kuerten of Brazil could prove himself grass worthy. And two Russians, Yevgeny Kafelnikov and Marat Safin, may also thrive in the draw. If the tweaks in Andre Agassi's back disappear, his recent slide could cease despite playing in the same quadrant as Tim Henman, Goran Ivanisevic and Mark Philippoussis.</p>
        <p>Back ailments are not confined to the men's draw. Lindsay Davenport's sore back will be tested by the cool conditions and slippery grass. ''I want to walk out on my first match at Wimbledon thinking, 'I can win this thing,' '' Davenport said after her first-round exit in the French Open.</p>
        <p>With Davenport's health muddled, there is room for the paparazzi to leave their shutters open to the possibility of, at long last, a serious run by the downloaded queen of the Internet, Anna Kournikova. More realistically, there is an opening for the supremely confident Martina Hingis, the French Open winner Mary Pierce and the trendsetting Venus and Serena Williams, both of whom have healed from their springtime injuries.</p>
        <p>''Right now, what I see, is that I don't think anyone can outrun them,'' Richard Williams said after watching his daughters practice today and strolling the grounds during his first trip to Wimbledon. ''You know from watching some players in the past, like Michael Chang, if you can get to the ball, you can be pretty dangerous. They're going to get to the ball. They're not just going to lay down and go to sleep. They're going to do the best they can do. If they do half as well as they're capable of doing, they can do some damage.''</p>
        <p>It is easy to ponder an array of possibilities in the women's draw. If Sampras's quirky back holds out, the men's title is in his hands. His first opponent has no illusions about it.</p>
        <p>''My coach told me, if it's a good draw, maybe I'll get some Spanish guy,'' Vanek said. ''But it was Sampras. It's unbelievable. His specialty is grass. Here, he's won six times. I think Pete at Wimbledon, it's like playing Michael Jordan in basketball.''</p>
        <p>Jordan had an air of invincibility about him. The air around Sampras, if it remains cool and damp, may be the only element that makes him vulnerable on his beloved surface.</p>
        <p>''It's fine,'' Sampras said of his back, which he tweaked in practice on Friday. ''It gets stiff now and again with the cold weather. And it's been cold this week, plus a little wet and windy. When you have those conditions, you'll have little niggles now and then. A little stretching and warming up, and hopefully I'll be at 100 percent.''</p>
        <p>If so, by the end of the fortnight, Sampras may finally have the leverage to lure his parents out of anonymity.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
