<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Armstrong Challengers Have Kept Low Profile</title>
    <meta content="26TOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abt, Samuel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DD1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Armstrong Challengers Have Kept Low Profile</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL ABT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abt, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for Tour de France bicycle race (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Looking for a patsy, a pool hustler will warm up by sinking the eight-ball and then scratching a shot. Once money is on the line, he runs the table.</p>
        <p>Some bicycle riders are like that. They call it hiding their game, finishing deep in the pack in minor races, lagging in the mountains until they arrive at a big race, the Tour de France, say, and then they shine. Or at least they hope to.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Looking for a patsy, a pool hustler will warm up by sinking the eight-ball and then scratching a shot. Once money is on the line, he runs the table.</p>
        <p>Some bicycle riders are like that. They call it hiding their game, finishing deep in the pack in minor races, lagging in the mountains until they arrive at a big race, the Tour de France, say, and then they shine. Or at least they hope to.</p>
        <p>When the 87th Tour de France begins its three-week journey on Saturday in western France, the list of contenders who have been hiding their game lately will be longer than usual, for a couple of reasons.</p>
        <p>Foremost is that Lance Armstrong, the defending champion, has been convincingly strong in the run-up to the Tour. Few rivals were eager to risk their morale by seriously challenging Armstrong in a minor race.</p>
        <p>Armstrong, the leader of the United States Postal Service team, even skipped his final prep race, last week's Route du Sud, because he felt he was ahead of last year's form and worried about peaking too early.</p>
        <p>Physically he is at least as good as last year, and mentally he is stronger than he was in 1999, in the judgment of Armstrong's team director, Johan Bruyneel. At this point, Armstrong has to be considered a strong favorite to repeat last year's emotional victory during his comeback from cancer.</p>
        <p>The second reason to have kept a low profile is that the Tour has become such a monument that many riders concentrate exclusively on it. Once the season begins in February, no other victory seems to matter.</p>
        <p>Heading this list is France's Richard Virenque, who has won the leading climber's jersey the last five years and who finished on the Tour's final victory podium in 1996 and 1997. He has never won the event. Now riding in Italy for the Polti team, he has not posted a significant result yet this year.</p>
        <p>Bobby Julich, an American with the Credit Agricole team in France, is also a member of the Polti club. Hampered by illness and injury, yet yearning to repeat at least his third-place finish in the 1998 Tour, he was hardly heard from this spring.</p>
        <p>The same is true for Franck Vandenbroucke, the troubled Belgian leader of the Cofidis team from France; Michael Boogerd, the fragile Dutch leader of the Rabobank team from his homeland; Fernando Escartin, the Spaniard who finished third in the last Tour as the leader of the Kelme team from Spain; and Alex Zulle, the Swiss leader of the Banesto team from Spain.</p>
        <p>All except Vandenbroucke are legitimate challengers to Armstrong in July, but only on the basis of their press clippings.</p>
        <p>Two previous Tour winners, Marco Pantani and Jan Ullrich, have not only been hiding their fitness levels, but also themselves.</p>
        <p>Pantani, the superb Italian climber who won the Tour and the Giro d'Italia in 1998 in the colors of Mercatone Uno, emerged from long seclusion in May to return to the Giro and display his rustiness. Holding a big lead on the next-to-last day of that race last year, he was expelled for failing a blood test that hinted at the use of drugs. His subsequent funk leaves his state of mind and his legs uncertain.</p>
        <p>Ullrich, the German who finished first in the Tour in 1997 at age 23, has been troubled this year by illness and he has also gained some weight. From a low-water mark in early June, when he pulled out of a race as the pack was coasting to the starting line, Ullrich rebounded to a strong Tour of Switzerland, even wearing the leader's jersey for a few days.</p>
        <p>Finally among the contenders are two men who dominated the early races this season, pulled their heads back into their shells six or seven weeks ago and are only now re-emerging. They are Abraham Olano, a Spaniard, and Laurent Jalabert, a Frenchman, who share the leadership of the ONCE team from Spain.</p>
        <p>Although Olano usually runs out of steam by the third week of the Tour, he is described as unusually motivated this year. That is also said of Jalabert, who never makes it over the highest climbs. Both men have been out of sight the last few weeks, training in the mountains the Tour will cover.</p>
        <p>The two, as well as any other contenders for Armstrong's title, have run out of room to hide. Now it is time to go seek.</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
