<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toll Phone Lines Promise Jobs, But Hide Price</title>
    <meta content="26PHON$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waldman, Amy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EEDD1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1311" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toll Phone Lines Promise Jobs, But Hide Price</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMY WALDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Waldman, Amy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Telephone lines with 540 exchange, promising jobs, hides high cost of call; many flyers containing information concerning 540 lines, most aimed at poor neighborhoods, cost as much as $19 per call; vendors running 540 lines are considered legal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The fliers cover the South Bronx like urban wallpaper. ''Jobs,'' they announce, with a roster of respectability: Marriott Hotels. Home Depot. United Parcel Service. ShopRite. ''With or without experience.''</p>
        <p>And they give a phone number: the area code is usually 718; the exchange is 540. One must look closely, very closely, to see the tiny, handwritten print that says each call costs $19. A version of the flier posted in Washington Heights does not mention the charge at all. ''We need men and women immediately'' to clean homes and offices, or work in stores or factories, it says, in Spanish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The fliers cover the South Bronx like urban wallpaper. ''Jobs,'' they announce, with a roster of respectability: Marriott Hotels. Home Depot. United Parcel Service. ShopRite. ''With or without experience.''</p>
        <p>And they give a phone number: the area code is usually 718; the exchange is 540. One must look closely, very closely, to see the tiny, handwritten print that says each call costs $19. A version of the flier posted in Washington Heights does not mention the charge at all. ''We need men and women immediately'' to clean homes and offices, or work in stores or factories, it says, in Spanish.</p>
        <p>But when you call 540-1095, the recording mentions no specific jobs. It merely gives the telephone numbers for job information lines at three hotels, two hospitals, and the health and hospitals division of 1199, the hospital workers' union.</p>
        <p>The service, one of dozens of special 540 toll lines offered by Bell Atlantic, is legal. The vendors who run 540 lines, offering information on obtaining things like jobs, apartments, dates or credit cards, say they are useful.</p>
        <p>But others say the lines, particularly those that aim at residents of poor neighborhoods who are often desperate for jobs or apartments, are predatory.</p>
        <p>''They are spread in every poor area of the South Bronx where people are out of work,'' said the Rev. Joseph Towle, a Jesuit priest who said he had worked in the area for a long time.</p>
        <p>Over the years, he said, he has seen the cost of the calls go up and the number of fliers proliferate.</p>
        <p>''I've seen 80 of these in four square blocks,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Certainly, some of the lines seem to walk a fine line between assistance and exploitation. One 540 line, for example, advertises ''city jobs -- no experience necessary'' in the classified section of The Daily News. The call is $2.95 a minute. The recording offers many time-eating phrases -- ''postal jobs are really good jobs -- starting pay is really good,'' and ''the information we are going to give you is going to be short and brief but very important'' -- but little real information. After five minutes, and almost $15, the caller will have the addresses and phone numbers of the main post offices in Manhattan, Brooklyn and Queens.</p>
        <p>Others, like several lines advertised in El Diario, the Spanish-language daily newspaper, charge $15 or more, and boast of good jobs working in factories or assembling dolls at home. The recordings tell the listener to write to a post office box or address for more information, but it is not clear whether the companies mentioned -- sometimes in Florida, sometimes in New Mexico -- exist.</p>
        <p>And one ad in El Diario offers jobs cleaning the homes of ''rich families,'' with excellent benefits and vacations.</p>
        <p>Call the recording, and another number is given, which turns out to be a voice mail recording for ''Nannies for You'' -- in Halifax, Nova Scotia. Add the 83 cents per minute plus tax it costs to call Halifax to the initial call's $16.95, and the caller will have spent nearly $18 -- for a job advertised as paying $10 an hour -- and still have no real information.</p>
        <p>Bell Atlantic, which offers the 540 numbers in the New York City region, says it imposes strict regulations on the 540 providers, along with the New York State Public Service Commission. Ads are supposed to state the cost of the call, and any call that can go over $3.50 has to state the cost at the outset and then give the caller 20 seconds to hang up. Bell Atlantic also offers call blocking, which can prevent 540 numbers from being dialed on a phone.</p>
        <p>But many of the 540 lines skirt these restrictions, like 540-HOME, which fails to advertise its $5 toll, or other lines, which fail to provide 20 seconds to disconnect. Bell Atlantic, which gets 26 cents for the first minute of every call and 7 cents per minute thereafter, says it cannot check if the jobs promised exist.</p>
        <p>''We can't police all of them,'' John J. Bonomo, a Bell Atlantic spokesman, said. Vendors go to the phone company with a proposal and they can charge virtually any price.</p>
        <p>''If it's not obscene, unlawful or illegal, I can't recall any case where we've turned them away,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Kevin Ortiz, a spokesman for the City Department of Consumer Affairs, said it briefly shut down one line, in conjunction with Bell Atlantic, in February because neither the fliers -- posted in immigrant communities -- nor the phone message indicated a fee. ''That's the first time we've ever dealt with it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The 540 lines have been around for more than a decade, the descendants of the lines that offered the time or the weather.</p>
        <p>The development of interactive technology -- which allow callers to press buttons for different options, like jobs in health care or retail, and have their choice recognized by a computer -- aided their birth.</p>
        <p>Dating lines were the mainstay for a long time, but the field has since diversified greatly. One man offered, for $85 a call, stock tips for those investing $1 million or more a day; he was able to support himself while dying of cancer, according to Larry Weiss, who was a pioneer of the technology and today runs a service bureau for 540 line providers.</p>
        <p>Many of the lines are now directed at immigrants, by immigrants -- immigration and employment information for newly arrived Russians, for example. Job lines offer information on work like fish processing jobs in the Northwest (in addition to the $12 for the 540 call, an application fee of $38 is required) and jobs on casino ships.</p>
        <p>The vendors are a tight-knit group. Mr. Weiss said he had helped set up and run ''dozens and dozens'' of 540 lines.</p>
        <p>He conceded that the field was ripe for deception. In one case, he said, a 540 vendor sent out teams of deliverymen who went to offices, pretended they were at the wrong place and asked to call their home office. Instead, they called their boss's 540 number, for a toll of $50. The man was eventually prosecuted.</p>
        <p>Others have figured out ways to page people to call costly 540 lines.</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Weiss said, most vendors he works with try to offer a useful service, regularly updating their job lines, for example.</p>
        <p>The job lines, he said, get ''hundreds and hundreds'' of calls each day.</p>
        <p>He would not say how much he earns, but said the lines provide a ''nice living'' for entrepreneurs.</p>
        <p>The field is lucrative enough for providers to have sued when Bell Atlantic tried to suspend the service for technical reasons.</p>
        <p>A year ago, the Federal Trade Commission ruled that the 540 lines should have at least five more years of business. Mr. Weiss said he was confident a way would be found to extend that.</p>
        <p>Unless, that is, another technological advance like the one that gave rise to the lines puts them out of business.</p>
        <p>''The biggest competitor right now is the Internet,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
