<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hours Past Deadline, Tentative Deal Averts a Strike at Con Ed</title>
    <meta content="26CONE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consolidated Edison Co of New York Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Utility Workers Union of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1D81530F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hours Past Deadline, Tentative Deal Averts a Strike at Con Ed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Steven</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Consolidated Edison and Utility Workers Union of America, union representing 9,200 of its workers, avert strike, reaching tentative contract settlement four hours after midnight deadline (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Consolidated Edison and the union representing 9,200 of its workers averted a strike yesterday, reaching a tentative contract settlement four hours after a midnight deadline.</p>
        <p>After a week of intense talks that repeatedly appeared near collapse, the two sides said they were relieved to have prevented a painful walkout, and to have spared Con Ed's 3.2 million customers any inconvenience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Consolidated Edison and the union representing 9,200 of its workers averted a strike yesterday, reaching a tentative contract settlement four hours after a midnight deadline.</p>
        <p>After a week of intense talks that repeatedly appeared near collapse, the two sides said they were relieved to have prevented a painful walkout, and to have spared Con Ed's 3.2 million customers any inconvenience.</p>
        <p>In the days before the strike deadline at 12:01 a.m. yesterday, Con Ed officials sought to reassure customers in New York City and Westchester County that a walkout would hardly disrupt service. But the union, Local 1-2 of the Utility Workers Union of America, warned that despite Con Ed's denials, a strike would hurt business and residential customers by causing delays in repairs and in reaching customer service representatives.</p>
        <p>Just hours before the strike deadline, union officials were warning that the outlook was bleak largely because of Con Ed's demand to reduce employees' paid sick days. On Friday, the union declared that the negotiations had reached an impasse, and a federal mediator quickly joined the talks, held in a conference center in Glen Cove, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Minutes after the midnight deadline, a union spokesman announced a breakthrough. So, instead of ordering the workers to walk out at midnight, as planned if there had been no agreement, the union's leaders continued negotiations into the early hours of the morning.</p>
        <p>The two sides declined to reveal details of the proposed contract, saying they first wanted the union to explain the details to the rank and file.</p>
        <p>Stephen Mangione, a union spokesman, said, ''The settlement includes across-the-board improvements and gains in wages, medical coverage and pensions.''</p>
        <p>He also said management had agreed to renew job security protections and to relent on its demands to reduce sick time. He declined to give further details.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mangione said the union's executive board was likely to vote today to send the proposed four-year contract to the members. They will vote on the agreement in a mailed ballot during July.</p>
        <p>Joseph Petta, a Con Ed spokesman, said the utility had only a brief statement: ''We are pleased to have reached a tentative settlement that is fair to the men and women of Con Edison who provide such an important service to our customers.''</p>
        <p>There were other positive developments in negotiations this weekend. The union reached tentative settlements with three new but smaller companies that provide more than half the city's electricity.</p>
        <p>Those companies, which entered the market in recent years after New York State deregulated its power industry, are KeySpan Energy, Orion Power Holdings and the NRG unit of Northern States Power. Together, they employ 332 unionized workers.</p>
        <p>Con Ed officials said that to minimize disruptions during a strike, the utility had worked in recent weeks to train and retrain more than 1,000 management employees to handle many of the responsibilities usually handled by union members.</p>
        <p>But union officials asserted that the lack of skilled employees resulting from a strike would have led to delays in getting repair workers to homes and businesses and in getting service representatives to answer customers' telephone calls.</p>
        <p>The union's leaders also said that if a blackout or storm damaged the system during a strike, repairs would take longer than usual.</p>
        <p>The unionized workers, who earn about $50,000 a year on average, include meter readers, linemen, manhole workers, emergency repair crews, splicers and power plant workers.</p>
        <p>In the two days before the strike deadline, union officials said, the talks were snarled the most over Con Ed's demand that the union agree to concessions in its sick leave formula -- a formula the company viewed as far too generous. Union officials said Con Ed was seeking concessions in a plan that allows workers to accumulate five days' sick leave for each year on the job. Con Ed executives were said to be upset that the old four-year agreement included a formula that allowed, for example, a worker with 20 years' experience to accumulate 100 sick days, which the worker could eventually cash out.</p>
        <p>The last Con Ed strike took place in 1983, when 16,500 workers went out for nine weeks. That walkout had little effect on most customers, although union officials said a lack of workers delayed repairs at an electrical substation in the garment district that was knocked out by a water main break. As a result of damage to the substation, the garment district endured a three-day blackout. Con Ed officials said the pace of repairs had not been affected.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mangione declined to discuss details of the tentative settlements that the union reached on Saturday with KeySpan, Orion and NRG.</p>
        <p>KeySpan, which operates a power station in Ravenswood, Queens, produces about one-fourth of the city's electricity and employs 131 unionized workers. KeySpan bought the plant from Con Ed in June 1999.</p>
        <p>Orion employs 186 unionized workers and provides about one-fifth of the city's power. It runs a generating station in Astoria, Queens, and two stations in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>NRG employs 15 unionized workers and runs a gas turbine generating station in Astoria, which, union officials estimate, produces about 15 percent of the city's electricity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
