<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Penn's Wrestling Coach, Match in the Trials Cut Too Close</title>
    <meta content="26OLYM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Wrestling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wrestling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DD1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Penn's Wrestling Coach, Match in the Trials Cut Too Close</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LIZ ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, June 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses results at US Olympic wrestling trials (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tears of celebration and anguished wails shook Reunion Arena on Saturday night, the pictures of victory framed separately from defeat.</p>
        <p>But for Roger Reina, joy and pain collided during the 167.5-pound freestyle wrestling final of the United States Olympic trials. ''If you heard a loud snap during the match,'' he said, ''that was my heart.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tears of celebration and anguished wails shook Reunion Arena on Saturday night, the pictures of victory framed separately from defeat.</p>
        <p>But for Roger Reina, joy and pain collided during the 167.5-pound freestyle wrestling final of the United States Olympic trials. ''If you heard a loud snap during the match,'' he said, ''that was my heart.''</p>
        <p>Reina is the University of Pennsylvania's wrestling coach. Brandon Slay, once his prized recruit, had just defeated Brian Dolph, his cherished assistant coach, 5-2 and 3-1 in the two-of-three-match finals at the trials. Slay and Dolph have been friends and training partners for five years, but Saturday night they competed against each other for only the third time.</p>
        <p>Slay broke their series tie in dominating fashion. It was too much for Reina, trying to congratulate and console, the conflicting emotions pouring out of him.</p>
        <p>''I've never experienced anything close to this for my 16 years as a coach and 30 years total in the sport,'' he said, tears forming in his reddened eyes. ''I've had assistant coaches who have been to the trials, and Brandon at the N.C.A.A. championships, but I have never had anything come close to this intensity, to this irony.''</p>
        <p>Slay, a 24-year-old native of Amarillo, Tex., received the loudest cheers from his home state crowd. After the referee raised Slay's hand, student and teacher clenched tightly for more than a minute. As they released their embrace, the 33-year-old Dolph kissed his friend on the cheek.</p>
        <p>''I owe my success to Brian Dolph,'' Slay said into a microphone for the 9,434 fans as Dolph walked away somberly to accept the end of his Olympic dream.</p>
        <p>''I put everything I had into training him,'' Dolph said. ''It was a no-win, no-lose situation.''</p>
        <p>Dolph has been an assistant at Penn for seven years. He will return to Philadelphia and will probably be Slay's training partner as Slay prepares for the Sydney Olympics.</p>
        <p>Slay left Penn in 1998 with an undergraduate degree in finance from the Wharton School. He also studied Dolph, a former National Collegiate Athletic Association champion at Indiana. ''My style is essentially his style,'' Slay said.</p>
        <p>Reina watched, helpless, as the two shadows dueled Saturday night. He had been in Dolph's corner coaching him through his three preliminary matches, but when Dolph and Slay wrestled, Reina said he could witness the scene only from the far mat, chin in hand, registering these thoughts:</p>
        <p>''What great friends these two are. How they helped each other get to the pinnacle of the country and possibly the world. I remember road trips, I remember when Brian and I went down to recruit Brandon.''</p>
        <p>Since leaving Penn, Slay has excelled on and off the mat. He works part time as an investment assistant for Charles Schwab while training at the Olympic Training Center in Colorado Springs. Slay won the national championship and had the bye at the trials through the finals, while Dolph, seeded third, had to upset the second-seeded wrestler and wrestle three times before meeting Slay.</p>
        <p>Dolph's body could not take the pounding.</p>
        <p>Slay is just starting to peak. ''I really believe I deserved to win this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He was not the only wrestler Saturday night with that kind of belief in himself. Rulon Gardner, 28, a Greco-Roman heavyweight, was tired of Matt Ghaffari, an Olympic silver medalist, drawing all the attention. After Gardner outlasted the 38-year-old Ghaffari, 1-0, in overtime, he could not hide his satisfaction.</p>
        <p>Sammie Henson, wrestling freestyle at 119 pounds, took bubble baths to clear his mind before the finals. Cary Kolat, at 138.75 pounds in freestyle, cleared his wife and family out of his hotel room, where he watched movies until he was numb.</p>
        <p>Melvin Douglas returned to the Olympics in the 213.75-pound freestyle weight class because his close friend, Dominic Black, defaulted after their first finals match, having aggravated the knee injury he sustained while training with Douglas last week.</p>
        <p>At 36, Douglas is the oldest wrestler on the team. At 20, Garrett Lowney became the youngest, in the Greco-Roman 213.75-pound class.</p>
        <p>As Slay became the first Texan to make an Olympic wrestling team, he rendered his coach speechless. Reina first found Dolph, then Slay. In tears, he hugged each of them, his heart torn, barely beating.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
