<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Convertible Debt Offerings Set for This Week</title>
    <meta content="26EQUI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4DB1530F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Convertible Debt Offerings Set for This Week</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>3TEC Energy Corp., Houston, 6.3 million shares. Bear, Stearns &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>7-Eleven Inc., Dallas, 10 million shares. Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Accord Networks Ltd., Petach-Tikva, Israel, an initial public offering of 5 million shares. CIBC Wood Gundy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The following equity and convertible debt offerings are expected this week:</p>
        <p>3TEC Energy Corp., Houston, 6.3 million shares. Bear, Stearns &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>7-Eleven Inc., Dallas, 10 million shares. Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Accord Networks Ltd., Petach-Tikva, Israel, an initial public offering of 5 million shares. CIBC Wood Gundy.</p>
        <p>ASCO P.L.C., Aberdeen, Scotland, an initial public offering of 12.5 million American depositary shares, each share represents 5 ordinary shares. Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette.</p>
        <p>Basic Energy Services Inc., Midland, Tex., an initial public offering of 4.9 million shares. Prudential Securities.</p>
        <p>CareScience Inc., Philadelphia, an initial public offering of 4 million shares. Deutsche Bank Alex. Brown.</p>
        <p>Click Commerce Inc., Chicago, an initial public offering of 5 million shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Dialog Semiconductor P.L.C., Teck-Nabern, Germany, an initial public offering of 8.5 million American depositary shares, each share represents one ordinary share. Deutsche Bank Alex. Brown and Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Divine InterVentures Inc., Lisle, Ill., an initial public offering of 14.3 million class A shares. Robertson Stevens.</p>
        <p>eFunds Corp., Milwaukee, an initial public offering of 6.3 million shares. Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>Exfo Electro-Optical Engineering Inc., Quebec, Canada, an initial public offering of 6 million suborindated voting shares. Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>FutureLink Corp., 6 million shares. Bear, Stearns &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Genuity Inc., Burlington, Mass., an initial public offering of 173.9 million class A shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter and Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Marvell Technology Group Ltd., Hamilton, Bermuda, an initial public offering of 6 million shares. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Mobile Telesystems O.J.S.C., Moscow, an initial public offering of 15 million of American depositary shares, each share represents 20 shares. Deutsche Bank Alex. Brown and ING Barrings.</p>
        <p>Mobility Electronics Inc., Scottsdale, Ariz., an initial public offering of 4 million shares. Deutsche Bank Alex. Brown.</p>
        <p>Netease.com Inc., Beijing, an initial public offering of 4.5 million American depositary shares, each share represents 60 ordinary shares. Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Precise Software Solutions Ltd., Savyon, Israel, an initial public offering of 4.3 million ordinary shares. Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Prudential P.L.C., London, an initial public offering of 15 million American depositary shares, each share represents 2 ordinary shares. Morgan Stanley Dean Witter.</p>
        <p>Santa Fe International Corp., Dallas, 30 million ordinary shares. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>StorageNtwks Inc., Waltham, Mass., an initial public offering of 9 million shares. Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>Stratos Lightwave Inc., Chicago, an initial public offering of 8.8 million shares. Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>Syntroleum Corp., Tulsa, Okla., 5.3 million shares. Merrill Lynch &amp; Co.</p>
        <p>TrueVision International Inc., Albuquerque, N.M., 750,000 units and each unit consists of one common share and one warrant. Kashner Davidson Securities Corp.</p>
        <p>(Source: MCM EquityWatch.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
