<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lives of Latinos, Beyond Tortillas and Salsa</title>
    <meta content="26SALA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Resurrection Blvd (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">la boda (tv program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Pov (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mexican-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EFDB1530F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1330" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lives of Latinos, Beyond Tortillas and Salsa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Julie Salamon reviews Resurrection Blvd, Showtime's new dramatic series, and documentary La Boda, part of PBS's POV series; both focus on Mexican-Americans; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''Viva Zapata!,'' the 1952 movie collaboration between Elia Kazan and John Steinbeck, the Mexican revolutionary leader was played by Marlon Brando. In the 1960 film ''Hell to Eternity,'' about a Mexican-American who fought in World War II, the part of the heroic marine, Guy Gabaldon, went to Jeffrey Hunter. The casting was in tune with the times. In those days, a Hispanic could be a hero but not a leading man.</p>
        <p>By the time ''Chico and the Man'' -- a sitcom about a Mexican-American character -- appeared on television in 1974, such casting had become more or less unacceptable. So a Hispanic actor, Freddie Prinze, was the star (though he was part Puerto Rican, part Hungarian and not at all Mexican). The show was hardly politically correct by today's standards. In one episode, Prinze's co-star said to Chico, ''Get outta here, and take your flies with you.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''Viva Zapata!,'' the 1952 movie collaboration between Elia Kazan and John Steinbeck, the Mexican revolutionary leader was played by Marlon Brando. In the 1960 film ''Hell to Eternity,'' about a Mexican-American who fought in World War II, the part of the heroic marine, Guy Gabaldon, went to Jeffrey Hunter. The casting was in tune with the times. In those days, a Hispanic could be a hero but not a leading man.</p>
        <p>By the time ''Chico and the Man'' -- a sitcom about a Mexican-American character -- appeared on television in 1974, such casting had become more or less unacceptable. So a Hispanic actor, Freddie Prinze, was the star (though he was part Puerto Rican, part Hungarian and not at all Mexican). The show was hardly politically correct by today's standards. In one episode, Prinze's co-star said to Chico, ''Get outta here, and take your flies with you.''</p>
        <p>While many shows focusing on black characters and culture have prospered in the 25 years since ''Chico,'' Latino dramas and sitcoms have been noticeably absent. (If you blinked, you probably missed ''A k a Pablo,'' the 1984 ABC sitcom starring Paul Rodriguez, or ''Condo,'' the 1983 sitcom about a Hispanic family.)</p>
        <p>Certainly, actors of Latin origin have done well on nonethnic shows: Jimmy Smits (''L.A. Law'' and ''N.Y.P.D. Blue''); Edward James Olmos (''Miami Vice''); Hector Elizondo ( ''Chicago Hope''). But the country's Hispanic population has been pretty much denied (or perhaps spared) a television version of their lives.</p>
        <p>This summer, however, television is offering a few opportunities to examine the heritage and homilies of Mexican-American culture. Last week the public television station WLIW showed ''The Mexican-Americans,'' a primer in that culture as well as a homage to some of its successful members, like Energy Secretary Bill Richardson, the director Luis Valdez and the actor Ricardo Montalban. It will be broadcast nationally on PBS in August. Tomorrow PBS's ''P.O.V.'' series presents another documentary, ''La Boda,'' a one-hour film that uses a migrant farm worker's wedding as the centerpiece for an intimate and sympathetic portrait of a Mexican-American family.</p>
        <p>On July 23 Nickelodeon presents ''The Brothers Garcia,'' which the cable network is promoting as ''the first English-language sitcom with an all-Latino cast.'' But, judging from the first episode, ''The Brothers Garcia'' is more rooted in television culture than in any other. With its kindly, baffled dad and slightly embarrassing but lovable mom, the show -- designed as a childhood memoir in the ''Wonder Years'' mode -- doesn't push its Latino identity much beyond a smattering of Spanish and tortillas and salsa for breakfast.</p>
        <p>Much riskier is Showtime's new weekly one-hour dramatic series, ''Resurrection Blvd.,'' about an East Los Angeles family. It's one thing to present a culture journalistically, another to bring it to life dramatically without veering into caricature. At news conferences for the show, which has a special movie-length premiere tonight at 10, the producers have emphasized their attempts to make the show authentically Latino, not only through the casting of actors but by filling crucial behind-the-scenes positions with people of Hispanic origin.</p>
        <p>So the director of tonight's episode is Jesus Salvador Trevino, whose credits include such mainstream shows as ''N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' ''The Practice'' and ''Nash Bridges.'' The show's creator, writer and co-executive producer is Dennis E. Leoni, whose background is Mexican.</p>
        <p>At first, in the clunky opening scenes of ''Resurrection Blvd.'' it feels as though all this earnest good will has been wasted on low-budget exploitation. The show begins with a grunting sex scene in a familiar setting, a car overlooking the Hollywood Hills. Thus we meet Carlos (Michael DeLorenzo), the would-be pride of the Santiago family.</p>
        <p>Shortly thereafter, Carlos and his brothers, driving around in a big car, find their younger sister Victoria (Marisol Nichols) flirting with a hunk. His badness is palpable. ''Stay away from my sister,'' snarls Carlos.</p>
        <p>You might wonder: How does this cliche differ from Anglo-invented cliches about Mexican-Americans?</p>
        <p>It doesn't, but ''Resurrection Blvd.'' does eventually distinguish itself. After the awkward opening scenes, the Santiagos begin to emerge as a real family, at least a real television family: big, noisy, argumentative and simmering with conflicts to play out in subsequent episodes. But they are also different from other television families. They casually mingle Spanish and English, and their cultural references are Hispanic as well as American.</p>
        <p>For example, the elder daughter, Yolanda (Ruth Livier), who works in a Beverly Hills law firm, complains that she can't meet a nice Hispanic man in Beverly Hills. Her aunt Bibi, played with sassy bluntness by Elizabeth Pena, advises her against marrying a Latino, ''a macho cabrone who's going to tell you when, where and how to do everything.'' The words would have a different meaning if an outsider uttered them.</p>
        <p>The Santiagos are working-class but upwardly mobile. Roberto, the father, and his oldest son, Miguel,  work in an auto repair shop, but Yolanda commutes to Beverly Hills and the youngest son, Alex (Nicholas Gonzalez), is a pre-med student. The mother is dead. (Her picture sits in the homemade altar where her husband lights candles every day.)</p>
        <p>Like ''Price of Glory,'' the recent Jimmy Smits movie failure, ''Resurrection Blvd.'' is about a father determined to have his sons carry on a thwarted boxing career. But in ''Resurrection Blvd.'' the father's ambition, while central to the drama, becomes one of the many desires fulminating in the Santiago household. Indeed, there's much fulmination in the first episode, which makes the requisite concessions to sex and violence -- but also some moments of grace, which cast light on this family and its culture. With its appealing cast, especially the charming newcomer Mr. Gonzalez, this show has a chance for ratings success, and that may open the door for more Hispanic programs (just as failure may well slam it shut again).</p>
        <p>While the fictional Santiagos are well into the process of assimilation, Elizabeth Luis de Guerrero, subject of the documentary ''La Boda,'' feels neither here nor there. ''I confuse my American values and Mexican values,'' the 22-year-old migrant farm worker tells Hannah Weyer, the filmmaker.</p>
        <p>Ms. Weyer has shot her film in a personal, casual style. To begin a new scene, she may simply ask, ''So what are we doing today?''</p>
        <p>What Elizabeth and her family are doing throughout the film is preparing for ''la boda,'' the wedding between Elizabeth and Artemio, her fiance. But we also see them doing what they usually do: Get up before dawn, ride to a field in a van, cover noses and mouths with scarves and begin picking grapes on a day when the temperature will reach 110 degrees.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth is a tiny woman with the eager grin and spontaneity of a very young girl. She and her family live in a small house in Mission, Tex., 15 minutes north of the Mexican border. It's more like a home base than a home. Elizabeth calculates that in her 22 years she has traveled the 1,800 miles to California 44 times to work with her family.</p>
        <p>But she isn't self-pitying, being far more preoccupied with wedding day details -- which range from the kind of mints she wants at the reception to having sex for the first time -- than with poverty and constant dislocation. With this portrait, Ms. Weyer has delivered a lovely Hispanic heroine playing herself.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
