<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; Playing 'Catch and Grope' in the Schoolyard</title>
    <meta content="26MON3$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Rican Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Puerto Ricans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central Park (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Staples, Brent</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Editorial Observer (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DD1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; Playing 'Catch and Grope' in the Schoolyard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRENT STAPLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Staples, Brent</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brent Staples's Editorial Observer column says sexual rampage against women in Central Park by gangs of men during Puerto Rican Day parade could transform how US looks at sexual harassment and violence against women; says fact that attacks were carried out by young men without criminal records shows extent to which harassment and violence against women have been normalized, making perpetrators regard it as form of recreation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ten years have passed since an amateur video cameraman filmed Los Angeles police officers beating Rodney King as he lay on the pavement. The sight of the officers savaging an unarmed man while colleagues stood casually by elevated police brutality as a civic concern and stimulated a broader discussion about its effects on the culture.</p>
        <p>The Central Park rampage could similarly transform how this country looks at sexual harassment and violence against women. The police have now identified more than 40 suspects from the mobs that harassed and assaulted what now appear to be as many as 50 women, many of whom were doused with water and stripped while young people stood by cheering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ten years have passed since an amateur video cameraman filmed Los Angeles police officers beating Rodney King as he lay on the pavement. The sight of the officers savaging an unarmed man while colleagues stood casually by elevated police brutality as a civic concern and stimulated a broader discussion about its effects on the culture.</p>
        <p>The Central Park rampage could similarly transform how this country looks at sexual harassment and violence against women. The police have now identified more than 40 suspects from the mobs that harassed and assaulted what now appear to be as many as 50 women, many of whom were doused with water and stripped while young people stood by cheering.</p>
        <p>Men around the city have expressed surprise. But most of the women I spoke with saw the attacks in the park as a logical extension of the public sexual harassment that has shadowed them throughout their lives, from grade-school playgrounds into middle age, up and down nearly every street in the city. The festive attitudes of the mobs and the public nature of the attacks lend credence to what these women have been saying.</p>
        <p>Relying on amateur videotapes, New York City police have arrested more than 20 young men. According to a senior police official, most do not have criminal records. The lack of career criminals in this group suggests that these were ''ordinary'' men who drank too much while attending the National Puerto Rican Day Parade. Stoked with booze, they worked up from hooting at women, to grabbing them, to drenching them with water and pulling off their tops and pants. The escalation from verbal harassment to unwanted touching to full-fledged physical assault is crucial to understanding this problem. The cycle reflects the pervasive sense among many American men that they are entitled to own women's bodies and to force the issue if they wish to.</p>
        <p>The rampage would be less puzzling had it been conducted by, say, a band of rapists on parole. But the fact that it was carried out by ''ordinary'' young men without records shows the extent to which harassment and violence against women have been normalized -- and that many young men regard this behavior as a form of recreation.</p>
        <p>The only bright spot lies in the fact that the public responded sympathetically to the victims. As recently as 30 years ago, many would have dismissed the events as horseplay by ''red blooded'' young men, granting them symbolic ownership of the women they harassed. The real Neanderthals would have said that the women ''deserved it'' for going about scantily clad. Fearing blame and recrimination, the victims would have gone home in shame, relieved at having escaped rape.</p>
        <p>That the Central Park victims came forward shows that things have changed dramatically. That they kept pressing the case even after a few police officers ignored their pleas for help underscores a bravery that would have been difficult to come by in the late 1960's, when the women's movement was just getting under way.</p>
        <p>Those who get convicted in connection with the Central Park rampage could eventually meet a 27-yearold woman named Misu Byrd, a domestic violence consultant who furnishes court-mandated treatment for men who come into the court system for battering women. Ms. Byrd said in an interview last week that she was ''not at all surprised'' by the episode since the culture tolerates harassment of women from a very young age, starting in the schoolyard. ''It is a typical thing that takes place,'' she said. ''I remember growing up it happened on the schoolyard, from elementary into middle school. We had this game in which boys converged on girls, and groped them and pulled at their clothing, then ran away. My mother asked me recently why I never told her, but I grew up thinking it was normal. I thought that because no one at school did anything about it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Byrd argues that the culture takes sexual crimes lightly, even at the criminal level. ''Seventy-five percent of domestic violence cases are pled down to misdemeanors. The average child-molesting relative gets five years max -- because the judicial system does not see it as an important crime. . . . We have normalized sexual abuse. Orders of protection are the typical response to assaults on women -- but orders of protection do not stop bullets.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Byrd does not talk like an optimist. But just last week something in one of her sessions cheered her. When a man called an instructor ''sweetheart,'' she rebuked him, and was joined by another man in the class who said: ''She's right. We have to be more aware . . . especially after that Central Park thing.'' This is good advice for the rest of us, whether we are parents, baby sitters or principals patrolling grade school playgrounds. We either break these habits early or risk that they will become permanent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
