<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Mexican Slum, 2 Views Of the Government's Help</title>
    <meta content="Y26CHA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Valle de Chalco (Mex)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thompson, Ginger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D71530F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Mexican Slum, 2 Views Of the Government's Help</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINGER THOMPSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thompson, Ginger</byline>
      <dateline>VALLE DE CHALCO, Mexico, June 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Valle de Chalco, Mex, are distrustul of government's recent handouts and promises of better tomorrow as presidential vote nears, and are staging demonstrations demanding that it do more to eliminate squalor and improve quality of life; Institutional Revolutionary Party, which has used election-year handouts and public works projects to keep control of most depressed and isolated parts of country, has repeatedly reneged on promises to turn Valle de Chalco into shining model of prosperity; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As she worked to dig out her family's belongings from a flood of raw sewage that swallowed her ramshackle house, a scowling Maria de la Luz recalled the years when the government promised to turn her neighborhood into a shining model of prosperity.</p>
        <p>It began more than a decade ago when the country's last president, Carlos Salinas de Gortari, stood in a plaza just a few blocks away and announced a new public works project called Solidaridad that would turn rural villages and hideous slums into models of Mexico's new prosperity. The promises lured Mrs. de la Luz and her family to Valle de Chalco, some 20 miles east of Mexico City, which was to be Solidaridad's main showplace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As she worked to dig out her family's belongings from a flood of raw sewage that swallowed her ramshackle house, a scowling Maria de la Luz recalled the years when the government promised to turn her neighborhood into a shining model of prosperity.</p>
        <p>It began more than a decade ago when the country's last president, Carlos Salinas de Gortari, stood in a plaza just a few blocks away and announced a new public works project called Solidaridad that would turn rural villages and hideous slums into models of Mexico's new prosperity. The promises lured Mrs. de la Luz and her family to Valle de Chalco, some 20 miles east of Mexico City, which was to be Solidaridad's main showplace.</p>
        <p>Today, however, she compares those promises to the smelly gunk she wiped off her television set -- a result a few weeks ago when a canal that runs alongside her neighborhood ruptured under heavy rain and gushed raw sewage, waist high, into hundreds of homes.</p>
        <p>The barrio -- with its filthy streets, unreliable water system and cinder-block houses that look only half completed -- already stood as an example of the poverty and federal neglect that persisted despite the government's promises. But for Mrs. de la Luz, the sewage explosion was the ultimate humiliation. So when government officials showed up offering handouts and promises for a better tomorrow, she and hundreds of others said those expressions of good intentions were no longer enough.</p>
        <p>For five nights last week, gangs of residents from Valle de Chalco and its neighboring communities blocked a major east-west highway, stopping traffic there for hours each night to demand that the government install a drainage system in the canal to prevent its walls from collapsing.</p>
        <p>They said they had warned the government about the fragility of the canal for years, and for years local leaders reneged on their promises to take heed. Tired of being ignored, residents like Mrs. de la Luz looked forward to the national elections.</p>
        <p>''They humiliate us and treat us like beggars with their bags of blankets and old clothes,'' said Mrs. de la Luz, referring to government officials. ''Well, the truth is, right now we are beggars because we have lost everything. But they are beggars too, because they know that they are close to losing everything.''</p>
        <p>For more than seven decades, the ruling Institutional Revolutionary Party, known as the PRI, has used handouts and election-year public works projects to keep control of the most depressed and isolated parts of Mexico. And as the party faces one of the most serious electoral challenges of its history -- a presidential election on July 2 that polls describe as a virtual tie between the PRI candidate, Francisco Labastida Ochoa, and the center-right candidate, Vicente Fox Quesada -- the reported distribution of handouts has soared.</p>
        <p>But in places like Valle de Chalco, it seems that the power of the freebie has greatly diminished, and with it, the popularity of the PRI, as voters continue to live in miserable conditions, weary of short-term fixes.</p>
        <p>Still, even with all the hardships here, there lingers earnest support for the PRI. And the contradictory opinions mirror those of communities across the country and help explain why no one can predict the election's outcome.</p>
        <p>Mrs. de la Luz said she had always voted for the PRI. But even after the government has given her family $1,000 to help replace all she has lost, she does not plan to continue giving the ruling party her support.</p>
        <p>Neither will Paulino Rosas Ramirez. ''They think they can buy our dignity,'' he said. ''They are wrong.''</p>
        <p>That is just whining to people like Evangelina Mondragon, 38. Like Mrs. de la Luz, she also remembered when President Salinas first came to Valle de Chalco. The streets were a maze of muddy lanes. The houses were made from flimsy scraps of wood and tin. And no one had safe sources of water and electricity. All that has changed for the better, she said, thanks to the PRI. ''We still have a lot to do,'' she said, wearing a PRI campaign T-shirt, ''but the answer is not to change parties. We have to keep moving ahead.''</p>
        <p>Bryan Hernandez, a 34-year-old father of two, agrees. He drives a bicycle taxi and charges two pesos (about 20 cents) per ride. On a good day, he said, he earns $7. It is not much, but his family gets by. And, he said, the government has helped.</p>
        <p>''Things here go up and down,'' he said, ''but at least the country is stable. Who knows what would happen if we changed the government. It would be worse.''</p>
        <p>Things could not get much worse for Rocio Dominguez, 30. Her home and livelihood were wiped out in the recent flood, and her husband makes less than $40 a month at a paint factory. She made a living as a seamstress, but the flood destroyed all her sewing machines. And when the government came to deliver her a bag of unlaundered used clothes, she said, it felt like salt in an open wound.</p>
        <p>''I am not going to say they have not sent things to us, because they have,'' she said of the government. ''But what they send is very little. And our needs are great.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
