<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deutsche Telekom Web Unit Ends Its Talks for Freeserve</title>
    <meta content="26DEUT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210534"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">T-Online International Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Telekom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dixons Group Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Freeserve Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE5DA1530F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deutsche Telekom Web Unit Ends Its Talks for Freeserve</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>T-Online International, Deutsche Telekom Internet unit, reportedly ends talks to acquire Internet service provider Freeserve PLC from Dixons Group (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Deutsche Telekom's Internet arm, T-Online International, has withdrawn from negotiations to acquire Britain's largest Internet service provider, Freeserve P.L.C. for about $9 billion, according to executives close to the discussions.</p>
        <p>The talks, which had taken place in fits and starts over the last several months between T-Online, Freeserve and its parent, the Dixons Group, a British electronics retailer, stalled last week after the companies could not agree on a variety of management issues, the executives said. Price was not a sticking point, the executives added.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Deutsche Telekom's Internet arm, T-Online International, has withdrawn from negotiations to acquire Britain's largest Internet service provider, Freeserve P.L.C. for about $9 billion, according to executives close to the discussions.</p>
        <p>The talks, which had taken place in fits and starts over the last several months between T-Online, Freeserve and its parent, the Dixons Group, a British electronics retailer, stalled last week after the companies could not agree on a variety of management issues, the executives said. Price was not a sticking point, the executives added.</p>
        <p>T-Online could still return to the bargaining table, the executives emphasized, though Freeserve is now looking to court several other possible buyers. Potential suitors include NTL Inc., a telecommunications and cable television company that last year acquired Cable and Wireless's consumer phone, cable television and Internet business, and Terra Networks, the Internet unit of Telefonica of Spain, which recently bought the Internet portal site Lycos.</p>
        <p>T-Online may now start its own Internet service in Britain in conjunction with another Deutsche Telekom unit, the British mobile phone operator One2One, an executive close to the company said.</p>
        <p>Freeserve, which is less than two years old, was the first company in Britain to market an Internet service with no online charges, a business model that has been widely imitated here and across Europe. The company is seen as an attractive acquisition target because of its broad audience. Potential buyers hope to sell Freeserve customers other services like cable television and phone service.</p>
        <p>Instead of charging a subscription fee, Freeserve makes money by retaining a percentage of the revenue generated by the cost of a user's telephone call. It also gains revenue from advertising and electronic commerce.</p>
        <p>Dixons, which owns 80 percent of Freeserve, formed it as a vehicle to get into the Internet business. Freeserve surprised competitors by quickly becoming Britain's most heavily used Internet access provider, displacing AOL U.K.</p>
        <p>Freeserve's stock price has been volatile lately, amid speculation that the company might soon be acquired at a premium to its market capitalization of $6.7 billion. Freeserve is planning to announce its full-year operating results on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
