<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Freeing Spirits From a Prayer Circle</title>
    <meta content="26RHYT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210514"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rhthmek (Dance Troupe)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunning, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4DB1530F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Freeing Spirits From a Prayer Circle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunning, Jennifer</byline>
      <dateline>BECKET, Mass., June 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jennifer Dunning reviews performance by new dance troupe Rhthmek at Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, Becket, Mass; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rhythmek could well have adopted the hyperbole of international ballet tours and called itself ''Stars of the Modern Dance.'' There has seldom been such an assemblage of charismatic lead modern-dance performers as in this new group, founded by the former Alvin Ailey dancers Elizabeth Roxas, Karine Plantadit-Bageot and Michael Thomas.</p>
        <p>The dances did not quite measure up to the gifts of their interpreters. But during thin spots in the program, presented on Friday in the Doris Duke Studio Theater at the Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, there were always interesting stage personalities and good-looking bodies with impressive control and strength.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rhythmek could well have adopted the hyperbole of international ballet tours and called itself ''Stars of the Modern Dance.'' There has seldom been such an assemblage of charismatic lead modern-dance performers as in this new group, founded by the former Alvin Ailey dancers Elizabeth Roxas, Karine Plantadit-Bageot and Michael Thomas.</p>
        <p>The dances did not quite measure up to the gifts of their interpreters. But during thin spots in the program, presented on Friday in the Doris Duke Studio Theater at the Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival, there were always interesting stage personalities and good-looking bodies with impressive control and strength.</p>
        <p>The suite of seven dances by seven choreographers, called ''Lightbody,'' purported to examine seven kinds of relationships. The first two dances, both new, were essentially examples of the tiresome strike-an-attitude modern-dance genre popular in small, performer-driven modern dance troupes today. ''Sherash (Relationship With the Group),'' created by Mia Michaels, a jazz-dance choreographer, and set to Robert Slap's ''Eternal Om'' and music by In Nursery and Klive and Nigel Humberstone, opened with all 12 performers in a dancers' prayer circle. ''Sherash'' degenerated into aimless angst expressed at very great length in group and ensemble dances.</p>
        <p>Bill Hastings's ''Nabta Playa (Relationship in Partnership),'' danced to music by Marty Beller, deposited Ms. Roxas and Ms. Plantadit-Bageot in and near broken beach chairs on condemned land. Mr. Thomas moved among the two, drawing them eventually into his dance. The best moments in the piece, as badly in need of editing as Ms. Michaels's dance, occurred when Mr. Hastings, a Broadway choreographer, freed his dancers from their locked bodies and allowed them to cover more space.</p>
        <p>The evening picked up with ''Secret Self (Relationship With Self),'' two solos and a duet from Zvi Gotheiner's ''Chairs.'' Rebecca Rigert created an overpowering sense of despair as she writhed in a chair to Rachmaninoff. Elizabeth Parkinson looked like a party girl gone bad -- and mad -- in a twisting, finicky solo with chair to the soundtrack from ''Talk Radio.'' A duet for Roger Bellamy and Dwight Rhoden, danced on a chair to Russian Orthodox Church music, was less clear emotionally.</p>
        <p>Gary Pierce, a former ballroom champion, made a romantic boxing match of tangos for two pairs of lovers in ''On the Ropes (Relationship in Love),'' set to music by Astor Piazzolla. Clever and enjoyably sultry, the dance drew extra-intense and playful performing from Ms. Roxas and Desmond Richardson in a cast completed by Leonora Stapleton, a powerful modern dancer uncomfortable in the tango, and the genially gallant Antonio Scott.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas turned Zane Booker into a statue come alive with dignity yet a capacity for human pain in ''Shout Out (Relationship With the Voice),'' performed to music by Mr. Scott. And Mr. Rhoden, whose Complexions company was the model for companies of independent dancers like Rhythmek, gave Sarita Allen a chance to be her distinctive force-of-nature self in ''Growth (Relationship With the Body),'' set to music by Steve Reich.</p>
        <p>''Lightbody'' closed with Ulysses Dove's ''Episodes,'' which looks much better close up in this intimate theater space. The dance is essentially a series of racing stage crosses and brutal collisions along stark paths of white light. Seen up close, the dancers become humans, their bodies more than mere hurtling missiles. Another revelation was just how big and affectingly Ms. Rigert and Ms. Plantadit dance. Ms. Rigert seethes with quiet drama. Ms. Plantadit pounces like a playful lioness.</p>
        <p>The handsome costumes were designed by Mary Jane Marcasiano. The dramatic lighting was by Brenda Dolan.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
