<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nader, Nominated by the Greens, Attacks Politics as Usual</title>
    <meta content="Y26GRE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210560"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GREEN PARTY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Party</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reform Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1D61530F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nader, Nominated by the Greens, Attacks Politics as Usual</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, June 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Consumer advocate Ralph Nader is nominated for president by Green Party; accepts nomination with blistering attack against Republicans, Democrats, Congress, corporate America and commission that sets rules for presidential debates; condemns political system for making Democratic candidate Vice Pres Al Gore and Republican rival Gov George W Bush virtually indistinguishable; says he and Reform Party nominee should be allowed to participate in campaign debates; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a blistering attack against Republicans, Democrats, Congress, corporate America and the commission that sets the rules for presidential debates, Ralph Nader today accepted the presidential nomination of the Green Party, a growing political force that could weaken the prospects of Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Condemning a political system that he said makes Mr. Gore and his likely Republican opponent, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, virtually indistinguishable, Mr. Nader said he could imagine winning in November, especially if the Presidential Debate Commission -- and by extension, its corporate sponsors and the two major parties -- allowed him and the Reform Party nominee to take part in the debates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a blistering attack against Republicans, Democrats, Congress, corporate America and the commission that sets the rules for presidential debates, Ralph Nader today accepted the presidential nomination of the Green Party, a growing political force that could weaken the prospects of Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Condemning a political system that he said makes Mr. Gore and his likely Republican opponent, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, virtually indistinguishable, Mr. Nader said he could imagine winning in November, especially if the Presidential Debate Commission -- and by extension, its corporate sponsors and the two major parties -- allowed him and the Reform Party nominee to take part in the debates.</p>
        <p>''Polls show that the American people want the debates opened to my candidacy and that of Pat Buchanan,'' Mr. Nader said at the Green Party National Convention, referring to the leading contender for the Reform nomination. ''But the demands of the people mean little to Gore and Bush. It is very important to them that the electoral process remains a closed-door affair between the Republican and Democratic parties.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader, a well-known consumer advocate who won less than 1 percent of the vote four years ago when he ran a symbolic presidential campaign as a Green, had little trouble gaining the nomination for the 2000 race. He faced only marginal opposition and won 295 of the 319 votes, or 92 percent, from delegates representing the District of Columbia and the 39 states where the Greens have a party organization.</p>
        <p>No other candidate ran a serious campaign. Jello Biafra (whose real name is Eric Boucher), leader of the now-defunct punk-rock band Dead Kennedys, and Stephen Gaskin, the founder of a commune in Tennessee, each won 10 votes. Joel Kovel, the Green candidate for the Senate from New York in 1998, got 3 votes, and one voter abstained.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader, who belongs to no political party, including the Greens -- ''It's a thing with me,'' he told reporters -- has demonstrated broad appeal to voters who see Mr. Gore's moderate positions on many issues, including support of the death penalty and international trade agreements, as a betrayal of traditional Democratic constituencies, like labor unions. Because of his opposition to global trade agreements, Mr. Nader also has a certain attractiveness to some Republican conservatives.</p>
        <p>But with Mr. Nader's strongly held liberal views on social issues, views  that most Republicans would oppose -- he favors gun control and abortion rights for women, which are popular among Democrats -- his support in the fall's election is far more likely to come at the expense of Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>And with the support he predicted he would win from people who are disenchanted with the electoral process because of the influence of money on the major parties, Mr. Nader has appeared to eclipse Mr. Buchanan as the leading third-party contender. A recent NBC/Wall Street Journal poll found Mr. Bush leading Mr. Gore by 43 percent to 39 percent and Mr. Nader leading Mr. Buchanan, a Republican-turned-Reform candidate, by 7 percent to 4 percent.</p>
        <p>In his denunciation of Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush as ''drab and dreary'' choices whose policies largely reflect the influence of corporate campaign contributions, Mr. Nader called on the debate commission to change the  criteria for participation. Currently, a candidate must show at least 15 percent support in the polls.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nader said that with so many voters yearning for more choices, the commission should open the debates to any candidate who has reached 5 percent -- the level that qualifies a candidate for federal matching funds in the next election -- or to a candidate who has qualified for the ballot in a majority of states. Currently, Mr. Nader is on the ballot in 20 states and the District of Columbia.</p>
        <p>While the focus of Greens around the country has largely been environmental issues, Mr. Nader has made the centerpiece of his campaign the influential role of corporations in  politics. He insisted that Democrats and Republicans have become beholden to corporations through large campaign contributions that win them preferential treatment, leaving average Americans to suffer with needlessly low wages, inadequate health care and failing schools.</p>
        <p>He chided both parties for pursuing a missile defense system that he contended was unworkable, dangerous to American foreign policy and too expensive. He said the leaders of both major parties supported the missile system because defense contractors who have a stake in building it were major campaign donors.</p>
        <p>Further, he charged that corporate influence has blurred any meaningful distinctions between the parties, referring to President Clinton as ''George Ronald Clinton.''</p>
        <p>In his acceptance speech today, Mr. Nader told delegates that corporate interests have virtually strangled the ability of government to represent ordinary citizens, pushing them away from politics.</p>
        <p>''Feelings of powerlessness and the withdrawal of massive numbers of Americans from both civic and political arenas are deeply troubling,'' Mr. Nader said. ''The situation has to be addressed by a fresh political movement arising from the citizenry's labors and resources and dreams about what American could become at long last.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE GREEN PARTY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
