<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GOVERNING PARTY IN JAPAN SUFFERS ELECTION SETBACK</title>
    <meta content="26JAPA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mori, Yoshiro (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">French, Howard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2DE1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GOVERNING PARTY IN JAPAN SUFFERS ELECTION SETBACK</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">French, Howard W</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, Monday, June 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japan's governing Liberal Democratic Party suffers stinging setback in Parliamentary elections, barely retaining control over powerful lower house in surprisingly weak showing that could put strong pressure on recently appointed prime minister, Yoshiro Mori, to resign; finishes with 271 seats in lower house, or 56 percent, compared with 65 percent before vote; opposition Democratic Party advances from 95 seats to 127 seats; strong turn away from government in urban areas, and even some rural regions that are main beneficiaries of government's largesse, noted; suggest shifts away from Liberal Democrats, who have ruled country for all but 18 months since 1955; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japan's governing Liberal Democratic Party suffered a stinging setback in parliamentary elections on Sunday. It barely retained control over the powerful lower house in a surprisingly weak showing that could put strong pressure on its recently appointed prime minister, Yoshiro Mori, to resign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mori and his allies rushed to put as good a spin on the results as they could, saying that the party's sharp decline still left it with a mandate to govern. But as it barely met its own minimum goals for the election, many are already expecting calls for a replacement of the prime minister after Japan is host to a summit meeting of leading industrial nations next month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japan's governing Liberal Democratic Party suffered a stinging setback in parliamentary elections on Sunday. It barely retained control over the powerful lower house in a surprisingly weak showing that could put strong pressure on its recently appointed prime minister, Yoshiro Mori, to resign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mori and his allies rushed to put as good a spin on the results as they could, saying that the party's sharp decline still left it with a mandate to govern. But as it barely met its own minimum goals for the election, many are already expecting calls for a replacement of the prime minister after Japan is host to a summit meeting of leading industrial nations next month.</p>
        <p>For the meantime, the narrow victory for the governing coalition  seemed to pave the way for a continuation of the heavy spending that for a decade has kept Japan's stagnant economy barely afloat.</p>
        <p>In complete but unofficial returns, the governing coalition finished with 271 seats in the lower house, or 56 percent, compared with a 65 percent hold before the vote.</p>
        <p>The opposition Democratic Party made dramatic gains, advancing from 95 seats in the last lower house elections, in 1996, to 127 in the new Parliament.</p>
        <p>The strong turn against the governing party in urban areas and even in rural regions that are the main beneficiaries of the lavish government spending suggested that Japanese yearn for a shift away from the Liberal Democrats, who have ruled the country for all but 18 months since 1955. But voters apparently do not yet regard the Democratic Party as a viable alternative.</p>
        <p>''It's a major defeat for the L.D.P.,'' the national newspaper Asahi declared in an editorial early today. ''What the election results show is the public's hope for a change -- not approval.''</p>
        <p>The force of the electoral tide against Mr. Mori could be seen in the embarrassing fact that two of his ministers, Trade Minister Takashi Fukaya and Agriculture Minister Tokuichiro Tamazawa, were unable to keep their Parliament seats.</p>
        <p>The Mori administration has held power only two months but has been stricken with crises. Most of them were self-inflicted in extraordinarily provocative comments by Mr. Mori himself, from the very moment he replaced his predecessor, Keizo Obuchi, who was hit by a sudden stroke in early April and later died.</p>
        <p>In a post-election interview on the NHK television network, Hiromu Nonaka, the Liberal Democratic Party's secretary general, called his party's position ''very severe,'' and said it was ''regrettable that we did not win the trust of the people.'' Later, with the vote counting completed, Mr. Nonaka expressed relief that his party had won 233 seats, just 4 more than the minimum tally that he said would lead him to resign. ''It is only natural for Mr. Mori to stay in power,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Disaffection with the conservative Liberal Democratic Party, whose heavy spending has left Japan with a still-sputtering economy and the heaviest debt burden of any industrial nation, has been creeping steadily upward for years. In this election for the first time, most polls showed that unaffiliated and undecided voters together made up the largest electoral group, surpassing governing party supporters.</p>
        <p>In the final week of campaigning, Mr. Mori expressed satisfaction over polls that showed his party doing well. Asked about the large number of undecided voters on Tuesday, he said, ''If they still have no interest in the election, it would be all right if they just slept.''</p>
        <p>The Democratic Party claimed that its performance, after a campaign that stressed fiscal responsibility, would help push Japan toward a two-party system, which has been a treasured goal for Japan's fragmented opposition for years.</p>
        <p>''This is a major step forward toward a two-party system, and the voters' understanding of the Democratic Party has deepened,'' Yukio Hatoyama, the leader of the Democratic Party, said at a post-election news conference at his headquarters. ''Voters have expressed their discontent with the Mori government. They have shown that they don't approve of the current situation.''</p>
        <p>Despite this triumphant claim, though, many voters said today that they still saw little to choose between in the policies of the Liberal Democrats and the Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>The surprisingly severe narrowing of the government's working majority and the emergence of the Democratic Party as a major force, but still one far short of a majority, left the country strangely without any clear direction for change.</p>
        <p>''The Liberal Democratic Party doesn't rest on any solid foundation anymore,'' said Gerald L. Curtis, an expert in Japanese politics at Columbia University who monitored the vote here. ''It wins by default, and that is not a recipe for long-term success. There is a lot of uneasiness about the future and concern about stagnation, but there is no view of what an alternative policy vision should look like. Nothing has captured the imagination of anybody.''</p>
        <p>The Liberal Democrats appeared to be severely hobbled by Mr. Mori's unusually low popularity ratings. Public support for the Mori cabinet has been stuck in the 12 to 25 percent range almost since his appointment on April 5.</p>
        <p>The Liberal Democrats were widely criticized for a daylong delay after Mr. Obuchi's stroke before the country was told what had happened, and for a prime ministerial succession that was arranged in secret.</p>
        <p>Barely over that popularity-sapping sequence, Mr. Mori, who has long been known for verbal gaffes, began making a string of statements that strongly echoed the militarist propaganda of Japan's pre-World War II regime.</p>
        <p>One comment called Japan a ''divine nation with an emperor at its center.'' Another remark, just days before the election, told voters in southern Japan to ''defend the home front,'' and used another militarist term to praise the memory of fallen soldiers from the wartime Army.</p>
        <p>Asked in a televised interview late Sunday whether his remarks had hurt his party, a grim-faced Mr. Mori said, ''I am taking that criticism very seriously.''</p>
        <p>The day's other big losers were the Liberal Democrats' coalition partners, particularly the Buddhist-affiliated New Komeito Party, which saw its seats decline to 31 from 42. The other coalition party, the New Conservatives, was left struggling for life, with 7 seats, down from 18 before the election.</p>
        <p>For months, opinion polls have shown that voters disapproved of the one-year-old coalition between the conservative Liberal Democrats and New Komeito, whose policies are associated with social welfare spending and pacifism, as a cynical marriage of convenience.</p>
        <p>The government's terrible poll numbers, coming on top of a record-hugging unemployment rate, near-zero economic growth and a national debt approaching crisis levels, seemed to offer the opposition a rare opportunity to unseat the Liberal Democrats. Still, opinion polls were almost unanimous in the days leading up to the vote in predicting a solid win by the Liberal Democrats and their coalition partners. The opposition's chances appeared even further diminished by rainy weather over most of the archipelago on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Early estimates of turnout were about 63 percent, which would make it the second lowest turnout ever in a modern parliamentary elections here. With its well-oiled machine and plethora of incumbents, the governing party is believed to do best in situations of low voter turnout.</p>
        <p>In the final days before the voting, Mr. Hatoyama, the leader of the opposition Democrats, sought to portray the election as a clear choice between his party and the Liberal Democrats. ''It is meaningless for you to vote for a third party,'' he said in a rally in Osaka on Saturday.</p>
        <p>After years of heavy, pork-barrel spending, officially justified by the need to keep the sputtering economy's pumps primed, the Democratic Party has spoken of the ''bitter medicine'' that heavily indebted Japan must now take. During the campaign, Mr. Hatoyama said the medicine would have to include increased taxes, which he said would have to be shared by lower-income people.</p>
        <p>One price of Mr. Hatoyama's decidedly unpopulist campaign was that he barely kept his own seat, winning re-election in a squeaker.</p>
        <p>Many voters apparently saw little to distinguish the two main parties from each other.</p>
        <p>Sadayasu Tonegi, a 56-year-old restaurant owner in Tokyo's Shinjuku ward, said, ''I don't understand the differences in policies among the parties, they all look the same to me.'' He said he had voted for a Democratic Party candidate.</p>
        <p>Another voter, Yasushi Osawa, a 28-year-old construction company worker, said he knew little about policy matters, but had voted for the Liberal Democrats. He said their policies ''may be obscure, but are better than the Democratic Party, which has no policies at all.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
