<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Last Lap in the Genome Race</title>
    <meta content="26MON1$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210590"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Human Genome Project</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Celera Genomics Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Institutes of Health</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DD1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Last Lap in the Genome Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial lauds as landmark in scientific discovery reported deciphering of entire human genome by teams of scientists at Celera Genomics and National Institutes of Health (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists from rival teams are scheduled to announce today that they have come very close to deciphering the entire human genome, a feat that will stand as a landmark in scientific discovery. The publicly financed Human Genome Project has put together a ''working draft'' of the genome, while Celera Genomics, a private company, has completed its ''first assembly'' of the genome. Neither side in this bitter rivalry has deciphered every single chemical unit of the human genetic material -- that is not possible with today's technology -- but each side has made tremendous contributions toward what future historians will surely rate as a pivotal scientific achievement, ushering in an exciting new stage of biological exploration.</p>
        <p>It is humbling to recall that when the idea of deciphering the human genome was first proposed in the 1980's, most of the major figures in biology deemed it a waste of time, talent and resources that would generate reams of useless data. It was the Energy Department that pushed for a federally financed project, forcing the National Institutes of Health to join the task to preserve leadership in its own domain. Since then, mainstream biologists have embraced the cause with enthusiasm, largely because automation and other technical advances made the task far easier and faster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scientists from rival teams are scheduled to announce today that they have come very close to deciphering the entire human genome, a feat that will stand as a landmark in scientific discovery. The publicly financed Human Genome Project has put together a ''working draft'' of the genome, while Celera Genomics, a private company, has completed its ''first assembly'' of the genome. Neither side in this bitter rivalry has deciphered every single chemical unit of the human genetic material -- that is not possible with today's technology -- but each side has made tremendous contributions toward what future historians will surely rate as a pivotal scientific achievement, ushering in an exciting new stage of biological exploration.</p>
        <p>It is humbling to recall that when the idea of deciphering the human genome was first proposed in the 1980's, most of the major figures in biology deemed it a waste of time, talent and resources that would generate reams of useless data. It was the Energy Department that pushed for a federally financed project, forcing the National Institutes of Health to join the task to preserve leadership in its own domain. Since then, mainstream biologists have embraced the cause with enthusiasm, largely because automation and other technical advances made the task far easier and faster.</p>
        <p>Understanding the genome is important because it contains the chemical code letters that direct cells to make the proteins that carry out all the body's vital functions, usually by catalyzing chemical reactions or building cellular structures. Thus it will be enormously handy to have the exact letter-by-letter sequence of the entire genome as a framework from which to determine how many genes there are, where precisely on the chromosomes they are located, and how they function. That will open the way to a far deeper understanding of everything from normal cell function to human development to cancer and other disease states. With a gene-detector chip at hand, scientists will be able to tell which genes are turned on and which are not in both normal and diseased cells, providing a powerful new tool for analysis and treatment.</p>
        <p>Deciphering the human genome has been likened to discovery of the periodic table of elements, which accelerated chemical research, and to the first detailed description of the human anatomy, which facilitated subsequent advances in medical treatments. Some practical results may come in a matter of years, including new drugs already in clinical trials that were derived from the rapidly accumulating knowledge of the genes. But for lots of diseases, scientists must first identify the gene or genes involved and then find a way to intervene therapeutically. That will not be easy. Scientists have known about the genetic defect that causes sickle cell disease for decades but still have no way to cure it.</p>
        <p>The race to decipher the human genome  has been, some say, a race to the starting line, not an end in itself. The contestants will have compiled, in one scientist's analogy, a genetic dictionary filled with letters and words, most of which have not  yet been given any meanings. Identifying what proteins the genes produce and how those proteins generate their effects in the body will be far harder than simply deciphering the genome. Eminent biologists describe it as a quest that will occupy their discipline for at least the next 50 years, if not the next century.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
