<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plywood Air Pollution Case Is Settled for $93.2 Million</title>
    <meta content="Y21AIR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216493"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Willamette Industries</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E6D6163AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plywood Air Pollution Case Is Settled for $93.2 Million</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>EPA and Justice Department announce that Willamette Industries, plywood manufacturer with 13 factories in four states, has agreed to $93.2-million settlement over air pollution violations; company will spend $8 million on environmental projects and $74 million on new pollution-control equipment (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency and the Justice Department announced today that a plywood manufacturer with 13 factories in four states had agreed to a $93.2 million settlement over air pollution violations, the largest settlement based on pollution from factories.</p>
        <p>The accord means that the environmental agency has settled pollution cases in the last few years with companies that make up more than half the wood products industry. In a sector-by-sector campaign to enforce the terms of the Clean Air Act, the agency has also reached agreements with diesel engine manufacturers, but it is still battling with  refineries and with coal-burning power plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency and the Justice Department announced today that a plywood manufacturer with 13 factories in four states had agreed to a $93.2 million settlement over air pollution violations, the largest settlement based on pollution from factories.</p>
        <p>The accord means that the environmental agency has settled pollution cases in the last few years with companies that make up more than half the wood products industry. In a sector-by-sector campaign to enforce the terms of the Clean Air Act, the agency has also reached agreements with diesel engine manufacturers, but it is still battling with  refineries and with coal-burning power plants.</p>
        <p>The settlement with Willamette Industries Inc., a plywood and building materials manufacturer based in Portland, Ore., with plants in Arkansas, Louisiana and South Carolina as well, follows settlements with Louisiana-Pacific, Georgia-Pacific and Weyerhaeuser; the government is still pursuing Boise-Cascade.</p>
        <p>In addition to a civil penalty of $11.2 million, Willamette will spend $8 million on environmental projects, and $74 million on new pollution-control equipment, government officials said. Carol M. Browner, the E.P.A. administrator, said that the company had saved money for years by not installing equipment to reduce emissions but that with the settlement, ''the economic benefit has been captured in the penalty, and then some.''</p>
        <p>In a statement, Duane McDougall, the company's chief executive officer, said the company had reached the agreement ''to resolve certain historic air permit questions.'' Willamette will install emission control equipment that is ''well beyond what is required,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. says factories that emit pollutants into the air must have permits to make changes in the plants. Ms. Browner said, ''These guys didn't even say they needed a permit.'' Mr. McDougall said that Willamette had consulted with state authorities as it made changes to its factories over the years and had been told that no permits were required but that the environmental agency had ''revisited these decisions based on a revised interpretation of long-established standards and practices.''</p>
        <p>The company's defense is similar to the one still being raised by electric utilities companies that the agency last year accused of not seeking permits for changes they had made to their plants.</p>
        <p>Willamette makes plywood and composite panels. The adhesives used to bond sheets of plywood together, or form composites, give off pollutants, volatile organic compounds, that react with nitrogen compounds in sunlight to form smog.</p>
        <p>Under the settlement, the company will install equipment to reduce emissions of the compounds, as well as cut emissions of small particles and carbon monoxide. The company will spend money to improve municipal sewer systems, acquire parkland and build ethanol fueling stations to encourage companies that own fleets of vehicles to use clean fuel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
