<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Take the Marines Off Okinawa</title>
    <meta content="21HEIL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Okinawa and Other Ryukyu Islands</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heilbrunn, Jacob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Okinawa and the Ryukyu Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2D9163AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Take the Marines Off Okinawa</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jacob Heilbrunn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heilbrunn, Jacob</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jacob Heilbrunn Op-Ed article calls for closing down US military bases on Okinawa (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton's arrival in Okinawa today for the Group of 8 meeting of big industrial nations calls attention to something beyond the international economic issues that the leaders there will discuss: the debate about whether the time has come to end the American military presence on Okinawa.</p>
        <p>The Okinawans who have used the visit of the world leaders as a stage for demonstrating in favor of American withdrawal are protesting acts like a hit-and-run incident involving an Air Force staff sergeant and the molestation of a 14-year-old Okinawan girl in which a marine was accused. The Japanese government, however, shows no interest in a removal of the Americans, because Japan's defenses are bolstered by the American base.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton's arrival in Okinawa today for the Group of 8 meeting of big industrial nations calls attention to something beyond the international economic issues that the leaders there will discuss: the debate about whether the time has come to end the American military presence on Okinawa.</p>
        <p>The Okinawans who have used the visit of the world leaders as a stage for demonstrating in favor of American withdrawal are protesting acts like a hit-and-run incident involving an Air Force staff sergeant and the molestation of a 14-year-old Okinawan girl in which a marine was accused. The Japanese government, however, shows no interest in a removal of the Americans, because Japan's defenses are bolstered by the American base.</p>
        <p>In the United States, however, the issue is most often framed as a debate between isolationists who want us to get out of Asia and champions of maintaining our presence in Okinawa as a sign of American resolve in that part of the world. Both have it wrong. The United States can afford to pull its troops out of Okinawa with no loss of our commitment to Asian security. In fact, America's position would be enhanced.</p>
        <p>A decade after the fall of the Soviet Union, the challenges to America in Asia are a Chinese military buildup, the China-Taiwan conflict and North Korea. Yet in Okinawa, 20,000 marines remain as a relic of the cold war.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the status quo argue that the marines on Okinawa could help move supplies in the event of a war in Korea or Taiwan and that they provide ready reinforcements for possible rapid deployment to other regions, like the Persian Gulf. The Clinton administration codified this consensus in the 1995 Nye report, when it declared that America would keep a minimum of 100,000 troops in Asia until at least 2015, explicitly including the 20,000 on Okinawa in that total.</p>
        <p>The truth is that the United States can not only retain but improve upon these goals by removing its forces from Okinawa. Over the past decade the Pentagon has been moving toward a new strategy based on getting American troops to global hot spots by sea and air, a strategy known as maritime pre-positioning force. International seas offer complete and expeditious freedom of movement, and the Marines already have the equivalent of a division stationed on ships around the globe. The Navy is also working to improve the replenishment of ships already at sea with missiles, cannon rounds, bullets and fuel. The marines  in Okinawa might be redeployed to bolster this strategy.</p>
        <p>There are disadvantages, after all, in keeping them where they are. Okinawa is what is known as an unaccompanied tour, which means the marines cannot bring their wives. The small Okinawa base also has no room for large-scale battle training.</p>
        <p>More fundamentally, as the military expert Paul Bracken points out in his recent book, ''Fire in the East,''  maintaining a string of bases in Asia has rendered the American military dangerously vulnerable to chemical and ballistic missile attacks. The United States, he says, needs to restructure the military to allow it to operate at greater distances from home and become ''less reliant on vulnerable forward bases.''</p>
        <p>One step would be to shift the basing of fleets so that destroyers can remain permanently stationed in the Pacific rather than trundling to and from the West Coast. Facilities in Japan are already being built up, Guam could be expanded, and most intriguingly, Vietnam might be willing to consider leasing Cam Ranh Bay back to the United States, especially as it fears growing Chinese military strength.</p>
        <p>In an era of tight military budgets and limited manpower, such measures would improve the speed with which American firepower can reach Asia, and they would have none of Okinawa's drawbacks.</p>
        <p>Jacob Heilbrunn writes often about American foreign policy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jacob Heilbrunn writes often about American foreign policy.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
