<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cabaret Guide</title>
    <meta content="21CABA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1DE163AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cabaret Guide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Holden</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL, Bemelmans Bar, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. This agelessly chic red-haired pianist and singer seems to know every important popular song ever written and to be able to perform from memory in any key. Her elegant, lyrical pianism is a compendium of 20th-century jazz styles, from Count Basie to Erroll Garner to Bill Evans and beyond. And her clipped, understated vocals, which verge on speech-song, approach lyrics from a wry but warmhearted point of view. Tonight and tomorrow night, beginning at 9:30. From 5:30 to 8, Michael Devine. No cover for early show; cover for late show: $15. No minimum; $5 cover at the bar. Peter Mintun begins Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>BARBARA CARROLL, Bemelmans Bar, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. This agelessly chic red-haired pianist and singer seems to know every important popular song ever written and to be able to perform from memory in any key. Her elegant, lyrical pianism is a compendium of 20th-century jazz styles, from Count Basie to Erroll Garner to Bill Evans and beyond. And her clipped, understated vocals, which verge on speech-song, approach lyrics from a wry but warmhearted point of view. Tonight and tomorrow night, beginning at 9:30. From 5:30 to 8, Michael Devine. No cover for early show; cover for late show: $15. No minimum; $5 cover at the bar. Peter Mintun begins Tuesday.</p>
        <p>* KT SULLIVAN, Firebird Cafe, 363 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 586-0244. This singer's latest whimsically quirky exploration of a particular composer's work casts an astute sideways gaze at Richard Rodgers, concentrating on his work with Lorenz Hart rather than Oscar Hammerstein. High points include a bizarre earlier version of the song we all know as ''Blue Moon'' and ''10 Cents a Dance'' done as an intimate interior monologue full of subtle mood swings. Larry Woodard supplies brisk, incisive piano accompaniment and occasional vocal support. Tonight at 9 and 11. Cover: $30; $15 minimum. Also at the Firebird, tomorrow at 9 and 11 p.m., Spider Saloff, singer. Cover: $20; $15 minimum. Sunday at 7 p.m., David Friedman, part of the singer-songwriters series; at 9, James Beaman, singer and impersonator. Cover: $30; $15 minimum.</p>
        <p>* ''OUR SINATRA,'' Blue Angel Theater, 323 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. The rising young cabaret star Eric Comstock is the mastermind behind this utterly winning tribute to Ol' Blue Eyes, which focuses on what Mr. Comstock calls the hidden gems and orphan songs that Sinatra made popular. Joined by Christopher Gines, a creamy baritone who echoes Dick Haymes and Steve Lawrence in their prime, and Hilary Kole, a perky swinger, Mr. Comstock conducts a witty and knowledgeable survey of the Sinatra canon. Mr. Comstock concentrates on the mature Sinatra and Mr. Gines on the dreamy 1940's balladeer, with Ms. Kole bridging the gap. The memorable show proves that there are still young singers good enough to keep the tradition alive. Billy Stritch fills in for Mr. Comstock through Wednesday, except on Monday. Tonight, Monday through Wednesday nights at 8; tomorrow at 2:30 and 8 p.m.; Sunday at 7:30. Tickets: $50 and $55 (premium ringside seating, $75 and $80).</p>
        <p>* LILLIAS WHITE, Arci's Place, 450 Park Avenue South, at 30th Street, (212) 532-4370. If there's such a thing as a pop diva without airs, Lillias White, who last appeared on Broadway in ''The Life'' (and Off Broadway in ''Dinah Was''), is it. This singer, who grew up in Crown Heights, Brooklyn, melds classic jazz, funk, pop-soul and even calypso influences into a style that at moments suggest a theater-wise hybrid of Chaka Khan and Dinah Washington. Her program runs from a calypso singalong and showstoppers from ''Dream Girls'' (in which she also appeared) to Cher's hit ''Believe.'' Everything she does is infused with an unflagging emotional honesty that is upbeat without ever becoming saccharin. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30 and 11. Also at Arci's, Monday nights at 8 in July, Jim Caruso, singer, with Billy Stritch, pianist. Cover: $25; $15 minimum.</p>
        <p>CARNEGIE CLUB, 156 West 56th Street, (212) 957-9676. Cary Hoffman, with the 11-piece Carnegie Club Orchestra, plays music made famous by Frank Sinatra in the 1950's, featuring the original arrangements by Nelson Riddle. Fridays and Saturdays at 9:30 and 11 p.m. Cover: $20; two-drink ($15) minimum.</p>
        <p>DANNY'S SKYLIGHT ROOM, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133. Tonight at 7, Francine Whitney, singer; from 9 to 1 in the piano bar, Jerry Scott; at 9:15, Sandy Salko-Parra, singer, in ''So Many Lifetimes.'' Tomorrow night at 7, ''Savoring the Brew: A Taste of Shakespeare's Women,'' by Mary Emily Deal, Michelle Jordan and Christina Purcell; from 9 to 1, in the piano bar, Mr. Scott; at 9:15, Mark LeBlanc and Richard Van Slyke in ''Duets.'' Sunday night at 8:30, ''Savoring the Brew: A Taste of Shakespeare's Women.'' Cover: free to $12; $10 minimum.</p>
        <p>DON'T TELL MAMA, 343 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 757-0788. Tonight at 6:30,''It's the Cherries: Ray Henderson Songbook,'' ensemble musical revue; at 8:30, ''Poole Party's New Talent Night,'' stand-up comedy, with Rock Albers; at 8:30, ''The Next Big Broadway Musical,'' musical improvisational comedy; at 11, Ron Seykell, singer, with Lennie Babbish, pianist. Tomorrow night at 6:30, Beth Valenti, singer, with Rick Jensen, pianist; at 8, Tommy Femia impersonates Judy Garland; at 8:30, ''Poole Party!,'' comedy variety show; at 11, Steven Brinberg impersonates Barbra Streisand. Sunday at 5, ''It's the Cherries: Ray Henderson Songbook,'' ensemble musical revue; at 5, Yolanda Tolentino, singer, with band. Cover: Free to $18. Two-drink minimum. No credit cards.</p>
        <p>FEINSTEIN'S, at the Regency, 540 Park Avenue, at 61st Street, (212) 339-4095. Marc Salem, mentalist. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30 and 11; Sunday at 1:30; Wednesday and Thursday nights at 8:30. Cover: $40 for weekends; no cover on weekdays; dinner required for early show on weekends, with seating beginning at 6; a la carte supper menu with $20 minimum for late show; $35 for early show; Sunday brunch is $30 and cover is $30. Through Sept. 2.</p>
        <p>HUDSON RIVER PARK'S MOONDANCE SERIES, Pier 25, North Moore Street, near West Street, Lower Manhattan, (212) 533-7275. Sunday night, dancing and music begins at 6:30, swing and lindy hop with Beale Street Swing Mavens. Free.</p>
        <p>JOE'S PUB, Public Theater, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778 or (212) 239-6200. Tonight, Wednesday, and Thursday and next Friday at 8:30 p.m., Sandra Bernhard, singer and comedian, in ''Songs I Sang on the Kibbutz,'' with a five-piece band. Tomorrow night at 9, Diamanda Galas, vocalist. Tickets: $30. Sunday night at 8:30 and 9:30, tap and Latin music with Ayodele Casel. Tickets: $20. Monday night at 8:30, Absolute Ensemble, electro-acoustic band. Tickets: $15.</p>
        <p>JUDY'S CHELSEA, 169 Eighth Avenue, at 18th Street, (212) 929-5410. Tonight at 8:30, Julie Reyburn, singer, in ''Fate Is Kind,'' with Mark Janas, pianist; at 11 p.m. (and Monday at 8:30), Miles Phillips, singer, in ''Might as Well Be . . .,'' with Mark Janas, pianist, and Julie Reyburn, guitarist. Sunday at 2 p.m., Arthur Williams Studio presents ''Cabaret Concert''; at 5:30 p.m., the musical group Eastern Standard Time in ''The Time Is Now . . . the Songs are Timeless.'' Monday at 10 p.m., ''Leer Mondays,'' with the Lounge-O-Leers, Ricky Ritzel and Aaron Morishita. Cover: $10 to $20; $10 minimum.</p>
        <p>OAK ROOM, Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, (212) 840-6800. Loston Harris Trio. Tonight and tomorrow at 9 and 11:30; Tuesday through Thursday nights at 9. Cover: $40, with dinner required for early shows Fridays and Saturdays; $15 food or drink minimum for other shows; suggested dinner arrival for early show is 7. Through July 29.</p>
        <p>SUPPER CLUB, 240 West 47th Street, (212) 921-1940. Tonight and tomorrow night from 8 to midnight, the Supper Club's 17-piece big band. Also, the 25-minute swing revue ''This Joint Is Jumpin' '' at 9:30 and 10:30 p.m., with Larry Marshall. Swing dance lessons every Friday and Saturday night from 11:15 to midnight in the Blue Room. Tonight, Jumpin' Gigolos; tomorrow night, Nick Palumbo and the Flipped Fedoras, from 12:30 to 2:30 a.m. Cover: $25 before 11, $15 after.</p>
        <p>UPSTAIRS AT ROSE'S TURN, 55 Grove Street, West Village, (212) 366-5438. Tonight at 9, ''Something Funny's Going On,'' stand-up; at 11, ''Candy Comedy Hour.'' Tomorrow night at 11, ''Candy Comedy Hour.'' Sunday night at 10, Adria Malcolm, singer. Cover: $5 to $7; two-drink minimum. No credit cards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
