<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Among Israelis, Congratulations and Condemnation</title>
    <meta content="Y21ISRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jerusalem</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EED8163AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Among Israelis, Congratulations and Condemnation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenberg, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israelis, following Camp David summit meeting from afar, react to reports of concessions on status of Jersusalem (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For a moment early this morning, when she heard the announcement that the Camp David talks had ended with no agreement, Gaby Bar-Zakai breathed easier.</p>
        <p>''I felt relieved,'' recalled Mrs. Bar-Zakai, who lives in Maaleh Adumim, an Israeli suburb of Jerusalem in the West Bank. ''I was very concerned that if the talks didn't break up, the Israeli concessions would be total.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For a moment early this morning, when she heard the announcement that the Camp David talks had ended with no agreement, Gaby Bar-Zakai breathed easier.</p>
        <p>''I felt relieved,'' recalled Mrs. Bar-Zakai, who lives in Maaleh Adumim, an Israeli suburb of Jerusalem in the West Bank. ''I was very concerned that if the talks didn't break up, the Israeli concessions would be total.''</p>
        <p>Then came the news that the talks would continue after all, and Mrs. Bar-Zakai seesawed back to reality. By tonight she was more sober.</p>
        <p>''It was clear to me that things would swing back and forth,'' she said. ''I'm skeptical, because I don't think the Palestinians are ripe for a comprehensive agreement. But I think there will be a partial accord, because both sides have no other choice.''</p>
        <p>Everything seemed the same today in Jerusalem, but it was not. For the first time, an Israeli prime minister had negotiated with the Palestinians on the future of the city, which Israel has always claimed as its indivisible capital -- and it was going over quietly.</p>
        <p>''People are apathetic; they're too busy with their daily lives,'' said Avi Mizrahi. He allowed that he was no fan of Prime Minister Ehud Barak, who was ''just doing everything to earn a place in the history books, without a coalition or proper support.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Barak's efforts seem to have the quiet support of many liberal Israelis.</p>
        <p>Reflecting their views, the newspaper Haaretz said, ''Barak should be congratulated for his readiness to smash the taboo on negotiations over Jerusalem.''</p>
        <p>Meron Benvenisti, an expert on the Palestinian-Israeli conflict, wrote in Haaretz that ''the very fact that the taboo has been broken and Israel is holding a discussion on Jerusalem that means division of the city'' is ''an act from which there can be no return.''</p>
        <p>Talk shows were dominated by discussions of solutions for Jerusalem, and some callers from the city said they supported the idea of putting Arab neighborhoods under Palestinian control.</p>
        <p>Long-repeated assertions by Israeli politicians that Jerusalem would remain Israel's united capital seemed to be giving way to a more pragmatic debate about the city's future.</p>
        <p>Sensing the shift, Ariel Sharon, the leader of the opposition Likud Party, accused Mr. Barak today of giving up too much, creating ''impossible starting lines for any future negotiation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak had ''already given Arafat a deposit, and we will have to work hard to erase the withdrawal lines drawn by Barak on the map at Camp David,'' Mr. Sharon said.</p>
        <p>Natan Sharansky, who left Mr. Barak's cabinet in protest over the summit meeting, sent a letter to the prime minister, urging him to submit any agreement on Jerusalem for approval by Jewish leaders, as well as by Parliament. Sitting in a tent near Mr. Barak's office, Mr. Sharansky is advocating a broad government including opposition parties, in order to reach a wide consensus on peace moves.</p>
        <p>Founders of the Jewish settlement movement have set up their own tent nearby and are holding a hunger strike for the duration of the summit meeting. Today, scores of settlers swayed there in prayer on a religious fast day that carried added significance for them.</p>
        <p>The fast commemorates the breaching of the walls of Jerusalem before the destruction of the first Jewish temple in 587 B.C. and the second temple in A.D. 70. Mr. Barak's plans for the city, the settlers assert, are tantamount to another destruction.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
