<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dying Hipster Full of Song, Poetry and Sweet Nonsense</title>
    <meta content="21SMOK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Smoke (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, A O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Benjamin (Robert Dickerson) (d1999)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sillen, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Jem</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Benjamin Smoke (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By A. O. Scott</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7DF163AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dying Hipster Full of Song, Poetry and Sweet Nonsense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By A. O. SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, A O</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>A O Scott reviews Benjamin Smoke, documentary film by Jem Cohen and Peter Sillen about life of Atlanta musician, hustler and occasional drag queen Benjamin (aka Robert Dickerson); photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the beginning of ''Benjamin Smoke,'' some lines from a Patti Smith poem appear on screen, and later Ms. Smith herself appears, to recite the poem and pay tribute to the life and music of the film's subject, an Atlanta musician, hustler, and occasional drag queen known to his fans and collaborators as Benjamin. Ms. Smith's presence is especially fitting, and not only because of her personal connection with Benjamin, who opened for her shortly before he died in 1999 from liver failure linked to hepatitis C and AIDS. From Jim Morrison to Kurt Cobain, she has always been a connoisseur of rock 'n' roll martyrdom, and Benjamin, born Robert Dickerson in rural Georgia in 1960, seems to have materialized from one of her songs -- a wispy, sensitive, self-destructive soul full of sweet beatnik romanticism, pop poetry and entertaining nonsense.</p>
        <p>Jem Cohen and Peter Sillen's new documentary, which opens today at the Screening Room, is a loving piece of hipster iconography, a poignant and respectful memorial to a troubled and talented man. More impressionistic than biographical, ''Benjamin Smoke'' is a collage of interviews, performance and rehearsal clips, and evocative glimpses of Cabbagetown, the shabby, reluctantly gentrifying Atlanta neighborhood where Mr. Dickerson lived much of his adult life -- an area, as he describes it, where children build go-carts, go to jail early and watch their parents do lots of inhalants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the beginning of ''Benjamin Smoke,'' some lines from a Patti Smith poem appear on screen, and later Ms. Smith herself appears, to recite the poem and pay tribute to the life and music of the film's subject, an Atlanta musician, hustler, and occasional drag queen known to his fans and collaborators as Benjamin. Ms. Smith's presence is especially fitting, and not only because of her personal connection with Benjamin, who opened for her shortly before he died in 1999 from liver failure linked to hepatitis C and AIDS. From Jim Morrison to Kurt Cobain, she has always been a connoisseur of rock 'n' roll martyrdom, and Benjamin, born Robert Dickerson in rural Georgia in 1960, seems to have materialized from one of her songs -- a wispy, sensitive, self-destructive soul full of sweet beatnik romanticism, pop poetry and entertaining nonsense.</p>
        <p>Jem Cohen and Peter Sillen's new documentary, which opens today at the Screening Room, is a loving piece of hipster iconography, a poignant and respectful memorial to a troubled and talented man. More impressionistic than biographical, ''Benjamin Smoke'' is a collage of interviews, performance and rehearsal clips, and evocative glimpses of Cabbagetown, the shabby, reluctantly gentrifying Atlanta neighborhood where Mr. Dickerson lived much of his adult life -- an area, as he describes it, where children build go-carts, go to jail early and watch their parents do lots of inhalants.</p>
        <p>In part because of the straitened circumstances in which it was made, the film has a richer, more various visual texture than most documentaries, combining still photographs, black-and-white video and Super-8 film, sometimes with wild sound or none at all. The ragged, absent-minded lyricism that results suits the subject. Mr. Dickerson, bone thin, his voice ravaged by ill health and cigarettes, has a hustler's easy charm. He also has a tendency to wander toward the far edge of coherence. His rambling owes something to his poet's sense of discursive possibility; it may also be a result of a life of heavy drug use. In any case, we get a sense of his taste for inspired goofing (''Tell me what a really great orgasm is like . . . It's like chicken, only a little gamier''), his fantasy life (''I used to pretend I was Claudine Longet, and I'd just murdered my ski-instructor boyfriend'') and his literary vision (a ballad about Luke Perry's feet).</p>
        <p>But we don't learn much about the details of his death and life. There is more information about Benjamin's music, his travels and his childhood in the movie's affiliated Web site (www.benjaminremembered.com)  than in the film itself. The best parts of ''Benjamin Smoke'' are the musical passages, which provide necessary evidence that Mr. Dickerson was not just a colorful, doomed eccentric and which make ''Benjamin Smoke'' authentically respectful rather than lurid or condescending.</p>
        <p>His music -- chanted more than sung, over the sounds of the band Smoke, which features a droning banjo, a squalling electric guitar and a keening cello -- owes a lot to Ms. Smith and to the beatnik tradition she upholds. You may hear echoes of Tom Waits, the Velvet Underground, Allen Ginsberg and William S. Burroughs, and of the recently reissued Harry Smith Folkways compilation. Mr. Cohen and Mr. Sillen should be commended for preserving this small, vital piece of American weirdness.</p>
        <p>BENJAMIN SMOKE</p>
        <p>Directed by Jem Cohen and Peter Sillen; directors of photography, Mr. Cohen and Mr. Sillen; edited by Nancy Roach; music by Smoke; released by Cowboy Booking International. At the Screening Room, 54 Varick Street, at Laight Street, TriBeCa. Running time: 80 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Robert Dickerson/Benjamin, Patti Smith and members of Smoke: Tim Campion, Brian Halloran, Coleman Lewis and Bill Taft.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
