<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="21MBRF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6DB173AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Anthony Ramirez</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: ACQUITTAL IN DIVORCE CASE  A Manhattan lawyer was acquitted yesterday of charges that he bribed a court clerk to alter paperwork relating to a divorce and to speed the case through the judicial system. The lawyer, Dean Emmanuelli, had been indicted on 38 counts of bribery and charged with paying a clerk $40 for each of 37 divorce applications handled last year. Another lawyer accused of offering bribes pleaded guilty last year, as did the supervising clerk for matrimonial cases in Manhattan State Supreme Court who was accused of accepting bribes.</p>
        <p>Katherine E. Finkelstein (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: ACQUITTAL IN DIVORCE CASE  A Manhattan lawyer was acquitted yesterday of charges that he bribed a court clerk to alter paperwork relating to a divorce and to speed the case through the judicial system. The lawyer, Dean Emmanuelli, had been indicted on 38 counts of bribery and charged with paying a clerk $40 for each of 37 divorce applications handled last year. Another lawyer accused of offering bribes pleaded guilty last year, as did the supervising clerk for matrimonial cases in Manhattan State Supreme Court who was accused of accepting bribes.</p>
        <p>Katherine E. Finkelstein (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: ARCHBISHOP HAS SURGERY  Archbishop Edward M. Egan, head of New York's Roman Catholic Archdiocese, underwent surgery yesterday to mend torn cartilage in his left knee. The 90-minute operation, performed at Saint Vincent's Medical Center in Bridgeport, Conn., was a success, said Joseph Zwilling, spokesman for the archdiocese. The archbishop, 68, had had knee trouble since last fall, Mr. Zwilling said.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>ALBANY: NEW STATE TOURISM PROMOTION ENACTED  To improve promotion of tourist attractions in New York State, a new law permits county tourist agencies to use state money in joint advertising programs with neighboring states and Canadian provinces. Previously, county tourist promotion agencies could seek matching funds from the state's Department of Economic Development only for promotions in New York State. The new law, Gov. George E. Pataki said on Wednesday, will enable counties that share attractions with neighboring states and Canada, like Niagara Falls, to ''take advantage of joint opportunities to promote these sites.''</p>
        <p>Joseph P. Fried (NYT)</p>
        <p>MANHATTAN: COMPLAINTS ABOUT RATS  The city's week-old rat-complaint hot line has received more than 470 calls, mostly from Harlem, the Upper East Side and the Lower East Side of Manhattan, C. Virginia Fields, the Manhattan borough president, said yesterday. The complaints go to the city's Department of Health. Ms. Fields urged Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani to exclude the Department of Health's Pest Control Division from a new hiring freeze.</p>
        <p>Eun Lee Koh (NYT)</p>
        <p>UTICA: MAYORAL ELECTION ORDERED  A special election must be held this fall to determine who will succeed Mayor Edward Hanna, a State Supreme Court justice ruled in a decision released Wednesday. Mr. Hanna quit on July 3, citing health reasons and amid allegations of sexual harassment. He named Timothy Julian, the Common Council president, to serve the remaining 3 1/2 years of his term. Mr. Julian said the city would appeal the judge's decision.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NIAGARA FALLS: LOOKOUT TOWER REVAMPED  The state will lop 60 feet from the top of the Prospect Point observation tower overlooking Niagara Falls because Gov. George E. Pataki called the tower ''hideous.'' The State Parks commissioner, Bernadette Castro, announced a $23 million plan on Wednesday to shorten the 280-foot structure and replace the two original elevators with four that are faster.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT</p>
        <p>EAST HAVEN: SHOOTINGS AT CONCERT  An elderly man shot his estranged wife then turned the gun on himself last night in front of a crowd that had gathered for a concert on the town green, the police said. The police said the woman was seated in a lawn chair when the man walked up behind her and shot her in the head, then walked a short distance away and shot himself in the head. The gunman, who appeared to be in his 70's, died at the scene, and his victim was in critical condition at a local hospital, said Leonard Gallo, the police chief. The names of the couple were not released.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW LONDON: TROOPER SHOOTING  Lawyers for a man accused of the attempted murder of a state trooper asked a judge to dismiss a charge that carries the possibility of the death penalty. The lawyers for the man, Van Schrvyer, 18, argued that the charge of criminal attempt to commit capital felony should not apply because the trooper he shot at did not die. Under Connecticut law, capital felony charges can be filed in the murder of a police officer, murder during the commission of another felony or the killing of two or more people at the same time.</p>
        <p>Theresa Crapanzano (NYT)</p>
        <p>HARTFORD: END TO PROBATION SOUGHT  Dawn March, a woman who spent time in a mental hospital instead of prison for the drowning death of her baby, has asked to be released from probation. In what became a landmark case, Ms. March, who threw her daughter into the Housatonic River in 1989, was acquitted when a judge recognized postpartum psychosis as a defense for her actions. The state's Psychiatric Security Review Board is to meet in September to report to a judge who will decide whether to grant Ms. March's petition.</p>
        <p>Theresa Crapanzano (NYT)</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>NEWARK: JETS PASS TOO CLOSE  A Continental Airlines jet taking off from Newark International Airport Wednesday morning flew within 500 feet of an American Trans- Air jet on the ground, prompting an investigation by the Federal Aviation Administration. An air traffic controller was suspended for failing to order the TransAir jet to stop after it landed.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: PRINCETON SMOKING BAN  A local judge yesterday temporarily blocked a ban on smoking in Princeton Borough and Township. The ban, enacted but not yet in effect, prohibits smoking in all public accommodations, including bars and restaurants. Three borough restaurants and bars, along with the National Smokers Alliance, sued to block the ban.</p>
        <p>Kushanava Choudhury (NYT)</p>
        <p>TRENTON: WETLANDS CONTROVERSY  The State Department of Environmental Protection said yesterday that it would allow a cranberry farmer to continue farming 22 acres he had illegally flooded, provided he followed the permit process. The farmer, J. Garfield DeMarco, a former Burlington County Republican chairman, was charged in September with expanding his fields into wetlands without a permit.</p>
        <p>Steve Strunsky (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
