<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Old Course Lets Down Its Guard For Els</title>
    <meta content="21GOLF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Els, Ernie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woods, Tiger</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">British Open (Golf)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2DF173AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1208" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Old Course Lets Down Its Guard For Els</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>ST. ANDREWS, Scotland, July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ernie Els leads by one stroke over Tiger Woods after opening round of British Open; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ernie Els opened his eyes this morning, turned on the television in his hotel room and got an immediate wake-up call. He saw players with early tee times pummeling the Old Course at St. Andrews with birdies. He saw Tiger Woods make a back-nine surge and charge his way onto the leader board.</p>
        <p>By the time Els reached the driving range to prepare for his afternoon round, the pressure was inescapable. Either he would join the leaders with a strong opening round at the British Open, or he would face an early deficit that might be too large to overcome.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ernie Els opened his eyes this morning, turned on the television in his hotel room and got an immediate wake-up call. He saw players with early tee times pummeling the Old Course at St. Andrews with birdies. He saw Tiger Woods make a back-nine surge and charge his way onto the leader board.</p>
        <p>By the time Els reached the driving range to prepare for his afternoon round, the pressure was inescapable. Either he would join the leaders with a strong opening round at the British Open, or he would face an early deficit that might be too large to overcome.</p>
        <p>Els did more than join the leaders. He passed them. Shooting an opening-round six-under-par 66, including a rare birdie on the No. 17 Road Hole, one of the world's toughest par 4's, Els held a one-stroke lead over Woods and Steve Flesch after today's first round.</p>
        <p>Both Woods and Flesch shot 67's, while seven players were tied at 68, two strokes off the lead: Tom Lehman, the 1996 British Open champion; Scott Dunlap and Ian Garbutt of England; Sergio Garcia of Spain; Padraig Harrington of Ireland; Shigeki Maruyama of Japan; and Dennis Paulson.</p>
        <p>Several players who expected to contend virtually eliminated themselves with poor rounds. Hal Sutton shot 75, Nick Price and John Daly both shot 76, and the defending champion Paul Lawrie shot 78.</p>
        <p>Fifty of the 151 players in the field shot under par, as afternoon temperatures were in the 70's, and there was not enough wind to seriously affect ball flight or club selection. At times, it felt more like San Diego than St. Andrews. If conditions remain that way, it will be difficult for Woods or anyone else to run away, because many players will continue to shoot under par.</p>
        <p>Remember last year's British Open at Carnoustie, Scotland, when the winning score was six over par? This will be a far different championship if the weather remains calm.</p>
        <p>''The course is firm and fast, but if you are playing well, the course is there for the taking,'' Lehman said.</p>
        <p>Hitting precise and powerful drives that gave him great angles into the greens, Els took the lead with the cool and calculating style that has made him a two-time United States Open champion (1994 and 1997).</p>
        <p>He entered the tournament with momentum, winning last week's Standard Life Loch Lomond Invitational in Scotland, and he has played strong golf the entire year.</p>
        <p>Yet, Els has been overshadowed and outplayed by Woods, just like everyone else in golf. When Woods won the United States Open by a record-setting 15 strokes last month, it was Els who tied for second with Miguel Angel Jimenez. When Vijay Singh won the Masters in April, Els finished second. And when Woods opened the year with a thrilling victory at the Mercedes Championships, he had to beat Els in a riveting battle that lasted until the second hole of sudden death.</p>
        <p>If Els were to finish second this weekend, he would become the first player to finish second in three consecutive majors. But finishing second is not what Els is about. With people looking for the latest rival for Woods, Els may be playing well enough to assume that role shortly, perhaps this weekend.</p>
        <p>''There's quite a few players that can step up and be the rival, whatever you want to call it,'' Els said. ''If I play well, I'm probably going to play with Tiger sometime this week. He plays at that level just about every week.</p>
        <p>''I really don't want to think about it too much. Tiger is a good friend of mine and he's one heck of a player. Whoever wins this week is probably the next rival of Tiger Woods, if it's not him.''</p>
        <p>If Woods wins, at age 24, he will become the youngest player to win the career Grand Slam. For Woods, it was important to avoid an early deficit that would force him to play catch-up, and today's strong start put him in excellent position. After dominating last month's United States Open at Pebble Beach, Woods entered this tournament as the overwhelming favorite. But Woods will gladly settle for any victory, whether it's by 15 strokes or one stroke. And today, he took the first step toward that mission.</p>
        <p>''After what happened at the U.S. Open, you have to put it behind you,'' said Woods, after a bogey-free round that included a furious flurry -- five birdies in a seven-hole stretch beginning with a 12-foot birdie putt on No. 9, and ending with a 10-foot birdie on No. 15.</p>
        <p>Woods said he had never played St. Andrews in more favorable conditions. ''I don't think I've ever played any links golf like this,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Els overtook Woods with a strong start, making four birdies and just one bogey on the front nine. Then, playing into the wind on the back nine, Els added birdies on Nos. 10, 12 and 14, followed by his final birdie on No. 17, which was world class. How difficult is the par 4, 455-yard No. 17 at St. Andrews? There were 4 birdies there today, 70 bogeys, 21 double-bogeys and 7 scores worse than double-bogey.</p>
        <p>But Els had one of the four birdies. The tee shot at No. 17 is unnerving, forcing players to hit over a portion of the Old Course Hotel into a fairway they cannot see. Players chose their line on the tee shot by using a sign that sits against the wall of the hotel.</p>
        <p>''You look at the word ''course', and you go over the letter U,'' Els said. ''That's the exact line.''</p>
        <p>That works if you are as good as Els. After hitting a perfect tee shot at No. 17, Els hit a gorgeous 6-iron shot from 183 yards that landed six feet from the pin. The gallery in the stands adjacent to the 17th green roared, then Els made the putt to take the lead. And Els almost birdied No. 18 as well, missing a 12-foot attempt before a tap-in par ended his day.</p>
        <p>Early in his career, Els was not a big fan of St. Andrews. He has begun to change his mind.</p>
        <p>''There's a couple of blind shots, but if you start getting your lines right off the tees, the golf course becomes a little more fun,'' he said.  ''As to where it ranks as my favorite courses? Let's see after this week.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
