<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y21CAM$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E3DC173AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>BRADLEY TO CAMPAIGN IN HOMETOWN  Former Senator Bill Bradley of New Jersey will campaign in his hometown of Crystal City, Mo., on Saturday with Gov. Mel Carnahan, a Democrat who is trying to unseat Senator John Ashcroft, a one-term Republican, in one of the year's hardest-fought Congressional races. The event will be part of a four-day, 22-stop train tour across Missouri by Mr. Carnahan that is intended to recreate the 1948 whistle-stop tours around America by another Missourian, President Harry S. Truman. Mr. Bradley will be campaigning for just the second time since he dropped out of the Democratic presidential primaries in March; last week, he endorsed Vice President Al Gore in Wisconsin. Although Mr. Bradley lost the Missouri primary to Mr. Gore, he remains wildly popular in Crystal City, the small town on the Mississippi River where he kicked off his presidential campaign last year.</p>
        <p>James Dao (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>BRADLEY TO CAMPAIGN IN HOMETOWN  Former Senator Bill Bradley of New Jersey will campaign in his hometown of Crystal City, Mo., on Saturday with Gov. Mel Carnahan, a Democrat who is trying to unseat Senator John Ashcroft, a one-term Republican, in one of the year's hardest-fought Congressional races. The event will be part of a four-day, 22-stop train tour across Missouri by Mr. Carnahan that is intended to recreate the 1948 whistle-stop tours around America by another Missourian, President Harry S. Truman. Mr. Bradley will be campaigning for just the second time since he dropped out of the Democratic presidential primaries in March; last week, he endorsed Vice President Al Gore in Wisconsin. Although Mr. Bradley lost the Missouri primary to Mr. Gore, he remains wildly popular in Crystal City, the small town on the Mississippi River where he kicked off his presidential campaign last year.</p>
        <p>James Dao (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE POLLS</p>
        <p>BUSH LEAD SLIPS IN OHIO  Gov. George W. Bush has lost some ground to Vice President Al Gore in Ohio, considered a swing state in the fall election, a new poll shows. The poll, released yesterday by the University of Cincinnati's Institute for Policy Research, has Mr. Bush leading Mr. Gore by four points in a two-candidate field, 49 percent to 45 percent, and by six points, 47 percent to 41 percent, in a four-candidate field that includes Patrick J. Buchanan of the Reform Party and Ralph Nader of the Green Party. In April, a poll by the institute gave Mr. Bush a nine-point lead over Mr. Gore in a two-candidate race and an eight-point lead when Mr. Buchanan and Mr. Nader were included. In both polls the third-party candidates had 4 percent or less. The new poll, which surveyed 537 likely voters from July 5 to 13 and has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus four percentage points, also found that roughly a third of Bush and Gore supporters might switch their vote to another candidate before Nov. 7.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>CLINTON WOULD FIND TOUGH FIGHT  He has never given any real indication that he might try it, but President Clinton would face a hard fight if he ran for the Senate in his native Arkansas after leaving the White House, a new poll shows. The Mason-Dixon poll, commissioned by The Arkansas Democrat-Gazette, shows Mr. Clinton trailing Senator Tim Hutchinson, a Republican whose first term ends in 2002, by eight points, 49 percent to 41 percent, with 10 percent undecided. There has been periodic speculation that Mr. Clinton might seek a Senate seat somewhere, as his wife, Hillary, is doing in New York. But he has always laughed off the prospect, without flatly ruling it out. The poll, conducted July 13-15 and covering 622 registered voters, has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus four percentage points.</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>THE CONVENTIONS</p>
        <p>A GRAHAM TO DELIVER BENEDICTION  Franklin Graham, the eldest son of the Rev. Billy Graham and an evangelist in his own right, will deliver the benediction that closes the first day of the Republican National Convention in Philadelphia on July 31. Mr. Graham, who lives in North Carolina and is president of Samaritan's Purse, a Christian relief organization, offered a prayer at the 1996 Republican convention in San Diego. To attend the convention, Mr. Graham will fly from an international evangelists' conference in Amsterdam, which is being arranged by his father's organization, the Billy Graham Evangelistic Association. Franklin Graham will then return to the conference, where he is to be a speaker later in the week, a spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>Gustav Niebuhr (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
