<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stalled but Alive, Peace Talks On Mideast Reach 10th Day</title>
    <meta content="21MIDE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EEDE173AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1443" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stalled but Alive, Peace Talks On Mideast Reach 10th Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>THURMONT, Md., July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton's departure for economic summit in Japan drains energy from Israeli-Palestinian peace conference at Camp David, as exhausted delegations sleep late and then work with American team trying to help them beyond impasse and mutual accusations of bad faith; photo of Sec Madeleine Albright with Yasir Arafat; map; Israelis stay only at Clinton's request, Prime Min Ehud Barak having concluded that Palestinians are procrastinating and not presenting clear position on core issues; Palestinians deny interpretation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With President Clinton's departure for Japan, the energy drained from the Israeli-Palestinian peace conference as the exhausted delegations slept late today and then worked with the American team to determine how to move beyond the impasse and the mutual accusations of bad faith.</p>
        <p>Squirreled away in their cabins in the woods, the Israelis and the Palestinians tried to recover from the roller-coaster drama of late Wednesday night when, within the span of an hour and a half, the summit meeting died and was reborn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With President Clinton's departure for Japan, the energy drained from the Israeli-Palestinian peace conference as the exhausted delegations slept late today and then worked with the American team to determine how to move beyond the impasse and the mutual accusations of bad faith.</p>
        <p>Squirreled away in their cabins in the woods, the Israelis and the Palestinians tried to recover from the roller-coaster drama of late Wednesday night when, within the span of an hour and a half, the summit meeting died and was reborn.</p>
        <p>After teetering on the edge of a collapsed peace effort, and contemplating an uncertain future with the potential for renewed violence, they returned this afternoon to the same stumbling blocks, the same frustrations and the same elusive prospects for a final accord.</p>
        <p>The Israelis said they had stayed only because Mr. Clinton asked that they remain until his return on Sunday or Monday. ''When the president asks, you can't say no,'' a senior Israeli official said.</p>
        <p>About 5 a.m. on Wednesday, after finishing a third straight all-nighter of negotiations, Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel came to the conclusion that the Palestinians were not negotiating in good faith, the Israeli official said. Mr. Barak believed that the Palestinians were procrastinating and, even after nine days at Camp David, were not presenting a clear position on several core issues, including borders, settlements and security matters.</p>
        <p>The prime minister concluded that the meeting had reached a deadlock, and he wrote Mr. Clinton a letter to voice his concern, the official said. Mr. Barak also requested that his Israeli plane be prepared for departure, which many saw as a tactic. On Wednesday night, the Israeli delegation held a somber farewell dinner, and the White House announced that the talks were over.</p>
        <p>The Israeli official said the Israelis believed that the American announcement at 11 p.m. on Wednesday was a maneuver meant to provoke some 11th-hour decision-making. But when no decisions were provoked, the Israeli said, Mr. Clinton decided to continue the conference.</p>
        <p>American officials contest this account, saying Mr. Barak took the initiative when, facing going home empty-handed, he asked that the talks continue. They also said Shlomo Ben-Ami, one of his negotiators, had helped talk Mr. Barak into staying.</p>
        <p>Publicly, however, Israeli officials said today, on the 10th day of the meeting, that they did not see anything left to discuss. They said they were awaiting answers from the Palestinians, who, they claim, have hedged their responses to American compromise proposals on most issues. ''The ball is now in Arafat's court,'' Yitzhak Herzog, the Israeli cabinet secretary, said in an interview, referring to Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader. ''My uncle Abba Eban once said the Palestinians never miss a chance to miss a chance, and I hope and pray for all our children that they don't miss this one.''</p>
        <p>Palestinian officials denied the Israelis' interpretation, saying the Israelis were simply trying to portray themselves as flexible and the other side as intransigent. It was the Israelis who wanted to leave, they said, and the Palestinians agreed to remain to leave no stone unturned.</p>
        <p>''We don't want to be held responsible for the failure of the talks,'' said Samir Ghousheh, a member of the Palestine Liberation Organization's executive committee. ''If we hang tough, it will become clear that it is the Israeli side that is insincere.''</p>
        <p>Many Palestinians believe that the Americans are permanently biased toward Israel, even if Mr. Clinton has diligently nurtured a relationship with Mr. Arafat, and they contend that the meeting is inherently built to disfavor them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat, they say, has the ultimate power to say no, but after seven years of building an international consensus for a Palestinian state, he wants to reserve that power so as not to endanger what he has created.</p>
        <p>''We are worried about the failure of the summit,'' said Sulaiman al-Najjab, a member of the P.L.O. executive committee. ''We are worried, too, about the bias of the United States. Any failure will be as a result of such bias.''</p>
        <p>The State Department said the negotiators would return to the table to tackle the division of the West Bank, the future of Jewish settlements, the fate of Palestinian refugees and the thorniest issue, the status of Jerusalem. Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright held long meetings with both leaders today.</p>
        <p>''This is Day 10, and the success is that they're still talking,'' Richard Boucher, the State Department spokesman, said today.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Clinton departed, Mr. Boucher took over from the White House spokesman the task of managing the news blackout. American officials distribute nuggets of logistical information in lieu of substance to reporters at the Thurmont Elementary School, where local volunteers sustain the press corps with blueberries and home-baked pies.</p>
        <p>In Israel, the peace camp and members of the silent majority that supports peace voiced relief that Mr. Barak had decided to stay.</p>
        <p>Rightist leaders expressed anxiety about the concessions that Mr. Barak seemed prepared to make turning over Palestinian neighborhoods in Jerusalem to Palestinian control, for instance, as well as any that might go even further.</p>
        <p>''Barak has set a dangerous precedent,'' Ariel Sharon, leader of the Likud Party, said in a television interview. ''We'll have to work hard to reverse the decisions he made in the last nine days.''</p>
        <p>In the West Bank, a number of Palestinians said they were relieved that the talks were continuing because they feared a disintegration of the region into chaos and violence.</p>
        <p>And several analysts in the Arab world said that while they were heartened that substantive talks had taken place, they believed that the stumbling blocks -- particularly the disagreement over Jerusalem -- might be insurmountable.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that the outcome of this summit is zero,'' Abdel Barri Utwan, editor of a London-based Arabic newspaper, said in an interview on Al Jazeera satellite television. ''They wouldn't keep going for nine days if there was no understanding.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat reportedly told the Americans that he did not believe that he has a formal mandate from the Arab and Muslim world to recognize the Israeli annexation of East Jerusalem and cede sovereignty forever. That kind of recognition is what Israel is seeking, in exchange for giving the Palestinians control over Palestinian neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>To avoid what is seeming like an irresolvable issue and a potential deal-breaker, the Americans have fashioned a draft agreement that leaves the issue to the side, while pronouncing an end to the conflict, diplomats say. But both Israelis and Palestinians are extremely reluctant to back a partial deal.</p>
        <p>Because of the news blackout, it is impossible to know precisely what is on the table. But, at its core, analysts and diplomats in contact with the parties believe that the discussions are about establishing a demilitarized Palestinian state on 90 to 95 percent of the West Bank, with the rest being annexed to Israel. The territory would be transferred gradually to the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Palestinian officials acknowledge that over time, Mr. Barak has agreed to give more and more land, from a starting point of 50 percent of the West Bank. But they say it is hard to talk about land without talking about Jerusalem.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials argue that the Palestinians should not reject what the Israelis consider a generous offer that goes beyond what any politician who comes after Mr. Barak would be likely to make. A rightist politician would never contemplate it, and those doves who are Mr. Barak's political rivals do not have his security credentials, as a former general.</p>
        <p>''I tend to think history will judge the Palestinians harshly if they miss the Barak moment,'' said David Makovsky, a senior fellow at the Washington Institute for Near East Policy who has chronicled the peace effort for the last decade. ''I don't think they'll find a more accommodating Israeli leader, or one with equal clout. I think he's Israel's de Gaulle and this is the chance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Utwan, the editor in London, disagreed, saying that if Mr. Arafat ''comes back without having offered any concessions concerning Jerusalem, he will be received as a hero.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
