<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Welfare-Contract Testimony Is Sealed</title>
    <meta content="21HRA.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Workfare and Employment of Welfare Recipients</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Housing Works (Orgn)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Human Resources Administration (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Maximus Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turner, Jason A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoover, Mark S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marrero, Victor (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipton, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E1DE173AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Welfare-Contract Testimony Is Sealed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC LIPTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipton, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judge Victor Marrero seals testimony of New York City's top two social services administrators, Mark S Hoover and Jason A Turner, in a lawsuit in which Housing Works, a nonprofit AIDS service organization, charges that city withheld payments and prevented it from receiving a contract in retaliation for its frequent criticism of Giuliani administration; lawyers for officials argued that testimony might be used against them in separate criminal investigations concerning allegations that Human Resources Administration gave Maximum Inc of Virginia special access to city officials and documents as it prepared to bid on city contracts to help welfare recipients find jobs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A federal judge has granted New York City's top two social services administrators permission to keep their testimony about contested welfare-to-work contracts secret, responding to arguments by their lawyers that the testimony might be used against them in separate criminal investigations.</p>
        <p>Mark S. Hoover, deputy commissioner of the Human Resources Administration, testified yesterday and his boss, Commissioner Jason A. Turner, is scheduled to do so next Thursday, in response to a suit filed by Housing Works, a nonprofit AIDS services organization. In the suit, Housing Works asserts that the city withheld payments and prevented it from receiving a contract in retaliation for its frequent criticism of the Giuliani administration. The city disputes the claims.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A federal judge has granted New York City's top two social services administrators permission to keep their testimony about contested welfare-to-work contracts secret, responding to arguments by their lawyers that the testimony might be used against them in separate criminal investigations.</p>
        <p>Mark S. Hoover, deputy commissioner of the Human Resources Administration, testified yesterday and his boss, Commissioner Jason A. Turner, is scheduled to do so next Thursday, in response to a suit filed by Housing Works, a nonprofit AIDS services organization. In the suit, Housing Works asserts that the city withheld payments and prevented it from receiving a contract in retaliation for its frequent criticism of the Giuliani administration. The city disputes the claims.</p>
        <p>The Housing Works suit, on its face, has little to do with the $104 million worth of welfare-to-work contracts that have sparked investigations by the United States attorney's office and the Manhattan district attorney. The inquiries concern allegations that Human Resources last year gave Maximus Inc. of Virginia special access to city officials and documents as it prepared to bid on city contracts to help welfare recipients find jobs. Investigators also are examining the circumstances surrounding jobs that Maximus offered to Commissioner Turner's father-in-law and a family friend as the company pursued the New York contracts.</p>
        <p>After Housing Works lawyers indicated that they planned to inquire about the Maximus contracting process, the city asked Judge Victor Marrero of Federal District Court in Manhattan in June to bar the questions or to seal any testimony to keep it from the public and from law enforcement authorities.</p>
        <p>''Because Hoover and Turner are threatened with grand jury proceedings and a criminal prosecution,'' says a letter written by Bob Bailey, a lawyer for Human Resources, the questions would force them to ''provide testimony which may reveal the basis of their criminal defense,'' or provide information ''otherwise unavailable to prosecutors.'' Mr. Bailey also said that Mr. Turner and Mr. Hoover might choose to ''invoke the Fifth Amendment privilege,'' to avoid self-incrimination.</p>
        <p>The Giuliani administration and Maximus officials have consistently disputed suggestions, first raised by City Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi, that city contracting rules had been violated. Mr. Hevesi refused in March to approve two Maximus contracts, a decision that was upheld in April by a State Supreme Court justice, who called the contracting process ''corrupted.'' The city has appealed the ruling, and Maximus officials said yesterday that the company, which suspended its initial work on the contracts in April, was ready to return if the Giuliani administration won.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately we believe the company will be vindicated,'' said Rachael Rowland, a Maximus spokeswoman. ''We have always conducted ourselves with the highest integrity.''</p>
        <p>Two city officials said last night that neither Mr. Turner nor Mr. Hoover planned to exercise their Fifth Amendment rights, as they had nothing to hide.</p>
        <p>Debra Sproles, a spokeswoman for the Human Resources Administration, issued a statement last night reiterating that the agency had acted properly and was cooperating with the investigations, including providing all materials sought.</p>
        <p>The Giuliani administration and Housing Works had been at odds for at least two years, with the city contending in 1998 that the group mismanaged public funds, and Housing Works repeatedly protesting administration policies and claiming the mayor had made it difficult for people with H.I.V. or AIDS to obtain public assistance. A federal court in November vindicated Housing Works on one point, determining that it had cleared up its financial problems and had been unfairly denied a contract.</p>
        <p>In its most recent court filings, the city claimed that Housing Works was merely trying to harass Human Resources officials because the city's dealings with Maximus were unrelated to the decision not to award Housing Works a new contract. But Judge Marrero ruled on Wednesday that Housing Works should be allowed to ask questions about Maximus, given that Housing Works had bid on a contract to help welfare recipients with HIV find jobs, a task that Human Resources may have discussed with the Virginia company.</p>
        <p>Charles King, a Housing Works co-executive director, said that he was pleased that the judge had allowed the group to question Mr. Turner and Mr. Hoover about Maximus, but that he regretted the decision to seal testimony related to the company.</p>
        <p>In the law enforcement inquiries, several Maximus executives and the top contracting officials at Human Resources have already been questioned by investigators, and cartons filled with city documents, e-mail message files, a computer hard drive and other materials have been seized, city officials said. In addition to the Manhattan district attorney and the United States attorney, the city Department of Investigation is conducting its own inquiry, focusing on an allegation of conflict of interest involving at least one top Human Resources official, a city official said.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the United States attorney and the Department of Investigation said they could not comment on the matter. The Manhattan district attorney's office did not respond to a request for comment.</p>
        <p>Human Resources, meanwhile, is making several top-level management changes. Steven Stein Cushman, former deputy chief of the Corporation Counsel's contracts and real estate division, was named the agency's acting counsel in June, replacing Jack McCay, who city officials said retired. Jean Sheil, deputy commissioner for policy and program development, whom Mr. Turner recruited from Wisconsin to take the New York City job, will also be leaving the city. She declined to comment yesterday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
