<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y21BRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E7DA163AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2436" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>CORSICA: AUTONOMY PLAN ACCEPTED  Corsican nationalists said they had accepted French proposals to grant autonomy to their island in a crucial step toward ending 20 years of separatist violence. Speaking after a key round of talks with officials in Paris, Corsica's politicians said they were satisfied with proposals that opened the door for the island eventually to make its own laws.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>CORSICA: AUTONOMY PLAN ACCEPTED  Corsican nationalists said they had accepted French proposals to grant autonomy to their island in a crucial step toward ending 20 years of separatist violence. Speaking after a key round of talks with officials in Paris, Corsica's politicians said they were satisfied with proposals that opened the door for the island eventually to make its own laws.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>FRANCE: HUMAN TRAFFICKING TALKS  Officials from around the world, disturbed by the deaths of 58 Chinese illegal immigrants trying to enter Britain, called for tough new measures to halt the worldwide trafficking of humans. At a two-day seminar in Paris, Italy announced it had broken a ring that smuggled Chinese into Europea via the Balkans. Interior Minister Jean-Pierre Chevenement of France, above, said Russian, Turkish and Albanian groups controlled trafficking networks.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>FRANCE: CARLOS SUES  The convicted murderer known as Carlos the Jackal is taking France to the European Court of Human Rights for holding him in solitary confinement for almost six years. The Venezuelan-born ex-guerrilla, whose real name is Illich Ramirez Sanchez, was sentenced to life in prison in 1997 for murdering three people. He is accusing the French of using isolation as a torture tactic.</p>
        <p>Suzanne Daley (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: IRAQI CHEMICALS RULED OUT  The Ministry of Defense said a study had found no evidence that Iraq used chemical weapons against British troops in the gulf war. Many servicemen have suffered illnesses, sometimes called gulf war syndrome, since the 1990-91 conflict, but British researchers believe the cause was vaccines that troops were given rather than exposure to chemical weapons.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: 'DOCTOR DEATH' INQUIRY  Families of the victims of Dr. Harold Shipman, 54, convicted of murdering 15 patients with heroin injections and suspected of killing nearly 200, forced the government to hold a public inquiry. Health Secretary Alan Milburn had sought a private session, saying it would be quicker. But Lord Justice Kennedy of the High Court in London said there were ''many powerful considerations in favor of an open inquiry.''</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>CHECHNYA: 6 RUSSIANS KILLED  Chechen rebels rampaged through Russian-held towns near Grozny, killing at least six Russian soldiers, reports from both sides said. Guerrillas have stepped up activity in the past week, killing 25 Russians and wounding 74, said Valery Manilov of Russia's general staff.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MOLDOVA: PRESIDENTIAL VETO  President Petru Lucinschi vetoed a law that would end presidential elections and allow Parliament to elect the head of state, saying he refused to become a puppet. Mr. Lucinschi, a top Communist official in the Soviet era, urged the assembly to accept his proposal for a referendum to work out the country's future institutions.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>CANADA: INDIAN CANDIDATES  Indians are planning to run candidates in parliamentary elections, expected next spring. The move, either with a new First Nations Party or with existing parties, comes after the rise of Stockwell Day, leader of the right-wing Canadian Alliance, and after the election of Matthew Coon Come, a confrontational Cree leader, as national chief of the Assembly of First Nations. Indians are believed to hold swing votes in 10 percent of the 301 parliamentary districts.</p>
        <p>James Brooke (NYT)</p>
        <p>MEXICO: BANK CHIEF QUITS  Vicente Corta, the top administrative officer of Mexico's bank rescue agency, said he would leave his post Sept. 1. He cited personal reasons, but the resignation comes as the agency's work has provoked a new battle over whether the government has protected millionaires who committed fraud during the bailout that began in 1995, which has cost taxpayers nearly $100 billion.</p>
        <p>Sam Dillon (NYT)</p>
        <p>MEXICO: GOVERNOR TELLS OF BUGGING  The governor of Oaxaca, Jose Murat, from the ruling party known as the PRI, said he had found hidden microphones in his office and had ordered his own detectives to investigate, saying he had no confidence in federal security agencies. His remarks seemed directed at Interior Ministry officials, some of whom have been active in a rival faction of the PRI, consumed by infighting since its electoral defeat.</p>
        <p>Sam Dillon (NYT)</p>
        <p>CHILE: PINOCHET MOVE  The Supreme Court has begun analyzing an appeal to decide if Gen. Augusto Pinochet should lose his legislative immunity in order to stand trial on charges that he ordered executions and torture. The Court of Appeals decided last month to strip General Pinochet, who is a senator for life under the Constitution written during his regime, of his immunity. The Supreme Court is expected to rule next month.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>PERU: LONELY INAUGURATION  Presidents Hugo Banzer of Bolivia and Gustavo Noboa of Ecuador are the only heads of state to have accepted invitations to attend the July 28 inauguration of President Alberto K. Fujimori, who won a recent election marred by charges of irregularities and fraud.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRAZIL, VENEZUELA: PLEA TO SWISS  The two countries have asked the Swiss for help in finding millions of dollars they say was embezzled by ex-officials. Swiss officials said Venezuela is seeking money in three accounts believed to be tied to Carlos Andres Perez, who was twice president. Brazil wants legal aid in connection with a Geneva account said to belong to a fugitive judge, Swiss officials said.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Olson (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: PRESIDENT JEERED  Legislators jeered President Abdurrahman Wahid after he defied attempts to question him about his leadership, including the firing of two ministers. Mr. Wahid, the first president to be summoned before Parliament, said that under the Constitution he was not accountable to them. ''I came here today because of the consideration that we are just building up real democracy in this country,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Joe Cochrane (NYT)</p>
        <p>PHILIPPINES: GARBAGE DUMP CLOSED  President Joseph Estrada said he would not reopen Manila's biggest garbage dump, where at least 216 people died after a wall of rubbish collapsed on a squatter community. Mr. Estrada promised to move residents whose homes were destroyed to safer locations during a visit to the dump in a Manila suburb, saying 2,000 to 3,000 houses are available.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>BURUNDI: REBELS REJECT PLAN  The main Hutu rebel group in Burundi's civil war with the Tutsi-dominated army said it would not sign a draft peace plan drawn up by Nelson Mandela, and the government also voiced objections. The rebels said that while they supported the peace effort they would not sign because they had not been involved in the last two years of talks.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: REFORMIST SPEAKS OUT  After suppressing the news media and student groups seeking greater social and political freedom, the hard-line judiciary is taking aim at political parties, the leaders of Iran's largest reformist party said. Several members of the Islamic Iran Participation Front have been attacked in Tehran and elsewhere, but authorities have not gone after suspects, said Mohammad-Reza Khatami, a party chief. Mr. Khatami said hard-liners want to derail the reforms of his brother, President Mohammad Khatami.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>LEBANON: JAILED AS COLLABORATORS  A military court sentenced 26 people to prison terms ranging from 3 weeks to 15 years for collaboration or contact with Israel. It was the 18th group of people accused of being collaborators to be tried since the withdrawal of Israelis from southern Lebanon on May 24 and the collapse of the Israeli-allied South Lebanon Army militia.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
