<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nuclear Agency Delays Reopening of Con Ed's Indian Point 2 Plant</title>
    <meta content="21NUKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant (NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consolidated Edison Co of New York Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nuclear Regulatory Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indian Point Nuclear Power Plant (NY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE6DE173AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nuclear Agency Delays Reopening of Con Ed's Indian Point 2 Plant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD with RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard; Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nuclear Regulatory Commission says Con Edison is not ready to reopen Indian Point 2 nuclear reactor with its existing steam generators, one of which caused an accident on Feb 15 and will require further analysis; decision makes it less likely that the plant will resume operations this summer and more likely that consumers will see higher utility bills; Con Edison's critics say company could have saved its customers money by replacing the generators months or even years ago; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission today said that Con Edison was not ready to reopen the Indian Point 2 nuclear reactor with its existing steam generators. The decision makes it less likely that the plant will resume operations this summer and more likely that consumers will see higher utility bills.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission, in a letter sent to plant managers today, asked for extensive further analysis of the steam generators, one of which caused an accident that shut down the plant on Feb. 15. The commission staff said that the accuracy of the instrument for measuring flaws in the tube walls had been determined by using a tube at another reactor and that the tubes at Indian Point might differ.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission today said that Con Edison was not ready to reopen the Indian Point 2 nuclear reactor with its existing steam generators. The decision makes it less likely that the plant will resume operations this summer and more likely that consumers will see higher utility bills.</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commission, in a letter sent to plant managers today, asked for extensive further analysis of the steam generators, one of which caused an accident that shut down the plant on Feb. 15. The commission staff said that the accuracy of the instrument for measuring flaws in the tube walls had been determined by using a tube at another reactor and that the tubes at Indian Point might differ.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the company, Joseph P. Petta, said, ''Right now the immediate focus is getting these answers to the N.R.C.'' But he said that the company might try to reduce the uncertainty by sealing off the tubes most likely to leak, or that it might go ahead with replacing the steam generators immediately, a step that would preclude operation for months. ''We haven't ruled anything out,'' Mr. Petta said.</p>
        <p>But critics said that the company could have saved its customers money by replacing the generators months or even years ago. Loss of the plant for the rest of the summer would also increase the risk of the region's running short of power during the season when heat waves can challenge the system's ability to produce enough electricity.</p>
        <p>''Seemingly, this is the opportunity for Con Ed to go ahead and do the right thing and replace the steam generators, and not put the public at any greater risk than they have to be,'' said James P. Riccio, a nuclear expert at the Critical Mass Energy Project, a nonprofit group founded by Ralph Nader that had petitioned the regulatory commission to keep the plant shut. ''If they had replaced the steam generators in February, they would be making money hand over fist right now. Instead, they're paying it out hand over fist.''</p>
        <p>Representative Sue Kelly, a Republican of Katonah whose district includes the plant, said: ''Today's action by the N.R.C. only confirms my belief that Con Edison has kept our community in the dark and has put its bottom line above the public's safety. Con Ed needs to do the right thing and install the new steam generators now.''</p>
        <p>After the February accident, the company inspected the steam generators and asked for permission to run the plant for up to 10 months. But it also said it planned to shut down and replace the steam generators in the fall.</p>
        <p>It now faces the prospect of buying replacement power through the high-demand, high-cost weeks of late July through early September, while it repairs the steam generators to the satisfaction of the regulators or installs replacement generators already at the plant site, in Buchanan, N.Y., on the east bank of the Hudson River near Peekskill.</p>
        <p>Costs are higher this summer because oil and natural gas, the substitutes, are up in price. And because New York State has deregulated its utilities, power costs now vary much more sharply according to the time of year. Con Ed has sold off nearly all of its own generators, and is seeking to sell Indian Point.</p>
        <p>The steam generators are giant heat exchangers. Indian Point 2 heats water in the nuclear core and then pumps it into the steam generators, into thousands of thin-walled metal tubes. Outside the tubes, clean, nonradioactive water is pumped in and boiled into steam, which is used to spin a turbine, which turns a generator that makes electricity. In February, one of the tubes leaked water from the core, which is contaminated with radioactive material, into the clean, non-radioactive steam. Con Ed said the release of radiation was too small to be measured, but the plant has been shut for analysis and repairs ever since.</p>
        <p>Steam generators are designed with extra tubes so bad ones can be plugged. But that, too, could take days or weeks; the company may simply decide to go ahead and replace the generators.</p>
        <p>In actions unrelated to the decision by the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Assembly speaker and an assemblyman from a district near the plant asked the State Public Service Commission to impose $195 million in costs, for the shutdown and for a blackout in Upper Manhattan last summer, on Con Ed's shareholders rather than its ratepayers.</p>
        <p>Two Democratic assemblymen, Richard L. Brodsky of Westchester County, chairman of the Environmental Conservation Committee, and Adriano Espaillat of Manhattan, have filed a complaint with the state's Public Service Commission, charging that the accident resulted from Con Edison's own ''imprudency.'' If the commission agreed, it could force the company to refund the money to customers.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Brodsky and Mr. Espaillat, joined by Speaker Sheldon Silver, a Manhattan Democrat, proposed a settlement for $195 million, the first time they have put a dollar figure on it. The figure, more than double the record payout of that type, covers expenses only through Aug. 1.</p>
        <p>The Legislature has passed a bill that would disallow many of the same charges, and that bill was formally delivered today to Gov. George E. Pataki, a Republican. That puts Mr. Pataki squarely on the spot, because he must decide in the next two weeks whether to sign the bill, and because he controls the Public Service Commission, which will determine the fate of the imprudency complaint and today's offer.</p>
        <p>The assemblymen say that Con Edison's failure to replace the steam generators when other reactor owners did was imprudent. About half of the $195 million figure is the cost of providing power to replace the electrical output that was lost when the plant shut down. Some of it stems from expenses the company has incurred over the last decade to keep the generators running, including occasional shutdowns for maintenance. And $45 million would go to settle claims made after last summer's blackout in Washington Heights.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
