<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indoor-Outdoor Relations Along the Hudson Valley</title>
    <meta content="21JOHN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">King, Storm, a</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bard Colllege</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Loeb Art Center (Vassar College)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vassar College</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Katonah Museum of Art</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hudson River Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Ken</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldsworthy, Andy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kabakov, Ilya</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sugiura, Kunie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fasanella, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03EFD61F3BF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indoor-Outdoor Relations Along the Hudson Valley</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ken Johnson reviews exhibitions along Hudson Valley, NY: Andy Goldsworthy at Storm King Art Center, Ilya Kabakov at Bard College, Kunie Sugiura at Loeb Art Center of Vassar College, Maine and the Modern Spirt show at Katonah Museum of Art, and Ralph Fasanella and 19th-century drawing shows at Hudson River Museum; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For anyone venturing north of New York City with contemporary art in mind, two destinations are not to be missed this summer. Storm King Art Center in Mountainville, N.Y., just south of Newburgh, is presenting recent works by the English sculptor Andy Goldsworthy, and the Center for Curatorial Studies at Bard College in Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., has mounted a three-decade retrospective of the works of the Russian conceptualist Ilya Kabakov, including paintings, drawings and installations. You could take in both shows in a day if you set out early, but give yourself more time. One requires a lot of walking, the other a lot of reading; both are worth the effort.</p>
        <p>In certain ways these two artists could not be more different. Mr. Goldsworthy likes to use natural resources to create outdoor works of sensuously rich concreteness. Mr. Kabakov prefers the indoors, where he can generate brain-teasing mischief with multiple visual as well as verbal languages. Yet both are products of permissions issued during the 1960's, when the making of formally convincing objects gave way to the idea of art as the orchestration of interesting experiences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For anyone venturing north of New York City with contemporary art in mind, two destinations are not to be missed this summer. Storm King Art Center in Mountainville, N.Y., just south of Newburgh, is presenting recent works by the English sculptor Andy Goldsworthy, and the Center for Curatorial Studies at Bard College in Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y., has mounted a three-decade retrospective of the works of the Russian conceptualist Ilya Kabakov, including paintings, drawings and installations. You could take in both shows in a day if you set out early, but give yourself more time. One requires a lot of walking, the other a lot of reading; both are worth the effort.</p>
        <p>In certain ways these two artists could not be more different. Mr. Goldsworthy likes to use natural resources to create outdoor works of sensuously rich concreteness. Mr. Kabakov prefers the indoors, where he can generate brain-teasing mischief with multiple visual as well as verbal languages. Yet both are products of permissions issued during the 1960's, when the making of formally convincing objects gave way to the idea of art as the orchestration of interesting experiences.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldsworthy's is a paradoxical enterprise. He is almost puritanical in his insistence on using materials like sticks, stones, leaves or water found on site to create often ephemeral works that minimally affect the environment. In this respect he is like two other well-known British outdoor conceptualists, Richard Long and Hamish Fulton. Yet far from a pious environmental absolutism, Mr. Goldsworthy, 44, produces works of magical artificiality in which there is almost always a play of opposites: between the natural and the unnatural, inside and outside, order and disorder, reality and illusion.</p>
        <p>Storm King Art Center</p>
        <p>Storm King's indoor galleries have some of the beautiful photographs Mr. Goldsworthy takes to preserve his otherwise short-lived productions. These include a picture of a black hole in the ground, around which he made a round halo that fades from bright yellow to deep red. It has an extraordinary painterly intensity, yet it was made entirely of sumac leaves.</p>
        <p>Of considerably more palpable presence are three massive works that toy with relations between inside and outside. One is a circular wall 6 feet tall and 25 feet in diameter, built of red sandstone imported from Scotland (a departure from his usual preference for on-site materials). Constructed like traditional stone sheepfolds in Scotland, where the artist lives, the wall encircles a large tree growing near a corner of the small mansion that houses Storm King's indoor galleries. The wall has an indoor section, so that it seems to pass through two ground-floor, floor-to-ceiling windows. This has a curiously dematerializing effect on the architecture and results in a kind of spiritual recentering around the tree.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere Mr. Goldsworthy knitted twisted oak logs (also imported from Scotland) into two enormous balls, nearly 10 feet in diameter. One fills an indoor room like a giant apple in a Magritte painting. As you contemplate this one indoors, you can look through the windows of a gallery to the right and see its companion outside across the yard, a distant, dreamlike echo.</p>
        <p>Hyphenating these gnarly spheres is a third element: the entire floor of the intervening gallery is covered inches thick in mud that has dried to an allover craquelure pattern, but with the outline of a meandering ribbon running down the middle. (An underlying plywood foundation caused the ribbon image to emerge from the drying mud.) Called ''The River,'' this elemental inscape exhilaratingly overturns habitual expectations of what goes inside and what goes out.</p>
        <p>The serpentine image in ''The River'' also refers to Mr. Goldsworthy's most impressive work at the art center, ''Storm King Wall,'' or, as it is also known, ''Wall That Went for a Walk.'' Built in 1997-98 to be part of Storm King's permanent outdoor collection of modernist sculpture, the 5-foot-tall, 2,278-foot-long wall was made from local fieldstones by English wall-building craftsmen under Mr. Goldsworthy's direction. The wall runs straight down a hill into a pond, re-emerges on the other side and ascends into the woods. There it snakes back and forth between tall trees that grow in a straight line. It is delightful how this solid, inanimate structure seems to have an errantly playful mind of its own and fits the landscape like a glove. Few artists working today have a better sense than Mr. Goldsworthy of how to do outdoor sculpture.</p>
        <p>Bard College</p>
        <p>Inside-outside relations also figure in Ilya Kabakov's work, though not in the literal indoor-outdoor sense. Mr. Kabakov was born in Ukraine in 1931 and has lived in the United States since 1988. He started out as a children's book illustrator but came into his own as an artist in Moscow in the 1960's under the liberating influence of International Conceptualism, to which he joined his own highly developed traditional skills, visual as well as literary. What you feel at the center of his enterprise is a wild desire to escape the dreary, claustrophobic confines of one-dimensional, Communist reality through fantastic shifts of perspective.</p>
        <p>One expansive installation, a re-creation of a trash-strewn housing committee meeting room with typewritten grievances submitted by apartment residents tacked up on the walls, gives a vivid sense of that grim reality. Here is the background, one guesses, of another enigmatic installation, a ramshackle collection of large paintings in a hallway, whose title refers, evidently, to an artist who could not take it anymore: ''He Went Crazy, Undressed, Ran Away Naked.''</p>
        <p>That possibly insane impulse to escape is poetically expressed, too, in an installation consisting of a chair holding a man's neatly folded clothes standing next to a big painting on the floor of a partly cloudy sky. ''I'll return by April 12th,'' reads a mysterious note on a stand next to the chair. Has the artist, having stripped himself of the clothing of conventional consciousness, launched himself into the illusory, empyrean space of the painting? Or is there some more prosaic explanation? A certain melancholy ambiguity -- a sense that despite the possibilities of imaginative invention, real freedom may be impossible -- runs throughout Mr. Kabakov's oeuvre.</p>
        <p>It is not simply a matter of fantasy's being preferable to reality for Mr. Kabakov. The imperative is, rather, not to be psychologically trapped within any one system. His best installations use words and pictures to create structures in which alternative versions of reality are dizzyingly layered and intricately interconnected. His art is an argument for pluralism in the deepest sense of the word, not a lazy relativism but a belief in the multiplicity of worlds born of an all-too-intimate knowledge of ideological fundamentalism.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kabakov's works often comment upon themselves, including written stories, criticisms and interpretations in a multitude of voices that produce head-spinning changes in points of view. In a tableau called ''Artist's Despair, or Conspiracy of the Untalented,'' three ordinary representational paintings that have been vandalized hang on the wall.</p>
        <p>Broken glass and an ax lie on the floor behind a wooden barrier. On a table are typewritten texts, one of which explains that after the painter, in a fit of depression, destroyed his own works and disappeared, a critic proposed turning the scene into a Conceptual installation. ''A table and two chairs could be placed in front of the barrier,'' he suggests excitedly, ''and a story placed on the table about how all this happened, and we will get one of the most interesting types of installations, combining the visual level and texts, one of the most sophisticated and witty genres of this type of art.''</p>
        <p>This is funny, the artist spoofing his own avant-gardist pretensions, but it also sets up a kind of Borgesian hall of mirrors wherein one glimpses the mind-boggling complexity of self-consciousness. In Mr. Kabakov, the thought comes to mind, the world may have gained a wonderful artist, but it may have lost a great novelist.</p>
        <p>Loeb Art Center</p>
        <p>While traveling along the Hudson, you might also make a brief stop in Poughkeepsie at the Loeb Art Center at Vassar College, which has an excellent college-level collection, ranging from medieval to Modernist artworks and including a remarkable minicollection of small Hudson River School paintings. Featured this summer is Kunie Sugiura, a Japanese artist who has lived in New York City since 1967. Ms. Sugiura creates large photograms by exposing objects like flowers, fish, frogs or, in one case, live kittens directly on large sheets of photographic paper. She brushes and splashes on chemicals to produce combinations of ghostly, sometimes ritualistically composed images and Abstract Expressionistic gesturalism. Her works are more formally elegant than wildly visionary, however. It would be interesting to see what would happen if she added color.</p>
        <p>Katonah Museum of Art</p>
        <p>Off to the east, the Katonah Museum of Art has a painting show called ''Maine and the Modern Spirit.'' The title is promising, considering the major-league talent that has been drawn to that rustic state in the 20th century, but the exhibition is disappointingly uneven. It starts out well with good if not great early Modernist works by Marsden Hartley, John Marin, Marguerite Zorach, Edward Hopper and others. There is a surprising painting from the 1930's by Louise Nevelson, a picture of a hillside village in a rhythmic, expressionist style. There are mid-century pictures, too, by Fairfield Porter and Alex Katz.</p>
        <p>But among more recent works, the big names disappear and various forms of retrograde mediocrity in representation and abstraction prevail.</p>
        <p>Hudson River Museum</p>
        <p>Finally the Hudson River Museum in Yonkers is offering two very different shows. ''Open Air Sketching,'' a fine small group of drawings by 19th-century American landscape painters, was put together by the Albany Institute of History and Art from its own collection. The show includes works of exquisite technical finesse and, as in a small, dark picture of Niagara Falls by Thomas Cole, transcendentalist drama. Other artists include Frederic Church, Martin Johnson Heade, Jasper Cropsey and Sanford Gifford. Hudson River School fans, take note.</p>
        <p>The other show at the Hudson River Museum is a selection of paintings by the self-taught artist and working-class socialist Ralph Fasanella. A kind of urban Grandma Moses, Fasanella created ham-fisted but industriously detailed and festively colored cityscapes, some celebrating metropolitan life and baseball, some designed to advance his leftist politics. His feisty work presents a bracing contrast to the pantheistic refinement of the drawings in ''Open Air Sketching.''</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
