<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Backstage Drama And Bolshoi Power</title>
    <meta content="21SYMP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lincoln Center Festival 2000</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bolshoi Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Balanchine, George (1904-83)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4DE163AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Backstage Drama And Bolshoi Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews Bolshoi Ballet in Lincoln Center Festival 2000 program including Balanchine's Symphony in C; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sheer dance power is what the Bolshoi Ballet has brought back to New York. There was no better showcase than its exciting second program of the season, which introduced a phalanx and variety of dancers on a mixed bill that ranged from Marius Petipa to George Balanchine.</p>
        <p>The performance of ''Symphony in C,'' the first Balanchine work ever danced here by the company from Moscow, had been preceded by backstage drama. The initial movement of the 1948 Balanchine-Bizet classic was led on Wednesday night at the New York State Theater by Anastasia Goriacheva, who turned 19 on the same day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sheer dance power is what the Bolshoi Ballet has brought back to New York. There was no better showcase than its exciting second program of the season, which introduced a phalanx and variety of dancers on a mixed bill that ranged from Marius Petipa to George Balanchine.</p>
        <p>The performance of ''Symphony in C,'' the first Balanchine work ever danced here by the company from Moscow, had been preceded by backstage drama. The initial movement of the 1948 Balanchine-Bizet classic was led on Wednesday night at the New York State Theater by Anastasia Goriacheva, who turned 19 on the same day.</p>
        <p>Yet until Tuesday, she had never even rehearsed the role. Nonetheless, when Svetlana Lunkina, the company's rising young star, injured herself, Ms. Goriacheva was plucked out of the corps to replace her and put into nonstop rehearsal mode.</p>
        <p>It is a measure of the depth of the Bolshoi's youngest ranks that Ms. Goriacheva could sail so smoothly through the lively first movement with such charm, confidence and polish and also keep up in the unison finale with three, mostly senior, ballerinas. ''Symphony in C,'' which closed the program, brought the audience to its feet in an ovation so strong and prolonged that it seemed to catch the dancers by surprise.</p>
        <p>It was a capital idea for Lincoln Center Festival 2000 to offer the equivalent of what the Bolshoi Ballet used to call a concert program -- mainly excerpts with a full ballet (''Symphony in C'') thrown in. The major excerpt was the Kingdom of the Shades scene from Petipa's ''Bayadere,'' with a juicy, disciplined corps framing the stunning grand style of Galina Stepanenko, perfect in her form and musicality, and Nikolai Tsiskaridze, an extraordinary dancer both wayward in his charisma and brilliant in his virtuosity.</p>
        <p>The program opened shrewdly with the blast of male bravura once synonymous with the Bolshoi. In this case, it was the ''Appian Way'' scene from Yuri Grigorovich's 1968 ''Spartacus,'' in which the Thracian slave of the title prepares for battle against the Romans.</p>
        <p>Drama and brawn revved up the audience, paving the way for Nina Ananiashvili and her elegant new partner Andrei Uvarov, in the ''Don Quixote Grand Pas,'' the Bolshoi staple that backs up the familiar pas de deux with a small female ensemble.</p>
        <p>In this limited panorama of the company as a whole, the surprise is the stylish new form of the men, from corps to principals. They move easily from classical precision to the expressive and athletic stamina of the ''Spartacus'' excerpt.</p>
        <p>The women are more unpredictable. On one hand there is Maria Alexandrova, the company's new golden girl. She dances big in the Bolshoi style and she and Mr. Tsiskaridze, in the third movement of ''Symphony in C,'' made the Balanchine ballet breathe with the spirit and energy it deserved. The stage was too small for their leaps and their dynamism.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, there is occasional disdain for niceties of form. For every supple arched back in a perfect line of women as the ghosts or shades in ''La Bayadere,'' there are soloists whose feet are not neat or in the right position.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ananiashvili (partnered by Mr. Uvarov), could get away with her blurred passes in ''Don Quixote'' because she communicates something larger: the exhilaration and joy of dancing.</p>
        <p>In its approach to ''Symphony in C,'' the company did what it was taught: it danced a version that differed in some respects from the current staging at New York City Ballet, Balanchine's own company. The differences are in the group formations and especially in the second movement where the ballerina turns her back to the audience several times. This is the version preferred by John Taras, Balanchine's longtime associate. He owns the rights to the ballet and staged it in Moscow with Patricia Neary. Since they were also credited with the Kirov Ballet's staging last year, one can wonder why the two ballets look so different.</p>
        <p>Some of it has to do with the Bolshoi's style. Ms. Ananiashvili, a guest in 1988 with City Ballet, still prefers to snap into positions rather than flow into them in the second movement, in which she is basically miscast.</p>
        <p>Mr. Uvarov was a fine and forceful partner, as was Sergei Filin in the first movement, where Ms. Goriacheva did wonders with music that sagged under Andrei Sotnikov's baton. The orchestra comes from the New York City Opera.</p>
        <p>It took some time for both the dancing and the music to sing. But when Ms. Stepanenko and Dmitri Belogolovtsev, with his ultrahigh spring, led the fourth movement, the female corps was ready to shed its square-cut phrasing and mechanical precision. Energy finally poured forth from all for a dazzling finale.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stepanenko is a solid ballerina who promises little refinement and yet surprises with her gift to make form exquisite and expressive. Her dancing as Nikiya in ''La Bayadere'' was impressive for its technical perfection, subtle in its musical climaxes. Repeatedly, Mr. Tsiskaridze as her partner left her to balance in arabesque. Repeatedly, she came softly down from toe and followed him.</p>
        <p>In his solo and coda, Mr. Tsiskaridze flew around the stage in arrow-sharp leaps, a god of the wind with whirlwind grace. He carried off the virtuosic double assemble turns in the air with ease.</p>
        <p>As for the excerpt from ''Spartacus,'' it is easy to see why Mr. Grigorovich's shrewd blend of cinematic dissolves and mass groupings retains its power. Mr. Belogolovtsev may be slim and not in the heroic mold of the past. But there is no question that every tattered shepherd on stage, dancing his heart out, will rally to this Spartacus.</p>
        <p>He triumphs through the sheer conviction of his performance.</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
