<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investors Weed Out Thorns From Greenspan's Message</title>
    <meta content="Y21STO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenspan, Alan (Chmn)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7D8163AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investors Weed Out Thorns From Greenspan's Message</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investors focus on all positives in testimony of Federal Reserve chairman, Alan Greenspan, before Senate Banking Committee and send stock and bond prices sharply higher and interests lower; Nasdaq composite index jumps 128.93 points, to 4,184.56, while Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index rises 13.61 points, or 0.9 percent, to 1,495.57; Dow Jones industrial average rises 147.79, to 10,843.87; yield on Treasury's 10-year note falls to 6 percent, from 6.15 percent, while price rises 1 3/32, to 103 19/32; yield on 30-year bond falls to 5.81 percent from 5.91 percent; graphs; chart on key US interest rates (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Are investors looking at Alan Greenspan through rose-colored glasses?</p>
        <p>They may have done just that yesterday, focusing on all the positives of the testimony by the Federal Reserve chairman before the Senate Banking Committee and sending stock and bond prices sharply higher and interest rates lower.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Are investors looking at Alan Greenspan through rose-colored glasses?</p>
        <p>They may have done just that yesterday, focusing on all the positives of the testimony by the Federal Reserve chairman before the Senate Banking Committee and sending stock and bond prices sharply higher and interest rates lower.</p>
        <p>The Nasdaq composite index jumped 3.2 percent. The Dow Jones industrial average climbed 1.4 percent, led by a 12 percent surge in I.B.M. after it reported strong second-quarter profits late on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>What investors and analysts saw, to their surprise, was Mr. Greenspan offering encouragement for the view that the central bank would be able to slow economic growth enough to contain inflation, without risking a recession and, possibly, without any more interest rate increases.</p>
        <p>''What has captured the markets' attention here is that Greenspan has raised the possibility that the Fed is done,'' said Louis Crandall, chief economist at R. H. Wrightson &amp; Associates.</p>
        <p>Richard Berner, chief United States economist at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, said the Fed's aggressive stance of last spring had mellowed. ''The tone is one of a Fed that is going to be in a watchful, waiting mode, but doesn't see any catalyst for acting,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But investors may be too optimistic, and this could trip up markets in the days ahead, when the euphoria created by a mellow Alan Greenspan wears off.</p>
        <p>First, even some Wall Street analysts who were surprised by Mr. Greenspan's optimism still say more Fed rate increases will be needed in the future to finally slow economic growth to a manageable, noninflationary pace.</p>
        <p>While the chances of a rate increase in late August, when Fed policy makers next meet, are diminishing, Richard Berner, chief United States economist at Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, expects at least one more rate rise before the central bank is finished.</p>
        <p>But there may be an even bigger problem lurking for investors if Mr. Greenspan's remarks bring a lot of bulls back to the stock and bond markets. Strong rallies in both markets, on the belief that the worst of a yearlong series of Fed increases is over, could make slowing economic growth much more difficult and require more increases than now expected. Stocks rising to new highs could set off a burst of consumer spending -- through what is known as the wealth effect -- of the kind that has reignited economic growth the last several years. Declining interest rates will help spur both businesses and consumers.</p>
        <p>''If we were to rally 15 percent or 20 percent from here, that would negate some of the Fed's tightening pressure,'' Mr. Berner said.</p>
        <p>Because of this threat to a successful slowdown, or soft landing, ''most of us didn't expect him to be this market-friendly,'' Mr. Crandall said. ''This was the surprise.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan also warned that a soft landing for the economy was not assured. But that message seemed to be drowned out yesterday by the market applause for Mr. Greenspan's unexpected optimism.</p>
        <p>In the stock market, the Nasdaq index jumped 128.93 points, to 4,184.56, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index rose 13.61, or 0.9 percent, to 1,495.57. The Dow rose 147.79, to 10,843.87. I.B.M., which had announced a 12 percent earnings gain, accounted for half the Dow's rise. I.B.M. rallied in after-hours trading on Wednesday, but that did not show up in the Dow until yesterday, when the stock rose $12.84, to $117.</p>
        <p>In the bond market, prices were higher as yields, which move in the opposite direction, fell. The yield on the Treasury's 10-year note fell to 6 percent, from 6.15 percent on Wednesday, while the price rose 1 3/32, to 103 19/32. The yield on the 10-year note has been fighting to move back below 6 percent for five weeks. The yield on the 30-year bond fell to 5.81 percent from 5.91 percent.</p>
        <p>One significant monitor of concern about Fed rate increases did ease yesterday. The yield fell on the futures contracts on the federal funds rate, the central bank's short-term interest rate target, for August, October, November and December.</p>
        <p>In his testimony on monetary policy, Mr. Greenspan pointed out several factors restraining consumer spending, including rising consumer debt, rising oil and gasoline prices and the flat performance of the stock market so far this year. And he said that this consumer slowdown, if it continued, might be enough to bring economic growth down to the noninflationary pace Fed officials want. That is somewhere around 3.5 percent, well below the 6 percent pace of last year's fourth quarter and this year's first.</p>
        <p>''Should this favorable outcome prevail,'' he said, ''the immediate threat to our prosperity from growing imbalances in our economy would abate.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Greenspan also warned that it was too early to declare victory. ''It is much too soon,'' he said, ''to conclude that these concerns are behind us. We cannot yet be sure that slower expansion of domestic final demand, at a pace more in line with potential supply, will persist.''</p>
        <p>In past years, the economy has reaccelerated after slowing in the second quarter, a fact that Mr. Greenspan mentioned. The next key economic report is the Employment Cost Index, which measures worker compensation and is one of the Fed's favorite inflation barometers. It will be released Thursday.</p>
        <p>The next several days ought to indicate if investors have become Fed-happy. The stock and bond markets have often responded nicely on the day some positive news is released, only to settle back after investors realize that they -- and the Fed -- still need to see more positive data before they know they are out of the woods. But if investors conclude too early that they are out of the woods, their optimism, and the rallies it creates, may put them back in again.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
