<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bitter Rivals Inaugurate Zimbabwe Multiparty Era</title>
    <meta content="Y21ZIM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zimbabwe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mugabe, Robert (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zimbabwe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4DC173AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1214" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bitter Rivals Inaugurate Zimbabwe Multiparty Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>HARARE, Zimbabwe, July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zimbabwe's Parliament opens with Robert Mugabe's governing party forced to share power with formidable oppposition for first time in more than decade; photos; Movement for Democratic Change now controls 57 of 150 seats, enough to block Mugabe from unilaterally changing Constitution; Mugabe offers markedly conciliatory speech (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cameras flashed, the crowds cheered and the bitter rivals strode in side by side. One month after this country's momentous elections, Parliament officially opened today with the governing party forced to share space and power with a formidable opposition for the first time in more than a decade.</p>
        <p>But as Foreign Affairs Minister Stan Mudenge marched alongside Evelyn Masaiti, a teacher who was attacked by supporters of Mr. Mudenge's party during the harsh and violent campaign, he bowed graciously to the new reality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cameras flashed, the crowds cheered and the bitter rivals strode in side by side. One month after this country's momentous elections, Parliament officially opened today with the governing party forced to share space and power with a formidable opposition for the first time in more than a decade.</p>
        <p>But as Foreign Affairs Minister Stan Mudenge marched alongside Evelyn Masaiti, a teacher who was attacked by supporters of Mr. Mudenge's party during the harsh and violent campaign, he bowed graciously to the new reality.</p>
        <p>''He greeted me,'' marveled Mrs. Masaiti, who braved the political violence to win a seat for the opposition. ''He said, 'How are you?' He said he was lucky to be standing near me because the cameras would all concentrate on the man next to such a smartly dressed woman. And I just laughed.''</p>
        <p>With nervous glances and awkward handshakes, President Robert Mugabe's ZANU-P.F. party formally ceded its near-total monopoly on power today. And as the opposition party members took their seats in the chamber, thousands of flag-waving, singing supporters danced in the streets and welcomed a new, raucous era of multiparty democracy.</p>
        <p>For first time, a single opposition party -- the Movement for Democratic Change -- now controls 57 seats in the 150-member Parliament, a share large enough to block Mr. Mugabe's party from unilaterally changing the Constitution. The ZANU-P.F., which won 62 seats, had controlled all but 3 seats since the late 1980's. (The public elects 120 of the 150 members of Parliament, the president appoints 20, and local chiefs select 10.)</p>
        <p>And as the president entered Parliament this afternoon and saw the new faces in the chamber, he clearly knew the political landscape here had dramatically shifted.</p>
        <p>''The results of the elections are here, fully reflected in this significantly changed composition of this august house,'' Mr. Mugabe said today in a markedly conciliatory speech to the new Parliament. ''To you, all honorable members, I say congratulations while expressing the fervent hope that you will shoulder your weighty responsibilities in this house with dignity, a sense of responsibility and seriousness of purpose.''</p>
        <p>The government maintains its majority in Parliament, but the political realignment is still unprecedented here. And as cannons boomed and fighter jets whizzed over the capital, thousands of people flocked to see the spectacle with their own eyes.</p>
        <p>''I took off from work; I had to see it for myself,'' said Theresa Macheche, 18, a manicurist. ''We voted for change. We are fed up. Now we finally have a mixed Parliament with different parties.''</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Mugabe promised to address some of the concerns of the disenchanted urban electorate. He promised to focus on the ailing economy and move quickly to withdraw thousands of soldiers from the civil war in Congo, as well as step up the pace of land redistribution to poor black farmers, an issue that appeals to his rural support base.</p>
        <p>Government officials have also tempered their fiery statements against the white minority and black supporters of the Movement for Democratic Change. And last Saturday, Mr. Mugabe announced the formation of a new cabinet that has been widely praised across the political spectrum. The important ministries of finance and industry, for instance, are now run by Simba Makoni and Nkosana Moyo, respectively, two highly regarded businessmen who have at times been at odds with the government.</p>
        <p>That move was a critical first step in the effort to woo back Western donors, who have withdrawn desperately needed financial assistance from Zimbabwe, saying the economy is severely mismanaged.</p>
        <p>''The inclusion of private-sector business leaders to head the key economic ministries is in itself a powerful signal that this is the time for fundamental change,'' said Kumbirai Katsande, president of the Confederation of Zimbabwe Industries.</p>
        <p>But two Western officials said financial rescue would not come soon. They fear that the new ministers will lack the political clout to make painful but critical economic decisions. And they point to the government's continuing threats to seize white-owned land without compensation as a continuing source of concern.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, there is likely to be no change at all to the system of management and the style of leadership,'' said John Makumbe, a political analyst at the University of Zimbabwe and a frequent government critic.</p>
        <p>But the political shift is nothing short of extraordinary for many opposition legislators who are still learning parliamentary rules and how to wend their way through a building most had only seen on television. They are teachers, lawyers, students and small-business men who feel bewildered by government budgets and committees. And some are scrambling to find money to rent offices or print business cards.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Masaiti, 35, whose car was burned in the political violence that swept the country before the elections, had to squeeze into a public bus to make the four-hour journey from her rural district in Mutasa.</p>
        <p>Dunmore Makuvasa, 43, is praying he will find money to rent an office. When asked if he planned to buy business cards, he laughed. He makes fiberglass goods for a living and with soaring inflation, he said, even meat is a luxury now.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the new legislators took their oaths of office in a festive ceremony marked by dueling chants. ''Zimbabwe's independence was won through bloodshed!'' the ZANU-P.F. members chanted.</p>
        <p>Opposition members shouted back, startling their opponents into silence. ''ZANU-P.F. is rotten!'' they cried.</p>
        <p>But their jubilation faded as they promptly lost their first battle over the choice of the new speaker of Parliament. The governing party closed ranks and selected its preferred candidate, reminding the downcast opposition of the limits of its newfound power.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Moyo, the chief spokesman in Mr. Mugabe's office, says the members of the Movement for Democratic Change must learn to work with the majority or risk becoming ''noisemakers, not lawmakers.'' And some opposition legislators admit that they will be repeatedly outnumbered unless they find allies across the aisle.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Masaiti says she is undeterred by challenge. After all, she survived the campaign of violence waged by government supporters, who killed an estimated 30 people and injured hundreds more, most of them supporters of the opposition.</p>
        <p>In Mutasa, a mob burned the houses of dozens of her party members, leaving about 90 people homeless, including Mrs. Masaiti's in-laws.</p>
        <p>She said she got into politics because she was tired of struggling to feed her family. And this morning, on her big day, when she looked at her reflection in the mirror, she finally believed that she had made it. ''That woman,'' she said she told herself, ''is an M.P.''</p>
        <p>And by 9 a.m., hours before the opening ceremony, the new M.P., or member of Parliament, was already at work, meeting with women's groups and taking careful notes in her tiny spiral notebook.</p>
        <p>''People are saying they want development, roads, schools, irrigation, health facilities,'' she said as she rushed off to her next meeting. ''I know it won't be easy. I just promise I will try my best.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
