<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Candidate Begs to Lose In Florida Election Twist</title>
    <meta content="Y21FIR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Broward County (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southwest Ranches (Fla)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami-Dade County (Fla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Couvertier, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7D9163AF932A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Candidate Begs to Lose In Florida Election Twist</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, July 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Douglas Couvertier urges voters not to elect him to city council in newly-formed town of Southwest Ranches, in Broward County, Fla, even though he is on ballot; Couvertier began campaign before he found out he could lose job with Miami-Dade Fire Department if he holds elective office; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like most candidates for public office, Douglas Couvertier needed a clear, strong message, something that would cut through the other candidates' talk about what they would do for the voters, if elected.</p>
        <p>He needed a catchy slogan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Like most candidates for public office, Douglas Couvertier needed a clear, strong message, something that would cut through the other candidates' talk about what they would do for the voters, if elected.</p>
        <p>He needed a catchy slogan.</p>
        <p>''Please don't vote for me, please,'' seemed about right.</p>
        <p>Mr. Couvertier, whose name will be on the ballot Tuesday when voters go to the polls to elect a city council for the newly formed town of Southwest Ranches in Broward County, is running hard, and running to lose.</p>
        <p>''I've talked to civic leaders asking them not to vote for me,'' or to support him in any way, said Mr. Couvertier. ''I've sent out letters saying, 'Please don't vote for me.' I've talked to people.''</p>
        <p>''I stood a real good chance of being elected,'' he said, forlorn. ''In fact, my fear is I still stand a real good chance of being elected.''</p>
        <p>If that happens, he said, he will resign from the council without serving.</p>
        <p>It did not start that way, of course. He ran because he wanted to help shape the future of the town, one of the last mostly rural places in South Florida that is neither parkland nor under water in the rainy season.</p>
        <p>But on Tuesday, the 54-year-old Mr. Couvertier, a battalion chief for the Miami-Dade Fire Department, was told by his boss that the Miami-Dade County charter prohibits employees from holding elective office.</p>
        <p>Under the charter, candidates must go on leave when they begin campaigning and must quit their job if they win. Mr. Couvertier could, his superiors told him, lose a big part of his pension if he resigned from the fire department now.</p>
        <p>He did not know the charter had such a provision, and it came to his bosses' attention too late. He wanted to bow out, but was told by election officials that it was too late to have his name removed from the ballot.</p>
        <p>So he is campaigning fast and furious, as dedicated as anybody who is actually trying to win, to derail his candidacy. He has stopped short of name calling and character assassination, but there is no telling how low he may have to stoop if things keep going the way they are going.</p>
        <p>He hears he is the front-runner.</p>
        <p>With eight candidates seeking four at-large seats, he has a 50-50 chance at least, but early indications are that Mr. Couvertier, a 27-year veteran of the fire department and a popular figure in his community of 7,000 to 9,000 people, has been pulling ahead.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, in what seemed like a good thing at the time, he won the endorsement of The Miami Herald.</p>
        <p>His home bustles with anti-campaign activity.</p>
        <p>''Thank God you called,'' said a friend, Sara Horowitz, when told it was The New York Times on the line. ''We're trying so desperately not to get him elected.''</p>
        <p>With no budget for television advertising -- if he just had some television money, he could blow himself right out of contention -- he must try  other tactics.</p>
        <p>But it is tricky.</p>
        <p>He could post signs that read ''Vote for anybody but me,'' but that could backfire. In the attention span of many voters, it might be just enough information to trip their memories on election day and cause them to vote for him.</p>
        <p>''I really believe in this area,'' he said. ''I've lived here for over 20 years and I love it here. I thought it was important for my town for me to get involved.''</p>
        <p>But now is not the time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Couvertier is three years from retirement. If he is elected and then resigns, he will probably be able to save his pension. But he would prefer not to go through that bureaucratic ordeal and not have friends and neighbors elect him to a job that he immediately rejects.</p>
        <p>His decision to quit the race came too late to just take him off the ballot, said Jane Carroll, the Broward County elections supervisor.</p>
        <p>''There's no way to correct them at this point,'' Ms. Carroll said.</p>
        <p>Sixty-four absentee ballots are already in. With Mr. Couvertier's luck, he is probably already ahead. ''That makes me nervous,'' Ms. Horowitz said.</p>
        <p>For the other candidates, it seems like a lot of good votes going to waste.</p>
        <p>''Well, first, I think Doug is a good candidate and it's a shame that he has to back out,'' said Forest Blanton, 47, who is running for the council.</p>
        <p>But politics is politics.</p>
        <p>''If I were more aggressive, I'd try to ask him to recommend me to voters,'' Mr. Blanton said.</p>
        <p>Carlos J. Castillo, the Miami-Dade County assistant fire chief, said Mr. Couvertier was not going to be disciplined for not taking a leave because it was ''an honest mistake.''</p>
        <p>''Basically,'' he said, ''everyone is chuckling.''</p>
        <p>Even though it appears that Mr. Couvertier will be able to reclaim his job if he is elected, then resigns, he takes the election seriously and does not want to have to say ''No thank you,'' if he is unsuccessful in not winning.</p>
        <p>''My only out now is to lose,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
