<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bon Voyage Doesn't Mean What It Used To</title>
    <meta content="CUNARD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/travel/CUNARD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Furlaud, Alice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6DF153AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bon Voyage Doesn't Mean What It Used To</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALICE FURLAUD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Furlaud, Alice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alicia Furlaud travel essay recalls bygone era of bon voyage parties on ocean liners as they prepared to leave New York City piers; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A TICKET for two passengers (Biglietto di Passaggio) on the Andrea Doria, sailing March 31, 1956, from New York to Naples, fluttered out of an old suitcase of mine the other day. Under ''Nome dei Passeggeri'' are our names:  ''Mr. and Mrs. Maxime Furlaud.'' In another miscellany of forgotten letters and bills, I've found a blurry, distant photograph of Max and me looking over the rail as the liner eased away from the pier, to head slowly down the Hudson estuary to the sea. I am wearing glasses so I can see the friends on the dock who are taking the picture -- at least six of them, not counting my mother, who had come to see us off. Somewhere I have the picture Max took of these friends, waving heartily at us.</p>
        <p>I felt a pang of sadness when I found that photograph of us, age 26 and 31, remembering that lovely voyage with Max -- he died last year -- and regretting the end of the  pleasant custom of seeing the seagoing traveler off, which disappeared when airplanes became cheaper than ocean liners. By the late 1960's air travel was so widespread, inexpensive and swift that trans-Atlantic steamers began to look like expensive old slowpokes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A TICKET for two passengers (Biglietto di Passaggio) on the Andrea Doria, sailing March 31, 1956, from New York to Naples, fluttered out of an old suitcase of mine the other day. Under ''Nome dei Passeggeri'' are our names:  ''Mr. and Mrs. Maxime Furlaud.'' In another miscellany of forgotten letters and bills, I've found a blurry, distant photograph of Max and me looking over the rail as the liner eased away from the pier, to head slowly down the Hudson estuary to the sea. I am wearing glasses so I can see the friends on the dock who are taking the picture -- at least six of them, not counting my mother, who had come to see us off. Somewhere I have the picture Max took of these friends, waving heartily at us.</p>
        <p>I felt a pang of sadness when I found that photograph of us, age 26 and 31, remembering that lovely voyage with Max -- he died last year -- and regretting the end of the  pleasant custom of seeing the seagoing traveler off, which disappeared when airplanes became cheaper than ocean liners. By the late 1960's air travel was so widespread, inexpensive and swift that trans-Atlantic steamers began to look like expensive old slowpokes.</p>
        <p>And now that passenger liners are cruise ships, the classic seeing-off ceremony has become a pastiche of its former self. You are seeing off your friend or mother or uncle on a little pleasure trip, not on a Voyage Out to a Junior Year Abroad, complete with steamer trunk (or on a journey to a new job or a new life). Anyway, few cruises leave from New York. You usually have to board the ship in San Juan or Piraeus.</p>
        <p>And who wants to be seen off at an airport? It's miles from town, takeoff can be delayed for hours, and goodbye has to be said anticlimactically at the terrorist-detecting security gate. No comparison to the farewell parties on the French or Italian or Holland America or Cunard lines that left from piers right in New York City, along the Hudson between, roughly, 40th and 55th Streets.</p>
        <p>The ship usually sailed at noon, with passengers' friends allowed on board between 9 and 11 a.m. They would marvel at the ship from outside, decked with festive pennants. They'd share with you the excitement of finding your cabin (I always went cabin class, never first -- where they would be called staterooms -- or tourist class, which was the cheapest), and the relief if it had a porthole. If you were traveling alone in cabin class, you would all arrive and wonder if it was cricket to reserve the lower bunk with a coat before your cabinmate showed up.</p>
        <p>Often there would be telegrams waiting in your cabin. I have one here, sent to the Nieuw Amsterdam from San Francisco on July 1, 1949: BON VOYAGE LOVE AUNT HALLIE. She was my great-aunt, a fervent Francophile, happy that I, age 18, was sailing off to study in her beloved France.</p>
        <p>Also delivered to my cabin that day was a large package of books from Scribner's, sent by a friend who knew I was going to Italy, and that I would, of course, have a trunk. The five or six hardback books included the complete works of Robert Browning and two E. M. Forster novels, with careful instructions from my friend as to where in Italy to read each poem or passage.</p>
        <p>Usually, friends seeing you off on those grand old ships would have brought along liquor or candy. Baskets of cellophane-covered fruit might have been sent on board from Maison Glass. At that Andrea Doria send-off one friend brought us a miniature chess set. We lost a queen overboard the second day out and replaced her with a tiny papier-mache Easter bunny that had decorated a box of gift candy.</p>
        <p>But there would be time to explore the ship before crowding into the cabin to open the presents and champagne. ''Sign up for the second sitting,'' someone would always advise at the dining room door, where a steward was stationed with a book for signatures. (The first sitting was unfashionably early and full of infants.)</p>
        <p>Another friend would study the passenger list to see if anybody famous was sailing with us. If the ship was a Cunard liner, someone would be sure to say ''Remember not to mention the Titanic if you're at the captain's table!'' And if you were on, say, the Ile de France, a facetious friend would warn you that French crews obeyed the order ''Sauve qui peut'' -- loosely translated ''Every man for himself'' -- never ''Women and children first.''</p>
        <p>At 11 the ship's horn would rend the air with its first deep, shattering blast, the official signal ''I have intent to depart.'' This steam-driven hoot reverberated through the body as chillingly as the roar of a lion heard from a nearby tent on the Serengeti. Everyone would jump, ears covered. Passengers would watch their seers-off wobble down the gangplank, holding to its canvas sides. Then the gangplank would be drawn away, and there were your friends on the dock below, shouting last-minute remedies for seasickness or names of not-to-be-missed restaurants in Rome, across the widening watery gap between you.</p>
        <p>Once the ship was really under way, humming and vibrating its way out to sea, accompanied by fussy little tugboats all  named for members of the Moran family, there was a kind of silence. It could be a slightly embarrassing silence, in spite of the drumming of the engines. You now had to face your fellow passengers alone, without your happily celebrating group of supporters. Social life on the ship for the next five or six days would be a grab bag, and in my experience you were likely to find yourself assigned to the same table as someone you didn't like very much in the third grade.</p>
        <p>I don't mean to imply that departure was the best feature of a typical trans-Atlantic voyage, but it was often the most memorable part.</p>
        <p>MY mother witnessed a moving scene in the autumn of 1915. She had been in Paris all year with Aunt Hallie, and they were bound for New York from Cherbourg on a small ship, the Rochambeau. The Atlantic was perilous that year: the Lusitania had been sunk by a German submarine in May, and 1,195 people had died. My mother never forgot seeing the captain at the top of the gangplank, kissing both cheeks of the French Line official who was seeing the ship off. ''Au revoir, mon ami! Au revoir, la France!'' was his grandiloquent farewell.</p>
        <p>Meeting ocean-liner passengers at their destination wasn't half as exciting as seeing them off. Welcomers had to wait for hours, shut out from the dock, while their arriving friends or relations sat on trunks waiting their turn for Customs officers to search baggage.</p>
        <p>But I remember vividly a ship's arrival in early September 1945. My mother and I were driving through New York on our way from Cape Cod to our home in Philadelphia. We were going along 12th Avenue above the river, and there was the Queen Mary, heading for the piers below us, her decks crammed with cheering, cap-waving, khaki-clad soldiers home from the war. My mother hastily pulled over to the side of the road, saying ''Quick! Get out! They'll want to see a young girl. Wave! Wave!'' I got out, feeling, at 15, very inadequate as a female greeter. But I waved, and waved.</p>
        <p>ALICE FURLAUD is a commentator on ''The Next Big Thing,'' Sunday morning on WNYC-FM in New York.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ALICE FURLAUD is a commentator on ''The Next Big Thing,'' Sunday morning on WNYC-FM in New York.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
