<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TELEVISION: Track Records; As Thoroughly a Doctor as He Was a Cop</title>
    <meta content="01RAFF$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/arts/01RAFF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234990"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Braugher, Andre</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rafferty, Terrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gideon's Crossing (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE4DA133AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2009" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TELEVISION: Track Records; As Thoroughly a Doctor as He Was a Cop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRENCE RAFFERTY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rafferty, Terrence</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Terrence Rafferty profiles and interviews Andre Braugher, star of new television series Gideon's Crossing; photo (Special Section: Television) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SO far, we've had kidney cancer, breast cancer, prostate cancer, leukemia and myelofibrosis,'' says Andre Braugher, reciting the dire list with remarkable equanimity. He is referring, fortunately, not to his personal medical history but to the ordeals undergone weekly by the patients of Dr. Ben Gideon, the hero of the new ABC hospital drama ''Gideon's Crossing,'' which has its premiere on Oct. 10. Playing Dr. Gideon, he says, involves ''a steep learning curve,'' and, judging by the professional coolness with which he is now rattling off the names of life-threatening diseases and risky, radical therapies, it appears that he's negotiating that daunting curve with ease: six weeks into production of ''Gideon's Crossing,'' Mr. Braugher sounds uncannily like a real doctor, able to speak the unspeakable trippingly on the tongue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braugher's fluency with medical terminology is, of course, a product of his own scrupulous professionalism: immersing himself in the language, techniques and manner of a high-powered, research-oriented physician so that he can approximate (for the viewer and for himself) the experience of seeing the world through Dr. Gideon's eyes is his job, for as long as the series stays on the air. And, he says, ''I'm a lover of this profession.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SO far, we've had kidney cancer, breast cancer, prostate cancer, leukemia and myelofibrosis,'' says Andre Braugher, reciting the dire list with remarkable equanimity. He is referring, fortunately, not to his personal medical history but to the ordeals undergone weekly by the patients of Dr. Ben Gideon, the hero of the new ABC hospital drama ''Gideon's Crossing,'' which has its premiere on Oct. 10. Playing Dr. Gideon, he says, involves ''a steep learning curve,'' and, judging by the professional coolness with which he is now rattling off the names of life-threatening diseases and risky, radical therapies, it appears that he's negotiating that daunting curve with ease: six weeks into production of ''Gideon's Crossing,'' Mr. Braugher sounds uncannily like a real doctor, able to speak the unspeakable trippingly on the tongue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braugher's fluency with medical terminology is, of course, a product of his own scrupulous professionalism: immersing himself in the language, techniques and manner of a high-powered, research-oriented physician so that he can approximate (for the viewer and for himself) the experience of seeing the world through Dr. Gideon's eyes is his job, for as long as the series stays on the air. And, he says, ''I'm a lover of this profession.''</p>
        <p>''I like getting out of bed and going to work -- going to rehearsals when I'm doing a play, or going to the set every day when I'm shooting a movie or a series,'' he says. ''Not every day, maybe, but essentially I like the challenge of discovering the truth of the behavior and the inner lives of all these characters.''</p>
        <p>I meet Mr. Braugher at the poolside restaurant of a West Hollywood hotel on one of his rare days off from filming ''Gideon's Crossing,'' and I'm immediately struck by how relaxed and unpretentious he is. (He actually introduces himself -- as if I might not recognize him otherwise -- and then, very considerately, suggests moving the table so my New York skin won't get burnt to a crisp by the midday L.A. sun.) Over lunch, the conversation flows smoothly enough that I never have to consult the questions I've prepared.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Braugher, whose acting style is invariably described by journalists as ''intense,'' has been so successful at portraying wary, tightly wound, uncompromising characters -- notably Frank Pembleton, the implacable Baltimore police detective he played for six years on ''Homicide: Life on the Streets'' -- I'm pleasantly surprised by his looseness and amiability. (I didn't really expect Pembletonian disdain from him, but the relationship between an actor and a journalist can be uncomfortable; I'm always relieved not to be treated like a suspect in a senseless killing.)</p>
        <p>Although ''Homicide'' was never a ratings colossus, Pembleton is the role most people identify Andre Braugher with; he won a couple of Emmys for it, and his departure in 1998 (a year before the show went off the air) made entertainment-page news. He points out to me that his six seasons of ''Homicide'' represent half of his working life: he completed his studies at Juilliard only a dozen years ago. When Mr. Braugher auditioned for the series, he had already appeared in an important supporting role in the film ''Glory'' (1989), and had begun to make a name for himself in the theater, but his reading took the executive producers, Barry Levinson and Tom Fontana, by surprise; they were, Mr. Fontana remembers, ''blown away by his presence.'' Mr. Fontana also vividly recalls the power of the first episode in which Mr. Braugher and Kyle Secor (as Pembleton's partner, Tim Bayliss) grilled a suspect in the homicide division's stark, cheerless interrogation room. ''I was so inspired by the chemistry between Andre and Kyle that I went off and wrote an episode in which the whole hour was an interrogation,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Frank Pembleton's crafty, systematic demolitions of suspects' defenses quickly became the signature scenes of ''Homicide,'' and Mr. Braugher -- one of the lesser-known members of the series' initial ensemble, which included Ned Beatty, Yaphet Kotto, Jon Polito and Richard Belzer -- became, as if by a process of natural selection, the show's undisputed star. He knows that Pembleton was a great part. ''You couldn't figure out whether he was a villain or a hero,'' Mr. Braugher says. ''Even his partner could never quite decide.'' But he got restless. Mr. Fontana recalls: ''At a certain point Andre said to me, 'I feel like I've done the interrogation room. The character's too smart, too on his game.' So I said, 'What if he had a stroke?' And he said, 'Let's do it.' ''</p>
        <p>THE diminishment of the ace detective's intellectual acuity and verbal dexterity -- his proudest possessions -- gave the actor the sort of challenge he needed to keep him on the show a while longer. (And he played Pembleton's affliction and recovery with a subtlety uncommon in dramatic portrayals of disability.) Eventually, though, as ''Homicide'' approached its 100th episode, Mr. Braugher decided that ''we'd told all the stories we possibly could, and it was time for me to go home.''</p>
        <p>As it turned out, however, he would spend just two months of the next year at home with his wife, Ami Brabson (who played Pembleton's wife on ''Homicide''), and their two small sons. ''I was afraid of being too closely associated with a single character,'' says Mr. Braugher, who is 37. ''I'd seen it happen before, and to people I thought were admirable actors. I felt I was in a race to get as much material out there as I could that was different from Frank Pembleton; I didn't want to play another aggressive, manipulative, self-absorbed prima donna for a while.'' To implement his ''I'm not Pembleton'' program, Mr. Braugher in rapid succession took on film roles as a sweet-natured karaoke-singing drifter (in the recently released ''Duets''), a thoughtful hit man (in ''A Better Way to Die''), an elegant gangster (in ''Thick as Thieves''), a secretive, sexually confused lawyer (in ''It's the Rage'') and an idealistic priest coaching a black high school basketball team in the segregated South of the early 60's (in the made-for-cable movie ''Passing Glory''). He also found time to direct a segment of the Showtime anthology ''Love Songs.'' All that furious activity must have helped him distance himself from Pembleton -- enough, at least, to allow him to play another homicide detective (albeit a conspicuously less fearsome one) in Gregory Hoblit's ingenious time-travel movie ''Frequency.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Braugher probably didn't need to run quite so grueling a race in order to re-establish his versatility. Everybody knew already. Mr. Fontana, Mr. Hoblit and Paul Attanasio, the creator of both ''Homicide'' and ''Gideon's Crossing,'' each at some point uttered the words ''He can do anything.'' Mr. Attanasio went further: ''He's also game to do pretty much anything. You can throw any acting task at him. He's like one of those ninja masters, taking on seven guys at once and dispatching them all.''</p>
        <p>I suspect, in fact, that the frenzy of Mr. Braugher's post-''Homicide'' career has less to do with proving something to producers and directors than with proving something to himself. Between the six-year grind of the series and his duties as a husband and father -- which he takes extremely seriously -- he has had to scale down an enormous creative ambition. When I ask him what roles he dreams of playing, he says: ''Every one of Shakespeare's heroes, and eventually every one of Shakespeare's clowns.'' We spend quite a lot of our long poolside lunch, actually, talking not about television or movies, but about ''Macbeth,''  ''Coriolanus,''  ''Henry V'' and, especially, ''Hamlet,'' which was the play that got Mr. Braugher into the acting business in the first place. He was only marginally involved in theater during his high school years in Chicago. But in his freshman year at Stanford, he was persuaded by a friend to try out for a production of ''Hamlet'' that had just lost its Claudius. He got the part, and, he says, ''It was the most fun I'd had lately. And at the end of the evening the audience applauded -- I mean, I don't think we were very good, but they applauded. I was electrified.''</p>
        <p>Within minutes of our meeting, Mr. Braugher launches into a theory about how the Prince of Denmark should be played, complete with detailed refutations of several scholarly interpretations of the character. And a couple of hours later he returns to the theme again, while he's explaining to me why actresses like Alfre Woodard and Meryl Streep inspire him more than male actors do.</p>
        <p>A CTRESSES are vastly more interesting to me,'' he says. ''What happens with men is that there's a code of behavior that crushes various aspects of the masculine personality. There's behavior that's forbidden: weakness is despised, absolutely. For example -- to get back to my fixation on 'Hamlet' -- I've never seen an actor playing Hamlet who has dared to be a coward. And I say 'dared' because cowardice is something that people recoil from, and you risk losing the sympathy of the audience. But if you don't deal with the issue of cowardice, the character can't make sense.''</p>
        <p>Clearly this is an actor with intellectual and emotional energy to burn, and the role of Ben Gideon, while it isn't exactly Hamlet, appears to be complex enough to keep Mr. Braugher's fires fed for now. (And for whatever reasons, the movies have so far failed to provide him with a role commensurate with his talent.) The character is based on Dr. Jerome Groopman, a Boston physician who chronicled his clinical experiences in the 1997 book ''The Measure of Our Days.''  ''We were looking for an actor who could combine strength and command and toughness with real emotional depth and warmth,'' Mr. Attanasio says. ''Andre is one of the few who could do that. I wrote the character as a white, Jewish man, like Dr. Groopman, and cast an African-American actor -- and the character never changed.'' If the author of ''Henry V'' had seen Mr. Braugher's performance of that title role in Central Park in 1996, he might have said something similar.</p>
        <p>Mr. Braugher says, ''This is a role that I felt I had to rise to meet; it's quite a challenge.'' The script, he says, was exciting enough to make him do something he profoundly did not want to do -- leave his new home in New Jersey and commit himself to several months of shooting in Southern California. It probably helps, though, that the role not only stimulates his creative imagination but also satisfies a personal ambition: ''I want to show my sons images of black men in America who are fundamentally intelligent, articulate, decent men. Sometimes I feel as if I have a duty to combat the ritual demonization of African-American males.''</p>
        <p>That Mr. Braugher can deliver such a high-minded declaration without sounding the least bit sanctimonious augurs well for his portrayal of Dr. Gideon: it's likely that the actor will rise to meet this noble character without allowing his feet to leave the ground. The role might even lay to rest the uneasy ghost of Frank Pembleton. In ''Gideon's Crossing,'' Andre Braugher is once again playing a tenacious and sharp-witted investigator, but this character is searching for more elusive truths than Pembleton ever did, and confronting destructive forces that can't be cajoled or browbeaten into giving up their secrets. If nothing else, this part should have enough depth and variety to keep Mr. Braugher's restless imagination occupied while he readies himself for the Macbeth, the Coriolanus, perhaps the Hamlet in his future. And, as he obviously understands, in an actor's life the readiness is all.</p>
        <p>Terrence Rafferty is critic at large for GQ magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Terrence Rafferty is critic at large for GQ magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
