<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nemesis</title>
    <meta content="01BRONNET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bronner, Ethan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Rich</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Avengers, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0DA103BF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nemesis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ethan Bronner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bronner, Ethan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ethan Bronner reviews book The Avengers by Rich Cohen; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Avengers</p>
        <p>By Rich Cohen.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 261 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Avengers</p>
        <p>By Rich Cohen.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 261 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>In the Book of Exodus, God complains that the Jews are ''a stiff-necked people.'' Over the years, others too have complained that Jews are not easily yoked. Yet the modern era altered that perception. Herded into boxcars and massacred in death camps, the Jews of World War II evoke images of victims.</p>
        <p>Not all of Europe's Jews acceded to their unimaginable fate, however. There were those who grasped what the Nazis had in mind and scaled frozen mountains or hid for months under floorboards or in caves. A few stayed and fought back. The way they saw it, according to Rich Cohen, author of this fascinating -- but frustrating -- story of a small group of Jewish partisans, ''It was fight and die, or don't fight and still die.''</p>
        <p>In truth, the successes of the Jewish partisans were few -- a blown-up rail car here, several dozen dead enemy officers there -- and most were captured and executed. But the depth of their courage, the unambiguous justice of their cause and the raw evil of their tormentors make for an inspiring tale. What does it take to crawl in human waste through the sewers of the Vilna ghetto to transport parts of a single machine gun? To live without bread on a swamp island in the Rudnicki forest of southern Lithuania worrying not only about invading German soldiers but neighboring Jew-hating Polish partisans? To carry out a revenge plot against the Germans after the war? Those are the stories that Cohen tells in ''The Avengers.''</p>
        <p>Cohen, a contributing editor at Rolling Stone, seems to have a special interest in stiff-necked Jews. His first book, ''Tough Jews,'' was a well-received account of American Jewish gangsters. This new book comes from somewhere quite personal. One of its three main characters, Ruzka Korczak, who as a young woman was a fierce partisan, is a relative of his, and he grew up visiting her and her two colleagues in arms, Vitka Kempner and Abba Kovner, on family trips from suburban Chicago to Israel. He says he decided their story had to be told before it was lost.</p>
        <p>Many Israelis know vaguely about Abba Kovner, who died in 1987 after fame as a partisan and poet. In the early 1990's, his name surfaced again, however, with the publication of ''The Seventh Million,'' by Tom Segev, an Israeli historian and newspaper columnist. Segev took on the then-taboo topic of the contempt with which many Israelis viewed the Holocaust and its survivors. For the first time, Segev revealed a shocking plot hatched by Kovner to bring a small group of fighters, named the Avengers, back to Germany after the war. The plan was to poison the country's water supply in an effort to kill six million Germans. Apparently tipped off by Zionist leaders, who saw the plan as dangerous to their state building, the British jailed Kovner as he was trying to leave Palestine in late 1945. He got word to his colleagues, however, and a much scaled-back version of his plot was carried out several months later and did have some effect. A couple of thousand Nazi officers were fed bread poisoned by the Avengers at the local bakery. How many died, if any, remains unclear.</p>
        <p>Cohen says that he, in effect, informally interviewed Kovner and his wife, Vitka, on and off during family visits over the years. Then, in 1998, he spent some weeks in Israel interviewing Vitka, who took him to see other aging partisans. He put together the full story of Kovner and his two women partners starting from their days as partisan fighters and ending with the founding of Israel. It is a story that has been told in bits and pieces in a number of different books but never in an accessible, clear narrative.</p>
        <p>Cohen is a skilled writer. His language is spare and muscular, his descriptions evocative, his technique suspenseful. He is moved by this story and he moves us. We meet brave Jews and cowardly ones, as well as other intriguing characters -- a mother superior who sews a yellow star on her coat to work for the Jewish fighters, a German officer who risks everything to help and is ultimately captured and killed. This book would no doubt make a powerful movie.</p>
        <p>But as a piece of history, even oral history, it is irresponsible. Cohen makes no attempt to sort out versions of the past and offers no narrative tools to help readers understand where a particular account or detail comes from. The omniscient narrator simply tells the tale, complete with long quotations and inner monologues from the dead. It is therefore impossible to take the book seriously as a work of nonfiction.</p>
        <p>A useful example of this concerns Kovner's assertion (in oral history interviews at Hebrew University) that Chaim Weizmann, Israel's first president, encouraged him to try to poison Germans after the war. In Cohen's account, the encounter is simply told as objective truth. Segev, on the other hand, tells the same story and then writes:</p>
        <p>''Kovner has remained the sole source for this part of the story. The Weizmann archives contain no mention of a discussion with Kovner; Weizmann was out of the country at the time. It is possible, then, that the poet dreamed up the meeting. He may have wished, after the fact, to claim official support for his plan of revenge.''</p>
        <p>If this point, or some version of it, appeared even in a footnote by Cohen, that would be enough. But Cohen has no footnotes. It may be that his research convinced him that Kovner's account of the Weizmann endorsement is legitimate. But we can't tell, just as we can't tell if other details come from other histories or from a 20-minute conversation on a kibbutz with an aging partisan. The ideological divisions among the partisans colored much of what they subsequently wrote and said. The historian Lucy S. Dawidowicz, who told key parts of the Vilna partisan story in her book ''The War Against the Jews,'' stated explicitly there that the accounts vary markedly. Cohen seems to care little about such details. He wants only to tell a good story. This is a pity because what could have been a thrilling and authoritative work remains thrilling alone.</p>
        <p>Ethan Bronner, education editor for The Times, was the Jerusalem correspondent for The Boston Globe from 1991 to 1997.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ethan Bronner, education editor for The Times, was the Jerusalem correspondent for The Boston Globe from 1991 to 1997.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
