<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Britain Rethinks Costly Millennium Projects</title>
    <meta content="01REP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Millennium Dome (London)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tate Gallery (London)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stadiums and Arenas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E5DA1E3BF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Britain Rethinks Costly Millennium Projects</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travel article assesses success and failure of wide array of Millennium projects throughout Great Britain; attendance at London's Millennium Dome, initially projected at 15 million for this year, stands at 4.27 million through August; Tate Modern gallery, on other hand, has done far better than expected; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THINK of Britain's ambitious Millennium projects and the tendency is to focus on the ill-fated Dome, the inverted-wok edifice at Greenwich that provided so little bang for its billion-plus public bucks.</p>
        <p>And certainly, as failures -- or at least spectacular underperformers -- go, the Millennium Dome remains by far the most costly and least loved of the many projects that were supposed to transform the face of Britain at the start of a new era.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THINK of Britain's ambitious Millennium projects and the tendency is to focus on the ill-fated Dome, the inverted-wok edifice at Greenwich that provided so little bang for its billion-plus public bucks.</p>
        <p>And certainly, as failures -- or at least spectacular underperformers -- go, the Millennium Dome remains by far the most costly and least loved of the many projects that were supposed to transform the face of Britain at the start of a new era.</p>
        <p>Its projected attendance was initially 15 million for this year, then scaled back to 12 million. Through August, the Dome had 4.27 million visitors, and the operators now say that this year they expect 4.5 million to visit its exhibits on themes like the human body, faith, work and play, its music-and-dance extravaganza, and its restaurants.</p>
        <p>Since its disastrous opening party on New Year's eve, when celebrities were obliged to stand in line in the chill just like the ordinary folks who paid for the Dome through their National Lottery tickets, it has needed injections of extra cash to meet operating costs -- the latest was $74 million in National Lottery funds early last month. The total cost has surpassed a billion dollars.</p>
        <p>And so tangled have its finances become that Nomura, a Japanese bank, which offered in July to buy the Dome for $157 million and turn it into a theme park, announced on Sept. 12 that it was withdrawing its offer. The bank complained that the Dome's government-appointed operators have not even drawn up a register of assets.</p>
        <p>Yet, beyond the Dome and one or two other singularly unfortunate projects -- like the Millennium footbridge across the  Thames that swayed so much it has been  closed to the public indefinitely -- Britain's hinterland is freckled with some $2.5 billion in ambitious projects designed to rejuvenate tired urban landscapes and provide jobs and new focal points for the arts.</p>
        <p>Some have worked. Some have not.</p>
        <p>The Dome is not alone in its poor track record. The National Center for Pop Music in the northeastern city of Sheffield and the Earth Center, a theme park highlighting environmental issues in Doncaster, a little farther north, have both fared poorly, with attendance running far below projections.  In its first year, 1999, the Center for Pop Music drew half its projected 400,000 visitors, and is closing for a makeover. ''It lacked the 'wow' factor,'' said Neil Anderson, its spokesman. The Earth Center drew only 120,000 of a projected 320,000 visitors.</p>
        <p>But other prestigious projects -- like the Lowry Center, a collection of arts and theater facilities in the docklands of Salford near Manchester, and the huge Tate Modern gallery on the south bank of the Thames -- have done far better than expected.</p>
        <p>According to the latest figures from the Millennium Commission -- an official body that with the Arts Council distributes National Lottery money -- the Lowry has drawn 270,000 visitors since opening in May, compared with a projected 128,000. The Tate Modern drew over one million in the same period, far above its expected 387,000. Surprisingly, one of the most successful ideas has been the Eden Project, near St. Austell in Cornwall. This botanical park has drawn 110,000 people even though it has not yet opened its huge dome greenhouses.</p>
        <p>This patchy record has provoked a debate about whether Britain should have embarked on such a costly array of attractions with such optimistic assessments. In reality, said Patrick Greene, president of the  British Museums Association, representing museum operators, there had been ''an underestimate of the amount of competition there is out there for people's leisure time.''</p>
        <p>Of course, the situation is not that simple.</p>
        <p>The Dome is the only Millennium project initiated and overseen by successive British governments purely for its prestige. With its organizers' poor sense of public relations, it was bound to draw political flak, particularly as the costs to the public skyrocketed.</p>
        <p>Then, there was a lesson to be drawn from the real estate agents' mantra: location, location, location. Built at the end of a new subway line from central London, but difficult to reach by car, the Dome seemed too much of a trek for some Londoners used to spending chunks of their week in the grim confines of the city's underground system.</p>
        <p>There's a debate, too, about the cost. The Tate Modern, with its slick promotion and central location, is free. The Dome costs up to $30 a person, almost in the same league as a theme park, but without the rides -- a high price for an attraction that the public had already financed with lottery tickets. The Pop Music Center in Sheffield lowered its fee to $7, from $11, but still could not ward off collapse, according to Mr. Anderson, its spokesman. Yet, the biggest millennial modification to the London skyline -- the privately financed London Eye Ferris wheel -- charges a hefty $13 for a 40-minute spin, and has been successful.</p>
        <p>The lessons from all this will be debated for years, but if the Dome is anything to go by, two things are clear: high prices don't work, and neither does the heavy hand of the state on ventures that should stand or fall on their merits alone.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
