<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Long Way From Ipanema</title>
    <meta content="01MALCOMT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Malcomson, Scott L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Azevedo, Aluisio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, David H</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Slum, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDA103BF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1117" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Long Way From Ipanema</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Scott L. Malcomson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Malcomson, Scott L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scott L Malcomson reviews book The Slum by Aluisio Azevedo, translated by David H Rosenthal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Slum</p>
        <p>By Aluisio Azevedo.</p>
        <p>Translated by David H. Rosenthal.</p>
        <p>222 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Oxford University Press. $30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Slum</p>
        <p>By Aluisio Azevedo.</p>
        <p>Translated by David H. Rosenthal.</p>
        <p>222 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Oxford University Press. $30.</p>
        <p>We may have a title problem here. ''The Slum'': is there anyone whose interest would be ignited by these words on a dust jacket? In a better world, the name Aluisio Azevedo would mean something to North Americans. He was a major figure in late 19th-century Brazilian letters, and ''The Slum'' is considered his masterpiece. He planned the book to be Volume 1 in a five-part series analogous to Balzac's ''Human Comedy'' -- an all-encompassing portrait of one society. Not long after ''The Slum'' was published in 1890, however, Azevedo gave up writing. He served as a diplomat until his death in 1913. ''What's the use of writing? For whom?'' he asked a friend. ''We have no readers. . . . I've had it up to here with literature!''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, ''The Slum'' sold steadily through the 20th century as literacy spread across Brazil. It is not difficult to see why. Azevedo had trained to be an artist, and his strong eye shows in his prose: ''The washtubs stood abandoned; there was no one on the bleaching ground. Baskets heaped with ironed garments left the little homes, mostly borne by the washerwomen's children, almost all dressed in clean clothes. Short jackets fluttered above brightly colored calico skirts. Straw hats and burlap aprons were scorned. Instead, the Portuguese women wore bright flowered kerchiefs around their heads, while the Brazilians had combed their hair and stuck two-vintem bouquets among their curls.'' Azevedo traveled with his sketchbook to Rio's slums, returning home to render the visual into words. ''The Slum'' is the sort of novel Tom Wolfe has ordered his colleagues to write, a Great American Novel with great American themes, notably greed and race.</p>
        <p>Does ''The Slum'' have sex? ''With a sudden, savage spasm, they both collapsed in each other's arms, panting. Her mouth was wide open, her tongue hung out, her arms and fingers were stiff, and her whole body shuddered as though she were dying, while Jernimo, flung far from life by that unexpected explosion, surrendered to a delightful intoxication, feeling the entire world and his own past vanish like vain shadows. Unaware of anything around him or even of his own existence, eyeless, earless and senseless, he retained one clear, vivid, inextinguishable sensation: that warm, vibrant flesh.'' Azevedo's novel, in this agile translation by David H. Rosenthal, covers many of the varieties of sexual experience. One of its more levelheaded characters is very clearly a lesbian.</p>
        <p>However, in Azevedo's swirling world good sense and sexual passion most often work at cross-purposes. Passion tends to lead from light skin to dark, coolness to heat (the American sun is the fatal Zeus of Azevedo's tragedy), spirituality to lust, hard work to lazy pleasure. The sentences after desire usually feature coiling vipers in a symbolism familiar to readers of the Bible. But Azevedo loves tropical America, and sees surrender to its marriage of Eros and Thanatos as inevitable, if not exactly wise.</p>
        <p>The alternative to carnal passion, broadly understood, is a passion for money. In Azevedo's slum, self-advancement means taking more from others than you have paid for. The slum constitutes the human manure (a ubiquitous Azevedo metaphor) in which fortunes are seeded and grow. The flower of such cultivation in ''The Slum'' is a Portuguese landlord named Jo  Scott L. Malcomson is the author of ''One Drop of Blood: The American Misadventure of Race,'' to be published this month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Scott L. Malcomson is the author of ''One Drop of Blood: The American Misadventure of Race,'' to be published this month.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
