<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Traffic Jam at the Wharf</title>
    <meta content="CRUZIN$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FALL AND WINTER CRUISES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kidd, Vernon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3DE153AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="19546" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Traffic Jam at the Wharf</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VERNON KIDD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kidd, Vernon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Directory of cruises scheduled from November 1, 2000, to February 28, 2001; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the Caribbean, cruise lines are seeking new ports as competition grows for space in this prime winter destination. The larger ships, unable to dock in many ports, take another tack, concentrating on the ship itself as the main destination and visiting fewer ports.</p>
        <p>Beginning in May, the Grand Princess of Princess Cruises will call at the recently opened port of Mahahual on the Yucatan Peninsula south of Cancun, where excursions are offered to the Museum of Mayan Culture in Chetumal. From this port, the Maya ruins of Oxtankah and the recently excavated Chakchoben, dating from 360 B.C., are accessible, as is the Chinchorro coral reef, which is comparable in size to the 189-square-mile island of Cozumel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the Caribbean, cruise lines are seeking new ports as competition grows for space in this prime winter destination. The larger ships, unable to dock in many ports, take another tack, concentrating on the ship itself as the main destination and visiting fewer ports.</p>
        <p>Beginning in May, the Grand Princess of Princess Cruises will call at the recently opened port of Mahahual on the Yucatan Peninsula south of Cancun, where excursions are offered to the Museum of Mayan Culture in Chetumal. From this port, the Maya ruins of Oxtankah and the recently excavated Chakchoben, dating from 360 B.C., are accessible, as is the Chinchorro coral reef, which is comparable in size to the 189-square-mile island of Cozumel.</p>
        <p>The ports of Houston and New Orleans and some on the west coast of Florida as well as Fort Lauderdale and Miami are departure points for the increasingly busy western Caribbean, with several cruise lines including a partial transit of the Panama Canal through the Gatun Locks for a turnaround in Gatun Lake, then calling at another recently developed Yucatan port, Calica.</p>
        <p>For the first time in at least 40 years regularly scheduled cruises to Havana for Americans are being offered by Cuba Cruise out of Nassau and by West Indies Cruising out of Montego Bay. Citizens can take these cruises without violating federal regulations on travel to Cuba because the trips start outside the United States, are booked in a foreign country and are being operated by a foreign line. Also, passengers eat and sleep  on board in port, and shore excursions are run by a  Canadian philanthropic group, so no money is spent in Cuba.</p>
        <p>Royal Olympic Cruises' newest ships, the Olympic Voyager and the Olympic Explorer, each carrying 836 passengers and having cruising speeds of 28 knots, are using their higher speeds to cover distances between a wider choice of ports during 11-  to 16-night cruises that include the Amazon and the Orinoco Rivers, and Windstar's luxury sail cruises continue their calls to Nicaragua and Costa Rica's less visited Pacific Coast ports.</p>
        <p>The United States Lines, returning to ocean travel as part of American Classic Voyages, offers whale watching on its seven-night Hawaiian Islands cruises aboard the Patriot, the former Nieuw Amsterdam, out of Honolulu, starting in December, and for the first time, Norwegian Cruise Lines moves into Southeast Asia next year for a series of cruises from Bangkok, Tianjin (the port for Beijing), Singapore and Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>At least eight ships are roaming the globe on world cruises this season, one of which, P &amp; O Cruises' newest ship, the Aurora, will depart from Southampton on Jan. 6 on its 90-night inaugural world cruise.</p>
        <p>Giving new meaning to the term ''grand tour,'' the first floating condominium, named the World, will try to follow fair weather while visiting natural attractions and attending cultural events when it makes its debut in 2002, offering 110 two-  or three-bedroom apartments of 1,100 to 3,200 square feet. Travelers can buy the right to use this seafaring home for 50 years, starting at $2 million. Information: www.residensea.com.</p>
        <p>This directory mainly covers cruises from Nov. 1 to Feb. 28. Dates, ports of call and fares are for one person in double occupancy, excluding port taxes. Except where noted, all major ships have sprinkler systems throughout. More information is available from travel agents or the cruise lines. Addresses, telephone numbers and Web addresses appear on Page 30.</p>
        <p>Caribbean And Southeastern Waters</p>
        <p>Cape Canaveral Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Dolphin IV</p>
        <p>Capacity 718 passengers; 13,650 tons, outdoor pool, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Zion in 1956, refurbished in 1999.  Year round -- Two-  and four-night cruises from Cape Canaveral, calling at Grand Bahama Island and, on four-night cruises, Key West. From $149 to $999. Vacation package at Universal Studios, Orlando, available.</p>
        <p>Carnival Cruise Lines</p>
        <p>Carnival Destiny</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,642 passengers; 101,353 tons, four outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine and choice of restaurants; entered service in 1996.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises from San Juan, calling at St. Thomas, St. Lucia, Curacao and Aruba or St. Thomas, Antigua, Guadeloupe and Aruba. From $1,339 to $3,189.</p>
        <p>Carnival Triumph</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,758 passengers; 102,000 tons, four outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1999.</p>
        <p>Year round -- Seven-night cruises from Miami, calling at Playa del Carmen, Cozumel, Grand Cayman and Ocho Rios or San Juan, St. Thomas and St. Croix. From $1,339 to $3,189.</p>
        <p>Carnival Victory</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,758 passengers; 102,000 tons, four outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in August.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises from Miami, calling at San Juan, St. Croix, St. Thomas, St. John or Playa del Carmen, Cozumel, Grand Cayman and Ocho Rios. From $1,339 to $3,189.</p>
        <p>Celebration</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,486 passengers; 47,262 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1987.  Year round -- Four-  and five-night cruises departing on Thursday and Saturday from Galveston, calling at Cozumel on four-night cruises or Cozumel and Calica on five-night cruises. From $705 to $1,765.</p>
        <p>Ecstasy</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,052 passengers; 70,376 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1991.  Year round -- Three-  and four-night cruises departing on Friday and Monday from Miami, calling at Nassau on three-night cruises or Key West and Cozumel on four-night cruises. From $615 to $1,385.</p>
        <p>Fantasy</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,056 passengers; 70,367 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1990.  Year round -- Three-  and four-night cruises departing on Thursday and Sunday from Port Canaveral, calling at Nassau on three-night cruises or Freeport and Nassau on four-night cruises. From $615 to $1,385.</p>
        <p>Fascination</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,052 passengers; 70,367 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1994.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises depart Saturday from San Juan, calling at St. Thomas, St. Martin, Dominica, Martinique, Barbados. From $1,139 to $2,689.</p>
        <p>Imagination</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,052 passengers; 70,367 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995.  Year round -- Four-  and five-night cruises from Miami, calling at Key West and Cozumel on four-night cruises or either Grand Cayman and Calica or Grand Cayman and Ocho Rios on five-night cruises. From $705 to $1,765.</p>
        <p>Inspiration</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,052 passengers; 70,367 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1996.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from New Orleans, calling at Montego Bay, Grand Cayman and Cozumel. From $1,139 to $2,689.</p>
        <p>Jubilee</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,486 passengers; 47,262 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1986.  Starting Nov. 13 -- Four-  and five-night cruises departing on Thursday and Monday from Tampa, calling at Key West and Cozumel on four-night cruises or Grand Cayman and Cozumel on five-night cruises. From $705 to $1,765.</p>
        <p>Paradise</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,044 passengers; 70,367 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, no smoking aboard; entered service in 1998.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Miami, calling at Nassau, San Juan and St. Thomas or Cozumel, Grand Cayman and Ocho Rios. From $1,139 to $2,689.</p>
        <p>Sensation</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,052 passengers; 70,367 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1993.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Tampa, calling at Grand Cayman, Cozumel and New Orleans. From $1,139 to $2,689.</p>
        <p>Tropicale</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,022 passengers; 36,674 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1982, refurbished in 1998.  Nov. 22 to Jan. 31 -- Ten-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Aruba, Cartagena, Gatun Lake, Limon and Key West. From $1,649 to $3,049.  Starting Feb. 10 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Key West, Belize, Cozumel and Progreso (Mexico). From $1,139 to $2,689.</p>
        <p>Celebrity Cruises</p>
        <p>Century</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,750 passengers; 70,606 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995.  Nov. 4 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Ocho Rios, Grand Cayman, Cozumel and Key West or San Juan, St. Thomas, St. Martin and Nassau. From $1,149 to $5,949.</p>
        <p>Galaxy</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,870 passengers; 77,713 tons, indoor and two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1996.  Nov.4 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from San Juan, calling at St. Croix, St. Lucia, Barbados, Antigua and St. Thomas. From $1,099 to $5,899.</p>
        <p>Horizon</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,354 passengers; 46,811 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1990, refitted in 1998.  Nov. 4 -- Seven-night voyage from San Juan to Aruba, calling at St. Thomas, St. Kitts, St. Lucia, Barbados and Grenada. From $699 to $3,599.  Nov. 11 to Dec. 30 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from Aruba, calling at St. Thomas, St. Kitts, St. Lucia and Barbados, and from Jan. 6 to Feb. 24, calling at Colon, Gatun Lake, Limon, San Blas Islands and Cartagena. From $899 to $3,799.</p>
        <p>Mercury</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,870 passengers; 77,713 tons, indoor pool and two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1997.  Nov. 26 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to La Guaira, calling at Key West, Calica, Cozumel, Grand Cayman, Limon, San Blas Islands, Cartagena, Aruba and Curacao. From $1,599 to $9,929.</p>
        <p>Millennium</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 91,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entering service in November.  Starting Nov. 26 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Fort Lauderdale, calling at San Juan, Catalina Island (Dominican Republic), St. Thomas and Nassau or Key West, Calica, Cozumel and Grand Cayman. From $1,199 to $6,399.</p>
        <p>Zenith</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,375 passengers; 47,255 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1992, refitted in 1999.  Nov. 4 -- Eight-night voyage from New York to San Juan, calling at Nassau, Tortola, St. Martin and St. Thomas. From $799 to $3,749.  Nov. 12 -- Five-night voyage from San Juan to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Catalina Island (Dominican Republic), Tortola and Nassau. From $499 to $3,449.  Starting Nov. 17 -- Ten-  and 11-night cruises departing from Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. Martin, St. Lucia, Barbados, Antigua and St. Thomas on 10-night cruises or Curacao, La Guaira, Grenada, Barbados, Martinique and St. Thomas on 11-night cruises. From $1,399 to $4,499.</p>
        <p>Club Med</p>
        <p>Club Med 2</p>
        <p>Capacity 392 passengers; 14,983 tons, seven computer-operated sails, two outdoor pools, retractable marina, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1992, refitted in 1998.  November to March -- Seven-night cruises from Martinique calling at St. Lucia, Tobago Cays, Bequia, Barbados, Mayreau, Grenada or St.-Barthelemy, Virgin Gorda, Jost Van Dyke, St. Thomas and St. Kitts. From $1,613 to $4,132.</p>
        <p>Commodore Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Enchanted Capri</p>
        <p>Capacity 637 passengers; 15,410 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the Azerbaijan in 1975, refurbished in 1997; no full sprinkler system.  Year round -- Two-night cruises to nowhere departing on Friday from New Orleans and five-night cruises departing on Sunday, calling at Cozumel and Progreso. From $369 to $1,845.</p>
        <p>Enchanted Isle</p>
        <p>Capacity 725 passengers; 23,395 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the Argentina in 1958, refurbished in 1994; no full sprinkler system.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from New Orleans, calling at Playa del Carmen, Cozumel, Grand Cayman and Montego Bay. (Sailings from Jan. 27 to Feb. 3 call at Roatan and Belize instead of Grand Cayman and Montego Bay, and on Dec. 12 an 11-night voyage from San Juan to New Orleans calls at St. Croix, Soufriere and Castries on St. Lucia, Grenada, Aruba and Ocho Rios.) From $1,180 to $2,800.</p>
        <p>Costa Cruises</p>
        <p>Costa Atlantica</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,112 passengers; 84,000 tons, three outdoor pools, one with sliding glass roof; spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entering service in November.  Nov. 19 to Feb. 25 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Fort Lauderdale calling at Key West, Cozumel, Ocho Rios and Grand Cayman or San Juan, St. Thomas, Catalina Island (Dominican Republic) and Nassau. From $799 to $4,399.</p>
        <p>Costa Victoria</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,928 passengers; 76,000 tons, indoor pool and two outdoor pools, spa, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1996.  Dec. 3 and 11 -- Five-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Cozumel and Grand Cayman. From $449 to $1,699.  Dec. 16 and 23 -- Seven-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Key West, San Juan, St.Thomas and Nassau or Nassau, Ocho Rios, Grand Cayman and Cozumel. (Eight-night cruise on Dec. 30 calls also at Catalina Island in the Dominican Republic and Tortola.) From $699 to $4,199.  Jan. 7 to Feb. 25 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Key West, Cozumel, Ocho Rios and Grand Cayman or San Juan, St. Thomas, Catalina Island (Dominican Republic) and Nassau. From $749 to $3,399.</p>
        <p>Crown Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Crown Dynasty</p>
        <p>Capacity 800 passengers; 20,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1993, refurbished in 1999.  Nov. 4 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from Aruba, calling at Curacao, Soufriere and Castries (St. Lucia), Barbados, Grenada and Bonaire. Fare $1,280 to $3,270.</p>
        <p>Crystal Cruises</p>
        <p>Crystal Harmony</p>
        <p>Capacity 940 passengers; 49,400 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1990, renovated in 2000.  Dec. 20 -- Thirteen-night voyage from New Orleans to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Playa del Carmen, Cozumel, Aruba, St. Lucia, St.-Barthelemy and St. Thomas. From $4,525 to $21,395.</p>
        <p>Cuba Cruise</p>
        <p>La Habana</p>
        <p>Capacity 340 passengers; 6,000 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the Arion in 1965, renovated in May.  Starting Nov. 16 -- Three-  and four-night cruises departing on Thursday and Sunday from Nassau, calling at Havana. From $335 to $1,895, including shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Cunard Line</p>
        <p>Queen Elizabeth 2</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,778 passengers; 70,327 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1969, refitted in 1999.  Dec.20 -- Sixteen-night cruise from New York, to Miami, Montego Bay, Curacao, Bonaire, Barbados, St. Thomas, Cape Canaveral and Miami. From $5,080 to $54,750.</p>
        <p>Caronia</p>
        <p>Capacity 665 passengers; 24,492 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Vistafjord in 1973, refitted and renamed in 1999.  Nov. 27 and Dec. 9 -- Twelve-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. Croix, Antigua, Barbados, St. Martin, Tortola and San Juan. From $3,240 to $12,890.  Dec. 21 -- Sixteen-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. Thomas, Antigua, Barbados, Grenada, Margarita Island, Bonaire, Aruba, St. Martin and Tortola. From $5,680 to $22,960.</p>
        <p>Disney Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Disney Magic, Disney Wonder</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,750 passengers each; 83,000 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, choice of restaurants, international cuisine; entered service in 1998 and 1999, respectively.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises on Disney Magic departing Saturday from Port Canaveral, calling at St. Martin, St. Thomas and Castaway Cay. From $799 to $4,089.  Year round -- Three-  and four-night cruises on Disney Wonder departing on Sunday and Thursday from Port Canaveral, calling at Nassau and Castaway Cay. From $434 to $2,864. Cruise-vacation packages at Disney World available on both ships.</p>
        <p>EuroCruises</p>
        <p>Black Watch</p>
        <p>Capacity 761 passengers; 28,492 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the Royal Viking Star in 1972, refurbished in 2000.  Nov. 7 -- Fourteen nights from Freeport to Barbados, calling at Nassau, Grand Turk, Road Town, St. Martin, St. John's, Portsmouth, Roseau, Martinique, St. George's, Trinidad and Plymouth. From $2,690 to $7,170.  Nov. 21 -- Fourteen-night cruise from Barbados, calling at Scarborough, Macapa, Curua Una River, Boca de Valeria, Manaus, Alter do Chao, Macapa and Devils Island. (Sailing on Dec. 5 calls at Scarborough, Port Elizabeth, St. John's, Guadeloupe, St. Martin, Virgin Gorda, La Guaira, Isla Blanquilla, St. George's and Castries.) From $2,520 to $7,395.</p>
        <p>First European Cruises</p>
        <p>Mistral</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,200 passengers; 47,900 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1999.  Dec. 22 -- Seven-night cruise from Guadeloupe, calling at St. Kitts, Antigua, Tortola, St. Martin, St.-Barthelemy and Martinique. From $950 to $2,160.  Dec. 29 -- Seven-night cruise from Guadeloupe, calling at St. Vincent, Barbados, Tobago, Grenada, Dominica and St. Lucia. From $1,000 to $2,280.  Jan. 5 to Feb. 23 -- Seven-night cruises from Guadeloupe, calling at St. Martin, Tortola, St.-Barthelemy, Dominica, Antigua and Barbuda or Martinique, Trinidad, Grenada, Barbados, St. Lucia and Barbuda. From $799 to $1,830.</p>
        <p>Holland America Line</p>
        <p>Maasdam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,266 passengers; 55,451 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1993, refurbished in 1999.  Dec. 13 -- Ten-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Aruba, Cartagena, San Blas Islands, Gatun Lake and Grand Cayman. From $1,279 to $4,203.  Dec. 24 -- Eleven-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Kralendijk, Margarita Island, Castries, Soufriere, Guadeloupe, Philipsburg, St. Thomas and Half Moon Cay. From $2,149 to $13,016.  Jan. 14 to Feb. 25 -- Seven-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Cozumel, Grand Cayman, Ocho Rios and Half Moon Cay. From $959 to $4,041.</p>
        <p>Noordam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,494 passengers; 33,930 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1984, renovated this year; no full sprinkler system.  Dec. 8 -- Ten-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Half Moon Cay, Cartagena, Gatun Lake, Limon and Grand Cayman. (Nine-night cruise on Dec. 18 calls at San Blas Islands instead of Limon and Grand Cayman.) From $1,099 to $3,082.  Dec. 27 -- Eleven-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to Tampa, calling at Grand Cayman, Gatun Lake, San Blas Islands, Cartagena, Half Moon Cay and Fort Lauderdale. From $1,339 to $3,557.</p>
        <p>Ryndam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,266 passengers; 55,451 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service 1994, refurbished in 2000.  Dec. 23 -- Seven-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Key West, Playa del Carmen, Cozumel and Half Moon Cay. (Sailing on Dec. 30 calls at Philipsburg, St. Thomas and Half Moon Cay.) From $1,199 to $8,227.</p>
        <p>Veendam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,266 passengers; 55,451 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1996, refurbished in 1999.  Nov. 3 to Feb. 26 -- Seven-night cruises from San Juan, calling at Santo Domingo, Barbados, Martinique, St. Martin and St. Thomas. (Dec. 29 sailing calls at St. Croix, St. Thomas, Margarita Island, Castries, Soufriere and Guadeloupe.) From $829 to $8,227.</p>
        <p>Volendam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,440 passengers; 60,906 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1999, refurbished in 2000.  Nov. 12 and Dec. 2 -- Ten-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. Kitts, Martinique, Trinidad, Roseau and Cabrits on Dominica, St. Thomas and Half Moon Cay. (Sailings on Nov. 22 and Dec. 12 call at Antigua, St. Lucia, Barbados, Point-a-Pitre and Basse-Terre on Guadeloupe, St. Thomas and Nassau.) From $1,179 to $4,103.  Dec. 22 -- Seven-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Key West, St. Thomas and and Half Moon Cay. (Eight-night cruise on Dec. 29 calls at Half Moon Cay, Ocho Rios, Grand Cayman, Cozumel and Key West.) From $1,199 to $8,992.  Jan. 6 to Feb. 25 -- Ten-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Curacao, La Guaira, Trinidad, Martinique, St. Thomas and Half Moon Cay or Bonaire, Margarita Island, St. Lucia, St. Kitts, St. Thomas and Nassau. From $1,469 to $5,421.</p>
        <p>Westerdam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,494 passengers; 53,872 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the Homeric in 1986, refurbished this year; no full sprinkler system.  Nov. 4 to Feb. 25 -- Seven-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Nassau, San Juan, St. Thomas and Half Moon Cay. (Five-  and eight-night cruises from Jan. 6 to Feb. 25 also stop at St. Martin.) From $599 to $2,701.  Dec. 23 and 30 -- Seven-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Half Moon Cay, San Juan, St. Thomas and Nassau on Dec. 23 and Half Moon Cay, Montego Bay, Grand Cayman and Cozumel Dec. 30. From $1,069 to $3,247.</p>
        <p>Zaandam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,440 passengers; 60,906 tons, two outdoor pools one with retractable dome, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, Italian restaurant; entered service in May.  Nov. 3 and Dec. 13 -- Ten-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Half Moon Cay, St. Thomas, Cabrits and Roseau (Dominica), Trinidad, Martinique and St. Kitts. (Sailings on Nov. 13 and Dec. 3 call at Antigua, St. Lucia, Barbados, Guadeloupe, St. Thomas and Nassau.) From $1,179 to $4,103.  Dec. 23 -- Seven-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Half Moon Cay, Ocho Rios, Grand Cayman and Key West. (Sailing on Dec. 30 calls at Half Moon Cay, St. Croix, St. Thomas and Nassau.) From $1,199 to $8,227.  Jan. 6 to Feb. 15 -- Seven-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Bonaire, Margarita Island, St. Lucia, St. Kitts, St. Thomas and Nassau or St. Kitts, Martinique, Trinidad, Dominica, St. Thomas and Half Moon Cay. From $1,469 to $5,421.</p>
        <p>Mediterranean Shipping Cruises</p>
        <p>Melody</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,076 passengers; 36,500 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, international and Italian cuisine; entered service as the Atlantic in 1982, refurbished in 1997.  Jan. 13, Feb. 4 and 26 and March 20 -- Eleven-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. Thomas, Antigua, Grenada, St. Lucia, Guadeloupe, Tortola and Nassau. (Sailings on Jan. 24, Feb. 15, March 9 and March 31 call at Montego Bay, Cartagena, San Blas Islands, Gatun Lake, Limon and Key West.) From $995 to $2,195.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Norway</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,032 passengers; 76,049 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the France in 1962, rebuilt and refurbished in 1999.  Year round -- Six-night cruises departing on Saturday from Miami, calling at St. Martin, St. Thomas and Great Stirrup Cay. From $749 to $6,599.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Dream</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,748 passengers; 50,760 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Dreamward in 1992, lengthened in 1998.  Nov. 26 -- Seven-night cruise from San Juan, calling at St. Lucia, Antigua, St. Martin, St. Croix and St. Thomas. From $999 to $5,399.  Dec. 3 -- Five-night voyage from San Juan to Miami, calling at St. Thomas and Great Stirrup Cay. From $759 to $3,759.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Majesty</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,462 passengers; 40,876 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Royal Majesty in 1992, lengthened in 1999.  Nov. 6 to Dec. 8 -- Three-  and four-night cruises from Miami, calling at Key West and Cozumel. (Sailings on Nov. 24, Nov. 27 and Dec. 4 call at Nassau and Great Stirrup Cay.) From $379 to $2,939.  Dec. 8 -- Nine-night voyage from Miami to San Juan, calling at Tortola, Antigua, Martinique, St. Martin, St. Croix and St. Thomas. From $959 to $5,159.  Dec. 24 to Feb. 25 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from San Juan, calling at St. Lucia, Antigua, St. Martin, St. Croix and St. Thomas or Aruba, Curacao, Tortola and St. Thomas. From $949 to $5,499.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Sea</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,518 passengers; 42,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Seaward in 1988, refurbished in 2000.  Nov. 5 to Jan. 7 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Houston, calling at Cancun, Cozumel and Roatan. From $829 to $5,899.  Jan. 10 -- Five-night cruise from Miami, calling at Key West, Nassau and Great Stirrup Cay. From $479 to $2,839.  Jan. 15 to Feb. 26 -- Three-  and four-night cruises departing on Monday and Friday from Miami, calling at Nassau and Great Stirrup Cay and, on four-night cruises, Key West. From $429 to $2,839.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Sky</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,002 passengers; 78,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1999.  Nov. 5 to Feb. 25 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Miami, calling at Grand Cayman, Ocho Rios, Nassau and Great Stirrup Cay or Nassau, San Juan, St. Thomas and Great Stirrup Cay. From $899 to $5,799.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Wind</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,748 passengers; 50,760 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Windward in 1993, lengthened and refurbished in 1998.  Dec. 5 -- Eleven-night cruise from Miami, calling at Great Stirrup Cay, Tortola, Antigua, St. Martin, St. Croix and St. Thomas. From $1,299 to $5,399.  Dec. 16 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from Miami, calling at Grand Cayman, Roatan, Belize and Cozumel. (Dec. 23 sailing calls at Key West instead of Grand Cayman.) From $899 to $5,499.</p>
        <p>Princess Cruises</p>
        <p>Crown Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,590 passengers; 70,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1990, renovated in 2000.  Oct. 31 to April 29 -- Ten-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Cartagena, Gatun Lake, Limon, Grand Cayman and Cozumel, or Ocho Rios, Limon, Gatun Lake, Cartagena and Aruba. From $1,399 to $4,999.</p>
        <p>Dawn Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 77,000 tons, four outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1997.  Nov. 4 to April 14 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from San Juan, calling at Trinidad, Barbados, Antiqua, Tortola and St. Thomas, or St. Thomas, St. Kitts, Martinique, Margarita Island and Curacao. From $699 to $2,849.</p>
        <p>Grand Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,600 passengers; 109,000 tons, five outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; casino, spa, fitness center, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. Thomas, St. Martin and Princess Cays, or Princess Cays, Grand Cayman and Cozumel. From $849 to $3,899.</p>
        <p>Ocean Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 77,000 tons, four outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in February.  Nov. 5 to April 22 -- Seven-night cruises from San Juan, calling at Aruba, La Guaira, Grenada, Dominica, St. Thomas or Barbados, St. Lucia, St. Kitts, St. Martin and St. Thomas. From $699 to $2,849.</p>
        <p>Sea Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 77,000 tons, four outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998.  Nov. 4 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Princess Cays, Ocho Rios, Grand Cayman and Cozumel. From $699 to $2,849.</p>
        <p>Sun Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 77,000 tons, four outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995, refurbished in 1999.  Jan. 28 to Feb. 4 -- Seven-night cruises from San Juan, calling at Aruba, La Guaira, Grenada, Dominica and St. Thomas. From $1,049 to $2,449.</p>
        <p>Radisson Seven Seas Cruises</p>
        <p>Radisson Diamond</p>
        <p>Capacity 350 passengers; 20,295-ton, twin-hull ship, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, retractable marina, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1992.  Nov. 15 -- Five-night cruise from San Juan, calling at Virgin Gorda, St. Thomas, St.-Barthelemy and St. Martin. From $1,448 to $4,346.  Nov. 20 -- Seven-night cruise from San Juan, calling at St. Martin, Barbados, Martinique, St. Kitts and St. Thomas. (Additional sailings on Nov. 27 and Dec. 4, alternating between San Juan and Aruba and calling at St. Thomas, St. Kitts, Martinique, Barbados and Grenada.) From $1,948 to $5,921.  Dec. 11 -- Seven-night voyage from San Juan to Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. Martin, St. Thomas, San Salvador and Nassau. From $1,948 to $5,921.  Jan. 28 -- Four-night cruise from San Juan, calling at Virgin Gorda, St.-Barthelemy and St. Martin. From $1,795 to $3,595.  Feb. 5 -- Seven-night voyage from San Juan to Gatun Yacht Club, calling at Curacao and Cartagena. (Sailing in reverse direction on Feb. 12 calls also at San Blas Islands.) From $2,321 to $5,596.</p>
        <p>Regal Cruises</p>
        <p>Regal Empress</p>
        <p>Capacity 900 passengers; 21,909 tons, outdoor pool, gym, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the Olympia in 1953, refurbished in 1999.  Nov. 1 -- Ten-night cruise from New Orleans, calling at Cozumel, San Andres Island, Gatun Lake and Limon. From $599 to $1,699.  Nov. 16 -- Seven-night cruise from New Orleans, calling at Progreso, Cozumel and Belize. (Additional sailing on Feb. 24 from Port Manatee calls at New Orleans and Key West.) From $399 to $1,559.  Nov. 29 and Dec. 15, 16 and 22 -- Overnight cruises to nowhere from Port Manatee. From $49 to $139.  Nov. 30, Dec. 7 and Feb. 1 -- Three-night cruises from Port Manatee, calling at Key West. (Four-night sailings on Dec. 3, Dec. 29, Jan. 18 and Feb. 4 call at Playa del Carmen, Cancun and Cozumel.) From $289 to $919.  Dec. 10 and 17 and Jan. 2 -- Five-night cruises from Port Manatee, calling at Progreso and Cozumel. (Six-night sailings on Dec. 23 and Feb. 18 call also at Costa Maya.) From $399 to $1,129.  Jan. 7 -- Eleven-night cruise from Port Manatee, calling at Puerto Plata, Tortola, St. Kitts, Nevis, St. Croix, Santo Domingo and Key West. From $979 to $2,079.  Jan. 22 and Feb. 8 -- Ten-night cruises from Port Manatee, calling at Grand Cayman, San Andres Island, Gatun Lake, San Blas Islands and Limon. From $899 to $1,999.</p>
        <p>Royal Caribbean International</p>
        <p>Enchantment of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 74,140 tons, two outdoor pools, sliding glass dome, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1997.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. Martin, St. John, St. Thomas and Nassau or Key West, Cozumel, Grand Cayman and Ocho Rios. From $1,399 to $5,349.</p>
        <p>Explorer of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 3,114 passengers; 142,000 tons, indoor pool and two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entering service this month.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from Miami, calling at Labadee, San Juan and St. Thomas. From $1,949 to $10,949.</p>
        <p>Grandeur of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 74,140 tons, two outdoor pools, sliding glass dome, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1996.  Nov. 4 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from San Juan, calling at Aruba, Curacao, St. Martin and St. Thomas. From $1,399 to $5,349.</p>
        <p>Majesty of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,350 passengers; 73,941 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1992.  Nov. 3 to Feb. 26 -- Three-  and four-night cruises departing on Friday and Monday from Miami, calling at Nassau and Coco Cay and, on four-night cruises, Key West. From $599 to $2,599.</p>
        <p>Monarch of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,350 passengers; 73,941 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1991.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from San Juan, calling at St. Thomas, Antigua, Barbados, St. Lucia and St. Martin. From $1,299 to $5,249.</p>
        <p>Nordic Empress</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,600 passengers; 48,563 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1990.  Nov. 3 to Feb. 26 -- Three-  and four-night cruises departing on Friday and Monday from San Juan, calling at St. Thomas and St. Martin and, on four-night cruises, St. Croix. From $599 to $2,649.</p>
        <p>Sovereign of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,250 passengers; 73,192 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1988.  Nov. 2 to Feb. 26 -- Three-  and four-night cruises departing on Thursday and Sunday from Port Canaveral, calling at Nassau and Coco Cay and, on four-night cruises, Key West. From $599 to $2,399.</p>
        <p>Splendour of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,800 passengers; 69,130 tons, two outdoor pools, retractable glass dome, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1996.  Nov. 6 to Feb. 26 -- Ten-  and eleven-night cruises departing every third Monday and Friday from Miami, calling at Key West, Cozumel, Grand Cayman, Ocho Rios, Aruba and Curacao, omiting Key West on 10-night cruises. From $2,199 to $8,549.</p>
        <p>Voyager of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 3,114 passengers; 142,000 tons, indoor and two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1999.  Nov. 5 to Feb. 26 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Miami, calling at Labadee, Ocho Rios and Cozumel. From $1,999 to $6,999.</p>
        <p>Royal Olympic Cruises</p>
        <p>Olympic Voyager</p>
        <p>Capacity 836 passengers; 25,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service in June.  Dec. 11 -- Eleven-night Orinoco River cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at San Juan, Tortola, Barbados, Puerto Ordaz (Venezuela), Trinidad, Martinique and St. Thomas. From $3,065 to $7,115.  Dec. 23, Jan. 9 and 26 and Feb. 12 -- Sixteen-night Amazon River cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at San Juan, Tortola, Barbados, Boca da Valeria, Manaus, Santarem, Devil's Island, Trinidad, Martinique and St. Thomas. From $4,475 to $9,845.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Seabourn Goddess I</p>
        <p>Capacity 116 passengers; 4,250-ton luxury yacht, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1984, refurbished in 1997; no full sprinkler system.  Nov. 2 and Dec. 9 -- Four-night cruises from Barbados, calling at St. Lucia, Bequia and Mayreau. From $1,990 to $3,040.  Nov. 6 -- Seven-night voyage from Barbados to St. Thomas, calling at Mayreau, St. Lucia, Dominica, Nevis, St. Croix and Virgin Gorda. From $3,510 to $5,440.  Nov. 13 -- Five-night cruise from St. Thomas, calling at Virgin Gorda, Antigua, St. Croix and Jost Van Dyke. (Additional sailings on Jan. 3 and Jan. 8 call at St. John, St. Croix, St.-Barthelemy and Jost Van Dyke.) From $1,748 to $3,920.  Nov. 18 and 25 -- Seven-night cruises from St. Thomas, calling at Virgin Gorda, St. Croix, Antigua, St.-Barthelemy, St. Martin and Jost Van Dyke and in reverse direction on Nov. 25. From $3,510 to $5,440.  Dec. 2 -- Seven-night voyage from St. Thomas to Barbados, calling at St. Croix, St.-Barthelemy, Nevis, Martinique, Mayreau and Carriacou. (Sailing in reverse direction on Dec. 13 calls at Bequia, St. Lucia, Dominica, Les Saintes, Nevis and Jost Van Dyke.) From $3,380 to $5,440.  Dec. 20 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises from St. Thomas, calling variously at St.-Barthelemy, St. Martin, Antigua, Virgin Gorda, St. Croix, Jost Van Dyke and St. John. From $2,587 to $8,640.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Goddess II</p>
        <p>Capacity 116 passengers; 4,260-ton luxury yacht, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1985, refurbished in 1998; no full sprinkler system.  Nov. 10 -- Five-night cruise from Barbados, calling at St. Lucia, Bequia, Grenada and Mayreau. From $2,570 to $3,950.  Nov. 15 -- Seven-night voyage from Barbados to St. Thomas, calling at Mayreau, St. Lucia, Dominica, Guadeloupe, Nevis and Virgin Gorda. (Sailing in reverse direction on Dec. 27 calls at St. Croix, St.-Barthelemy, Nevis, Dominica, Mayreau and Carriacou. From $3,540 to $8,640.  Nov. 22 to Dec. 20 -- Seven-night cruises from St. Thomas, variously calling at Virgin Gorda, St. Croix, St.-Barthelemy, Nevis, Dominica, Grenada, Tobago, St. Lucia, St. Kitts, Les Saintes, Fajardo, St. John, Tortola and the Grenadines. (Additional sailings from Barbados from Jan. 13 to Feb. 24.) From $2,587 to $8,640.  Jan. 3 and Jan. 8 -- Five-night cruises from Barbados, calling at Bequia, St. Lucia, Carriacou and Mayreau. From $1,748 to $4,180.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Legend</p>
        <p>Capacity 208 passengers; 10,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, retractable marina, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service as the Royal Viking Queen in 1992, being refurbished in December; no full sprinkler system.  Nov. 8 and 20 -- Twelve-night cruises from Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. John, Virgin Gorda, St. Croix, St. Thomas, St.-Barthelemy, San Juan, Samana (Dominican Republic) and Key West. From $5,760 to $13,480.  Dec. 16 and 21 -- Sixteen-night cruises from West Palm Beach, calling at St. Croix, Antigua, Barbados, St. Martin, Tortola and San Juan. From $11,290 to $26,420.  Feb. 19 -- Eight-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to San Juan, calling at Samana, Virgin Gorda, St.-Barthelemy, St. Martin and Nevis. From $3,276 to $8,018.  Feb. 27 -- Seven-night cruise from San Juan, calling at Guadeloupe, St.-Barthelemy, Gustavia and Marigot (St. Martin), Virgin Gorda and St. Croix. From $2,853 to $7,032.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Pride</p>
        <p>Capacity 208 passengers; 10,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, retractable marina, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1988, refurbished this year; no full sprinkler system.  Nov. 2 -- Eight-night voyage from St.Thomas to New Orleans, calling at Virgin Gorda, San Juan and Key West. From $2,990 to $7,000.  Nov. 17 -- Twelve-night voyage from New Orleans to San Juan, calling at Cozumel, Calica, Port Antonio, Santo Domingo, Fajardo, St.-Barthelemy and St. Martin.  Nov. 29 -- Seven-night cruise from San Juan, calling at Roseau and Portsmouth, St. Martin, Virgin Gorda, St. Croix and Santo Domingo. (Additional sailing on Dec. 6 calls at Guadeloupe, Antigua, St. Kitts, St.-Barthelemy and Fajardo.) From $2,290 to $7,680.  Dec.13 -- Seven-night voyage from San Juan to Fort Lauderdale, calling at St. Martin, St.-Barthelemy, Virgin Gorda and Fajardo. From $2,290 to $7,680.  Dec. 20 -- Sixteen-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Cozumel, Calica, Port Antonio, Santo Domingo, St. John, St. Croix, St.-Barthelemy, Virgin Gorda and San Juan. From $11,290 to $26,420.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Sun</p>
        <p>Capacity 758 passengers; 38,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service as the Royal Viking Sun in 1988, refurbished in 1999; no full sprinkler system.  Nov. 24 -- Thirteen-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Ocho Rios, Grand Cayman, Belize, Cozumel, New Orleans and Key West. From $3,390 to $14,880.  Dec. 7 -- Fourteen-night cruise from Fort Lauderdale, calling at San Juan, St. Kitts, St. Lucia, Grenada, Barbados, Dominica, St.-Barthelemy, Tortola and St. Croix. From $3,630 to $16,010. Segments available.</p>
        <p>Silversea Cruises</p>
        <p>Silver Wind</p>
        <p>Capacity 296 passengers, all in outside suites; 16,800 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1995.  Nov. 3 -- Seven-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to Barbados, calling at Tortola, Virgin Gorda, St.-Barthelemy and Martinique. From $4,595 to $10,195, including air fare and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>West Indies Cruising</p>
        <p>Valtur Prima</p>
        <p>Capacity 502 passengers; 16,144 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, free wine; entered service as the Stockholm in 1948, rebuilt in 1995.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Friday from Montego Bay, calling at Grand Cayman, Havana, Calica and Isle of Youth (Cuba). From $1,095 to $3,495, including a shore excursion in Havana.</p>
        <p>Trans-Panama Canal</p>
        <p>Celebrity Cruises</p>
        <p>Infinity</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 91,000 tons,indoor pool and two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entering service in February.  Feb. 3 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to San Diego, calling at Key West, Cozumel, Limon, Caldera, Acapulco and Cabo San Lucas. From $1,559 to $10,109.</p>
        <p>Mercury</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,870 passengers; 77,713 tons, indoor and two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1997.  Nov. 12 -- Fourteen-night voyage from San Diego to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Cabo San Lucas, Acapulco, Caldera, Cartagena and Aruba. From $1,699 to $10,279.</p>
        <p>Crystal Cruises</p>
        <p>Crystal Harmony</p>
        <p>Capacity 940 passengers; 49,400 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1990, renovated this year.  Nov.16 -- Ten-night voyage from Caldera to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Aruba, St. Lucia, St.-Barthelemy and St. Thomas. From $2,870 to $15,190.  Nov. 27 -- Ten-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to Acapulco, calling at Playa del Carmen, Cozumel, Grand Cayman, San Blas Islands and Caldera. (Eleven-night voyage in reverse direction on Dec. 8 omits San Blas Islands and ends in New Orleans.) From $2,280 to $15,190.</p>
        <p>Crystal Symphony</p>
        <p>Capacity 940 passengers; 51,044 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995, renovated in 1999.  Nov. 20 -- Ten-night voyage from Barbados to Acapulco, calling at Curacao, Aruba and Caldera. (Additional sailing on Dec. 1 calls at Nassau instead of Curacao.) From $2,655 to $15,190.</p>
        <p>Cunard Line</p>
        <p>Caronia</p>
        <p>Capacity 665 passengers; 24,492 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Vistafjord in 1973, refitted and renamed in 1999.  Jan. 6 -- Eighteen-night voyage between Fort Lauderdale and Valparaiso, calling at Cartagena, Manta (Ecuador), Callao, Arica and Coquimbo (Chile). From $3,265 to $14,578.</p>
        <p>Holland America Line</p>
        <p>Amsterdam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,380 passengers; 61,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entering service this month.  Nov. 9 to Jan. 8 -- Ten-night voyages alternating between Caldera and Fort Lauderdale, calling at San Juan del Sur (Nicaragua), Aruba, St. Thomas and Half Moon Cay. From $1,579 to $11,139.  Jan. 8 to Feb. 27 -- Ten-night voyages alternating between Caldera and Fort Lauderdale, calling at San Juan del Sur (Nicaragua), Golfo Dulce (Panama), Curacao, St. Thomas and Half Moon Cay. From $1,599 to $9,693.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Norwegian Dream</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,748 passengers; 50,760 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Dreamward in 1992, lengthened in 1998.  Dec. 8 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Miami to Valparaiso, calling at Ocho Rios, Montego Bay, Limon, Manta, Callao, Arica and Coquimbo (Chile). From $1,899 to $6,699.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Wind</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,748 passengers; 50,760 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Windward in 1993, lengthened and refurbished in 1998.  Nov. 19 -- Sixteen-night voyage from San Diego to Miami, calling at Puerto Vallarta, Manzanillo, Acapulco, Puntarenas and Great Stirrup Cay. From $1,929 to $6,299.</p>
        <p>Peter Deilmann Cruises</p>
        <p>Deutschland</p>
        <p>Capacity 513 passengers; 22,400 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998, refurbished this year.  Jan. 7 -- Thirteen-night voyage from Montego Bay to Balboa, calling at Playa del Carmen, Cozumel, Puerto Cortes (Honduras), San Andres, Cartagena, El Porvenir and Isla Carti. From $3,519 to $10,791.</p>
        <p>Princess Cruises</p>
        <p>Sun Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 77,000 tons, four outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995, refurbished in 1999.  Nov. 1 to Feb. 28 -- Ten-night cruises between San Juan and Caldera, calling at St. Thomas, Dominica, Barbados, Aruba and Cartagena, except from Jan. 28 to Feb. 4. From $1,399 to $5,299.</p>
        <p>Radisson Seven Seas Cruises</p>
        <p>Radisson Diamond</p>
        <p>Capacity 350 passengers; 20,295-ton, twin-hull ship, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, retractable marina, casino, international cuisine, tips included; dates to 1992.  Dec. 21 -- Twelve-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to Caldera, calling at Key West, Cozumel, Grand Cayman, Montego Bay and Cartagena. From $3,821 to $9,708.  Jan. 2 -- Eight-night voyage from Caldera to San Juan, calling at Gatun Yacht Club, Cartagena and Aruba. From $2,621 to $6,383.  Feb. 19 -- Seven-night voyage between Aruba and Caldera, calling at Curacao, Cartagena and Gatun Yacht Club. (Sailing in reverse direction on Feb. 26.) From $2,321 to $5,596.</p>
        <p>Seven Seas Navigator</p>
        <p>Capacity 490 passengers, all in suites; 30,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1999.  Jan. 7 -- Ten-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to Caldera, calling at Key West, Calica, Cozumel, Grand Cayman, Cartagena and Gatun Yacht Club. (Nine-night sailing in reverse direction on Jan. 17 omits Key West.) From $2,696 to $11,808.</p>
        <p>Royal Caribbean International</p>
        <p>Vision of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,000 passengers; 78,491 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998.  Nov. 4 and Dec. 2 -- Fourteen-night voyages between Fort Lauderdale and San Diego, calling at Aruba, Caldera, Acapulco and Cabo San Lucas. (Sailing in reverse direction on Nov. 18.) From $3,149 to $9,799.</p>
        <p>Royal Olympic Cruises</p>
        <p>Stella Solaris</p>
        <p>Capacity 620 passengers; 18,000 tons, double outdoor pool, spa, continental cuisine; entered service as the Cambodge in 1953, renovated in 1994.  Dec. 22 -- Thirteen-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to San Diego, calling at Grand Cayman, Balboa, Caldera, Acapulco, Mazatlan and Cabo San Lucas. (Sailing in reverse direction on Jan. 5.) From $3,265 to $5,360.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Seabourn Pride</p>
        <p>Capacity 208 passengers; 10,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, retractable marina, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1988, refurbished this year; no full sprinkler system.  Jan. 5 -- Eighteen-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to Valparaiso, calling at Calica, Cozumel, Guayaquil, Callao, Pisco, Arica, Iquique and Coquimbo (Chile). From $7,229 to $17,888.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Sun</p>
        <p>Capacity 758 passengers; 38,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service as the Royal Viking Sun in 1988, refurbished in 1999; no full sprinkler system.  Nov. 7 -- Seventeen-night voyage from San Diego to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Puerto Vallarta, Zihuatanejo, Acapulco, Puerto Quetzal (Guatemala), Caldera, Coiba Island (Panama), Cartagena and Grand Cayman. (Nineteen-night sailing in reversed direction on Dec. 21 calls at Cartagena, Caldera, Puerto Quetzal, Acapulco, Puerto Vallarta, Mazatlan and San Diego and endsin San Francisco.) From $4,980 to $35,080.</p>
        <p>Silversea Cruises</p>
        <p>Silver Wind</p>
        <p>Capacity 296 passengers, all in outside suites; 16,800 tons, enclosed outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1995.  Nov. 10 -- Twelve-night voyage from Barbados to Caldera, calling at Canouan (Grenadines), Tobago, Curacao, Aruba, Cartagena and Limon. From $8,545 to $19,145, including air fare and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Pacific Coast and Hawaii</p>
        <p>American Hawaii Cruises</p>
        <p>Independence</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,066 passengers; 20,221 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, Hawaiian cuisine; entered service in 1951, refurbished in 1998.  Starting Nov. 11 -- Seven-night inter-Hawaiian Islands cruises departing on Saturday from Kahului (Maui), calling at Hilo and Kona (Hawaii), Honolulu (Oahu) and Nawiliwili Bay (Kauai). From $1,349 to $3,549.</p>
        <p>Carnival Cruise Lines</p>
        <p>Elation</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,052 passengers; 70,367 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises departing on Sunday from Los Angeles, calling at Puerto Vallarta, Mazatlan and Cabo San Lucas. From $1,139 to $2,689.</p>
        <p>Holiday</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,452 passengers; 46,052 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, casino, international cuisine, choice restaurants; entered service in 1985, refurbished in 1998.  Year round -- Three-  and four-night cruises departing on Friday and Monday from Los Angeles, calling at Ensenada and, on four-night cruises, Santa Catalina Island. From $615 to $1,385.</p>
        <p>Celebrity Cruises</p>
        <p>Infinity</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 91,000 tons, indoor pool and two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entering service in February.  Feb. 17 -- Eleven-night voyage from Ensenada to Honolulu, calling at Kailua, Kona and Hilo (Hawaii), Nawiliwili Bay (Kauai) and Lahaina (Maui). (Ten-night sailing in reverse direction on Feb. 28.) From $1,399 to $8,299.</p>
        <p>Crystal Cruises</p>
        <p>Crystal Symphony</p>
        <p>Capacity 940 passengers; 51,044 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995, renovated in 1999.  Jan. 5 -- Six-night cruise from Los Angeles, calling at Puerto Vallarta and Cabo San Lucas. From $2,455 to $10,115.</p>
        <p>Holland America Line</p>
        <p>Statendam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,266 passengers; 55,451 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1993, refurbished this year.  Dec. 18 -- Fifteen-night cruise from San Diego, calling at Hilo, Honolulu, Na Pali Coast and Nawiliwili Bay (Kauai), Maui, Kona and Ensenada. (Additional sailings on Jan. 12 and Feb. 16.) From $2,859 to $18,660.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Norwegian Wind</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,748 passengers; 50,760 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Windward in 1993, lengthened and refurbished in 1998.  Nov. 9 -- Ten-night cruise from San Diego, calling at Ensenada, Cabo San Lucas, Acapulco, Manzanillo and Puerto Vallarta. From $1,269 to $3,919.</p>
        <p>Royal Caribbean International</p>
        <p>Viking Serenade</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,512 passengers; 40,132 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the Scandinavia in 1981, refurbished in 1997.  Year round -- Three-  and four-night cruises departing on Monday and Friday from Los Angeles, calling at Ensenada and, on four-night cruises, San Diego, Santa Catalina Island and Ensenada. From $499 to $1,899.</p>
        <p>Vision of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,000 passengers; 78,491 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998.  Jan. 6 to Feb. 7 -- Ten-  and eleven-night cruises departing on Wednesday and Saturday from San Diego, calling at Cabo San Lucas, Mazatlan, Puerto Vallarta, Acapulco and Manzanilla and, on 11-night cruises, Zihuatanejo. From $2,099 to $8,229.  Feb. 17 -- Eleven-night voyage from Ensenada to  Honolulu, calling at Kailua, Kona and Hilo  (Hawaii), Nawiliwili Bay (Kauai) and Lahaina (Maui).  (Ten-night sailing in reverse direction on Feb. 28.)  From $2,199 to $8,299.</p>
        <p>Silversea Cruises</p>
        <p>Silver Wind</p>
        <p>Capacity 296 passengers, all in outside suites; 16,800 tons, enclosed outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1995.  Dec. 6 -- Twelve-night voyage from Valparaiso to Caldera, calling at Arica, Callao and Guayaquil. From $8,145 to $18,045, including air fare and hotel stay.  Dec. 18 -- Sixteen-night voyage from Caldera to Los Angeles, calling at Golfito, Puerto Quetzal, Acapulco, Puerto Vallarta, Cabo San Lucas and San Diego. From $12,645 to $28,745, including partial Panama Canal transit, air fare and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>United States Lines</p>
        <p>Patriot</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,212 passengers; 33,930 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, American and Hawaiian cuisine; entered service as the Niew Amsterdam in 1983, being refurbished and renamed in December.  Starting Dec. 9 -- Seven-night interisland Hawaiian cruises from Honolulu, calling at Nawiliwili Bay (Kauai), Kahului (Maui), Hilo and Kona (Hawaii). From $1,599 to $4,249.</p>
        <p>Trans-Atlantic</p>
        <p>Celebrity Cruises</p>
        <p>Millennium</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,950 passengers; 91,000 tons (first gas-turbine/electric cruise ship), two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in June.  Nov. 3 -- Twelve-night crossing from Genoa to New York, calling at Livorno, Villefranche and Gibraltar. From $1,299 to $10,899.</p>
        <p>Costa Cruises</p>
        <p>Costa Atlantica</p>
        <p>Capacity 2,112 passengers; 84,000 tons, three outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in July.  Nov. 3 -- Fourteen-night crossing from Genoa to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Barcelona, Tenerife, Barbados, Martinique, St. Martin and Nassau. From $2,500 to $5,650, including air fare from New York.</p>
        <p>Costa Victoria</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,928 passengers; 76,000 tons, indoor and two outdoor pools, spa, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1996.  Nov. 17 -- Sixteen-night crossing from Genoa to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Malaga, Casablanca, Madeira, Guadeloupe, Antigua, St. Martin, Tortola and Freeport. From $2,350 to $5,500, including air fare.</p>
        <p>Crystal Cruises</p>
        <p>Crystal Symphony</p>
        <p>Capacity 940 passengers; 51,044 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995, renovated in 1999.  Nov. 10 -- Nine-night crossing from Lisbon to Barbados, calling at Cadiz and the Canary Islands. From $2,870 to $13,810.</p>
        <p>Cunard Line</p>
        <p>Caronia</p>
        <p>Capacity 665 passengers; 24,492 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Vistafjord in 1973, refitted and renamed in 1999.  Nov. 9 -- Eighteen-night crossing from Southampton to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Madeira, Barbados, Dominica, Antigua, St. Martin and St. Thomas. From $3,940 to $15,820.</p>
        <p>Queen Elizabeth 2</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,778 passengers; 70,327 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1969, refitted in 1999.  Dec. 14 -- Six-night crossing from Southampton to New York. From $1,700 to $16,600, including one-way air fare.</p>
        <p>EuroCruises</p>
        <p>Black Watch</p>
        <p>Capacity 761 passengers; 28,492 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the Royal Viking Star in 1972, refurbished this year.  Dec. 19 Sixteen-night crossing from Barbados to Southampton, calling at Roseau, Basseterre, St. John's, Road Town and Madeira. From $3,460 to $9,220.  Jan. 4 -- Eighteen-night crossing from Southampton to Rio de Janeiro, calling at Lisbon, Tenerife, Dakar, Recife and Salvador. From $3,025 to $8,065.  Feb. 18 -- Twenty-four-night Panama Canal transit and Atlantic Ocean crossing from Callao to Southampton, calling at Manta, San Blas Islands, Cartagena, Ocho Rios, Santiago de Cuba, Grand Turk, Hamilton and Ponta Delgada. From $4,320 to $11,520.</p>
        <p>First European Cruises</p>
        <p>Mistral</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,200 passengers; 47,900 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1999.  Dec. 7 -- Fifteen-night crossing from Genoa to Guadeloupe, calling at Almeria, Malaga, Funchal, Barbados, Grenada, St. Lucia and Antigua. From $1,770 to $3,470.</p>
        <p>Holland America Line</p>
        <p>Noordam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,494 passengers; 33,930 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1984, renovated this year; no full sprinkler system.  Nov. 28 -- Ten-night crossing from Lisbon to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Ponta Delgada, Horta and Half Moon Cay. From $969 to $3,345.</p>
        <p>Rotterdam VI</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,316 passengers; 59,652 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1997, refurbished this year.  Nov. 16 -- Twenty-six-night crossing from Piraeus to Baltimore, calling at Kusadasi, Istanbul, Haifa, Ashdod, Alexandria, Valletta, Majorca, Almeria, Gibraltar, Madeira, St. Thomas, Half Moon Cay and Fort Lauderdale. From $3,199 to $13,238.</p>
        <p>Mediterranean Shipping Cruises</p>
        <p>Melody</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,076 passengers; 36,500 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, international and Italian cuisine; entered service as the Atlantic in 1982, refurbished in 1997.  Dec. 27 -- Seventeen-night crossing from Genoa to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Gibraltar, Madeira, Martinique, Antigua, Tortola, San Juan and Key West. From $1,495 to $3,595.</p>
        <p>Rhapsody</p>
        <p>Capacity, 750 passengers; 17,500 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, casino, international and Italian cuisine; entered service as the Cunard Princess in 1976, refurbished in 1998.  Nov. 15 -- Eighteen-night crossing from Genoa to Rio de Janeiro, calling at Almeria, Malaga, Casablanca, Tenerife, Dakar, Maceio, Salvador, Ilheus and Buzios. From $1,248 to $2,760.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Norwegian Dream</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,748 passengers; 50,760 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Dreamward in 1992, lengthened in 1998.  Nov. 14 -- Twelve-night crossing from Barcelona to San Juan, calling at Cadiz, Madeira and St. Thomas. From $1,899 to $6,299.</p>
        <p>Orient Lines</p>
        <p>Marco Polo</p>
        <p>Capacity 848 passengers; 22,080 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Alexandr Pushkin in 1965, rebuilt in 1993.  Nov. 15 -- Fourteen-night crossing from Barcelona to Barbados, calling at Malaga, Funchal, Cape Verde Islands and Martinique. From $4,490 to $8,445, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Peter Deilmann Cruises</p>
        <p>Deutschland</p>
        <p>Capacity 513 passengers; 22,400 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998, refurbished this year.  Dec. 22 -- Sixteen-night crossing from Dakar to Montego Bay, calling at Cape Verde Islands, Tobago, Trinidad, Barbados, Guadaloupe, St. Thomas, San Juan and Ocho Rios. From $5,390 to $16,240.</p>
        <p>Princess Cruises</p>
        <p>Royal Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,200 passengers, all in outside cabins; 45,000 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1984, refurbished in 1999.  Nov. 5 -- Twenty-night crossing from Civitavecchia to Buenos Aires, calling at Livorno, Cannes, Barcelona, Casablanca, Dakar, Recife, Rio de Janeiro and Montevideo. From $3,775 to $9,910.</p>
        <p>Royal Olympic Cruises</p>
        <p>Olympic Voyager</p>
        <p>Capacity 836 passengers; 25,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service in June.  Nov. 25 -- Eleven-night crossing from Piraeus to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Messina, Civitavecchia, Villefranche, Barcelona and Madeira. From $2,465 to $6,215.</p>
        <p>Stella Solaris</p>
        <p>Capacity 620 passengers; 18,000 tons, double outdoor pool, spa, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Cambodge in 1953, renovated in 1994.  Dec. 1 -- Twenty-night crossing from Piraeus to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Naples, Capri, Civitavecchia, Villefranche, Cartagena, Tangier, Lisbon, Madeira and San Juan. From $3,245 to $7,745.</p>
        <p>Far Pacific</p>
        <p>Orient Lines</p>
        <p>Crown Odyssey</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,036 passengers; 34,250 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998, renovated this year.  Nov. 27 -- Eleven-night voyage from Bombay to Singapore, calling at Cochin, Colombo, Phuket, Penang and Kuala Lumpur. From $5,090 to $11,195, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.  Dec. 20 -- Nine-night voyage from Hong Kong to Singapore, calling at Halong Bay, Da Nang and Ho Chi Minh City. From $3,890 to $8,390, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.  Jan. 4 -- Eighteen-night voyage from Singapore to Sydney, calling at Semarang, Bali, Darwin, Cairns, Hamilton Island and Brisbane. From $5,645 to $14,395, including air fare from New York and hotel stay. Segments available.  Feb. 3 -- Nine-night voyage from Sydney to Auckland, calling at Melbourne, Milford Sound, Picton and Tauranga. From $3,885 to $8,140, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.  Feb. 13 -- Nine-night cruise from Auckland, calling at Tauranga, Picton, Marlborough and Milford, Doubtful and Dusky Sounds, Dunedin, Christchurch and Wellington. From $3,640 to $7,840, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.  Feb. 22 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Auckland to Papeete, calling at Bay of Islands, Suva and Yasawa (Fiji), Apia (Western Samoa), Pago Pago (American Samoa), Bora Bora and Moorea (French Polynesia). From $4,440 to $11,840, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Princess Cruises</p>
        <p>Regal Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,590 passengers; 70,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1991, renovated this year.  Nov. 3 -- Nineteen-night voyage from Laem Chabang (for Bangkok) to Sydney, calling at Kuantan, Singapore, Semarang, Bali, Perth, Albany, Melbourne and Tasmania. From $3,470 to $7,420.  Nov. 22 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Sydney to Auckland, calling at Melbourne, Hobart, Dunedin, Christchurch, Wellington, Tauranga and Bay of Islands. (Additional sailings on Dec. 6, Feb. 1 and Feb. 25.) From $2,695 to $6,645.  Dec. 20 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Sydney to Papeete, calling at Bay of Islands, Auckland, Tauranga, Fiji, Western Samoa, Bora Bora and Moorea. From $2,890 to $6,840.  Jan. 3 -- Twelve-night voyage from Papeete to Oahu, calling at Moorea, Bora Bora, Christmas Island, Maui, Kauai and Hawaii. (Additional voyage in reverse direction on Jan. 15.) From $2,195 to $10,172.  Jan. 27 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Papeete to Sydney, calling at Moorea, Bora Bora, Western Samoa, Fiji, Auckland and Bay of Islands. From $2,695 to $6,645.  Feb. 25 -- Twenty-eight-night voyage from Sydney to Singapore, calling at Melbourne, Hobart, Dunedin, Christchurch, Wellington, Tauranga, Bay of Islands, Great Barrier Reef, Cairns, Darwin, Bali and Kuala Lumpur. From $4,640 to $10,443.</p>
        <p>Radisson Seven Seas Cruises</p>
        <p>Paul Gauguin</p>
        <p>Capacity 320 passengers; 18,800 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, retractable marina, international cuisine, open seating, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service in 1997.  Year round -- Seven-night Tahitian cruises departing on Saturday from Papeete, calling at Raiatea, Tahaa, Bora Bora and Moorea. From $3,095 to $10,595.</p>
        <p>Renaissance Cruises</p>
        <p>R2</p>
        <p>Capacity 684 passengers; 30,200 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, open seating, choice of restaurants, no smoking aboard; entered service in 1998.  Dec. 7 to Feb. 20 -- Fifteen-night voyages between Hong Kong and Singapore, calling at Guangzhou, Da Nang, Ho Chi Minh City and Bangkok. From $1,999 to $5,399.</p>
        <p>R3, R4</p>
        <p>Capacity 684 passengers (18 and older only); 30,200 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, open seating, choice of restaurants, no smoking aboard; entered service in 1999.  Year round -- Ten-night cruises from Papeete, calling at Moorea, Huahine, Raiatea and Bora Bora. From $1,499 to $3,999.</p>
        <p>Royal Caribbean International</p>
        <p>Legend of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,800 passengers; 69,130 tons, indoor pool and outdoor pool with retractable dome, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995.  Dec. 16 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Bombay to Singapore, calling at Goa, Cochin, Phuket, Penang and Port Kelang. From $2,299 to $11,299.  Dec. 30 -- Fourteen-night cruise from Singapore, calling at Phuket, Penang, Port Kelang, Ko Samui, Laem Chabang (for Bangkok) and Ho Chi Minh City. From $2,999 to $11,999.  Jan. 13 -- Sixteen-night voyage from Singapore to Sydney, calling at Bali, Darwin, Cairns and Brisbane. (Sailing in reverse direction on Feb. 26.) From $2,899 to $11,899.  Jan. 29 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Sydney to Auckland, calling at Melbourne, Hobart, Fjordland National Park, Milford Sound, Doubtful and Dusky Sounds, Port Chalmers, Lyttelton Harbour, Wellington, Napier and Maunganui. (Sailing in reverse direction on Feb. 12.) From $2,699 to $11,599.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Seabourn Spirit</p>
        <p>Capacity 208 passengers; 10,000 tons, outdoor pool, retractable marina, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service in 1989, refurbished this year; no full sprinkler system.  Dec. 7 -- Twelve-night voyage from Bangkok to Singapore, calling at Langkawi, Phuket, Penang, Port Kelang and Malacca. From $4,530 to $8,420.  Dec. 19 -- Sixteen-night voyage from Singapore to Hong Kong, calling at Angthong Marine Park (Bangkok), Ho Chi Minh City, Nha Trang, Danang and Hanoi. (Fourteen-night voyage in reverse direction on Jan. 28 calls at Haiphong, Danang, Ho Chi Minh City and Ko Kood.) From $7,281 to $27,580.  Jan. 4 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Hong Kong to Bangkok, calling at Haiphong, Danang, Ho Chi Minh City and Ko Kood. (Fifteen-night voyage in reverse direction on Jan. 13 omits Ko Kood.) From $6,861 to $20,680.  Feb. 11 -- Fourteen-night cruise from Singapore, calling at Langkawi, Yangon (formerly Rangoon), Phuket and Ko Hong (Thailand), Penang, Port Kelang and Malacca. From $5,531 to $13,700.</p>
        <p>Silversea Cruises</p>
        <p>Silver Cloud</p>
        <p>Capacity 296 passengers; 16,800 tons, enclosed outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service in 1994.  Nov. 24 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Singapore to Hong Kong, calling at Ho Chi Minh City and Nha Trang (Vietnam), Muara (Brunei), Kota Kinabalu, Ramblon Island and Manila. (Voyage in reverse direction on Dec. 8 calls at Haiphong, Da Nang, Ho Chi Minh City, Bangkok and Ko Samui in Thailand). From $9,595 to $22,095, including air fare and hotel stay.  Dec. 22 -- Sixteen-night voyage from Singapore to Sydney, calling at Semarang, Broome, Freemantle, Adelaide and Melbourne. From $13,295 to $29,695, including air fare and hotel stay.  Jan. 7 and Feb. 16 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Sydney to Auckland, calling at Melbourne, Hobart, Dunedin, Lyttelton Harbour and Tauranga. (Voyage in reverse direction on Feb. 2 calls at Adelaide instead of Tauranga.) From $9,595 to $22,195, including air fare and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Star Cruises</p>
        <p>Superstar Gemini</p>
        <p>Capacity 788 passengers; 20,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service as the Crown Jewel in 1992, refurbished in 1999.  Year round -- Seven-night cruises from Singapore, calling at Port Dickson, Penang, Phuket, Langkawi, Port Kelang and Malacca. From $1,350 to $1,990.</p>
        <p>Superstar Leo</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,960 passengers; 76,800 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service in 1998.  Year round -- Three-  and five-night cruises from Hong Kong, calling at Sanya, Halong Bay and Haikou. From $580 to $1,780.</p>
        <p>Superstar Virgo</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,960 passengers; 76,800 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered in 1999.  Year round -- Three-  and five-night cruises from Singapore, calling at Phuket, Langkawi, Port Dickson and Port Kelang. From $580 to $1,780.</p>
        <p>Swan Hellenic</p>
        <p>Minerva</p>
        <p>Capacity 300 passengers; 12,500 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service in 1996.  Jan. 2 -- Thirteen-night voyage from Calcutta to Bangkok, calling at Port Blair, Phuket, Penang and Singapore. From $5,184 to $9,900, including air fare from London to Calcutta and return from Bangkok and shore excursions.  Jan. 15 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Bangkok to Hong Kong, calling at Kompong Som, Ho Chi Minh City, Nha Trang, Da Nang and Halong Bay. From $5,877 to $11,230, including air fare from London to Bangkok and return from Hong Kong and shore excursions.  Jan. 29 -- Sixteen-night voyage from Hong Kong to Bali, calling at Manila, Cebu, Kota Kinabalu, Sandakan, Pare and Komodo. From $5,893 to $11,262, including air fare from London to Hong Kong and return from Bali.</p>
        <p>European Waters And the Mediterranean</p>
        <p>Costa Cruises</p>
        <p>Costa Allegra</p>
        <p>Capacity 820 passengers; 28,500 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service in 1992.  Nov. 1 -- Ten-night cuise from Genoa, calling at Naples, Catania, Alexandria, Port Said, Ashdod, Limassol (Cyprus), Rhodes and Cytheria. From $2,840 to $5,840, including air fare.</p>
        <p>Costa Classica</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,308 passengers; 53,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service in 1991.  Nov. 6 -- Seven-night cruise from Venice, calling at Bari, Katakolon, Santorini, Mykonos, Rhodes and Dubrovnik. From $2,280 to $4,630, including air fare.  Nov. 13 -- Five-night voyage from Venice to Genoa, calling at Bari, Corfu, Malta and Naples. From $1,885 to $4,135, including air fare.</p>
        <p>Costa Riviera</p>
        <p>Capacity 974 passengers; 30,400 tons, outdoor pool, spa, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Guglielmo Marconi in 1963, refitted as Riviera in 1983, refurbished in 1996.  Dec. 17 -- Ten-night cruise from Savona, calling at Naples, Catania, Alexandria, Port Said, Ashdod, Limassol and Rhodes. (Eleven-night sailing on Feb. 9 calls also at Githion and Malta.) From $1,749 to $4,099, including air fare.  Dec. 27 -- Eleven-night cruise from Savona, calling at Barcelona, Casablanca, Canary Islands, Madeira, Malaga and Almeira. (Additional sailings on Jan. 18, Feb. 20 and March 15 call also at Agadir.) From $1,749 to $4,099, including air fare.</p>
        <p>Costa Victoria</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,928 passengers; 76,000 tons, indoor pool and two outdoor pools, spa, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1996.  Nov. 5 -- Seven-night cruise from Genoa, calling at Naples, Palermo, Tunis, Majorca and Barcelona. (Five-night cruise on Nov. 12 calls at Naples, Tunis, Majorca and Barcelona.) From $1,885 to $4,150, including air fare.</p>
        <p>Cunard</p>
        <p>Queen Elizabeth 2</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,778 passengers; 70,327 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1969, refitted in 1999.  Nov. 6 -- Nine-night cruise from Southampton, calling at the Canary Islands and Agadir. From $1,500 to $14,920.  Nov. 15 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Southampton to Cape Town, calling at Madeira, Cape Verde Islands and St. Helena. From $2,170 to $21,910.  Nov. 30 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Cape Town to Southampton, calling at St. Helena, Dakar, the Canary Islands and Lisbon. From $2,110 to $21,230.</p>
        <p>EuroCruises</p>
        <p>Black Prince</p>
        <p>Capacity 412 passengers; 11,209 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, retractable marina, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1966, refurbished in 1999.  Nov. 6 -- Fourteen-night cruise from Southampton, calling at Cadiz, Casablanca, the Canary Islands, Funchal and Villagarcia. From $2,100 to $4,200.  Nov. 20 -- Fourteen-night cruise from Southampton, calling at Funchal, the Canary Islands, Gibraltar and Lisbon. From $2,020 to $4,035.  Dec. 4 -- Thirteen-night cruise from Southampton, calling at Funchal, Canary Islands, Ceuta, Gibraltar and Vigo. (Additional sailing on Jan. 17 calls at Vigo, Funchal, the Canary Islands, Agadir and Lisbon.) From $1,635 to $3,900.  Dec. 20 -- Sixteen-night cruise from Southampton, calling at Lisbon, Tangier, the Canary Islands, Funchal and Porto Santo. From $2,880 to $5,760.</p>
        <p>First European Cruises</p>
        <p>Azur</p>
        <p>Capacity 720 passengers; 15,000 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Eagle in 1971, refurbished in 1996.  Nov. 7, 18 and 29 -- Eleven-night cruises from Savona, calling at Naples, Sitia (Crete), Alexandria, Port Said, Haifa, Piraeus and Civitavecchia. (Sailing on Nov. 29 ends in Genoa, and sailing on Dec. 27 calls also at Ashdod.) From $2,310 to $4,700, including air fare from New York, Boston and Philadelphia.  Dec. 21 -- Six-night cruise from Genoa, calling at Naples, Malta, Tunis, Palermo and Civitavecchia. From $2,030 to $2,930, including air fare from New York, Boston and Philadelphia.  Jan. 7 -- Ten-night voyage from Genoa to Venice, calling at Katakolon, Alexandria, Port Said, Ashdod, Limassol, Rhodes and Piraeus. From $680 to $1,680.  Jan. 17 and 27 and Feb. 6 and 26 -- Ten-night cruises from Venice, calling at Katakolon, Port Said, Ashdod, Limassol, Rhodes and Piraeus. (Additional sailing on Feb. 16 calls at Catania, Malta, Sousse, Tunis and Dubrovnik and returns to Venice for two-night stay aboard ship for Carnival.) From $640 to $1,960.</p>
        <p>Flamenco</p>
        <p>Capacity 800 passengers; 17,270 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Sun Princess in 1972, refitted in 1997.  Nov. 3, 14, 25 and Dec. 27 -- Eleven-night cruises from Genoa, calling at Almeria, Malaga, Funchal, the Canary Islands, Safi, Casablanca, Tangier, Alicante and Marseille. From $2,310 to $4,590, including air fare from New York, Boston and Philadelphia.  Jan. 7 to Feb. 20 -- Eleven-night cruises from Savona, calling at Almeria, Malaga, Madeira, the Canary Islands, Safi, Casablanca, Alicante and Marseille. From $750 to $2,730.</p>
        <p>Mistral</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,200 passengers; 47,900 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1999.  Nov. 4 -- Ten-night voyage from Venice to Genoa, calling at Iraklion, Limassol, Tartus, Beirut, Rhodes, Piraeus and Civitavecchia. From $2,860 to $4,370, including air fare from New York, Boston and Philadelphia,  Nov. 14 and 25 -- Eleven-night cruise from Genoa, calling at Naples, Santorini, Limassol, Ashdod, Port Said, Alexandria, Piraeus and Civitavecchia. From $2,550 to $4,230, including air fare from New York, Boston and Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Holland America Line</p>
        <p>Noordam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,494 passengers; 33,930 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1984, renovated this year; no full sprinkler system.  Nov. 8 -- Ten-night voyage from Istanbul to Civitavecchia, calling at Alexandria, Ashdod, Haifa, Limassol, Rhotes and Messina. From $1,199 to $4,384.  Nov. 18 -- Ten-night voyage from Civitavecchia to Lisbon, calling at Livorno, Monte Carlo, Ajaccio, Majorca, Casablanca and Cadiz. From $1,199 to $4,384.</p>
        <p>Rotterdam VI</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,316 passengers; 59,652 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1997, refurbished this year.  Nov. 4 -- Twelve-night voyage from Civitavecchia to Piraeus, calling at Valletta, Katakolon, Alexandria, Ashdod, Haifa, Limassol, Rhodes and Kusadasi. From $2,199 to $8,899.</p>
        <p>Mediterranean Shipping Cruises</p>
        <p>Melody</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,076 passengers; 36,500 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, international and Italian cuisine; entered service as the Atlantic in 1982, refurbished in 1997.  Nov. 2 -- Eleven-night cruise from Genoa, calling at Salerno, Port Said, Beirut, Tartus, Iraklion and Capri. (Additional sailing on Nov. 13 calls at Malaga, Madeira, Tenerife, Casablanca, Cadiz and Baracelona.) From $1,299 to $2,799.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Norwegian Dream</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,748 passengers; 50,760 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restrurants; entered service as the Dreamward in 1992, lengthened in 1998.  Nov. 4 -- Nine-night voyage from Istanbul to Barcelona, calling at Piraeus, Messina, Naples, Civitavecchia, Livorno and Cannes. From $1,899 to $6,799.</p>
        <p>Princess Cruises</p>
        <p>Pacific Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 640 passengers; 20,000 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Sea Venture in 1971, refurbished in 1999; no full sprinkler system.  Nov.26 -- Twelve-night voyage from Civitavecchia to Istanbul, calling at Sorrento, Alexandria, Port Said, Haifa, Ashdod, Piraeus and Kusadasi. From $2,190 to $4,920.  Dec. 8 -- Twelve-night voyage from Istanbul to Piraeus, calling at Kusadasi, Santorini, Rhodes, Haifa, Ashdod, Port Said and Alexandria. (Fourteen-night voyage in reverse direction on Dec. 20 also calls at Iraklion and Kusadasi.) From $2,090 to $5,820.</p>
        <p>Renaissance Cruises</p>
        <p>R1, R5</p>
        <p>Capacity 684 and 698 passengers, respectively; 30,200 tons, outdoor pool, spa, casino, open seating, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, no smoking aboard; entered service in 1998 and February this year, respectively.  Year round -- Fifteen-night voyages between Piraeus and Istanbul, calling at Alexandria, Ashdod, Haifa, Limassol, Rhodes, Iraklion and Kusadasi. From $1,799 to $4,799.</p>
        <p>R6</p>
        <p>Capacity 698 passengers; 30,200 tons, outdoor pool, spa, casino, international cuisine, open seating, choice of restaurants, no smoking aboard; entered service in June.  November to March -- Fifteen-night voyages between Barcelona and Lisbon, calling at Nice, Marseille, Minorca, La Goulette (Tunisia), Cagliari, Majorca, Valencia, Alicante, Malaga, Tangier, Gibraltar, Casablanca and Cadiz. From $2,999 to $7,499.</p>
        <p>R7</p>
        <p>Capacity 698 passengers; 30,200 tons, outdoor pool, spa, casino, international cuisine, open seating, choice of restaurants, no smoking aboard; entering service this month.  December to March -- Series of 10-night voyages from Istanbul, Cairo, Civitavecchia and Piraeus, calling at Kusadasi, Rhodes, Ashdod, Haifa and Alexandria or Naples, Palermo, Cagliari, Tunis and Malta or Rhodes, Katakolon, Messina and Palermo. From $1,999 to $4,099, including air fare.</p>
        <p>Royal Caribbean International</p>
        <p>Legend of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,800 passengers; 69,130 tons, indoor pool and outdoor pool with retractable dome, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995.  Nov. 8 -- Ten-night voyage from Barcelona to Piraeus, calling at Livorno, Civitavechia, Naples, Iraklion, Santorini, Rhodes and Kusadasi. From $2,799 to $11,499.</p>
        <p>Royal Olympic Cruises</p>
        <p>Olympic Voyager</p>
        <p>Capacity 836 passengers; 25,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service in June.  Nov. 4, 11 and 18 -- Six-night cruises from Piraeus, calling at Santorini, Alexandria, Ashdod, Rhodes, Istanbul, Kusadasi and Mykonos. From $2,150 to $4,950.</p>
        <p>World Renaissance</p>
        <p>Capacity 455 passengers; 12,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Renaissance in 1966, renovated in 1996.  Nov. 3 and 10 -- Two-night cruises from Piraeus, calling at Mykonos, Rhodes, Patmos and Kusadasi. (Three-night cruise on Nov. 6 calls at also at Iraklion and Santorini.) From $635 to $2,195.</p>
        <p>South America</p>
        <p>Celebrity Cruises</p>
        <p>Mercury</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,870 passengers; 77,713 tons, indoor pool and two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1997.  Dec. 10 -- Twelve-night voyage from La Guaira to Rio de Janeiro, calling at Devil's Island, cruising the Amazon River, Fortaleza and Recife. From $1,799 to $10,129.  Dec. 22 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Rio de Janeiro to Valparaiso, calling at Santos, Buenos Aires, Puerto Madryn, Cape Horn, Ushuaia, Strait of Magellan, Chilean Fjords and Puerto Montt. From $2,199 to $10,529.  Jan. 5 and 31 -- Twelve-night voyages from Valparaiso to Buenos Aires, calling at Puerto Montt, Strait of Magellan, Punta Arenas, Ushuaia, Cape Horn, Puerto Madryn and Montevideo. (Fourteen-night voyage in reverse direction on Jan. 17 also calls at Port Stanley and Chilean Fjords.) From $1,799 to $10,329.  Feb. 12 -- Ten-night cruise from Buenos Aires, calling at Rio de Janeiro, Santos, Florianapolis and Montevideo. From $1,449 to $9,779.  Feb. 22 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Buenos Aires to La Guaira, calling at Rio de Janeiro, Fortaleza, cruising the Amazon River and Devil's Island. From $2,999 to $11,329, including two-night stay aboard ship for Carnival in Rio.</p>
        <p>Crystal Cruises</p>
        <p>Crystal Harmony</p>
        <p>Capacity 940 passengers; 49,400 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1990, renovated this year.  Jan. 13 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to Buenos Aires, calling at Barbados, Fortaleza, Salvador and Rio de Janeiro. From $3,360 to $18,065.  Jan. 29 -- Eleven-night voyage from Buenos Aires to Valparaiso, calling at Montevideo, Puerto Madryn, Punta Arenas and Puerto Montt. (Twelve-night voyage in reverse direction on Feb. 10.) From $3,525 to $1,545.  Feb. 23 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Buenos Aires to Manaus, calling at Rio de Janeiro, Fortaleza, Santarem and Parintins. From $4,115 to $20,240.</p>
        <p>Cunard Line</p>
        <p>Caronia</p>
        <p>Capacity 665 passengers; 24,492 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Vistafjord in 1973, refitted and renamed in 1999.  Jan. 24 -- Twenty-three-night Chilean Fjord voyage from Valparaiso to Rio de Janeiro, calling at Puerto Montt, Castro, Puerto Chacabuco, Punta Arenas, Ushuaia, Port Stanley, Buenos Aires and Montevideo. (Voyage in reverse direction on Feb. 16.) From $4,978 to $22,642.</p>
        <p>EuroCruises</p>
        <p>Switzerland</p>
        <p>Capacity 440 passengers; 15,739 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, international cuisine; entered service as the Port Sydney in 1955, refurbished in 1997.  Nov. 15 to Feb. 28 -- Seventeen-  and 18-night cruises between Buenos Aires and Valparaiso, calling at Puerto Madryn, Cape Horn, Beagle Channel, Ushuaia, Tierra del Fuego, Punta Arenas, Chilean Fjords and Puerto Montt and, on 18-night cruises, Montevideo. From $2,200 to $7,575.</p>
        <p>Black Watch</p>
        <p>Capacity 761 passengers; 28,492 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, international, cuisine; entered service as the Royal Viking Star in 1972, refurbished this year.  Jan. 22 -- Twenty-seven-night voyage from Rio de Janeiro to Callao, calling at Buenos Aires, Port Stanley, Cape Horn, Ushuaia, Beagle Channel, Punta Arenas, Chilean Fjords, Puerto Montt, Valparaiso and Arica. From $5,185 to $13,825.</p>
        <p>Holland America Line</p>
        <p>Ryndam</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,266 passengers; 55,451 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service 1994, refurbished this year.  Jan. 6 and Feb. 9 -- Seventeen-night voyages from Fort Lauderdale to Valparaiso, calling at Grand Cayman, Limon, Panama Canal, Guayaquil, Salaverry, Callao, San Martin, Arica and Coquimbo. From $2,659 to $12,020.  Jan. 23 and Feb. 26 -- Seventeen-night voyages from Valparaiso to Rio de Janeiro, calling at Puerto Montt, Chilean Fjords, Strait of Magellan, Ushuaia, Falkland Islands, Buenos Aires and Montevideo. From $2,749 to $14,672.</p>
        <p>Mediterranean Shipping Cruises</p>
        <p>Rhapsody</p>
        <p>Capacity, 750 passengers; 17,500 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, casino, international and Italian cuisine; entered service as the Cunard Princess in 1976, refurbished in 1998.  Dec. 9 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises from Rio de Janeiro, calling at Porto Seguro, Salvador, Arraial Beach and Buzios. From $681 to $2,760.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Norwegian Dream</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,748 passengers; 50,760 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service as the Dreamward in 1992, lengthened in 1998.  Dec. 23 to Feb. 18 -- Fourteen-  and fifteen-night voyages between Valparaiso and Buenos Aires, calling variously at Puerto Montt, Chilean Fjords, Strait of Magellan, Punta Arenas, Ushuaia, Port Stanley, Puerto Madryn and Montevideo. From $1,899 to $6,699.</p>
        <p>Orient Lines</p>
        <p>Marco Polo</p>
        <p>Capacity 848 passengers; 22,080 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Alexandr Pushkin in 1965, rebuilt in 1993.  Dec. 2 -- Twelve-night Amazon River voyage from Barbados to Manaus, calling at St. Lucia, Grenada, Tobago, Devil's Island, Santarem and Boca da Valeria. From $3,345 to $7,700, including air fare from New York.  Dec. 13 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Manaus to Buenos Aires, calling at Boca da Valeria, Santarem, Recife, Rio de Janeiro and Montevideo. From $4,245 to $8,200, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.  Dec. 28 -- Thirteen-night Antarctic voyage from Buenos Aires to Ushuaia, calling at Falkland Islands, Bransfield Strait, Deception Island, Le Maire Channel, Port Lockroy, Paradise Harbor, Neumayer Channel and Half Moon Island. From $5,745 to $12,250, including air fare from New York.  Jan. 9 to Feb. 2 -- Eight-night Antarctic cruises from Ushuaia, calling at Bransfield Strait, Deception Island, Le Maire Channel, Port Lockroy, Paradise Harbor, Neumayer Channel and Half Moon Island. (Thirteen-night voyage on Feb. 10 ends in Valparaiso and also calls at Seno Eyre Fjord and Puerto Montt.) From $4,500 to $12,250, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.  Feb. 22 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Valparaiso to Buenos Aires, calling at Puerto Montt, Puerto Chacabuco, Punta Arenas, Ushuaia, Falkland Islands and Montevideo. From $4,245 to $9,700, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Peter Deilmann Cruises</p>
        <p>Deutschland</p>
        <p>Capacity 513 passengers; 22,400 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998, refurbished this year.  Feb. 4 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Balboa to Valparaiso, calling at Guayaquil, Callao, Arica, and Antofogasta. From $4,060 to $12,451.  Feb. 26 -- Twenty-two-night voyage from Valparaiso to Rio de Janeiro, calling at Puerto Montt, Chilean Fjords, Strait of Magellan, Beagle Channel, Ushuaia, Puerto Madryn and Buenos Aires. From $5,945 to $12,451.  Feb. 26 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Rio de Janeiro to Manaus, calling at Salvador, Recife, Fortaleza, Belem and Alter do Chao. From $3,788 to $11,620.</p>
        <p>Princess Cruises</p>
        <p>Royal Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,200 passengers, all in outside cabins; 45,000 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1984, refurbished in 1999.  Nov. 5 and Dec. 23 -- Fourteen-night voyages from Buenos Aires to Valparaiso, calling at Montevideo, Puerto Madryn, Falkland Islands, Cape Horn, Ushuaia, Strait of Magellan, Beagle Channel, Punta Arenas, Seno Eyre Fjord and Puerto Montt. (Voyages in reverse direction on Dec. 9 and Jan. 6.) From $2,995 to $9,355.  Jan. 20 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Buenos Aires to Manaus, calling at Montevideo, Rio de Janeiro, Santarem and Boca da Valeria. From $2,995 to $9,130.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Seabourn Pride</p>
        <p>Capacity 208 passengers; 10,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, retractable marina, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1988, refurbished this year; no full sprinkler system.  Jan. 23 and Feb. 6 and 20 -- Fourteen-night cruises from Valparaiso, calling at Castro, Punta Arenas, Ushuaia, Puerto Natales and Puerto Montt. From $6,993 to $17,416.</p>
        <p>Silversea Cruises</p>
        <p>Silver Shadow</p>
        <p>Capacity 388 passengers; 28,000 tons, enclosed outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service last month.  Nov. 1 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Barbados to Buenos Aires, calling at Devil's Island, Salvador, Rio de Janeiro, Santos, Florianopolis and Punta del Este. From $10,595 to $24,895, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.  Nov. 17 -- Seven-night voyage from Buenos Aires to Rio de Janeiro, calling at Montevideo, Sao Francisco do Sul and Santos. (Voyage in reverse direction on Nov. 24 calls at Punta del Este instead of Santos.) From $5,895 to $12,995, including air fare and hotel stay.  Dec. 1 -- Eighteen-night voyage from Buenos Aires to Valparaiso, calling at Montevideo, Puerto Madryn, Punta Arenas, Chilean Fjords, Ushuaia, Puerto Chacabuco, Laguna San Rafael, Castro and Puerto Montt. (Voyages in reverse direction on Dec. 19, also calling at Port Stanley, and on Feb. 6; 15-night voyage on Jan. 6 omits Chilean Fjords.) From $10,495 to $35,595, including air fare and hotel stay and, on Dec. 1 and Dec. 19 voyages, shore excursions.  Jan. 21 -- Sixteen-night cruise from Valparaiso, calling at Puerto Montt, Castro, Ushuaia, Punta Arenas, Puerto Chacabuco and Puerto Montt. From $11,295 to $26,195, including air fare and hotel stay.  Feb. 24 -- Seven-night voyage from Buenos Aires to Rio de Janeiro, calling at Montevideo and Santos. From $5,495 to $11,995, including air fare and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Silver Wind</p>
        <p>Capacity 296 passengers, all in outside suites; 16,800 tons, enclosed outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1995.  Nov. 22 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Caldera to Valparaiso, calling at Golfito, Guayaquil, Callao and Arica. From $9,745 to $21,845, including air fare and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Special Cruises</p>
        <p>Abercrombie &amp; Kent International</p>
        <p>Explorer</p>
        <p>Capacity 100 passengers; double ice-hardened hull, outdoor pool, sauna, fitness center, international cuisine.  Dec. 6 -- Eighteen-night cruise from Port Stanley, circumnavigating South Georgia and Falkland Islands. (Fifteen-night voyage on Dec. 21 ends in Ushuaia.) From $7,555 to $17,090.  Jan. 2 and 12 -- Thirteen-night cruises from Ushuaia, calling at the northern Antarctic Peninsula and South Shetland Islands. From $6,455 to $14,335.  Feb. 9 -- Sixteen-night voyage from Port Stanley to Ushuaia, calling at Antarctica, the western Falklands and South Shetland Islands. (Nineteen-night voyage in reverse direction on Feb. 22 also calls at South Georgia, South Orkney and Coronation Islands.) From $8,185 to $17,590.</p>
        <p>American Canadian Caribbean Line</p>
        <p>Grande Caribe  Capacity 100 passengers; American cuisine.  Dec.15 and 29 -- Eleven-night cruises from Nassau, calling at Round Bay, Roadtown, Salt Island, Peter Island, Spanish Town, Vixen, Anegada, Jost Van Dyke, Leverick Bay, Norman Island and Francis Bay. From $2,235 to $2,735.  Jan. 12 -- Eleven-night voyage from St. Martin to Antigua, calling at Marigot, Il Pineel, Tintamarre, Anguilla, St. Barthelemy, Saba, St. Kitts, Nevis, Falmouth Harbor, Darkwood Beach, Bird Island and Deep Bay. From $2,565 to $3,110.  Jan. 26 -- Eleven-night voyage from Antigua to Grenada, calling at Basse-Terre, Les Saintes, Dominica, Fort de France, Soufriere, Bequia, the Grenadines, Mayreau and Union Island. From $2,565 to $3,110.  Feb. 9 -- Eleven-night voyage from Trinidad to Curacao, calling at Port of Spain, Macareo River, Orinoco Delta, Margarita Island, Tortuga, Isla Los Roques and Bonaire. From $2,695 to $3,260.</p>
        <p>Grande Mariner</p>
        <p>Capacity 100 passengers; American cuisine.  Dec. 15 -- Eleven-night voyage from St. Martin to Antigua, calling at Marigot, Il Pineel, Tintamarre, Anguilla, St. Barthelemy, Saba, St. Kitts, Nevis, Falmouth Harbour, Darkwood Beach, Bird Island and Deep Bay. (Voyage in reverse direction on Dec. 29.) From $2,565 to $3,110.  Jan. 12 -- Eleven-night cruise from St. Thomas, calling at Round Bay (St. John), Tortola, Salt Island, Peter Island, Spanish Town, Vixen Point, Anegada, Jost Van Dyke, Leverick Bay, Norman Island and Francis Bay. From $2,235 to $2,735.  Feb. 2 and 16 -- Eleven-night cruises from Nassau, calling at Spanish Wells, Governor's Harbour, Cape Eleuthera, Galliot Cay, Staniel Cay, White Point Beach, Highborne Cay, Warderick Wells Cay, Norman's Cay and Allan's Cay. From $2,235 to $2,735.</p>
        <p>Niagara Prince</p>
        <p>Capacity 84 passengers; American cuisine.  Dec. 15 and Jan. 26 -- Eleven-night cruises from Belize, calling at Goff Cay, Tobacco Range, Laughing Bird Cay, Placencia, Lime Cay, Utila, Southwest Cays, Roatan, Punta Gorda, West Snake Cay, Punta Icacos, Tom Owens Cay and Northwest Pelican Cay. (Additional sailings on Dec. 29 and Jan. 12 call at Goff Cay, Tobacco Range, Victoria Channel Reef, Moho Cay, Laughing Bird Cay, Placencia, Punta Gorda, Livingston, Rio Dulce, El Golfete, Lago de Isabel, Fort San Felipe, Quirigua Mayan Ruins, Miramonk, West Snake Cay, Punta Icacos, Lone Cay and Water Cay.) From $1,830 to $2,665.</p>
        <p>American Cruise Lines</p>
        <p>American Eagle</p>
        <p>Capacity 49 passengers; American cuisine.  Nov. 4 -- Fourteen-night Intracoastal Waterway voyage from Baltimore to Jacksonville, calling at Oxford, Yorktown, Coinjock, Belhaven, Beaufort, N.C., Wrightsville Beach, Myrtle Beach, Charleston, Beaufort, S.C., Savannah and St. Simons Island. From $4,760 to $9,730.  Nov. 18 and Dec. 2 -- Seven-night voyages from Jacksonville to Charleston, calling at St. Simons Island, Savannah, Hilton Head Island and Beaufort, S.C. (Reverse departures on Nov. 25 and Dec. 9.) From $2,380 to $4,865.  Dec. 16 -- Ten-night voyage from Jacksonville to Fort Myers, calling at St. Simons Island, St. Augustine, Cape Canaveral, St. Lucie and Lake Okeechobee. From $3,400 to $6,950.  Jan. 2 to Feb. 24 -- Four-night cruises from Fort  Myers, calling at Fort Pierce and Lake Okeechobee.  From $1,360 to $2,780.</p>
        <p>Blue Lagoon Cruises</p>
        <p>Mystique Princess, Nanuya Princess, Yasawa Princess, Lycianda</p>
        <p>Capacity 42 to 70 passengers; South Pacific cuisine.  Year round -- Two-  to six-night Yasawa Islands cruises from Lautoka. From $298 to $781, including shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Classical Cruises</p>
        <p>Callisto</p>
        <p>Capacity 34 passengers; international cuisine.  Nov. 8 -- Ten-night voyage from Corinth to Nafplio, calling at Itea, Nafpaktos, Katakolon, Pylos, Koroni, Kalamata, Githion and Monemvasia. From $3,895 to $4,995, including hotel stay and shore excursions.  Jan. 1 to Feb. 26 -- Eight-night cruises from Hurghada (Egypt), calling at Aqaba, Eliat and Shram (Egypt). From $3,895 to $5,195, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Clelia II</p>
        <p>Capacity 84 passengers; international cuisine.  Nov. 30 -- Eleven-night voyage from Tartus (Syria) to Alexandria, calling at Beirut, Limassol, Haifa and Ashdod. From $6,095 to $12,995, including hotel stay and shore excursions.  Dec. 8 -- Twenty-five-night voyage from Alexandria to Bombay, calling at Safaga, Djibouti, Salalah, Sur, Dubai, Ra's al Khaymah, Fujayrah, Muscat, Okha and Porbandar. From $9,995 to $17,995, including hotel stay and shore excursions.  Dec. 28 and Jan. 17 -- Sixteen-night voyages from Bombay to Madras, calling at Goa, Mangalore, Cochin, Tuticorin, Colombo and Galle (Sri Lanka). (Voyages in reverse direction on Jan. 7 and Jan. 27.) From $8,995 to $15,945, including hotel stay and shore excursions.  Feb. 11 -- Sixteen-night voyage from Bombay to Kuwait, calling at Porbandar, Okha, Sur, Muscat, Fujayrah, Ra's al Khaymah, Dubai, Al Manamah, Dammam and Bushehr. From $8,995 to $15,995, including shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Halcyon</p>
        <p>Capacity 46 passengers; international cuisine.  Jan. 21 and 28 and Feb.11 -- Thirteen-night cruises from Dakar, calling at Albreda, Jamel Island, Tendaba, Banjul, Karabane Island, Ziquinchor, Saloum Delta and Fediout. From $5,595 to $6,495, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Panorama</p>
        <p>Capacity 44 passengers; 175-foot, three-mast motor yacht with sports platform, international cuisine.  Nov. 26 -- Twenty-two-night trans-Atlantic crossing from Malaga to Antigua, calling at Safi, Agadir, Lanzarote, Grand Canary, Novadhiba and Sao Vicente. From $5,695 to $6,995, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Classic Cruises of Newport</p>
        <p>Arabella</p>
        <p>Capacity 44 passengers; 160-foot, three-mast yacht, American and Caribbean cusine.  Jan. 14 to May 6 -- Six-night cruises from St. Thomas, sailing through the British Virgin Islands. From $1,995 to $2,895.</p>
        <p>Clipper Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Clipper Adventurer</p>
        <p>Capacity 122 passengers; A-1 ice-class expedition vessel, Zodiacs, fitness center, American cuisine.  Nov. 15 -- Seven-night voyage from Ushuaia to Puerto Montt, calling at Beagle Channel, Garibaldi Fjord, Puerto Natales, Seno Eyre, Puerto Eden, Isla Wellington and English Narrows. (Voyage in reverse direction on Nov. 22.) From $4,950 to $7,230, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.  Nov. 28 and Dec. 8 and 19 -- Ten-night cruises from Ushuaia, calling at Drake Passage, Deception Island, Antarctic Peninsula and Elephant Island. From $7,330 to $10,920, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.  Dec. 28 -- Eleven-night voyage from Ushuaia to Port Stanley, calling at Drake Passage, Deception Island, Antarctic Peninsula, Elephant Island, West Point Island and Carcass Island. From $7,780 to $11,690, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Clipper Odyssey</p>
        <p>Capacity 128 passengers; 338-foot luxury yacht, outdoor pool, fitness center, Continental and American cuisine.  Nov. 22 and Dec. 10 -- Nine-night voyages from Auckland to Milford Sound, calling at Tauranga, Napier, Queen Charlotte Sound, Lyttelton and Dunedin and cruising Doubtful and Dusky Sounds. (Voyage in reverse direction on Nov. 29.) From $5,670 to $7,870, including air fare and hotel stay.  Dec. 17 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Queenstown to Auckland, calling at Milford Sound, cruising Doubtful and Dusky Sounds, Stewart Island, Dunedin, Akaroa, Lyttelton, Kaikoura, Abel Tasman National Park, Nelson, Queen Charlotte and Marlborough Sounds, Picton, Wellington, Napier, Tauranga and Bay of Islands. From $7,950 to $11,100, including air fare and hotel stay.  Jan. 2 -- Seven-night voyage from Auckland to Lyttelton, calling at Tauranga, Napier, Wellington, Picton and Kaikoura Peninsula. (Voyage in reverse direction on Feb. 23.) From $5,680 to $7,500, including air fare and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Nantucket Clipper</p>
        <p>Capacity 100 passengers; Continental and American cuisine.  Nov. 4 and 18 -- Seven-night Intracoastal Waterway voyages between Jacksonville and Charleston, calling at St. Marys, Brunswick and Savannah. (Voyages in reverse direction on Nov. 11 and 25.) From $1,950 to $3,330.  Dec. 23 to Feb. 17 -- Seven-night British and American Virgin Islands voyages between Antigua and St. Martin, calling at Falmouth Harbour, St. Kitts, Saba, St. Eustatius, Gustavia, St. Barthelemy, Road Harbor, Sandy Cay and Anguilla. From $1,980 to $3,500.</p>
        <p>Yorktown Clipper</p>
        <p>Capacity 138 passengers; Zodiacs, American cuisine.  Nov. 15 -- Seven-night islands of the Gulf of California cruise from La Paz. From $1,800 to $2,930, including shore excursions.  Nov. 28, Dec. 6 and 10 -- Six-night Panama and Costa Rica voyages between Caldera and Colon, visiting the Darien Jungle and the Panama Canal. From $2,390 to $3,650, including hotel stay in San Jose and shore excursions.  Dec. 21 -- Eight-night voyage from Curacao to Trinidad, calling at Bonaire, Margarita Island and Tobago. From $2,230 to $3,750, including hotel stay.  Dec. 29 -- Seven-night Orinoco River cruise from Trinidad, calling at Ciudad Guayana, Man of War Bay and Tobago. From $1,980 to $3,500.  Jan. 6 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night Grenadines, Windward and Leeward Islands voyages between Grenada and St. Kitts, calling at Union Island, Bequia, St. Lucia, Dominica and Nevis. From $1,980 to $3,500.</p>
        <p>Compagnie des Iles du Ponant</p>
        <p>Le Levant</p>
        <p>Capacity 90 passengers; 330-foot luxury yacht with ice-hardened hull, Zodiacs, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, water sports platform, French cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included.  Nov. 18 and Dec. 28 -- Eight-night Orinoco River voyages from Guadeloupe to Cayenne (Salvation Islands), calling at Bequia, Tobago, Cana Duriapo, El Toro, Guyana, Canaima, El Arroyo, Arature and Paramaribo. (Additional voyages on Nov. 26, from Cayenne to Manaus, which includes Amazon River trip, and in reverse direction on Dec. 20.) From $4,640 to $5,200.  Dec. 4 -- Eight-night Amazon River voyage from Manaus to Iquitos. (Voyage in reverse direction on Dec. 12. From $4,460 to $5,200.  Jan. 20 and Feb. 3 -- Seven-night cruises from Guadeloupe, calling at Pointe-a-Pitre, Bequia, Grenada, Caracas Islands, Mochima, Los Testigos, Sandy Island or Carriacou, Dominica and Les Saintes. (Additional sailings on Jan. 27 and Feb. 24 call at Pointe-a-Pitre, St. Kitts, Virgin Gorda, Jost Van Dyke, Culebra, St. John and St. Barthelemy.) From $3,430 to $4,270, including round-trip air fare from Puerto Rico to Guadeloupe.</p>
        <p>Cruise West</p>
        <p>Spirit of Endeavour, Spirit of '98</p>
        <p>Capacity 102 and 98 passengers, respectively; American cuisine.  Dec. 9 and Jan. 6 -- Seven-night voyage on Dec. 9 on Spirit of Endeavour from San Diego to Cabo San Lucas and on Jan. 6 on Spirit of '98 from San Diego to La Paz, calling at Ensenada and Bahia Magdalena. From $1,595 to $3,795.  Dec. 16 to Feb. 28 -- Three-, four-  and seven-night islands of the Gulf of California cruises departing on Wednesday and Saturday from Cabo San Lucas or La Paz. From $1,095 to $4,695, including shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Global Quest</p>
        <p>Akademik Sergey Vavilov</p>
        <p>Capacity 76 passengers; ice-strengthened expedition vessel, indoor pool and sauna, Continental cuisine.  Nov. 20 to Feb. 26 -- Ten-  to 19-night cruises from Ushuaia, calling at the Antarctic Peninsula and South Atlantic islands. From $3,795 to $9,895, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Ambasador I</p>
        <p>Capacity 100 passengers; outdoor pool, American cuisine.  Year round -- Eleven-night Galapagos Islands cruises from Baltra. From $3,215 to $5,085, including air fare from Miami.</p>
        <p>Eclipse</p>
        <p>Capacity 48 passengers; outside pool, American cuisine.  Year round -- Twelve-night Galapagos Islands cruises from Isla San Cristobal. From $4,245 to $4,845, including air fare from Miami.</p>
        <p>Skorpios I, Skorpios II, Skorpios III</p>
        <p>Capacity 76 to 130 passengers; Continental cuisine.  Nov. 6 to Feb. 26 -- Ten-night Chilean coastal cruises from Puerto Montt, including fjords and visit to San Rafael Glacier. From $2,835 to $3,825, including air fare from Miami, hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Terra Australis</p>
        <p>Capacity 114 passengers; Continental cuisine, tips included.  Nov. 4 to Feb. 24 -- Eleven-night cruises of Chile's Patagonia and Tierra del Fuego region departing on Saturday from Punta Arenas, including the Almirantazgo and D'Agostini Fjords, Ballenero and O'Brien Channels and Ushuaia. From $2,885 to $3,585, including air fare from Miami and hotel stay. Segments available.</p>
        <p>Lindblad Expeditions</p>
        <p>Caledonian Star</p>
        <p>Capacity 110 passengers; expedition ship with ice-strengthened hull, outdoor pool, international cuisine.  Nov. 13 -- Twelve-night voyage from Salvador to Buenos Aires, calling at Ilheus, Vitoria, Rio de Janeiro, Parati, Paranagua, Curitiba and Montevideo. From $6,990 to $12,060, including hotel stay and shore excursions.  Nov. 22 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Buenos Aires to Ushuaia, calling at Montevideo, Mar del Plata, Puerto Madryn, Falkland Islands, Saunders and Carcass Islands, West Point and New Islands. From $7,990 to $13,880, including shore excursions.  Dec. 18 and Jan. 2 and 28 -- Eleven-night Antarctica voyages from Ushuaia to Punta Arenas, cruising in Beagle Channel and Drake Passage. From $7,520 to $12,800, including hotel stay and shore excursions.  Dec. 18 and Jan. 2 -- Fifteen-night voyages from Punta Arenas to the Falkland Islands, cruising Drake Passage, Cape Horn and Beagle Channel From $9,620 to $16,800, including hotel stay and shore excursions.  Feb. 8 -- Twenty-one-night Antarctic voyage from Punta Arenas to Ushuaia, cruising South Orkney and Georgia Islands and calling at Port Stanley. From $12,720 to $22,800, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Polaris</p>
        <p>Capacity 80 passengers; fitness center, Zodiacs and glass-bottom tender, international cuisine.  Year round -- Seven-night Galapagos Islands cruises departing on Saturday from Baltra except from Sept. 2 to 23. From $2,980 to $5,140, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Sea Bird, Sea Lion</p>
        <p>Capacity 70 passengers each; American cuisine.  Dec. 6 to Feb. 24 -- Four-, six-  and seven-night Gulf of California cruises from San Carlos or La Paz. From $2,390 to $4,430, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Marine Expeditions</p>
        <p>Marine Adventurer II, Marine Discovery</p>
        <p>Capacity 128 passengers each; expedition ships, fitness center, international cuisine.  November to March -- Eight-  to 21-night Antarctic cruises from Ushuaia, calling at the Antarctic Peninsula and the South Shetland, the Falkland and the South Georgia Islands. From $4,695 to $9,495, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Touring</p>
        <p>Isabela II, Santa Cruz</p>
        <p>Capacity 40 and 90 passengers, respectively; international cuisine.  Year round -- Seven-night Galapagos cruises from Baltra. From $1,784 to $3,625, including shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Norwegian Coastal Voyage</p>
        <p>Kong Harald, Nordkapp, Nordlys, Nordnorge, Polarlys and Richard With and five other Norwegian coastal vessels</p>
        <p>Capacity 464 to 490 passengers; fitness center, Scandinavian cuisine.  Year round -- Five-, six-  and 11-night cruises from Bergen or between Bergen and Kirkenes, calling variously at 34 ports along the coast of Norway. From $715 to $2,195.</p>
        <p>Peter Deilmann Cruises</p>
        <p>Lilli Marleen</p>
        <p>Capacity 50 passengers; 249-foot, three-mast bark, international cuisine.  Nov. 3 to Feb. 27 -- Seven-  to 14-night Persian Gulf and Arabian Sea cruises from Dubai, Hodeidah, Muscat and Abu Dhabi, calling variously at Aden, Mukalla, Salalah, Sur, Suhar, Khor Fakkan, Limah, Khasab, Musandam, Abu Dhabi, Musandam, Dibba, Bandar Abbas and Kish Island. From $2,340 to $5,965.</p>
        <p>Quark Expeditions</p>
        <p>Kapitan Dranitsyn</p>
        <p>Capacity 106 passengers; expedition vessel, indoor pool, fitness center, international cuisine.  Nov. 22, Dec. 11 and Jan. 7 -- Nineteen-night cruises from Ushuaia, visiting the Falkland Islands, the South Georgia and the South Shetland Islands, Cuverville Island and Ronge Island, the Antarctic Peninsula, the Neumayer and Lemaire Channels and Drake Passage. (Additional sailing on Feb. 21 calls also at the Orkney Islands.) From $7,695 to $10,395, including hotel stay and shore excursions.  Dec. 10 to Feb. 22 -- Ten-night cruises from Ushuaia, calling at Drake Passage, Paradise Harbor, Port Lockroy, Cuverville Island, Ronge Island, the Neumayer and Lamaire Channels, Petermann Island and Drake Passage. (Eleven-night sailing on Dec. 28 and 12-night sailing on Jan. 8.)  From $3,995 to $6,395, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Kapitan Khlebnikov</p>
        <p>Capacity 114 passengers; 12,288-ton icebreaker, indoor pool, fitness center, international cuisine.  Dec. 3 to Feb. 14 -- Twenty-four and 25-night Antarctic cruises from Hobart (Tasmania) or between Hobart and Bluff (New Zealand), calling in the Ross Sea and the sub-Antarctic Islands of New Zealand. From $13,795 to $21,495, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Professor Multanovskiy</p>
        <p>Capacity 49 passengers; ice-strengthened expedition vessel, international cuisine.  Dec. 13 to Feb. 27 -- Ten-  to 20-night cruises from Ushuaia, exploring the Falkland, South Orkney and South Shetland Islands and other islands, channels and straits of Antarctica. From $3,095 to $10,995, including hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Radisson Seven Seas Cruises</p>
        <p>Song of Flower</p>
        <p>Capacity 180 passengers, all in outside suites; luxury yacht with outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included.  Nov. 14 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Muscat to Phuket, calling at Bombay, Mangalore, Cochin, Male and the Maldives. From $6,995 to $10,395, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.  Nov. 28 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Phuket to Hong Kong, calling at Penang, Kuala Lumpur, Singapore, Ho Chi Minh City, Qhi Nhon, Da Nang and Haiphong. (Fifteen-night voyage on Dec. 18 calls also at Pulau Pangkor.) From $6,295 to $10,895, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.  Jan. 2 -- Twelve-night voyage from Phuket to Bali, calling at Penang, Kuala Lumpur, Singapore, Pulau Pelangi, Semarang, Surabaya, Lombok, Larantuka and Komodo. From $6,995 to $10,395, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.  Jan. 14 -- Eleven-night voyage from Bali to Singapore, calling at Komodo, Larantuka, Bau Bau, Palopo (Sulawesi), Lombok, Semarang and Pulau Pelangi. From $6,395 to $9,595, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.  Jan. 25 -- Eleven-night voyage from Singapore to Hong Kong, calling at Ho Chi Minh City, Qhi Nhon, Da Nang and Haiphong. (Voyage in reverse direction on Feb. 27.) From $6,495 to $9,695.  Feb. 5 -- Eleven-night voyage from Hong Kong to Bangkok, calling at Haiphong, Da Nang, Qhi Nhon and Ho Chi Minh City. (Voyage in reverse direction on Feb. 16.) From $6,495 to $9,695, including air fare, hotel stay and shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Sea Cloud Cruises</p>
        <p>Sea Cloud</p>
        <p>Capacity 68 passengers; 360-foot, four-mast, square-rigged bark, international cuisine.  Nov. 3 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises departing from Antigua, Las Palmas, St. Lucia or Barbados, variously calling at Tobago, Grenada, Carriacou, Bequia, Les Saintes, Domenica, St.-Barthelemy, Virgin Gorda, Tortola and Jost Van Dyke. From $3,400 to $10,000.</p>
        <p>Society Expeditions</p>
        <p>New World Discoverer</p>
        <p>Capacity 138 passengers; 285-foot expedition ship, outdoor pool, fitness center, Continental cuisine, tips included.  Nov. 30 -- Eighteen-night voyage from Punta Arenas to Ushuaia, calling at the Falkland South Georgia and South Orkney Islands and the Antarctic Peninsula. (Additional voyages on Dec. 18 and Jan. 15 depart from Ushuaia.) From $8,410 to $17,940, including hotel stay and shore excursions.  Jan. 5 -- Ten-night cruise from Ushuaia, calling at the Antarctic Peninsula, King George and Deception Islands, Paradise Bay, Elephant Island, Anvers Island, Port Lockeroy, Paulet Island and Petermann Island. From $5,790 to $10,300, including hotels stay and shore excursions.  Feb. 20 -- Sixteen-night voyage from Ushuaia to Puerto Montt, calling at the Antarctic Peninsula, Tierra del Fuego and the Chilean Fjords. From $7,980 to $14,290, including hotel stay and excursions.</p>
        <p>Star Clippers</p>
        <p>Royal Clipper</p>
        <p>Capacity 228 passengers; 439-foot steel-hull, five-masted sailing ship, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, retractable water sports platform, international cuisine.  Nov. 4 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from Barbados, calling at the Grenadine and the Windward Islands, including Martinique, St. Lucia, Bequia, Tobago Cays, Grenada and Captain's Best (Grenadines) or Martinique, Les Saintes, Antigua, St. Kitts, Dominica and St. Lucia. From $1,575 to $4,695.</p>
        <p>Star Clipper</p>
        <p>Capacity 170 passengers; 360-foot, steel-hull sailing ship, two outdoor pools, international cuisine.  Nov. 3 to Feb. 26 -- Seven-night Caribbean cruises from St. Martin, calling at St.-Barthelemy, Nevis, Guadeloupe, Dominica, Les Saintes and Antigua or Anguilla, Sandy Cay or Jost Van Dyke, Soper's Hole, Norman Island, Virgin Gorda, St. Kitts and St.-Barthelemy. (Six-night sailing on Dec. 17 calls at Sandy Cay, Soper's Hole, Norman Island, Virgin Gorda, St. Kitts and St.-Barthelemy.) From $1,155 to $3,595.</p>
        <p>Star Flyer</p>
        <p>Capacity 170 passengers; 360-foot, steel-hull sailing ship, two outdoor pools, international cuisine.  Jan. 6. to Feb. 26 -- Seven-night cruises departing on Saturday from Phuket (Thailand), calling at Batong Islands (Thailand), Penang, Ko Lipe, Ko Khai Nok, Phang Nga, Ko Dam Hok and Similan Islands or Surin Islands, Ko Miang (Thailand), Ko Rok Nok, Langkawi, Phi Phi Islands and Ko Dam Hok (Thailand). From $1,345 to $3,555.</p>
        <p>Temptress Adventure Cruises</p>
        <p>Temptress Explorer, Temptress Voyager</p>
        <p>Capacity 100 and 63 passengers, respectively; water sports platform, international cuisine.  January to April -- Seven-night Costa Rican cruises from Los Suenas, calling at Curu Wildlife Refuge, Tortuga Islands, Corcovado National Park, Coiba Island, Manuel Antonio National Park, Drake Bay and Golfito. From $1,210 to $2,695, including shore excursions.</p>
        <p>Windjammer Barefoot Cruises</p>
        <p>Amazing Grace</p>
        <p>Capacity 94 passengers; supply ship, American cuisine.  Year round -- Thirteen-night voyages between Freeport and Trinidad, calling at Antigua, Bequia, Conception, Cooper Island, Dominica, Dominican Republic, Grand Bahama, Grand Turk, Great Inagua, Grenada, Les Saintes, Jost Van Dyke, Nevis, Norman Island, Plana Cay, St.-Barthelemy, St. Kitts, St. Lucia, St. Martin, Tortola, Trinidad and Virgin Gorda. From $1,375 to $3,075.</p>
        <p>Flying Cloud</p>
        <p>Capacity 66 passengers; three-mast 208-foot yacht, American cuisine.  Year round -- Five-night British Virgin Islands cruises departing on Monday from Tortola, calling at Salt Island, Cooper Island, Virgin Gorda and Jost Van Dyke or Cooper Island, Peter Island, Norman Island and Virgin Gorda. From $900 to $1,300.</p>
        <p>Legacy</p>
        <p>Capacity 122 passengers; four-mast, 294-foot bark, American cuisine.  November to May -- Five-night cruises departing on Monday from St. Thomas, calling at Jost Van Dyke, St. John, Norman Island, St. Croix, Tortola and Vieques. From $1,100 to $1,525.</p>
        <p>Mandalay</p>
        <p>Capacity 72 passengers; three-mast, 236-foot bark, American cuisine.  November to May -- Twelve-night voyages departing on Mondays between Grenada and Antigua, calling at Bequia, Canouan, Carriacou, Dominica, Les Saintes, Martinique, Mayreau, Nevis, St. Lucia and St. Vincent. From $1,875 to $2,225.</p>
        <p>Polynesia</p>
        <p>Capacity 124 passengers; four-mast 248-foot schooner, American cuisine.  November to May -- Five-night cruises departing on Monday from St. Martin, calling at St.-Barthelemy, Anguilla, Tintamarre and Saba or St.-Barthelemy, St. Eustatius, Nevis and St. Kitts. From $700 to $1,200.</p>
        <p>Yankee Clipper</p>
        <p>Capacity 64 passengers; three-mast 197-foot racing yacht, American cuisine.  Year round -- Five-night cruises departing on Monday from Grenada, calling at Bequia, Carriacou, Mayreau and St. Vincent or Bequia, Canouan, St. Vincent and Union Island. From $900 to $1,100.</p>
        <p>Windstar Cruises</p>
        <p>Wind Song</p>
        <p>Capacity 148 passengers; four-mast motorized sailing vessel; outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, water sports platform, casino, international cuisine.  Nov. 18 -- Fourteen-night trans-Atlantic voyage from Lisbon to Barbados. From $1,323 to $3,170.  Nov. 4 -- Seven-night voyage from Barcelona to Lisbon, calling at Majorca, Marbella, Gibraltar and Cadiz. From $2,003 to $7,200.  Dec. 2 -- Fourteen-night Panama Canal voyage from Barbados to Caldera, calling at Bequia, Tobago, Margarita Island, Bonaire, Curacao, Aruba and San Josecitas (Costa Rica). From $4,442 to $7,600.  Dec. 16 to Feb. 24 -- Seven-night cruises from Caldera, calling at San Juan del Sur (Nicaragua), Playa Flamingo, Quepos, San Josecitos, Curu National Rafuge and Tortuga Island. From $2,482 to $4,290, including air fare from Miami to San Jose, Costa Rica, on Dec. 16 only.</p>
        <p>Wind Spirit</p>
        <p>Capacity 148 passengers; four-mast motorized sailing vessel; outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, water sports platform, casino, international cuisine.  Nov. 4 -- Seven-night voyage from Civitavecchia to Monte Carlo, calling at Bastia, Portoferraio, Livorno, Portofino, Villefranche and St.-Tropez. From $2,003 to $4,000.  Nov. 11 -- Eight-night voyage from Monte Carlo to Lisbon, calling at Majorca, Valencia, Malaga and Tangier. From $2,877 to $4,510.  Nov. 19 -- Fourteen-night trans-Atlantic voyage from Lisbon to St. Thomas. From $1,573 to $3,170.  Dec. 3 and 10 -- Seven-night cruises from St. Thomas, calling at St. John, St. Martin, St.-Barthelemy, Tortola, Jost Van Dyke and Virgin Gorda. From $2,412 to $4,090.  Dec. 17 -- Ten-night cruise from St. Thomas, calling at St. John (Cruz Bay), Saba, Les Saintes, Vieux Forte (St. Lucia), Barbados, Bequia, Mayreau and St.-Barthelemy. (Eleven-night cruise on Dec. 27 calls at Cruz Bay, Anguilla, St. Martin, St.-Barthelemy, Les Saintes, May reau, Fort-de-France and Grand Anse on Martinique, Nevis, Tortola and Virgin Gorda.) From $3,063 to $6,700.  Jan. 7 to Feb. 25 -- Seven-night cruises from St. Thomas, calling at St. John, St. Martin, St.-Barthelemy, Tortola, Jost Van Dyke and Virgin Gorda. From $2,482 to $4,200.</p>
        <p>Wind Star</p>
        <p>Capacity 148 passengers; four-mast motorized sailing vessel; outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, water sports platform, casino, international cuisine.  Nov.5 -- Seven-night cruise from Barcelona to Lisbon, calling at Minorca, Ibiza, Marbella, Tangier and Portimao. From $2,962 to $5,000, including air fare from New York to Lisbon, Barcelona or Nice.  Nov. 12 -- Fourteen-night Atlantic crossing from Lisbon to Barbados. From $1,323 to $3,270.  Nov. 26 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Barbados to Calica, calling at Bequia, St. Lucia, Les Saintes, St.-Barthelemy, Anguilla, Tortola, Puerto Plata, Montego Bay, Little Cayman and Cozumel. From $3,553 to $7,200, including air fare from Miami and return from Cancun.  Dec. 10 -- Seven-night cruise from Calica, calling at Roatan, Goff's Cay, Half Moon Cay Reserve and San Pedro (Belize) and Cozumel. From $2,597 to $4,090.  Dec. 17 -- Ten-night cruise from Calica, calling at Roatan, Sapodilla Cay, Goff's Cay, Belize City, Turneffe Islands, Half Moon Cay Reserve, Xcalak (Mexico), Playa del Carmen and Cozumel. (Eleven-night cruise on Dec. 27 calls also at Dangriga in Belize.) From $3,912 to $6,700.  Jan. 7 to Feb. 25 -- Seven-night cruises from Puerto Morelos (Cancun), calling at Coxen Hole and West End (Roatan), Laughing Bird Cay, Dahgnga, Coco Plum Cay and Goff's Cay (Belize), and Cozumel. From $2,862 to $4,200.</p>
        <p>Wind Surf</p>
        <p>Capacity 312 passengers; five-mast, motorized sailing vessel; two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, water sports platform, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants.  Nov. 4 -- Seven-night voyage from Civitavecchia to Nice, calling at Bonifacio, Portoferraio, Portovenere, St.-Tropez and Monte Carlo. (Eight-night voyage from Nice to Lisbon on Nov. 11 calls at Majorca, Valencia, Malaga and Tangier.) From $2,263 to $7,398, including round-trip air fare from New York.  Nov. 26 -- Fourteen-night trans-Atlantic voyage from Lisbon to Barbados. From $1,323 to $4,668.  Dec. 10 and Jan. 7 to Feb. 18 -- Seven-night cruises from Barbados, calling at Nevis, St. Martin, St.-Barthelemy, Les Saintes and Pigeon Island (St. Lucia). From $2,412 to $6,038.  Dec. 17 -- Ten-night cruise from Barbados, calling at Mayreau, St.-Barthelemy, Anguilla, St. Martin, St. Vincent, Tobago and Bequia. (Eleven-night cruise on Dec. 27 calls at Tobago, Los Roques, Bonaire, Aruba, Curacao, Margarita Island, Grenada and Mayreau.) From $3,073 to $9,898.</p>
        <p>Indian Ocean</p>
        <p>Global Quest</p>
        <p>Royal Star</p>
        <p>Capacity 210 passengers; 5,600 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the San Georgio in 1956, renovated in 1992.  Year round -- Sixteen-  to 23-night cruises from Mombasa, calling variously at Zanzibar, Shungu Mbili, Mayotte, Nosy Be, the Maldive Islands and the Seychelles. From $3,495 to $14,900, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Mediterranean Shipping Cruises</p>
        <p>Monterey</p>
        <p>Capacity 550 passengers; 20,000 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, casino, international and Italian cuisine; entered service as the Free State Mariner in 1952, refurbished in 1998.  Nov. 5 -- Twenty-two-night voyage from Genoa to Durban, calling at Naples, Ashdod, Port Said, Aqaba, Port Victoria, Mombasa and Zanzibar. From $2,000 to $3,350.</p>
        <p>Orient Lines</p>
        <p>Crown Odyssey</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,036 passengers; 34,250 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998, renovated this year.  Nov. 12 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Mombasa to Bombay, calling at Zanzibar, Mayotte (Comoro Islands), Nosy Komba (Madagascar), Mahe (Seychelles), Male (Maldives) and Goa. From $6,690 to $14,645, including air fare from New York and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Peter Deilmann Cruises</p>
        <p>Deutschland</p>
        <p>Capacity 513 passengers; 22,400 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1998, refurbished this year.  Nov. 11 -- Thirteen-night voyage from Port Louis (Mauritius) to Cape Town, calling at Reunion Island, Fort Dauphin (Madagascar), Richards Bay, Durban, East London and Port Elizabeth. From $4,240 to $11,820.  Nov. 24 -- Twelve-night cruise from Cape Town, calling at Durban, Port Elizabeth and Walvis Bay. From $3,930 to $10,990.  Dec. 6 -- Sixteen-night voyage from Cape Town to Dakar, calling at Luderitz (Namibia), Walvis Bay, Sao Tome Island, Lome (Togo) and Takoradi (Ghana). From $4,560 to $13,060.</p>
        <p>Princess Cruises</p>
        <p>Pacific Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 640 passengers; 20,000 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Sea Venture in 1971, refurbished in 1999; no full sprinkler system.  Jan. 28 -- Twenty-two-night voyage from Cape Town to Mombasa, calling at East London, Durban, Nosy Be, Mayotte, Zanzibar, Bombay, Cochin, Maldive Islands and the Seychelles. From $3,680 to $11,850.</p>
        <p>Renaissance Cruises</p>
        <p>Renaissance VII, Renaissance VIII</p>
        <p>Capacity 114 passengers; 4,500 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service in 1992.  November to March -- Eight-night cruises from Mahe (Seychelles), calling at Praslin, La Digue, Curieuse and Desroches. From $3,999 to $5,499, including air fare.</p>
        <p>Royal Caribbean International</p>
        <p>Legend of the Seas</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,800 passengers; 69,130 tons, indoor pool and outdoor pool with retractable dome, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995.  Nov. 17 -- Seventeen-night voyage from Piraeus to Mombasa, calling at Haifa, Ashdod, Port Said, Sharm el Sheik, Aqaba and Safaga. From $3,749 to $12,549.  Nov. 29 -- Seventeen-night voyage from Mombasa to Bombay, calling at Victoria (Seychelles), Cochin and Marmugao (Goa). From $3,749 to $12,549.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Seabourn Spirit</p>
        <p>Capacity 208 passengers; 10,000 tons, outdoor pool, retractable marina, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service in 1989, refurbished this year; no full sprinkler system.  Feb. 25 -- Seventeen-night voyage from Singapore to Dubai, calling at Penang, Colombo, Cochin, Goa and Mumbai (India) and Muscat (Oman). From $5,580 to $13,840.</p>
        <p>Silversea Cruises</p>
        <p>Silver Cloud</p>
        <p>Capacity 296 passengers; 16,800 tons, enclosed outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service in 1994.  Nov. 2 -- Eight-night voyage from Safaga to Dubai, calling at Aden and Muscat. From $5,795 to $11,595, including air fare and hotel stay.  Nov. 10 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Dubai to Singapore, calling at Bombay, Marmagoa, Cochin, Colombo, Phuket and Port Kelang. From $8,595 to $18,395, including air fare and hotel stay.</p>
        <p>Swan Hellenic</p>
        <p>Minerva</p>
        <p>Capacity 300 passengers; 12,500 tons, outdoor pool, fitness center, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service in 1996.  Nov. 8 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Antalya to Aqaba, calling at Tasucu, Iskenderun, Latakia, Tartus, Tripoli, Beirut, Alexandria, Port Said and Sharm el Sheik. From $4,560 to $8,968, including air fare from London to Antalya and return from Aqaba and shore excursions.  Nov. 22 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Aqaba to Dubai, calling at Sharm el Sheik, Safaga, Hodeidah, Salalah and Muscat. From $4,568 to $8,984, including air fare from London to Aqaba and return from Dubai and shore excursions.  Dec. 13 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Dubai to Colombo, calling at Fujaira, Muscat, Mumbai, Goa and Kochi. From $4,488 to $10,048, including air fare from London to Dubai and return from Colombo and shore excursions.  Dec. 20 -- Fourteen-night voyage from Bombay to Calcutta, calling at Goa, Cochin, Colombo, Galle and Chennai (Madras). From $5,520 to $11,208, including shore excursions.  Feb. 13 -- Fifteen-night voyage from Bali to Colombo, calling at Semarang, Singapore, Port Kelang, Penang and Port Blair. From $5,667 to $10,843, including air fare from London to Bali and return from Colombo shore and excursions.</p>
        <p>Extended Cruises</p>
        <p>Crystal Cruises</p>
        <p>Crystal Symphony</p>
        <p>Capacity 940 passengers; 51,044 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995, renovated in 1999.  Jan. 12 -- Voyage of 103 nights from Los Angeles to London, calling at Honolulu, LaHaina, Pohnpei (Micronesia), Palau Island, Apra (Guam), Naha (Okinawa), Keelung, Hong Kong, Hailong Bay, Kompong Som (Cambodia), Singapore, Yangon (formerly Rangoon), Colombo, Male (Maldive Islands), Cochin, Bombay, Dubai, Muscat , Victoria (Seychelles), Mombasa, Zanzibar, Mayotte, Nosy Be, Durban, Cape Town, Walvis Bay, Bom Bom Island Resort, Takoradi (Ghana), Abidjan, Banjul (Gambia), Dakar, Tenerife, Madeira, Casablanca, Malaga and Bilbao. From $38,990 to $166,075, including air fare. Segments available.</p>
        <p>Cunard Line</p>
        <p>Queen Elizabeth 2</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,778 passengers; 70,327 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1969, refitted in 1999.  Jan. 5 -- World cruise of 104 nights from New York or Miami, calling at Cartagena, Acapulco, Los Angeles, Honolulu, Pago Pago, Suva, Auckland, Sydney, Hobart, Melbourne, Adelaide, Fremantle, Padang Bay, Bali, Manilla, Kobe, Hong Kong, Ho Chi Minh City, Laem Chabang (for Bangkok), Singapore, Phuket, Colombo, Bombay, Dubai, Muscat, Aqaba, Safaga, Port Suez, Naples, Marseille, Lisbon and Southampton. From $28,480 to $356,030. Segments available.</p>
        <p>EuroCruises</p>
        <p>Black Prince</p>
        <p>Capacity 412 passengers; 11,209 tons, indoor and outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, retractable marina, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1966, refurbished in 1999.  Jan. 30 -- Thirty-five-night Caribbean cruise from Southampton, calling at Funchal, St. John's, St. Thomas, Ocho Rios, Grand Cayman, Punta Frances, Playa del Carmen, Cozumel, Havana, Bimini, Hamilton and Ponta Delgada. From $5,665 to $11,340.</p>
        <p>Black Watch</p>
        <p>Capacity 761 passengers; 28,492 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service as the Royal Viking Star in 1972, refurbished this year.  Jan. 4 -- Sixty-nine-night European, South America, Panama Canal and Caribbean cruise from Southampton, calling at Lisbon, Tenerife, Dakar, Recife, Salvador, Rio de Janeiro, Buenos Aires, Port Stanley, Cape Horn, Ushuaia, Beagle Channel, Punta Arenas, Chilean Fjords, Puerto Montt, Valparaiso, Arica, Callao, Manta, Panama Canal, San Blas Islands, Cartagena, Ocho Rios, Santiago de Cuba, Grand Turk, Hamilton and Ponta Delgada. From $12,420 to $33,120.</p>
        <p>Holland America Line</p>
        <p>Rotterdam VI</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,316 passengers; 62,000 tons, two outdoor pools, one with retractable dome; spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine; entered service in 1997.  Jan. 18 -- Voyage of 99 nights from Los Angeles to New York, calling at San Juan del Sur, Puntarenas, Guayaquil, Callao, Easter Island, Pitcairn Island, Papeete, Bora Bora, Bay of Islands, Auckland, Wellington, Sydney, Cairns, Darwin, Lombok, Manila, Hong Kong, Singapore, Bombay, Aqaba, Sharm el Sheikh, Haifa, Kusadasi, Istanbul, Palermo, Motril, Lisbon, Punta Delgada, the Azores and Fort Lauderdale. From $28,822 to $146,821, including air fare. Segments available.</p>
        <p>P &amp; O Cruises</p>
        <p>Aurora</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,870 passengers; 76,000 tons, indoor pool with retractable dome, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in April.  Jan. 6 -- Ninety-night maiden world cruise westbound from Southampton, calling at Madeira, Antigua, Barbados, Curacao, Puntarenas, Acapulco, San Francisco, Honolulu, Pago Pago, Auckland, Sydney, Brisbane, Whitsunday Island, Guam, Yokohama, Kagoshima, Shanghai, Hong Kong, Singapore, Phuket, Bombay, Safaga, Suez, Port Said, Ashdod, Kusadasi and Barcelona. From $30,715 to $141,292. Segments available.</p>
        <p>Oriana</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,800 passengers; 69,153 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1995.  Jan. 5 -- Ninety-two-night world cruise eastbound from Southampton, calling at Tenerife, Cape Verde Islands, Walvis Bay (Nambia), Cape Town, Port Elizabeth, Nosy Be, the Seychelles, Colombo, Singapore, Kota Kinabalu, Bali, Perth, Adelaide, Sydney, Auckland, Bora Bora, Papeete, Honolulu, Vancouver, San Francisco, Acapulco, Puerto Quetzal (Guatemala), Aruba, Grenada, Barbados and Madeira. From $34,020 to $90,880. Segments available.</p>
        <p>Princess Cruises</p>
        <p>Pacific Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 640 passengers; 20,000 tons, two outdoor pools, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Sea Venture in 1971, refurbished in 1999; no full sprinkler system.  Jan. 3 -- Thirty-six-night voyage from Istanbul to Mombasa, calling at Malta, La Goulette, Casablanca, Dakar, Abidjan, Accra, Lome, Cotonou, Walvis Bay, Luderitz, East London, Cape Town, Durban, Nosy Be, Mayotte and Zanzibar. From $5,835 to $12,621. Segments available.</p>
        <p>Royal Princess</p>
        <p>Capacity 1,200 passengers, all in outside cabins; 45,000 tons, three outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, Continental cuisine, choice of restaurants; entered service in 1984, refurbished in 1999.  Jan. 6 -- Forty-night voyage from Valparaiso to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Montevideo, Puerto Madryn, Falkland Islands, Cape Horn, Ushuaia, Strait of Magellan, Beagle Channel, Punta Arenas, Seno Eyre Fjord, Puerto Montt, Valparaiso, Rio de Janeiro, Amazon River, Santarem, Boca da Valeria, Manaus, Devil's Island, Trinidad and Tortola. From $7,460 to $21,539. Segments available.  Feb. 11 -- Seventy-two-night voyage from Fort Lauderdale to Civitavecchia, calling at Cartagena, Manta, Callao, Easter Island, Papeete, Pago Pago, Suva, Auckland, Bay of Islands, Sydney, Cid Harbor (Great Barrier Reef), Cairns, Bitung (Indonesia), Manila, Hong Kong, Ho Chi Minh City, Singapore, Port Kelang, Cochin, Bombay, Salalah, Safaga, Port Said, Ashdod, Piraeus and Naples. From $29,850 to $75,617, including air fare.</p>
        <p>Radisson Seven Seas Cruises</p>
        <p>Seven Seas Navigator</p>
        <p>Capacity 490 passengers, all in suites; 30,000 tons, outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1999.  Nov. 11 -- Voyage of 58 nights from Hong Kong to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Hanoi, Da Nang, Ho Chi Minh City, Singapore, Semarang, Surabaya, Bali, Komodo, Larantuka, Darwin, Thursday Island, Cooktown, Cairns, Noumea, Suva, Apia, Christmas Island, Honolulu, Los Angeles, Cabo San Lucas, Puerto Vallarta, Acapulco, Huatulco, Caldera, Gatun Yacht Club, Cartagena, Grand Cayman and Cozumel. From $20,395 to $55,895, including air fare and hotel stay. Segments available.  Feb. 2 -- Cruise of 58 nights from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Key West, Grand Cayman, Limon, Gatun Yacht Club, Manta, Salaverry, Callao, Pisco, Coquimbo, Valparaiso, Puerto Montt, Chilean Fjords, Ushuaia, Falkland Islands, Puerto Madryn, Buenos Aires, Montevideo, Rio de Janeiro, Salvador, Fortaleza, Amazon River, Alter do Chao, Boca da Valeria, Manaus, Parintins, Santarem, Devil's Island, Barbados, Antigua and St. Thomas. From $17,010 to $61,233. Segments available.</p>
        <p>Royal Olympic Cruises</p>
        <p>Stella Solaris</p>
        <p>Capacity 620 passengers; 18,000 tons, double outdoor pool, spa, Continental cuisine; entered service as the Cambodge in 1953, renovated in 1994.  Jan. 19 -- Fifty-seven-night cruise around South America from Fort Lauderdale, calling at Ocho Rios, San Andres, Limon, Balboa, Manta, Salavery, Callao, Valparaiso, Puerto Montt, Patagonian Channel and Straits of Magellan, Punta Arenas, Ushuaia, Cape Horn, Puerto Madryn, Montivideo, Buenos Aires, Rio de Janiero, Salvador, Recife, Belem, Amazon Delta, Devil's Island, Trinidad, Barbados and St. Thomas. From $7,345 to $17,945. Segments available.</p>
        <p>Seabourn Cruise Line</p>
        <p>Seabourn Sun</p>
        <p>Capacity 758 passengers; 38,000 tons, two outdoor pools, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, choice of restaurants, tips included; entered service as the Royal Viking Sun in 1988, refurbished in 1999; no full sprinkler system.  Jan. 9 -- Inaugural world cruise of 99 nights from San Francisco to Fort Lauderdale, calling at Nuku Hiva, Papeete, Moorea, Bora Bora, Rarotonga, Nuku'alofa, Sydney, Cid Harbor (Great Barrier Reef), Cairns, Madang, Davao and Manila (Philippines), Hong Kong, Da Nang, Ho Chi Minh City, Singapore, Port Kelang, Colombo, Bombay, Dubai, Muscat, Aqaba, Safaga, Sharm el Sheikh, Suez, Civitavecchia, Barcelona, Cadiz, Canary Islands, Barbados and San Juan. From $30,880 to $145,330. Segments available.</p>
        <p>Silversea Cruises</p>
        <p>Silver Wind</p>
        <p>Capacity 296 passengers, all in outside suites; 16,800 tons, enclosed outdoor pool, spa, fitness center, casino, international cuisine, tips included; entered service in 1995.  Jan. 3 to April 9 -- Voyage of 125 nights from Los Angeles to London, calling at San Francisco, Honolulu, Lahaina (Maui), Suva, Noumea, Auckland, Lyttelton, Dunedin, Milford Sound, Melbourne, Sydney, Great Barrier Reef, Townsville, Cairns, Darwin, Bali, Singapore, Bangkok, Ho Chi Minh City, Da Nang, Hong Kong, Manila, Kota Kinabalu, Brunei, Port Kelang, Phuket, Yangon (formerly Rangoon), Cochin, Bombay, Dubai, Muscat, Salalah, Aden, Hodeidah, Safaga, Port Said, Haifa, Kusadasi, Istanbul, Mykonos, Piraeus, Messina, Civitavecchia, Monte Carlo, Marseille, Barcelona,  Casablanca, Lisbon, Bilbao, Bordeaux and St.-Malo.  From $73,495 to $171,195, including air fare, hotel  stay and shore excursion to Agra, India. Segments available.</p>
        <p>FALL AND WINTER CRUISES VERNON KIDD writes about cruises for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">VERNON KIDD writes about cruises for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
