<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Star Mezzo Role Finds a Mezzo Star to Sing It</title>
    <meta content="01MERM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/arts/01MERM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heggie, Jake</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mermelstein, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dead Man Walking (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DB133AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Star Mezzo Role Finds a Mezzo Star to Sing It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID MERMELSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mermelstein, David</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Mermelstein profiles American mezzo-soprano Susan Graham, who will star in San Francisco Opera production of Jake Heggie's Dead Man Walking; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE American mezzo-soprano Susan Graham has for the better part of a decade impressed audiences with her creamy singing and chiseled characterizations, sharing the stage with stars like Renee Fleming, Thomas Hampson and Dawn Upshaw, and consistently earning reviews as strong as theirs. In December, Ms. Graham gained new prominence in John Harbison's ''Great Gatsby'' at the Metropolitan Opera. Now she is ready for her close-up, at the center of another new work, Jake Heggie's ''Dead Man Walking,'' which opens on Saturday at the San Francisco Opera.</p>
        <p>''Dead Man Walking,'' with a libretto by the playwright Terrence McNally, is based on Sister Helen Prejean's book of the same name, which also inspired a 1995 movie that earned the actress Susan Sarandon an Oscar. It tells of Sister Helen's attempts to save the soul of a murderer sentenced to death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE American mezzo-soprano Susan Graham has for the better part of a decade impressed audiences with her creamy singing and chiseled characterizations, sharing the stage with stars like Renee Fleming, Thomas Hampson and Dawn Upshaw, and consistently earning reviews as strong as theirs. In December, Ms. Graham gained new prominence in John Harbison's ''Great Gatsby'' at the Metropolitan Opera. Now she is ready for her close-up, at the center of another new work, Jake Heggie's ''Dead Man Walking,'' which opens on Saturday at the San Francisco Opera.</p>
        <p>''Dead Man Walking,'' with a libretto by the playwright Terrence McNally, is based on Sister Helen Prejean's book of the same name, which also inspired a 1995 movie that earned the actress Susan Sarandon an Oscar. It tells of Sister Helen's attempts to save the soul of a murderer sentenced to death.</p>
        <p>The opera is confrontational, Ms. Graham said last month, during rehearsals here at the War Memorial Opera House. ''It makes you go places you might not ordinarily go.''</p>
        <p>''Dead Man Walking'' is the first opera by Mr. Heggie, who has mostly written art songs for reigning divas, especially the mezzo-soprano Frederica von Stade. Ms. Graham, who had never sung any of his songs, said she was surprised when Mr. Heggie approached her about his opera, and daunted by the idea.</p>
        <p>''When Jake told me of the project over a cup of coffee in the summer of 1997, I dissolved in tears,'' she recalled. ''I said, 'I can't do it.' But Jake persuaded me otherwise. He told me that because of my reaction to the description, I'd be perfect for the role.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Heggie had his heart set on Ms. Graham nearly from the start. ''I originally offered the role to Flicka,'' Mr. Heggie said, referring to Ms. von Stade, ''but she declined in favor of someone younger. And so Terrence and Patrick Summers, who will conduct, and I immediately thought of Susan. We were after a Janet Baker type.''</p>
        <p>Ms. von Stade will sing the supporting role of the killer's mother and has only kind words for Ms. Graham, whose career echoes her own. ''I think the world of Susan,'' she said. ''Everybody does. She has a terrifically warm voice, but it's also incredibly clear.'' Ms. von Stade describes Ms. Graham as ''sano,'' Italian for ''healthy'' or ''wholesome,'' a term not often applied to opera singers.</p>
        <p>For Mr. McNally, a longtime opera enthusiast, Ms. Graham's naturalism is an asset. ''She is one of those opera singers who don't sound like opera singers,'' he said. Mr. McNally collaborated with the composer Robert Beaser on one act of the trilogy ''Central Park,'' which had its debut last year, but ''Dead Man Walking'' represents his first full-scale libretto. ''When Susan sings, it's like she's talking,'' he added. ''Her expression is so unforced.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Graham, 40, speaks excitedly of playing the protagonist in a new opera, an honor seldom accorded a mezzo. ''I normally play Eve Arden,'' she said. ''I don't usually get to play Bette Davis.''</p>
        <p>But there are hurdles. ''To portray a living person is a special challenge,'' Ms. Graham said. ''And the music is not as simple as it sounds. Part of it is very middle range, speech rhythms and the like. But it is never on a beat, and was very hard to learn, because it goes against what you hear in the orchestra.''</p>
        <p>Then there are the incendiary issues at the heart of the opera. ''Dead Man Walking'' deals with the death penalty, and debates forgiveness and redemption for killers. Its themes are the stuff of heated arguments, at the dinner table or in the barroom.</p>
        <p>''I think both positions are represented with great intensity,'' Ms. Graham said. ''But Sister Helen is decidedly against the death penalty, and she gets more air time, so there is a slant in that direction.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Graham, who was born in Roswell, N.M., moved to Midland, Tex., when she was 13. She attended Texas Tech University in Lubbock and earned a master's degree in opera performance at the Manhattan School of Music.</p>
        <p>Her voice is light for a mezzo, her lyric timbre possessing something of a soprano's brightness; she could never be mistaken for a contralto. Her signature roles include Cherubino in Mozart's ''Nozze di Figaro,'' Octavian in Strauss's ''Rosenkavalier,'' Charlotte in Massenet's ''Werther'' and, recently, Iphigenie in Gluck's ''Iphigenie en Tauride.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Graham's performances in ''Rosenkavalier'' have won special praise, as at the Met in January. ''It was as if suddenly everyone had discovered that Octavian is the title character in this opera,'' Ms. Graham said. Bernard Holland, in The New York Times, praised her ''clear, assertive voice,'' adding that she ''looked the perfect Octavian.''</p>
        <p>It was not the first time Ms. Graham's physique received mention. A handsome woman who stands 5 feet 10 inches (not 6 feet, as sometimes reported), she cuts an excellent figure on stage. And although artists can take little credit for what nature bestows, Ms. Graham has used her stature to enrich her portrayals.</p>
        <p>''The thing that matters most to me is realism,'' she said. ''I don't care if I'm playing a 17-year-old boy, an unhappily married woman or a nun.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Graham first gained wide recognition three years ago, with her debut solo recording, a Berlioz recital from Sony Classical, which included ''Les Nuits d'Ete.'' The Sunday Telegraph of London called it ''one of the finest recorded performances of Berlioz's evocative and haunting song cycle.'' Ms. Graham acknowledged that ''it was some sort of turning point.''</p>
        <p>A year later, Sony issued her collection of perfumed songs by Reynaldo Hahn, also well received. Ms. von Stade termed the record ''my idea of sensational singing.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Graham is now under exclusive contract to the French label Erato, which recently released her CD of songs by Ned Rorem. Erato has also issued a live recording of Handel's ''Alcina'' at the Paris Opera with Ms. Graham, Ms. Fleming and the soprano Natalie Dessay. Future discs will offer opera arias by Mozart and Gluck, and selections from French operettas.</p>
        <p>As Ms. Graham looks beyond ''Dead Man Walking,'' she sees, among other things, the challenging role of Dido in a production of Berlioz's ''Troyens'' at the Theatre du Chatelet in Paris in 2004. ''That's the goal, the Everest,'' she said. ''It's the closest you get to singing Wagner without singing Wagner. It contains lyricism, vulnerability, pain and nobility.''</p>
        <p>Much has been written about the recent proliferation of high-profile mezzos, a list that always starts with Cecilia Bartoli and includes singers like Vesselina Kasarova, Jennifer Larmore and Anne Sofie von Otter. Never, surely, have more of them simultaneously occupied a place in the public consciousness. Yet Ms. Graham is unfazed by what some might consider competition.</p>
        <p>''There have been lots of mezzos throughout my career,'' she said. ''But everyone has her own specialty. Only Vesselina and Anne Sofie overlap somewhat with me, and so much neglected material has been rediscovered.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Graham is probably right. Changing conditions require recalibrated expectations. And with new operas like ''Dead Man Walking'' favoring mezzos over sopranos, this voice type has obviously attained increased status. As Ms. Graham put it, ''I guess we're Eve Arden no more.''</p>
        <p>MUSIC David Mermelstein writes about music for The New Criterion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Mermelstein writes about music for The New Criterion.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
