<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Workshop's Bounty: Fellowship, Feedback</title>
    <meta content="01PLAY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234976"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Theater Artists Workshop (Westport, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minor, E Kyle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D6123AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Workshop's Bounty: Fellowship, Feedback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Minor, E Kyle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Theater Artists Workshop of Westport, Conn, where playwrights can try out new material and get feedback from peers; photos (Special Issue: Entertainment) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT separates playwrights from novelists, poets and artists? Chilton Ryan, the president of the Theater Artists Workshop of Westport, says it is collaboration.</p>
        <p>''A sculptor can just go into a room and work alone,'' said Mr. Ryan, who lives in Wilton. ''A playwright eventually needs actors. Our workshop is a gymnasium where playwrights can work out.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT separates playwrights from novelists, poets and artists? Chilton Ryan, the president of the Theater Artists Workshop of Westport, says it is collaboration.</p>
        <p>''A sculptor can just go into a room and work alone,'' said Mr. Ryan, who lives in Wilton. ''A playwright eventually needs actors. Our workshop is a gymnasium where playwrights can work out.''</p>
        <p>Doug Scott, a member of the workshop since 1984, described the group as ''a great big sandbox to play in,'' and said, ''It's absolutely the best thing a writer can be involved with.''</p>
        <p>During the last 17 years, Connecticut has seen lots of playwrights' sandboxes come and go, but none have persisted like the Theater Artists Workshop of Westport. Though the annual National Playwrights Conference, at the Eugene O'Neill Center Theater in Waterford, is better known, it is conveneed only during the summer. The Theater Artists Workshop, on the other hand, has met nearly every week since Valentine's Day 1983. Its playwrights have the chance to try out new material with the help of professional actors and directors ''at no risk,'' Mr. Ryan said.</p>
        <p>''David Wiltse came in one day with 20 pages just to hear if he wanted to continue with it,'' he said. ''He liked what he heard and it became 'Doubles,' which went on to become a Broadway hit.''</p>
        <p>Theater Artists Workshop of Westport was formed by a handful of professionals: Keir Dullea, Susie Fuller, Sandy Dennis, Morton DaCosta, Jerome Kilty, Burry Fredrik, Patricia Englund and Haila Stoddard among them. They wanted to create a workshop where they could sharpen their skills between plays and movies.</p>
        <p>The workshop has persevered in spite of a steady change of membership as well as an unwelcome change of venue a few years ago.</p>
        <p>The workshop now consists of more than 100 theater professionals, Mr. Ryan said. ''We have about 15 to 20 writers, about 20 directors and the rest are mostly actors,'' he said. ''Some of our actors have turned out to be good writers too.''</p>
        <p>Danny Magee, whose play ''Paddywhack'' was produced at Long Wharf Theater six years ago before going Off Broadway, said he enjoyed the self-contained nature of the workshop.</p>
        <p>''All of the performers are drawn from within the workshop,'' he said. ''A writer can arrange with particular actors to work on their script at any time, it being up to the participants to arrange when and how they get there. Every member has access to the premises 24 hours a day, so rehearsals can be done when it suits everyone involved.''</p>
        <p>On other occasions, Mr. Magee said, actors come at a moment's notice to do something. ''In fact, one of the members introduced the idea of ''the word of the week,'' where a word is designated and anyone who wishes can write a brief script using that particular word in any way they choose,'' he said. ''The following week actors are chosen or volunteer to perform the piece. The element of short notice in this exercise is both deliberate and productive.''</p>
        <p>The workshop is organized yet casual, Mr. Ryan said. ''There's no guru, nobody telling anybody else what they must do,'' he said. ''If a playwright wants to hear a new scene, or an actor wants to try a scene, they book the slot.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Magee said that he learned more about his work when it was read by professional actors. ''I find real value in watching actors doing things, which they are doing for their own actor reasons, which points out weaknesses or strengths in the scripts they are using,'' he said. ''So, although the particular piece of work is not being done with my requirements in mind, it can still be informative and useful to me as a writer.''</p>
        <p>An open critique follows each scene, unless members say they ''are just stretching their theatrical legs,'' Mr. Magee said.</p>
        <p>''It also happens that a writer feels they'd like their work to be given a limited airing in front of the public,'' he said. ''On these occasions, there is a reading given on a Friday evening, which is open to anyone.''</p>
        <p>While the criticism is supposed to constructive, the feedback sessions can grow tense. The urge to tell a playwright how best to revise his or her work is sometimes irresistible. ''I will sometimes lose sleep trying to figure out how I will rewrite someone else's play,'' Mr. Scott said.</p>
        <p>William F. Brown, the librettist of ''The Wiz,'' said that sometimes a playwright's head can spin from the suggestions. ''You really have to know how to take the feedback,'' he said. ''I'd tape it. Then I'd pick the things I thought would help.''</p>
        <p>Besides the fellowship and feedback, playwrights benefit from the connections found within the workshop. Because so many accomplished professionals have been involved with the workshop, playwrights often have access to productions that outsiders miss.</p>
        <p>'' 'Doubles' is the only play from the workshop to be produced on Broadway,' Mr. Ryan said. ''Many other plays have been done in regional theater, though.''</p>
        <p>After the workshop, another of Mr. Wiltse's plays, ''Triangles for Two,'' recently had its premiere at Westport Country Playhouse. Mr. Scott's play about Justice William O. Douglas, ''Mountain,'' had its premiere at Lucille Lortel's White Barn Theater in Westport in 1984 before eventually moving to the Lortel Theater Off Broadway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Magee said that his latest play, ''The Prodigal,'' was given a staged reading at the Festival of Irish Arts and Letters at Fairfield University's Quick Center for the Arts as a direct result of the workshop.</p>
        <p>''The event was thanks largely to June Walker-Rogers, a talented director who took an interest in my work through the workshop,'' said Mr. Magee, adding that ''The Prodigal'' is scheduled for production next year in London, with the possibility of a transfer to the United States.</p>
        <p>While the playwrights of the Theater Artists Workshop cannot always count on having their work produced in top-flight theaters, they can rely on the weekly collaboration with other professionals.</p>
        <p>''It's so much better than writing in a garret,'' Mr. Scott said. ''Would that every theater had one.''</p>
        <p>Admission to the Westport Artists Workshop is by audition, script submission or by a substantial body of recognized professional work. The number to call for more information is (203) 854-6812.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
