<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Truer Than History</title>
    <meta content="01MCGRAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vidal, Gore</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgrath, Charles</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Golden Age, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFD9103BF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Truer Than History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Charles McGrath</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgrath, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Phone conversation with author Gore Vidal, who comments on his latest book, The Golden Age; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since 1972, Gore Vidal has split his time between Ravello, in Italy, and a house in the Hollywood Hills -- which means, he likes to say, that arguably he no longer lives in the United States. He was here for the conventions, however, and returned last month for the revival of his play ''The Best Man'' at the Virginia Theater. The following conversation took place, by phone, when he was briefly back in Italy.</p>
        <p>Q. ''The Golden Age,'' your new book, is the last in a sequence of historical novels that began with ''Burr''?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since 1972, Gore Vidal has split his time between Ravello, in Italy, and a house in the Hollywood Hills -- which means, he likes to say, that arguably he no longer lives in the United States. He was here for the conventions, however, and returned last month for the revival of his play ''The Best Man'' at the Virginia Theater. The following conversation took place, by phone, when he was briefly back in Italy.</p>
        <p>Q. ''The Golden Age,'' your new book, is the last in a sequence of historical novels that began with ''Burr''?</p>
        <p>A. Chronologically it was ''Burr.'' But the first to be written was ''Washington, D.C.,'' which takes place during the New Deal.</p>
        <p>Q. This one takes place, for the most part, between 1939 and 1945, so it's set in the even more recent past. It's history that at least some of your readers will remember, and in fact you yourself were there for some of it. Does that make a difference?</p>
        <p>A. Well, yes, it makes it very different. At times you sort of feel like a voyeur looking at people, particularly at older people whom you knew as a child, who'd come to the house -- people like Alice Longworth or Eleanor Roosevelt, who lived on and on into my adult life. There was a lot of actually trying to discover who they were.</p>
        <p>Q. A subtheme of the book is the nature of history itself, and how history exists perhaps not so much in the making as in the writing. In one scene Harry Truman even says something to that effect. Is that how you see it?</p>
        <p>A. I think we're in Pontius Pilate land -- what is history other than a narrative that is being reported?</p>
        <p>I use the phrase, which drives some academics crazy, ''agreed-upon facts.'' They like to think there are real facts when, actually, nearly everything can be contested.</p>
        <p>I would never have written this series had American history not been so badly taught in the schools -- including Phillips Exeter Academy, my school, as well. Luckily, I had a very good history teacher -- certainly better than the textbook, by a Mr. Muzzey, a kind of Ivory Soap version of Mount Rushmore.</p>
        <p>Because of what I had learned of history growing up with my grandfather, Senator T. P. Gore, in Washington, I was skeptical of official versions. The official narrator always has one story to tell and, often, a story to suppress. To look for what is not told is the adventure.</p>
        <p>Q. So in some ways, as you say in the afterword, historical novels may be truer than official history?</p>
        <p>A. Some of them, certainly. Did you read Frances FitzGerald's book on American history textbooks for high schools? For those writers, our history is nothing but the ongoing absorption of happy minorities into a more perfect whole.</p>
        <p>Novels set in history ought to stay with the agreed-upon facts. But, sometimes, when the facts give out, one can draw upon intuition. For instance, the Burr-Hamilton relationship. The latest biographer of Burr has come to the conclusion that my guess was right about the despicable act that Hamilton ascribes to Burr -- it was, very likely, an accusation of incest with his daughter.</p>
        <p>In theory, the historian needs a smoking gun -- or at least the appearance of one that other historians for the moment subscribe to -- while the novelist may speculate, within reason.</p>
        <p>Q. Not so much in this book, but elsewhere, you've taken a dim view, shall we say, of literary culture now and of the health of the novel. And yet you persist in writing novels.</p>
        <p>A. Well, I'm a novelist. Novelists write novels. We have just as many talented novelists today as we ever had. But we all know the problem. Bright kids don't read as we did. Video games are popular. And so on. But that has nothing to do with me. I keep on writing as if it were a golden age.</p>
        <p>Every now and then I think, rather wistfully, about the theater. Then I think about Tennessee Williams's last nightmare years, trying to get produced: ''I sent the play to Gadge. Marlon hasn't returned my call.'' I don't know how even young playwrights endure the process. At least the novelist is solitary.</p>
        <p>Q. What did you make of the conventions?</p>
        <p>A. Hugely expensive commercials for products no one wants, voluntarily, to buy.</p>
        <p>Everything is now money. To pay for TV in order to raise hard and soft money on TV, to pay for more TV. Networks, cable, etc. should be obliged to provide free time nationally and locally and no candidate should be able to buy time during, let's say, an eight-week election period. Civilized countries do this.</p>
        <p>Q. One of the things we learn from ''The Golden Age'' is that TV coverage of the conventions had begun as early as 1940.</p>
        <p>A. Oh yeah, and weird things began to happen.</p>
        <p>You'd have these great orators -- you know, the ''Out of the Monongahela Valley strode a man'' sort. And you'd see him, at a distance, up there with long hair, sweeping gestures. Then, in a close shot, you'd see what looked like Boris Karloff about to strangle a child. The orator was used to projecting this huge voice and face to 10,000 people and he'd never been seen in close-up before.</p>
        <p>So a whole generation of politicians was swept away after that convention, never to be seen again. Same thing happened earlier with radio -- orators used to boom and howl. Then F.D.R. mastered low-key radio.</p>
        <p>So a lot of things have changed. Of course, we've always been reasonably corrupt. That is the price of democracy, and a small amount does no great harm. But when it is totally accepted that he who pays the most money to buy the most time is going to be the president, or at least the nominee, I think something is off the rails.</p>
        <p>INTERVIEW Charles McGrath is the editor of the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Charles McGrath is the editor of the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
