<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Picking Up a Path Trod by Sibelius And Even Haydn</title>
    <meta content="01GRIF$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/arts/01GRIF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Orchestra</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindberg, Magnus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Griffiths, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DC133AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1259" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Picking Up a Path Trod by Sibelius And Even Haydn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL GRIFFITHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Griffiths, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of contemporary composer Magnus Lindberg, whose new work, Cantigas, will be performed by Cleveland Orchestra at Carnegie Hall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMONG the great crowd of composers working at the moment, the spotlight of current events falls just now on the brilliantly accomplished Magnus Lindberg.</p>
        <p>On Thursday evening at Carnegie Hall, the Cleveland Orchestra, conducted by Christoph von Dohnanyi, will play the new orchestral piece it commissioned from him, ''Cantigas.'' Deutsche Grammophon, meanwhile, has released a CD offering ''Aura,'' an earlier piece of his for big orchestra, and ''Engine,'' for a smaller ensemble, both in performances conducted by Oliver Knussen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMONG the great crowd of composers working at the moment, the spotlight of current events falls just now on the brilliantly accomplished Magnus Lindberg.</p>
        <p>On Thursday evening at Carnegie Hall, the Cleveland Orchestra, conducted by Christoph von Dohnanyi, will play the new orchestral piece it commissioned from him, ''Cantigas.'' Deutsche Grammophon, meanwhile, has released a CD offering ''Aura,'' an earlier piece of his for big orchestra, and ''Engine,'' for a smaller ensemble, both in performances conducted by Oliver Knussen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindberg, who was born 42 years ago in Helsinki, has played a central role in the renaissance of Finnish music that came along a century after Sibelius. Among his student friends was Esa-Pekka Salonen, now the music director of the Los Angeles Philharmonic, and the two gained a lot of their important early musical experiences performing in Ears Open, an exploratory ensemble, with other young musicians.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindberg is also a contemporary of the Finnish composer Kaija Saariaho, and like her, he went to Paris in the 1980's to work at Ircam, Pierre Boulez's electronic music institute, and meet the French composers, notably Gerard Grisey and Tristan Murail, who were associated with ''spectral'' music: music with extreme, dense and rich harmonies composed on the model of the overtones in natural resonances.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Lindberg belongs to a wider community of composers. Like such American colleagues as John Adams, Augusta Read Thomas, Peter Lieberson and Gerald Levinson, he has been finding ways to recapture the drive, colorfulness and amplitude of music just before modernism. This has been one of the strongest tendencies in the music of the last 20 years, to join hands with Mahler, with early Stravinsky, with Ravel or -- in Mr. Lindberg's case, especially -- with Sibelius.</p>
        <p>The link with Sibelius seems to irk Mr. Lindberg a little, no doubt because he does not want to be defined as a Finnish composer, working within a narrow national tradition. Yet the connection is unmistakable. There are points in ''Aura'' and ''Engine'' where one feels, as powerfully as in Sibelius, the swell of harmony striving to erupt from underneath, to break through to a point of culmination. And it is in speaking about Sibelius that Mr. Lindberg is most eloquent about his own music.</p>
        <p>''While his language was far from modern, his thinking, as far as form and the treatment of materials is concerned, was ahead of its time,'' Mr. Lindberg has said. ''In his last symphonic works the development and thematic work are particularly interesting. Each theme gives rise to another, according to genuine cycles of metamorphosis. The work -- the whole work -- is in perpetual evolution.''</p>
        <p>This sounds like ''Aura,'' or like the new ''Cantigas.'' Mr. Lindberg does not use themes; he remains too committed to his modernist background for that, too unwilling to abandon altogether his student enthusiasm for Karlheinz Stockhausen, Luciano Berio and Milton Babbitt. But his music conveys a feeling of continuous, urgent movement onward, thanks in particular to the way each emphatic harmony presses forward into the next. The music is filled with strong arrows of direction and gleaming points of arrival. It also draws at times on the dynamo of pulsation and reiteration, inherited from Minimalism, and, more rarely now, on the force of flung blocks of tone, of strident dissonances, reminiscent of Edgard Varese.</p>
        <p>Varese was a more prominent model in the work that made Mr. Lindberg's reputation when he was still in his mid-20's: ''Kraft'' (1983-85), a piece of heavy metal for symphony orchestra with percussion soloists. From there Mr. Lindberg turned to investigating the softer substances in his musical makeup -- the sea foams and the thick carpets -- and developing a virtuosity in orchestral writing that few of his contemporaries can rival.</p>
        <p>He also turned out to have a rare sense of humor. For though his music will often suggest immense machines in sound, what those machines are prone to produce is pure comedy. Like Stravinsky, Mr. Lindberg appreciates the clowning capabilities of bassoons -- in the first movement of ''Aura,'' for example -- and the big climax of that work's second movement comes with Oriental gong crashes that sound at once weird and jokey.</p>
        <p>''Aura,'' in four movements, both is and is not a symphony. ''I believe the overall form of 'Aura' would make it appropriate to call the piece a symphony,'' Mr. Lindberg has written. ''Still it is not a symphony.''</p>
        <p>Why not? Perhaps because of its playfulness and its luminous high color. For symphonies that are such fun, one has to look back to Haydn; for symphonies so gorgeous, to Scriabin. Mr. Lindberg -- who likes to think of himself as a classicist, and whose music cheerfully overturns all notions of musical history as progressive -- stands somewhere between those composers, or to the side, with Sibelius and Stravinsky flanking him.</p>
        <p>With him, as with other contemporary artists, the magic window into the past is the computer, and what it shows has a glowing unreality. His father was a computer engineer, and Mr. Lindberg grew up with computers in the house, able to program with as much facility as he could play the piano. But though he has now and again used computer techniques of electronic sound synthesis -- whether in preparing music on tape or in making instrumental parts to be played on keyboard synthesizers -- his most regular recourse to the digital world has been to help him in handling harmonic progressions.</p>
        <p>A personal harmonic labyrinth, built up over the years, has given him the means to parallel what Haydn and Scriabin could accomplish with the language of tonality that had stored itself in their internal hard drives. The computer provides a cleaner memory. Diving into it, Mr. Lindberg can come up with the athletic and assured strategies of music performed entirely on traditional instruments.</p>
        <p>In the case of ''Cantigas,'' the labyrinth is entered at the door of one of the most elementary intervals: the perfect fifth -- the bare fifth that was the basic concord of medieval music. The title alludes to this, to the ''cantigas,'' or songs, of medieval Spain, but it also suggests that the work is composed of songs happening now, in the orchestra.</p>
        <p>In half a minute, at the start, the music has zoomed from the simple fifth of the 12th century, sung by a solo oboe, to a piling-up of fifths that make a modern 10-note chord, swung forward as the first marker in the harmonic journey.</p>
        <p>From that point the music is off, careering with Mr. Lindberg's characteristic ebullience and propulsion, often at the energetic high speeds that are also typical of his music. But there are moments for reflection, too, and for perhaps a new and firmer melodic definition. By the end, the oboe, now playing with its companion, has learned to sing a far more extravagant kind of song: the kind of song, maybe, that will come in the opera Mr. Lindberg has long been promising.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
