<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Founding Villains</title>
    <meta content="01EVERDET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1234916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Everdell, William R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jennings, Francis</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Creation of America, The: Through Revolution to Empire (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFDA103BF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1107" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Founding Villains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William R. Everdell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Everdell, William R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Everdell reviews book The Creation of America: Through Revolution to Empire by Francis Jennings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Creation of America</p>
        <p>Through Revolution to Empire.</p>
        <p>By Francis Jennings.</p>
        <p>340 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Cambridge University Press.</p>
        <p>Cloth, $54.95. Paper, $19.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Creation of America</p>
        <p>Through Revolution to Empire.</p>
        <p>By Francis Jennings.</p>
        <p>340 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Cambridge University Press.</p>
        <p>Cloth, $54.95. Paper, $19.95.</p>
        <p>WE all know how men of integrity risked their lives, rose against taxes and other oppressions and created a free and independent democratic republic in North America around 1776. Or do we? For the American historian Francis Jennings, this is ''the Revolutionary fairy tale.'' Historians have long known better, thanks in part to Jennings's own patient labor on the Revolution's distant origins. ''The Creation of America,'' which extends Jennings's history to 1787, not only leaves all the inconvenient chips and cracks in the heroic profiles of the founders, it shows how a whole new history can be made out of them. John Hancock, who fled the oncoming redcoats at Lexington, embraced the patriot cause in part because he was the biggest smuggler in Boston and would have lost his shirt on import taxes. Henry Laurens acted in part to protect his interest as the biggest slave trader in Charleston, S.C. Ben Franklin, the most democratically inclined of all the founders, did his best to preserve the value of prewar land grabs after the British proclaimed Indian property west of the Appalachians off limits to colonials (or assigned it to Roman Catholic Quebec). So did George Washington, who by 1773 had managed to illegally accumulate more than 20,000 acres of land originally set aside for his enlisted men in areas that did not really belong to Virginia.</p>
        <p>Long since retired after a distinguished career, Jennings has tried to sum up a lifetime of learning here, but it is not comfortable learning, and it is very far from what local school boards call ''heritage.'' He began upsetting historiography 25 years ago in a book with the memorably contentious title ''The Invasion of America: Indians, Colonialism and the Cant of Conquest.'' Then came ''The Ambiguous Iroquois Empire'' and ''Empire of Fortune,'' which took the story up to 1763, the canonical end of the colonial period, and completed a trilogy called the ''Covenant Chain'' (after the Iroquois diplomatic network). The trilogy remains, to some extent, the definitive work on how Britain and its colonies, or, as they are called on the left, ''colonial settler states,'' created a North American empire.</p>
        <p>''The Creation of America'' extends the trilogy through the framing of the Constitution in 1787, and it presents the American Revolution as fundamentally a war for imperial succession. Independence for the United States meant independence for each state, which meant local sovereignty over the only wealth that counted in the 18th century -- land -- and a warrant for each settler to take as much of it as possible at the expense of Indians and Africans, without regard to equality, democracy or, all too often, liberty.</p>
        <p>''The Creation of America'' can also be read as a valedictory -- Jennings's final attempt to frame for a general readership, and perhaps even for the public at large, what he and other revisionist historians have learned about the prehistory of American imperialism, racism and aristocracy. National reading scores and history standards suggest that the general public might never get wind of this newly realistic Revolution, much less digest it. A rare big-budget movie on the American Revolution, ''The Patriot,'' did not do as well as anticipated. That might have something to do with the unbelievability of its hero, a white man employing free black labor for wages in 1776 in South Carolina. In fact there were such men, but the first ''enemies'' the patriotic rebels of South Carolina killed in 1775 were unarmed escaped slaves in Charleston harbor.</p>
        <p>Americans have been uneasy about the imperial, aristocratic, racist side of their goodly heritage for centuries. Vietnam, which had a profound effect on Jennings's own thinking, brought this uneasiness into the open. Like any other mature people (and not only the Germans), we must now ask ourselves what can we do about the parts of our history of which we can no longer be proud. Do we litigate and politicize them in the present, or suppress them in hopes they will go away -- like the rest of the past? Do we repent of them publicly like the South Africans, or disown them like the Yugoslavs or rationalize them like the Europeans? Half a century ago, Edmund Wilson wrote ''Apologies to the Iroquois,'' but the imperial Iroquois did not reply. In 1777, the Six Nations gave up on their vast system of multicultural diplomacy and, as Jennings puts it, ''the great League council fire at Onondaga was 'covered.' ''Two years later an American ''patriot'' force laid waste to the neat New York farming villages of the Iroquois, burning their crops to the ground; in 1783 many of them moved to a territory the British offered them in Canada.</p>
        <p>Considering how noble revisionist history can be, one would like to say that Jennings's last volume treats it commensurately, but it doesn't. Jennings's authority as a historian and his trustworthiness as a researcher are hardly in question, even less his contentiousness and suspicion of human motives -- qualities he shares with the great novelists and the Puritans themselves. The one-sidedness of the resulting account will be a problem only for the rare reader who does not know all the other sides: that the revolutionaries were as civic-minded as they were selfish, taking risks not just for themselves but for others; that they were not only imperialists but also republicans who hated one-man rule; and that the disparagers of democracy were also lovers of liberty, who attacked religious tests and summary justice more often than they imposed them.</p>
        <p>But with any number of sides, this book would not make good on Jennings's promise of a fully reconstructed revisionist account of the American Revolution ''for adults.'' The seams show too much. Jennings repeatedly interrupts the narrative flow by his short, partly analytical chapters, revisited incidents in inverted chronologies and historiographical asides. Instead of newly telling the Revolution, Jennings tells you why conservative historians have mistakenly perpetuated the old one. Or how revisionists have provided materials toward the new one.</p>
        <p>One revisionist, Theodore Draper, whom Jennings generously singles out several times for credit, has written exactly the successful revisionist narrative history for which Jennings has so long been clearing the ground -- A Struggle for Power: The American Revolution.'' The debt, however, is entirely mutual. Draper is only one of dozens of historians and many thousands of students of the past 20 years who are very much obliged to Francis Jennings.</p>
        <p>William R. Everdell teaches history at St. Ann's School in Brooklyn and is the author of ''The End of Kings: A History of Republics and Republicans.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William R. Everdell teaches history at St. Ann's School in Brooklyn and is the author of ''The End of Kings: A History of Republics and Republicans.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
