<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation: Debatable; What to Do With All That Money</title>
    <meta content="01SANG$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/weekinreview/01SANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E4D8173DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation: Debatable; What to Do With All That Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>What to do with federal budget surpluses will likely be major topic of upcoming presidential campaign debate between Al Gore and George W Bush; various proposals discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE presidential debates of 1960 are best remembered today for the contrast between a tanned, youthful-looking John F. Kennedy and a pasty, sweaty-looking Richard M.  Nixon.</p>
        <p>What has been forgotten is that the 1960 debates were also the last occasions on which two presidential candidates argued at length about what to do with a government surplus, and whether it made sense to pay down America's debts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE presidential debates of 1960 are best remembered today for the contrast between a tanned, youthful-looking John F. Kennedy and a pasty, sweaty-looking Richard M.  Nixon.</p>
        <p>What has been forgotten is that the 1960 debates were also the last occasions on which two presidential candidates argued at length about what to do with a government surplus, and whether it made sense to pay down America's debts.</p>
        <p>It has been 40 years since a surplus intersected with a presidential election (though there was one balanced budget, in 1969) and far, far longer since there was any hope of paying off a debt that has now swelled to $3.63 trillion.</p>
        <p>Yet what to do with that opportunity will likely dominate Tuesday night's arguments, when Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore face off. Mr. Bush has not backed off a tax cut plan that has made some in his party so queasy that they have come up with their own, more modest proposals. And Mr. Gore has learned that even if paying down the national debt is, as one of his advisers puts it, ''an eat-your-broccoli message,'' it seems to be registering in the polls.</p>
        <p>In their more candid moments, Mr. Gore's strategists concede that the Clinton administration stumbled into debt reduction. Mr. Clinton used a State of the Union address to declare that America's mission was to ''save Social Security first,'' which was little more than a tactic for fending off Republican tax cuts. It worked.</p>
        <p>''To this day,'' said Robert L. Bixby, executive director of the Concord Coalition, a bipartisan fiscal watchdog group, ''most people still don't understand that using the surplus to shore up Social Security just means debt reduction.''</p>
        <p>He's right. Since the government doesn't have a savings account, any money that doesn't get spent is automatically used to buy back outstanding debt. (This may be the first time an accounting rule created a huge political following.) And it is not getting spent precisely because of that much-maligned Washington trait: gridlock.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing more American than to say your budget should be balanced and you should be paying off your debts,'' said Robert Reischauer, president of the Urban Institute and a former director of the Congressional Budget Office. ''But of course, what debt reduction really does is keep the money out of the hands of the other party, to spend on its priorities. It's everyone's second choice.''</p>
        <p>True, but a very popular second choice. So popular that both Democrats and Republicans in the House overwhelmingly approved legislation two weeks ago that would commit this year's surpluses to pay down debt. And President Clinton, beating the drum for his own legacy and Mr. Gore's candidacy, stepped out of the White House on Wednesday morning armed with a big magic marker to declare that the government's fiscal year was ending with a $230 billion surplus -- and that all but $7 billion of it would be used to pay down debt.</p>
        <p>That puts the United States on track to paying off the debt by 2012, Mr. Clinton said. By remarkable coincidence, Mr. Gore's plan sets the same date.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's plan would also pay off the debt, only in 2016. But he doesn't talk about it much, preferring instead to dwell on tax cuts that seem drawn from the playbook of Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, as Mr. Gore continues to portray himself as the man who will lift the debt off  the shoulders of the nation's children, Mr. Bush  has to make the case that under his plan Americans can have their big tax cuts and eat their  debt, too.</p>
        <p>''Bush is caught caught between a rock and a hard place,'' said Mr. Reischauer, ''because he wants to establish individual accounts for Social Security, and those will be funded out of the Social Security surplus. So there will be less debt paydown.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's advisers, not surprisingly, look at the numbers differently, arguing that Mr. Gore's surplus is a phantom that will disappear after Election Day. Mr. Gore, meanwhile, is betting on the analogy he believes Americans will make between debt reduction and the way they would like to manage their own household budgets. ''No one can relate to a $2 trillion budget,'' Mr. Bixby said. ''But they can understand that when you have a big expense coming up -- kids going to college, or retirement -- it makes sense to get rid of your debts.''</p>
        <p>Here it is the voters, not the politicians, who may be engaging in election-year hypocrisy. One of the strongest arguments for paying down the government's debt is that Americans are running up their private debts. And the two are related: If the government and its citizens are both borrowing, they are competing for the same cash. That sends interest rates higher.</p>
        <p>There are other virtues in paying down the debt. If the economy turns down sometime in the next few years, Washington will have more room to stimulate the economy, either with tax cuts or spending. Treasury Secretary Lawrence Summers calls that ''loading the cannon,'' and warns of the dangers of shooting it off too early.</p>
        <p>But other economists make the case that too much debt reduction can be, well, too much of a good thing.</p>
        <p>Virtuous as paying down the debt may be, it is not necessarily the best use of the government's money. Mr. Bush's tax cuts could, arguably, put more money in the stock market, where it would be available to old and new companies for research and new technologies. (If those cuts come too soon, though, they could also overstimulate an economy and a stock market that many fear is still flying too high, forcing the Federal Reserve to raise interest rates even more.) Or maybe the return on investment would be better if the money was spent on education. After all, a well-trained software engineer -- or 10 million of them -- can foster a lot of growth.</p>
        <p>So in the end, perhaps the most interesting question for Tuesday's debate won't even be asked. It is, to be fair, a technical query: What is the optimal debt for the United States? Elections don't often turn on arcane arguments over such issues. The country's economic future, however, may.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
