<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mets Receive a Boost From a Farmhand</title>
    <meta content="01METS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/sports/01METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montreal Expos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3D9153DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mets Receive a Boost From a Farmhand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Montreal Expos, 4-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tension has disappeared. The Mets are playing carefree and spirited baseball for the first time in a month. It is happening immediately after they clinched the National League wild card, and that is not a coincidence.</p>
        <p>''We're sharp right now; we look good,'' pitcher Mike Hampton said after the Mets beat the Montreal Expos, 4-2, yesterday on a three-run double by Jorge Toca in the eighth inning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tension has disappeared. The Mets are playing carefree and spirited baseball for the first time in a month. It is happening immediately after they clinched the National League wild card, and that is not a coincidence.</p>
        <p>''We're sharp right now; we look good,'' pitcher Mike Hampton said after the Mets beat the Montreal Expos, 4-2, yesterday on a three-run double by Jorge Toca in the eighth inning.</p>
        <p>''The clubhouse is loose, and that's a big thing. You kind of tense up; you want to win so bad. Well, we're playing our best ball when there's nothing to play for, because we're in the playoffs. If we can just realize that and go out and just play the game, we'll be all right.''</p>
        <p>Of course, Hampton does not know how to take that relaxed approach into the Mets' playoff series with the San Francisco Giants, which begins Wednesday at Pacific Bell Park. He went to the playoffs three years in a row with the Houston Astros, who lost in the first round each time.</p>
        <p>''You get there, and everybody tries so hard,'' Hampton said. ''The biggest thing is you can't worry about personal stuff, your batting average or E.R.A. It's really got to be an unselfish time.''</p>
        <p>To that end, Hampton and Al Leiter both say it does not matter which of them starts the first game of the playoffs.</p>
        <p>They will pitch the first two games; Rick Reed will start today and go two or three innings in preparation for his playoff start, probably in Game 3 at Shea Stadium on Saturday. Manager Bobby Valentine said he did not think he would start Reed in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>But Valentine and General Manager Steve Phillips have been silent publicly on who will get the call for Game 1, even though they have decided.</p>
        <p>As for Game 4, Glendon Rusch pitched five solid innings today and could make the start, but so could Bobby J. Jones. The candidates have not been told.</p>
        <p>''I just hope we know before we get on the plane,'' Leiter said.</p>
        <p>Leiter, who had been scheduled to start today, suspects Hampton will pitch Game 1 -- and a fifth game, if necessary -- because of the way the two react to extra rest.</p>
        <p>If Hampton pitches the opener, he will have his usual four days of rest. Leiter would then start Game 2 on eight days' rest, which he welcomes because he relies more on throwing hard and exerting himself physically.</p>
        <p>''He's learned to pitch better being a little bit more tired,'' Leiter said of Hampton, who shut out the Expos for five innings Friday. ''Yesterday, he threw five scoreless, and he was sinking his fastball, ranging the fastball from 83 to 90. He does that well. If you give rest to somebody who doesn't need or want the extra rest in a big game, he's going to overthrow. For somebody like that, who relies on keeping the ball down and sinking it, you elevate the ball.''</p>
        <p>Hampton said he was similar to Leiter early in his career, when he threw harder more often and thus could benefit from more rest. Now, he said, it does not really matter.</p>
        <p>''It's fine to have extra rest, but if I don't, I don't see the problem,'' Hampton said.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's game had the feel of spring training, right down to the guest appearance by the Expos, the Mets' spring neighbors. Four Mets relievers worked an inning apiece, just to stay sharp. The regulars stuck around for a few innings, then departed. Valentine put an expanded roster to use, and the hero was a farmhand.</p>
        <p>Toca, a Cuban defector who has spent most of his two professional seasons at Class AAA Norfolk, had his first extra-base hit in nine at-bats with the Mets over the last two Septembers.</p>
        <p>After an intentional walk to Todd Pratt with one out loaded the bases, Toca came up against Javier Vazquez, the right-hander who baffled the Mets two weeks ago and for seven innings yesterday. Toca stroked a changeup to the gap in left-center field, clearing the bases.</p>
        <p>''I faced Vazquez in Puerto Rico before, and he always pitches me the same way,'' Toca said through an interpreter. ''I was prepared and waited for a good pitch to drive.''</p>
        <p>Toca's hit gave the victory to Turk Wendell (8-6), the third in the procession of relievers who followed Rusch. Pat Mahomes and Rick White preceded Wendell, and Armando Benitez followed to earn his 41st save.</p>
        <p>The left-handed Rusch gave up four hits and walked one, and he finished the regular season with a 4.01 earned run average, almost two runs lower than his career E.R.A. coming into this season. Rusch left the game trailing, and Valentine said he was happy the Mets came back. Rusch finished the regular season with an 11-11 record.</p>
        <p>''When it's November or December and I'm home with the family, I'll reflect back and definitely feel good about what I've accomplished this year,'' Rusch said. ''I don't think now's really the time to do it.''</p>
        <p>There are more pressing issues just ahead. It is up to the Mets to play as if they do not notice.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Left fielder BENNY AGBAYANI, who has missed a week with a strained right hamstring, had a thorough pregame workout yesterday and Manager BOBBY VALENTINE said he planned to start him today. TIMO PEREZ, Agbayani's replacement, left yesterday's game after feeling tightness in his right hamstring while running the bases in the first inning. Perez, who has almost certainly played his way onto the postseason roster, should not miss the playoffs because of the injury. ''It doesn't look that way now,'' Valentine said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
