<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shredding the Concept of 'Deadbeat Dads'</title>
    <meta content="01JOUR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Women For Fatherhood (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blake, Kasey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miles, Carolyn L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fischler, Marcelle S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Divorce, Separations and Annulments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EEDB113AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1684" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shredding the Concept of 'Deadbeat Dads'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE S. FISCHLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fischler, Marcelle S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Journal column: stay-at-home mom Kasey Blake of Setauket has formed organzation, Women for Fatherhood, in effort to empower blended families, find peaceful solutions to anger and bickering, put children first and improve image of divorced fathers; Carolyn L Miles of Huntington Station, self-described former crack and cocaine addict and recovering alcoholic, has turned to writing made-to-order poems; excerpt; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PAY, pay, pay. That's what divorced fathers are forced to do, said Sari Friedman, a matrimonial lawyer in Garden City with a mostly male clientele. Even divorced fathers who are nurturing, devoted and involved with their children's lives. They, too, are sometimes treated like wallets.</p>
        <p>Just ask Kasey Blake, a stay-at-home mom from Setauket. Mrs. Blake does not think she's a victim. She's just a second wife.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PAY, pay, pay. That's what divorced fathers are forced to do, said Sari Friedman, a matrimonial lawyer in Garden City with a mostly male clientele. Even divorced fathers who are nurturing, devoted and involved with their children's lives. They, too, are sometimes treated like wallets.</p>
        <p>Just ask Kasey Blake, a stay-at-home mom from Setauket. Mrs. Blake does not think she's a victim. She's just a second wife.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Blake 39, has been married to Kevin Blake, 39, an office manager, for 10 years. They have a 6-year-old son. Mr. Blake also has a 13-year-old daughter from his first marriage. He dotes on both his children. But his ex-wife, who has remarried, has custody of their daughter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blake says he has always paid his child support on time. His daughter stays with him on alternate weekends, and he has never canceled a visit. Mrs. Blake said she loves her stepdaughter as her own. Yet there is friction. Demands concerning visitation. Not letting Mr. Blake see the girl. Requests for more money.</p>
        <p>''It's like a wound that never heals for anybody,'' Mrs. Blake said. ''It's always there and we are married a long time. It shouldn't be like that, especially when you are doing the right thing with the kid. You love the kid. You embrace her in the family, you pay the child support. You are there all the time to be with her. What is the problem? It's such an adversarial thing. People are so locked in anger and it really hurts the kids so badly. It's like an open wound.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Blake said that many first wives use family court for revenge, as a tool against their ex-spouse, especially if he is happy with someone else and getting on with his life, just to keep making trouble. ''To me, if someone is paying their child support and visiting the child, what else is there to do?'' she said.</p>
        <p>Surfing the Web, Mrs. Blake found other second wives and stepmothers struggling with the same issues. To empower blended families, find peaceful solutions to the anger and bickering, put the children first and improve the image of divorced dads, Mrs. Blake started an organization, Women for Fatherhood. She brought in Ms. Friedman, 43, her husband's lawyer, a staunch advocate for divorced fathers and general counsel to the Fathers Rights Association of  New York and the Fathers Rights Association of Long Island, to help.</p>
        <p>''People are so keyed into believing fathers are these huge villains,'' Mrs. Blake said. ''What happens to all the guys that are good guys? What happens to all the guys who have other families? The system was designed to try and protect people but in the process other people are getting hurt.''</p>
        <p>Over the past three years, membership in Women for Fatherhood has grown to 1,000. There are chapters in North Carolina, Maryland and Ohio, bulletin boards and links to resources on the organization's Web site, www.women4fatherhood.org. The first live meeting of the flagship Long Island chapter will be held on Thursday at 7 p.m. at the Emma Clark Library in Setauket.</p>
        <p>''Because so many people have this perception about fathers, it's always assumed that because my husband is a non-custodial father that he's bad,'' Mrs. Blake said, asserting that the moniker ''deadbeat dad'' need not always apply. ''I felt that there was a skew in the public perception of fathers and a total lack of regard for subsequent children from second marriages.''</p>
        <p>Part of the problem, Ms. Friedman said, is that even though 50 percent of marriages end in divorce, unless it is arranged privately out of court, joint custody is not an option under New York State law.</p>
        <p>''This concept that only women know how to be nurturing and its something that's biologically instilled in you is just incorrect,'' said Ms. Friedman, 43, of Oyster Bay Cove, who has been married for 20 years and considers her husband, Ken, an actuary, a co-parent to their two daughters. ''Fathers can be as nurturing as mothers if they are allowed to be,'' she added. ''It's what society allows them to do. The concept of what a mother is and what a father is from years past, from the 1960's when we had shows like 'Ozzie and Harriet' telling us that Ozzie went to work and Harriet stayed home; it's just not reflective of society today.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Friedman contended that fathers are often treated as second-class citizens by the courts when it comes to rights and decision-making with respect to their children. If they lose their jobs or have been downgraded, they still have to pay. Paralegal support systems and resources offered to divorcing mothers are not readily available to men. And she claimed that statistics show that non-custodial mothers are more often delinquent in child support payments than fathers, yet don't seem to get a bad rap.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blake said he had to go to court to stop his ex-wife from moving out of state. She took him to court to raise support payments. But his ex is working, her new husband is working and as custodial parents, they get the tax write-off for their dependent.</p>
        <p>''The means for the children of her family are greater than the means for your family,'' Mr. Blake said, begrudging the system, not his child. ''I have a responsibility to help support and raise my daughter, but she has all the designer clothes and she is not lacking anything whereas I can't provide that for my son who lives with me. I'm glad she has all those things, but the economic status of the two is not the same.''</p>
        <p>Years ago, Mrs. Blake recalled, when she griped about another increase in the child support her husband would have to pay, a lawyer told her that if she wanted her own child to be considered, she should divorce her husband.</p>
        <p>While society as a whole has shifted, Mrs. Blake added, in the divorce arena, women are pretending it hasn't. ''We want equal pay and we want to be on all equal terms with them on everything else but not on this,'' she said. ''We still want the men to pick up the slack, leave the child rearing to us and give us the money.''</p>
        <p>Poetry for Sale</p>
        <p>When it comes to hawking her poetry, Carolyn L. Miles of Huntington Station can be relentless. At the gas station and the Laundromat, she hands out her ''Poems on the Go'' business card. When she takes her two daughters to the doctor, she pitches her verse. And she has knocked on doors from Port Washington to Riverhead selling customized rhymes.</p>
        <p>''I can put other people's happiness and sadness into words,'' said Ms. Miles, 41, who describes herself as a former crack and cocaine addict and recovering alcoholic who was on welfare for nearly 12 years.</p>
        <p>''Every time I write a poem it eases the pain of someone else. It brings me peace to shed light on someone's else's pain.''</p>
        <p>Determined to write her way off welfare, Ms. Miles turned to written-to-order sentimental verse three  years ago. Since then, she has composed 142 poems.</p>
        <p>Ms. Miles's poems are published in the Women's Center of Huntington newsletter every other month. One was included in the latest issue of Creations magazine, published every two months in Sea Cliff; two were included in books published by the National Library of Poetry in Owings Mills, Md.; and others have appeared in three anthologies.</p>
        <p>This is an excerpt from her poem ''Out of Sadness'':</p>
        <p>She climbed a mountain of broken childhood memories</p>
        <p>Searching for her emerald dreams</p>
        <p>Stopping now and then to mend</p>
        <p>Stones of sadness that did descend</p>
        <p>Under a blanket of snow</p>
        <p>White diamonds of hope</p>
        <p>That once lay silent</p>
        <p>Came to life</p>
        <p>Crystal tears of children</p>
        <p>Rested upon golden leaves</p>
        <p>Of make believe</p>
        <p>Ms. Miles hopes to be able to write full time someday, but in the meantime, she works as an electrical inspector at Comtech PST in Melville.</p>
        <p>Ms. Miles's inspirational verses, printed on scrolls and tied with red bows, have been sold to 22 Long Island businesses, including delis, bagel shops, pet shops, banks and gas stations, where they are handed out instead of calendars.</p>
        <p>But her forte is custom poetry.  ''You can't go into Hallmark and say, 'I just lost my son.' You can't go into Hallmark and say, 'I love my mother so much,' '' Ms. Miles said.</p>
        <p>So she listens to the tales people tell her, then writes odes to their estranged or deceased children, memorials to their parents, in-laws and beloved pets. Framed, her customized verse runs $80; laminated memorials to pets are $85. In bulk, 100 unframed copies run $70.</p>
        <p>As a child, Ms. Miles said, she was sexually abused and shuffled around among aunts and uncles. By age 22, she was addicted to drugs and alcohol, she said. Through the ups and downs over the past 17 years, she has worked in electronics, been counseled at Seafield Alcoholism Treatment Center in Melville and lived at Haven House, a shelter in Huntington.</p>
        <p>''My life growing up was sad,'' she said. ''I had no friends, no one to talk to. I used to go into a corner and write all the time.''</p>
        <p>Recently, Ms. Miles was able to move into a two-bedroom apartment. And she is selling her poetry at local craft fairs. ''Poetry fills in the blanks for the words that don't get said from parent to child,'' she said. ''People keep telling me I have a gift. Everything I write just hits home.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: lijournal@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
