<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Future In N.H.L., But Maybe No Present</title>
    <meta content="01RANG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/sports/01RANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E4D8153DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Future In N.H.L., But Maybe No Present</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses status of young New York Ranger hockey players as team prepares for upcoming season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barring a trade, the future doesn't appear to be now for two 19-year-old Rangers.</p>
        <p>After Friday night's 4-2 loss to the Atlanta Thrashers at Madison Square Garden, Coach Ron Low said he would try to dress his prospective regular-season lineup for today's preseason finale against the Islanders in Hartford, and the two 19-year-olds were not on the list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barring a trade, the future doesn't appear to be now for two 19-year-old Rangers.</p>
        <p>After Friday night's 4-2 loss to the Atlanta Thrashers at Madison Square Garden, Coach Ron Low said he would try to dress his prospective regular-season lineup for today's preseason finale against the Islanders in Hartford, and the two 19-year-olds were not on the list.</p>
        <p>''I want to get as close to our lineup as we can,'' Low said.</p>
        <p>Neither of the teenagers, Pavel Brendl and Jamie Lundmark, will be in the lineup, and that does not bode well for them.</p>
        <p>Lundmark was considered a long shot to make the team, mainly because he missed the second half of last season in the juniors with a broken right wrist.</p>
        <p>The expectations may have been a little higher for Brendl, who was written into the opening-night lineup last fall -- only to play his way out of a spot.</p>
        <p>Brendl, the fourth overall pick in the 1999 draft, started this year's camp slowly, but in his last two games, at left wing, he had a goal and four assists, all on the power play.</p>
        <p>Low seemed impressed with Brendl on Friday night, when he scored his first goal.</p>
        <p>''I thought Pavel was around the puck more tonight in the first period, although he died off a little after that,'' Low said. ''But he does show you that ability to put the puck in the net.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers still have to decide what is best for Brendl, to carry him with the team as an extra forward to start the season or send him back to the juniors in Calgary, where he can play every day but has nothing left to prove.</p>
        <p>The Rangers faced almost the same problem last season with Manny Malhotra. Malhotra, 18, made the team but was caught in a power struggle between Coach John Muckler and the team's president and general manager, Neil Smith. Carried as an extra for most of last season, Malhotra lost his confidence, which he has only now begun to regain.</p>
        <p>Malhotra will be in today's lineup, but only because Mark Messier will not. ''Manny had a great camp, I thought,'' Low said.</p>
        <p>But it is still unclear whether the Rangers will begin the season with Malhotra on their roster as a fourth-line center/left wing or whether he will start at their top minor league affiliate in Hartford, where he can take a regular shift.</p>
        <p>The Rangers would like to have the same options with Brendl and Lundmark, whom they both view as in-betweeners. Brendl and Lundmark are both ready to graduate from the junior leagues, but there is some question in the organization whether they are ready to play in the N.H.L. every day.</p>
        <p>However, under the N.H.L.'s agreement with the junior leagues, neither Brendl nor Lundmark are eligible to start the season in the minor leagues. It is either the N.H.L. or the junior leagues.</p>
        <p>Brendl was asked if he thought he was ready to play in the N.H.L.</p>
        <p>''I hope so,'' he said. ''But I do think I'm in better shape than last year. And I think physically, I'm ready to play here. I just have to think more on the ice.''</p>
        <p>The same question was put to Brendl's two linemates for Friday's game, Petr Nedved and Radek Dvorak. Brendl, Nedved and Dvorak are all from the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>''That's a tough question,'' Dvorak said. ''But the last two games, he's played like he can play in this league. I think he's ready, although it might take him a little bit of time to get used to the pace.''</p>
        <p>Nedved, the Rangers' best player last season, was noncommittal but encouraging. ''I don't know if Pavel's ready, but he has improved himself a lot from camp last year,'' he said. ''I don't think he was ready at all last year. But that is understandable. He was 18. This year, he's shown that he can be dangerous out there. He's got a major league shot; there is no question about that. The question is if he will get the opportunity. But whether he's ready or not, I think he's shown some signs out there that he can be a player in the National Hockey League. It will be interesting to see whether he makes it or not.''</p>
        <p>Brendl said: ''This year, I think I did my best. If not, I'm still 19. I have lots of time.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Injuries to BRIAN LEETCH (groin), RICH PILON (thumb) and DALE PURINTON (biceps) will give MIKE MOTTAU another chance to play today. Mottau is another of the young Rangers bidding to make the team. But because Mottau does not need to clear waivers to play in Hartford, he may begin the season there unless the team president and general manager, GLEN SATHER, can swing a trade.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
