<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="01GUID$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235021"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D8103AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Barbara Delatiner</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Best</p>
        <p>When it comes to tradition, the Long Island Fair is right up there with the most venerable events on the Island. Founded in 1842 and held at first in Hempstead and Mineola, it officially became the Mineola Fair in 1866 when a permanent fairgrounds was built. Then it moved to Roosevelt Field in 1953 when suburban sprawl invaded Mineola. Finally, in 1970 it found a home at the Old Bethpage Village Restoration on Round Swamp Road, where a replica of the original fair exhibition hall opened recently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Best</p>
        <p>When it comes to tradition, the Long Island Fair is right up there with the most venerable events on the Island. Founded in 1842 and held at first in Hempstead and Mineola, it officially became the Mineola Fair in 1866 when a permanent fairgrounds was built. Then it moved to Roosevelt Field in 1953 when suburban sprawl invaded Mineola. Finally, in 1970 it found a home at the Old Bethpage Village Restoration on Round Swamp Road, where a replica of the original fair exhibition hall opened recently.</p>
        <p>Celebrating ''Long Island's Natural and Historical Heritage,'' on Thursday this year's edition opens its six-day run through next Monday. Like most country fairs, it is agricultural in nature. But in addition to livestock and vegetable and flower competitions, it will feature riding and cavalry demonstrations by the ''Rough Riders and Theodore Roosevelt'' (a k a James Foote); horse-drawn wagon rides; the Flying Horses Carousel, a copy of a 19th-century folk art carousel; cross-cut sawing, corn husking and sheep herding contests; entertainment by performers including Skip Gorman, the folk singer; and championship matches of the village's Old Time Base Ball League. The fair is from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. daily (516) 572-8400.</p>
        <p>Come to the Fairs</p>
        <p>While the Long Island Fair is the most extensive seasonal fete this week, five more fall festivals also are on the schedule. Today there are two: the Nature Conservancy's ''Nature's Celebration Festival'' from 11:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. with nature walks, workshops and demonstrations and entertainment at Uplands Farm on Lawrence Hill Road in Cold Spring Harbor. (631) 367-3225, and the 20th annual fall festival and craft show with hay rides, a tractor pull, decoy-carving and rug-hooking demonstrations and entertainment by Morning Star and Buddy Merriam's Backroads, from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. at Hallockville Museum Farm and Folklife Center on Sound Ave in Riverhead (631) 298-5292.</p>
        <p>The weekend brings three events. The Seventh annual Long Island fall festival at Huntington opens Friday at 6 p.m. at Heckscher Park with a performance by the Russian-American Kids Circus and fireworks, and continues from 11 a.m. to 10 p.m. Saturday and 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. next Sunday with entertainment, children's activities, a crafts fair and equine exhibition at the park, and at the harbor on Saturday a 4-K Walk-a-Thon for the local Breast Cancer Coalition and on Sunday a parade of ships (631) 351-1910. Montauk holds its 20th annual fall festival from 10 a.m. to 3 p.m. Saturday and next Sunday with clam chowder, clam-chucking and pumpkin-carving contests, entertainment and hay and pony rides throughout the downtown area. (631) 668-2428. Finally, Deepwells Farm and County Park on Route 25A in St. James holds its fall festival with pony and hay rides, a haybale jump, petting farm and entertainment from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Saturday and next Sunday (631) 862-6080.</p>
        <p>Seasonal Openings</p>
        <p>The Island's two major performing arts venues open this week. In Stony Brook, the Staller Center on the State University campus begins its season today with Judy Collins. Appearing at 7 p.m., she ushers in a year that will also feature Ray Charles, Oct. 21; the Flying Karamazov Brothers, Nov. 5; Chamber Music of Lincoln Center, Nov. 10; and the Sydney Dance Company in ''Salome,'' Nov. 17. On Saturday at 8 p.m., the university's Symphony Orchestra, consisting of graduate students, plays its first concert of the year (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Tilles Center on the C. W. Post campus of Long Island University in Brookville starts its year with ''An Evening With Marvin Hamlisch'' at 8 o'clock. Accompanied by the Concert Pops of Long Island, the composer leads off a season that also will include such performers as Itzhak Perlman and the Mostly Mozart Festival Orchestra headlining ''Gala XX,'' Oct. 14; the United States Air Force and Concert Band and Singing Sergeants in a free concert, Oct. 19; the Tokyo String Quartet, Oct. 28; the New York Philharmonic, Nov. 11; and James Galway and the Orpheus Chamber Orchestra, Dec. 2 (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Museum Beat</p>
        <p>The fall art season is here with exhibitions at three of the Island's major museums. In Roslyn Harbor, the Nassau County Museum of Art, off Northern Boulevard, offers two related shows running through Jan. 14:  ''Surrealism'' and ''Dali: Works on Paper.'' The 95 works in the former include paintings by such leaders in the provocative 20th-century movement as Arp, Chirico, Dali, Ernst, Magritte, Miro, Picasso and Man Ray; the latter focuses on prints by Dali (516) 484-9338.</p>
        <p>Exploring the present, the Parrish Art Museum on Job's Lane in Southampton has ''The Perpetual Well: Contemporary Art From the Collection of the Jewish Museum.'' Drawn from the New York museum's holdings, the exhibition, accompanied by lectures and films, runs through Nov. 12 (631) 283-2118. Finally, the Museums at Stony Brook on Route 25A feature ''Pencil to Paint to Print,''  preliminary sketches and drawings and completed paintings and prints by William Sidney Mount and his brother, Shepard Alonzo Mount, that illustrate the process that begins with an artist's initial ideas  (631) 751-0066.</p>
        <p>Piano, Piano</p>
        <p>What do stride piano and cabaret piano have in common? Judy Carmichael and Steve Ross, that's what. The two pianists -- Ms. Carmichael the jazz performer, and Mr. Ross, the cafe singer -- join forces Saturday at the Bay Street Theater in Sag Harbor. They will play together and alone at 7 and 9 p.m. and Ms. Carmichael will offer a free children's concert at 1 p.m. (631) 725-9500.</p>
        <p>Ethnicity Reigns</p>
        <p>Don't look now, but October has a dual personality. It pays tribute to both Italian- and Hispanic-Americans.</p>
        <p>Italian celebratory highlights this week include an Italian-American Columbus Day Parade and Festival today at 11 a.m. at Kennedy Plaza in Long Beach (516) 431-3890 and on Tuesday, a concert by the Risorgimento Project of Italian art songs at 8 p.m. in Hofstra University's Monroe Lecture Center Theater in Hempstead (516) 463-6644.</p>
        <p>The Hispanic programs include a performance by Afro-Dysia, which blends Latin sounds with funk, the classics and jazz, at 2 p.m. today at the Half Hollow Hills Library on Vanderbilt Parkway in Dix Hills (631) 421-4530, and on Saturday, Amigos de la Zarzuela performing traditional music and dance from Spanish musical theater at 7:30 p.m. at the Community Library on Floyd Parkway in Shirley (631) 399-1511, extension 240.</p>
        <p>Some Plain Talk</p>
        <p>Some talk this week may be cheap -- actually it's free -- but that doesn't mean it won't be interesting. For example, inviting Long Islanders to ''Tune off E.R. and Attend Mini-Med School for Free,'' the University Hospital and Medical Center at the State University at Stony Brook begins a nine-week series of Wednesday lectures at 7 p.m. designed to introduce laymen to what's new (and old) in medicine. The subjects vary from the first session's ''Evolution, Sex and Bad Knees'' to ''Get Into Your Genes,'' Oct. 18 (631) 444-4393.</p>
        <p>In Lynbrook, the local library on Thursday opens ''Looking at Ourselves Through the Eyes of Others,'' a weekly series through Nov. 2 that explores the United States as a nation of immigrants. After ''What Americans Believe In: An Overview,'' the first entry at 7:30 p.m., the lectures get down to specifics, dealing with stereotypes of Italians, Latinos, African-Americans and Jews on successive weeks (516) 599-8630.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TODAY -- Music still dominates the library lineup. Daryl Jordan, soprano, appears at 2 p.m. at the Blue Point Library (631) 363-6133; members of the Long Island Original Music Association perform at 1:30 p.m. at the Central Islip Library (631) 234-9333; the Mirabai Ensemble plays classical music at 2:30 p.m. at the Freeport Library (516) 379-3274, and Bradley Garner, flutist, plays the classics at 2:30 p.m. at the Lynbrook Library (516) 887-3712.</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- Bob Spiotto appears as ''P. T. Barnum: The Greatest Showman on Earth'' at 7:30 p.m. at the Clark Library in Setauket. (631) 941-4080.</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- The Provost Lecture Series at the State University at Stony Brook begins with Dr. Paul R. Erlich, the best-selling author and professor of population studies in Stanford University's department of biological sciences, discussing ''Human Natures: Genes, Ethics and the Human Predictament'' at 7 p.m. in the Student Activities Center.</p>
        <p>THURSDAY -- ''From the Fires: Voices of the Holocaust,'' a drama by Jeffrey Sanzel about a Berlin teenager's experiences from 1937 to 1945, will be performed at 7:30 p.m. at Theater Three on Main Street in Port Jefferson. (631) 928-9100.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- The Amityville Highland Pipe Band performs at 2, 3 and 4 p.m. at Osprey's Dominion Vineyard on Main Road in Peconic. (631) 765-6188.</p>
        <p>Compiled by Barbara Delatiner</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
