<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Footnotes</title>
    <meta content="01FOOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="57" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cassatt, Mary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chang, Joyce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EED9103AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Footnotes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joyce Chang</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chang, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Footnotes on items used in Mary Cassatt apparel show (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>1. More than just paintings, Delia Brown's artwork is a modern happening. After setting up a scene, she has it photographed paparazzi-style and then renders the glamorous sequence of events in watercolors. Neither brush nor camera shy, Brown always includes herself in the picture -- a task made infinitely easier with Nikon's new Coolpix 990 digital camera with remote self-timer. ($999.95 at Alkit Pro Camera). Satisfying the same itch is Givenchy's new Miroir lipstick, with a mirror embedded in the tube. ($21 at Sephora.)</p>
        <p>2. Never one to be prim, Brown staged her decadent tea party in a setting fit for a king -- or a movie mogul. Chateau du Coeur in Paradise Cove, Malibu, can be rented for $2,500 a day, complete with a waterfall in the pool. The ''model-guests'' lounged poolside sipping Champagne donated by Mot &amp; Chandon and nibbling on Cheetos and Doritos. (DKNY's Ultra Violet boots, $375, are seen here worn by our hostess.) Although excess was one of Brown's themes, no chariots awaited her guests at party's end, just a regulation van.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>1. More than just paintings, Delia Brown's artwork is a modern happening. After setting up a scene, she has it photographed paparazzi-style and then renders the glamorous sequence of events in watercolors. Neither brush nor camera shy, Brown always includes herself in the picture -- a task made infinitely easier with Nikon's new Coolpix 990 digital camera with remote self-timer. ($999.95 at Alkit Pro Camera). Satisfying the same itch is Givenchy's new Miroir lipstick, with a mirror embedded in the tube. ($21 at Sephora.)</p>
        <p>2. Never one to be prim, Brown staged her decadent tea party in a setting fit for a king -- or a movie mogul. Chateau du Coeur in Paradise Cove, Malibu, can be rented for $2,500 a day, complete with a waterfall in the pool. The ''model-guests'' lounged poolside sipping Champagne donated by Mot &amp; Chandon and nibbling on Cheetos and Doritos. (DKNY's Ultra Violet boots, $375, are seen here worn by our hostess.) Although excess was one of Brown's themes, no chariots awaited her guests at party's end, just a regulation van.</p>
        <p>3. Since antiquity, art has been a mirror for the ebb and flow of fashion trends. Just as Brown's party scenes seem to draw on Dionysius and Narcissus for inspiration, the ancients drew on the gods of fashion. On this pyxis, for example, the drape and details of an ancient ''tea'' gown are as carefully drawn as a Christian Dior ruffle in one of Brown's paintings.</p>
        <p>4. An alternative to Brown's worldly tea is the traditional Japanese tea ceremony taught at the Urasenke Chanoyu Center in Manhattan. Rooted in Zen Buddhism, Chado, or the Way of Tea, reflects a minimalist aesthetic. The school teaches its students not only how to prepare the special powdered green tea that is the basis of Chado but also how to bow, walk and, most important, create a spiritual connection between guest and host. ''It is impolite to bring the outside into the tea room,'' explains Hisashi Yamada, the school's executive director. ''Usually there is freedom to talk. But the greater freedom is not to talk.'' The next open house is Oct. 18 at 5:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>5. Brown's revelers could not possibly have achieved a Zen frame of mind knowing that they were dangling gold-rimmed cups and saucers worth $1,520. Commissioned by a Prussian duke in 1790, the tea set (available at Gump's) is the work of Konigliche Porzellan Manufaktur, a company founded by Frederick the Great.</p>
        <p>6. Talonlike nails applied by Lisa Jachno didn't help the precarious handling of the pricey dishes. Although Jachno is manicurist to the likes of Madonna and Jennifer Lopez, this look can be achieved with Lee press-on nails and a coat of L'Oreal Wear Extraordinaire in Key Lime.</p>
        <p>7. What did our revelers talk about? Alas, it wasn't Dorothea Tanning, whose book of paintings was artfully strewn on the floor between the Champagne empties and the Dolce heels. Tanning, who was married to Max Ernst, just happens to be one of Brown's favorite painters. ''I like the way she uses her dog,'' Brown says. ''It is a very sensual use of pets.'' But unlike those other fashion pets -- Tamara de Lempicka comes to mind -- Tanning is not terribly chic. Which is probably why Brown likes her. ''I don't hear anyone talk about her,'' she says. ''I snuck her in hoping someone would notice and say, 'Who is she again?''' -- Text by Joyce Chang</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
