<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debate Stakes Seen as Critical By Candidates</title>
    <meta content="01DEBA$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/politics/01DEBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Winston-Salem (Nc)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">St Louis (Mo)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina/Winston-Salem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri/St. Louis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFDA153DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1597" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debate Stakes Seen as Critical By Candidates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stakes will be far greater than anticipated in presidential debate because contest is so excruciatingly tight; operatives for Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush suspend many important strategic decisions, at least until day after first debate, so they can gauge whether fundamental dynamics of contest have shifted; these decisions include where to buy advertising and where, precisely, candidates should be deployed in final weeks of campaign; first debate will be held on Oct 3 in Boston, followed week later with debate in Winston-Salem, NC, then one in St Louis week after that; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore appear side by side in Boston on Tuesday before the largest single television audience of the presidential campaign, officials in both camps say, the stakes will be far greater than they had anticipated because the contest is so excruciatingly tight.</p>
        <p>The debate has emerged as so consequential, in fact, that operatives for Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush said they had suspended many important strategic decisions, at least until Wednesday, so they could gauge whether the fundamental dynamics of the contest have been shifted. Those decisions include where to buy advertising and where, precisely, the candidates should be deployed in the final weeks of the campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore appear side by side in Boston on Tuesday before the largest single television audience of the presidential campaign, officials in both camps say, the stakes will be far greater than they had anticipated because the contest is so excruciatingly tight.</p>
        <p>The debate has emerged as so consequential, in fact, that operatives for Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush said they had suspended many important strategic decisions, at least until Wednesday, so they could gauge whether the fundamental dynamics of the contest have been shifted. Those decisions include where to buy advertising and where, precisely, the candidates should be deployed in the final weeks of the campaign.</p>
        <p>Karl Rove, Mr. Bush's chief strategist, played down the debates a few weeks back, saying they tended only to reinforce voters' support of one candidate or another.</p>
        <p>Now, given that the race has no front-runner, Mr. Rove argues that the 90-minute debates -- the one is Boston is followed a week later with a debate in Winston-Salem, N.C., then one in St. Louis a week after that -- may be pivotal. Not since Richard M. Nixon and John F. Kennedy squared off in 1960, he said, have debates been so significant in a presidential contest.</p>
        <p>''With the polls so close,'' Mr. Rove said, ''an impact of three or four or five percentage points could easily have a significant impact on the race.''</p>
        <p>Mark Fabiani, a strategist for Mr. Gore, put it this way: ''No question it's a huge event. It's a really, really important event. It's a time when people really tune in to who you are and what you've done.''</p>
        <p>The campaigns have been so preoccupied with the debates that negotiators on both sides devoted more than six days of closed talks to the details before they emerged on Friday with a detailed agreement that spells out everything from the height of the lecterns to the number of aides each candidate can have backstage. Negotiators discussed such seemingly trivial matters as the temperature in the hall (65 degrees) and whether to allow props (no).</p>
        <p>Officials involved in the negotiations said that they had not been particularly contentious, but that the Gore representatives -- who had more collective background in debate talks -- were more aggressive in making demands, though not all were met.''A lot of this was head-fake stuff,'' said a person involved in the talks.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign had one victory before the negotiations began:  the Bush organization had abandoned its objections to having all three events sponsored by the bipartisan Commission on Presidential Debates. (The commission will also sponsor the vice-presidential debate in Danville, Ky., on Thursday.) Bush representatives had also opposed Boston as the site of the first debate.</p>
        <p>Both sides had some modest successes and disappointments in the details of the negotiations.</p>
        <p>For example, the Gore negotiators pressed, unsuccessfully, for the candidates to be able to wear lapel microphones in the first debate, presumably so the vice president could leave his lectern and prowl the stage, as he sometimes did in debates in the primaries.</p>
        <p>Officials involved in the discussions said backers of Mr. Bush had asked that the height of his lectern be lowered, apparently because he is slightly shorter than Mr. Gore and did not want to appear diminished in his presence. But both lecterns will stand 48 inches high.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's representatives prevailed, however, in altering the format so that there will be more time than in the past for give and take on a single topic.</p>
        <p>One official scoffed at all the maneuvering, given that there was precious little to maneuver over. ''Part of this is a geometry question,'' the official said. ''You can't do the flying Wallendas when you've got two guys standing at a podium.''</p>
        <p>Beyond the polls showing a see-saw contest in which Mr. Gore seems slightly up one day and Mr. Bush the next, another reason both camps are so focused on the debates might be that they are well aware that the impact of television seems particularly strong in this election.</p>
        <p>Many Democrats and Republicans credit Mr. Gore's speech at the Democratic convention -- even the kiss he gave his wife, Tipper -- as propelling Mr. Gore in the polls.</p>
        <p>The first debate is often the one that draws the highest audience. This time, viewership might be diminished because NBC plans to give its affiliates the option of broadcasting a baseball playoff game instead of the debate, and Fox is scheduled to offer entertainment programming.</p>
        <p>Even so, the debates are expected to reach many more millions of people than the two political conventions this summer. For many people, it will be the first time they see the two competitors live -- and for longer than a snippet in a commercial or on the news.</p>
        <p>Yet for all those millions, officials in both campaigns say Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore will focus their messages on the narrow swath of swing voters who are expected to decide the election.</p>
        <p>For the Bush campaign, officials said, the goal is to demonstrate to those wavering voters that the Texas governor has a command of the issues and a presidential bearing. They also intend to assure women and undecided voters that he is no uncompromising conservative.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove said the best way for the governor to reassure the public is ''to let the American people know what his agenda is, what he would do as president, what his philosophy is and to contrast it with Gore whenever possible.''</p>
        <p>The pressure is particularly intense for Mr. Bush because he needs to address lingering concerns that he lacks the capacity to be president.</p>
        <p>As Bob Dole, the Republican nominee in 1996, put it plainly in a speech  this week at Denison University in Ohio, ''There's a feeling that he's not quite ready for prime time, that he doesn't fill the suit.''</p>
        <p>For the Gore campaign, the aim is to underscore Mr. Gore's grasp of the issues by offering many specifics, as he did in his speech at the Democratic convention. His aides said he was aiming his appeals at working-class families by presenting himself as someone who will fight for them.</p>
        <p>''This is our opportunity to talk in some specificity and detail about our ideas and our plans for the country,'' said Carter Eskew, a veteran strategist for Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Strategists on both sides hope, of course, that the debates will nudge their candidate into the lead. Mr. Eskew, for one, says the debates will define the next three weeks of the campaign. ''They will, to some extent, freeze the race for a few weeks,'' he said. ''It's certainly the main event for the next three weeks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is a far more accomplished debater than Mr. Bush, having dispatched politicians ranging from Bill Bradley in the Democratic primaries this year to Jack Kemp in the vice-presidential debates in 1996 to Ross Perot before that. That does not mean it will be a lopsided matchup. Mr. Bush is less versed in the issues, but his advisers said his personality might shine through -- and his affable, everyday-guy appeal might score points with voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also benefits from low expectations. If he makes it through Tuesday night without a discernible gaffe or tangled syntax, the pundits -- and more importantly, the voters -- could pronounce him the victor.</p>
        <p>''It's nearly impossible to win a debate but it is possible to lose one,'' said Nelson Polsby, a political scientist at the University of California at Berkeley. ''Therefore, whoever is perceived going in as having the higher level of expectations is the one that's most at risk. I would say that's Gore.''</p>
        <p>And the Bush campaign was trying mightily to keep the expectations high for the vice president. ''He is one of the most practiced debaters in American politics,'' said Karen Hughes, Mr. Bush's communications director. ''He's debated 30 or 40 times over the last 12 years.''</p>
        <p>In keeping with their attempts to lower expectations, neither side would dare predict that his candidate would walk away as the front-runner on Tuesday evening.</p>
        <p>''I don't necessarily think we expect that somehow the debate is going to be a breakout event,'' Mr. Eskew said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rove agreed, saying, ''I don't think in a race this close there's likely to be any dynamic that puts anyone ahead.''</p>
        <p>But for the candidates at least, the pressure will be intense. Walter F. Mondale, Gerald R. Ford, Michael S. Dukakis and former President George Bush have all told interviewers that their stumbles in debates -- or the nimbleness of their opponent -- might have cost them the White House.</p>
        <p>''The debates have been elevated to high drama in this country and particularly in this election year,'' said former Representative Bill Paxon, an adviser to Mr. Bush. ''This election is just about as close as you can have it.''</p>
        <p>If people are waiting for a fatal blow, he said, they may be disappointed. ''We're not going to see any huge knockouts,'' Mr. Paxon predicted. ''We're going to continue to slog through, World War I trench warfare style, right to election eve.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
