<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Club Noise Draws Criticism, But Partyers Say It's Cultural</title>
    <meta content="01CLUB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235149"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: RICHMOND HILL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jamaican-Americans</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Casa Latina (Nyc)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Calypso City (Nyc)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EED9163DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Club Noise Draws Criticism, But Partyers Say It's Cultural</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRI DAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents, following stabbing near Casa Latina, step up efforts to close it and another Caribbean dance club, Calypso City, on Jamaica Avenue in Richmond Hill, Queens; club owners contend complaints are racial; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When two nightclubs on Jamaica Avenue close at 4 a.m. on weekends, revelers continue to party in the streets. And many of the neighbors are furious.</p>
        <p>''There's fights all the time,'' said John O'Brien, a retired union organizer and homeowner who lives near Calypso City, a Caribbean dance club near 121st Street. ''They're always urinating in the streets.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When two nightclubs on Jamaica Avenue close at 4 a.m. on weekends, revelers continue to party in the streets. And many of the neighbors are furious.</p>
        <p>''There's fights all the time,'' said John O'Brien, a retired union organizer and homeowner who lives near Calypso City, a Caribbean dance club near 121st Street. ''They're always urinating in the streets.''</p>
        <p>Residents have complained about Calypso City since it opened six years ago. But a stabbing six weeks ago opposite a later arrival, Casa Latina, at 116th Street, has led to stepped-up efforts to close both clubs.</p>
        <p>A petition complaining about drug use, public sex acts and the use of weapons outside Casa Latina was signed by nearly 100 people and submitted to Community Board 9 last month. Mary Ann Carey, the district manager, said she had received no subsequent complaints about either club, and credits the change to a bigger police presence.</p>
        <p>But many residents remain unhappy. ''It's really taking a toll on the community,'' said Simcha Waisman, president of the Richmond Hill Block Association. He contends that the clubs have hurt the area and caused homeowners to move away.</p>
        <p>According to the police, the owners of both clubs have been cited for excessive noise and assaults that have occurred inside the clubs. Calypso City has been cited for health and fire violations and underage drinking, the police said.</p>
        <p>The owners of Calypso City, Mohan Jaikaran and Fred Mahabii, say the dispute is not about property values but about the neighborhood's changing demographics. Mr. Jaikaran, who is Guyanese, and Mr. Mahabii, who is from Trinidad, say the real issue is resentment against the growing Latino and West Indian population. ''There's no question about it,'' Mr. Jaikaran said. ''This was an abandoned building, and we took it and tried to do something for our community.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Waisman insists the issue is not race but quality of life.</p>
        <p>''Once they start talking about race, that's part of the coverup,'' said Mr. Waisman, who emigrated from Israel. ''They want to get away from the truth.'' Koomall Shamlall, a Guyanese jeweler who once picketed Calypso City, agrees. ''I am an Indian just like them,'' said Mr. Shamlall, who lives a block from the club. ''They should take this club and put it in front of their neighborhood, not mine.''</p>
        <p>SHERRI DAY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: RICHMOND HILL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
