<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Slide Continues, Yankees Hope They Can Turn It Around in Playoffs</title>
    <meta content="01YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/sports/01YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Orioles</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0D8153DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Slide Continues, Yankees Hope They Can Turn It Around in Playoffs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, Sept. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Baltimore Orioles defeat New York Yankees, 9-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is too late for the Yankees to reverse their horrible slump before the playoffs begin, too late to recapture their sense of invincibility. They were routed again tonight, losing to the Orioles, 9-1, as Manager Joe Torre rested many of his regular players, the day after the team clinched the American League East.</p>
        <p>There is an old saying in baseball that goes like this: Momentum is today's starting pitcher. And with his team's losing streak now at six games, Torre is banking heavily on his two best starting pitchers to turn around the Yankees in the playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is too late for the Yankees to reverse their horrible slump before the playoffs begin, too late to recapture their sense of invincibility. They were routed again tonight, losing to the Orioles, 9-1, as Manager Joe Torre rested many of his regular players, the day after the team clinched the American League East.</p>
        <p>There is an old saying in baseball that goes like this: Momentum is today's starting pitcher. And with his team's losing streak now at six games, Torre is banking heavily on his two best starting pitchers to turn around the Yankees in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Roger Clemens and Andy Pettitte will pitch the first and second games of the playoffs for the Yankees, whether the games are in Oakland or Chicago or Seattle; tonight's defeat insured that the Yankees will open the postseason on the road.</p>
        <p>If Games 4 and 5 are necessary, Clemens and Pettitte will pitch them with three days' rest. Orlando Hernandez will start Game 3 and the left-hander Denny Neagle, who was awful in his last three starts, will be shifted to the bullpen.</p>
        <p>Major League Baseball announced tonight that the Yankees would not have to play a makeup game against the Florida Marlins on Monday.</p>
        <p>David Cone is expected to be part of the postseason roster despite a poor finish to his miserable season. Cone allowed eight hits, three walks and six runs in tonight's blowout, the Yankees' 14th loss in their last 17 games, and their eighth loss of eight or more runs since Sept. 13. Over the last six games, the Yankees have been outscored by 61-12.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' late-season collapse ruined any chance that they would open the division series at Yankee Stadium. Rather than play his regular players in a game that was all but meaningless, Torre treated tonight's contest as if it were a spring-training game. Catcher Jorge Posada was out of the lineup, after starting 14 consecutive games; he may sit out Sunday's game, as well.</p>
        <p>Third baseman Scott Brosius, his legs hurting, was given the night off. First baseman Tino Martinez, nagged by a sore elbow, was out of the lineup, although he will probably play Sunday. David Justice, ailing with a strained groin, was moved to designated hitter. Right fielder Paul O'Neill and shortstop Derek Jeter were taken out after three at-bats.</p>
        <p>There was a sense of imminent doom tonight, Cone acknowledged after the game, once the Yankees fell behind in the second inning, because the All-Star Mike Mussina was pitching what might be his last game for the Orioles. He also was working with a wide strike zone: after O'Neill took a called third strike to end the first inning, he crossed paths with Mussina on the way to right field and asked, ''Were any of those pitches strikes?''</p>
        <p>Mussina replied, ''I think the last one was.''</p>
        <p>Mussina, eligible for free agency after this season, allowed a run over six and a third innings and departed to a standing ovation. Cone closed out the regular season with a 4-14 won-lost record and a 6.91 earned run average. Under normal circumstances, he would have no chance of pitching in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>But Ramiro Mendoza had shoulder surgery last week, Jason Grimsley is out with an elbow injury, and Cone is next in line. ''I want David to be on the roster,'' said Torre, who will consult with club officials before a final decision is made Monday. ''If there's still that one guy you need to get out, I still trust him.''</p>
        <p>Cone said, ''I'm looking for some way to help the team, some sort of redemptive game.''</p>
        <p>But the simple reality is that if the Yankees get into a position where their postseason middle relievers must be relied upon, they are probably going to be in deep trouble anyway. The staff is thin and the Yankees need Clemens, Pettitte and Hernandez to pitch deeply into games.</p>
        <p>Clemens pitched poorly in his last two outings, but he did not in July and August and most of September. Pettitte was routed Friday, but led the team with 19 victories and was remarkably consistent. Hernandez has been dominant the last six weeks, and the Yankees are undefeated in his six postseason starts.</p>
        <p>''I'm excited,'' Clemens said of pitching in Game 1. ''I don't care how long you've been in this league, it's still an honor'' to pitch the first game of a postseason series.</p>
        <p>Pettitte has some recent experience in pitching on three days' rest, throwing well but losing on July 9 against the Mets; he allowed two runs over six and a third innings. Clemens embraced the theory that he might pitch on three days' rest, but added that the decision would be reviewed after he saw how his body responded to throwing in Game 1. His history of throwing on three days' rest is dubious.</p>
        <p>He has not started under those circumstances since Aug. 31, 1993, and in five regular-season starts on three days' rest, his won-lost record is 3-2. But he has allowed 20 earned runs in 33 1/3 innings, for an E.R.A. of 5.40. He has not won a game on three days' rest since 1990.</p>
        <p>The last time he started a postseason game on three days' rest was in 1990: facing Oakland as a member of the Boston Red Sox, Clemens was ejected in the second inning of the game after protesting a ball-strike call, and was the losing pitcher.</p>
        <p>In reducing his rotation to three pitchers and shifting Neagle to the bullpen, Torre will also create more depth for his beleaguered middle relief.</p>
        <p>''That's fine with me,'' said Neagle, who occasionally worked out of the bullpen in the postseason for the Atlanta Braves. ''It's the same situation I had in Atlanta. We had Maddux, Glavine and Smoltz, and the same goes here.''</p>
        <p>Torre has not bothered trying to recast the shocking depth of the recent blowouts; he knows the Yankees have looked terrible. But he has little choice but to have faith that the postseason experience of his players, who among them have participated in 288 celebrations of everything from division titles to World Series championships. He has little choice but to have faith in the ability of his starting pitchers.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DEREK JETER singled in the fourth inning to reach 200 hits for the third consecutive year. Jeter is the third player in club history to do so, joining Lou Gehrig (1927-29) and DON MATTINGLY (1984-86). In the last 50 years, only three American League players other than Jeter and Mattingly have totaled 200 or more hits in three straight years: JIM RICE, WADE BOGGS and KIRBY PUCKETT.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
