<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Costly Prescriptions: One Issue That Fits All</title>
    <meta content="01ADS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/politics/01ADS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1D7143DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Costly Prescriptions: One Issue That Fits All</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rising cost of medication is major campaign theme of candidates around nation in 2000 elections; topic has become such ubiquitous feature of this year's advertising that it is virtually requirement for candidates to have prescription drug commercial; candidates of every stripe, and running for variety of offices, all seek to sound like friends of little guy in his fight against escalating drug costs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brian Schweitzer, a peppermint, alfalfa and cattle farmer running for the Senate in Montana, holds up a pair of pill bottles for the camera and declares, ''I bet you'd be surprised to find out that veterinarians prescribe the exact same medicine for dogs, and charge half as much.''</p>
        <p>In a New Hampshire television commercial, Gov. Jeanne Shaheen, seeking re-election, has found a novel way to attack her Republican opponent, former Senator Gordon Humphrey: she says his vote against creating a prescription drug benefit under Medicare makes him ''an extremist.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brian Schweitzer, a peppermint, alfalfa and cattle farmer running for the Senate in Montana, holds up a pair of pill bottles for the camera and declares, ''I bet you'd be surprised to find out that veterinarians prescribe the exact same medicine for dogs, and charge half as much.''</p>
        <p>In a New Hampshire television commercial, Gov. Jeanne Shaheen, seeking re-election, has found a novel way to attack her Republican opponent, former Senator Gordon Humphrey: she says his vote against creating a prescription drug benefit under Medicare makes him ''an extremist.''</p>
        <p>And an advertisement for the Democratic hopeful for the Senate in Minnesota, Mark Dayton, shows the candidate riding a bus with elderly people to buy their pills for lower prices in Canada. ''He's helping us,'' one of the retirees, Buzz Otte, exclaims. ''He likes us old-timers!''</p>
        <p>In the 2000 campaign, no question is getting more play from more candidates than what to do about the rising cost of medication. It is, in fact, the issue that spin doctors prescribe most. Jim Jordan, political director for the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee, says that he knows how many of the Democrats waging television advertising campaigns are invoking the issue: all of them.</p>
        <p>''There is just so much wind in the sails of this issue,'' he said. ''I have no doubt that by election day every single Democrat who is on the air will have run ads about prescription drugs.''</p>
        <p>The topic has become such a ubiquitous feature of this year's advertising that it is virtually a requirement for candidates to have a prescription drug commercial. And some contenders have already produced as many as six advertisements on the subject. ''It's stunning,'' said Neil Newhouse, a Republican pollster who has advised several of his clients across the country to weave the subject into their messages.</p>
        <p>''In terms of campaign advertising, it's hard to think back and find an issue that bridges federal and state candidates, Republicans and Democrats, the way that prescription drugs has,'' Mr. Newhouse said.</p>
        <p>That such a narrowly defined issue could dominate commercials from coast to coast illustrates how swiftly and widely potentially winning messages can be franchised, almost like coffee houses or fast-food outlets.</p>
        <p>''I guess voters want to hear you have a plan,'' said Mac McCorkle, an issues consultant to Democrats in races for governor in North Carolina and Missouri. ''They don't trust all the protestations about what a great character I am, but they do relate to whether you get the message on prescription drugs.''</p>
        <p>Candidates of every stripe are seeking to sound like friends of the little guy in his fight against escalating drug costs.</p>
        <p>''Slade Gorton stared down the drug companies to lower the unfair prices of prescription medicines,'' an announcer says in an advertisement for the Republican senator's re-election campaign in Washington State.</p>
        <p>Three thousand miles away, another Republican, Senator Olympia J. Snowe of Maine, offers a similar theme. ''No senior citizen,'' she says in her commercial, ''should ever have to choose between putting food on the table and getting the medicine that they need.''</p>
        <p>And it is not just the candidates who are weighing in. The A.F.L.-C.I.O., various state parties and the Democratic and Republican national committees have all run prescription drug advertisements. That is not to mention the Citizens for Better Medicare, a group allied with the pharmaceutical industry that has spent more than $34 million this year on a nationwide advertising campaign against those who support a Clinton administration proposal to make the drug benefit a part of Medicare. Dan Zielinski, a spokesman for Citizens for Better Medicare, said that he believed the group's adversaries had spent just as much.</p>
        <p>Both parties, of course, say they support lowering the drug costs for older people, but it was the Democrats who were first to recognize the telegenic appeal of mixing pills and politics. Democratic Party officials say it was no coincidence that they made Vice President Al Gore's support for the drug benefit the subject of his campaign's first commercial.</p>
        <p>Regardless of party affiliation, the rewards can be handsome for candidates who have taken early stands on the issue.</p>
        <p>Dr. Paul Perry, a surgeon from Evansville, Ind., and first-time candidate for Congress, says he went from relative unknown to victor in the Democratic primary in Indiana's Eighth Congressional District on the strength of health care concerns in general and the economics of pharmaceuticals in particular.</p>
        <p>''We had nine weeks of TV advertising, talking about H.M.O. reform and the cost of prescription drugs,'' said Dr. Perry, who defeated John Hamilton, nephew of the popular former House member Lee Hamilton, in the primary. ''The power of that message took us to a 20-point win. Patients understand that the power of the insurance companies has become so great. And prescription drugs play into the whole idea of who's in control of health care.''</p>
        <p>Those in the business of promulgating campaign messages and measuring their effect say the issue is keenly calibrated to these political times. Voters, their surveys show, are not impressed with thematic advertising that highlights values or vision. In this peacetime era of relative economic security, they say they want to hear about plans to solve problems in their own lives. And they want details.</p>
        <p>''You've got to go specific,'' said Lee M. Miringoff, director of the Marist Institute for Public Opinion in Poughkeepsie, N.Y.</p>
        <p>The message is not only tailored to the elderly. Joe Andrew, national chairman of the Democratic National Committee, said that in advising the party to focus heavily on prescription drugs, he saw the issue's appeal as ''cross-generational'': a health care issue for the oldest voters, a financial issue for baby boomers worried about how to support an aging parent and a matter of social responsibility for young people.</p>
        <p>In some races, like the Senate contest in Michigan between the Republican incumbent, Spencer Abraham, and his challenger, Representative Debbie Stabenow, the fight over whose prescription drug plan is more effective has spawned a campaign that at times feels like a visit to an insurance broker. On a recent evening, a Detroit television station, WXYZ, devoted several minutes to trying to decipher the dueling claims, right down to a discussion of co-payment fees.</p>
        <p>''This is a bigger pocketbook issue than taxes right now,'' said Karl Struble, a Washington media consultant who has made prescription drug advertisements for clients like Mr. Schweitzer in Montana and Ed Bernstein, a Democrat running for an open Senate seat in Nevada. ''I've sat in focus groups. I've watched people talk about it. I've been a pied piper telling people, 'This is where you want to go.' ''</p>
        <p>In no campaign have prescription drugs played a larger role than in the bid by Mr. Schweitzer to unseat a Republican incumbent, Senator Conrad Burns. A year ago, Mr. Schweitzer said, he drove across the state talking to voters. ''It wasn't the first issue that most people talked about, but it was the second or third,'' he recalled. ''It was a matter of listening to what they were saying.''</p>
        <p>Not long after, Mr. Schweitzer began signing up Montanans for chartered-bus trips to Canada to buy prescription medications at lower prices there. Coverage of Mr. Schweitzer's trips -- he called them ''The Run for the Border'' -- spawned imitators. Mr. Dayton began an ''Rx Express'' from Minnesota to Canada, and Mark Lawrence, Ms. Snowe's opponent in Maine, boarded buses for Canada, too.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schweitzer has run several drug commercials, including the one in which he compares the prices with those of pet medicines. It was reminiscent of a statement by Mr. Gore that his mother-in-law paid three times as much for an arthritis medicine as he did for the drug for his dog. (The Gore campaign later acknowledged the anecdote was based on a Congressional study.)</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Schweitzer's advertisements have boosted his poll numbers, his advisers say, and forced the opposition to respond. In a new advertisement, the state Republican Party asserts that Mr. Schweitzer ''backs Al Gore's big government health care agenda,'' a plan it calls ''bad medicine for Montana.''</p>
        <p>Dick Wadhams, a spokesman for Senator Burns's campaign, said, ''It is fair to say the prescription drug issue has been fairly dominant in the campaign, largely because Schweitzer has been a one-issue candidate since last year.''</p>
        <p>From any camera angle, it is clear Mr. Schweitzer thinks that one issue might just be enough.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
