<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.Y.I.</title>
    <meta content="01FYI.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Debt (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Daniel B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE5DA163DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.Y.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Daniel B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions about New York University football team, meaning of words Sixth Avenue Bottom Lines Debt Clock painted on facade of building at Ninth Avenue and 43rd Street and busiest day in history of New York City subway; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Violet Pigskins</p>
        <p>Q.: What ever happened to the N.Y.U. football team?</p>
        <p>A.: ''Raise on high the Violet . . . flow'r we'll ne'er forget . . . Oh New York University . . . Hurrah for old New York . . . Ta ra ra ra ra ra ra ra. . . .''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Violet Pigskins</p>
        <p>Q.: What ever happened to the N.Y.U. football team?</p>
        <p>A.: ''Raise on high the Violet . . . flow'r we'll ne'er forget . . . Oh New York University . . . Hurrah for old New York . . . Ta ra ra ra ra ra ra ra. . . .''</p>
        <p>It has been almost 50 years since the Violets last stormed the gridiron, and though the idea has now taken on almost comic overtones, there was a time New York University was a mighty force on the football field, playing home games at the University Heights campus in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>The Violets played their first game in 1873 and compiled an overall record of 199 victories. 226 losses and 31 ties over 79 seasons.</p>
        <p>N.Y.U. football reached its zenith in the 1920's and early 30's, a period that is considered the heyday of college ball in the city, when Columbia, Fordham and N.Y.U. played in packed stadiums, sometimes against national powers.</p>
        <p>From 1926 to 1928, the Violets, led by the versatile tailback Ken Strong, suffered only four losses. Strong, who could run, pass, kick and tackle, later played professionally for the Staten Island Stapletons and the New York Giants, and is in the Pro Football Hall of Fame. In 1935, Frank Eliscu, sculptor of the Heisman Trophy,  chose Ed Smith, an N.Y.U. player, as his model.</p>
        <p>The Violets cooled off considerably in the late 1930's, and football was suspended during World War II. As the team struggled to rebuild after 1944, the ascendance of televised sports and professional football franchises seemed to limit its drawing power, and it didn't help that many players had to travel from the Washington Square campus to University Heights just to practice.</p>
        <p>In March 1953, citing the fading interest of students, alumni and the public and its unwillingness to commit more resources to the team, N.Y.U. officially canceled its intercollegiate program. Violet football has been intramural ever since.</p>
        <p>Debt Clock Tribute</p>
        <p>Q.: The words ''Sixth Avenue Bottom Lines Debt Clock'' are painted onto the upper facade of a pale green three-story building at 611 Ninth Avenue. I know about the recently retired National Debt Clock on Sixth Avenue, but what does this building have to do with it?</p>
        <p>A.: The National Debt Clock, which was turned off Sept. 7, was conceived by Seymour B. Durst, political gadfly, real estate developer and longtime president of the Durst Organization. Until several years ago, the little building near the corner of West 43rd Street and Ninth Avenue was among the firm's properties. According to Mortimer Matz, a spokesman for the organization, after Mr. Durst died in 1995, his nephew, Joshua Durst, had the building painted with the words, which run vertically down the second and third stories, to the left of the windows, in three columns.</p>
        <p>Even those familiar with the Debt Clock three blocks to the east might find the message opaque, but Mr. Matz said it was probably meant as a tribute to Seymour Durst, who took out more than 200 of the minuscule advertisements on the bottom of the front page of The New York Times -- the bottom lines cited on the facade -- and assembled substantial real estate holdings on the Avenue of the Americas.</p>
        <p>When the cryptogram is read from left to right instead of up and down, the letters at the top of the facade, which unlike the others are painted gold, are S, B and D, the initials of  Seymour B. Durst.</p>
        <p>Big Day Underground</p>
        <p>Q.: What was the busiest day in the history of the New York City subway?</p>
        <p>A.: Dec. 23, 1946, when according to the New York City Transit 8,872,244 rode the trains. The daily average today is about 3.5 million.</p>
        <p>DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
