<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mary Kate Wynperle, James Moriarty</title>
    <meta content="01WYNP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WYNPERLE, MARY CATHERINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORIARTY, JAMES JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D9163DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mary Kate Wynperle, James Moriarty</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mary Catherine Wynperle, a daughter of Mary and William Wynperle of Great Neck, N.Y., was married yesterday to James John Moriarty, a son of Josephine and Thomas Moriarty of East Atlantic Beach, N.Y. Msgr. James Kelly, an uncle of the bridegroom, performed the ceremony at the Church of St. Jean Baptiste in New York.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wynperle, 29, is known as Mary Kate and is keeping her surname. She is an associate at LeBoeuf, Lamb, Greene &amp; MacRae, a law firm in New York. She graduated from Duke University and the Fordham University Law School.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mary Catherine Wynperle, a daughter of Mary and William Wynperle of Great Neck, N.Y., was married yesterday to James John Moriarty, a son of Josephine and Thomas Moriarty of East Atlantic Beach, N.Y. Msgr. James Kelly, an uncle of the bridegroom, performed the ceremony at the Church of St. Jean Baptiste in New York.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wynperle, 29, is known as Mary Kate and is keeping her surname. She is an associate at LeBoeuf, Lamb, Greene &amp; MacRae, a law firm in New York. She graduated from Duke University and the Fordham University Law School.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moriarty, 31, is the corporate counsel at Online Retail Partners, a New York company that creates software and provides technical support for Internet retailers. He graduated from Williams College and the New York University School of Law.</p>
        <p>The first time Ms. Wynperle laid eyes on Mr. Moriarty, he was barefoot, unshaven and clad in a frayed baby-blue bathrobe. It was a late morning in January 1994. She was sitting in the living room of the Manhattan apartment where Mr. Moriarty lived with his brother and a friend. Ms. Wynperle was visiting Mr. Moriarty's roommates, who had shared a Hamptons summer rental with her the year before.</p>
        <p>''He was not looking very attractive,'' she recalled. ''But I still thought he was cute. He was so much more serious than the men I was meeting at the time. And Valentine's Day was fast approaching.''</p>
        <p>But Ms. Wynperle also thought Mr. Moriarty had a girlfriend, and she found it strange that none materialized when she met him at a party a week or so later. He knew better, and they definitely talked. ''My rap at the party was that she was a law student and I was the all-knowing veteran law school guy,'' he remembered.</p>
        <p>When she learned afterward that Mr. Moriarty and his girlfriend had broken up, she made her move. ''Although I knew that his roommates were out of town,'' she said, ''I decided that I would call to invite them out and act surprised that they were not there, and invite him instead.''</p>
        <p>The two spoke on the phone for about an hour and made plans to meet at a local bar that evening with other friends of hers. When Mr. Moriarty showed up about an hour late with a male friend, Ms. Wynperle assumed he had taken so long because he was trying to find someone to accompany him.</p>
        <p>''It took so long because I had to finish studying, like a geeky loser,'' he explained later.</p>
        <p>Last February, toward the end of a joint vacation in Costa Rica, Mr. Moriarty decided it was time to propose. He knew that on their last day off back in New York, he would be able to slip away to buy the ring because she had scheduled some root canal work at her dentist's on Long Island.</p>
        <p>He made a beeline to the jeweler's and then suggested they have dinner out, stopping off first to see the Temple of Dendur at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. The Met isn't his kind of place, but ''Mary Kate has a background in art history,'' he explained, and they had talked about traveling in Africa one day. It seemed like the perfect time and place, dental aftereffects notwithstanding.</p>
        <p>''I bought the ring for her in the morning,'' he said, ''and hoped that by the evening her mouth wouldn't be too swollen to say yes.''</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
