<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Pay More? Go Ask The Germans</title>
    <meta content="01CONT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/business/01CONT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE CONTRARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lidl (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aldi (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wal-Mart Stores Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Akst, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Contrary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3D8163DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Pay More? Go Ask The Germans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL AKST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Akst, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Akst comment on German Cartel Office's decision ordering German Wal-Mart Stores to increase prices on some food items so German supermarket chains Lidl and Aldi can remain competitive; says that while German government is ordering Wal-Mart to increase prices, Aldi stores in Hudson Valley, NY, are cutting prices on groceries to beat out competition; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE events I'm about to relate are almost too terrible to publish in a family newspaper. Nothing is being done to halt the abuse I'm about to describe, but somebody has to blow the whistle. So if you're the squeamish type, turn the page now.</p>
        <p>The situation is this: Not far from where I live in the Hudson Valley, a couple of stores named Aldi are engaged in the most outrageous of business practices. No, they are not selling drugs or trafficking in stolen property. What these stores do is offer customers groceries and other goods at unconscionably low prices -- so low, in fact, that even though each outlet is practically in the shadow of a Wal-Mart, a chain notorious for similar dealings, the Aldi outlets have managed to stay in business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE events I'm about to relate are almost too terrible to publish in a family newspaper. Nothing is being done to halt the abuse I'm about to describe, but somebody has to blow the whistle. So if you're the squeamish type, turn the page now.</p>
        <p>The situation is this: Not far from where I live in the Hudson Valley, a couple of stores named Aldi are engaged in the most outrageous of business practices. No, they are not selling drugs or trafficking in stolen property. What these stores do is offer customers groceries and other goods at unconscionably low prices -- so low, in fact, that even though each outlet is practically in the shadow of a Wal-Mart, a chain notorious for similar dealings, the Aldi outlets have managed to stay in business.</p>
        <p>As a result of this scheme -- known to hardened economists by the deceptively clinical term ''price competition'' -- working people are seduced into shopping at Aldi's for the things their families need. Perhaps saddest of all, government authorities stand by and do nothing while this brazen trade in discounted cornflakes and children's shoes goes on in broad daylight.</p>
        <p>Not so in Germany. There, enlightened officials at the aptly named German Cartel Office, aghast at the low prices in German Wal-Mart stores, recently stepped in and demanded that the big American discounter charge customers more for staples like milk, butter, flour and cooking oil. German competitors of Wal-Mart were also ordered to charge more, but they probably didn't mind, since the American company had started all the trouble.</p>
        <p>The government's aim, it said, was to protect smaller grocers. The German Retail Trade Association, a trade group, applauded the decision as a ''hopeful signal for the end of the ruinous cutthroat competition'' between Wal-Mart and two rival German supermarket chains, Lidl and Aldi.</p>
        <p>But wait a minute. Is that the same Aldi that freely and shamelessly competes on price at 549 stores in 21 states from upstate New York to Kansas? Indeed it is. In fact, on its Web site, the company boasts of how it keeps prices down by selling house brands in a no-frills setting; low prices are a major emphasis. In other words, Aldi of Germany is happily doing in this country precisely what Wal-Mart is being blocked from doing in Germany.</p>
        <p>What is to be done? Well, we could retaliate against the Germans by making Aldi's stores on this side of the Atlantic charge us more. Consumers could even be exhorted to notify the authorities of any markdowns.</p>
        <p>But in the absence of evidence of truly predatory pricing -- there certainly is no sign that Aldi is driving Wal-Mart to the brink -- what would be the point? Customers benefit from low prices, after all. One Aldi shopper I know, an older woman with a large family who has to scrimp to make ends meet, likes getting warehouse prices without having to pay membership fees. By forcing Aldi to charge more, the government would just be imposing a regressive tax on Aldi shoppers -- and making a gift of the proceeds to a German multinational.</p>
        <p>It is easy to poke fun at regulators who insist on higher prices, and sooner or later German customers will demand a more competitive retail environment, with lower prices and longer store hours. Then the country's merchants will finally have to give people what they want, which, of course, is what retailing is all about.</p>
        <p>But there is a much more interesting lesson here, one that goes far beyond the price of milk at Wal-Mart. For nations that impose them, trade restrictions are their own punishment. If the Germans do something stupid, like demanding that stores raise their prices, why should we follow suit?</p>
        <p>IN other words, the only sensible approach to international trade is unilateral disarmament. The benefits of letting Aldi's compete freely with Wal-Mart -- and letting imports flow unrestricted -- are just too great, and any remedy we could impose would be worse than the ''problem.'' Seen in this light, trade negotiations are like one of those standoffs in which an armed gunman takes himself hostage. As the economist N. Gregory Mankiw of Harvard likes to say, multilateral trade pacts mean agreeing with other nations that ''I won't shoot myself in the foot if you won't shoot yourself in the foot.''</p>
        <p>Just to see what the reaction would be, I put in a call to executives at Aldi's American headquarters in Batavia, Ill., intending to plead with them to raise prices in their stores. They never called me back. Probably just as well: I might have persuaded them.</p>
        <p>ON THE CONTRARY Daniel Akst's column tilts at conventional business wisdom and appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daniel Akst's column tilts at conventional business wisdom and appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
