<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peru Turning a Colder Shoulder</title>
    <meta content="Y01PER$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/world/01PERU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Peru</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krauss, Clifford</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fujimori, Alberto K (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E6D8143DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peru Turning a Colder Shoulder</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krauss, Clifford</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, Sept. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis: Pres Alberto K Fujimori's surprise two-day visit to Washington momentarily freezes deteriorating political situation in Peru, where opposition is on the march, truck drivers are staging crippling protests against rising fuel prices, and even Fujimori's own prime minister tacitly concedes that military is restive; senior American officials say Fujimori's leverage and his ability to get his way through guile and audacity appear to be declining (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Alberto K. Fujimori's surprise two-day visit to Washington momentarily froze a deteriorating political situation here in which all the most important buttresses of his power appear to be cracking. The opposition is on the march, truck drivers have staged crippling protests against rising fuel prices and even Mr. Fujimori's own prime minister has tacitly conceded that the military is restive.</p>
        <p>Peru's capital was in no mood for a hero's welcome.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Alberto K. Fujimori's surprise two-day visit to Washington momentarily froze a deteriorating political situation here in which all the most important buttresses of his power appear to be cracking. The opposition is on the march, truck drivers have staged crippling protests against rising fuel prices and even Mr. Fujimori's own prime minister has tacitly conceded that the military is restive.</p>
        <p>Peru's capital was in no mood for a hero's welcome.</p>
        <p>Despite the expressions of support Mr. Fujimori received from senior American officials to forge ahead with new elections, in which Mr. Fujimori says he will not run, political experts here say his leverage and his ability to get his way through guile and audacity appear to be declining  daily.</p>
        <p>Only four months after he declared victory in a vote stained by widespread accusations of fraud, Mr. Fujimori -- first elected in 1990 and now in his third term -- already seems to be a lame duck who is struggling to salvage his reputation for history.</p>
        <p>After a videotape that was leaked to a cable television station two weeks ago showed Vladimiro Montesinos, his top intelligence aide, apparently handing a bribe to an opposition congressman-elect to switch allegiances to the government, Mr. Fujimori was forced to call new elections and agreed not to be a candidate.</p>
        <p>He has since made a mighty effort to retain his authority until next year when a new president can be inaugurated -- one whom experts say he will try to handpick. But in the last week, Mr. Fujimori's ability to do this has looked increasingly uncertain, as crucial elements of his power structure have shown signs of buckling.</p>
        <p>Ten legislators have resigned from his party, erasing his majority in Congress and his ability to set the rules and dates for the elections. Tabloid newspapers that once supported him are now declaring that Peru is in chaos. Plummeting stock prices have that whatever support he had left among business executives and international investors has evaporated.</p>
        <p>Most of the top officials heading the discredited government election apparatus have resigned, and the government's top prosecutor, who has always been willing to press or block cases to help Mr. Fujimori, is under increasing pressure to follow suit. The intelligence apparatus that Mr. Fujimori relied on in the past to defeat terrorists and drug traffickers has been disbanded by Congress, albeit with his acquiescence, as its discredited former chief seeks asylum in Panama.</p>
        <p>''In the past, Fujimori was always able to defy the laws of political physics but this time there is just no way,'' said Enrique Zileri, editor of Caretas, Peru's leading political weekly magazine. ''All that is left is a process of disintegration.''</p>
        <p>A government-controlled television station that boycotted the opposition during the recent election campaign began interviewing opposition politicians this week. It was just one of several signs that the many opportunists in the news media and political establishment who backed the Fujimori government in previous crises now perceived strong winds blowing in a whole new direction.</p>
        <p>And even while Mr. Fujimori was in Washington publicly assuring reporters that there was no chance of a military coup, his own prime minister conceded Friday that government officials were concerned about the restiveness of an army high command that had been chosen by Mr. Montesinos, the former intelligence chief.</p>
        <p>''I can't deny that all these rumors worried us and other governments,'' said Prime Minister Federico Salas, who had formerly steadfastly claimed that everything was under control. His news conference only fueled speculation that Peru is in a state of flux. In a further sign of unraveling, Congresswoman Martha Hildebrandt, , the leader of Mr. Fujimori's forces in Congress, told reporters on Friday that a shake-up in the congressional leadership was likely -- hinting that opponents of the president would probably be included in the new leadership.</p>
        <p>Negotiations brokered by the Organization of American States between the government and opposition are now likely to produce elections that will choose a new president and Congress months before the target of July 28, 2001, the date Mr. Fujimori originally envisaged.</p>
        <p>Once the negotiators settle on an election date in the next few weeks, they are likely to discuss who will take charge of the election apparatus, changes in the election rules and even which military officers will be permitted to succeed the top commanders of the army set to retire in December. Such powers were once the exclusive domain of President Fujimori and Mr. Montesinos, but those days are over.</p>
        <p>The negotiators are also likely to settle the conditions for the return in ownership of two television stations to businessmen who lost control of their properties because they broadcast critical exposes about Mr. Fujimori, Mr. Montesinos and corruption in the military.</p>
        <p>President Fujimori cannot even count on the absolute support of the current army commanders, who appear to be operating in an effort to protect Mr. Montesinos and themselves from prosecution for various human rights violations, gun-running and money-laundering.</p>
        <p>In the days prior to Mr. Fujimori's trip to Washington, Lima faced the threat of a transportation stoppage as truck drivers and other protesters blocked roads and fuel shipments. The army and police did little to stem the crisis, giving the impression that much of the high command and security apparatus were lending implicit support to the protests as a means of gaining leverage.</p>
        <p>Senior American military officials have let the Peruvian Army know a coup is unacceptable, and they have the support of the Peruvian Navy and Air Force.</p>
        <p>But while the threat of a coup and the energy crisis in Lima have eased, protests by drivers continue in several other cities. Meanwhile, an expanding government deficit and difficulties in raising international loans remain big problems.</p>
        <p>Consequently when Mr. Fujimori returns to Peru, his political standing will remain deeply precarious.</p>
        <p>''This is a fluid situation,'' said Mr. Zileri, the editor of Caretas. ''We don't know what is going to happen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
