<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Kingsbridge, a Sycamore Faces an Unwelcome Neighbor</title>
    <meta content="01SYCA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK TREES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Riverdale Family Practice</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcelroy, Rose</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1DE173DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="483" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Kingsbridge, a Sycamore Faces an Unwelcome Neighbor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROSE McELROY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcelroy, Rose</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Kingsbridge section of Bronx worry that 180-year-old Corlear Sycamore may be harmed during construction of new building for Riverdale Family Practice; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Can a tree be a local celebrity?</p>
        <p>It can if it's the Corlear Sycamore, a magnificent specimen that is 87 feet high, 49 inches wide and more than 180 years old. A silent sentinel to the passage of time, it stands on Corlear Avenue near West 231st Street in Kingsbridge, next to the Church of the Mediator. The sycamore, considered the oldest living thing in the Bronx, is included in the book ''Great Trees of New York City,'' a publication of the Parks and Recreation Department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Can a tree be a local celebrity?</p>
        <p>It can if it's the Corlear Sycamore, a magnificent specimen that is 87 feet high, 49 inches wide and more than 180 years old. A silent sentinel to the passage of time, it stands on Corlear Avenue near West 231st Street in Kingsbridge, next to the Church of the Mediator. The sycamore, considered the oldest living thing in the Bronx, is included in the book ''Great Trees of New York City,'' a publication of the Parks and Recreation Department.</p>
        <p>The tree managed to survive benign neglect until 1983. Then a neighbor became aware of a problem. ''Passing by each day, I noticed its leaves were dry and withered,'' said Bruce Snowden, a 69-year-old retired food service worker. Concerned, he wrote a letter describing the problem to The Riverdale Press.</p>
        <p>It turned out that the tree was, in effect, being strangled by the sidewalk, and water was not seeping into its roots. Prompted by Mr. Snowden's letter, local children and neighbors raised money to replace the sidewalk and buy topsoil. After the repair work was done, William Calabrese, a Bronx horticulturist, predicted, ''With good care, it could live another hundred years.''</p>
        <p>Now the tree is facing new woes. The Riverdale Family Practice plans to build a seven-story building in the shadow of the tree that would include medical offices, stores and housing for the elderly. Earth-moving equipment has already been seen on the site.</p>
        <p>Residents are worried that new construction will harm the tree's root system. Assemblyman Jeffrey Dinowitz, whose office is just down the street from the sycamore, is one of those concerned.</p>
        <p>''This is mainly a residential area,'' Mr. Dinowitz said. ''I love trees, and that's why I'm involved.''</p>
        <p>Others disagree.</p>
        <p>''What's all the fuss over a big old ugly tree?'' asked John Lese, the developer, who said, however, that he had hired an arborist to draft a report on ways to protect the sycamore. The project's architect, Gloria Glas of the New York firm of Schuman Lichtenstein Claman Efron, said the base of the building would be indented to protect the tree's roots and that the lower stories would be recessed to allow in sunlight.</p>
        <p>But, added the landscape architect Richard Horsman, who is not involved with the project, ''The problem lies not with the architect or the developer so much as with the contractor.'' His solution? An on-site person to supervise construction.</p>
        <p>ROSE McELROY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK TREES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
