<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greene Says It Again: He's Sorry</title>
    <meta content="01APOL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: RELAY CELEBRATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brink, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Track and Field</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Track and Field</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D8153DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greene Says It Again: He's Sorry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL BRINK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brink, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sunday,Oct. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Members of gold medal US men's 4x100 meters relay team apologize for unseemly celebration following race (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A day after a preening celebration of his team's victory in the 4x100-meter relay race, Maurice Greene of the United States acknowledged today that he had received some negative reaction to the display and reiterated an apology he had first issued after the race.</p>
        <p>Greene and his relay partners -- Jon Drummond, Bernard Williams and Brian Lewis -- celebrated their victory Saturday night before more than 100,000 spectators by posing like professional wrestlers, flexing their muscles during their victory lap and on the medal stand afterward. Greene also stuck out his tongue at the cameras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A day after a preening celebration of his team's victory in the 4x100-meter relay race, Maurice Greene of the United States acknowledged today that he had received some negative reaction to the display and reiterated an apology he had first issued after the race.</p>
        <p>Greene and his relay partners -- Jon Drummond, Bernard Williams and Brian Lewis -- celebrated their victory Saturday night before more than 100,000 spectators by posing like professional wrestlers, flexing their muscles during their victory lap and on the medal stand afterward. Greene also stuck out his tongue at the cameras.</p>
        <p>''We're truly sorry if we offended anyone,'' Greene, who also won the gold medal in the 100 meters last week, said this morning at a news conference featuring several American athletes. ''It was just the first reaction. As athletes we hold so much inside and then at the end, we just let it out. As athletes, we just get caught up in the moment.''</p>
        <p>Greene said he could sense a negative reaction to the celebration at the news conference after the victory. He said he had heard from some people that the scene did not go over well and appeared tasteless.</p>
        <p>''When it first came to my attention, I didn't understand what people were talking about,'' Greene said. ''I can see now why some people were offended. I've talked to the runners. I can assure you it will never happen again.''</p>
        <p>Three More Fail Drug Tests</p>
        <p>Another weight lifter, a bronze medalist from Armenia, was among three more who have tested positive for steroids at the Sydney Olympics, the International Olympic Committee said today. The other two athletes did not win medals.</p>
        <p>The I.O.C. said that it had stripped the medal from the Armenian weight lifter, the heavyweight Ashot Danielyan. Danielyan, who lifted a total of 1,025 pounds, tested positive for nandrolone after his competition Tuesday, the final day of weight lifting.</p>
        <p>He was the fourth weight lifter to test positive at the Games, but the first from a country other than Bulgaria. The International Weightlifting Federation expelled the Bulgarian team, although a member of the team was later allowed to compete under an arbitration court ruling.</p>
        <p>Prince Alexander de Merode, the chairman of the I.O.C. medical commission, said that a Greco-Roman wrestler, Fritz Aanes of Norway, also tested positive for nandrolone after losing a bronze-medal match Wednesday.</p>
        <p>De Merode also formally announced that Svetlana Pospelova, a 400-meter runner from Russia, tested positive for the steroid stanozolol in an out-of-competition test.</p>
        <p>Eight athletes now have tested positive in Sydney since the Games began Sept. 16, with more than 50 others caught in tests before the Games around the world.</p>
        <p>''I'm actually quite pleased that we caught a number of cheats,'' said Michael Knight, Australia's Olympics minister. ''I think it's the worst-kept secret that drug-assisted cheating was going on.''</p>
        <p>De Merode said a total of 1,946 in-competition urine tests had been conducted at the Games, in addition to 404 out-of-competition urine tests and 313 blood-urine tests for the hormone EPO, conducted both in and out of competition.</p>
        <p>De Merode said more tests would be conducted today throughout the final day of competition, when 24 gold medals are to be awarded before the closing ceremony. (AP)</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: RELAY CELEBRATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
