<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Appears the United States Will Not Win a Gold Medal for the First Time Since 1948</title>
    <meta content="01BOXI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235373"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E4D7153DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Appears the United States Will Not Win a Gold Medal for the First Time Since 1948</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sunday, Oct. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses possibility that United States boxing team will not win gold medal at Sydney Games (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States boxing team began these Olympics hoping to be favorably compared to the 1976 United States Olympic team that won five gold medals.</p>
        <p>It appears it will end the tournament linked instead to the 1948 United States team -- the last roster of United States boxers who competed in an Olympics without winning a gold medal. (The United States boycotted the 1980 Moscow Olympics.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States boxing team began these Olympics hoping to be favorably compared to the 1976 United States Olympic team that won five gold medals.</p>
        <p>It appears it will end the tournament linked instead to the 1948 United States team -- the last roster of United States boxers who competed in an Olympics without winning a gold medal. (The United States boycotted the 1980 Moscow Olympics.)</p>
        <p>Today, after the American featherweight Ricardo Juarez was defeated in his gold medal bout by Bekzat Sattarkhanov of Kazakhstan, and after the American light-welterweight Ricardo Williams Jr. lost his final fight to Mahamadkadyz Abdullaev of Uzbekistan, the American team leader, Gary Toney, stood not far from the ring saying he was lodging an official protest of Juarez's loss.</p>
        <p>But as Toney maintained that Sattarkhanov should have been disqualified for holding too often, the Kazakh fighter stood 75 feet away on the top platform during the gold medal ceremony inside the ring.</p>
        <p>Juarez, the reigning world champion, had a silver medal around his neck, but stood with his head down throughout the entire medal ceremony, briefly wiping tears from his cheeks.</p>
        <p>More than an hour after the Juarez fight, officials from the Amateur International Boxing Association had not announced their ruling on the American protest. But in the Olympics' computerized scorekeeping system, which lists protested fights as unofficial until the protest is ruled on, the decision declaring Sattarkhanov the winner was categorized as official.</p>
        <p>Before today there were five other protests of bouts during the tournament. All of them had been dismissed.</p>
        <p>''I counted nine times that the referee cautioned the fighter from Kazakhstan,'' Toney said of Referee Stanislav Kirsanov of Russia. ''The rule is that after the third caution the referee must issue a warning which brings about an automatic 2-point deduction. After the fifth caution the fighter is supposed to be disqualified.</p>
        <p>''It's very hard to score blows inside when your opponent is constantly holding. I don't know if the protest will do any good, but I'm going to file it.''</p>
        <p>A gold medal bout cannot be refought, but decisions have been reversed in highly unusual circumstances.</p>
        <p>Juarez, who had won his last 68 fights, was disconsolate.</p>
        <p>''It's no consolation to have the silver medal,'' he said. ''I didn't come here for the silver.''</p>
        <p>Evander Holyfield, who has acted as an unofficial coach to the United States team in Sydney, said he thought the Russian referee was biased toward the fighter from Kazakhstan, one of several nations created after the breakup of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>''They split up the Soviet Union, but those countries are still associated with the Russians,'' Holyfield said. ''They all speak Russian. The ref didn't do his job. He didn't let Juarez get a chance to fight. You've only got two minutes in there per round. How you going to score points if the guy is holding you as soon as you get close to him?''</p>
        <p>United States Coach Tom Mustin  aid repeatedly last week that he did not want to become the first American boxing coach in 52 years to have to go home without a gold medal.</p>
        <p>''And I thought we'd get two today,'' Mustin said. ''But it didn't work out that way, and the officials didn't help us in the first fight.''</p>
        <p>The United States finishes the 2000 Olympic boxing tournament with two silver medals and two bronze medals.</p>
        <p>Most of the cautions for holding that Sattarkhanov received were in the fourth round, when Sattar khanov, who must have known he held a commanding lead on points, was clutching and grabbing Juarez.</p>
        <p>Juarez, however, trailed the entire fight, falling behind by 4-1 early in the first round.</p>
        <p>Sattarkhanov is 4 inches taller than the 5-foot-3-inch Juarez and scored easily with his left jab. Juarez had been effective in the tournament getting inside taller opponents -- he says he is used to it because all his opponents are taller -- but he had trouble figuring out a way to penetrate Sattarkhanov's solid defense. And Sattarkhanov did not allow Juarez to battle him inside.</p>
        <p>The second round, scored in favor of Sattarkhanov, 10-2, put the Kazakh fighter way ahead on points, 15-4. While Sattarkhanov was using stalling tactics, Juarez did seem slower to the punch and repeatedly gave away points in his efforts to get inside.</p>
        <p>With left-and-right-hand combinations midway through the third round, Juarez rallied to close the gap to 18-13 as Sattarkhanov seemed to tire. But Sattarkhanov caught a second wind late in the round and padded his led to 20-13 with consecutive straight right-hand leads.</p>
        <p>Juarez began the fourth round with a big lead right hand of his own, but Sattarkhanov spent the last minute of the fight on the run, clutching and occasionally scoring with left hands off the break.</p>
        <p>Williams appeared sluggish after his difficult, toe-to-toe victory over the Cuban Diogenes Luna in Friday night's semifinals. That fight, which Williams won, 42-41, was the highest scoring fight of the Olympic tournament.</p>
        <p>Today Williams fell behind early and never recovered.</p>
        <p>He was behind, 10-5, after two rounds and briefly closed the gap to 15-11 at the start of the fourth round. But Abdullaev appeared the stronger fighter in the end and with a series of quick left hands padded his lead to win on points, 27-20.</p>
        <p>''I have no excuses,'' Williams said. ''I came out a little slow,but I thought I did enough in the last two rounds to win. Unfortunately, the judges didn't see it that way. I guess he was the better fighter today.''</p>
        <p>Bulat Jumadilov, the reigning flyweight world champion, became the first fighter from Kazakhstan to lose in the medal round. He lost on points, 19-12, to Wijan Ponlid of Thailand, who had a large rooting section at the boxing site.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
