<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sizing up Children's Museums...Sending In Pint-Size Critics; Newcomer Is Put Through Its Paces</title>
    <meta content="MB001304" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DD163DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="902" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sizing up Children's Museums...Sending In Pint-Size Critics; Newcomer Is Put Through Its Paces</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAURA CASEY</byline>
      <dateline>NORWALK, Conn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Stepping Stones Museum for Children opened here in March after eight years of planning and fund-raising. Its one-story building in Mathews Park contains six galleries that offer about 40 different activities for children up to 10 years old.</p>
        <p>To test the museum's mettle, I enlisted two willing judges, my children, Timothy Panzarella, 6, and Anna Panzarella, 12.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Stepping Stones Museum for Children opened here in March after eight years of planning and fund-raising. Its one-story building in Mathews Park contains six galleries that offer about 40 different activities for children up to 10 years old.</p>
        <p>To test the museum's mettle, I enlisted two willing judges, my children, Timothy Panzarella, 6, and Anna Panzarella, 12.</p>
        <p>This was the third children's museum they have visited in two years. My children are neither sophisticated nor sheltered, although they haven't yet been to Disney World and aren't allowed to own Nintendo, an occasional source of contention in our house. Tim is a fan of ''Star Wars,'' interested in the Civil War and an avid collector of Pokemon cards. When Anna isn't going to school, she's listening to rock music or practicing splits and cartwheels for gymnastics.</p>
        <p>Tim gave the museum a solid B. Anna made allowances for the fact that the activities in the museum aren't designed to engage someone quite her age and admitted that some areas bored her. But even she found some exhibits interesting and said that she would also give the museum a B for children younger than she.</p>
        <p>Both hugely enjoyed the gallery called ''I Spy Connecticut,'' which focuses on transportation and gives children realistic simulations of driving a Metro-North train and flying a helicopter. The helicopter, which comes complete with the sound of rotating blades, holds four children at once, and two can handle the controls. The train's controls operate model trains, and monitors inside the cab show the trains responding to the directions of the young engineers. But the controls are a little obscure and may take initial adult supervision for youngsters to operate without frustration.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the gallery, a video monitor gives children the sights and sounds of flying a helicopter over real Connecticut landscapes. A ''submarine'' with a periscope rounds out the exhibit.</p>
        <p>Tim loved the ''Waterscape'' gallery. The availalbe rubber aprons came in handy here as children of all ages manipulated toy boats through rapidly flowing water in routes of the children's own choosing, tossed plastic balls into a vortex to see what would happen and observed where ''rain'' goes and what it does. Tim returned to this gallery again and again for the pure fun of splashing and playing.</p>
        <p>Anna pointed out, and I agreed, that the museum offered a paucity of explanations on the scientific principles behind the activities. Children can observe that water in the vortex moves clockwise, but there is nothing posted to explain why it doesn't go counter-clockwise; they can see that water moves more swiftly downhill, but there's no explanation so parents with a nonscientific background can supply more in-depth information to children.</p>
        <p>Rhonda Kiest, the museum's executive director, said the museum was still a work in progress. ''Traditionally, in children's museums there is not as much labeling as in other museums,'' she said. ''We're constantly improving.''</p>
        <p>The ''In the Works'' exhibit was another crowd-pleaser. Children have a chance to build Lego cars and race them, four at a time, down a tilted racetrack, complete with an electronic scoreboard that gives the time of the fastest car down to hundredths of a second. Yet here, too, I wished for explanations that weren't offered about the role of weight and gravity that made some cars finish faster than others. The children, though, didn't care.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in this section, a small crane that Tim was happy to manipulate used a large magnet to pick up metal weights. A small sailboat allowed him to hoist a sail. Balls placed in a machine traveled through an elaborate route of gutters and slides to end up at different destinations.</p>
        <p>The ''Express Yourself'' gallery specializes in activities that help children communicate, whether with music, art or language. It has a darkened room in which they can make glow-in-the-dark drawings with special pens, which interested both Anna and Tim. It also has an exhibit with drums of different sizes and sounds that Tim could pound on to his satisfaction. Other activities in this section, though, seemed either more obscure or simply less engaging to my more physically oriented son.</p>
        <p>Parents with small children may find a haven in ''Toddler Terrain,'' which has places for the children to crawl and walk and areas for their tired parents to sit down.</p>
        <p>Both my children made a beeline to the gift shop, which has a nice variety of educational toys, puzzles and kits for sale.</p>
        <p>All in all, we spent a solid two hours at the museum. And in the ultimate compliment, when we were leaving, Tim turned to me and said, ''Mom, when will we go here again?''</p>
        <p>What museum could ask for more?</p>
        <p>Stepping Stones Museum for Children, off Interstate 95 in Mathews Park, Norwalk. Hours: 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tuesday through Saturday and noon to 5 p.m. Sunday. Admission: $6; children under 1 free. Free parking. Vending machines and small snack area for visitors. Information: (203) 899-0606.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
