<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Bridges Begin And Skyscrapers End</title>
    <meta content="01S10NWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="67" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOR YOUNG VIEWERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shattuck, Kathryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Building Big (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DD153DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="369" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Bridges Begin And Skyscrapers End</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kathryn Shattuck</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shattuck, Kathryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Television series Building Big previewed; photo (For Young Viewers) (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As a child living in England, without a television to watch and largely dependent on himself for entertainment, David Macaulay began erecting bridges, skyscrapers, even cable car systems, out of homemade materials on his living room floor. Forty years later, as a writer and illustrator living in the United States, he has turned the science of engineering into a source of entertainment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As a child living in England, without a television to watch and largely dependent on himself for entertainment, David Macaulay began erecting bridges, skyscrapers, even cable car systems, out of homemade materials on his living room floor. Forty years later, as a writer and illustrator living in the United States, he has turned the science of engineering into a source of entertainment.</p>
        <p>In ''Building Big,'' a five-part mini-series on megastructures to be shown on Tuesdays at 8 p.m. on Channel 13, Mr. Macaulay, who has a degree in architecture, explores the history and ingenuity behind some of the world's greatest feats of engineering.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to produce two things that would support each other,'' Mr. Macaulay said of the mini-series and its companion book of the same name.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to look at what kind of people build these things,'' he said. ''In the film, we're dealing with the human element behind these structures. In the book, I said, 'You're the designer. Here's the problem. Solve it.' ''</p>
        <p>''Building Big'' offers armchair engineers 10 and older the answers to some challenging questions: How does a graceful suspension bridge withstand the forces of nature and traffic? What does it take to build a skyscraper 100 stories tall? What keeps these gravity-defying giants from collapsing?</p>
        <p>To that end, Mr. Macaulay supplemented his job as the series' narrator with his own illustrations - sometimes drawn upside down while he talks on screen - to show the logical progression of creativity and circumstance.</p>
        <p>''There's a sort of sequence in the early drawings,'' he said, ''where suddenly you see these things assembled and it's just amazing.''</p>
        <p>Over the course of filming, Mr. Macaulay journeyed to hallowed structural ground, from the 5,000-year-old Sadd el Kafara dam in Egypt to the 1,475-foot Petronas Towers in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, the world's tallest structures.</p>
        <p>Still, he remains unjaded. ''There wasn't one structure you could look at and take for granted after you got to know it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Well, maybe one. ''I can't get my own house finished,'' he said with a laugh. ''It's taking me forever.''</p>
        <p>Kathryn Shattuck</p>
        <p>FOR YOUNG VIEWERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
