<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In an Apartment Turned Museum, a Dominican Trove</title>
    <meta content="01MUSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: WASHINGTON HEIGHTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carnival (Pre-Lenten)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Dominican Republic</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of Dominican Folkloric Carnival</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Amaro, Isaias</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kugel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Dominican Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDF173DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In an Apartment Turned Museum, a Dominican Trove</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH KUGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kugel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Isais Amaro has turned his apartment on West 176th Street into Museum of Dominican Folkloric Carnival, featuring elaborate masks and costumes used during Dominican street festivals, traditional musical instruments, paintings by local artist Ezequiel Jimenez and photos from carnival celebrations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Isaias Amaro made his first carnival mask out of a school notebook when he was 5, and from the looks of his living room walls he's been making them ever since. Tomorrow, that  living room, the dining room and one bedroom in his first-floor apartment at 507 West 176th Street will cease to exist, replaced by New York City's newest attraction: the Museum of the Dominican Folkloric Carnival.</p>
        <p>The museum will showcase elaborate masks and costumes that Mr. Amaro and others have created for carnival, a Dominican street festival not unlike Mardi Gras, and for parades in the New York region. Also on display will be traditional musical instruments, paintings by Ezequiel Jimenez, a local artist, and photographs from Dominican carnival celebrations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Isaias Amaro made his first carnival mask out of a school notebook when he was 5, and from the looks of his living room walls he's been making them ever since. Tomorrow, that  living room, the dining room and one bedroom in his first-floor apartment at 507 West 176th Street will cease to exist, replaced by New York City's newest attraction: the Museum of the Dominican Folkloric Carnival.</p>
        <p>The museum will showcase elaborate masks and costumes that Mr. Amaro and others have created for carnival, a Dominican street festival not unlike Mardi Gras, and for parades in the New York region. Also on display will be traditional musical instruments, paintings by Ezequiel Jimenez, a local artist, and photographs from Dominican carnival celebrations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amaro, the museum's founder, is still working on an exhibit of traditional Dominican cooking utensils, and plans to install an old-fashioned Dominican country-style bed with a mattress made of dried plantain leaves.</p>
        <p>''The idea is, first, to introduce our culture to everyone,'' Mr. Amaro said of the museum, which will be free. ''Second, to bring us closer to other Latino groups who have a similar heritage. And third, to keep our young people off the streets, to create new artists and artisans.''</p>
        <p>Besides serving as a museum and living quarters -- Mr. Amaro will live in a second small bedroom near the entrance -- the apartment will do triple duty as a workshop, the new site for mask-making classes he gives to neighborhood children.</p>
        <p>For as long as he can remember, Mr. Amaro has been obsessed with carnival, which in the Dominican Republic takes place in February. Traditional costumes vary by region, he said, but often include some variation of masked ''diablos cojuelos.'' The museum will display masks from different provinces, as well as a whip made from a cow bladder, used to deal playful blows to carnival spectators.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amaro is also a comedian who has performed on Spanish-language television. He teaches art, too, in the after-school program at P.S. 210.</p>
        <p>There is no sign outside the decidedly informal museum, nor any labels on the displays, at least not yet.  Mr. Amaro -- or his many friends and students who constantly stop by -- serve as impromptu tour guides.</p>
        <p>Although museum hours will be from 9 a.m. to 2 p.m. and 6 p.m. to 9 p.m., Monday through Friday, and 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. on Saturday and Sunday, it is pretty clear that, basically, the museum will be open whenever Mr. Amaro is home. (The museum telephone is (212) 568-0972.)</p>
        <p>Does giving up his privacy bother him? ''To the contrary,'' Mr. Amaro said. ''If I didn't, I'd feel lonely. I love to share, to teach, to spread knowledge.''</p>
        <p>SETH KUGEL</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: WASHINGTON HEIGHTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
