<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Company Is Silent But Keeps Struggling</title>
    <meta content="01CROS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Crossroads Theater Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woliver, Robbie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DD1F3AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Company Is Silent But Keeps Struggling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBBIE WOLIVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woliver, Robbie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Crossroads Theater Company's continuing struggles less than two years afer winning Tony Award as outstanding regional theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LESS than two years after winning a Tony Award as outstanding regional theater, the Crossroads Theater Company, in New Brunswick, is struggling to survive.</p>
        <p>The financially plagued theater, acclaimed for its commitment to African-American plays, has canceled the first two shows of its 23rd season: Samm-Art Williams's ''Conversations on a Dirt Road,'' and a production of the Tony-winning Fats Waller musical ''Ain't Misbehavin'.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LESS than two years after winning a Tony Award as outstanding regional theater, the Crossroads Theater Company, in New Brunswick, is struggling to survive.</p>
        <p>The financially plagued theater, acclaimed for its commitment to African-American plays, has canceled the first two shows of its 23rd season: Samm-Art Williams's ''Conversations on a Dirt Road,'' and a production of the Tony-winning Fats Waller musical ''Ain't Misbehavin'.''</p>
        <p>Not only is the beleaguered theater going dark, it is also falling silent. Dale Caldwell, president of Crossroads' board of trustees, who has publicly expressed concern about the theater's $1.7 million debt and the organization's fiscal disarray, did not respond to telephone calls seeking comment. Equally quiet have been the general manager, Deborah Stapleton, and the executive producer, Andre Robinson Jr. All e-mail sent to the theater's Web site is returned, and this week callers to the theater's offices got a recording that said the phones were temporarily disconnected.</p>
        <p>The theater has had arts organizations, politicians and supporters scurrying to help keep it afloat. But there has been a series of defections and departures, including the loss of the theater's founder and artistic director, Ricardo Khan (who says he will return as a fund-raiser), and two board members who quit this past summer. The theater also reduced its staff to 4, from 20.</p>
        <p>For patrons like Red Barker, a lawyer from Lawrenceville, the possibility of Crossroads not reopening is a sad one. ''The theater exposed all sorts of people to the life, historical and cultural experiences of people of color,'' Mr. Barker said. ''It would be a shame to lose that.''</p>
        <p>Laura Aden, executive director of the New Jersey Theater Group, said: ''It's a very important institution for both the state and the country. Not producing shows would be a terrible loss.'' Ms. Aden said she was hopeful that the theater would rebound and launch its season in January.</p>
        <p>More than $835,000 is budgeted for the theater, including as much as $335,000 waiting to be awarded by the New Jersey State Council on the Arts as soon as the theater supplies an agreeable plan to reduce its debt. Accountants from Johnson &amp; Johnson, the New Brunswick-based corporate giant, have been consulted to help put the theater's books in order.</p>
        <p>''We requested a great deal of information from them,'' said Nina Stack, spokeswoman for the Arts Council. ''We received some, and there's more that we expect to receive.''</p>
        <p>Last year, the theater canceled previews of ''Play On!'' because it could not pay for costumes, sets or actors' salaries. Low ticket sales also hurt the theater. In 1998, only 54 percent of its seats were sold. Creditors began to line up.</p>
        <p>In another stinging blow, the Geraldine R. Dodge Foundation, based in Morristown, held back its annual $100,000 grant last year. David Grant, the foundation's executive director, said that in June, as a gesture of good will, $50,000 was released to the theater for general operating support. ''The theater had begun external financial planning, which helped the Dodge trustees release funds that they were holding back,'' Mr. Grant said. ''We wanted them to know we were long-term fans.''</p>
        <p>It was the theater's 1991 move to its new $4 million location on Livingston Avenue that many believe caused the downward spiral, along with diminishing arts financing. As the new building's debts grew, Crossroads never caught up, even with major support from the state and local organizations like New Brunswick's New Millennium Bank, community groups, churches and the N.A.A.C.P.</p>
        <p>A plan to reorganize, which included a $500,000 loan from the New Jersey Redevelopment Authority and a $400,000 fund-raising campaign, was put into place last year. But the theater fell behind in its new loan payments. A marketing campaign also fell apart and no subscriptions were sold.</p>
        <p>Besides the State Legislature's approval of $500,000 in emergency financing and the $335,000 the arts council held in reserve, an additional $500,000 in federal grant money was offered for an after-school program to be held at the theater.</p>
        <p>In June, Governor Whitman, who approved the $500,000 in special state aid, stated ''Crossroads Theater, the nation's premier African-American theater, is unfortunately experiencing substantial financial difficulties and cannot wait for the possibility of future funding.''</p>
        <p>Until the theater can prove its fiscal responsibility and stability, Crossroads will remain silent. But many in the New Jersey arts community believe that the theater will fulfill the requirements to expand its board, mend its finances and professionalize their organization.</p>
        <p>''Writing their obituary is very premature,'' Ms. Aden said.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
