<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milosevic's Worst Nightmare</title>
    <meta content="01GART$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/opinion/01GART.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kostunica, Vojislav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garton Ash, Timothy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D6173DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milosevic's Worst Nightmare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Timothy Garton Ash</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Garton Ash, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>OXFORD, England</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Timothy Garton Ash Op-Ed article profiles Vojislav Kostunica, quiet-spoken constitutional lawyer who has brought final, successul, challenge to Serb leader Slobodan Milosevic; reports that 'one of gloomiest men I know' is also genuine moderate supported by coalition of democrats who are less nationalistic than he is (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vojislav Kostunica is one of the gloomiest men I know. This may be an advantage for a new president of whatever remains of Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>Even if the miracle happens and Slobodan Milosevic, who is denying that Mr. Kostunica won an absolute majority in the presidential election and insisting on a runoff, goes without bloodshed, gloom will still be in order. A new federal republic of Yugoslavia will have a ruined economy, like Romania after 1989; a burden of guilt, like Germany after 1945; ubiquitous corruption, like Russia today; and still unresolved ethnic-territorial issues, like, well, old Yugoslavia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vojislav Kostunica is one of the gloomiest men I know. This may be an advantage for a new president of whatever remains of Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>Even if the miracle happens and Slobodan Milosevic, who is denying that Mr. Kostunica won an absolute majority in the presidential election and insisting on a runoff, goes without bloodshed, gloom will still be in order. A new federal republic of Yugoslavia will have a ruined economy, like Romania after 1989; a burden of guilt, like Germany after 1945; ubiquitous corruption, like Russia today; and still unresolved ethnic-territorial issues, like, well, old Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>Who is the man upon whom such a heavy burden may fall, if he becomes president? Large, gray-suited, quiet-spoken, painstakingly analytical, Mr. Kostunica talks more like an academic than a politician. Indeed, until 10 years ago, he was just that -- a constitutional lawyer and a political scientist. Now 56, he has been an active party politician only since 1989, when non-Communist party politics became possible.</p>
        <p>The first time we met, in 1997, during the last great anti-Milosevic demonstrations, he took me to an old-fashioned restaurant in central Belgrade and told me he really believed in the original Yugoslavia -- that is, the Serb-dominated unitary kingdom that existed between the two world wars. (His father was an officer in its royal army.) It was, he said, or at least should have been, an exercise in nation-building under a British-style constitutional monarchy. Look how the king had given his first son a Serbian name, his second a Croatian name and his third a Slovenian one -- rather as British monarchs deliberately called their heir the Prince of Wales. Croats, Slovenes and Bosnians would find that a rose-tinted view of the past.</p>
        <p>But for today, he explained at great length, a new Yugoslavia needed what he called asymmetric federalism -- with different rights and powers for the different component parts -- as a solution for Kosovo, Montenegro and Vojvodina, and perhaps also for the Serb republic in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>Vojislav Kostunica is a very serious man. Solid. Consistent. Knowledgeable and capable of sophisticated rational argument. Principled, too. But hardly a bundle of fun. Short on charisma.</p>
        <p>Nor is he a great believer in the politics of the street. During the 1997 protests, he told me that he was wary of the demonstrators' cult of spontaneity, their belief in ''the movement'' as an end in itself. Yet his own future, and with it that of all southeastern Europe, now depends on his ability to lead a peaceful, inventive, effective movement of mass protest and civil disobedience.</p>
        <p>In late 1998, we met in the spartan office of his tiny opposition party, the Democratic Party of Serbia. His talk was all of Kosovo and how its future inside Serbia must be secured by constitutional, peaceful means. Ordinary, decent Serbians would be dismayed at what Mr. Milosevic was doing there, he said. In an election held under international supervision, Mr. Milosevic could be defeated. Fat chance, I thought.</p>
        <p>A year later, after the war and the NATO bombing, which he criticized fiercely, the office seemed even more spartan and bare. This time, he was furious with the United States and Britain. TonyBlair! Robin Cook! He spat out the names of the British prime minister and foreign minister with contempt. ''But,'' he added, ''I know they are not the West.'' The West was also Henry Kissinger, whom he took to be a critic of the Kosovo war, and Noam Chomsky and Harold Pinter.</p>
        <p>So is Mr. Kostunica a ''moderate nationalist,'' as some newspapers are calling him? What exactly is a moderate nationalist? Some old Yugoslav hands, shocked by his strong support for the Bosnian and Kosovo Serbs, say he's as bad as Slobodan Milosevic. Some even say he's more deeply nationalist than Mr. Milosevic, the post-Communist opportunist.</p>
        <p>This is both true and completely false. It's true that Mr. Kostunica has been more seriously and consistently concerned about the fate of the Serbian nation than Mr. Milosevic. In other, happier places and times he would be a conservative, romantic patriot of the kind frequently encountered in the British Conservative Party (and they have some pretty rose-tinted views of the national past, too). In this unhappy place and time, he has said and done things he should regret: being photographed holding an automatic weapon among Kosovo Serbs, for example, whatever his explanation for the incident is.</p>
        <p>But I have no doubt that he is genuinely moderate -- and what matters is his moderation. It is not just that he is supported by a coalition of democrats who are less nationalist than he is. He is himself, in his style and intellectual formation, profoundly committed to using civilized, peaceful, constitutional means. And one lesson of Europe's terrible 20th century is that the means you embrace are quite as important as the ends. Perhaps more important.</p>
        <p>This is a man who is passionate about the rule of law. Who believes in elections, institutions, negotiations. And he sees that the only future for his country lies in a return to Europe.</p>
        <p>Whether Mr. Kostunica gets a chance to show if he has it in him to become a popular leader of a peaceful, negotiated revolution, we shall see. But human beings can grow with a great challenge. History makes the most unlikely heroes. He may yet be one.</p>
        <p>Timothy Garton Ash, a fellow at St.  Antony's College, Oxford, and at the Hoover Institution, is author of the forthcoming ''History of the Present.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Timothy Garton Ash, a fellow at St.  Antony's College, Oxford, and at the Hoover Institution, is author of the forthcoming ''History of the Present.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
