<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jones Math: Endurance Plus Speed Equals No. 5</title>
    <meta content="01TRAC$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/olympics/01TRAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235352"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: TRACK AND FIELD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0D8153DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jones Math: Endurance Plus Speed Equals No. 5</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They were not all gold, as she had hoped, but Marion Jones became the first woman to win five medals in track and field in the same Olympics today. The measure of her greatness as a sprinter was most evident by her withering speed and endurance in the 400 meters, a race she hardly ever runs.</p>
        <p>Another favorite, Suzy Favor Hamilton, also appeared to be in position for victory in the women's 1,500 meters, an event in which no American had ever won a medal, only to fall to the track in the homestretch, suffering from overexertion and dehydration. Her collapse was symbolic of the American underachievement at these Sydney Games. Not since 1896 had the United States won as few as 20 medals in track and field at the Summer Games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They were not all gold, as she had hoped, but Marion Jones became the first woman to win five medals in track and field in the same Olympics today. The measure of her greatness as a sprinter was most evident by her withering speed and endurance in the 400 meters, a race she hardly ever runs.</p>
        <p>Another favorite, Suzy Favor Hamilton, also appeared to be in position for victory in the women's 1,500 meters, an event in which no American had ever won a medal, only to fall to the track in the homestretch, suffering from overexertion and dehydration. Her collapse was symbolic of the American underachievement at these Sydney Games. Not since 1896 had the United States won as few as 20 medals in track and field at the Summer Games.</p>
        <p>Jones's Olympic reach exceeded her gold medal grasp, but she established herself indisputably as the world's greatest female sprinter. After rescuing a bronze medal in the shaky 4x100-meter relay today, Jones took the baton for the third leg of the American 4x400-meter relay today abreast of Jamaica's Deon Hemmings.</p>
        <p>Usually, the third leg is one where a coach might try to hide an uncertain sprinter, but neither of these runners could be called unreliable. Hemmings was the 1996 Olympic champion in the 400-meter hurdles. Jones had run one open 400 this year in 49.59 seconds, which would have won the event at the 1999 world track championships.</p>
        <p>Into the first curve, Jones opened a slight lead, and she would not relinquish it. Out of the final turn, where she might have been expected to grow fatigued and heavy-legged, she instead increased her margin to 10 meters, then 15, then 20 before passing the baton. She had not run a 400 since May. Still, her split today was 49.4 seconds. While a direct comparison is not possible, her effort would have been fast enough to win a silver medal in the open 400 at the Sydney Games.</p>
        <p>Her leg put the Americans comfortably on their way to a victory in 3 minutes 22.62 seconds, providing Jones with her third gold medal of the Sydney Games. In the 4x100-meter relay, a pair of poor exchanges put the Americans in fourth place when Jones got the baton today. She still rescued a bronze medal, however, in 42.20 seconds.</p>
        <p>Fanny Blankers-Koen of the Netherlands remains the only woman to win four gold medals in track and field at the same Olympics. She won the 100, 200, 4x100 relay and 80-meter hurdles at the 1948 London Games. With victories in the 100, 200 and 4x400 relay, Jones became the first female American sprinter to win three golds since Florence Griffith Joyner in 1988. Jones also won bronze medals in the long jump and the 4x100 relay. No other woman has left a Summer Games with so much Olympic jewelry around her neck.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Jones's accomplishment must be weighed against the pressure of her own expectation, widespread public anticipation and the turmoil of the disclosure that her husband, the shot-putter C. J. Hunter, had tested positive for elevated levels of the steroid nandrolone. Inevitably, there were stated suspicions about her own achievement, too. But however disruptive the maelstrom surrounding Jones and her husband, her own achievements appeared to come in moments of calm endeavor.</p>
        <p>''When I walked into the stadium, it seemed like everything off the track was just that, off the track,'' said Jones, who trains in Raleigh, N.C. ''We've had a very long season. We weren't going to let something ruin it. We worked too hard, had too many days in 20-degree temperature. The sacrifices go on and on. Once I stepped on the track, it was no problem.''</p>
        <p>In the women's 1,500 meters, the Americans appeared ready to challenge for their first medal since it became an Olympic event in 1972. After the race crawled through the first 400 meters in 70.56 seconds, Marla Runyan of the United States took the lead. She is the first legally blind athlete to make an American Olympic team in any sport. Favor Hamilton moved near the front and then went to first place as the race reached 800 meters in 2:15.93.</p>
        <p>After jockeying at the front, Hamilton regained the lead with about 250 meters remaining, but as several runners passed her coming out of the final turn she began to lose her form, her arms pumping wildly, a contorted look on her face. She stumbled to the track as her right leg strayed wide and gave out.</p>
        <p>Nouria Merah-Benida of Algeria won the gold medal in 4:05.10, becoming the second Algerian woman in the past three Summer Olympics to win the metric mile. Violeta Szekely of Romania took the silver in 4:05.15, and Gabriela Szabo of Romania, the 5,000-meter winner in Sydney, made a furious closing charge to take the bronze in 4:05.27 after nearly tripping over a fallen British runner. The obstruction probably cost Szabo the gold medal in a race that was the slowest at the Olympics since 1976.</p>
        <p>Favor Hamilton got to her feet and crossed the finish line in 12th and last place in 4:23.05, but she was taken from the track in a wheelchair and did not speak with reporters. Jill Geer, a spokeswoman for the United States track and field federation, said Favor Hamilton was treated with intravenous fluids before returning to her hotel. The fall did not appear to be related to an injury, Geer said, adding that Favor Hamilton seemed disoriented after the race.</p>
        <p>Runyan, who finished eighth in 4:08.30, said she spoke with Favor Hamilton and asked what happened. She said Favor Hamilton had been breathing heavily and had not replied. She appeared to be on the verge of losing consciousness, and her head lolled to one side as she was taken off the track. No medical explanation was provided by the American team for the incident.</p>
        <p>''Maybe it was the disappointment, the fall and the shock all at once,'' Runyan said.</p>
        <p>As expected, the Americans dominated the relays. With Maurice Greene, the men's 100-meter gold medalist, running anchor, the American men won the 4x100 relay in 37.61 seconds. The disappointment of losing to Canada four years ago was erased, but the relay members came under jeering whistles from fans and criticism from other sprinters for posturing like professional wrestlers after the race.</p>
        <p>The United States men also won the 4x400-meter relay in 2:56.35, with Michael Johnson running anchor and winning his fifth career gold medal.</p>
        <p>The chances of winning the women's 4x100-meter relay had seemed remote for the United States, given that Inger Miller, the 1999 world silver medalist in the 100, and Gail Devers, the two-time Olympic champion in the 100, were unavailable because of hamstring injuries.</p>
        <p>The resulting team of Chryste Gaines, Torri Edwards, Nanceen Perry and Jones never practiced as a group, which showed in clumsy exchanges between Edwards and Perry and Perry and Jones. The Bahamas, featuring athletes trained and educated in the United States, won its first track and field gold medal in 41.95. Jamaica, with 40-year-old Merlene Ottey winning her eighth career Olympic medal, took the silver in 42.13.</p>
        <p>Two hours later, Jones ran the 4x400-meter relay. She has not even rehearsed the 400 meters since May, her coach, Trevor Graham, said. Yet, she ran the fastest split on the relay.</p>
        <p>''I felt surprisingly good,'' Jones said. ''I was concerned that when I hit the straightaway, my legs were going to say, 'No more, Marion, no more.' They didn't.''</p>
        <p>If Jones trained seriously, Graham said, she could probably break the 15-year-old world record in the open 400, of 47.60, held by Marita Koch of East Germany. But Jones said unambiguously today that she had no interest in the event.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, the question arose: Would she consider trying for five golds at the 2004 Summer Games in Athens when she will be 28? ''I'm just going to really enjoy this now,'' Jones said. ''Trevor and I will sit down in the next couple months, the next couple years. Right now I'm just going to take this all in. It was a very good experience for me.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: TRACK AND FIELD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
