<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/Long Island; KeySpan Ponders the Future of 500 Riverhead Acres</title>
    <meta content="01LIZO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Riverhead (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Keyspan Energy Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rather, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4D8103AF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/Long Island; KeySpan Ponders the Future of 500 Riverhead Acres</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RATHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rather, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Keyspan Energy, formed by merger of Brooklyn Union Gas and Long Island Lighting Co, prepares to divest itself of more than 500 acres of farmland, woods and shorefront in Riverhead with eye toward preservation; photo; maps (In the Region/Long Island) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>KEYSPAN ENERGY, the giant gas and electric concern formed two years ago by the merger of Brooklyn Union Gas and the Long Island Lighting Company, is preparing to divest itself of more than 500 acres of farmland, woods and Long Island Sound shorefront in the Town of Riverhead, potentially with an eye toward preservation, its officials said.</p>
        <p>In an unusual turn for a publicly traded corporation, KeySpan officials said they were looking beyond the land's enormous development potential to explore ways to preserve much if not all of the holding in its current state, provided a method could be found for fair compensation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>KEYSPAN ENERGY, the giant gas and electric concern formed two years ago by the merger of Brooklyn Union Gas and the Long Island Lighting Company, is preparing to divest itself of more than 500 acres of farmland, woods and Long Island Sound shorefront in the Town of Riverhead, potentially with an eye toward preservation, its officials said.</p>
        <p>In an unusual turn for a publicly traded corporation, KeySpan officials said they were looking beyond the land's enormous development potential to explore ways to preserve much if not all of the holding in its current state, provided a method could be found for fair compensation.</p>
        <p>The property, where Lilco proposed building two nuclear power plants in the 1970's, is among the largest remaining privately owned open expanses on eastern Long Island and would be worth tens of millions of dollars if sold for development. Farmland currently sells for $25,000 an acre in the area, and prime shoreline lots near bluffs on the property's northern boundary, with spectacular views over Long Island Sound, would sell for more than $300,000 an acre, real estate agents said.</p>
        <p>The land is currently zoned to allow industrial use, but could also be used for expensive housing, condominiums or a private or public golf course with town permission. But residents of the North Fork of Long Island and all of Suffolk County have repeatedly voted for programs to preserve farms and open space.</p>
        <p>Farmland, farm stands and vineyards are also crucial to the traditionally agricultural North Fork's appeal to tourists and weekend visitors, many of whom come from densely suburban western Long Island. Voter-approved land protection programs have been slowed, however, by a lack of willing sellers.</p>
        <p>KeySpan said that while no final decisions had been made it was considering a number of preservation approaches for the property, including transfer of development rights to Suffolk County, sale of the land to New York State for a park, and other types of purchase or preservation plans that combined state, county, local and even Federal financing sources.</p>
        <p>KeySpan's senior vice president for corporate affairs, David J. Manning, said the challenge for the company was finding harmony with environmental and public interests while protecting shareholders.</p>
        <p>''We have been in discussion with local politicians, state officials, community leaders, environmentalists and developers,'' Mr. Manning said. ''There are a number of people who are interested in the potential for the property in all directions.'' Mr. Manning said that KeySpan considered the site too remote for a power station.</p>
        <p>The land is in an agricultural corridor along Sound Avenue in the eastern part of Riverhead. A small portion is within the Town of Southold. Keyspan currently leases 230 acres to two farmers who grow potatoes, corn, squash and other crops, but the leases expire at the end of this year.</p>
        <p>The Hallockville Museum Farm and Folklife Center, a not-for-profit historic preservation group, owns eight acres of land and historic buildings contiguous to the KeySpan property. The museum's name is derived from the Hallock family, who were among early English settlers of the North Fork. The Hallock homestead, restored to interpret farm life a century ago, is open to the public and is on the National Register of Historic Places.</p>
        <p>KEYSPAN officials said they hoped to make a good impression on Long Islanders by being sensitive to preservation sentiment and the goals of the museum.</p>
        <p>''We're just trying to do the right thing,'' Mr. Manning said.</p>
        <p>Company officials inclined toward preservation, however, must contend with possible investor backlash, Mr. Manning said, if KeySpan passes up likely offers from private developers willing to pay large amounts for the property.</p>
        <p>But KeySpan officials said they would also risk severe approbation from environmental and civic groups as well as some elected officials if the company took a more conventional path and sold the property to the highest bidder regardless of future use.</p>
        <p>Under a takeover plan carried out two years ago, Lilco sold its electric transmission and delivery system to the Long Island Power Authority but retained power plants and other assets, including the Riverhead land, which passed to KeySpan after the merger.</p>
        <p>During the 1970's, Lilco had sought federal and state permission to build two nuclear power plants on the property, but a state board rejected the plan in 1980 and said that only a coal-powered generating station would be permitted. The coal-powered station was never built, and the property -- though deeply scarred on a section of its shoreline where another former owner, Levon Corporation, mined large volumes of sand and destroyed coastal bluffs -- has remained undisturbed since then.</p>
        <p>As KeySpan edged closer to divesting the property, there were many suggestions about how the company should proceed.</p>
        <p>John Eilertsen, the executive director of the Hallockville Museum Farm and Folk Life Center, said the group was requesting that KeySpan donate 50 acres of farmland to the museum to restore the Hallock farmstead to its size of 100 years ago. He said the group wanted the remainder of the farmland preserved in some way and favored public access routes to the Sound.</p>
        <p>''With more and more of the farmland disappearing, the land is becoming a greater and rarer asset,'' Mr. Eilertsen said. ''It should be a resource for all of Long Island.'' The nightmare, he said, would be ''an intensive housing development with little or no preservation or another golf course.''</p>
        <p>In the last five years, several Riverhead farm owners have converted fields into public golf courses. One developer, William Talmage, ignored offers from Suffolk County to acquire an environmentally sensitive wooded area on the Talmage farm and cleared fairways for an 18-hole course on 286 acres of fields, woods and Long Island Sound bluffs shortly after the town board approved the controversial project.</p>
        <p>Two environmental groups, the Long Island Pine Barrens Society and the North Fork Environmental Council, are suing the town for allowing the project, but lost a lower court ruling last month.</p>
        <p>Preservation groups were eager to avoid a repetition on the KeySpan property. ''We have certainly expressed our interest in helping KeySpan,'' said John Halsey, the president of the Peconic Land Trust, a not-for-profit group that promotes farm and open space preservation on Long Island's East End.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halsey said a plan could include limited development on a portion of the property in an area set back from the bluffs but also away from farm fields. ''It would also be nice if there was a gift component,'' Mr. Halsey said. He said such a gift would carry substantial tax benefits for the company.</p>
        <p>Others said preservation of all of the nearly last-of-its-kind parcel was warranted. ''We have told KeySpan they should make the property available for acquisition in total,'' said Richard L. Amper Jr., the executive director of the Long Island Pine Barrens Society. ''There should be no partial development. We are asking them to do the environmentally correct thing.''</p>
        <p>Joseph M. Gergela, the executive director of the Long Island Farm Bureau in Riverhead, where the largest remaining farm area on the East End is situated, said the bureau ''would love to see if there is some way to save that farmland.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gergela said he recommended cutting the farmland into several sections, transferring the development rights to the government and selling the remaining rights to the highest private bidders.</p>
        <p>In development rights programs, used by Suffolk County since the late 1970's as a tool to save working farms, the county or another government buys and holds the development rights in perpetuity, lowering the price and taxes for land that remains available only for agricultural uses.</p>
        <p>George Gatta, the deputy Suffolk County executive for economic development, said the county was prepared to participate with New York State in a preservation plan for the KeySpan property. Mr. Gatta and state officials said the property had been recommended for a state open-space list, enhancing chances of state financing for a purchase. One possibility would be for some or all of the property to become a state park that provided public access to Long Island Sound. Roads on the property's western and eastern borders connect Sound Avenue to the shoreline.</p>
        <p>John Atkins, the president of Save the Sound Inc. of Stamford, Conn., a group leading a coalition promoting federal legislation  that would set up a Long Island Sound reserve, said KeySpan would perform an immense public service by preserving the land and allowing shoreline access.</p>
        <p>Senator Joseph Lieberman of Connecticut, the Democratic candidate for vice president, has said he would consider introducing a bill creating the reserve. Mr. Atkins said the bill could lead to federal financing for purchase of lands along Long Island Sound, where public access is limited.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
