<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In London, Ho-Hum Ends In Smash Finale</title>
    <meta content="01FASH$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/01/living/01FASH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235176"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FASHION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcqueen, Alexander</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chalayan, Hussein</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horyn, Cathy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5DF173DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In London, Ho-Hum Ends In Smash Finale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Sept. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cathy Horyn reviews British spring 2001 fashion collections, focusing on those of Alexander McQueen and Hussein Chalayan; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was close to midnight on Wednesday in the old Gainsborough film studios when the last of the reporters and camera crews elbowed their way into the grim little corner where Hussein Chalayan waited. Mr. Chalayan is famously aloof, and at times his comments add up to mumbo jumbo, but there is nothing vague about his talent. It punches you in the nose with its audacity, and makes you feel grateful for the blow. Without Mr. Chalayan and Alexander McQueen here to deliver such jolts, the British spring 2001 collections would be as inconsequential as a baby's burp.</p>
        <p>But it's interesting: both Mr. Chalayan and Mr. McQueen, who alluded to images of trauma and insanity in a brilliant show on Tuesday night in a padded glass cell, sent out clothes that were  then destroyed by the models wearing them. In Mr. McQueen's show, they battered skirts made with loosely strung seashells that had been gathered by his relatives in the Norfolk marshes, leaving unsightly bare spots on the fabric and a floor littered with broken ornament. In Mr. Chalayan's show, the models put a little more elbow grease into it. They used hand mallets to chip away at dresses of sugar glass that had caused their maker, a product designer named Paul Topen, considerable grief that morning as he ferried them in a van from his home in Scotland. ''One of them did crack,'' Mr. Topen said of the molded frocks, ''but we managed to repair it.'' So it could be wrecked properly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was close to midnight on Wednesday in the old Gainsborough film studios when the last of the reporters and camera crews elbowed their way into the grim little corner where Hussein Chalayan waited. Mr. Chalayan is famously aloof, and at times his comments add up to mumbo jumbo, but there is nothing vague about his talent. It punches you in the nose with its audacity, and makes you feel grateful for the blow. Without Mr. Chalayan and Alexander McQueen here to deliver such jolts, the British spring 2001 collections would be as inconsequential as a baby's burp.</p>
        <p>But it's interesting: both Mr. Chalayan and Mr. McQueen, who alluded to images of trauma and insanity in a brilliant show on Tuesday night in a padded glass cell, sent out clothes that were  then destroyed by the models wearing them. In Mr. McQueen's show, they battered skirts made with loosely strung seashells that had been gathered by his relatives in the Norfolk marshes, leaving unsightly bare spots on the fabric and a floor littered with broken ornament. In Mr. Chalayan's show, the models put a little more elbow grease into it. They used hand mallets to chip away at dresses of sugar glass that had caused their maker, a product designer named Paul Topen, considerable grief that morning as he ferried them in a van from his home in Scotland. ''One of them did crack,'' Mr. Topen said of the molded frocks, ''but we managed to repair it.'' So it could be wrecked properly.</p>
        <p>Up until Mr. McQueen's glorious crack-up, there was no discernable reason to get out of bed for the London shows, much less cross the Atlantic. Whatever became of London's surly, shoestring inventiveness? And where is that sense of outrage that spawned rebels like Vivienne Westwood? The new British designers don't seem mad at or amused by anything.</p>
        <p>Sure, there were moments of honest fun: Matthew Williamson's agreeably raunchy skirts with baseball sweaters flocked with rhinestones; Luella Bartley's nouvelle-punk leather splashed with graffiti or electrified with neon wool ribbing. Marjan Pejoski showed sequined cartoon figures having sex on the front of otherwise banal dresses, and while it's hard to picture Yogi as anything other than a common bear, Mr. Pejosky's casual perversion of popular images is completely consistent with themes of contemporary British art.</p>
        <p>But mostly what one noticed were designers mired in revivalism (the 1980's) or unable to impart through their clothes a burning need for self-expression other than, say, recycling vintage. It was unclear from Roberto  Menichetti's overworked Burberry collection what vital theme he was serving by putting models in fattening layers of cotton. Similarly, there was nothing in Clements Ribeiro's history of quirky romance to explain the sudden assault of grommet-riddled leather and Grecian drapery in the sex-pot style of Gianni Versace.</p>
        <p>With the Tate Modern drawing crowds, and all the attention in the London newspapers on the Young British Artists and the ''Apocalypse'' exhibition at the Royal Academy, you have to wonder how young designers like Marcus Constable and Emma Cook can be turned on by something as safe as an off-the-shoulder top and a crepe skirt with a flounced hem. Maybe that's as far as their talent stretches, and certainly there's nothing wrong with making clothes that sell. But after heeding all the criticism stressing the need to be less eccentric and more commercial, perhaps British fashion finally has what it deserves. A creative vacuum.</p>
        <p>This was the talk of the collections, or at any rate, when people weren't talking about Mr. McQueen or Mr. Chalayan. ''Don't you think it's a hard time in fashion right now?'' asked Joan Kaner, the fashion director of Neiman Marcus, who was among a handful of American retailers at the shows. ''I think we went away from individuality to 'this is what the season is going to be about.' '' Certainly, on the streets here, you don't see the peacock displays that were abundant in the 80's, when Westwood groupies abounded in tartan bondage trousers.</p>
        <p>''People aren't buying designer labels like they did before,'' the hat maker Philip Treacy said Thursday in his Chelsea workroom. ''They're making up their own minds about what they think is comfortable. It's fashionable to look unfashionable.''</p>
        <p>''What you saw in the mid-80's in fashion,'' he added, ''you see now in the art world. They're getting the breaks that young designers had before, but it's the art world that's coming out stronger.''</p>
        <p>The morning after the McQueen show, I went to see the ''Apocalypse'' exhibition, whose theme is beauty and horror in contemporary art. Looking at Maurizio Cattelan's life-size waxwork of Pope John Paul II being struck by a meteorite or at Jake and Dinos Chapman's vitrines of Bosch-like war mutants in ''Hell,'' I had a better appreciation of Mr. McQueen's presentation. And I could see that the emotions elicited by the show were consonant with a great designer who is not only making beautiful clothes, but also responding, like an artist, to the horror and insanity in contemporary culture.</p>
        <p>By having his audience view the collection through the one-way glass of a large padded room (the models could not see out), Mr. McQueen was, of course, setting up a spatial relationship -- a room within a room -- that could feel threatening to all. As the models appeared, their heads wound with white gauze, the clothes were undeniably exquisite -- ripples of nude pleated silk with fuzzy caterpillars of fabric running over a shoulder, a pencil-thin coat in chalky pink stripes over trousers and a filmy jersey blouse, a long sleeveless coat with a digitalized portrait of a face in acid tones. But then, almost immediately, there was a sense of decay and delirium as the shell dresses were shattered, and other models, with taxidermied birds on their heads or shoulders, swanned out in feathered skirts jutting eccentrically away from their bodies, as if in some bird-kingdom display of courtship. You can find similar uses of feathers at the Tate Modern.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most paradoxical aspect of Mr. McQueen's show was that amid the extravagant show pieces there was not a single garment that couldn't be worn or didn't say ''Now.'' Afterward, Mr. McQueen said: ''I think the ugly or the frightening can be beautiful. It's the way my mind works.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Chalayan's show was perhaps not as ambitious, or as mesmerizing, as previous ones, but he, too, is working within the ethos of the contemporary art world, largely by using technology to manipulate what is real and not real; futuristic and historical. He opened his show with a kind of video game involving dolls that he projected on a screen. The models themselves resembled dolls, with porcelain makeup and identical wigs and stiff movements, so that they almost seemed inanimate. (Dolls also figure in some of the Chapman brothers' work, but with a different effect. Theirs seem eerily human.)</p>
        <p>Among the clothes Mr. Chalayan showed were neat blazers in graphite gray over white cotton shirts and skirts with pencil-like scribbles of embroidery across the front. There were pleated skirts with a displaced flap of pleats on one side, and a number of variations on denim jackets and skirts, with contrasting panels of, say, blue cut out in somewhat elliptical shapes and inset into khaki or white.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chalayan revisited his hourglass silhouette, and there were beautiful dresses printed with red or deep blue poppies that were life-size at the hem and then seemed to extend into infinity as your eye traveled up the dress. After the show, when it was almost midnight, Tim Blanks, a reporter for one of the cable television fashion programs, went up to the pale Mr. Chalayan and asked why his shows so often deal with themes of catastrophe and displacement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chalayan smiled. ''I suppose,'' he said, ''I'm quite a negative person.''</p>
        <p>FASHION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
