<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuba Cruises to Third Straight Gold</title>
    <meta content="Y01VOL$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000: VOLLEYBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volleyball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Volleyball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volleyball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEFDC153DF932A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuba Cruises to Third Straight Gold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Sept. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cuba defeats Russia, 3-2, to win gold medal in women's volleyball at Sydney Olympics; Russia wins silver medal and Brazil wins bronze; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The thick gray hair of the Russian coach, Nikolai Karpol, bounced as he barked at his blank-faced players, and his thick eyeglasses slid down his nose while he shook his fists at them.</p>
        <p>Everything and nothing set him off today. With the abrupt fury of a steam whistle, Karpol unleashed his notorious rage on the Russian players whether they were in the midst of taking a two-game lead against Cuba or mentally buckling to lose the women's gold medal match to their long-time rivals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The thick gray hair of the Russian coach, Nikolai Karpol, bounced as he barked at his blank-faced players, and his thick eyeglasses slid down his nose while he shook his fists at them.</p>
        <p>Everything and nothing set him off today. With the abrupt fury of a steam whistle, Karpol unleashed his notorious rage on the Russian players whether they were in the midst of taking a two-game lead against Cuba or mentally buckling to lose the women's gold medal match to their long-time rivals.</p>
        <p>From beginning to end, Karpol was incorrigible, but this is who he is. For 20 years, he has been a coach capable of turning Bobby Knight's temper into an undercard event. Even though many of those in the stands today had witnessed Karpol before, they were still appalled. Throughout the match, they booed and hissed at the Russian coach.</p>
        <p>Near the end of the fourth game, just after a misstep by Yelena Vassilevskaia set off an outburst by Karpol, a heckler from the stands yelled out, ''Why don't you shut up, Coach. You're a disgrace.''</p>
        <p>''I always say I'm like an actor playing a role,'' Karpol explained afterward. ''Whether my role is positive or negative, it depends on the players. The players create the screenplay.''</p>
        <p>While Kapol's anger-for-effect method was failing him, Cuban coach Louis Calderon's patient style stood in brilliant contrast. The Cubans squandered early leads, were out of sync in their defense for two games and were on the verge of collapse, but Calderon kept clapping, remained upbeat and pushed his team to believe in comebacks.</p>
        <p>The positive reinforcement worked. As Regla Torres put away a final kill to win Cuba's third consecutive gold medal in women's volleyball, the team celebrated the faith they had in themselves to deliver a 25-27, 32-34, 25-19, 25-18, 15-7 victory. Cuba has now won every major international event since the 1992 Olympics.</p>
        <p>''I'm relieved,'' said the 6-foot-3-inch Torres, who, at 25, has been the long-time star of the team. ''The first two sets, I was a little out of focus; I was frightened. I was too excited. I was talking too much. I had to shut up. I started listening to what my teammates and coaches were telling me.''</p>
        <p>The calm of the Cubans is legendary. They are masters of the comeback, and pulled out today's gold medal with a mix of athletic skill, unshakeable defense and endurance. The longer the match grew, the more weary the Russians became.</p>
        <p>''In the third, fourth and fifth sets, we were showing fatigue,'' Vassilevskaia said. ''They were playing very well. We couldn't resist the pressure from the Cuban team.''</p>
        <p>The tension even before the first serve was evident. As the coach of the teams from the Soviet Union that won gold medals in 1980 and 1988, Karpol was under pressure to return Russia to the top of the medal stand after the team finished fourth in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>The Cubans were also bearing a heavy burden. With their nation hungry for a gold medal after the baseball team was shocked by the United States, with their countrymen waking up to watch their beloved women's team play in the early morning hours, the Cubans felt the weight of the moment.</p>
        <p>''We were tense at first,'' Torres said. ''Then we relaxed and played together.''</p>
        <p>Once Cuba loosened up, the younger Russians withered. They started to miss routine kills and became confused on the court. Everyone was coming undone. Inside one timeout huddle, Karpol started lashing out at the long-limbed scorer Yelena Godina before aiming a tirade at the defensive specialist, Yelena Tiorina, then moving on to the next target. On one last substitution, he berated the outgoing Elizaveta Tichtchenko, then started in on another player for failing to be in the right place.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately for our players, we do not have enough experience to survive these trials,'' Karpol said. ''We lost our concentration in the third set, and it led to the defeat.''</p>
        <p>The loss was hard for him to accept. Even at the end, as the elated Cuban team danced on the floor, Karpol was spotted yelling at an official. Slowly, his dispirited team assembled on the bench. Some began to sob in their towels, others just stared straight ahead. In his disgust, Karpol walked away.</p>
        <p>As he departed, the Cuban team was hugging each other and waving their country's flag. It was the same good vibe that sustained them when the Cuban were down by two games.</p>
        <p>''I never really thought the Olympics could be so difficult, never in my life,'' said Torres, who dominated the middle and wore down the Russians. ''I cannot express what I feel. I'm very emotional.''</p>
        <p>Early this afternoon, the United States lost the bronze medal match to the experienced Brazilians, 25-18, 25-22, 25-21. For the United States, there was some consolation. They entered the Olympics ranked No. 10 in the world.</p>
        <p>''I think it would have been difficult to win today, but not impossible,'' said Tara Cross-Battle. ''We were just a little off. Maybe we were a little too fired up.''</p>
        <p>At age 32, Cross-Battle is retiring from the United States team. ''It was hard knowing that this was probably my last match in a U.S. uniform,'' she said. ''But I have no regrets.''</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000: VOLLEYBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
