<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two inventors honored for seminal work on the balloon catheter and wireless communications.</title>
    <meta content="22PATE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PATENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Catheters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lemelson-Mit Prize</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riordan, Teresa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">fogarty, thomas j (dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">gross, al</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6D9113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two inventors honored for seminal work on the balloon catheter and wireless communications.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Teresa Riordan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riordan, Teresa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dr Thomas J Fogarty is awarded Lemelson-MIT Prize for his Fogarty Embolectomy Catheter, invention that revolutionized vascular surgery, which he first described in paper published in 1963; Lemelson-MIT Lifetime Achievement Award for Invention is awarded to Al Gross, pioneer in wireless communications, who received patents over the years for technologies that anticipated inventions ranging from garage door openers to cell phones and paging systems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the eighth grade in the late 1940's, Thomas J. Fogarty, in order to help his widowed mother make ends meet, went to work at Good Samaritan Hospital in Cincinnati, cleaning medical equipment.</p>
        <p>By the time he got to high school, the hospital promoted him to scrub technician. ''So at a very early age I saw a lot of surgery,'' said Dr. Fogarty, who often witnessed the complications arising from blood clots, which surgeons struggled to remove with forceps after a large part of an artery had been cut open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the eighth grade in the late 1940's, Thomas J. Fogarty, in order to help his widowed mother make ends meet, went to work at Good Samaritan Hospital in Cincinnati, cleaning medical equipment.</p>
        <p>By the time he got to high school, the hospital promoted him to scrub technician. ''So at a very early age I saw a lot of surgery,'' said Dr. Fogarty, who often witnessed the complications arising from blood clots, which surgeons struggled to remove with forceps after a large part of an artery had been cut open.</p>
        <p>Last month Dr. Fogarty was awarded the annual Lemelson-M.I.T. Prize to inventors for his Fogarty Embolectomy Catheter, an invention that revolutionized vascular surgery after he published a paper describing the device in 1963. Still the world's most widely used catheter for blood-clot removal, the Fogarty balloon catheter was the progenitor of a family tree of balloon catheters used for a wide range of surgeries.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fogarty, who is now 66, envisioned his balloon catheter while still a student at the University of Cincinnati Medical School. Working in his attic, he fashioned a prototype by snipping the pinkie finger off a surgical glove and then -- using fly-tying knots he had learned while fishing as a boy -- attaching it to a catheter.</p>
        <p>With Dr. Fogarty's invention, surgeons make small incisions and insert the catheter, with the balloon not yet inflated, into the artery. After threading the catheter down the artery so that the balloon passes the clot, the balloon is inflated and retracted, pulling the clot along with it.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fogarty, who lives in Portola Valley, Calif., and is a professor of surgery at Stanford University, is still a practicing surgeon. He is also a successful entrepreneur who develops new medical devices through his company, Fogarty Engineering, and a venture capitalist who funds budding medical companies through Three Arch Partners. He also owns a 325-acre eponymously named vineyard west of Palo Alto that produces 15,000 cases of wine annually.</p>
        <p>The Lemelson-M.I.T. prize, which comes with a $500,000 purse, is awarded by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and the Lemelson Foundation. The prize is named for the late Jerome H. Lemelson, a prolific inventor whose mechanisms were used in the fax machine, the supermarket checkout scanner, the Sony Walkman and other devices.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fogarty -- who credits his childhood deprivation with much of his entrepreneurial drive -- said he planned to give the prize money to charity. It is the award itself that is important, he said.</p>
        <p>''The fact that this award is being given to a physician, particularly one who is in practice, is meaningful,'' said Dr. Fogarty, noting that such awards are usually given to academics who conduct basic research. ''You can spend your whole life in a basic research lab,'' he said, ''but until something is implemented and used by people, it doesn't bring real social value.''</p>
        <p>Another inventor, Al Gross, 82, received the Lemelson-M.I.T. Lifetime Achievement Award for Invention. And last week the Federal Communications Commission sent him a letter of commendation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gross, a pioneer in wireless communications, has received patents over the years for technologies that anticipated inventions ranging from garage door openers to cell phones and paging systems. Alas, he notes, the patents expired before any of those devices came into common use. ''Otherwise I'd be as rich as Bill Gates,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gross was introduced to radio transmissions at the age of 9, when his parents took him on a Lake Erie steamer cruise. The ship's wireless operator beckoned him to come into the communications room and give a listen. He was hooked. By the time he was 12, he had patched together his own ham radio from junkyard parts. At age 16, he earned his amateur radio operator's license. But Mr. Gross was restless being anchored to the desk-bound ham radio.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to be able to walk around and talk to other hams,'' Mr. Gross said. He experimented with a hand-held radio that made use of unexploited frequencies above 100 megahertz. By 1938 he had created a mobile ham radio that worked. He dubbed it the ''walkie-talkie.''</p>
        <p>Soon came World War II, and Mr. Gross, who was then 22, was invited down to Washington to demonstrate his walkie-talkie in front of William J. Donovan, the founder of the Office of Strategic Services -- the precursor to the C.I.A. ''Donovan liked the idea,'' Mr. Gross said. ''He recruited me and converted me from a civilian to a captain.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gross's top-secret mission in the O.S.S. was to develop a two-way air-to-ground voice communications system so that spies in enemy territory could transmit information to allied pilots flying overhead. By 1941, Mr. Gross had perfected such a system. The Joint Chiefs of Staff later said the project, code-named ''Joan-Eleanor,'' was among the Allies' ''most successful wireless intelligence-gathering operations, saving millions of lives by shortening the war.''</p>
        <p>Shortly before the end of the war, Mr. Gross demonstrated the O.S.S. walkie-talkie to the Federal Communications Commission's chairman, E. K. Jett, who was so impressed he wrote an article for the Saturday Evening Post titled ''Phone Me By Air.'' The article announced the creation of a Citizens' Radio Communications Service that would allow for private, short-range radio transmissions. In it, Mr. Jett marveled at the possibilities of what he referred to as ''handie-talkies.''</p>
        <p>A staged photo accompanying the article featured a milkman talking into a radio that, minus the antenna, somewhat resembles a modern-day cell phone, except that it is about the size of a large loaf of bread. ''Handie-talkies may result in a civilian world seething with airborne languages,'' the caption predicts. ''Even the milkman can be reached en route and told to go back and leave an extra quart of Grade-A for Mrs. Ramsay.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gross, who left the O.S.S. to form his own electronics company, was the first to get a citizens' band license from the F.C.C. His target market was not milkmen but farmers who, while they were in the fields on their tractors, wanted to keep in touch with their wives at home.</p>
        <p>Soon he was developing new ideas, among them a paging system for doctors that he introduced in 1949, according to Mr. Gross, who long ago gave up running his own company but is still working, as a staff engineer for the Orbital Sciences Corporation in Chandler, Ariz.</p>
        <p>The pager apparently was an idea way before its time. ''The doctors hated it,'' Mr. Gross said. ''They complained that it would interrupt their golf games.''</p>
        <p>PATENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
