<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bishop Who Finds Men to Answer the Call</title>
    <meta content="22PRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bridgeport (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Edward M (Bishop)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schemo, Diana Jean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Connor, John (Cardinal)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6DD1E3AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bishop Who Finds Men to Answer the Call</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schemo, Diana Jean</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bishop Edward M Egan of Bridgeport, who will become next archbishop of New York, has vigorously recruited men for priesthood at time when other dioceses are struggling through shortage of priests; his success has reportedly weighed heavily on selection as successor to late John Cardinal O'Connor, a sign that Vatican considers shortage one of most serious problems facing church; Egan has aggressively courted men for priesthood, not by softening or popularizing church's stands, but by stressing orthodox view of clergy's role; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Nicholas Pavia, a city councilman and mechanic in Stamford, Conn., the call to the priesthood was neither an urgent whisper nor a siren. It was a tugging, always in the background, that stayed with him as one election followed another. And it was a summons put off by earthly misgivings.</p>
        <p>Until, that is, Mr. Pavia met the emissaries of Edward M. Egan, the bishop of Bridgeport, soon to become New York's archbishop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Nicholas Pavia, a city councilman and mechanic in Stamford, Conn., the call to the priesthood was neither an urgent whisper nor a siren. It was a tugging, always in the background, that stayed with him as one election followed another. And it was a summons put off by earthly misgivings.</p>
        <p>Until, that is, Mr. Pavia met the emissaries of Edward M. Egan, the bishop of Bridgeport, soon to become New York's archbishop.</p>
        <p>''I never felt empty, or anything like that,'' said Mr. Pavia, a 40-year-old who is to be ordained Saturday in Bridgeport. ''But I felt I could be doing something more.''</p>
        <p>At a time when other dioceses throughout the nation are struggling through a shortage of priests, Bishop Egan has vigorously recruited men like Mr. Pavia for the priesthood,  ordaining a higher proportion of priests than any other diocese in the Northeast. The bishop's success weighed heavily in his being made  head of the New York archdiocese, said one church official involved in the highly secretive selection process, a sign that the Vatican considers the shortage one of the most serious problems facing the church.</p>
        <p>In his first news conference after he was named archbishop-elect this month, Bishop Egan boasted that his business card gave not only his own phone number, but also that of his diocese's recruitment director. The bishop's accomplishment, it seems, lies in creating the structures that have allowed others to nurture aspiring priests.</p>
        <p>Though Bridgeport's diocese is only one-sixth the size of New York's,  Bishop Egan opened a minor seminary soon after arriving there in 1988, modeled on one that Cardinal John O'Connor established in the Bronx, to embrace men considering the priesthood and to allow them a year to glimpse the life they would take on if they proceeded to a seminary with a program that could lead to ordination.</p>
        <p>But the bishop also created a full-time recruitment team, headed by the Rev. Christopher Walsh, whose stated purpose was to recruit aggressively for the priesthood. They keep track of men who express an interest in becoming priests, following those who enter the seminary the bishop created, St. John Fisher in Stamford, at every step of their preparation. The diocese also adapts the seminarians' training to accommodate each candidate's interests and circumstances, and, like many other dioceses hard pressed for new priests, it readily accepts older men into the ranks of seminarians.</p>
        <p>''The Lord is calling, but there's a lot of static out there,'' Father Walsh said. ''My job is to reduce the static. To create the environment where the call can be heard.''</p>
        <p>While Bishop Egan has aggressively courted men for the priesthood, he has not done so by softening or popularizing the church's stands, but rather by stressing the orthodox view of the clergy's role. It remains to be seen how Bishop Egan's approach to training men for the priesthood will influence relations between the church and the New York archdiocese's 2.4 million Roman Catholics.</p>
        <p>Many of the priests Bishop Egan has ordained say his emphasis on restoring the traditions of the church  was one of the reasons they chose to serve in Bridgeport.</p>
        <p>Father Walsh said that some of the seminarians seemed nostalgic for a church steeped in rituals they had imagined, but not known.</p>
        <p>''Many of them are not into getting all excited about guitar Masses and Masses on the beach,'' Father Walsh said. ''They're, to be honest, more attracted to the tradition, to the liturgical tradition, to some of the devotions of the church, rosaries, novenas and eucharistic adoration.</p>
        <p>''In a sense, the generation that's coming up now have been deprived of that tradition; they're the children of the baby boomers who discarded much of that,'' Father Walsh added. ''I don't see it as an ideological fixation on the past, but as a longing for the tradition that they've missed.''</p>
        <p>Underscoring the priority he sets on building up the priesthood, Bishop Egan -- officially not New York's archbishop until his installation on June 19 -- ordained this year's graduates of St. Joseph's Seminary at St. Patrick's Cathedral on Saturday. The priests prostrated themselves on the cathedral's marble floor as the congregation prayed over them.  Bishop Egan closed his hands over theirs while the men swore lifelong respect and obedience to the archbishop-elect and his successors.</p>
        <p>But there were only five of them. Over the last year, considered an average one, more than a score of  priests have died in the New York archdiocese. And a declining enrollment of candidates for the priesthood at St. Joseph's suggests the number of new priests will slide even further in the next few years.</p>
        <p>The problem is not limited to New York. With fewer and fewer young men choosing a life of celibacy and sacrifice, many priests across the nation must serve at more than one parish. While the Roman Catholic population in America has grown 30 percent over the last 35 years, to 59.2 million from 45.6 million in 1965, the number of priests has dropped 21 percent, to 46,352 from 58,632.</p>
        <p>Dean R. Hoge, a professor at Catholic University and the author of ''The Future of Catholic Leadership,'' said that a generally rising standard of living had given young men today more career options, making the cost of the priesthood's demands -- particularly celibacy -- seem higher.</p>
        <p>''We've come to a crossroads in Catholic history,'' Dr. Hoge said. ''There's not enough candidates. We have a problem producing high quality product.''</p>
        <p>Sister Katarina Schuth, author of the 1999 book ''Seminaries, Theologates, and the Future of the Church Ministry,'' said strict traditionalists were having an increasing influence in seminaries, though they might not represent a greater share of students. Nearly half of today's seminarians, she found, begin their studies for the priesthood after a religious conversion. One out of four speak English as a second language.</p>
        <p>In such an atmosphere, even Father Walsh wonders why Bridgeport is succeeding where others are struggling.</p>
        <p>Some of the newer priests or those soon to be ordained chose the Bridgeport diocese because it was their home. But others selected Bridgeport from a number they had considered, attracted by Bishop Egan's reputation for orthodoxy and for fostering an esprit de corps.</p>
        <p>''If the diocese or priests in the diocese are being hypercritical, or saying Rome is way off base, that doesn't attract young men,'' Father Walsh said. ''You aren't going to get young men to give their lives to an institution if you're criticizing that institution.''</p>
        <p>Though the Bridgeport diocese, like New York's, is home to a large number of Hispanics, none of the young men graduating from the seminary this year are Hispanic. ''It's sort of a fluke this year,'' said Father Walsh, noting that five of the 30 seminarians considering the priesthood at St. John Fisher are Hispanic.</p>
        <p>Among those who are joining the Bridgeport diocese are Robert Kinnally, the 39-year-old dean of admissions and financial aid at Stanford University, who will enter St. John Fisher this fall. Mr. Pavia will take his vows in Bridgeport on Saturday, along with two other graduating seminarians, Peter Lenox, 24, and Andrew M. Walter, 35.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Thomas W. Powers, 35, the priest at St. Theresa's in Trumbull, Conn., left a promising job at a global consulting firm to join Bishop Egan's diocese.</p>
        <p>Father Powers calls Bishop Egan ''an impressive man, the kind of guy you want to follow,'' and he does so with an absence of reservations that can be striking in an age of skepticism. ''I trust him,'' Father Powers said. ''He's been a spiritual father to me. He inspires me.</p>
        <p>''I do God's will by obeying my bishop.''</p>
        <p>Joining the diocese not only meant giving up a successful job but also, in a way, erasing his ego so his sense of God could take over, Father Powers said. ''We really must die to ourselves,'' he said. ''He must increase, while I must decrease.''</p>
        <p>Father Powers said he was drawn to Bishop Egan's ''orthodoxy'' and ''holiness.'' Staunchly anti-abortion, Father Powers sometimes prays the rosary outside abortion clinics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kinnally, an organist who once worked as musical director of St. Augustine's Cathedral in Bridgeport, said Father Walsh's encouragement played an important role in his decision to return to the diocese. He also considered applying to the diocese in San Jose, Calif.</p>
        <p>''There's an openness to guys like me who are coming at this a little later, and the sense that what we bring to it can enrich the priesthood,'' Mr. Kinnally said. ''Bridgeport is doing so well. The simple way to say it is, they're doing something right.''</p>
        <p>In Mr. Pavia's case, the diocese tackled his misgivings head on. It even allowed him to keep his full-time job as a mechanic in the maintenance department of Stamford Hospital while he attended St. John Fisher, until he was sure about committing to the priesthood.</p>
        <p>While priests ordained in the 1960's and '70's generally do not describe the ritual of their ordination as something they gave much thought to beforehand, seeing it mostly as a necessary step to becoming the spiritual shepherd of Catholics, Mr. Pavia is awed by the moment he will deliver his personal will to the church.</p>
        <p>''The Holy Spirit at that time is coming over you,'' Mr. Pavia said. ''Everyone, from saints in heaven to the people in the pews, are praying for you. My life is now totally in God's hands.''</p>
        <p>As a newspaper boy long ago, Mr. Pavia would get so wrapped up talking to his customers that he sometimes forgot to collect their money. Now, he sees the essence of his new life in the Masses, baptisms, and confessions ahead. He envisions going door to door once again, visiting nursing homes and hospitals, seeing to the needs of his parishioners with Bible in hand. The impulse to do for others, he said, will probably never leave him.</p>
        <p>''I think that's the calling and we all have it,'' he said. ''We just respond to it in different ways.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
