<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Renting Software and the Skills to Go With It</title>
    <meta content="22APPS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201527"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Laurie J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5DA113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1636" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Renting Software and the Skills to Go With It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Small businesses are 'renting' business software from growing number of Internet companies known as ASP's--application service providers; ASP's use Internet to offer range of software and technology-related services that would otherwise be performed by internal departments at customer's company; big corporate computing departments are also striking deals with ASP's to shed at least some of their applications; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the last year, Rave Sports, a small, privately held maker of inflatable water trampolines that is based in St. Paul, has been scrambling to keep up with its sales.</p>
        <p>The last thing its executives wanted was the expense of hiring a computing staff to manage the company's accounting and sales management systems. So as a lot of other small-business executives do these days, Rave's chief financial officer, Pat Golden, decided to ''rent'' its main business software from one of a growing number of Internet companies known as A.S.P.'s.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the last year, Rave Sports, a small, privately held maker of inflatable water trampolines that is based in St. Paul, has been scrambling to keep up with its sales.</p>
        <p>The last thing its executives wanted was the expense of hiring a computing staff to manage the company's accounting and sales management systems. So as a lot of other small-business executives do these days, Rave's chief financial officer, Pat Golden, decided to ''rent'' its main business software from one of a growing number of Internet companies known as A.S.P.'s.</p>
        <p>An A.S.P. -- short for application service provider -- uses the Internet to offer a range of software and technology-related services that would otherwise be performed by internal departments at the customer's company.</p>
        <p>Some customers are contracting with application providers to handle a few computing functions, like accounting, while others, including Rave, are finding that it pays to farm out just about everything, including e-mail, human resources management and online travel booking.</p>
        <p>By signing up with an application provider, ''we've eliminated having to spend a lot of cash upfront,'' Mr. Golden said.</p>
        <p>The trend has caused an explosion of young companies specializing in the service, with the leaders including Rave's provider, Agiliti, as well as Corio, Futurelink and Managed  Opportunity. But the demand has also led to hefty investments by big telecommunications carriers, including Sprint and Qwest, which plan to expand into the market. Meanwhile, many of the the nation's Internet service providers, such as the Concentric Network Corporation, are moving into the business to make themselves more competitive.</p>
        <p>Last year at this time, there were only a few dozen companies calling themselves A.S.P.'s. By the end of this year, analysts predict, there may be several hundred application providers clamoring for the attention of small and midsize businesses, as well as the information technology departments at bigger corporations.</p>
        <p>And the clamor is likely to fall on receptive ears, as businesses seek to let somebody else deal with the headaches of operating a computer network, dealing with frequent software upgrades and running out of data storage space.</p>
        <p>Although Rave is now one of only a few thousand small businesses that use an application service provider, the number is expected to rise to 136,000 companies by the end of next year, according to Cahners In-Stat, a market research company. And by the end of 2004, according to Cahners In-Stat's forecast, more than three million small businesses will be using application providers.</p>
        <p>''This is fundamentally changing the way information technology is purchased and delivered,'' said Tom Kieffer, chief executive of Agiliti, based in Minneapolis.</p>
        <p>Small businesses typically look at application providers as a way to ''take away all the pain,'' of computing services, Mr. Kieffer said.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, big corporate computing departments are also rushing to strike deals with application providers to shed at least some of their applications. National Airlines, for one, has discovered that it can keep its technology costs down by contracting out not only basic services, like e-mail, but some of its more complex tasks as well, like operating its frequent-flier program.</p>
        <p>And it may not be long before the trend touches consumers, too. Instead of buying the latest new calendar software, a customer could simply subscribe to a calendar program,  accessing it over the Web so that it would hog memory on a server computer rather than on a PC, Palm hand-held device or, eventually, even a telephone. The only requirement is a device with a Web browser.</p>
        <p>Several Web sites already offer consumers scheduling and other basic software. Still missing is the business model that enables companies to offer consumers a full range of software services at a profit.</p>
        <p>As a result of all this activity, though, the application provider business is among the fastest-growing information technology categories today -- one whose growth rate will only accelerate, analysts predict. In 1998, revenues for application service providers totaled about $400 million in North America, according to the research firm Dataquest. Last year, that figure rose to just over $1  billion, and it is expected to double this year, to $2.4 billion. And in 2001, revenues will more than double again, to $5.3 billion, Dataquest predicts.</p>
        <p>A major force behind the predicted surge is the expected arrival in the market later this year of Sprint, Qwest and other communications carriers. Those companies are investing substantially in systems that will let them supply application services, even as they roll out high-speed networks capable of carrying voice, data and images.</p>
        <p>As the carriers enter the market, a rash of partnerships is likely to break out among the various players. By the end of the year, in fact, analysts are predicting that some companies will be offering a package of rented software and high-speed Internet access.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T, for example, has already signed a deal with USinternetworking to deliver application services over AT&amp;T's planned high-speed networks through an AT&amp;T program called Ecosystem. Eventually, analysts predict, buying a business network computing service will be like choosing a telephone calling plan.</p>
        <p>''Businesses aren't going to say, 'I want a D.S.L. line,' '' said Kneko Burney, director of markets and computing for Cahners In-Stat, referring to a type of high-speed Internet connection. ''They'll say, 'We want these business services.' ''</p>
        <p>Analysts say another factor driving growth is an increasing confidence that businesses have with the security of online communications. Because of that confidence, they are willing to make the offerings of application providers available to more employees.</p>
        <p>And businesses say they are reaping substantial savings by renting software remotely rather than buying it and installing it on site. An e-mail system, for example, can cost a company several hundred dollars for each employee to operate internally each month. By contracting with an outsider, some businesses say they can get the cost down to about $100. Other services, like travel booking and expense management, are often priced for each transaction.</p>
        <p>Some analysts predict that only the most mundane and basic computing programs, like word processing, are likely to remain on the hard disks of office computers as A.S.P.'s gain momentum.</p>
        <p>Rave, with 55 employees, has contracted with Agiliti to provide and maintain the company's e-mail, accounting and order management systems -- all for a monthly per-employee fee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Golden, Rave's chief financial officer, says the Agiliti contract has allowed Rave to avoid hiring the additional technical staff the company would have needed to handle those activities. Because of the Agiliti deal, Rave's entire internal computing operations can now be performed by one staff member, working half-time. Rave's information-technology spending is only 2 percent of sales, rather than the 5 percent Mr. Golden had been budgeting before signing with Agiliti.</p>
        <p>Contracting with an application provider has also meant that Rave can afford to use the latest accounting software, which would otherwise have been too expensive to buy for each employee, Mr. Golden said.</p>
        <p>Among bigger businesses, the construction company Morrison Knudsen decided to farm out management of its e-mail system after its acquisition of another company required adding nearly 6,000 e-mail addresses virtually overnight.</p>
        <p>''Imagine how long it would take to do that ourselves,'' said Brian Bertlin, information services director of Morrison Knudsen, based in Boise, Idaho.</p>
        <p>Morrison Knudsen also handed off operation of its online travel booking a few months ago to Unisys and is about to let Unisys take on the company's travel expense accounting system. The aim, Mr. Bertlin said, is to reduce costs in areas that do not directly generate revenues for the company.</p>
        <p>In many ways, the application provider business is similar to the network PC business model that concerns like Oracle and Novell tried to have companies embrace a few years ago. Under that plan, stripped-down personal computers were to function as terminals for software resources stored on remote computer servers. But some full-scale PC's became available for only a few hundred dollars, and the network PC model never took hold.</p>
        <p>The application provider is also reminiscent of elements of the mainframe era, when companies paid to time share the resources of giant systems owned and run by companies like I.B.M. and Digital Equipment. In the time-sharing systems of the 1970's, small and midsize companies found it more economical to rent the resources of a mainframe computer company rather than invest in  multimillion-dollar systems of their own, with all the attendant support and staffing costs.</p>
        <p>But in addition to the predominance of desktop PC's at most modern business, as opposed to the few, closely guarded mainframe terminals of yesteryear, there is at least one other key difference: in hiring an application provider, the customer is paying for the knowledge and skill of the supplier, not simply the software and server computers.</p>
        <p>''Today, it's not about economies of scale but about economies of skill,'' Ms. Burney said. ''It's all about expertise and the right operating environment.''</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
