<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ISRAEL SUMMONING NEGOTIATORS HOME AFTER NEW ATTACK</title>
    <meta content="22MIDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201627"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jericho (West Bank)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DC1E3AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ISRAEL SUMMONING NEGOTIATORS HOME AFTER NEW ATTACK</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, May 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Ehud Barak recalls peace negotiators from Sweden after firebomb critically wounds 2-year-old Israeli girl in car in Palestinian-ruled city of Jericho; attack prompts Israel to block entrance to Palestinian territories, declaring them unsafe for Israelis and tourists, and temporarily undercuts year of normalization efforts; has undermined Palestinian attempts to restore order, despite crackdown on street fighting for first time in 10 days; Palestinian officials denounce Barak, calling withdrawal of peace negotiators irresponsible decision that will lead to further deterioration and increased tensions; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak recalled his peace negotiators from Sweden today after a firebomb critically wounded a 2-year-old Israeli girl in a car passing through the sleepy Palestinian-ruled city of Jericho.</p>
        <p>The attack prompted Israel to block entrance to the Palestinian territories, declaring them unsafe for Israelis and tourists, and temporarily undercut a year of normalization efforts. The incident also undermined Palestinian attempts to restore order, although the Palestinians did clamp down on street fighting for the first time in 10 days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak recalled his peace negotiators from Sweden today after a firebomb critically wounded a 2-year-old Israeli girl in a car passing through the sleepy Palestinian-ruled city of Jericho.</p>
        <p>The attack prompted Israel to block entrance to the Palestinian territories, declaring them unsafe for Israelis and tourists, and temporarily undercut a year of normalization efforts. The incident also undermined Palestinian attempts to restore order, although the Palestinians did clamp down on street fighting for the first time in 10 days.</p>
        <p>Palestinian officials denounced Mr. Barak for pushing away from the peace table. Calling it an ''irresponsible decision,'' Ahmed Abdel Rahman, general secretary of the Palestinian Authority, said it would lead to ''further deterioration and increased tensions.''</p>
        <p>Late Saturday night, because of surging violence in the West Bank, Gaza and Lebanon, Mr. Barak also canceled a trip to consult with President Clinton on the American-mediated ''final status'' peace talks.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Clinton's advisers said they understood, the cancellation indicated that Israel was setting its own timetable despite prodding from administration officials who have devoted two terms to the Israeli-Palestinian peace effort and feel that their time is ebbing away.</p>
        <p>Middle East peace, however, does not work on anyone's schedule. Certainly, the last two weeks have produced an unpredictable shift on the ground, in which the Palestinians' frustration with the slow pace of peace erupted at the same time as officials finally got down to substantive negotiations in Stockholm.</p>
        <p>The negotiators face a September deadline, which is tight even without timeouts, given that other events will compete for the Israeli leader's attention. Soon, Mr. Barak, who is also the defense minister, will be forced to focus on the complex and delicate task of withdrawing Israeli troops from southern Lebanon by July 7.</p>
        <p>Many in the Arab world see Israel's withdrawal as a defeat to be celebrated, and as an object lesson that negates the value of peace negotiations. Fighters from Hezbollah, or the Party of God, are intensifying their attacks to ensure that Israel pulls out under fire.</p>
        <p>Today, for the first time in years, they attacked an Israeli outpost at the foot of Mount Hermon, in the Shebaa Farms area that was Syrian territory when Israel occupied the Golan Heights. Israel does not plan to withdraw from the Shebaa Farms even though Lebanon recently claimed the land as Lebanese.</p>
        <p>The United Nations, which will certify whether Israel's withdrawal is complete, is unlikely to accept Lebanon's assertion. Hezbollah sent a message today that it would keep fighting Israel if the withdrawal did not include the Shebaa Farms.</p>
        <p>Israeli television reported that Prime Minister Barak had told the military to prepare to pull its troops out of southern Lebanon in the next 10 days, but government officials immediately denied it.</p>
        <p>The approach of a full withdrawal is also prompting more defections from the Israeli-backed South Lebanon Army. Forty-six militia fighters reportedly abandoned three crucial outposts in Lebanon today.</p>
        <p>In interviews in the last week, Palestinian youths cited the Israeli withdrawal from Lebanon as proof that violence ''forces the Israelis to surrender,'' as one teenager said today. ''They are tired.''</p>
        <p>Nafez Azzam, a leader of the Islamic Holy War group in Gaza, said in reference to the uprising of the late 1980's: ''We hope that this will be a new intifada. It should continue as far as occupation remains. There is no excuse for resumption of talks under such an atmosphere. This is an atmosphere of war.''</p>
        <p>The street violence, which involved sustained gunfire between Israeli and Palestinian troops last Monday, provoked opposition forces on both sides to press their leaders to suspend the talks. At the Israeli Cabinet meeting today, Health Minister Shlomo Benizri of the ultra-Orthodox Shas Party said Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, was ''either a dead horse or a deadly one,'' and he declared the peace effort useless.</p>
        <p>Still, the Stockholm negotiations continued until today, when Mr. Barak halted them ''in light of the situation.'' He also deferred the transfer of Abu Dis and two other villages abutting Jerusalem to full Palestinian control.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's office said he viewed the incident in Jericho ''with the greatest concern'' and demanded that the Palestinian Authority track down those responsible. The little girl was severely burned, and her mother and aunt had less serious burns.</p>
        <p>The attack unnerved pro-peace Israelis, who have hesitated to regard the recent violence as anything but a short-lived spurt because such incidents were seen as a thing of the past. Many have touted the normalization of tourism to Jericho in particular as an emblem of successful ''people to people'' relations.</p>
        <p>It is also a reflection of the very successful casino there.</p>
        <p>''We today are not at peace with ourselves when we see what is happening with the Palestinians,'' said Shlomo Lahat, a former mayor of Tel Aviv and chairman of a pro-peace forum. ''We are sensitive people, and we understand their pain -- but to attack people and shoot at them -- that's the thanks we get? These things cause us to reconsider whether the road we are on is right one.''</p>
        <p>The Palestinians see things differently.</p>
        <p>In the last nine days, rubber-coated or live bullets fired by Israeli troops killed 5 Palestinians and wounded more than 1,000 others, the Palestinian Red Crescent Society said today. Palestinian human rights groups said the Israeli troops were using ''excessive force against unarmed Palestinians,'' although some of the protesters, who threw stones and firebombs, were backed by sharpshooters. The Israeli soldiers targeted chests, abdomens and necks, and used live ammunition to disperse crowds, the human rights advocates said.</p>
        <p>The violence grew out of street protests on behalf of the 1,650 Palestinian prisoners in Israel, coupled with demonstrations marking the anniversary of what Palestinians call the ''nakba,'' the ''catastrophe'' that coupled the destruction of Palestine with the birth of Israel.</p>
        <p>In a familiar ritual here, some protesters marched to Israeli guard positions on the outskirts of Palestinian areas and threw stones and firebombs. The Israeli soldiers responded by firing tear gas, rubber bullets and live bullets. And the Palestinian police were hesitant to place themselves between their own people and the Israeli forces.</p>
        <p>''The Palestinian Authority cannot use brutal measures on its own people,'' said Nabil Amr, the minister of parliamentary affairs.</p>
        <p>Today, however, the Palestinian police prevented most demonstrations in the West Bank and Gaza from escalating into violent clashes. In Ramallah, for instance, they set up roadblocks on all streets leading to an Israeli-guarded junction and then, using billy clubs, pushed hundreds of stone-throwing demonstrators away from the fence of a nearby settlement. In one instance, demonstrators began throwing stones at their own police officers, and some of the officers hid behind a wall and threw stones back.</p>
        <p>Some Palestinians said they thought a visit by Samuel R. Berger, Mr. Clinton's national security adviser, to Mr. Arafat in Ramallah on Saturday night helped calm the situation. Saeb Erekat, a senior Palestinian official, said ''the Americans affirmed their readiness to hold a trilateral summit'' with Mr. Arafat and Mr. Barak but insisted that progress in negotiations be made first.</p>
        <p>That would require talks to resume. And Mr. Berger, speaking at Tel Aviv University today, seemed to be urging the parties to rise above the moment and take the long view.</p>
        <p>''Today and in the months ahead, we have a historic opportunity that we must not allow to slip away -- a chance to resolve the Israeli-Palestinian problem, the core of the Arab-Israeli conflict,'' he said. ''The alternative to a peaceful compromise is not the status quo, it is something very different and, I am convinced, far worse.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
