<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maryland Rides Second-Half Rally to Sixth Straight Title</title>
    <meta content="22LACR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="LACROSSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Maryland</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Princeton University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollander, Sophia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lacrosse</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E3DE1E3AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maryland Rides Second-Half Rally to Sixth Straight Title</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA HOLLANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hollander, Sophia</byline>
      <dateline>EWING, N.J., May 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maryland defeats Princeton, 16-8, to win women's NCAA lacrosse championship (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Princeton band was playing the genie music from ''Aladdin'' late in the first half, as the orange and black heads in the stands bobbed and swayed, swept away by a first half that saw their women's lacrosse team leading five-time defending national champion Maryland, 3-1, in the championship game. With a 4-3 edge at halftime, Princeton wanted to believe.</p>
        <p>But starting the second half, the unruffled Terrapins unleashed their own magic: Jen Adams. A junior attack who did not have a shot in the first half, Adams scored five goals and had five assists, darting around a suddenly muddled Tiger defense.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Princeton band was playing the genie music from ''Aladdin'' late in the first half, as the orange and black heads in the stands bobbed and swayed, swept away by a first half that saw their women's lacrosse team leading five-time defending national champion Maryland, 3-1, in the championship game. With a 4-3 edge at halftime, Princeton wanted to believe.</p>
        <p>But starting the second half, the unruffled Terrapins unleashed their own magic: Jen Adams. A junior attack who did not have a shot in the first half, Adams scored five goals and had five assists, darting around a suddenly muddled Tiger defense.</p>
        <p>Adams's 10 points -- a women's lacrosse single-game tournament record -- powered the Terrapins past the Tigers, 16-8, giving Maryland (21-1) its sixth straight National Collegiate Athletic Association Division I championship and record eighth over all. It was Princeton's (15-4) first trip to the title game since 1995, when the Terrapins began their streak with a 13-5 victory.</p>
        <p>''After halftime it's how much you want it,'' said Adams, who finished with a record 136 points this season. ''A small spark can start a big fire. We weren't as composed in the first half, but people just took it to another level. A couple of goals can quickly change the game.''</p>
        <p>And they did.</p>
        <p>Twenty seconds into the second half, the sophomore midfielder Courtney Hobbs scooped in a pass from Adams and fired the ball into the net, the second of her four goals on the day.</p>
        <p>Maryland controlled the draw and streaked downfield, chipping the rust off a fast break that had been so fluid in the 17-7 semifinal victory against Loyola last Friday night. The senior goalie Laura Field blocked a hard Terrapin shot, but lost control of the ball and fell, frantically poking the ball away with her stick as players collapsed around her.</p>
        <p>Adams picked up the ball, drove and was fouled. The Australian converted the free-position shot, providing Maryland with a 5-4 lead -- its first since midway through the first quarter. One minute 19 seconds later, Adams scored again for a 6-4 lead, and Princeton would not recover as Maryland went on streaks of four and five goals, outscoring the Tigers by 12-4.</p>
        <p>''Maryland showed in the second half why they've won six in a row,'' Princeton Coach Chris Sailer said. ''We were so sharp defensively to hold them to three goals in the first half. The second half was a totally different story.</p>
        <p>''We had trouble defensively; on the fast breaks we were just a step behind. We got a little tentative.''</p>
        <p>Though Maryland scored first, on a free-position shot by Hobbs, Princeton consistently teased the defense out from around the goal, gaining clear looks at the net.</p>
        <p>The Tigers maintained possession and patience, and with 16:29 left in the first half, the sophomore attack Lauren Simone curved around the defense from the right corner and thrust the ball past Alex Kahoe to tie the score at 1-1. Two minutes later, the junior Julie Shaner bounced in a shot and, after Maryland tied the score at 3-3, Shaner scored again with four seconds left in the half.</p>
        <p>Princeton would not lead again.</p>
        <p>''I'm just speechless,'' Maryland Coach Cindy Timchal said. ''This season has been an incredible journey for us. Princeton was a formidable opponent. They took us to the limit and we really stepped it up in the second half.''</p>
        <p>''It's the best way to go out,'' said the senior Terrapin midfielder Christie Jenkins, who scored one goal. ''It's something we worked really hard for as a team. It's just amazing playing like this.''</p>
        <p>It might even be magical.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>College of New Jersey Wins</p>
        <p>In the day's first game, Dana Latona had five goals and two assists, setting one tournament record and tying another, as the College of New Jersey defeated Williams, 14-8, to win a record 10th N.C.A.A. Division III women's lacrosse championship.</p>
        <p>The Lions (17-0) won their seventh title in the last 10 years, while Williams (14-2) lost to the Lions in the finals for the second time in three years.</p>
        <p>The College of New Jersey, which has won 11 titles on the field but had to relinquish one in 1992 because of an ineligible player, extended its home winning streak to 76 games.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>LACROSSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
