<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Never Give Up, Vassar Graduates Told</title>
    <meta content="22COMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COMMENCEMENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vassar College</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St John's University (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laybourne, Geraldine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carew, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3DE1E3AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Never Give Up, Vassar Graduates Told</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>POUGHKEEPSIE, N.Y., May 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vassar College holds commencement; Geraldine Laybourne, former student who helped turn Vassar into co-educational school, speaks; St John's University holds commencement, where the motivational speaker Jack Carew speaks; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It would have been difficult to find a more fitting speaker for Vassar College's Class of 2000 commencement than Geraldine Laybourne, a former student who helped turn Vassar into a co-educational school and is among the most powerful women in television. She said so herself.</p>
        <p>''You couldn't have someone better than me'' to give the speech, she told thousands of graduates, family members and friends yesterday at the college's Sunset Lake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It would have been difficult to find a more fitting speaker for Vassar College's Class of 2000 commencement than Geraldine Laybourne, a former student who helped turn Vassar into a co-educational school and is among the most powerful women in television. She said so herself.</p>
        <p>''You couldn't have someone better than me'' to give the speech, she told thousands of graduates, family members and friends yesterday at the college's Sunset Lake.</p>
        <p>As a Vassar student in 1969, Ms. Laybourne was a student member of a group that was asked to find ways to ease the school's transition into a modern, co-educational college. Impossible to do, she was told over and over, sounding a theme that resonated throughout her speech. But Ms. Laybourne beamed as she showed that the naysayers had been wrong, and congratulated the 528 graduates, 40 percent of whom were men.</p>
        <p>Among them was Scott Rose, a 34-year-old father of three who, during the 1980's, was homeless. He graduated with a psychology degree.</p>
        <p>The class president, Shequila Jacobs, a political science major from Baltimore, paid homage to her mother as she stood on the podium wearing a kente cloth head wrap instead of a mortarboard.</p>
        <p>These students' determination seemed to match Ms. Laybourne's message. An art history major who began life after college as a teacher, Ms. Laybourne was the president of the Disney/ABC Cable Networks before she joined the Nickelodeon children's network in 1984. In 1996, Time magazine named her one of the 25 most influential people in America. In 1998, she founded Oxygen Media Inc., an Internet company aimed at women and children.</p>
        <p>Ms. Laybourne said she had learned three essential principles on her road to success. The first: good ideas make up for lack of experience.</p>
        <p>''Do you know who has the best ideas? Twenty-year-olds,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The second: Passion for one's work makes up for a lot of late nights. And the third: Never take no for an answer.</p>
        <p>Vassar's existence is emblematic of the last principle, she said. The college's founder, Matthew Vassar, was a 19th century Poughkeepsie brewer who had only a grammar school education but insisted that women should have the same opportunities for higher education as men.</p>
        <p>Imagine, she said, how many people called his idea not merely ridiculous, but impossible.</p>
        <p>St. John's University</p>
        <p>The 130th annual commencement at St. John's University began on a sobering note yesterday with a moment of silence to honor Malik Sealy,  the former St. John's basketball player who was killed Saturday in a car accident.</p>
        <p>But the mood on the Queens campus shifted as hundreds of red-gowned graduates in Alumni Hall applauded the guest speaker, Jack Carew, a motivational lecturer.</p>
        <p>''The noble road to greatness and success is, clearly, being a positive force in the lives of others,'' said Mr. Carew, an animated, round-faced man who pumped his fists in the air when he spoke. ''It is becoming mentors, because mentoring is all about the human spirit -- yours and the people that come into your life.''</p>
        <p>The university conferred 1,138 undergraduate degrees during morning and afternoon ceremonies.</p>
        <p>At the first ceremony, Mr. Carew entertained the crowd, identifying the graduates as leaders, intellectuals, innovators and masters of throwing parties and celebrations. Christine Budhwa, 21, who received her Bachelor of Arts in English, said she was moved by Mr. Carew's advice. ''I needed guidance while I was in college, and it seems very few people were willing to give,'' she said. ''Now, I'm going to help my friend make it through law school.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Budhwa also took the memorial to Mr. Sealy as a lesson. ''It put things in perspective. It reminds us we should take advantage of our brief time here.''</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
