<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Fast Start by Mr. Lazio</title>
    <meta content="22MON2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0DE1E3AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Fast Start by Mr. Lazio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says entry of Repr Rick Lazio into New York Senate race following withdrawal of Mayor Rudolph Giuliani seems likely to reignite voter interest in contest that will be one of most watched in country; says new dynamics will test Lazio's ability to adjust to broader arena and test Hillary Rodham Clinton's resilience and flexibility (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a quick announcement of his candidacy, rapid-fire attacks on Hillary Rodham Clinton and a sprint across New York State yesterday, Representative Rick Lazio has gotten off to an energetic start in his race for the Senate. All but anointed for the Republican nomination, he has not left any time for Republican leaders to wring their hands over Mayor Rudolph Giuliani's withdrawal. Five months before the election, the little-known Long Island Congressman must be rated the underdog. But Mrs. Clinton faces a challenge in having to adjust to his intensity, and to his strong drive toward establishing his stature as a credible candidate.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton should also expect an effort to revive the issue of her not being from New York. By campaigning hard upstate while Mr. Giuliani stayed home, she has overcome some skepticism but may find that voters outside New York City will see Mr. Lazio as a more comfortable figure than the mayor. Common sense suggests the G.O.P. will find the money to help Mr. Lazio close the gap in the polls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a quick announcement of his candidacy, rapid-fire attacks on Hillary Rodham Clinton and a sprint across New York State yesterday, Representative Rick Lazio has gotten off to an energetic start in his race for the Senate. All but anointed for the Republican nomination, he has not left any time for Republican leaders to wring their hands over Mayor Rudolph Giuliani's withdrawal. Five months before the election, the little-known Long Island Congressman must be rated the underdog. But Mrs. Clinton faces a challenge in having to adjust to his intensity, and to his strong drive toward establishing his stature as a credible candidate.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton should also expect an effort to revive the issue of her not being from New York. By campaigning hard upstate while Mr. Giuliani stayed home, she has overcome some skepticism but may find that voters outside New York City will see Mr. Lazio as a more comfortable figure than the mayor. Common sense suggests the G.O.P. will find the money to help Mr. Lazio close the gap in the polls.</p>
        <p>For all the freshness of the race, there was a certain familiarity to its themes and politics. Mr. Lazio describes himself as a centrist, but in 1995 he voted fairly regularly with Speaker Newt Gingrich in the budget battles against President Clinton. Mrs. Clinton is certain to accelerate her attacks on his record of deep cuts in education, Medicaid, Medicare and environmental programs. On the talk-show circuit yesterday, Mr. Lazio tried to dismiss these actions as not relevant, but his record will surely be thrown back at him.</p>
        <p>In speaking yesterday of repairing New York's roads and empowering its average citizens, Mr. Lazio was casting himself in the Republican populist mold of his fellow Long Islander, former Senator Alfonse D'Amato. But he could draw fire because of his prodigious record of fund-raising among those interests that have business before him on the Commerce and Banking Committees.</p>
        <p>The other familiar feature to the race is its reliance on the traditional building blocks for electoral success in New York. Against Mr. Giuliani, who was likely to get at least a third of the vote in traditionally Democratic New York City, Mrs. Clinton was under tremendous pressure to build up support in traditional Republican areas of the suburbs and upstate. She can now probably count on winning the city at least three to one and may not have to do as well outside it. Upstate Mrs. Clinton has presented herself as a kind of Daughter of the Great Lakes and has made great inroads, according to opinion polls. Ironically, Mr. Giuliani has always had his greatest popularity in the New York suburbs, where Mr. Lazio should also do his best.</p>
        <p>Although New York and the nation relished a Giuliani-Clinton showdown, the focus on the mayor's health and personal life had, in a curious way, diverted attention from the electoral competition. Mr. Lazio's weekend blitz seemed likely to reignite voter interest in a race that will still be one of the most watched in the country. Its new dynamics will test Mr. Lazio's ability to adjust to a broader arena and test Mrs. Clinton's resilience and flexibility. New Yorkers are fortunate to still have a lively contest of issues, ideas and personalities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
