<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Law firms rushed to raise salaries to stem an exodus to start-ups. Now, the bill is coming due.</title>
    <meta content="22NECO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201522"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW ECONOMY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Startup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/New Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DB113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1142" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Law firms rushed to raise salaries to stem an exodus to start-ups. Now, the bill is coming due.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Leonhardt</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Economy column says dot-com talent hunt for young lawyers made millionaires, at least on paper, of many lawyers who left behind law firm life for Internet; says this sparked chain reaction in law firms around nation, with starting salaries soaring to attract best talent; says now that many dot-coms are running out of cash, turnover at many California law firms is returning to normal levels; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONSIDER this logic problem: Event A causes Event B. B then causes C, and C causes D. Now assume A had never happened. Would D have ever occurred?</p>
        <p>This is the multimillion-dollar hypothetical question that the nation's top corporate lawyers find themselves uncomfortably pondering after a wild five months that have altered the American legal industry. If the answer to the question is no -- and there is some strong evidence to support that conclusion -- then the country's most prestigious law firms appear to have given themselves an unnecessary and expensive headache.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONSIDER this logic problem: Event A causes Event B. B then causes C, and C causes D. Now assume A had never happened. Would D have ever occurred?</p>
        <p>This is the multimillion-dollar hypothetical question that the nation's top corporate lawyers find themselves uncomfortably pondering after a wild five months that have altered the American legal industry. If the answer to the question is no -- and there is some strong evidence to support that conclusion -- then the country's most prestigious law firms appear to have given themselves an unnecessary and expensive headache.</p>
        <p>In their pain are lessons about the problems that overvalued equity prices can cause even for businesses that seem to have little relation to the stocks in question.</p>
        <p>The legal world's chain reaction had its beginnings last year in Silicon Valley. With fast-growing Internet companies desperate for employees, the Bay Area's law firms became prime hunting grounds. Dozens of young, well-educated associates were more than happy to accept the offers, leaving behind legal work that can resemble drudgery to receive stock options that could be worth millions. Turnover at the law firms soon hit new highs.</p>
        <p>The young lawyers' bosses began responding just before the new year. Gunderson Dettmer Stough Villeneuve Franklin &amp; Hachigian, a small firm in Menlo Park, Calif., led the way, increasing associates' salary as much as 40 percent. Larger Bay Area firms quickly matched and, to avoid morale problems, extended the raises to lawyers in offices around the country.</p>
        <p>That was the key moment, the one that turned a local problem -- the dot-com talent war -- into a national phenomenon. The biggest New York firms, which had always paid the highest salaries in the nation, then had little choice but to match the increases or risk losing their best lawyers to the East Coast branches of their California rivals. By the spring, first-year associates at top firms across the country were earning $125,000 a year, not including annual bonuses that often exceed $15,000.</p>
        <p>All the while, however, something ironic was happening. At the very companies stealing the lawyers, stock prices stopped rising. Between Jan. 1 and April 1, the Morgan Stanley Internet index fell 5 percent. In April, as everybody now knows, the real drop came. The index lost an additional 30 percent of its value in the first two weeks.</p>
        <p>Dozens of dot-com companies, running through their cash and no longer confident of being able to turn to the capital markets for another infusion, began to conduct business differently. Private companies had to delay their initial public offerings, making them less able to offer rich salary packages. Suddenly, the value of millions of stock options was in question.</p>
        <p>It was a rapid change from the two previous years, when many of the lawyers who left behind law firm life for the Internet quickly became millionaires, at least on paper. ''It appeared to people for a while that if you reached for the brass ring, you grasped it,'' said Frederick Muto, a partner who oversees the San Diego office of Cooley Godward, one of the firms with headquarters in Silicon Valley. ''That perception has changed already.''</p>
        <p>The result is predictable: turnover at many California law firms has returned to normal levels. The big raises have surely played some role in the decrease, but both partners and associates say the biggest factor has been the technology slump. After all, notes William F. Lee, the managing partner of Hale &amp; Dorr in Boston, ''we could never pay people enough'' to match the upside of stock options.</p>
        <p>Consider what happened in the San Francisco office of Brobeck Phleger &amp; Harrison, another big California firm. On April 14 -- the same day the Nasdaq hit its low for the year -- the lawyers there held a going-away party for a senior associate who was quitting to join an Internet company. On Saturday, a venture-capital firm backed out of a large investment it had been planning to make in the company. On Sunday, the lawyer called a partner to ask if she could have her job back. On Monday, she was sitting in her office again ''as if nothing had ever happened,'' said Tower C. Snow Jr., the firm's chairman.</p>
        <p>Over all, Brobeck's turnover rate for associates is running at an annual pace of about 16 percent this year. Because many fewer lawyers have left the last two months than in January and February, Mr. Snow said he expected the final number to be close to 11 percent, the same as in 1998. Last year, by contrast, nearly one-fourth of all Brobeck associates quit the firm.</p>
        <p>So the match that started the brush fire that grew into a forest fire has now been extinguished. The lawyers who run the large firms are reluctant to say they regret giving the raises -- which would be tantamount to saying their own employees are overvalued -- but many partners agree that had the market downturn come sooner, salaries might not be at their current level.</p>
        <p>''There's no question the environment would have been different,'' said Alan S. Jaffe, the chairman of Proskauer Rose in New York.</p>
        <p>Mr. Snow added: ''A lot of the firms were very, very unhappy to make the adjustments. I'm sure they're even more unhappy now.''</p>
        <p>One could argue that the firms overreacted in the first place and that the decline of many technology stocks in early 2000 should have suggested that the associate exodus would soon slow. On the other hand, any individual firm that did not give raises risked losing lawyers immediately, as would probably happen if the firms now tried to scale back salaries to their earlier levels.</p>
        <p>For the most profitable firms, the raises may do little other than cut the partners' annual pay by a hundred thousand dollars or so. But some firms are already considering steps that include raising their billing rates, cutting back on hiring, using lawyer-for-hire agencies more often and even withdrawing from some areas of the law. The drying up of the market for initial public offerings and the Federal Reserve's recent interest-rate increases could make cost-cutting more urgent if the lawyers' revenue begins to slow, too.</p>
        <p>In other words, the nation's biggest law firms are learning a tough lesson about a downside of the new economy. For everybody else, the moral of the story may be more familiar: be wary of accepting investment advice from your lawyer.</p>
        <p>NEW ECONOMY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
