<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spencer's Hamstring Is the Latest Injury</title>
    <meta content="22PINS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0D7113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spencer's Hamstring Is the Latest Injury</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, May 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Injuries beset New York Yankees (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There have only been six games in 40 this year when the Yankees have been able to field the lineup they projected at the end of spring training. Scott Brosius fell in a heap on the second day of the regular season, having strained a rib cage in batting practice, and when he came back Chuck Knoblauch got hurt, and then Derek Jeter was injured.</p>
        <p>Now Shane Spencer is hobbled by a strained left hamstring and Knoblauch is nursing a sore left wrist, an injury that forced him out of today's game in the eighth inning. Knoblauch bruised the wrist while tagging out Kenny Lofton on an attempted steal in the first inning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There have only been six games in 40 this year when the Yankees have been able to field the lineup they projected at the end of spring training. Scott Brosius fell in a heap on the second day of the regular season, having strained a rib cage in batting practice, and when he came back Chuck Knoblauch got hurt, and then Derek Jeter was injured.</p>
        <p>Now Shane Spencer is hobbled by a strained left hamstring and Knoblauch is nursing a sore left wrist, an injury that forced him out of today's game in the eighth inning. Knoblauch bruised the wrist while tagging out Kenny Lofton on an attempted steal in the first inning.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch will get treatment on his injury Monday but expects to be back in the lineup Tuesday, when the Yankees open a three-game series against the White Sox in Chicago. ''I'm not big on missing time,'' Knoblauch said. ''I've missed enough time already.''</p>
        <p>Spencer felt his hamstring tighten while rounding first base in the third inning of Saturday's game, and he removed himself from the game after playing in the field in the bottom of the third. Spencer will also receive treatment for the next two days -- the Yankees have a day off Monday -- and Manager Joe Torre said the team would know Tuesday whether Spencer would be restricted to a pinch-hitting role or could resume playing the outfield.</p>
        <p>There is always the possibility he could be placed on the disabled list. ''I don't think so,'' Spencer said. ''I was sore today, but my flexibility was much better than yesterday.''</p>
        <p>Jeter, on the 15-day disabled list with a strained abdomen, will swing a bat Tuesday as part of his rehabilitation, Torre said. Jeter is eligible to be activated on Saturday, but it is too soon to know if that will be possible.</p>
        <p>Allen Watson, on injury rehabilitation with Class AAA Columbus, pitched one and two-thirds hitless innings today for the Clippers and is expected to be activated on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Knoblauch's Jitters</p>
        <p>Chuck Knoblauch had another hit today and has propelled himself out of his offensive slump, waiting a little longer and driving the ball to the right side of the field; he has 11 hits in his last 28 at-bats, with three walks.</p>
        <p>But Knoblauch's throwing jitters from second base, which were mostly dormant through spring training and the first month of the season, have resurfaced in the last 10 days. Only two of Knoblauch's five errors have come on throws, but increasingly he is releasing the ball tentatively and coming up short on tosses to first base, where Tino Martinez has taken some throws on the bounce.</p>
        <p>Alfonso Soriano, the Yankees' shortstop in the absence of Derek Jeter, made his second error in three games. He has struggled badly fielding grounders hit to his right, trying to glove the ball with both hands in front of him rather than going to his backhand to make the play.</p>
        <p>Clemens vs. Martinez</p>
        <p>The Boston Red Sox will go to Yankee Stadium on Friday for a three-game series that should include a compelling pitching duel in the third and final game, unless the teams juggle their rotations: the Yankees' Roger Clemens against Boston's Pedro Martinez. Clemens and Martinez faced off in the playoffs last year, and beset by a bad lower back, Clemens was hammered for five runs in two innings of a 13-1 loss -- the Yankees' only defeat in last year's postseason.</p>
        <p>Ramiro Mendoza will pitch against Chicago on Thursday for the Yankees, in part to give David Cone at least one extra day of rest before he pitches against the Red Sox next weekend. Cone will pitch on Friday, in the series opener against Boston, and Orlando Hernandez will throw on Saturday.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
