<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Changed Photography And Transformed Society</title>
    <meta content="22GENZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genzlinger, Neil</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Experience, the (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wizard of Photography, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDB113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="731" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Changed Photography And Transformed Society</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neil Genzlinger reviews program The Wizard of Photography, on PBS series The American Experience; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's possible that people were sticking their fingers in their ears and going ''naaah'' before 1888. But it's also possible that this and every other gesture humans muster whenever a camera is aimed at them can be traced to George Eastman, the man who in that year transformed photography from an elitist art into an everyman pastime.</p>
        <p>Eastman, whose story is told in ''The Wizard of Photography,'' tonight's installment of ''The American Experience'' on PBS, did not invent photography. He did, however, put it within reach of plain folks when he introduced a simple camera called the Kodak, thereby dooming thousands of shoe boxes to be filled with millions of blurry, off-kilter or otherwise amateurish snapshots. One of the things this interesting program does is remind us that the word ''snapshot'' is a borrowed hunting term that means ''to shoot without aiming.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's possible that people were sticking their fingers in their ears and going ''naaah'' before 1888. But it's also possible that this and every other gesture humans muster whenever a camera is aimed at them can be traced to George Eastman, the man who in that year transformed photography from an elitist art into an everyman pastime.</p>
        <p>Eastman, whose story is told in ''The Wizard of Photography,'' tonight's installment of ''The American Experience'' on PBS, did not invent photography. He did, however, put it within reach of plain folks when he introduced a simple camera called the Kodak, thereby dooming thousands of shoe boxes to be filled with millions of blurry, off-kilter or otherwise amateurish snapshots. One of the things this interesting program does is remind us that the word ''snapshot'' is a borrowed hunting term that means ''to shoot without aiming.''</p>
        <p>Before Eastman, photography was like portrait painting. Subjects would sit prim and still while a photographer wielding a bulky camera, glass plates and assorted chemicals caught the moment. The moment, though, had to last some seconds to allow for exposure, and the life captured by these early photographers was one without spontaneity.</p>
        <p>Eastman changed all that. Yet he might easily have spent his life as a bank clerk, which is what he was in 1877 when he decided to dabble in real estate. He wanted to photograph some land he was considering buying, purchased a camera to do it with, then found he had to pay someone to teach him how to use the camera. There followed the exclamation that fueled so much of the industrial age: ''There must be an easier way.''</p>
        <p>What is striking about Eastman is that he did not say this only once; he found an easier way, then kept searching for even easier ones. First he replaced the wet-plate process, in which photographers had to cart chemicals around, with a dry-plate system, so they could just take along Eastman's precoated glass. Then he replaced the glass plates with paper film, leading to the Kodak.</p>
        <p>The Kodak, though, was relatively expensive, so he changed the quest slightly, to ''there must be a cheaper way,'' and in 1900 gave the world the Brownie camera, a boxful of visual memories for only $1. The name was taken from a storybook character in a conscious effort to appeal to children, a nonlethal Joe Camel.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the going was rough; the program details various reversals and near bankruptcies. And, like so many giants of the age, Eastman had his oddities: an overly meticulous streak, control-freak tendencies. If ''Wizard of Photography'' has a shortcoming it is in not letting us hear more about and from the people who had to work for him. His odd end, by suicide in 1932, is given a retrained and dignified treatment.</p>
        <p>In any case, Eastman ultimately made a fortune, and he transformed Rochester, site of his company's headquarters. What ''The Wizard of Photography'' nicely conveys is how much he also transformed us, the way we think of and document our own lives. Today, when the debate in many households is whether to jettison the old-fashioned camera (i.e., the one that uses film) in favor of a digital one, it is hard to fathom that countless generations had no easy way of preserving a visual record of everyday life. Those shoe boxes go back only a century or so; before that the slate is, by comparison, an elusive blank.</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAN EXPERIENCE  The Wizard of Photography  PBS, tonight at 9  (Channel 13 in New York)</p>
        <p>Written, produced and directed by James A. DeVinney; Barbara Moran, co-producer; Eric Handley, editor; Judith Light, narrator. A Green Light Productions Inc. film for ''The American Experience.'' ''The American Experience'' is produced by WGBH, Boston. Margaret Drain, executive producer; Mark Samels, senior producer. David McCullough, series host.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
