<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Johnson Is No Match for Mets' McEwing</title>
    <meta content="22METS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DD1E3AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Johnson Is No Match for Mets' McEwing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Arizona Diamondbacks, 7-6; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joe McEwing is one foot shorter than Randy Johnson, the 6-foot-10-inch pitcher who Bobby Valentine said looks 8 feet tall while he is lurking menacingly on the mound. When you see Johnson at a baseball game, you figure he is a powerful athlete. When you see McEwing, you feel like asking for two with mustard. McEwing would probably fetch the hot dogs, too.</p>
        <p>But there was McEwing talking softly and ever so humbly about conquering Johnson and helping the Mets burst past the Arizona Diamondbacks, 7-6, to complete the three-game sweep at Shea Stadium yesterday. Derek Bell lined a single off Byung-Hyun Kim in the ninth inning that enabled McEwing to hustle in from second base with the winning run and complete his own extraordinary day in style.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joe McEwing is one foot shorter than Randy Johnson, the 6-foot-10-inch pitcher who Bobby Valentine said looks 8 feet tall while he is lurking menacingly on the mound. When you see Johnson at a baseball game, you figure he is a powerful athlete. When you see McEwing, you feel like asking for two with mustard. McEwing would probably fetch the hot dogs, too.</p>
        <p>But there was McEwing talking softly and ever so humbly about conquering Johnson and helping the Mets burst past the Arizona Diamondbacks, 7-6, to complete the three-game sweep at Shea Stadium yesterday. Derek Bell lined a single off Byung-Hyun Kim in the ninth inning that enabled McEwing to hustle in from second base with the winning run and complete his own extraordinary day in style.</p>
        <p>Until yesterday, Johnson had dominated the National League with his ferocious fastball and an intimidating disposition. Until 10 days ago, McEwing was playing, but hardly dominating, with Class AAA Norfolk in the International League. But on a raw, rainy day, McEwing, the 28-year-old who is called Super Joe by his teammates, aggravated the Diamondbacks with a home run, two doubles, a walk, a crucial stolen base and three runs scored.</p>
        <p>''I think it's the ultimate challenge for us to face a guy like him,'' McEwing said of Johnson. ''As professionals, that's what we strive for. We went out and battled all day. We came from behind four times and didn't give up.''</p>
        <p>Indeed. Valentine mused that at least one person surely speculated that the game was over when the Diamondbacks went ahead, 1-0, in the first inning. But the Mets opened up with three consecutive doubles off Johnson to erase the first of three deficits against him.</p>
        <p>Johnson gave up five earned runs on three homers and five doubles in six and two-thirds innings, as many earned runs as he had allowed in his previous six starts over 47 2/3 innings.</p>
        <p>The Mets struck out 13 times against Johnson, including one stretch in which he fanned 11 of 14 batters. But the Mets pelted Johnson by being aggressive, by trying to avoid two-strike counts in which he could unleash his slider and by viewing the reigning Cy Young award winner as a mortal pitcher.</p>
        <p>''It just showed that none of our guys played that game before it started,'' Valentine said. ''They came out and had a little determined look in their eyes.''</p>
        <p>Twenty minutes after the victory, McEwing still had his cap pulled tight over his brow while he did a radio interview. There were bloodstains on the right knee of his white uniform pants and dirt stains splashed across the backside. McEwing, who had his first major league hit off Johnson while with the St. Louis Cardinals last season and who is now 5 for 16 off the left-hander, looked like a kid who had been frolicking in a puddle. That is how he wants to look.</p>
        <p>McEwing is not Rickey Henderson, which is a good thing for the Mets. He started the first rally with a double, he finished a memorable 12-pitch at-bat that featured seven two-strike fouls with another double, he lined a homer to spark another rally and he began the winning rally with a walk on a 3-2 pitch. In five times at bat, McEwing, the leadoff hitter, squeezed 34 pitches out of Johnson and Kim.</p>
        <p>''For what he lacks in pure size and ability, he makes up with his gutsy play,'' Mike Piazza said. ''He's fun to watch.''</p>
        <p>After McEwing, Bell and Edgardo Alfonzo doubled on three straight pitches in the first inning to put the Mets ahead, 2-1, Arizona clipped Rick Reed for two runs in the third to make it, 3-2. But Piazza belted a majestic homer, estimated at 492 feet, into the left-field mezzanine section to even the score.</p>
        <p>Travis Lee's two-run homer off Reed in the sixth gave Arizona a 5-3 lead, the third time the Mets trailed Johnson. No problem, the Mets thought. McEwing lumbered to the plate an inning later, holding his bat high above his shoulders, and hammered a fastball over the left-field fence. Alfonzo went deep one batter later to tie the score, 5-5.</p>
        <p>Steve Finley homered off Dennis Cook in the eighth to push Arizona ahead, 6-5, but once again the Mets displayed resilience. Robin Ventura, who did not start for the second straight game because of a strained left thigh muscle, was healthy enough to smack a pinch-hit homer off Mike Morgan and tie the score.</p>
        <p>The back-and-forth game drifted to the ninth, and it was a nice omen for the Mets when McEwing led off the inning. McEwing walked against the submarine-throwing Kim (2-2) and quickly stole second. He scored the decisive run when a diving Lee missed snaring Bell's liner to right by a few inches.</p>
        <p>The Mets sprinted out of the dugout to mob Bell and McEwing, who, fittingly, was the last player to leave the field on a day that he, not Johnson, dominated.</p>
        <p>''I'm a very humble person, so I'm not going to brag about myself, but I'm also a confident person and I believe in my abilities,'' McEwing said. ''You just got to go out and battle. That's what I do every day. I play hard.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>ROBIN VENTURA expects to start tonight against the Padres in San Diego, but Manager BOBBY VALENTINE said the third baseman would most likely miss at least one more game so his strained left thigh was completely healed. Ventura joked that he had to return because he gained six pounds while munching through Saturday's rain delay and game. ''I had breakfast, two lunches and a pack of sunflowers seeds every inning,'' he said. ''I set a new team record.'' . . . MELVIN MORA, who had the stitches removed from his right finger, will begin a rehabilitation assignment in Class AAA Norfolk today. He is eligible to be activated on Sunday. . . . TURK WENDELL received the victory and improved to 3-2.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
