<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study Finds Drivers at Fault in Bike Crashes</title>
    <meta content="22BIKE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Right of Way (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EEDE1E3AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study Finds Drivers at Fault in Bike Crashes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Right of Way, a pro-cycling advocacy group, analyzes four years of official reports on accidents in which bicyclists died in collisions with motor vehicles in New York City, and it concludes that drivers were to blame in most of crashes; analysis was prompted by police statements in January that cyclist error is primary contributing factor in nearly three-quarters of fatal crashes in 1999 and 1998 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An analysis of four years of official reports on accidents in which bicyclists died in collisions with motor vehicles in New York City has found that drivers were to blame in most of the crashes.</p>
        <p>The study, released yesterday by the pro-cycling advocacy group Right of Way, was prompted by police statements in January, in the aftermath of a 70 percent increase in cycling deaths in 1999, that cyclist error was the ''primary contributing factor'' in nearly three-quarters of fatal crashes in 1999 and in 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An analysis of four years of official reports on accidents in which bicyclists died in collisions with motor vehicles in New York City has found that drivers were to blame in most of the crashes.</p>
        <p>The study, released yesterday by the pro-cycling advocacy group Right of Way, was prompted by police statements in January, in the aftermath of a 70 percent increase in cycling deaths in 1999, that cyclist error was the ''primary contributing factor'' in nearly three-quarters of fatal crashes in 1999 and in 1998.</p>
        <p>Right of Way examined 71 fatal accidents from 1995 to 1998, the most recent years for which police and Department of Motor Vehicles reports were available. It found that in 30 of the 53 cases, or 57 percent, in which the group was able to fix blame, the driver was the primary culprit. Cyclists were the main cause of 12 accidents, or 23 percent, while blame was split in the other 11.</p>
        <p>For 1998, the only year in which Right of Way's analyzed data on which the police publicly commented, the group found that drivers were entirely at fault in 7 of the 17 accidents for which blame could be fixed and largely culpable in 6 others, leaving cyclists to blame for only 4 collisions, or 23 percent.</p>
        <p>Police officials who were shown the study would not comment.</p>
        <p>''We're going to stand on our analysis,'' said Detective Walter Burnes, a department spokesman. ''We're not going to get into trying to interpret someone else's data.'' Police officials said in January that they did not know why deaths increased last year -- to 34, from 20 the year before -- and that they planned to perform a five-year analysis of cycling deaths. Detective Burnes said the study was not done yet.</p>
        <p>After the increase in deaths was reported in January, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani threatened a crackdown on reckless driving, but Charles Komanoff, a transportation consultant and one of the study's authors, said that police efforts had focused on highways, where cyclists seldom venture.</p>
        <p>''Victim-blaming becomes a rationale for doing nothing to protect cyclists from drivers,'' Mr. Komanoff said.</p>
        <p>Detective Burnes said, however, that recent police initiatives have included a crackdown on speeders on some local streets, though he would not offer specifics. As of May 15, he said, two cyclists were killed this year, compared with six at the same time last year.</p>
        <p>''Do we really need to figure out where the blame goes?'' he asked. ''I think what's more important is that we saw an increase, and we've taken some actions and increased our education efforts, and now we're seeing a decrease.''</p>
        <p>Today, the City Council's transportation committee will hold a hearing to look into the reasons for last year's increase in cycling deaths. The councilman conducting the hearing, Adolfo Carrion Jr., Democrat of the Bronx, also plans to introduce a resolution urging the police to do more to protect cyclists and pedestrians.</p>
        <p>For its study, Right of Way, which did a similar analysis last year of nearly 1,000 pedestrian deaths, tried to reconstruct all the factors leading to each crash. The most frequent driver errors, the group found, were unsafe or aggressive passing, (12 cases), turning in front of the cyclist,  (8 cases), speeding (7.5 cases) and running a red light (5.5 cases). The leading cyclist errors were traveling the wrong way (5 cases) and running a light or stop sign (4 cases).</p>
        <p>Although the study was provocatively entitled ''The Only Good Cyclist...'' the researchers said they tried to be conservative. They said they did not automatically blame the driver in the 19 cases in which the driver was drunk or unlicensed or fled the scene, but instead relied on the details of the crash itself.</p>
        <p>In cases where both parties seemed at fault, though, Right of Way tended to blame the driver, noting that according to New York State motor vehicle law, ''notwithstanding the provisions of any other law to the contrary, every driver of a vehicle shall exercise due care to avoid colliding with any bicyclist, pedestrian or domestic animal.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
