<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Referendum on 2-Party Plan in Italy Fizzles</title>
    <meta content="22ITAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Voter Behavior</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Italy</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stanley, Alessandra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E7DF1E3AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Referendum on 2-Party Plan in Italy Fizzles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALESSANDRA STANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stanley, Alessandra</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, May 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ambitious referendum aimed at reducing instability in Italy's electoral system is invalidated after too few Italians turn out for vote; approximately 32.1 percent of voters cast ballots, far less than 50.1 percent quorum needed; most contentious of the seven questions before voters would have moved Italy to closer to two-party sytem by ridding it of parliamentary seats that are allotted proportionally (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An ambitious referendum aimed at reducing the instability in Italy's electoral system was invalidated tonight because too few Italians turned out for the vote to be accepted.</p>
        <p>Only about 32 percent of voters cast ballots today, far less than the 50.1 percent quorum needed. The referendum was supposed to make Italians decide seven questions, covering a broad range of political, economic and social issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An ambitious referendum aimed at reducing the instability in Italy's electoral system was invalidated tonight because too few Italians turned out for the vote to be accepted.</p>
        <p>Only about 32 percent of voters cast ballots today, far less than the 50.1 percent quorum needed. The referendum was supposed to make Italians decide seven questions, covering a broad range of political, economic and social issues.</p>
        <p>But the most contested item was an effort to move Italy closer to a two-party system by ridding it of the the parliamentary seats that are alloted proportionally. That measure, fiercely opposed by small parties who feared that they would be wiped out in the new system, was also opposed by Silvio Berlusconi, leader of the center-right party Forza Italia. An exit poll by the Abacus agency showed that 82 percent of the people who bothered to vote wanted to get rid of the old system.</p>
        <p>The low turnout was a blow to the embattled government of Giuliano Amato, which had hoped that a favorable vote would give it strong public backing for electoral reforms that previous center-left governments had not been able to pass in the badly divided Italian Parliament. A similar referendum on changing the electoral system narrowly failed to reach a quorum last year.</p>
        <p>This year the government passed a decree to purge electoral lists of deceased voters and some nonresidents, hoping that the decree would make it easier to reach a quorum. Even Sophia Loren, who does not reside in Italy, was removed from the lists of her native town of Potzzuoli, near Naples. After the voter rolls were cleaned up, just over 49 million Italians were registered.</p>
        <p>But the failure to win voter approval for a change in the electoral system means that it is likely that Italy's political instability will continue. The current center-left coalition is Italy's 58th government since World War II.</p>
        <p>The low turnout was a short-term political victory for Mr. Berlusconi, who leads the center-right opposition and is already campaigning to become prime minister in the next election. But the current system, which often forces the ruling majority to make ill-matched alliances with small parties that can easily balk and bring down a government, has inherent problems for any candidate. Mr. Berlusconi was prime minister in 1994 for less than a year, but lost office when a coalition partner defected and forced his center-right government to collapse.</p>
        <p>The low turnout did not necessarily mean that most Italians favor their current electoral system or disagreed with the referendum's other questions, like whether to loosen laws protecting employees from dismissal, or whether prosecutors can also serve as trial judges.</p>
        <p>The low attendance mainly reflected most Italians' disgust with politics as usual and widespread referendum fatigue. Voters have been summoned to vote in referendums seven times since 1990. The measure, once reserved for weighty social matters like abolishing the monarchy in 1946, or legalizing divorce in 1974, became a kind of political crutch for settling issues that Parliament was unable to resolve. (In 1990, a referendum on hunting regulations and the use of pesticides also failed to reach a quorum.)</p>
        <p>''People who are coming to vote are very confused, the issues are so diverse and complicated,'' said Laura Bianchi, 43, after she voted in  Rome. She said that with Italy's chronic revolving governments, '' ''the legislatures are so short that they can't pass any laws.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
