<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Communication Gear Maker to Seal Alliance</title>
    <meta content="22ALT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alteon Websystems</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lucent Technologies</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Akamai Technologies Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cisco Systems Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arrowpoint Communications</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E7D9113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Communication Gear Maker to Seal Alliance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alteon Websystems enlists two powerful allies, Lucent Technologies and Akamai Technologies, in reaction to Cisco Systems' acquisition of Arrowpoint Communications; is expected to announce that Lucent, Cisco's biggest enemy, has agreed to sell Alteon's gear under Lucent brand (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Cisco Systems agreed earlier this month to acquire Arrowpoint Communications, a maker of switches for Internet communications, for about $6 billion, some analysts interpreted the deal as a blow to Arrowpoint's main competitor, Alteon Websystems.</p>
        <p>But in the world of communications equipment, in which the torrid pace of growth is matched only by the ferocity of competition among giants like Cisco and Nortel Networks of Canada, small companies with attractive technology can almost always find friends. Reacting to Cisco's acquisition of Arrowpoint, Alteon intends to announce this week that it has enlisted two powerful allies: Lucent Technologies and Akamai Technologies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Cisco Systems agreed earlier this month to acquire Arrowpoint Communications, a maker of switches for Internet communications, for about $6 billion, some analysts interpreted the deal as a blow to Arrowpoint's main competitor, Alteon Websystems.</p>
        <p>But in the world of communications equipment, in which the torrid pace of growth is matched only by the ferocity of competition among giants like Cisco and Nortel Networks of Canada, small companies with attractive technology can almost always find friends. Reacting to Cisco's acquisition of Arrowpoint, Alteon intends to announce this week that it has enlisted two powerful allies: Lucent Technologies and Akamai Technologies.</p>
        <p>As Dominic P. Orr, Alteon's chief executive, put it last Friday: ''Up to 10 days ago, when Cisco acquired Arrowpoint, we were pretty neutral and worked with any backbone builder. Now Cisco has gone directly into our area. So now all enemies of Cisco are friends of ours.''</p>
        <p>There is certainly no bigger enemy of Cisco than Lucent, the former equipment arm of AT&amp;T that has stumbled recently, even as Cisco, the No. 1 maker of Internet communications gear, has become one of the world's most valuable companies.</p>
        <p>Lucent, which has roots in the manufacture of telephone switches, has spent billions trying to break into the data communications arena. This week, Alteon intends to announce that Lucent has agreed to sell Alteon's gear under the Lucent brand.</p>
        <p>Alteon and Arrowpoint each make equipment that sits between communications networks and the big computer servers that support Web sites  and other Internet systems. The gear made by the two companies helps distribute requests for Internet information among the various servers within a facility, and helps the owners of those servers use the computers more efficiently.</p>
        <p>Alteon, based in San Jose, Calif., hopes to benefit from Lucent's extensive sales force pushing more of its systems into the market. And Lucent, by putting its brand on Alteon's products, adds another arrow to its own quiver.</p>
        <p>Such deals can be mutually beneficial. But some other small communications equipment companies have come to believe that such arrangements favor the bigger player by allowing the giant access to the start-up's technology, while discouraging the smaller company from developing its own sales force.</p>
        <p>Besides the Lucent deal, Alteon also intends to announce this week that it has struck a partnership with Akamai under which Akamai will sometimes encourage its customers to purchase Alteon equipment. Akamai, based in Cambridge, Mass., helps Web sites distribute information to users more quickly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
