<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paramount could be going against the cultural grain by putting Laura Schlessinger on TV.</title>
    <meta content="22MEDI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Paramount Television</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schlessinger, Laura (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2DA113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paramount could be going against the cultural grain by putting Laura Schlessinger on TV.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Media column examines Paramount Television's decision to introduce syndicated talk show featuring Dr Laura Schlessinger, who has called homosexuality deviant behavior, at time when many other stations are broadcasting sit-coms and dramas with homosexual characters in sympathetic roles; notes Procter &amp; Gamble has already withdrawn its advertising from Schlessinger program; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A HUMOROUS television commercial for the Kia Spectra automobile, which began running this month, ends with a truck driver asking his male passenger, ''So you're a Pisces, too, huh?''</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, viewers of ''Dawson's Creek'' on the WB network will see what is being billed as the first romantic kiss between two male characters in a prime-time TV entertainment series.</p>
        <p>Come the fall, the linchpin of the NBC Must See TV Thursday prime-time lineup will be ''Will and Grace,'' a sitcom centered on a buttoned-down gay man and his life with a straight woman and a flamboyant gay pal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A HUMOROUS television commercial for the Kia Spectra automobile, which began running this month, ends with a truck driver asking his male passenger, ''So you're a Pisces, too, huh?''</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, viewers of ''Dawson's Creek'' on the WB network will see what is being billed as the first romantic kiss between two male characters in a prime-time TV entertainment series.</p>
        <p>Come the fall, the linchpin of the NBC Must See TV Thursday prime-time lineup will be ''Will and Grace,'' a sitcom centered on a buttoned-down gay man and his life with a straight woman and a flamboyant gay pal.</p>
        <p>And Fox Broadcasting has high hopes for a sitcom for the 2000-2001 season called ''Don't Ask,'' featuring John Goodman as a divorced father who is gay.</p>
        <p>Against that backdrop, Paramount Television is introducing a syndicated talk show featuring Dr. Laura Schlessinger, the conservative advice maven whose radio audience has listened to her stern declarations that homosexuality is a deviation from the biological norm and incompatible with Scripture.</p>
        <p>With timing being a crucial factor in the success of television programming, a question arises: how confident are Paramount executives about their abilities to swim against the tide?</p>
        <p>Publicly, Paramount remains fully committed to the Dr. Schlessinger TV program, saying it has no intention to contribute to ''an environment of hurt, hate or intolerance.'' In a statement last week, the company described commercial sales as ''strong.''</p>
        <p>However, times have changed and the statement may not be enough to soothe the offended sensibilities of an increasingly diverse audience. ''Offending gay people is not acceptable the way it may have been even five years ago,'' said Paul Poux, principal at the Poux Company in New York, an agency specializing in marketing to gay consumers.</p>
        <p>''Advertisers are becoming more aware of all their customers,'' he added, ''so maybe standards for talking about gay people are being brought into line with those for other groups.''</p>
        <p>One advertiser making its position clear is Procter &amp; Gamble, which sells packaged goods mainstays like Tide, Bounty and Charmin. It canceled plans to advertise on the TV program, citing  the controversy generated by increasingly angry protests against Paramount and Dr. Schlessinger by gay advocacy groups.</p>
        <p>Other advertisers like More.com, Toysrus.com and Xerox have either withdrawn from her radio program, announced they would not sponsor her TV program or both.</p>
        <p>The decision by Procter &amp; Gamble, the nation's second-largest advertiser, is a hurdle for the TV program to overcome because many advertisers ''would not go below the standards'' of a marketing giant like P.&amp; G., said Gene DeWitt, chairman and chief executive at Optimedia International U.S. in New York. His media services agency, formerly DeWitt Media, is owned by Publicis.</p>
        <p>To be sure, a hit syndicated talk show can generate enormous profits. It is estimated that ''The Oprah Winfrey Show'' earns $300 million annually for King World Productions. And according to The Hollywood Reporter, ''The Jerry Springer Show'' was being shopped around last year for $100 million.</p>
        <p>And it seems sensible to seek a TV talk show host from the ranks of popular radio talk show hosts. Dr. Schlessinger's radio ratings -- second highest among all national talk programs -- suggests she has loyal followers across the country. Indeed, in its statement last week, Paramount Television said it would ''expect that the fans of Dr. Laura will express their disappointment'' with P.&amp; G. for withdrawing its advertising ''without ever having seen the show or judging it on its own merits.''</p>
        <p>Even so, radio stars like Rush Limbaugh and Howard Stern, with legions of loyal fans, have found television tougher than their regular gigs. Dr. Schlessinger, in a recent appearance on ''Larry King Live'' on CNN, seemed strident and untelegenic.</p>
        <p>Asked whether Paramount executives would suspend production of the show at this point, Mr. DeWitt replied, ''Not if they can still make money.''</p>
        <p>''Morality may have moved as far West as Cincinnati,'' he added, referring to the headquarters of Procter &amp; Gamble, ''but it hasn't made it to the Coast yet.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
