<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Homing In on 'Intelligent' Web Design</title>
    <meta content="22SPOO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000523T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COMPRESSED DATA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Names, Organizational</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logotypes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Race, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Organizational</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E5DA113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Homing In on 'Intelligent' Web Design</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM RACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Race, Tim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Web-design firm in Chicago puts up parody Web site, eNoricom.com, that takes e-clients through process of selecting name, logo and motto for their new business; site pokes fun at recent dot-com conformity in naming and branding of new technology companies; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Agilent. Naviant. Novient. Scient. Teligent. Are the new economy's neologisms starting to blur?</p>
        <p>Yes, a certain dot-com conformity appears to be spreading in the naming and branding of technology companies. Four 26-year-old partners at a Web-design firm in Chicago have put up a parody Web site that takes you, the e-client, through the process of selecting a name, logo and motto for your new business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Agilent. Naviant. Novient. Scient. Teligent. Are the new economy's neologisms starting to blur?</p>
        <p>Yes, a certain dot-com conformity appears to be spreading in the naming and branding of technology companies. Four 26-year-old partners at a Web-design firm in Chicago have put up a parody Web site that takes you, the e-client, through the process of selecting a name, logo and motto for your new business.</p>
        <p>Nearly 50,000 different visitors have toured the site since it opened last month, the creators say.</p>
        <p>The site, eNoricom.com, presents 18 slides that depict the steps, beginning with the ''patented Nametron 3000'' machine to create a ''best-of-breed name that conveys the essence of your brand's soul.''</p>
        <p>After the Nametron spits out the name Similant, the word is run up the flagpole of a fictional focus group, a family of four. Dad finds that Similant evokes a ''very strong customer focus.'' For Daughter, the name is virtually synonymous with ''global.''</p>
        <p>Then, noting that ''nothing says innovation and cutting edge like having a curved swoosh in your logo,'' the site presents more than a dozen examples -- from Ameritech, to Gore 2000, to tickets.com -- before producing a suitably swerving nameplate for Similant, replete with an ''@'' instead of the ''a.''</p>
        <p>For focus-group Mom, the Similant logo signifies that ''anything is possible.'' For Son, it cries out ''empowered.''</p>
        <p>Finally, the site observes the popularity of three-word taglines, like ''Point. Click. Rent'' for apartmentguide.com and ''Beauty. Inspiration. Shopping'' for gloss.com.</p>
        <p>For Similant, the concocted tagline is ''Really. Really. Different.'' (Mom's impression: ''people focused.'' Daughter's: ''frictionless.'')</p>
        <p>Matt Linderman, a creator of the parody site, said the point (besides getting laughs) was to convey his own firm's philosophy that good Web design helps people communicate and interact.</p>
        <p>''It upsets us when we see these big companies acting Orwellian, making up words to make themselves sound important,'' Mr. Linderman said. ''Everyone sees logos like that all the time. But it's not until you see 30 of them together that you say, 'Wow, this is kind of ridiculous.' ''</p>
        <p>And what name did Mr. Lindeman's 10-month-old Web company select for itself? An arcane one: 37signals.</p>
        <p>The name, he explains, alludes to an experiment led by the astronomer Carl Sagan in the 1980's in which billions and billions of signals from outer space were analyzed by a radio telescope. Only 37 were identified as potential signs of intelligent life.</p>
        <p>''We liked this,'' Mr. Linderman said, ''because our goal is to create and propagate Web sites that show signs of intelligent life.''</p>
        <p>TIM RACE</p>
        <p>COMPRESSED DATA  Correction:  May 23, 2000, Tuesday  A report in the Compressed Data column of Business Day yesterday  about a parody Web site that takes visitors through the steps of naming an Internet company and choosing its logo misspelled the site's address. It is eNormicom.com, not eNoricom.com.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 23, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A report in the Compressed Data column of Business Day yesterday  about a parody Web site that takes visitors through the steps of naming an Internet company and choosing its logo misspelled the site's address. It is eNormicom.com, not eNoricom.com.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
