<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Muse Charmed by the Nature of Zero</title>
    <meta content="22HYPA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Soho Rep</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wellman, Mac</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McGrath, Bob</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hypatia (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E4DA113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Muse Charmed by the Nature of Zero</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews Mac Wellman play Hypatia directed by Bob McGrath, presented by SoHo Rep; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The title character of Mac Wellman's new theater piece at the SoHo Repertory Company, was a fifth-century mathematician in Alexandria who ran afoul of a Christian bishop -- apparently for being pagan, female and influential -- and was vengefully beaten to death in the street, her body mutilated by Christian monks. It is Mr. Wellman's conceit, in the 60 minutes of ruminative jabberwocky that make up ''Hypatia,'' that her spirit has revisited the world from time to time, inspiring select women in places from 8th-century Damascus to early-20th-century Alexandria, Va. Sexual, brilliant and questioning (she is inclined, like a spoiled 4-year-old, to repeating ''Why?''), Hypatia serves the play as a puzzling legend and elusive muse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wellman has never been a linear storyteller, and his interest in language has always had as much to do with exploiting the properties of its fundamental units -- letters, syllables, words -- as it has with using them to express meaning in its conventional sense. It's the kind of writing that, when it works, creates an enigmatic music of its own, the soundtrack for a theatrical tableau.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The title character of Mac Wellman's new theater piece at the SoHo Repertory Company, was a fifth-century mathematician in Alexandria who ran afoul of a Christian bishop -- apparently for being pagan, female and influential -- and was vengefully beaten to death in the street, her body mutilated by Christian monks. It is Mr. Wellman's conceit, in the 60 minutes of ruminative jabberwocky that make up ''Hypatia,'' that her spirit has revisited the world from time to time, inspiring select women in places from 8th-century Damascus to early-20th-century Alexandria, Va. Sexual, brilliant and questioning (she is inclined, like a spoiled 4-year-old, to repeating ''Why?''), Hypatia serves the play as a puzzling legend and elusive muse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wellman has never been a linear storyteller, and his interest in language has always had as much to do with exploiting the properties of its fundamental units -- letters, syllables, words -- as it has with using them to express meaning in its conventional sense. It's the kind of writing that, when it works, creates an enigmatic music of its own, the soundtrack for a theatrical tableau.</p>
        <p>In ''Hypatia,'' however, Mr. Wellman's base text, full of mathematical arcana and obscure historical references, is so distancing as to defy comprehension. And as directed by Bob McGrath, who has staged the play almost entirely behind a scrim on which grandiose projections appear throughout, the production itself seems designed to keep the audience at bay. The images -- from celestial views, mathematical equations and decorative mandalas to a baboon head and Hypatia herself, dead and bloodied in the street -- don't make a particularly beautiful display, but they do add another layer to the play's willful mask.</p>
        <p>Hypatia, played by Sophia Fox-Long with the self-involvement of someone hearing inner voices, is mostly at center stage, engaging with various folks as she passes ethereally through the ages. Meanwhile a variety of narrators, who are never identified but whose costuming and locutions place them anachronistically outside the basic time frame, are spotlighted and blacked out as they take turns speaking.</p>
        <p>One has the manner and dress of a television newswoman, another a businessman speaking in Brooklynese, a third a nightclub torch singer. A fourth emanates from an electronic device. Their echolalic repetitions as they puzzle over the legend of the main character are perhaps a suggestion that the mysteries that so appealed to Hypatia -- the nature of zero, for instance -- have remained symbolically in force through the ages. But perhaps not.</p>
        <p>One hesitates to dismiss what one has tried and failed to apprehend. But though there is obviously a theatrical code at work here -- the word cipher is bandied about like a shuttlecock -- its adamant opacity comes across as smug. You don't feel beguiled by its presumed complexity; you feel taunted by it.</p>
        <p>HYPATIA</p>
        <p>By Mac Wellman; directed by Bob McGrath; set by Molly Hughes; costumes by Laurie Olinder; lighting by Jane Cox; original music and sound design by J. Hagenbuckle; projection designer, Ms. Olinder; stage manager, Bridget Markov. Presented by SoHo Rep and Ridge Theater in association with Theodore C. Rodgers. At 46 Walker Street, SoHo.</p>
        <p>WITH: Aysan Celik (Musa), Sophia Fox-Long (Hypatia), Jonathan Hova (Narrator/Male Songs), Leopold Lowe (Orestes), Jeremy Proctor (Theon), Fred Tietz (Synesius) and Daniel Zippi (Cyril/Chorus).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
