<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exploring a Present That Is Invaded by the Past</title>
    <meta content="22EDER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eder, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sebald, W G</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Vertigo (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DA113AF931A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exploring a Present That Is Invaded by the Past</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD EDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eder, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Eder reviews book Vertigo by W G Sebald; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VERTIGO  By W. G. Sebald  Translated by Michael Hulse. 263 pages. New Directions. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Think of Proust as the Isaac Newton of memory. Instead of the possibly apocryphal apple triggering the Universal Law of Gravitation, a madeleine sets off a universal law of recollection.</p>
        <p>Think of W. G. Sebald as memory's Einstein, and his two great novels, ''The Emigrants'' (1996) and ''The Rings of Saturn'' (1998), as his Special Theory and General Theory, respectively. The first tells of half a dozen Jews who for one reason or another escaped the Holocaust; one because he lived before it. (Einsteinian time runs backwards as well as forward.) All collapse in nightmare or hallucination after lifetimes of prosperity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VERTIGO  By W. G. Sebald  Translated by Michael Hulse. 263 pages. New Directions. $23.95.</p>
        <p>Think of Proust as the Isaac Newton of memory. Instead of the possibly apocryphal apple triggering the Universal Law of Gravitation, a madeleine sets off a universal law of recollection.</p>
        <p>Think of W. G. Sebald as memory's Einstein, and his two great novels, ''The Emigrants'' (1996) and ''The Rings of Saturn'' (1998), as his Special Theory and General Theory, respectively. The first tells of half a dozen Jews who for one reason or another escaped the Holocaust; one because he lived before it. (Einsteinian time runs backwards as well as forward.) All collapse in nightmare or hallucination after lifetimes of prosperity.</p>
        <p>''Rings,'' taking the form of a monthslong ramble through the decayed towns of East Anglia -- interwoven with the narrator's meanderings through history, literature and his own depression -- makes a more general case. The Holocaust, lethally radiating in every temporal direction, contaminates in its foreshadowings and rememberings all human chronicles, not just those of the Jews.</p>
        <p>Proust, in the seclusion of his famous cork-lined room, recreated a past free from the interference of the present: a separate world, mesmeric, endlessly suggestive and utterly controlled. Mr. Sebald, a German writer, has no cork. And his novels, so very different, give rise to an equivalent sense (I will not say equal, since weights and measures are for another generation) that the ground of consciousness has shifted beneath us.</p>
        <p>The present that he explores is invaded, governed, sullied and eroded by the past. In a modern Europe Mr. Sebald has created a common market or free trade zone between memory and the senses, between then and now, between what we think or do and what the past has thought and done. There are no boundary markers or customs posts.</p>
        <p>Time is not what we employ to measure the distance we have come or plan to go. It is a mechanism set off in the past and advancing balefully upon us. It will not simply limit our future -- the classical notion -- it undoes our present. We resort to futile devices against it.</p>
        <p>''Vertigo,'' for example, describes a watchmaker's shop ''in which a host of long-case clocks, wall-mounted regulators, kitchen and living room clocks, alarm clocks, pocket and wristwatches were all ticking at once, just as if one clock on its own could not destroy enough time.''</p>
        <p>''Vertigo'' is Mr. Sebald's first novel, now rendered into English by his regular translator, Michael Hulse, whose fine transparency is the sheerest of silk gloves on the writer's hand. It has some of the instant bewitchment -- we enter Mr. Sebald's discourse like Alice going down the rabbit hole -- of the other books. Here the incantations of his style are used for a slighter purpose, as if he were honing his instruments. The exception may be the last of the book's four sections; a memoir, beguiling and troubling, of the Bavarian village where the narrator was raised.</p>
        <p>In all of Mr. Sebald's writing the narrator's identification with the author flickers; each leaves the other free. In any case, identity for Mr. Sebald is geological more than personal: the stratum deposits of history, reading, the imagination and dreams. ''Dream Is a Life'' would be Mr. Sebald's reversal of the title of Calderon de la Barca's celebrated play.</p>
        <p>The first three sections interweave the narrator's travels in Italy with those of Stendhal, Casanova and Kafka. N (I will call him) disappears into his subject; at times he is living their lives, at others it is as if they were living his. None of it makes a narrative, really; more like a nervous picking up of detail or incident, as a collector might proceed who is not certain what he should be collecting. ''Only collect'' could be N's motto; but the randomness is a statement of human existence.</p>
        <p>Photographs are used (as they are to more rending effect in the other books) to document the uncertainty. The receipt for a park fee in Verona, a railroad ticket extending the fare when N decides to go beyond his destination, the snapshot of a boarded-up pizzeria he once went to (and fled in panic). Life's meaning is uncertain, but: Look here, I have been to the park, on the train, at the restaurant.</p>
        <p>The first sketch is delicate but tenuous; a variation on the memoirs Stendhal wrote years after he went to Italy in Napoleon's army. More substantial are N's travels touching on Casanova's time in Venice, where he was imprisoned; and Kafka's visit to Lake Garda for a hydrotherapy cure.</p>
        <p>N makes the stops. At Desenzano he lies down on the grass as Kafka did; later he has a mild flirtation with the landlady of an inn on the lake. He gets into an imbroglio with the parents of two boys he accosts because he thinks they look like Kafka.</p>
        <p>He undergoes depressions and fears that seem to mirror Kafka's. He hallucinates glimpses of Dante, the daughter of James I and mad King Ludwig of Bavaria. We become what we know, goes the Aristotelian formulation; and Mr. Sebald's N becomes the history and literature he has read and the paintings he has seen.</p>
        <p>In this early book Mr. Sebald has not yet found a way to attach his melancholy and his oddly moving comedy to a convincing vision of history's fearful workings. ''Vertigo'' floats at times; meanwhile there is the lovely specificity of the writing: the seen characters and the unseen wildness, for instance, in the Alpine village where N grew up. Or the Verona dog.</p>
        <p>As N is chasing ghosts: ''A sandy-colored dog with a black mark like a patch over its left eye, that appeared like all stray dogs to run at an angle to the direction it was moving in, had attached itself to me outside the duomo and now kept a steady distance ahead of me. If I paused to gaze down at the river, it paused as well and looked pensively at the flowing water.''</p>
        <p>N has Kafka and a headful of cloudy connections. The dog has his modest canine day, and N.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
