<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Are They Dying in Cinnaminson?</title>
    <meta content="08COV.$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heroin</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cinnaminson (Nj)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Capuzzo, Jill P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heroin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E4D71E3DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="3579" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Are They Dying in Cinnaminson?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JILL P. CAPUZZO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Capuzzo, Jill P</byline>
      <dateline>CINNAMINSON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article explores possible reasons for rash of heroin overdoses in Cinnaminson, NJ, where four youths, all studens at Cinnaminson High School, have died in last 18 months; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was Christmas night and the festivities at the Fisher house were winding down. Like any 18-year-old, Bobby Fisher was eager to go hang with his friends. He had argued with his girlfriend Lizzie, who was home from college, earlier in the day because they weren't getting together on Christmas. But she agreed that they would celebrate the following day.</p>
        <p>Bobby called about midnight to tell his mother he was staying at a friend's house, but by late afternoon the next day, she began to worry. About 5 p.m. -- presents and love note in hand -- Lizzie Ritchie headed for Bobby's house. Since his car wasn't in the driveway, she went to see a friend next door.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was Christmas night and the festivities at the Fisher house were winding down. Like any 18-year-old, Bobby Fisher was eager to go hang with his friends. He had argued with his girlfriend Lizzie, who was home from college, earlier in the day because they weren't getting together on Christmas. But she agreed that they would celebrate the following day.</p>
        <p>Bobby called about midnight to tell his mother he was staying at a friend's house, but by late afternoon the next day, she began to worry. About 5 p.m. -- presents and love note in hand -- Lizzie Ritchie headed for Bobby's house. Since his car wasn't in the driveway, she went to see a friend next door.</p>
        <p>It was then that Lizzie found out. Bobby was dead. He had overdosed on heroin at his friend's house that morning.</p>
        <p>At Bobby's viewing later that week, Lizzie Ritchie, still numb, joined the stream of high school students, recent graduates, families and friends who waited for two hours to pay their final respects. A couple of weeks later, when it was time to return to college, she suffered a nervous breakdown and had to be hospitalized.</p>
        <p>Bobby's family, shattered and filled with unspeakable grief, prayed that their oldest child was finally at peace while friends asked, ''Why Bobby?'' the one who ''came from a good family,'' ''had his head on straight,'' and ''was going places.''</p>
        <p>Yet as shocking as the news was to this manicured suburb of 15,000 in southern Burlington County, Bobby Fisher was not the first Cinnaminson youth to die of a heroin overdose. Nor would he be the last.</p>
        <p>In the last 18 months, four of Cinnaminson's youth have died of heroin overdoses -- four boys who attended Cinnaminson High School, four boys who were well-acquainted, four boys who left families and friends mourning their loss and asking why. After all, Cinnaminson is not the only small town in the shadow of drug-riddled North Philadelphia, where users say buying heroin is as easy as placing an order at a fast-food restaurant. Nor is it the only wealthy suburb where hard drugs have found a home in recent years. One parent support group that tracks drug-related deaths in South Jersey estimates that so far this year 85 people have died of drug overdoses.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is just bad luck. Or perhaps Cinnaminson is simply a striking example of what is happening throughout the country. The local youths who have taken heroin -- as well as their families and friends -- talk of affluence, boredom, peer-pressure, thrill-seeking and depression as reasons they started using the highly addictive opiate. But those explanations have not made it any easier for the community to grapple with the stark reality of losing four young men to such a useless cause.</p>
        <p>Eight months before Bobby's death, Christopher Reed, a junior at Cinnaminson High School, had been playing basketball when friends said he complained that he did not feel well and headed home. The next morning, Chris's birthday, the police got a call from his home about an ''unresponsive 17-year-old male'' -- another drug overdose death. Fellow students called Chris, the son of a policeman, a ''rookie'' who had only been using heroin for a short time.</p>
        <p>On Jan. 25, just a month after Bobby's death, a snowstorm swept through the area, so nobody questioned it when Ty Saulli did not show up for work as a delivery man the next day. When a co-worker stopped by Ty's apartment the to pick him up the following day and things didn't look right, he summoned Ty's sister. It was she who found her brother -- who had just turned 21 -- bent over next to his bed, stone cold, with a needle and empty bag of heroin nearby. Although Ty had graduated from Cinnaminson High a couple years earlier, the word spread quickly. Ty's girlfriend, Dawn Stroemel, a senior there, was one of the people who got the news in school that day. She went screaming down the hall and called her mother, begging her to let her leave school.</p>
        <p>The deaths of Chris Reed, Bobby Fisher and Ty Saulli were enough to shake up some of the youths here who had become involved with heavy drugs over the last couple of years. But not all of them. On Aug. 30, a man pulling from his driveway on the way to work noticed a body on a lawn across the street. It was a neighbor, 19-year-old Jim Terenzi, who had died during the night of a drug overdose. Friends said Jim was ''a little wild,'' and some even speculated that his death might have been intentional.</p>
        <p>But one thing was certain, one more young man in this South Jersey town had killed himself with heroin, one more funeral had to be held for this dwindling group of friends.</p>
        <p>During that same harrowing period, the police here also found themselves looking into three other heroin overdose deaths, including that of a 17-year-old girl from Pennsylvania who was found in one of a string of budget motels that line the three-mile stretch of Route 130 that bisects the town.</p>
        <p>Cinnaminson's history is not very different from many of New Jersey's suburbs. Seeking the good life, a large influx of city dwellers moved here in the early 1960's, an era also reflected in the architecture that dominates the township -- sizable ranch and split-level homes on maturely landscaped properties. Yet lacking a downtown, Cinnaminson's main commercial activity has been relegated to the numerous low-rent motels, service stations and donuts shops that line the intrusive Route 130.</p>
        <p>The town's youths, who complain there is nothing to do here, find themselves congregating in Wood Park, the parking lot of the 7-Eleven, and the Harvest Diner, which is open 24 hours a day. Adults gravitate to the Acme supermarket, the public library and the Whistler's Inn pub.</p>
        <p>Of course, the township's two elementary schools, middle school and high school are also a main focus of community coherence.</p>
        <p>Today, even as the drug overdoses reverberate, no one is prepared to hold up Cinnaminson as being any different than any other suburban community with easy access to urban pockets where heroin is readily available. Indeed, around the country there has been a steady increase in heroin-related deaths, with the age of the typical heroin user dropping from 26.4 years old in 1990 to 17.6 today, according to the Drug Enforcement Administration.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the federal Department of Health and Human Services reports that the number of heroin-related emergency room visits by youths from 12 to 17 increased by 277 percent from 1990 to 1999, and tripled for those from 18 to 25 during the same years.</p>
        <p>In Cinnaminson, the succession of drug-related deaths has sent many here into a tailspin of fear and guilt -- particularly since the four deaths do not necessarily tell the whole story. For every young man who died, others have overdosed and been saved. Former heroin users here talk casually about a friend who has overdosed ''seven or eight times.'' One girl, whose parents threw her out of the house after putting her through eight unsuccessful detoxification treatments and three rehabilitation programs her senior year, was found on Easter morning, in the doorway of a building with a needle in her arm and almost no vital signs. The police rushed her to the hospital and she survived, but the young woman, now 20 and off drugs, is still serving time on a community service sentence for the crimes she committed while addicted to heroin.</p>
        <p>And for every person taking heroin, a wide network of family, friends and peers has been permanently affected.</p>
        <p>''People think of a junkie as a down-and-out person,'' said Rose Fisher, whose son, Bobby, had won the school's $7,000 Cooperative Industrial Education scholarship the same week he had to be rushed to a hospital for detoxification. ''You could never think of someone in your town doing this. But times have changed. We're all just regular, average people.''</p>
        <p>Kimberly Medina remembers the call she got from the high school asking permission to test her son, Glenn, who was suspected of using heroin -- ''a mother's second worst nightmare.'' It was a test that he would fail. When her boss found out, Ms. Medina lost her keys to the office, and eventually her job. She almost lost her house. And though Glenn has been clean for a year, she fears what the effects will be on Glenn's younger brother, who she is already sending to a different high school.</p>
        <p>Even those more peripherally involved have suffered lasting scars.</p>
        <p>''If people think it doesn't have anything to do with them, they should talk to me,'' said Maggie Ritchie, the mother of Bobby Fisher's girlfriend, Lizzie. ''It has completely shattered our lives. It was as if the drugs had not only killed Bobby, they took a piece of Lizzie too.''</p>
        <p>Getting a sense of the depth of the problem here -- and how it may vary from other communities in New Jersey -- is difficult. Everyone from the police to school officials to the students themselves carries a list in their heads of ''who's using.'' Nor do all the lists include the same names. Laurie Bass, one of two crisis counselors at Cinnaminson High School, estimates that a couple of years ago as many as 25 of the school's 795 students had been using heroin at one time. She believes the number is significantly lower this year, in part because of the deaths and the effect they have had on the community. But she admits that could change at any time.</p>
        <p>''Right now I only know of one person in the school who's using, but next week I might find out about another handful,'' said Ms. Bass, who has been a counselor at the school since the fall of 1997. ''The problem is still very much in the community.''</p>
        <p>The police agree that despite the latest death -- that of Jim Terenzi in August -- the problem has leveled off since 1999, a year they call ''pure hell.'' In the detectives' office, a bulletin board lists 30 home burglaries committed in 1999. Half of them have a series of green initials next to them -- indicating that they have been solved. The initials are all known drug users, and Det. Mark Siemietkoski suspects that virtually all of the unsolved cases are also drug-related. So far this year, only a handful of home burglaries have been reported, partly because those who committed last year's rash of break-ins are ''in the system and trying to be good,'' Detective Siemietkoski said.</p>
        <p>Assessing blame for the drug problem is even more difficult. Many cite the easy availability of heroin, since Cinnaminson sits just seven miles from the drug-infested neighborhoods of North Philadelphia. If a student here wants the drug badly enough, he can cross the Tacony-Palmyra Bridge, buy the drug and be back during a study hall period.</p>
        <p>The mother of the girl found nearly dead on Easter morning said her daughter would borrow the car and say she was going to the 7-Eleven. ''She'd be gone a half hour and I wouldn't think anything of it,'' the mother said.</p>
        <p>''It's like a McDonald's drive-through,'' said the girl, who declined to be identified, referring to the Kensington section of North Philadelphia. ''Everybody's shouting at you what they've got. You just walk up to them, give them your ten dollars, and you're set.''</p>
        <p>Another factor in heroin's growing popularity is its increasing purity and decreasing price. Since the mid-1990's, most heroin in the United States has come from South America, with Colombian drug cartels providing a far purer and less costly product.</p>
        <p>The federal Drug Enforcement Administration's domestic monitor program reports that heroin is now nearly 40 percent pure and costs 80 cents a milligram, as against $3.90 a milligram in 1980, when it was only 3 percent pure.</p>
        <p>While a typical $10 bag can get a novice high two or three times, the police say the varying degree of purity -- which can be as high as 90 percent -- can catch a user by surprise and lead to an overdose. The increased purity of the drug also means that users can now snort or smoke heroin rather than shoot it, removing some of the health risks and stigmatization connected with injecting the drug.</p>
        <p>''Years ago there was a serious social stigma attached to it because the only way you could use it was through needles,'' said the principal at Cinnaminson High School, Michael Zank. ''Now half the users never inject it, so it is a little more acceptable.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Zank is quick to point out that using heroin is ''not looked at as cool'' by most of the students. ''These kids are looked at as desperate, deceitful, deceptive kids who will steal from their families and friends. It's not a segment of society that gets much sympathy from other kids.''</p>
        <p>As at Columbine High School in Colorado -- where 2 youths murdered 12 students and a teacher before turning their weapons on themselves -- that same sense of being an outsider might contribute to the drug users' continued sense of worthlessness and resulting downward spiral. Some say the problem starts at home, where parental supervision is supplanted by families with enough disposable income to give their children anything they want.</p>
        <p>''Cinnaminson has money,'' said Ms. Medina, who discovered in Glenn's senior year that her son had been taking heroin for two years. ''The kids have cars. Their parents hand them the money and tell them 'go have a good time.' A lot of them have so much free time they don't know what to do with themselves.''</p>
        <p>When local rehabilitation programs did not work, Ms. Medina sent Glenn to her brother's home in Florida for several months to get him away from the influence of his friends and break his $50-a-day habit.</p>
        <p>Glenn's friend, Brad, said he got started out of boredom. ''We'd go play football once in a while, but there's not much else to do,'' said Brad, who is an 18-year-old college freshman today. ''You're with your friends and you're wanting to have some fun. It was fun for a while, but then it got to be a big struggle and then it was no fun.''</p>
        <p>Brad ended up missing most of his senior year in high school when his family sent him to a rehabilitation program in Utah for six months.</p>
        <p>Rose Fisher blames peer pressure and the lure of the drug itself.</p>
        <p>''You can't get between your kids and their friends when it comes to peer pressure,'' she said. ''The sad thing is Bobby really wanted to get off it. He kept trying, but he kept finding himself back with the same friends, and eventually it got the best of him. His problem was this drug, he started doing it and he just couldn't drop it.''</p>
        <p>This spring, the high school published a special issue of the school newspaper, ''Ship's Log,'' in memory of Bobby Fisher. The 14-page supplement included comments from fellow students and professionals, information on various drugs, a heart-wrenching two-page family history by Rose Fisher, and several writings by Bobby, which showed what a tight grip the drug had on him.</p>
        <p>In one poem, he pleaded:</p>
        <p>Mom take this pain away,</p>
        <p>Need to feel loved by you,</p>
        <p>Need you to push me through,</p>
        <p>This hell grows on for years.</p>
        <p>Mom please wipe all these tears,</p>
        <p>I want to go farther,</p>
        <p>Help me through and break this wall,</p>
        <p>It possessed me,</p>
        <p>It controlled me,</p>
        <p>Now I want</p>
        <p>The real me.</p>
        <p>Some here now worry that with each death, those who have a weakness for the drug will be driven back to it by their sadness.</p>
        <p>''These boys have lost four friends,'' said Lizzie Ritchie, who returned to George Washington University this fall after taking her spring semester off. ''The fact that their friends are passing away is so depressing they're going to want something to numb the pain.''</p>
        <p>Despite its sparkling hallways, talented drama department and a football team that lost only one game in the last year, Cinnaminson High School has been viewed by some as the source of the problem, even though the school is taking some of the most aggressive steps in the community to eradicate the problem. In addition to the crisis counselors, who are also licensed social workers, the school has brought in speakers to discuss drug abuse and has hired a police officer to serve as a deterrent and a resource for kids in need. A drug-testing program and a staff trained to detect possible drug use has also helped.</p>
        <p>''The fact is, their best chance for survival is when they're still here and 16,'' said Ms. Bass, one of the school's drug counselors. ''If we can't rehab them by the time they leave here, who's going to rehab them once they're 18 and out on their own?''</p>
        <p>All of the boys who died were well-known to Ms. Bass or her colleague, Jesus Powers, both of whom had worked with the youths and their families to try to get them rehabilitated. Those who survived and are now clean give a lot of credit to the counselors.</p>
        <p>''Miss Bass is doing a good job,'' said Glenn Medina. ''She really helped me out. If it wasn't for her, God only knows where I'd be.''</p>
        <p>And while Ms. Bass and Mr. Powers are the members of the staff in whom students sometimes confide, they are also the ones who flag students for drug testing. When the school suspects someone is using drugs, a urinalysis is performed, 99 percent of which come out positive, said Ms. Bass. The student is then suspended for 10 days and on returning to school must be accompanied by a parent, who participates in developing a treatment program.</p>
        <p>''We want the active drug person removed from the environment, then we get aggressive about treatment,'' said Dr. Zank, the high school principal. ''There has to be a punishment for this behavior, it's an illegal behavior and we have to set a standard. But we don't assume they're going to come back and be clean.''</p>
        <p>In addition to placing full-time officers in the high school and the middle school, the police department has beefed up its bike patrol this year and started an early-warning program they call ''knock and rap'' to let families know if they suspect a child is using drugs.</p>
        <p>''We're following up on hearsay,'' said Detective Siemietkoski. ''We go there not as officers, but as fellow parents. We're there to make them aware that rumors are out there and that there may be a problem.''</p>
        <p>But beyond the drug counselors and the police, some in the community are becoming more vocal about the drug problem. The Cinnaminson Alliance, one of 520 community-based drug prevention citizens' groups that make up the New Jersey Municipal Alliances, has been rallying township residents to participate in next Saturday's Walk Against Substance Abuse in Medford. Similar walks will be taking place throughout the state to support Governor Whitman's anti-drug campaign. The superintendent of schools in Cinnaminson, Salvatore Illuzzi, has arranged for four buses to transport what the Alliance hopes to be 100 students, Girl Scouts, and concerned residents to participate in the walk.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time we're showing total community support,'' said Eileen Hernandez, a member of the Cinnaminson Alliance and regional co-ordinator for the Girl Scouts. ''If we can get a large group of people out there to march, it's like we're saying 'we're not going to allow this to happen again.' ''</p>
        <p>But it did happen. Death did come to Cinnaminson and take its teenagers. And some of those shaken most harshly are skeptical that things are going to change very fast.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think Bobby would be the last one to die, and I don't think Jim is going to be the last one either,'' said Ms. Fisher, who nine months after her son's death still bakes four potatoes and sets out four plates at the dinner table. ''We haven't even started to address this problem. As long as it's not in their house, they don't care. Unless they get a call, they don't want any part of it. Nobody thinks its going to happen to them.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
