<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="08GUID$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1D61E3DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Barbara Delatiner</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>The Nassau County Museum of Art sees beyond the brush and canvas to define art, long enough at least for ''Gardens as Art: An Autumn Landscape and Garden Spectacular.'' The nine-day show, through Oct. 22, gets under way on Saturday, transforming the Great Lawn of what was once the Frick estate off Northern Boulevard in Roslyn Harbor into a series of innovative gardens created by some of the leading landscape designers on the Island. In addition to the gardens, the show features a marketplace of garden ornaments, furniture and decorative objects; daily lectures, including, on Oct. 19,  ''Tea and Conversation With Martha Frick Symington Sanger,'' who will reminisce about her childhood at the family estate; music by the Venus Flute Ensemble, a quartet from the Juilliard School of Music, during the first weekend; and on Oct. 21 and 22, a Family Festival with the Big Apple Circus to Go. Visitors will also be able to explore the newly restored Marian Cruger Coffin Formal Garden (516) 625-9397.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>The Nassau County Museum of Art sees beyond the brush and canvas to define art, long enough at least for ''Gardens as Art: An Autumn Landscape and Garden Spectacular.'' The nine-day show, through Oct. 22, gets under way on Saturday, transforming the Great Lawn of what was once the Frick estate off Northern Boulevard in Roslyn Harbor into a series of innovative gardens created by some of the leading landscape designers on the Island. In addition to the gardens, the show features a marketplace of garden ornaments, furniture and decorative objects; daily lectures, including, on Oct. 19,  ''Tea and Conversation With Martha Frick Symington Sanger,'' who will reminisce about her childhood at the family estate; music by the Venus Flute Ensemble, a quartet from the Juilliard School of Music, during the first weekend; and on Oct. 21 and 22, a Family Festival with the Big Apple Circus to Go. Visitors will also be able to explore the newly restored Marian Cruger Coffin Formal Garden (516) 625-9397.</p>
        <p>Community Orchestras</p>
        <p>Community orchestras are alive and well and still performing on the Island. And on Saturday, two of them begin their new seasons. In North Merrick at 8 p.m. at the Brookside School Center on Meadowbrook Road, the Merrick Symphony, conducted by Charles Peltz, starts its 25th anniversray year with a concert featuring Tchaikovsky's Violin Concerto performed by Joseph Lin, a guest artist (516) 623-6118. Also on the South Shore but in Massapequa, the Massapequa Philharmonic Orchestra, under the baton of Eckart Preu, guest conductor, and joined by Karen Gomyo, violinist, begins its 18th season with Brahms's Symphony No. 1 in C minor and Glinka's ''Russian and Ludmilla Overture.'' The free concert is at 8:30 p.m. at Berner Junior High School on Carmans Mill Road (516) 795-4071.</p>
        <p>American Music</p>
        <p>From Scott Joplin to Duke Ellington, American composers came into their own during six decades that spanned the 19th and 20th centuries. And in ''American Music Comes of Age, 1880-1940,'' the quintet Not Just Another Dixieland Band performs music by Joplin and Ellington and  works of such other popular composers of the period as John Philip Sousa, Jelly Roll Morton, Louis Armstrong and Benny Goodman. The concert is at 2:30 p.m. today at the Long Island Museum of American Art, History and Carriages (formerly the Museums at Stony Brook) on Route 25A in Stony Brook (631) 751-0066.</p>
        <p>Gala 'Gala XX'</p>
        <p>If you have to have a gala marking your 20th anniversary, it helps to have someone like Itzhak Perlman on board. So on Saturday the Tilles Center, on the C. W. Post campus of Long Island University in Brookville, marks its milestone with Mr. Perlman and the Mostly Mozart Festival Orchestra, conducted by Gerard Schwarz, performing excerpts from Handel's ''Water Music,'' Mozart's Symphony No. 26 (''Linz'') and Beethoven's Violin Concerto. The concert is at 8:30 p.m. following a black-tie dinner and before dessert and dancing. While the donation for the entire evening is $600, concert tickets alone are from $60 to $125 (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>Rock 'Legends'</p>
        <p>When it comes to rock ''legends,'' Poco and Firefall may be relatively unsung, known only to dedicated students of the genre. But back in the late 1970's both groups had a major impact, adding country harmonies to the rock beat: Poco, from Southern California, with such sometimes platinum hits as ''Crazy Love'' and ''Heart of the Night,'' and Firefall, based in Colorado, with ''You Are the Woman'' and ''Just Remember I Love You.'' The two groups bring their special sounds to the Westhampton Beach Performing Arts Center on Main Street today for an 8 p.m. concert (631) 288-1500.</p>
        <p>Biking Long Island</p>
        <p>Get out those three -- or 10 -- speeds, polish up the helmets and pad the seats. It's time for the ''Canon Discover Long Island Bike Tour.'' Not a race, but rather a family-oriented, traffic-free excursion through Nassau's South Shore, the event begins at 8 a.m. next Sunday at the Nassau Veterans Memorial Coliseum. Then, depending upon a cyclist's choice of 15-, 25- or 50-mile routes, riders will peddle down Meadowbrook Parkway to Point Lookout Beach, via the Loop Parkway, and return to the Coliseum for a reception. The event will benefit the Disabled Children's Relief Fund, the Education and Assistance Corporation, the National Heritage Trust, Friends of Nassau County Recreation and the New York State Games for the Physically Challenged (516) 735-3100.</p>
        <p>Still Fair Weather</p>
        <p>As the Long Island Fair at Old Bethpage Village Restoration winds down today and tomorrow from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. each day with activities like sheep herding at 11 a.m. and 3 p.m., crosscut sawing contests at 2 p.m. and contra dancing at 4 p.m. (516) 572-8400, five more festivals step up to take its place on Saturday.  In Cold Spring Harbor, the Fish Hatchery and Aquarium on Route 25A holds its Fall Fair with fishing for children under 12, environmental exhibitions, foods and games from 10 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. (516) 692-6768. In Long Beach, the Fall Festival from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. (and again next Sunday) is at Kennedy Plaza and features a pumpkin patch, rides, music and wine tastings (516) 431-1000, and at noon on Saturday a Halloween costume parade at the adjacent recreation field on Magnolia Boulevard (516) 431-3890.</p>
        <p>Oyster Bay holds its 17th annual Oyster Festival, complete with plenty of the delicacy on the half shell, fried or in chowder; a fine-arts and crafts show; an exhibition of historic wooden boats; tours of the sloop Providence; paddle-boat rides in the harbor; music and children's activities from 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. and again in Sunday, throughout the downtown village (516) 624-8082. In Southampton, the Celebrate Southampton Festival is a one-day affair, throughout the village from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. Saturday, with performances by groups like the Peconic Warpipes and the Thunderbird Sisters; face painting; street clowns and African dances, and, at the Historical Museum, traditional crafts demonstrations and blacksmithing, and at the Rogers Library, a square dance. (631) 283-2494. Finally, in another two-day event, there is the Harvest Festival of Greater Westhampton from noon to 5 p.m. with family activities and entertainment in the village of Westhampton Beach and, from 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. on the Village Green, an arts and crafts fair (800) 346-3290.</p>
        <p>Rating Presidents</p>
        <p>Hofstra University in Hempstead on Wednesday holds a one-day symposium, ''The Leadership Difference: Rating the Presidents.'' In addition to the usual scholarly papers by academicians, the day will feature a keynote address on ''Presidential Reputation: Image and Interpretation'' by Walter Isaacson, managing editor of Time Magazine (516) 463-5669.</p>
        <p>At the Libraries</p>
        <p>Luis Cordero and Los Amigos Del Amargue perform Dominican music at 2:30 p.m. today at the Freeport Library (516) 379-3274, while the Long Beach Library features Steve Adelson on the Chapman Stick, an unusual 12-string instrument, at 1:20 p.m. (516) 432-7201. Activity, curtailed by the holiday, picks up on Friday when Andrus Madsen and Kris Bezuidenhout perform Baroque music at 7 p.m. at the North Shore Library in Shoreham (631) 929-4488, while Saturday brings Heartland, a folk group, to the Lynbrook Library at 2 p.m. (516) 599-8630; Shlomo Haviv, an Israeli performer, to the Plainview Library at 8 p.m. (516) 938-0077; and the Garden City Readers Theater in ''Works by Woody Allen'' to the Syosset Library at 7:30 p.m. (516) 921-7161.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TODAY -- Naturalists from the Seatuck Environmental Association lead a family nature walk focusing on monarch butterflies as they migrate across Long Island on their journey to Mexico in ''Marvelous Monarch'' at 1:30 p.m. from Jones Beach State Park's Boat Basin parking lot (631) 581-6908.</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY -- In ''Shooting Jackson,'' Helen A. Harrison, director of the Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center, offers a behind-the-scenes look at the making of ''Pollock,'' the Ed Harris film that opens this month. The lecture, sponsored by the Artists Network of Great Neck, is at 8 p.m. at Great Neck House on Arrandale Avenue (516) 466-4922.</p>
        <p>SATURDAY -- The Walt Whitman Birthplace Association and the Long Island Greenbelt Trail Conference join forces for a ''Walt Whitman Walk and Poetry Fest.'' Following in the poet's footsteps, the 3.7-mile loop hike in West Hills County Park that includes Jayne's Hills, the highest spot on the Island, starts at 9 a.m. After the walk, activity shifts to the Whitman Birthplace on Old Whitman Road in Huntington Station for an open poetry reading, ''Celebrating Long Island'' (631) 567-9484.</p>
        <p>Compiled by Barbara Delatiner</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
