<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Avant-Garde, Now So Enduring</title>
    <meta content="08ART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wadsworth Atheneum (Hartford, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5D9103DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Avant-Garde, Now So Enduring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM ZIMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zimmer, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Zimmer reviews exhibit of Impressionist paintings of Argenteuil, France, on view at Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford, Conn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ARGENTEUIL, seven miles north of Paris, was a gathering spot for the Impressionists beginning in the 1870's. The first Impressionist exhibition was conceived there in 1874. The painters, who arrived soon after the town was rebuilt following the  Franco-Prussian War, found factories with belching smokestacks as well as weekend houses owned by people devoted to pleasure boating.</p>
        <p>This rich diversity is captured in the paintings of six artists featured in ''The Impressionists at Argenteuil'' at the Wadsworth Atheneum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ARGENTEUIL, seven miles north of Paris, was a gathering spot for the Impressionists beginning in the 1870's. The first Impressionist exhibition was conceived there in 1874. The painters, who arrived soon after the town was rebuilt following the  Franco-Prussian War, found factories with belching smokestacks as well as weekend houses owned by people devoted to pleasure boating.</p>
        <p>This rich diversity is captured in the paintings of six artists featured in ''The Impressionists at Argenteuil'' at the Wadsworth Atheneum.</p>
        <p>Too often Impressionism conjures up sometimes too airy delights along with the feeling that there's not enough to hold on to. This show conquers that sensation through the virtue of focus; one place, albeit with multiple aspects, is widely explored. The exhibition serves the art well by the limpid way it is installed. There is a lot of space between the paintings and in some rooms, only three walls hold art.</p>
        <p>Three of the six painters stand on the pinnacle of household names: Edouard Manet, Claude Monet and Auguste Renoir. The others are lesser known but their presence is no less formidable: Alfred Sisley, Eugene Boudin and Gustave Caillebotte.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, however, Monet dominates. His crowning portrait, set on a hilltop, is ''Woman with a Parasol: Madame Monet and Her Son.'' It is close to an apotheosis.</p>
        <p>Other artists documented Monet's family. Renoir, foremost a painter of people, lavishly portrayed Madame Monet reading, and did a close-up of Monet reading a book and smoking. Renoir also painted Monet at his easel and Madame Monet and her son at ease in their garden.</p>
        <p>A fine side-by-side comparison is Monet's ''Sailboats at Argenteuil'' and Renoir's painting of the same name and of the same scene. Renoir's is characterized by his customary warm burnished color, while Monet's recording of the scene is especially emphatic. He includes a couple of racing sculls as dashed red lines.</p>
        <p>Monet is particularly impressive in a couple of paintings of the railroad bridge at Argenteuil in which the emphasis is on the columnar concrete supports. Like the Precisionists half a century later, Monet endows these industrial forms with a classical grandeur. Yet it is clear that they are not easily integrated into the generally bucolic atmosphere. In another painting, though, what dominates are reeds rendered with calligraphic strokes, the influence of Japanese art.</p>
        <p>Manet's presence in the exhibition is a complex one. He was older than the others, except for Boudin, and was an influence on the Impressionists before being in turn influenced by them. He could often shock and in his masterwork here, ''Boating,'' the attitudes of the man and woman are easily read as sexually charged, while a large portrait of Monet and his wife in his floating studio isn't much more than a sketch, but one that catches precise gestures.</p>
        <p>The most elusive presence is that of Boudin, Monet's teacher in the 1850's. He represented by only one painting, ''The Seine at Argenteuil'' from 1866. The painting is important as a forerunner of Impressionism and because it features a rather insistent horizon line; it is also related to Boudin's most celebrated body of work, marine paintings of bathers in a line on the seashore.</p>
        <p>Although Sisley is represented by only four paintings, he is valuable because he best represented the urban aspect of Argenteuil. Two paintings represent streets in town, ''The Grande Rue, Argenteuil'' and ''The Boulevard Heloise, Argenteuil.'' Sisley seems to anticipate van Gogh in the way he outlines figures and other significant details in black. In his low-key way he can be dramatic: ''The Boulevard Heloise'' is depicted in a strong wind. In his two more languorous paintings, discrete clouds with definite outlines are the mesmerizing feature, and Sisley is something of a knowing primitive.</p>
        <p>Caillebotte, on the other hand, threatens to play the bull to Argenteuil's china shop. In the history books it is stressed that Caillebotte was wealthy and acted as a patron to many of the other Impressionists. It is clear that he felt he could go his own way. His paintings can elevate what to others would be unprepossessing or ugly details.</p>
        <p>''The Argenteuil Bridge and the Seine'' is framed by one of the seven stone and steel arches of the bridge, and girders and railings overwhelm everything more inviting. Caillebotte is in part an advanced abstract painter when he records the gleaming reflection in water of a stone pier crossing the shadow made by the bed of the tracks. Elsewhere he confronts the viewer with a long, monotonous, snaking line of laundry, a monotonous dry, green landscape -- and then for relief a somewhat comic yet incisive picture of a bearded gentleman walking several paces behind his prancing poodle.</p>
        <p>To mark the 25th anniversary of the Atheneum's contemporary art showcase, Matrix, Christian Jankowski, an artist based in Berlin, interviewed artists who had participated in Matrix over the years, along with the curator, Andrea Miller-Keller.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jankowski turned that oral history into theater, and children took the parts of and spoke the words of the artists and Ms. Miller-Keller. The result is a videotape that only a first-rate curmudgeon wouldn't find absolutely charming.</p>
        <p>The present curator, Nicholas Baume, writes in his accompanying essay that mistakes and confusions have always distinguished Mr. Jankowski's art, and that the artist delighted in the fact that his actors sometimes said ''critters'' for ''critics,'' ''hysterical'' for ''historical'' and ''contrary'' for ''contemporary.'' His whole intention was to make a fairy tale in which art keeps its devotees young.</p>
        <p>''The Impressionists at Argenteuil'' is at the Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford through Dec. 3. ''Christian Jankowski: The Matrix Effect'' continues through Jan. 7.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
