<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Continents, Three Days</title>
    <meta content="ISTAN.$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Istanbul (Turkey)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frantz, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey/Istanbul</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1D6123DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="3123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Continents, Three Days</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS FRANTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frantz, Douglas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Douglas Frantz travel article on Istanbul, Turkey; photos; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SPRAWLED elegantly along both shores of the Bosporus, in both Europe and Asia, Istanbul is a fabled amalgam of civilizations layered one upon the other across nearly 3,000 years. Its ancient Christian and Islamic monuments exist within a vibrant modern city, an intimate juxtaposition that makes Istanbul a fascinating place. The incandescence of this rich history amid a teeming metropolis, however, can leave even the most seasoned traveler too dazzled to truly appreciate one of the world's most splendid cities.</p>
        <p>So, just as the Ottoman Sultan Mehmet II understood when he drove out the last Byzantine emperor in 1453, a good plan is a necessity for conquering Istanbul. The contemporary tourist's assault need not be as arduous as pulling war ships over the hills with oxen as Mehmet did. But a thoughtful itinerary will help a visitor see the important sights, from the ''musts'' on every guidebook list to the unexpected places that illuminate the city's uniqueness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SPRAWLED elegantly along both shores of the Bosporus, in both Europe and Asia, Istanbul is a fabled amalgam of civilizations layered one upon the other across nearly 3,000 years. Its ancient Christian and Islamic monuments exist within a vibrant modern city, an intimate juxtaposition that makes Istanbul a fascinating place. The incandescence of this rich history amid a teeming metropolis, however, can leave even the most seasoned traveler too dazzled to truly appreciate one of the world's most splendid cities.</p>
        <p>So, just as the Ottoman Sultan Mehmet II understood when he drove out the last Byzantine emperor in 1453, a good plan is a necessity for conquering Istanbul. The contemporary tourist's assault need not be as arduous as pulling war ships over the hills with oxen as Mehmet did. But a thoughtful itinerary will help a visitor see the important sights, from the ''musts'' on every guidebook list to the unexpected places that illuminate the city's uniqueness.</p>
        <p>Exploring only the musts, however, could consume weeks, and three days seems the minimum necessary to get a sense of the past and present. Before devising a strategy to discover the essential Istanbul in that short period, a short geography lesson can be useful.</p>
        <p>The only major city on two continents, Istanbul was once a series of self-enclosed and distinct quarters and villages. As the city has grown to at least 12 million inhabitants, the borders have blurred, but the core can still be divided into four sections, each with a different flair.</p>
        <p>The oldest is Eminonu, centered around the architectural masterpieces, Topkapi Palace and the Hagia Sophia. Across the Golden Horn is the most cosmopolitan section, Beyoglu, for centuries home to Istanbul's foreigners. North along the European side of the Bosporus are the villages where the city's upper class and foreign diplomats spent summers. Finally comes the Asian side of the Bosporus, which remains the least-explored section, though it is packed with classical mosques and bustling urban life.</p>
        <p>A visit should begin early on the first day at the most extensive and fascinating monument of Ottoman architecture, Topkapi Palace. Between 1459 and 1465, Sultan Mehmet II built Topkapi as his principal residence and the seat of government on a hilly promontory where the Bosporus joins the Sea of Marmara. As succeeding sultans added their own flourishes, the complex grew to cover 173 acres.</p>
        <p>Not a palace in the European sense, Topkapi is a compound of gardens, workshops, government offices, courtyards and residences distributed among four courts. Spread among them are myriad treasures, including paintings, miniatures, armor, swords, jewelry, manuscripts and one of the world's finest collections of porcelain. Many rooms contain gorgeous tiles and most buildings have been restored to perfection.</p>
        <p>The palace would reward a full day, but,  with an early start, its many splendors can be sampled in three hours. Because of its immensity, it is useful to become familiar with Topkapi in advance through a good guidebook, and to consider using one of the licensed guides, some of whom are academics, sitting just inside the palace enclosure (not the hustlers outside).</p>
        <p>The best way to get a sense of Topkapi on your own is to head for the northwest corner of the second court and buy a ticket for the harem tour, which starts every half hour. While waiting, visit the imperial council chambers, where the viziers held session with the sultan observing covertly from a screened window on the second floor.</p>
        <p>''Harem'' is Arabic for forbidden and the harem was the labyrinthine residence of the sultan's wives, concubines and children, all guarded by black slave eunuchs. Among the fascinating places are the sultan's luxurious private bath and the chambers of the sultan's mother, who ruled the harem and sometimes the empire.</p>
        <p>A short stroll away, within the Topkapi compound, stands a sometimes overlooked treasure, the Archeological Museum. Established in 1896, the museum has superb exhibits from the prehistoric period through Ottoman times. The most spectacular item is the carved marble tomb from the late fourth century B.C., the Alexander Sarcophagus, depicting Alexander the Great winning a battle with the Persians.</p>
        <p>Outside the museum is a lovely cafe, its tables scattered among pieces of ancient sculpture. But better food is available at the Konyali restaurant at the Topkapi Palace or at an authentic neighborhood restaurant like Sultanahmet Koftecisi, at Divan Yolu 12, where the specialty is kofte, small rectangular meat patties.</p>
        <p>A few minutes' walk from Topkapi is one of the world's great architectural triumphs, the Hagia Sophia. Before proceeding, a word of caution: Tourists are routinely stopped by friendly men offering directions or advice. They are not threatening to anything but your bank account, since they try to persuade you to visit their carpet or antiquities shops. The best advice is the old adage caveat emptor, buyer beware.</p>
        <p>Fourteen centuries ago, the chronicler Procopius described the Hagia Sophia as it appeared during the reign of its founder, Emperor Justinian: ''The church presents a most glorious spectacle, extraordinary to those who behold it and altogether incredible to those who are told of it.  It is distinguished by indescribible  beauty, excelling both in is size and the harmonies of its measures. . . . ''</p>
        <p>For 900 years after it was completed in 537, the Hagia Sophia was the center of religious life in the Byzantine Empire. For nearly 500 years after the Turkish conquest, it was first among the city's mosques. Since 1935, it has been a museum, where tourists are as awed as Procopius was by the immense cupola floating above the prayer hall. Visitors can climb the ramp to the north gallery for a closer look at the remaining  stunning mosaics (most are gone).</p>
        <p>Before crossing the square to the Blue Mosque, take a detour a few steps northwest to the Yerebatan Sarayi, or Basilica Cistern. This sixth-century underground water cistern is a remarkable example of Byzantine engineering and a most unusual spot that many tourists miss.</p>
        <p>Descending the steps from the small entrance building, you follow walkways through a forest of beautiful 26-foot columns supporting the domed roof, with water dripping atmospherically into the pool. Not all of the 336 columns are visible, but two with Medusa heads at the far end should not be missed.</p>
        <p>Six graceful minarets identify the Sultan Ahmet Camii, or Blue Mosque. Light fills the cavernous mosque from 260 windows, and the main dome rises 77 feet above the floor. Its popular name comes from the blue tiles and painted arabesques of the domes and upper parts of the building, but the most subtle beauty lies in the Iznik tiles on the lower walls.</p>
        <p>As in all mosques, shoes must be removed and women should be dressed properly. Shawls are provided and a small contribution for the upkeep of the mosque is customary upon leaving.</p>
        <p>This first day is a full one, so the evening might be devoted to relaxing with a view. Local residents like Ulus Park, which is atop one of Istanbul's many hills north of the city and offers a vista over the city and inexpensive food in the tea garden. For a sumptuous and expensive meal and an equally superb view, try the Sunset Grill just below the park or one of the fish restaurants on the Bosporus, like Iskele in Rumeli Hisari, where the specialty is grilled calamari and dinner for two, with wine, is about $100.</p>
        <p>The Suleymaniye Mosque in the bazaar quarter is the perfect starting point for the second day. Though smaller than the Blue Mosque, it is the most magisterial of the imperial mosques, the masterwork of the greatest Ottoman architect, Mimar Sinan. Work began in 1550 and it took nine years to finish the mosque and the adjoining schools, hospital, public kitchen, bath and shopping street. A terrace on the north side of the grounds provides a commanding view of the Golden Horn, the Bosporus and Asia.</p>
        <p>The mosque's four minarets are said to represent that its founder, Suleyman the Magnificent, was the fourth sultan to reign in Istanbul. It is fitting that Suleyman built the city's finest mosque complex, for his reign from 1520 to 1566 was the longest and most illustrious of the Ottoman Empire. Unlike the Hagia Sophia, the mosque's immense central dome is not divided by galleries or even aisles, so the effect of a floating cupola is even more dramatic.</p>
        <p>The calm of the Suleymaniye contrasts with the cacophony of the Kapali Carsi, or Covered Bazaar, where merchants vie irresistibly for the attention of every passing tourist. The 450-year-old bazaar is really a small city that has changed little since an 1880 survey counted 4,399 shops, 2,195 ateliers, 497 stalls, 12 storehouses, 18 fountains and 12 small mosques.</p>
        <p>The bazaar's street names originated with the guilds that have traded in those locations for centuries, but it is still easy to get lost within the roofed labyrinth of passages. Many of the goods are mass produced, and some are overpriced, but there are fine pieces, too, and ancient and genuine items can be found in the Bedesten section.</p>
        <p>Bargaining is essential and the initial price will generally be at least a third higher than what the seller expects. Still, bargaining for an expensive rug is best left to an expert.</p>
        <p>The Covered Bazaar assaults your ears and eyes, while the smaller Spice Bazaar, or Misir Carsisi, just a 10-minute stroll toward the Golden Horn is a riot of aromas. The L-shaped building dates to the early 17th century. Along with all manner of spices and herbs, the stalls stock nuts, honey and other food as well as live animals.</p>
        <p>Next door is the Rustem Pasa Camii, with a beautiful small mosque by Sinan on the second floor. It is best known for its gorgeous blue and white tiles from Iznik, the lakeside town where the finest ceramics of the Ottoman Empire were produced.</p>
        <p>Stroll across the Golden Horn on the Galata Bridge to the foot of the hill that leads to Beyoglu. In 1348, the Genoese who lived in the district constructed the Galata Tower there and it still provides a great view.</p>
        <p>The heart of Beyoglu is Istiklal Caddesi, a long boulevard lined with 19th-century apartment houses and thronged with pedestrians day and night. Explore the winding side streets and alleyways, where jazz bars thrive and shops sell paintings, handcrafted jewelry and furniture.</p>
        <p>About midway along Istiklal is an arch marked ''Cicek Pasaji,'' or Flower Passage. The one-time flower stalls are now restaurants, but to find the best places, skip the ones inside the arch, wind past the fish and fruit stands and turn down one of the narrow passages filled with restaurants known as meyhanes. The tables and the festive atmosphere overflow onto the narrow street and every night seems like a giant outdoor party.</p>
        <p>Most of the restaurants do not have written menus. Instead, waiters bring trays displaying small dishes of meze, Turkish appetizers. There are hundreds, hot and cold, from melon platters and marinated sardines to elaborately stuffed vegetables and smoked eggplant. Meze can make a meal, but the restaurants also offer fresh fish and meat dishes. Everything goes best with raki, the clear anise-flavored national drink. It is difficult to spend more than $10 a person.</p>
        <p>Ortakoy, or ''middle village,'' is a few miles north of the city center on the European side of the Bosporus. The collection of cafes and restaurants along the water is a perfect place to start the third day with a traditional breakfast of tea, cheeses, olives and bread. Weekend mornings are best because the cafes are crowded and the lively flea market is bustling.</p>
        <p>Near the cafes, on a promontory at the edge of the water, stands the Ortakoy mosque. Built in 1854, it is a handsome building with a baroque exterior and a light-filled interior. But the focus of this third day is a visit to another continent by car or boat or both.</p>
        <p>Taxis are inexpensive and minivans and guides can be hired through hotels and travel agencies. Be warned that the traffic can be horrendous and even short drives can turn into ordeals at rush hour. There also are regular ferries from Eminonu and Kabatas, east of Beyoglu, for the trip to Asia.</p>
        <p>Uskudar is the largest of Istanbul's Asian quarters. Situated on the lower end of the Bosporus, its maze of narrow streets and old wooden houses retain an Oriental flair. There are also several important mosques, including Sinan's Iskele Camii, or Mosque of the Landing.</p>
        <p>A popular excursion in Uskudar is driving to the top of Camlica Tepesi, or the Pine Grove Hill, the highest point on the Bosporus, 875 feet. The cafe and teahouse at the summit are popular for wedding parties and the view is incomparable.</p>
        <p>No trip to Istanbul is complete without a cruise on the Bosporus. There are several options, from inexpensive ferries and tour boats to private boats with dinner and drinks. The ferries of the official Turkish Maritime Lines are the best value. They make three round trips daily from Eminonu to the upper Bosporus, stopping at several piers along the way. More romantic are boats operated by private owners, which carry anywhere from 4 to 40. A dinner cruise costs about $30 to $40 a person.</p>
        <p>Cruising north along the European side, the sights start with the opulent 19th-century Dolmabahce Palace and its ornate gates along the water; the Ciragan Palace and adjoining hotel, the city's most luxurious; the wooden houses of Arnavutkoy; and the luxurious summer houses and embassies of Yenikoy and Tarabya.</p>
        <p>The return trip along the Asian side is equally fascinating, from the splendid waterfront houses known as yalis to the shoreside pavilions of the Beylerbeyi Palace. If the boat stops in nearby Kanlica, you can enjoy a light yogurt with sugar found nowhere else in Istanbul.</p>
        <p>Whether by ferry or yacht, the cruise will reveal places you have not seen. How do you visit it all? Stay longer in the imperial city.</p>
        <p>Exploring up and down the Bosporus</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Yesil Ev, Kabasakal Caddesi 5, Sultanahmet, is a charming small hotel with a garden in a renovated wooden Ottoman mansion on the edge of a small park between the Hagia Sophia and the Blue Mosque. Doubles are $160, including tax and breakfast; the Pasha's suite is $250;  (90-212) 517-6785, fax (90-212) 517-6780.</p>
        <p>Istanbul's most luxurious hotel is the Kempinski Ciragan Palace Hotel, beautifully situated on the Bosporus at Ciragan Caddesi 84, Besiktas, but far from the center of town. Standard doubles are $300 to $400 (on the water side); suites are $750 to $3,500; (90-212) 258-3377, fax (90-212) 259-6687.</p>
        <p>The Marmara Istanbul, on Taksim Square, offers a ringside seat at the heart of the city, and one of the city's best fitness centers. Doubles are $260 including tax; suites $390 to $1,000, for the presidential suite, which has a stunning view of the Bosporus, Sea of Marmara and Golden Horn; (90-212) 251-4696, fax (90-212) 244-0509.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Istanbul offers hundreds of places to eat, from streetside doner kebab stands to elegant restaurants. A visitor can eat well, if simply, for $10 or less a person, at 667,000 lira to the dollar.</p>
        <p>No restaurant can top the view from Sunset Grill and Bar, Adnan Saygun Caddesi, Yol Sokak 2, overlooking the Bosporus in Ulus Park. It offers modern Turkish cuisine and sushi. The lamb shank wrapped in eggplant is outstanding. Dinner for two with wine, roughly $70. Reservations necessary; (90-212) 286-0357.</p>
        <p>A more intimate view of the Bosporus is available from a seaside table at Rumeli Iskele, Yahya Kemal Caddesi 1, a popular and expensive fish restaurant near the historic Rumeli Fortress. Fresh fish is served at market prices (the grilled squid is wonderful). Dinner for two with wine, $80. Reservations recommended; (90-212) 263-2997.</p>
        <p>Uludag, Istanbul Caddesi 12, is in Florya, a picturesque village on the Sea of Marmara about 30 minutes from the city center. Traditional meat dishes like Iskender kebab, a combination of meat, bread and sauces, are highlights. Dinner for two with wine, $40; (90-212) 624-9590.</p>
        <p>What to See</p>
        <p>Topkapi Palace, Babihumayun Caddesi, Sultanahmet, (90-212) 512-0480, is open daily except Tuesday 8:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Admission, $4.</p>
        <p>The Archeological Museum, on the palace grounds, (90-212) 520-7740, is open daily except Monday 9:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Admission, $5.</p>
        <p>Enter the Basilica Cistern, at 13 Yerebatan Caddesi, Sultanahmet; (90-212) 522-1259. Hours: 9 a.m. to 5:30 p.m. daily. Entry, $4.</p>
        <p>Hagia Sophia, Ayasofya Meydani, Sultanahmet, (90-212) 522-1750 charges $5 admission. The museum is open 9:30 a.m. to 4:30 p.m. Closed Monday.</p>
        <p>Like all of the Muslim places of worship, the Blue Mosque, Sultanahmet Meydani, Sultanahmet, (90-212) 518-1319, is always open and there is no entry fee. Proper attire is required, especially for women, and a donation is customary.</p>
        <p>The Suleymaniye Mosque is surrounded by charming shops in the heart of the old city at Prof. Siddik Sami Onar Caddesi, Sultanahmet; (90-212) 514-0139.</p>
        <p>The Grand Bazaar on Carsikapi Caddesi in the Beyazit district is open 9 a.m. to 7 p.m.; closed Sunday. Its smaller cousin, the Spice Bazaar, is on Cami Meydani Sokak and open 8 a.m. to 7 p.m., except Sunday.</p>
        <p>Municipal ferry boats leave Eminonu dock No. 3 daily at 10:35 a.m., noon and 1:35 p.m. and return from a round trip up the Bosporus four to five hours later, depending on how often you stop. The fare is about $3.</p>
        <p>Lufer boats carry 20 to 80 people and leave from Bebek, north of the city, at 7:30 p.m. The fixed menu includes four types of grilled meat and unlimited beverages. The fare runs $30 to $40 a person, depending on the size of a group. The minimum rental for an entire boat is about $240.</p>
        <p>DOUGLAS FRANTZ</p>
        <p>DOUGLAS FRANTZ is chief of the Istanbul bureau of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">DOUGLAS FRANTZ is chief of the Istanbul bureau of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
