<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Fairy Defense</title>
    <meta content="08MCCOLLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccullough, David Willis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bourke, Angela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoff, Joan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeates, Marian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cleary, Bridget</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cleary, Michael</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Burning of Bridget Cleary, The: A True Story (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cooper's Wife Is Missing, The: The Trials of Bridget Cleary (Book</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D91E3AF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Fairy Defense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Willis McCullough</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccullough, David Willis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Willis McCullough reviews books The Burning of Bridget Cleary: A True Story by Angela Bourke and The Cooper's Wife Is Missing: The Trials of Bridget Cleary by Joan Hoff and Marian Yeates (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BURNING</p>
        <p>OF BRIDGET CLEARY</p>
        <p>A True Story.</p>
        <p>By Angela Bourke.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 279 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>THE COOPER'S WIFE</p>
        <p>IS MISSING</p>
        <p>The Trials of Bridget Cleary.</p>
        <p>By Joan Hoff and Marian Yeates.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 458 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BURNING</p>
        <p>OF BRIDGET CLEARY</p>
        <p>A True Story.</p>
        <p>By Angela Bourke.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 279 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>THE COOPER'S WIFE</p>
        <p>IS MISSING</p>
        <p>The Trials of Bridget Cleary.</p>
        <p>By Joan Hoff and Marian Yeates.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 458 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $26.</p>
        <p>Did anyone ever consider the death of Bridget Cleary to be a simple matter of a husband killing his wife? The story was well known. It was covered, often in minute detail, in newspapers throughout Ireland and England. And with good reason: from the very beginning, a few days before St. Patrick's Day in 1895, when Bridget was reported missing from her home in rural Tipperary, there were attention-grabbing aspects of the case, details that indicated this wasn't just another murder. Michael Cleary, who made his living as a cooper, first claimed that his wife had been taken off by the fairies. Before her badly charred body was found in a shallow grave, he insisted that the woman called Bridget was not really his wife but a changeling that had been substituted in her place. The real Bridget, he said, would soon be found at a nearby fairy ring riding a white horse.</p>
        <p>As is so often the case in Ireland, there was a political issue involved. Generally, the more a newspaper was against Irish home rule, the more its coverage emphasized all that business about the fairies. How, asked the English and their loyalist Irish friends, could a people who still believed in evil spirits be trusted to govern themselves in the modern world? As for the Irish nationalists, some of whom had been promoting an interest in folklore and legend, the less said about fairies the better. The mutilated body of a country woman was not what William Butler Yeats, Lady Gregory and their circle had in mind when they went out among the poor asking for lyrical stories about wee folk in the heather.</p>
        <p>But there was indeed a body to reckon with, and a lot more murder suspects than just Michael Cleary. Soon there were arrests (nine of them, including that of Michael), followed by trials and prison sentences. The story itself became part of Irish folklore. Bridget Cleary was called ''the last witch burned in Ireland'' and (like America's Lizzie Borden and her ax) she was immortalized in a children's rhyme: ''Are you a witch or are you a fairy, / Or are you the wife of Michael Cleary?''</p>
        <p>Now, more than a century later, in one of those coincidences that seem to happen so often in publishing, two new books set out to analyze both what happened in the Cleary cottage in 1895 and what the outside world made of it. The core of each book is the extensive contemporary newspaper coverage of the case, but each book -- one of which can be considered Irish, the other American -- uses the source material in a very different way. Angela Bourke, author of ''The Burning of Bridget Cleary,'' is a senior lecturer at University College, Dublin, who is especially interested in the folklore elements of the case, and in the psychological and social implications of believing in fairies at the turn of the 20th century. ''The Cooper's Wife Is Missing'' is by Joan Hoff, director of the Contemporary History Institute at the University of Ohio (and the author of ''Nixon Reconsidered'' and ''Law, Gender and Injustice''), and Marian Yeates, who has a Ph.D. in American history. Apparently, their main goal is to present Bridget's death in the larger context of what was happening in Ireland at the time. Bourke's book was published earlier in England, and the American authors have had the advantage of being able to read it and note some points of disagreement.</p>
        <p>Both books suggest that Bridget may have had a secret lover, but suspect different men. Both agree that Bridget was not well even before her husband accused her of being possessed. Bourke thinks Bridget may have had pneumonia, while Hoff and Yeates opt for tuberculosis, which then had a somewhat shameful reputation. Hoff and Yeates see an anti-Catholic strain in the prosecution argument that Bourke doesn't mention. But both books agree on the basic facts of the case as it was revealed in newspaper accounts of the trial testimony.</p>
        <p>The Clearys were not quite like their neighbors. They were childless and, although Bridget was a local girl, they had lived in far larger towns than the nearby villages of Drangan and Cloneen. They may also have been richer than their neighbors. Coopers were well-paid craftsmen, and Bridget brought in extra money as a seamstress (she even owned a Singer sewing machine) and by selling eggs. The key to the mystery about her death lies in what happened during the week or so before she was declared missing. A doctor had been called but did not turn up for several days. A priest arrived promptly and administered the last rites.</p>
        <p>Some sort of trial or ritualistic ordeal seems to have gone on in the Cleary cottage, and it was attended by a substantial number of people. Bridget's father was there, as were her aunt and numerous cousins and neighbors. There was an old man with a knowledge of herbalism and even a true local rarity, a Protestant couple. Bridget was repeatedly asked if she was a fairy and tested to see if she would act like one. She was held over the kitchen fire in an effort to drive the spirit out. At least that was the testimony of the eyewitnesses. The next evening, after the priest returned and said Mass, something less ritualistic happened and Bridget was soon reported missing.</p>
        <p>Bridget herself is a puzzle. When, in the midst of her ordeal, she declared that her husband ''was making a fairy out of me,'' was it a cry for help? Was she simply teasing him? Or did she perhaps believe she was being possessed? When she asked for milk to drink (fairies were known for their fondness for milk) and then pretended to steal the shilling that paid for it (just as a fairy would have done), could she have been mocking her tormentors' fears? Or was it a sign that she was indeed not herself? When she accused Michael of having a mother who had run off with the fairies, was that the final provocation that led to her death (as Bourke suggests) or just a familiar taunt? Was she simply making a macabre joke? Could she have come to believe that she really was a changeling? Depending on what you want to hear, Bridget can seem to be fearful or deluded -- or a high-spirited teaser whose defensive jokes began to sound dangerously like mockery.</p>
        <p>Bourke's tightly constructed and authentically dramatic account sticks close to the details of the case. While acknowledging the political implications of the press coverage of the murder and embarking on a few short detours (such as a glimpse into the trial of Oscar Wilde, taking place at the same time in London), her focus remains on the crime and on the role of folk beliefs in a rural society that was gradually moving from oral tradition into literacy.</p>
        <p>Even with all its meticulous footnotes, there is little that's tidy about ''The Cooper's Wife Is Missing.'' Reading Hoff and Yeates's book might be compared to spending a long and fascinating evening in a busy Tipperary pub. One of the men at the bar is retelling the juicy details of a local murder while the other regulars keep interrupting with stories of their own: about the great Charles Stewart Parnell or the bishop of Cashel, who was unusually outspoken in his nationalism, or a much-loved local poet who had been imprisoned for his anti-English activities or the town of Clonmel's championship rowing team or the tale of a possessed bagpiper -- even about the 1895 St. Patrick's Day parade in Boston.</p>
        <p>It says a lot about Bridget Cleary's enigmatic story that it can bear so much freight, from scholarly folkloric interpretation to breezy social history. ''The Cooper's Wife Is Missing'' has the almost gossipy richness of a sprawling panorama, but it could be exasperating for a reader who expects simply to hear about the chain of events leading up to a bizarre disappearance in rural Ireland. ''The Burning of Bridget Cleary'' is a more powerful reconstruction of the crime, but Bourke might have made a stronger case for the value of folklore research if she had strayed a bit more from the events in the Cleary cottage.</p>
        <p>At the murder trial in the market town of Clonmel, charges against some of the accused were dropped, some reduced. Four of Bridget's neighbors were found guilty of ''wounding'' and given brief sentences. Michael served 15 years for manslaughter, then sailed for Montreal.</p>
        <p>As for the opening question about a simple explanation for Bridget's death, there was one observer who saw it as a perfectly ordinary example of premeditated murder. He was the judge who heard the case in the Clonmel courtroom, and it seems likely that he was the only one there who thought so.</p>
        <p>David Willis McCullough's latest book is a historical anthology, ''Wars of the Irish Kings.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Willis McCullough's latest book is a historical anthology, ''Wars of the Irish Kings.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
