<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Walls Bore Lessons For the Chic</title>
    <meta content="08OWEN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="45" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/arts/08OWEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wallpaper</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biennale International Des Antiquaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Paris (France)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dufour, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Owens, Mitchell</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFD6103DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Walls Bore Lessons For the Chic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MITCHELL OWENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Owens, Mitchell</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mitchell Owens article describes French panoramic wallpaper by Joseph Dufour, on view at Biennale International des Antiquaries in Paris; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EDUCATIONAL toys are commonplace, but what about educational decoration? Believe it or not, there was a time when wallpaper, fabrics and furniture were deemed tools for self-improvement, designed to spur curiosity and comprehension -- among adults as well as children.</p>
        <p>When the eminent French manufacturer Joseph Dufour began producing panoramic wallpapers depicting everything from the monuments of Paris to mythological tales at the turn of the 18th century, he and competitors like Jean-Baptiste Reveillon, Zuber and Jacquemart &amp; Benard were well aware of their products' decorative allure. Panoramic papers, with their blue skies, neo-Classical buildings and flourishing landscapes, visually expanded rooms with cramped floor plans and added an air of grandeur and sophistication suitable to the empire-building times. But Dufour also advertised his expensive, handblocked papers as knowledge-enhancing, a canny marketing decision perfectly attuned to the education-hungry, world-travelling citizens of the Age of Enlightenment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EDUCATIONAL toys are commonplace, but what about educational decoration? Believe it or not, there was a time when wallpaper, fabrics and furniture were deemed tools for self-improvement, designed to spur curiosity and comprehension -- among adults as well as children.</p>
        <p>When the eminent French manufacturer Joseph Dufour began producing panoramic wallpapers depicting everything from the monuments of Paris to mythological tales at the turn of the 18th century, he and competitors like Jean-Baptiste Reveillon, Zuber and Jacquemart &amp; Benard were well aware of their products' decorative allure. Panoramic papers, with their blue skies, neo-Classical buildings and flourishing landscapes, visually expanded rooms with cramped floor plans and added an air of grandeur and sophistication suitable to the empire-building times. But Dufour also advertised his expensive, handblocked papers as knowledge-enhancing, a canny marketing decision perfectly attuned to the education-hungry, world-travelling citizens of the Age of Enlightenment.</p>
        <p>In a room wrapped in a wall-to-wall panorama, Dufour wrote: ''a mother can give her daughter living lessons in history and geography, teaching her to make better use of her education. And even the trees and the flowers will serve as an introduction to botany.''</p>
        <p>One of his finest achievements in this curious hybrid of home-schooling and aesthetic swank was seen at the Biennale Internationale des Antiquaires, which closed here last Sunday. One of the more than 100 participating dealers, Carolle Thibaut-Pomerantz exhibited Dufour's ''Sauvages de la Mer Pacifique,'' the First Empire's largest and most profoundly important papier peint, or handblocked wallpaper. (It is commonly referred to as ''Les Voyages du Captaine Cook.'')</p>
        <p>Based on designs by Jean-Gabriel Charvet and printed in 1804-1805 by Dufour, ''Les Sauvages'' depicts a dreamy landscape populated with the Pacific islanders encountered between 1768 and 1778 by the English explorer James Cook and others. Though largely a happy fantasy of glittering lagoons and a stylish populace whose orderly disportment anticipates Georges Seurat's ''Sunday Afternoon on the Island of the Grand Jatte'' -- more than 220 figures are seen, including a hungry dog scavenging a lunch basket -- it does not shirk from reality. In a scene no larger than the palm of a hand and painted in purposefully discreet tones of gray and white, the 50-year-old Cook and his crew are seen meeting their doom on a distant beach, beneath the clubs and spears of enraged Hawaiians as a smoking volcano ominously towers over the carnage.</p>
        <p>''Hardly anyone ever notices that right away,'' Ms. Thibaut-Pomerantz said, adding that the death could be excised. Panoramas were often cut to fit around a mantlepiece or a window. ''They were made to be adjusted,'' she said, ''so it would be easy enough to edit out bits that one didn't like.''</p>
        <p>Composed of five panels measuring 7 feet high and between 5 feet 2 inches and 8 feet 8 inches wide, the complete set is priced at $250,000.</p>
        <p>The leading dealer in the genre, Ms. Thibaut-Pomerantz is participating in the International Fine Art and Antique Dealer Show at the Seventh Regiment Armory on Park Avenue (East 67th Street). Though she will not be bringing the Cook wallpaper to the show, which opens on Oct. 20 and runs through Oct. 26, she will exhibit other papiers peints, including a set of 1788 Reveillon panels from the collection of the society decorator Henri Samuel. And more of Dufour's work, including his celebrated 1814 ''Monuments of Paris,'' will be seen next May in ''A Room with a View: Landscapes and Wallpaper,'' an exhibition of 200 years of wallpaper design at the Cooper-Hewitt Design Museum in New York.</p>
        <p>Presented to the public in an 1806 exhibit of the best in French manufacturing, Joseph Dufour's Captain Cook panorama was an instant sensation, garnering enough orders for him to move his factory to Paris from the town of Macon, near Lyons. Ms. Thibaut-Pomerantz says probably no more than 50 to 100 sets of the paper were ever manufactured, some ending up in houses in the United States. The one in her possession was commissioned by the owners of a chateau in Provence, where it hung until recently. (Ms. Thibaut-Pomerantz found it at an auction in Paris, tattered and in pieces, and meticulously restored it.) Around 20 complete sets are known to survive, in public and private collections like the National Gallery of Australia in Canberra, which recently held a ''Les Sauvage'' exhibition in collaboration with the Art Gallery of New South Wales.</p>
        <p>''It was an incredibly time-consuming pattern to produce,'' Ms. Thibaut-Pomerantz said of the paper's rarity. More than 1,000 handcut woodblocks were dipped into brown, orange, green, black and blue distemper -- a chalky, waterbased paint -- and painstakingly stamped onto the heavy paper. After all of that, artists touched up the paper by hand, using brushes. From beginning to end, the process could take more than a year.</p>
        <p>Even after all that effort, Dufour's vision of the primitive but noble South Seas was dubious. Despite their feathered headresses and tribal accouterments -- baskets, dugout canoes, smoked fish -- the Pacific islanders look more like courtiers at a Napoleonic levee, right down to the Empire-waisted gowns and fashionable Grecian-style coiffures. And the trio of Tahitian dancers strike balletic poses copied directly from images of the mythological three Graces. Romantic, certainly, even atmospheric, but not particularly accurate.</p>
        <p>''No, it isn't,'' Ms. Thibaut-Pomerantz said, smiling. ''And that's the charm of it.''</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Mitchell Owens is a contributing writer at Architectural Digest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mitchell Owens is a contributing writer at Architectural Digest.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
