<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Operating System</title>
    <meta content="08PONIEWT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Poniewozik, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutschman, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jobs, Steven P</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Second Coming of Steve Jobs, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E3D91E3AF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Operating System</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Poniewozik</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Poniewozik, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Poniewozik reviews book The Second Coming of Steve Jobs by Alan Deutschman (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE SECOND COMING</p>
        <p>OF STEVE JOBS</p>
        <p>By Alan Deutschman.</p>
        <p>321 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Broadway Books. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE SECOND COMING</p>
        <p>OF STEVE JOBS</p>
        <p>By Alan Deutschman.</p>
        <p>321 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Broadway Books. $26.</p>
        <p>In the preface to ''The Second Coming of Steve Jobs,'' Alan Deutschman explains why he chose to profile Apple Computer's founder and C.E.O. Many people, he says, have written overawed articles about Jobs since he returned to Apple in 1996 after nearly 12 years in exile, turning the company from a has-been into a profitable trendsetter and restoring his reputation as a visionary. ''I was looking for Steve Jobs the person rather than Steve Jobs the icon,'' Deutschman writes. ''I set out to discover the deep sources of his character and motivation. I strived to find where he got his unusual ideas about leadership, management and the creative process.''</p>
        <p>This is a rather tactful description, since these ''management'' ideas, the author says, include screaming at employees to the point of hyperventilation, firing a P.R. consultant and refusing to pay her for completed work and taking enough stock options in his animation company, Pixar, to make himself a billionaire while leaving squat for all but a few of its longtime workers. Deutschman gives a truer indication of his quest by quoting the computer industry pundit Stewart Alsop, who posits that the major computer companies that are still run by their founders (Apple, Oracle, etc.) have one thing in common. They're all run by -- to paraphrase Alsop delicately -- complete jerks.</p>
        <p>This is the unspoken question of ''Second Coming'': Just how big a jerk is Steve Jobs? Pretty big, as Deutschman reveals in a study bursting with damning anecdotes, gleaned from interviews with nearly 100 of Jobs's friends and colleagues. Big enough to have refused to support his young daughter, Lisa, financially for years. Big enough to have played a pointlessly cruel practical joke on a nave underling, pretending to offer him the position of Apple C.E.O. Big enough to park his Mercedes in the handicapped spaces at Apple.</p>
        <p>In ''Second Coming,'' which examines the period from Jobs's ouster in 1985 to today, Deutschman, a contributing editor at Vanity Fair, links Jobs's business innovations and personal failings -- the ''insanely great'' products emerging from a great insanity. (Jobs has already assailed the book as a hatchet job.) That Jobs is less than a sweetheart is old news; and it would hardly be interesting if not for the nature of his success. Even technophiles probably care little about the real character of, say, Michael Dell. But Apple and Jobs have long received attention far out of proportion to the company's market share because, more than hardware and software, Apple makes symbols. At its peaks under Jobs, it sold its loyal users an image of themselves. In 1984, the graphics-based (rather than text-based) Macintosh made computing accessible. In 1998, the fruit-colored iMac epitomized today's cultural symbiosis of work and entertainment, enshrining a business tool as an artwork.</p>
        <p>In other words, an utter jerk helped change society by making computers known for their niceness. Steve Jobs did not succeed so much because he made better widgets but because, at some deep level, he understands us. If he is a jerk, he is our jerk. To understand Jobs, then, is to understand not just his personality -- vain, petulant, cruel, yet irresistibly seductive even to those he abuses most -- but his aesthetic.</p>
        <p>It is an aesthetic, Deutschman writes, influenced heavily by modernism and a back-to-the-land ethos -- the combo of spareness, sanctimony and gourmandism now de rigueur at better housewares and fine-foods stores across America. (Jobs wanted the original Apple computers to come in cases made of beautiful blond koa wood.) It was an outgrowth of Jobs's embrace of 60's counterculturalism -- he was a longtime, and rather irritating, vegetarian and lived in a commune. Yet he came of age after these movements were hip or cutting-edge. ''By the time Steve tried LSD,'' Deutschman notes, ''suburban housewives were reading 'The Electric Kool-Aid Acid Test.' ''</p>
        <p>In fact, Deutschman's most damning charge is really this: The aesthete and visionary who saw himself and his engineers as artists is at best a popularizer, at worst a poseur. Driven by ''an innate sense of the importance of aesthetics,'' he was painfully insecure in his tastes, compensating by making safe choices and spending a lot of money. He furnished his home in Spartan chic fashion -- some handmade wooden furniture in the Craftsman style, a $100,000 stereo, a Persian rug'' -- as if to risk as few errors as possible.</p>
        <p>Harnessed properly, this attitude made him a business success. He became not so much an artist as a connoisseur -- an artist of spending money, skilled at bargaining and obsessed with hiring the best. When he adapted his spare aesthetic to mass tastes, the results were the original Macintosh and the iMac. Pixar, which made the hit ''Toy Story'' movies, made Jobs rich -- and possibly saved his career -- precisely because he left its artists alone in its crucial early years. But, the author writes, when he let his perfectionist aesthetic run unchecked at Next, the computer company he founded after leaving Apple, he failed monumentally, building a powerful $6,500 machine that many admired but few bought. A sleek, black cube, it was ''elegant, yes, but . . . intimidating, even forbidding.''</p>
        <p>That is, it was Steve Jobs rendered in silicon. Deutschman's Jobs is an irresistibly charming man who can turn on a dime to cruelty, a man practically alien in his ignorance of civil niceties. Unfortunately, for all of Deutschman's well-chosen anecdotes, we never get a sense of how Jobs came to be this way. We read that he was adopted but learn little of his childhood; we see much of his behavior but only glimpses of his feelings.</p>
        <p>This may not be the author's fault; if the ''intensely private'' Jobs has ever opened up to anyone, he or she hasn't talked to Deutschman. In fact, he practically recommends supplemental reading: the novel ''A Regular Guy,'' by Mona Simpson (Jobs's biological sister, whom he discovered as an adult), a thinly veiled biography that captures ''the emotional and psychological truths about Steve.'' Deutschman, with all his research, finally seems to throw up his hands, drawing uninspired conclusions like ''he is a man of great contrasts and contradictions.''</p>
        <p>But he also avoids the pat ending, so common in comeback stories, in which the subject must be shown to have changed. Deutschman does credit Jobs with going through a humble phase after Next's failure, but by the end of ''Second Coming,'' ensconced as Apple's savior and a Hollywood player, he is again humiliating underlings and, yes, parking in the handicapped spaces.</p>
        <p>James Poniewozik is the television critic for Time magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Poniewozik is the television critic for Time magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
