<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Evanston, Ill., a Downtown Revitalization</title>
    <meta content="08AFOC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Evanston (Ill)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chanen, Jill Schachner</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE3DC1E3DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1341" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Evanston, Ill., a Downtown Revitalization</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JILL SCHACHNER CHANEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chanen, Jill Schachner</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes downtown residential and commercial revitalization project in Evanston, Ill; photo; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER languishing for more than 10 years, downtown Evanston, Ill., is experiencing a threefold increase in development this year with an estimated $200 million worth of new residential and commercial projects under way.</p>
        <p>Five buildings with a total of more than 350 condominium apartments have been started this year in the downtown area of this north shore Chicago suburb, which is perhaps best known as the home of Northwestern University, and two more buildings are planned. This is up sharply from 29 apartments last year and a total of 167 over the last five years, according to city officials. ''Ordinarily, in a good construction season, throughout the city we will see about $70 million worth of construction, which includes residential, commercial and university,'' said James Wolinski, director of  Evanston's Department of Building and Zoning. ''This year it's $200 million.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER languishing for more than 10 years, downtown Evanston, Ill., is experiencing a threefold increase in development this year with an estimated $200 million worth of new residential and commercial projects under way.</p>
        <p>Five buildings with a total of more than 350 condominium apartments have been started this year in the downtown area of this north shore Chicago suburb, which is perhaps best known as the home of Northwestern University, and two more buildings are planned. This is up sharply from 29 apartments last year and a total of 167 over the last five years, according to city officials. ''Ordinarily, in a good construction season, throughout the city we will see about $70 million worth of construction, which includes residential, commercial and university,'' said James Wolinski, director of  Evanston's Department of Building and Zoning. ''This year it's $200 million.''</p>
        <p>Developers say the new residential development in Evanston is, in part, an outgrowth of a condominium boom in downtown Chicago, which is only 15 miles to the south. Buyers in downtown Chicago, where over 6,000 new condominium apartments have been built in the last five years, are paying upward of $275 per square foot for newly constructed condominium apartments. Evanston developers say they are taking advantage of the demand for condominium apartments and marketing their apartments to would-be city purchasers at prices that are lower by $50 to $75 per square foot. In Evanston, one-bedroom apartments are selling for an average price of $148,000, while a two-bedroom is selling for an average of $215,000.</p>
        <p>Also drawing buyers is the infusion of new commercial activity in downtown Evanston, including a soon-to-be-completed 18-screen movie theater, a Hilton Gardens hotel and more than 250,000 square feet of retail space, which will be anchored by a new Sears department store.</p>
        <p>Evanston is an ethnically diverse city that has long attracted a mix of affluent families and young single professionals because of its urban feel in a suburban setting along the shores of Lake Michigan and because of its proximity to downtown Chicago. The city's downtown, however, did not keep pace. In the mid-1980's, the Marshall Field's department store in Evanston was closed, leaving behind a smattering of small retail shops, restaurants and old office buildings. The department store's building was turned into a mixed-use development of loft apartments and retail spaces.</p>
        <p>Three years ago the city of Evanston set the stage for the downtown area's revitalization when it modified plans to convert a parcel of downtown land into a high-tech research park. The land was previously used as a sanitation yard and for storage facilities for the city and Northwestern University. Though four research buildings were built on the property, the city decided to use the remainder of the land for a mixed-use development to help infuse new life into the downtown. The property is now the site of the new movie theater complex, hotel and a soon-to-be-built residential high-rise building.</p>
        <p>WHEN they made the decision to change the research park, it was significant,'' said Jim Klutznick, a principal in Sherman Plaza Venture, a development partnership that plans to raze nearly an entire city block in the center of downtown and rebuild it with the 250,000 square feet of retail space that includes Sears. The project will also include an upscale 200-unit senior citizen's apartment building that will be operated by the Senior Lifestyle Corporation of Chicago. Construction of the retail space and parking lot is scheduled to being next spring and be completed by early 2002. Construction on the seniors' residence is to begin in 2002, according to Mr. Klutznick.</p>
        <p>Mr. Klutznick, like other developers, said that without these new commercial and retail developments, the residential projects might not have drawn as much interest.</p>
        <p>Thomas Roszak, a residential developer with three current projects in Evanston, agrees. ''Downtown Evanston has really started to rejuvenate in the last five years with Starbucks, Barnes &amp; Noble, brick paving on the sidewalks and new landscaping,'' he said. ''You throw that all into the pot, and it really is a fabulous place to live.''</p>
        <p>He recently sold every apartment in a 31-unit condominium building on Sherman Avenue at the southern tip of Evanston's downtown. The building occupies a once-vacant parcel that fronted the railroad tracks for the city's elevated train line. Prices for the units ranged from $118,000 for a 811-square-foot one-bedroom apartment to $274,000 for a 1,840-square-foot three-bedroom, two-bathroom apartment, according to Mr. Roszak, principal of Roszak ADC in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Roszak is completing the construction of a 23-unit condominium apartment building on a property adjacent to his other project. All but two of those units have sales contracts, he said. Prices range from $153,000 for a 805-square-foot one-bedroom apartment to $445,000 for a 2,325-square-foot three-bedroom, two-bathroom apartment.</p>
        <p>Later this year Mr. Roszak will begin construction on a 156-unit condominium apartment building just a couple of blocks from his other buildings. Mr. Roszak is selling these apartments in phases and, so far, 25 of the 54 units in the first phase are sold. Prices in this building range from $132,000 for a 600-square-foot studio apartment to $354,000 for a 1,625-square-foot three-bedroom, two-bathroom apartment.</p>
        <p>This building, called Chicago Avenue Place, will also have a doorman and an indoor pool. Mr. Roszak said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roszak believes that downtown Evanston is starting to lure buyers from Chicago because property is more affordable  and the city now has more to offer its residents. ''If you can get an apartment that is 10 percent to 15 percent less, people will make the move here because Evanston is so geographically close to Chicago,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Janis Battle, 53, a widowed empty nester, bought one of the three-bedroom apartments in Mr. Roszak's first project after debating whether to move into Chicago. Price was not an issue for her, but lifestyle was. She moved to Evanston this year from Wilmette, a neighboring suburb to the north of Evanston, after selling her single-family house there.</p>
        <p>''I felt more comfortable living in Evanston because it had all the advantages of an urban lifestyle without all the congestion of the city,'' she said. ''The other thing I like about living in Evanston is that it is pretty easy to develop a sense of community here. When I go into Starbucks, they know what I drink. I know the soup guy. You can get to know your neighborhood and recognize people on the street.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Battle fits the demographics of potential buyers for another new condominium apartment building that is part of a mixed-use development just blocks away from her building. Developers of the project at 515 Main Street expected to draw empty nesters from Evanston and neighboring suburbs as well as young first-time buyers looking for better values than they could find in the city of Chicago. Almost half of the buyers have come from within a five-block radius of the building, said Steven Maher, a sales agent with Garrison Partners of Chicago, which is marketing the building.</p>
        <p>The nine-story building will offer street level retail space anchored by a bank, indoor parking and 63 apartments spread out over the top seven floors. Prices range from $150,000 for a 900-square-foot one-bedroom apartment to $350,000 for a 1,500-square-foot three-bedroom apartment, Mr. Maher said.</p>
        <p>Construction is under way, with first move-ins expected in the spring. All 63 apartments in the building are sold</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
