<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Again, Protecting the Barrens From a House in the Bogs</title>
    <meta content="08MAP.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE MAP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pine Barrens (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature Conservancy</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">White, J J, Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heasly, Anne E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nash, Margo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Elizabeth C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2DD163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Again, Protecting the Barrens From a House in the Bogs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGO NASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nash, Margo</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anne E Heasly, local Nature Conservancy official, answers questions about New Jersey chapter's new office in Pine Barrens, in former residence of Elizabeth C White, whose family owned J J White Inc cranberry growers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two months ago the New Jersey Chapter of the Nature Conservancy opened an office in the Pine Barrens, in Whitesbog, a hamlet where employees of the cranberry grower J. J.White Inc.  lived until the 1940's.  The building was the Arts and Crafts-style residence of Elizabeth C. White, whose family owned the business and were among the first to cultivate cranberries commercially in the Pine Barrens. She was also a conservationist and  gardener. Now her house, called Suningive, nurtures the Conservancy's new effort to protect the 1.4 million acres of the Pine Barrens, which the Conservancy calls one of ''America's Last Great Places.'' Anne E. Heasly, assistant state director of the New Jersey Chapter of the Nature Conservancy and director of the group's Pine Barrens Program Office, spoke from the new quarters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two months ago the New Jersey Chapter of the Nature Conservancy opened an office in the Pine Barrens, in Whitesbog, a hamlet where employees of the cranberry grower J. J.White Inc.  lived until the 1940's.  The building was the Arts and Crafts-style residence of Elizabeth C. White, whose family owned the business and were among the first to cultivate cranberries commercially in the Pine Barrens. She was also a conservationist and  gardener. Now her house, called Suningive, nurtures the Conservancy's new effort to protect the 1.4 million acres of the Pine Barrens, which the Conservancy calls one of ''America's Last Great Places.'' Anne E. Heasly, assistant state director of the New Jersey Chapter of the Nature Conservancy and director of the group's Pine Barrens Program Office, spoke from the new quarters.</p>
        <p>Q. Can you see cranberry bogs from your office?</p>
        <p>Q. I have an office on the second floor, and I look out on those bogs.  Elizabeth White talked about the bogs as being her lawn.</p>
        <p>Q. How isolated is your office?</p>
        <p>A. It takes 25 minutes to get here from the turnpike or the Garden State Parkway. There's a core village and a road that goes east and a couple of houses out on that. In the last 56 years, a lot of trees have grown up around Elizabeth White's house since she died. The house now is much more isolated. At one point the New Jersey Conservation Organization had an office here, and the Pineland Preservation Alliance was here until they moved out 10 years ago. So there's sort of a history of conservation groups being here.</p>
        <p>Q. Why did you open an office in the Pine Barrens?</p>
        <p>A. The Conservancy wants to preserve eight key ecological communities here including oak-pine forest, dwarf pine plains and Atlantic white cedar swamp. We're looking forward to building on our accomplishments in the region and to working more closely with local landowners and other partners. We have offices in every state, and we've had an office in New Jersey since 1988 in Chester, which is what we call the chapter office. About five years ago we also established an office in the Delaware Bay Shores area, and we found that  people came to us there, that landowners interested in selling a piece of land would call us, and that if a local conservation organization was doing an event, they would ask us to take part. We are a landowner in these communities, and we found that by participating in the life of the community like you would if you had a house on a property, it just really helps people to put a face on the Conservancy and to advance our conservation work.</p>
        <p>Q. What would the conservancy's role be here?</p>
        <p>A. There are some big areas that are in state ownership. That's one of the reasons why the Pine Barrens is what the Nature Conservancy would call a functioning ecosystem and  landscape where the natural process that shaped it -- the fire, the water, the soil -- are still working. There are a lot of people who have been working here already. The Pinelands Preservation Alliance has been working here very effectively, ensuring that the comprehensive management plan of the Pinelands Commission is followed, and we want to do what we do best, which is land acquisition.</p>
        <p>Q. What's left of Elizabeth's White's garden?</p>
        <p>A. People have been working to restore it. There's a little formal garden that opens into a larger lawn and, around that there are pines and oak. To the west there was a garden where she had wetland plants. That has kind of grown in so we are soliciting volunteers to remove some of the saplings and restore that portion.</p>
        <p>MARGO NASH</p>
        <p>ON THE MAP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
