<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Something to Offend Everyone</title>
    <meta content="08SCHONET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shone, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Self, Will</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">How the Dead Live (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E3D91E3AF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Something to Offend Everyone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Tom Shone</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shone, Tom</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tom Shone reviews novel How the Dead Live by Will Self; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How the Dead Live</p>
        <p>By Will Self.</p>
        <p>404 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Grove Press. $24.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How the Dead Live</p>
        <p>By Will Self.</p>
        <p>404 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Grove Press. $24.</p>
        <p>WILL SELF'S new novel consists of a monologue by a Jewish mother who goes by the name of Bloom. So naturally, the first thing you do upon picking up the book is flick to the final page to see what the last word is. And sure enough, instead of ''yes'' -- the word used by James Joyce to end ''Ulysses'' -- we find the contemporary negative ''Not,'' as used by Mike Myers in his canonical postmodern masterpiece, ''Wayne's World.'' A serious literary allusion, or a snickering joke? A dialogue with a classic or mere punkish self-adornment -- the literary equivalent of Johnny Rotten wearing a T-shirt of Queen Elizabeth? Practiced Self readers will know that the answer is all of the above, with a good helping of impudence thrown in for good measure.</p>
        <p>High horses, of course, should be kept under tight rein; and Joyce devotees keen to take offense ought to know that they will have to join a pretty long line. Among those who may take umbrage at Self's new book are: cancer sufferers, relatives of cancer sufferers, Jews both self-hating and regular, addicts, members of Alcoholics Anonymous, English doctors, nurses, stockbrokers and just about anyone, for that matter, who lives in any London suburb or who has ever bought lace curtains. Anyone not covered by the above will simply have to sit tight and hope for better luck next time.</p>
        <p>''How the Dead Live'' is narrated by one Lily Bloom, an American lying in a hospital in London, dying of cancer, although narrates is putting it politely: it's like saying the Ancient Mariner has a few things he'd like to share with us. Using her hospital bed as her pulpit, she discourses with haggard intensity on the iniquities in her life: on the tawdriness of the London suburbs, where she has spent the majority of her life marooned; on her drug addict daughter Natasha, busy snaffling what she can of her mother's prescription drugs; and on the cancer that is slowly eating her up. On Page 151 the cancer finally finishes the job, although that doesn't stop Lily for a second: ''The city is an encrustation upon a scab, cigarette ash flicked on to cigar ash. . . .'' and on she rattles -- unstoppable even in death -- with 250 pages still to go.</p>
        <p>Lily is met on the other side -- as one so often is on these occasions -- by an aboriginal spirit guide called Phar Lap Jones, who takes her on an exhaustive tour of the afterlife, which turns out to be much like life except with even more petty bureacracy. The dead float around the same colorless streets, take jobs in the same public relations firms and commute from chloroformed suburbs. It's a quietly horrifying conceit, one that Self first explored in his short story ''The North London Book of the Dead'' -- in which the dead are shown not ascending to another astral plane but simply moving to an even more remote London suburb.</p>
        <p>I'm not sure, however, that the idea wasn't best served first time around: visions of vast, numbing eternity and skills of concision are handy bedfellows. There are some great jokes in here; I loved the 12-step program for the ''Personally Dead'' (''Grant me the stupidity to deny there's anything I cannot change, the temerity to neglect the things I can, and the ignorance to be incapable of distinguishing between the two'') but, as usual with Self's novels, the conceit rides roughshod over such small matters as character and plot. Self fleshes Lily out with memories, a childhood, an ex-husband, a job or two, but the effort seems to hang perpendicularly to his talents -- the construction of an entire life, just so we can get to the punch line of her death -- and elsewhere Self seems more than content to let the drag act slip, and his hairy imaginings sprout forth: ''Five a.m., and the human collectivity is rubbing the gunge of urbanity from its filmy eyes'' and emitting ''the gas of lack-of-utility, and yawning asthmatically as it struggles to inhale another day.'' My, Grandma, what extended metaphors you use!</p>
        <p>If the aim is to suggest suave world-weariness, the effect is the exact opposite. Instead, we sense a schoolboy eagerness, tripping over itself in the rush to register disdain. Self has always given the impression of a man who intends to elope with his thesaurus at the first available opportunity; on the evidence of ''How the Dead Live,'' that opportunity has finally presented itself. We get pointless reiterations (''unbeatable gloating, unbelievable schadenfreude''); we get the word ''puling'' twice in eight pages, which, for a book that invokes Joyce, will not do; and we get wave after wave of viscous imagery (''congealed reality . . . blubbery blancmange of an evidence''). Throw this book at a wall and it will stick. After a while you simply grow bored, and end up inverting Self's images just for the hell of it; every time he compared the city to ''an encrustation upon a scab,'' or a person to a ''diseased yolk,'' I substituted instead ''wedding cake,'' or ''buttercup petal,'' and ended up with prose just an inch shy of that in a Harlequin romance. That's the problem with rococo disgust: take away the disgust and you turn into Barbara Cartland.</p>
        <p>Self's writing is, in other words, a handy illustration of the close link between cynic and sentimentalist. The person who looks at the world and sees nothing but pustulation is no better or worse -- philosophically speaking -- than the person who looks at the world and sees nothing but puppy dogs. As guides to the world they are equally reliable, which is to say not reliable at all. Self is writing literature, of course, not philosophy, and anyone using his work as a map deserves our every sympathy. More to the point, perhaps, is the way such cynicism flattens a writer's responses to the world: the snot that ''spews'' from the nose of a child grieving for her mother has no more emotive charge than the light that ''spews'' from a lamp. This is Will Self, of course, so heartlessness comes with the territory -- you feel wimpy and emotional for even raising the point. But you do wonder whether one day he will have the courage to turn the tables on that heartlessness -- to subject it to the same pitiless rigor with which he currently allows it to scour the world.</p>
        <p>Tom Shone is a staff writer at Talk magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Tom Shone is a staff writer at Talk magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
