<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Thing Dynasty</title>
    <meta content="HD4T" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="106" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernett, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tick, Suzanne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ive, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crasset, Matali</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Birsel, Ayse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sperlein, Bodo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mihm, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D9143BF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Thing Dynasty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Mihm</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mihm, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Mihm article on futuristic designers Jeffrey Bernett, Suzanne Tick, Jonathan Ive, Matali Crasset, Ayse Birsel and Bodo Sperlein; photos (special section, Home Design) (part 2 of 2-part section) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jeffrey Bernett Studio B, New York</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Bernett, opposite, 36, likes to get his hands dirty. ''I used to race motorcycles as a kid,'' he says, ''so I knew my way around a machine shop. That started my appreciation for design.'' And it has resulted in products as diverse as the luxurious Tulip chair for B&amp;B Italia and the mass-market Daisy doormat for Authentics. Before becoming a designer, Bernett, who started Studio B in 1995, toyed with the idea of a career in finance. But after the Wall Street crash of 1987, he drifted west to Colorado to ski. Another crash -- Bernett broke his back on the slopes -- provoked another career crisis. He enrolled in a design workshop in Aspen, where one of his teachers was the director of Parnham College, a crafts-based furniture school in England. Bernett signed up at Parnham shortly after, but found his Modernist sympathies at odds with the school's traditional ethos. He left after a year, but not before designing an umbrella stand -- part of a collection that won the editors' award for decorative accessories at the International Contemporary Furniture Fair in 1996 -- that is now made by the Italian manufacturer Cappellini. Other European clients followed, including Ligne Roset, who makes the magazine rack shown in the foreground opposite. In a nod to his sporting roots, Bernett now wants to design athletic equipment. ''I have a lot of knowledge of skiing in particular,'' he quips.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jeffrey Bernett Studio B, New York</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Bernett, opposite, 36, likes to get his hands dirty. ''I used to race motorcycles as a kid,'' he says, ''so I knew my way around a machine shop. That started my appreciation for design.'' And it has resulted in products as diverse as the luxurious Tulip chair for B&amp;B Italia and the mass-market Daisy doormat for Authentics. Before becoming a designer, Bernett, who started Studio B in 1995, toyed with the idea of a career in finance. But after the Wall Street crash of 1987, he drifted west to Colorado to ski. Another crash -- Bernett broke his back on the slopes -- provoked another career crisis. He enrolled in a design workshop in Aspen, where one of his teachers was the director of Parnham College, a crafts-based furniture school in England. Bernett signed up at Parnham shortly after, but found his Modernist sympathies at odds with the school's traditional ethos. He left after a year, but not before designing an umbrella stand -- part of a collection that won the editors' award for decorative accessories at the International Contemporary Furniture Fair in 1996 -- that is now made by the Italian manufacturer Cappellini. Other European clients followed, including Ligne Roset, who makes the magazine rack shown in the foreground opposite. In a nod to his sporting roots, Bernett now wants to design athletic equipment. ''I have a lot of knowledge of skiing in particular,'' he quips.</p>
        <p>Suzanne Tick Knoll Textiles, New York</p>
        <p>''Most people in textiles don't know how to make a yarn,'' Suzanne Tick, right, says incredulously. A weaver by training, she's fascinated by fiber, thread and ''the technical side of things.''</p>
        <p>Tick, 41, got her start while studying for her fine-arts degree at the University of Iowa. ''Weaving was in the home-economics department,'' she says. ''Eventually the art department let me have a loom.''</p>
        <p>Before joining Knoll Textiles, for which she is the creative director, Tick worked for the fabric manufacturer Boris Kroll, developed a collection of fabrics for the Groundworks division of Lee Jofa and formed her own carpet company, Tuva Looms. A 1998 show at the Museum of Modern Art showcased her experiments with Japanese steel yarn, which Tick had fashioned into shimmering curtains.</p>
        <p>In June, Knoll Textiles introduced Imago, a line of translucent panels made from woven fibers encapsulated in clear resin. Developed by Tick and Ray Goodson, an entrepreneur and aerospace engineer, this material can be used for everything from screens and panels to wall coverings, table tops, shelving and even marker boards. As a divider, it admits light while also affording privacy.</p>
        <p>Tick is currently playing with light in other ways. ''I'm interested right now in objects like surfboards and scooters and how the light reflects off them,'' she says. Coming soon: a silk carpet for Tufenkian that she describes as ''totally luminous, unlike anything you've ever seen.''</p>
        <p>''My philosophy,'' she says, ''is that the world doesn't need another fabric or carpet unless there's something unique about it.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Ive Apple, Cupertino, Calif.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Ive, left, 33, loves simplicity. ''I'm not talking about simplicity as style,'' he says. ''I'm talking about a simpler product to assemble and use. That's what informed the Cube.''</p>
        <p>He's talking about the Power Mac G4 Cube, of course, the latest in a series of technological marvels from Apple, for which he is the vice president of industrial design. ''There's too much visual clutter in our lives,'' he says. ''We went in the opposite direction, utterly serene and utterly quiet.''</p>
        <p>That sums up Ive, who speaks in measured tones and is modest to the point of self-deprecation. The son of a British silversmith (''I never grew my craft skills to the level of my father's," he laments), he studied design at Newcastle Polytechnic. After graduating, he designed ceramic washtubs and basins for Ideal Standard and soon began consulting for Apple.</p>
        <p>The challenge of designing a computer, he says, is that you can't fall back on centuries of examples for inspiration. ''When you look at a wash basin, you know what it is,'' he observes. ''But when you look at a circuit board, you don't understand it, and maybe even are frightened of it.''</p>
        <p>Intrigued by that challenge, Ive joined Apple in 1992, only to see the company lose its way in the wake of Steve Jobs's departure. ''We kept doing provocative studies that gathered dust,'' he recalls. Then Jobs returned, and Ive found himself in charge of the iMac, the symbol of the company's resurgence.</p>
        <p>''There is not a detail of the iMac that doesn't have a reason to be there,'' he says fondly. ''It's all about removing the unnecessary.''</p>
        <p>Matali Crasset Paris</p>
        <p>Matali Crasset, right, 35, is a master of reinvention, transforming the detritus of modern life into iconic objects. Born in a tiny village in Champagne, France, she attended Les Ateliers E.N.S.C.I. in Paris. While a student there, she cut her hair into her signature bob.</p>
        <p>After graduation she landed a job with Philippe Starck, designing for Thomson Multimedia, a European manufacturer of consumer electronics. Her whimsical, curvaceous radios and televisions did away with what Crasset derisively terms the ''black box'' paradigm.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, she struck out on her own. ''Many designers make things for the world,'' she observes. ''Instead, I started making things for my friends.'' Her guest bed, for example, is named ''When Jim Goes to Paris.''</p>
        <p>It is Crasset's humblest design, however, that has garnered the most attention. Digestions, her new product line for the Italian furniture maker Edra, transforms the plaid plastic shopping bags found in immigrant neighborhoods in Paris into foam-filled sofas, chairs and tables.</p>
        <p>A sense of playfulness pervades her work. ''I don't like to make oppressive decorations,'' she says. ''I designed the foam-filled bags to allow people to create their own space.''</p>
        <p>As Crasset sees it, she's less a designer than a collaborator. This fall she'll use that philosophy in helping wooden clog makers in rural France find new designs for their age-old skills. ''I don't want to impose anything on them,'' Crasset says. ''Designers need to work more on evolution and less on revolution.''</p>
        <p>Ayse Birsel Olive 1:1, New York</p>
        <p>When Ayse (pronounced EYE-sha) Birsel, opposite, was a teenager, a great-uncle in her native Turkey told her, ''Even though your husband and family will be there for you, you have to know how to take care of yourself.''</p>
        <p>Birsel, 36, took him at his word. She set up her own company in 1997, and, with her Resolve collection for Herman Miller, she is one of the rare women to have designed a line of office furniture for a major manufacturer. And it's a far cry from the sterile cubicles that fill most offices: everything about it echoes the natural world, from the petal-like canopies to the honeycomb-shaped work spaces. ''That's the structure nature uses,'' Birsel explains.</p>
        <p>It was her feminine perspective that catapulted Birsel to prominence five years ago with her design for the Zo Washlet, a combination toilet-bidet for the Japanese bathroom-fixture giant Toto. The Zo features a deodorizing fan and a heated, snap-on seat. ''I wanted it to be easy to clean,'' she says. At first, Toto's all-male design and engineering staff dismissed the detachable-seat idea. Realizing that none of them had ever cleaned a toilet, Birsel made it their homework assignment. They returned chastened, and Birsel got her way.</p>
        <p>Birsel has a host of new products in the works, including a version of Resolve for the dot-com set and a plastic sink inspired by the geometries of the Brazilian architect Oscar Niemeyer.</p>
        <p>She is fond of saying that ''design is kind of like bringing a child to life.'' At this rate, she'll have a bigger family than most.</p>
        <p>Bodo Sperlein London</p>
        <p>Bodo Sperlein, left, isn't pleased -- about the status of ceramics in the design world. ''People don't give it the respect it deserves,'' he says. ''It has a brown-rice, hippie reputation.'' Sperlein, 34, who prefers Burberry to Birkenstock, hopes to change all that.</p>
        <p>Sperlein came late to design. Born in Germany, he spent most of his 20's working as a translator in London. When it came time to furnish his own flat, he couldn't afford high-quality dishes and so decided to make them himself, enrolling in a local pottery class. ''I was the youngest one there,'' he recalls. ''It was full of grannies.''</p>
        <p>Hooked, Sperlein went back for more, eventually getting his degree at London's Camberwell College of Arts. He soon landed a contract with Nymphenburg, one of Germany's oldest and most established porcelain houses. Sperlein's minimalist pieces are a radical departure from Nymphenburg's famously ornate china and figurines. Indeed, some of his designs are subtle to the point of ambiguity. A tapas plate doubles as an ashtray; a sake beaker works as a bud vase; an espresso cup becomes a toothbrush holder.</p>
        <p>''Multifunctionality is very important to me,'' Sperlein notes.</p>
        <p>Much of his recent work incorporates a composite of bone china and synthetic resin that enables Sperlein to create thin, translucent ceramic sheets like the ones found in his ethereal lighting fixtures. ''I love it when materials are pushed to their limits,'' he says.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
