<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mural From the 30's Is Given Rebirth</title>
    <meta content="08OPOP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Works Progress Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daugherty, James (1887-1974)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daugherty, Charles</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruice, Valerie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putnam, Israel (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EEDA1E3DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mural From the 30's Is Given Rebirth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VALERIE CRUICE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cruice, Valerie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Restored mural created by Works Progress Administration artist James Daugherty, depicting life and times of General Israel Putnam of Connecticut, is unveiled at reading room of library in Greenwich, Conn; artist's son, Charles, 86, attends ceremony; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Colonial American hero General Israel Putnam is said to have slayed a vicious wolf in Pomfret, narrowly escaped a burning at the stake by Indians, led his militia in the Battle of Bunker Hill, and dodged the British in Greenwich by riding his white horse down a steep set of stone steps.</p>
        <p>But for the last 60 years Greenwich's favorite Revolutionary icon -- depicted in a spectacular mural measuring 9 feet by 22 feet and created by the W.P.A. artist James Daugherty -- was helplessly pummeled by basketballs and volleyballs in an elementary school gymnasium, the canvas having been glued directly onto the plaster wall between two basketball hoops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Colonial American hero General Israel Putnam is said to have slayed a vicious wolf in Pomfret, narrowly escaped a burning at the stake by Indians, led his militia in the Battle of Bunker Hill, and dodged the British in Greenwich by riding his white horse down a steep set of stone steps.</p>
        <p>But for the last 60 years Greenwich's favorite Revolutionary icon -- depicted in a spectacular mural measuring 9 feet by 22 feet and created by the W.P.A. artist James Daugherty -- was helplessly pummeled by basketballs and volleyballs in an elementary school gymnasium, the canvas having been glued directly onto the plaster wall between two basketball hoops.</p>
        <p>James Daugherty's works hang in the Smithsonian Institution in Washington, the Whitney Museum of American Art and the Museum of Modern Art in New York.</p>
        <p>This mural, commissioned by the Town of Greenwich for the First Selectman's office in the old Town Hall as part of the Works Progress Administration in 1935, was moved to the Hamilton Avenue School in 1940 when the Town Hall was renovated. The artist never signed it. Over time, people forgot.</p>
        <p>In 1998, the mural, which is entitled ''The Life and Times of General Israel Putnam of Connecticut,'' was rescued by the Daugherty Archive and restored through the efforts of many. It is insured for $250,000. On a recent afternoon in the reading room of the Cesar Pelli-redesigned Greenwich Library, the more luminous than ever mural was unveiled and displayed for all to see as the late-afternoon sun streamed through the windows.</p>
        <p>Charles Daugherty, who is 86 years old and lives in the same home in Weston that his father occupied from 1923 until his death in 1974, stood in front of the mural where a robust young man was painted in the lower right foreground of the center panel (there are three panels).</p>
        <p>''I posed for that,'' he explained. ''If my father needed a hand or a foot, I posed.''</p>
        <p>James Daugherty was a well-known illustrator, with 100 books to his credit. Several were on display in the reading room near the mural. ''A library is a perfect place for a mural of his,'' said John Solum of Westport, an associate of the Daugherty Archive and a professor of flute at Vassar College. ''All librarians knew his name, certainly the children's librarians.''</p>
        <p>The mural's trials and tribulations rival those of its subject. The Daugherty Archive became aware of the mural through studies left by the artist. Charles Daugherty recollected his father painting it. Mr. Solum's detective work led him to the school in the mid 90's, where on one occasion, he observed volleyballs bouncing off the mural. ''It didn't take much reasoning, this mural would be destroyed,'' Mr. Solum said. ''It was in an inappropriate place for it. It's not the kids' fault, it's a gymnasium! It's the adults' fault.'' He said he wrote a letter to the superintendent of schools, informing him that there would be a campaign to remove, restore and relocate the mural.</p>
        <p>The Ruth W. Brown Foundation offered $60,000 to support the endeavor. Joseph Matteis, an art conservator from Clinton, had restored another Daugherty W.P.A. mural several years ago. Entitled ''Nursery Tales'' and commissioned for the Holmes Elementary School in Darien, it had been painted over completely.</p>
        <p>Mr. Matteis said the whole process of restoring the General Putnam mural took five months and was very tough.</p>
        <p>He talked about the artist's technique: ''He only used 10 colors. Instead of mixing them, he laid them side by side. For flesh, he put red next to green, the green along the edge of the arm.'' As he pointed out details to a visitor, he added, ''As you stand back it all vibrates, it works.'' He went on to say that James Daugherty loved the works of Reubens. ''It explains the composition, the way it rolls together like a big wave. It just resonates,'' Mr. Matteis said.</p>
        <p>From a historical point of view, James Daugherty's mural represents a perspective of American history by an American of the 1930's. Rebecca Lawton, an art historian, told visitors, ''Someone like Daugherty is key to our understanding what happened to Americans exposed to European modernism. The dynamism of futurism, the wonderful liberating color of artists like Matisse. Daugherty was able to absorb, then translate to an American scene and subject.''</p>
        <p>Now that General Putnam is safely ensconced until his next adventure, the Daugherty Archive is trying to rescue murals that had been commissioned for Stamford High School in the 1930's. ''We're trying to raise $400,000 to give them to Stamford,'' Mr. Solum said.</p>
        <p>Four of the original seven murals are currently in the possession of an art conservator, who has slowly been selling them off to private collectors and corporations.</p>
        <p>''We want these murals to be seen,'' Mr. Solum said. ''We could wait around for years for Stamford. We won't ever give up on these murals.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
