<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOME DESIGN: Fall 2000; Style Counsel</title>
    <meta content="HD3T" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="72" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Floyd, Brad</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, William L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coddington, Grace</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3D9143BF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOME DESIGN: Fall 2000; Style Counsel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William L. Hamilton</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamilton, William L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William L Hamilton article on architect Brad Floyd's redesign of Vogue creative director Grace Coddington's two-story apartment on West 11th Street; photos (special section, Home Design) (part 2 of 2-part section) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brad Floyd is an architect, but he looks and acts like one of the laconic, downtown models in Andy Warhol's 1968 Factory film ''Lonesome Cowboys.'' Blue-eyed, wavy-haired and sideburned, Floyd, 44, is a Nashville native who studied at the Pratt Institute in Brooklyn and has lived in New York for 24 years. A vegetarian and a kayaker who floats his boat on the Hudson River a couple of evenings a week, Floyd is standing in the living room of Grace Coddington's two-story apartment on West 11th Street.</p>
        <p>Coddington is the creative director of Vogue. Floyd is her architect. Steven Meisel, the photographer, for whom Floyd designed a 4,000-square-foot office in 1994, introduced them. Floyd has also worked with Anna Sui and Narciso Rodriguez, both fashion designers, and Joe McKenna, a stylist. He has just finished offices for Fuel, a fashion consulting agency on West 29th Street that markets collections by Hussein Chalayan, Balenciaga and Maria Cornejo at Zero. Of his fashion-heavy clientele, Floyd says simply, ''I get passed around a lot.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brad Floyd is an architect, but he looks and acts like one of the laconic, downtown models in Andy Warhol's 1968 Factory film ''Lonesome Cowboys.'' Blue-eyed, wavy-haired and sideburned, Floyd, 44, is a Nashville native who studied at the Pratt Institute in Brooklyn and has lived in New York for 24 years. A vegetarian and a kayaker who floats his boat on the Hudson River a couple of evenings a week, Floyd is standing in the living room of Grace Coddington's two-story apartment on West 11th Street.</p>
        <p>Coddington is the creative director of Vogue. Floyd is her architect. Steven Meisel, the photographer, for whom Floyd designed a 4,000-square-foot office in 1994, introduced them. Floyd has also worked with Anna Sui and Narciso Rodriguez, both fashion designers, and Joe McKenna, a stylist. He has just finished offices for Fuel, a fashion consulting agency on West 29th Street that markets collections by Hussein Chalayan, Balenciaga and Maria Cornejo at Zero. Of his fashion-heavy clientele, Floyd says simply, ''I get passed around a lot.''</p>
        <p>What Floyd does with design -- and whom he does it for -- has much to do with his personality. He is the reverse of an egotistical architect, and his work is the antithesis of signature architecture. ''I listen more than I talk,'' he says. ''I'm not trying to push anything on my clients. I provide an architectural backdrop for their particular style.''</p>
        <p>For his clients, appearance, of course, is everything. And discretion is the very best label. ''It's not design,'' says Coddington, who shares her renovated apartment with Didier Malige, a hairstylist. ''I don't want you to walk in and say, 'It's a ''blah-blah'' house.' I want it to be my house.''</p>
        <p>It is: the collection of cat tchotchkes (Coddington also has four live cats), the Staffordshire dogs, the sofa draped with the Union Jack and the bathmat and towels from the Paris Ritz could be no one else's.</p>
        <p>For Coddington, Floyd basically came in and cleaned up. He redesigned the living room with a strong horizontal wall of 17-foot-long, 2-inch-thick solid mahogany bookshelves. He organized the editor's thousands of books, her issues of Vogue back to 1974 bound like the Koran in white and gold and her dozens of photographs by Penn, Lartigue, Weston, Newton and others. He stained the floors dark to picture-frame the white gallery walls and stripped a circular staircase to its original metal, which gives it the presence of an industrial piece by an early French Modernist, like Pierre Chareau.</p>
        <p>This gift for understatement also characterized the extensive design Floyd did for Alex Gonzalez and Raul Martinez, whose advertising agency, A/R Media, works with Valentino, Dolce &amp; Gabbana and Estee Lauder. Gonzalez and Martinez's apartment, on West 12th Street, has six high-ceilinged rooms in a stolid building that was a ''gentleman's residence'' when built, in the late 19th century.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to retain that level of masculinity,'' Gonzalez says, ''but we also wanted a combination of the traditional and the contemporary. We walked through with Brad. He really listens, and he listened to the apartment, too. There was a tremendous amount of work done, but it doesn't look like an architect's run through it.''</p>
        <p>Floyd regimented a 40-foot-long living room with an awkwardly placed structural column by flanking it with two decorative columns to create a majestic tripart entrance, making the problem the focus of the solution. He also restrategized the apartment's doors, streamlining a wall of dressing closets along a corridor and tucking a bedroom door into a corner behind a wall to make it more private.</p>
        <p>At Lori Goldstein's apartment, on West 23rd Street, Floyd delivered an underlying architectural order to provide a clean slate for the client's kaleidoscopic collection of furniture, fabrics and photographs. Goldstein, a fashion consultant who works with Italian Vogue and Versace, lives in three adjacent apartments that she joined together. Her furniture includes two zebra-skin rugs (bought as antiques, Goldstein is quick to point out); mid-20th-century modern pieces by T.H. Robsjohn-Gibbings, George Nelson and others; and a 10-foot sofa recently commissioned from Snook Studio.</p>
        <p>''Really integrating the place as much as possible,'' Goldstein recalls of the assignment she gave Floyd. ''And trying to incorporate everything.''</p>
        <p>In a single, straightforward stroke, the architect added a new wall in the open, double-width living room, reinforcing its graphic impact with picture ledges for Goldstein's photographs. He situated the master bedroom behind it on one side and a new kitchen, compact but complete, on the other. To the right of the living room, etched-glass doors slide open, shoji style, to reveal a tranquil suite for guests.</p>
        <p>''I don't know, I mean, that seemed like just a really good way to do it,'' Floyd says slowly, as if he's just slid down off a horse.</p>
        <p>It was.</p>
        <p>''You have no idea how atrocious some of these rooms looked,'' says Lafayette Compton, the general contractor who worked on the three projects with Floyd.</p>
        <p>''He does nice work,'' adds Compton, standing next to the architect at Goldstein's apartment, surveying the immaculately subtle results. ''But he's modest -- I'm not.''</p>
        <p>William L. Hamilton is a reporter for the House &amp; Home section of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William L. Hamilton is a reporter for the House &amp; Home section of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
