<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Confidence Drawn From a Charmed Life</title>
    <meta content="08KENN$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/arts/08KENN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hudson, Kate</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crowe, Cameron</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Dana</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Almost Famous (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dr T and the Women (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E7DF113DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Confidence Drawn From a Charmed Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANA KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Dana</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with actress Kate Hudson, who comments on working with director Cameron Crowe on Almost Famous; her latest project is Robert Altman's new film, Dr T and the Women; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to directing, Cameron Crowe has a reputation for being unflappable. But one day, on the set of his latest movie, ''Almost Famous,'' he almost lost it.</p>
        <p>The actress Kate Hudson was the center of a difficult scene in which her character, a vulnerable young groupie named Penny Lane, learns she has been sold to another band by the rock star she loves -- for $50 and a case of beer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to directing, Cameron Crowe has a reputation for being unflappable. But one day, on the set of his latest movie, ''Almost Famous,'' he almost lost it.</p>
        <p>The actress Kate Hudson was the center of a difficult scene in which her character, a vulnerable young groupie named Penny Lane, learns she has been sold to another band by the rock star she loves -- for $50 and a case of beer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crowe did not think Ms. Hudson had nailed the scene, but the shooting schedule was tight and he had to move on. He took her aside and let her know his disappointment. ''I was chiding both of us, in a way,'' he recalled. ''I said, I don't think we got it. It was a tough conversation. I was heartbroken. I knew I was going to have a sleepless night, and I was sure she was, too.''</p>
        <p>But ''the next day I see her,'' he went on, ''she's total sunniness and light. She had a great night's sleep. She hardly remembered the stress of the scene. She'd just moved on.''</p>
        <p>He was in for another surprise too. When he played back the scene, he said, ''it was great.''</p>
        <p>''She had delivered just what I needed without my realizing it at the time. This girl has a layer of belief in herself that beats anyone else's.''</p>
        <p>When told recently of Mr. Crowe's remarks, the 21-year-old Ms. Hudson smiled and leaned back on the sofa in the Manhattan suite she is sharing with her rock star boyfriend of eight months, Chris Robinson, 33, the lead singer of the Black Crowes. ''I remember that day,'' she said. ''I was really feeling Cameron's stress. At one point I took a walk way into this field just to get myself together. My acting coach came over and said: 'Are you O.K.? Can you do this?' And I said, 'Absolutely.' And I did. I knew Cameron was upset, but I didn't want to let it get to me.''</p>
        <p>It was a wise choice -- and one that Ms. Hudson appears to have made more than once in a life that has been mostly charmed. Thirty-two years after her mother, the actress Goldie Hawn, because a household name virtually overnight, Ms. Hudson, after a string of forgettable films, has suddenly become one of the most talked-about new actresses of the year.</p>
        <p>Besides winning rave reviews for ''Almost Famous,'' Mr. Crowe's semi-autobiographical movie about his years as a teenage rock journalist, she will be seen next in Robert Altman's new ensemble comedy, ''Dr. T and the Women'' (opening Friday), playing Dee Dee, the spoiled daughter of a successful Dallas gynecologist (Richard Gere). Dee Dee is planning an elaborate wedding, although she is hiding a secret that threatens to torpedo the big event. Ms. Hudson will also star in ''About Adam,'' a romantic comedy due out in the spring about a young Irishwoman in Dublin.</p>
        <p>''It's happened so fast, I still can't believe it or even sit down and take a breath and enjoy it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The speed with which her career has taken off may require some adjustment, but the transition from being the daughter of a movie star to becoming one herself has been remarkably smooth. The only real bump came one week last month when Ms. Hudson appeared on ''The Rosie O'Donnell Show'' and Ms. O'Donnell questioned her relationship with Mr. Robinson, implying she would be better off with someone more clean-cut. Ms. Hudson wears a large diamond ring, a gift from Mr. Robinson, but says the two have no official marriage plans.</p>
        <p>''I was so offended,'' Ms. Hudson said of Ms. O'Donnell's interview. The show's producers had told her that she would be asked about her relationship, she said, but she was not prepared for Ms. O'Donnell's criticism of Mr. Robinson, who looks the part of a dissolute rock star and has written songs about drug use. ''This is someone I really love and who my family loves. It was very hard to hear her talk about him that way.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hudson's handlers made a call to Ms. O'Donnell's staff after the show was broadcast, and the next day Ms. O'Donnell sang a little song apparently in apology. ''Whatever,'' Ms. Hudson said. ''I don't hold a grudge.''</p>
        <p>She said she inherited her sunny temperament from her mother. In person, Ms. Hudson, who is wafer thin and chain smokes Camel Lights, resembles Ms. Hawn slightly and has an eerily similar voice. ''My mother is not someone you feel you can compete with, so I don't,'' Ms. Hudson said of Ms. Hawn, now 54, who won an Oscar for best supporting actress in ''Cactus Flower'' when she was 24.</p>
        <p>''She's a huge personality -- like a big light, a real blessing in my life,'' Ms. Hudson said. ''We can't believe it when people ask if there's any competition between us. It is so not like that.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hudson is less likely to field the inevitable questions about nepotism, although the issue is always there. ''It's not my problem,'' she said simply. ''If other people want to think I got where I am just because of my mother, let them think that. Doors may have opened for me, but no one hires me unless they think I can do the job.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Crowe agrees. ''From a directing point of view,'' he said, ''all I can say is, men in dark clothes don't come to your door in the middle of the night and say: 'You must hire her. She's Hollywood royalty.' ''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Crowe originally hired Ms. Hudson for a smaller role, as the young journalist's rebellious older sister, and decided to give her a shot at the pivotal part of Penny Lane only after the actress Sarah Polley (''The Sweet Hereafter'') dropped out.</p>
        <p>''Kate's confidence is so much a part of who she is,'' Mr. Crowe said. ''Nothing beats that when you catch it onscreen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Altman went on at some length about Ms. Hudson's self-confidence. Before he hired her, he summoned Ms. Hudson to his Malibu home to talk about the part of the flighty rich girl who is engaged at the start of ''Dr. T and the Women'' but in love with someone else. ''I was struck by the fact that she had not the slightest bit of timidity,'' Mr. Altman said. ''She totally got that part. I didn't have to tell her anything.''</p>
        <p>That self-assurance, to hear Ms. Hudson tell it, is rooted in the kind of glamorous Hollywood childhood that usually breeds insecurity, not self-esteem. Ms. Hudson's parents divorced before she was 2 years old, and her relationship with her biological father, Bill Hudson, a 1970's television comedian and musician, has always been strained. When she was 3, her mother moved in with the actor Kurt Russell, whom Ms. Hudson calls ''Pa'' and regards as ''my real dad.'' She calls her mother ''a powerhouse.''</p>
        <p>''She's Jewish! She's like me,'' she said. ''She likes to have a lot of things going on at once. Pa's more of a homebody. He goes to work, but he lives for his kids.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hudson grew up on film sets and shuttling between the family's homes in Los Angeles, New York and Aspen, Colo., along with an older brother, a younger half-brother and Mr. Russell's son by a previous marriage. But unlike the offspring of other famous show business families, Ms. Hudson said, she had a rock-solid home life.</p>
        <p>''We'd go home after parties and we'd have to laugh at how some of these people lived and how they treated their kids,'' she said. ''It's a business where people are so me me me, they forget where the focus should be.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hudson leaves no doubt that her family was different. She prefers to talk about her parents and brothers more than herself, her career or even her boyfriend. ''They're the funnest people I know,'' she said. She still lives at home when she's not with Mr. Robinson.</p>
        <p>Her favorite memories are of the times spent on her parents' movie sets. Her first vivid memory is of ''Swing Shift'' (1984). ''It was when my mom met Kurt, and I fell in love with him immediately,'' she recalled. ''I remember my grandma having a small role in the movie and sitting with her in the makeup trailer and thinking how beautiful she was. And my brother sitting behind the camera. I even remember doing the clapper sometimes.''</p>
        <p>When she was 8, the entire family went on location to Mendocino, Calif., for ''Overboard,'' the 1987 romantic comedy starring Ms. Hawn and Mr. Russell. ''I always watch it whenever it comes on TV,'' Ms. Hudson said. ''I look at them and think: 'Those are my parents! They're so cute!' I always cry at the end.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hudson was 11 when she informed her mother that she wanted to act, and Ms. Hawn obliged by taking her to an audition for a new sitcom. ''I didn't find out until much later that they were interested in hiring me, but my mom said no. She wanted me to wait.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hawn said she had known her daughter was talented. ''The only scary thing for a mother who is successful is that you want your daughter to come out strong and self-possessed as well,'' she said. ''You want her to know she's not you, or just the daughter of somebody. I felt it would be a mistake to let her start working too soon. Acting is not a realistic world for a child.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Russell, a former child star himself, said he had felt the same way. He had allowed Ms. Hudson to audition for John Carpenter's ''Escape From L.A.,'' a 1996 movie he starred in and co-produced, and Mr. Carpenter had wanted to cast her as the president's daughter, Mr. Russell said. But ''we decided to hold back,'' he continued. ''We weren't afraid of failure; we were afraid of success. I thought Katie would be noticed in this film, but sometimes when you're noticed for something when you're so young, it eclipses your future work.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hudson's first professional job came in 1996 when she was 16: a guest-starring role on the Fox television drama ''Party of Five.'' She also got a recurring role on ''EZ Streets'' just before the series was canceled.</p>
        <p>Since then, she has left television behind. And college as well. She was accepted at New York University's Tisch School of the Arts but says she begged her parents to let her defer if she found work in movies -- and she did, receiving some attention for two independent films last year, ''200 Cigarettes'' and ''Desert Blue.'' She also co-starred in this year's glossy, trashy thriller ''Gossip.'' Her first film, however, was the little-seen ''Ricochet River'' in 1998.</p>
        <p>''I really don't know what it was about,'' Ms. Hudson said. ''I saw it for the first time in our house, and my dad fell asleep during the first half of the movie. I didn't care because it was so bad. He woke up at the climactic point, and we started laughing our heads off. Here it is my first movie and we're all laughing about how horrible it was. That's a perfect example of how cool my family is.''</p>
        <p>For now, she is taking a break from work and helping her boyfriend settle into a new Manhattan apartment. Even so, her thoughts are never too far from her home in California. ''We love getting back there as much as possible,'' she said. ''Just hanging out with my family. There's nothing better.''</p>
        <p>FILM Dana Kennedy is an entertainment reporter for MSNBC.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dana Kennedy is an entertainment reporter for MSNBC.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
