<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Hamptons Films, A Global Perspective</title>
    <meta content="08FILM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hamptons International Film Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinreich, Regina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Hamptons International Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1D91E3DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Hamptons Films, A Global Perspective</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REGINA WEINREICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weinreich, Regina</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on some of offerings at upcoming Hamptons International Film Festival; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE daytrippers have disappeared and at last it is safe to make a left turn on Montauk Highway. But ''the season'' is not over yet.</p>
        <p>Here comes the film community --  the stars, filmmakers, publicists, distributors, agents and press -- for the cinematic feast served up each fall by the Hamptons International Film Festival. The festival, now in its eighth year, will take place in East Hampton, Westhampton, and Sag Harbor from Thursday through Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE daytrippers have disappeared and at last it is safe to make a left turn on Montauk Highway. But ''the season'' is not over yet.</p>
        <p>Here comes the film community --  the stars, filmmakers, publicists, distributors, agents and press -- for the cinematic feast served up each fall by the Hamptons International Film Festival. The festival, now in its eighth year, will take place in East Hampton, Westhampton, and Sag Harbor from Thursday through Sunday.</p>
        <p>Smaller than the Toronto festival, less prestigious than New York with which it shares the fall, the Hamptons is a premier regional festival. ''I would not like to see the Hamptons become huge,'' said Lynda Hansen, the co-director of programming. '' Our charm is location, beauty, and intimacy.''</p>
        <p>In fact, presenting 54 programs this year, fewer than last, the festival is measuring bigness in other ways.</p>
        <p>''We're branching out as a world festival,'' said the event's executive director, Denise Kasell. ''When you get all the players, the major distributors like New Line, Lions Gate, Sony Picture Classics, you have a platform that's international, where filmmakers get noticed.''</p>
        <p>Only directors making their first or second feature films can compete for the Golden Starfish Award for fiction feature. Vying for this year's prize and its more than $160,000 of in-kind production services are Michael Bregman with ''Table One''; Dani Minnick with ''Falling Like This''; Daniel Cohen with ''Diamond Men''; Matthew Taback with ''Auggie Rose'' and Abraham Lim with ''Roads and Bridges.''</p>
        <p>This year that prize comes full circle. Eugene Martin, who won in 1998 for ''Edge City,'' will have a  Hamptons debut for his new film  ''Diary of a City Priest,'' set in North Philadelphia and based on the writings of the Rev. John McNamee.</p>
        <p>Kim Snyder's ''I Remember Me,'' a film about chronic fatigue syndrome, is in the documentary competition for the $10,000 prize. The first-time director from Springs hopes that recognition for this mysterious illness will result from her film, which features interviews with Michelle Akers, the soccer player, Keith Jarrett, the jazz musician, and Blake Edwards, the ''Pink Panther'' filmmaker.</p>
        <p>In the world cinema category, another film deals with the problem of alcoholism. In Hans Petter Moland's ''Aberdeen,'' Stellan Skarsgard plays an unrepentant lush whose daughter tries to reunite him with his estranged, dying wife, played by Charlotte Rampling.</p>
        <p>In the same category, the Academy Award-winner Nigel Noble, an East Hampton resident, will present ''The Charcoal People,'' a celebration of the migrant workers of Brazil's rain forest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Noble's film will go on to show in other festivals including one in December in Cuba, with which the Hamptons is forging a sister relationship.</p>
        <p>The Independent Film Channel is providing a variety of prizes: $2,500 for each of 10 student filmmakers and a $5,000 award to a short film. Other prizes include The Zicherman Family Foundation Award for Cinematography ($5,000) and a new award, the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation Feature Film Prize, $25,000 cash for a popular feature that explores science, mathematics and technology themes. ''Songcatcher,'' this year's opening night film in which Janet McTeer portrays a musicologist researching Appalachian song traditions, has been selected for its dramatization of the rigors of scientific inquiry.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most ambitious category is a newly inaugurated 10-year partnership with the Nobel Laureates Foundation, and its $25,000 cash prize awarded by an international jury. The prize, The Danny and Ewa Abraham Award for Films of Conflict and Resolution, ''enables us to concentrate on troubled areas, bringing in those filmmakers who come from regions of conflict who have made art nonetheless,'' said Ms. Kasell. Given the current headlines, it seems prescient that this year's focus is on the Middle East. ''We want to explore the issue, how do artists create in politically difficult worlds,'' she said</p>
        <p>The selections include Segell Ikhtifa's ''Chronicle of a Disappearance,'' vignettes of Jerusalem life seen through Palestinian eyes; Elia Suleiman's ''Cyber Palestine,'' in which Joseph and Mary, awaiting their baby's birth, travel from present-day Gaza to Bethlehem, and Avi Mograbi's semi-documentary, ''Happy Birthday, Mr. Mograbi,'' with its story of three birthdays: the 50th anniversary of the Israeli state, the 50th anniversary of the Palestinian refugee crisis and his own 42nd year.</p>
        <p>Special screenings include ''Pollock,'' Ed Harris's new film about the Abstract Expressionist, shot partly on location in Springs where the painter lived and died. The film will be followed by a seminar with Mr. Harris and John Anderson, a film critic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
