<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Food; Buried Treasure</title>
    <meta content="08FOODLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="107" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Truffles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reynolds, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Truffles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDE103DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Food; Buried Treasure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Reynolds</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reynolds, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Reynolds Food column on truffles; recipes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At $1,500 a pound for fresh whites, truffles may be the most expensive food in the world. Considering their price, are they as overrated as all but three movie directors, the cleverness of Bruce Vilanch and any five minutes in the Hamptons? Or are they worth the money? The answer -- if they are perfectly prepared, as they are below -- is yes, thunderingly so.</p>
        <p>But since the truffle is neither as bold in taste nor as shamelessly sexual on the tongue as those luscious little orgasmic explosions of caviar or the sultry flesh of foie gras as it melts on your gingivae, its presence is more difficult to detect. The truffle is almost never served by itself (except when a pig gets hold of one) and is considerably trickier to cook with than caviar or foie gras. After all, the truffle needs brides and bridesmaids (and whole wedding parties sometimes), whereas caviar and foie gras are at their best as bachelors -- caviar requiring only a splash of lemon, and foie gras nothing at all. And while you can ruin the sturgeon's roe with spoonfuls of onion, egg white and capers, and spoil the goose's liver with trendy sauces, it's difficult to obliterate them. Truffles, on the other hand, are so subtle that they can be wiped out with almost anything stronger than milk. But properly mated, they are sublime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At $1,500 a pound for fresh whites, truffles may be the most expensive food in the world. Considering their price, are they as overrated as all but three movie directors, the cleverness of Bruce Vilanch and any five minutes in the Hamptons? Or are they worth the money? The answer -- if they are perfectly prepared, as they are below -- is yes, thunderingly so.</p>
        <p>But since the truffle is neither as bold in taste nor as shamelessly sexual on the tongue as those luscious little orgasmic explosions of caviar or the sultry flesh of foie gras as it melts on your gingivae, its presence is more difficult to detect. The truffle is almost never served by itself (except when a pig gets hold of one) and is considerably trickier to cook with than caviar or foie gras. After all, the truffle needs brides and bridesmaids (and whole wedding parties sometimes), whereas caviar and foie gras are at their best as bachelors -- caviar requiring only a splash of lemon, and foie gras nothing at all. And while you can ruin the sturgeon's roe with spoonfuls of onion, egg white and capers, and spoil the goose's liver with trendy sauces, it's difficult to obliterate them. Truffles, on the other hand, are so subtle that they can be wiped out with almost anything stronger than milk. But properly mated, they are sublime.</p>
        <p>Their exorbitant price is due in part to the difficulty of cultivating them. To an even greater degree than the wine grape, the black diamond demands the right kind of soil, sun and time -- conditions met exactly on the hillsides around the Mediterranean and just about nowhere else. Proper growth depends on an intimate and complicated relationship between tree (usually an oak) and soil (ideally chalky). And the amount of time the truffle takes to mature -- 8 to 12 years -- doesn't exactly quicken the heartbeat of recent M.B.A.'s. Then, too, its scarcity has never been more acute: from a production high of 1,000 tons in 1900, only 10 tons were harvested last year, much of the land being lost to deforestation.</p>
        <p>Although rural legend has it that pigs are the truffle hunter's preferred divining rod, it's not true. Dogs are. The reason is that swine are more worldly. Everyone knows that pigs score higher than dogs on their college boards, but the news here is that they also have wittier and more urbane palates; porkers actually want to eat the truffle once they've dug it up. Protein-mad dogs, however, are too lowbrow to appreciate the fine flavor -- one more reason to let pigs live and replace them tonight on the dinner table with poodle chops, collie loin and rashers of Jack Russell.</p>
        <p>The lack of canine interest in the fungal fruit itself simplifies the harvester's job, and it's a lot easier to coax a dog into the back of a car than a pig. (If the pig is so damned bright, I hear you asking, why doesn't he learn that he's never going to get to eat the truffles? Why does he keep unearthing them? The answer is that he has such a rich fantasy life imagining himself, legs crossed in his easy chair, flute of Champagne in one trotter, a slice of Brie de Meaux aux Truffes in the other, that regardless of setbacks, he cannot stop trying to realize his dream. Like Buddha. Or Lyndon LaRouche.)</p>
        <p>In addition to the pig and dog, a certain upwardly mobile fly alerts the harvester -- in a sort of foot-stamping, insect version of ''my-child is going to Dalton or nowhere'' -- by buzzing over the buried truffle and trying to deposit her eggs on the ground above it. But it's pretty tough to school truffle flies, and the harvester can only depend on luck to find a swarm. At any rate, enough about the subspecies; what must you know in order to cook the truffles themselves?</p>
        <p>Well, there are 70 varieties, some of which were already on the menu in ancient Mesopotamia; and the only ones worth buying are the white (grown mostly in northern Italy), which are added to a dish after it's cooked, usually as a shaving; and the black (from France and Spain), which are used in cooking. I find that black truffles work best when cooked with eggs, cream, bechamels and breads.</p>
        <p>And where better to celebrate these precious gems than at the Connaught Hotel in London, a resting place so venerable that it sometimes seems that the staff is made of the same polished mahogany as the fabled staircase and walls? (The rooms, though not spacious, are impeccable, down to individual call buttons for Waiter, Valet and Maid; the elevator can fit only three affectionate bulimics without luggage and is so slow that a teenager can actually get through puberty between Floors 1 and 4. But such unrushed Edwardian elegance is precisely the point of this hotel consistently ranked as one of London's best.)</p>
        <p>Michel Bourdin, who has been chef here for 25 years (and who prefers to call the place ''a great restaurant that also rents out rooms''), produces an annual weeklong truffle festival in February. Though some truffle dishes are available on the hotel menu throughout the year, the special Menu de la Truffe is usually held during Valentine's Week because of the fungus's renowned (but unproven) reputation to seduce.</p>
        <p>A bristling champion of French haute cuisine, Chef Bourdin disdains both fusion cooking and mothers who phone him asking how their sons can get their own cooking shows. ''Nobody wants to learn the basics anymore,'' he complains. ''Picasso was appreciated because he was classically trained. It is the same with cooking.''</p>
        <p>So, of the purists, Chef Bourdin is the purest, and a key on his ring admits him and only him to the frozen-food locker containing, at the moment, $100,000 worth of black diamonds -- about 330 pounds. Why such security is necessary is more bewildering than the popularity of William Shatner reciting song lyrics to earsplitting (if well paid) applause: even if someone could get away with stealing a couple of truffles, where would he go to fence them? Or would the thief be so sophisticated, he'd want them just to eat? ''The truffle is to haute cuisine what garlic is to Proven--&gt;al and curry to Indian food,'' Bourdin, the ex-pat Frenchman, says patriotically.</p>
        <p>And his cuisine is haute indeed. Some of it, like the filet of Angus beef and ''Petite Eggs'cellent,'' a coyly dubbed concoction of quail eggs, hollandaise and truffles presented in a tiny pastry boat, is so scrumptious, the truffle becomes superfluous. But other plates are both transformed and transforming. The dizzying Souffle aux Truffes made me antisocial -- no talking, no touching, eyes closed, only smell and taste at work, the flavor sooo elusive, indefinable and yet irresistible! And the scallops with thin truffle shavings were pleasurably mellow, ensconced as they were amid delicious lobster ravioli. A few gasps for breath, then I ordered the Cr me Brlee aux Truffes . . . and did yet another culinary swoon!</p>
        <p>To swoon at home, here's what to do first: prepare some truffle oil by covering a golf-ball-size truffle (about 1.7 ounces) and two cloves of garlic with two liters of sunflower or peanut oil and put it aside. A week later, remove the truffle and use it in the methods below. Its flavor won't be diminished, but the oil's will be enhanced -- and will keep for two months in the fridge or much longer in the freezer.</p>
        <p>If you should have a few truffle slices lying around -- and who among us doesn't? -- an excellent use for them is to truffle-ize cheese. Again, the secret is to find a mild cheese: Chef Bourdin uses Brie de Meaux and Camembert. He cuts a slice horizontally through the middle of the cheese wedge, inserts a thin piece of black truffle that is roughly the size of the cut surface and lets it rest for at least two days. The cheese takes on the perfume of the truffle with just enough crunch from the diamond to contrast textures. Close your eyes.</p>
        <p>As for the recipes below, you won't want to eat both dishes on the same menu. Well, you may want to, but don't. Instead, eat each on a different day, and while digesting, figure out how to set up the experiment that will test if this most platinum of all thallophytes really does inspire the libido. (''Oh, nurse, could I be in the control group?'') If so, many body parts will be pleased. If not, at least you get to participate in an orgy of truffles.</p>
        <p>Truffles in Puff Pastry 'Cinderella'  (adapted from ''Secrets of the Great French restaurants,'' by Louisette Bertholle)  4 fresh or canned black truffles, 1 1/2 to 1 3/4 ounces each  1 cup dry Champagne</p>
        <p>1/4 cup dry sherry  3 ounces fresh or canned mousse de foie gras  1 sheet puff pastry, well chilled  4 (3-inch square) thin slices prosciutto cotto or other delicately flavored ham  1 egg yolk, beaten with  1/4 teaspoon water.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat the oven to 450 degrees. Butter a small baking sheet.</p>
        <p>2. Scrub truffles with a vegetable brush and put in a small saucepan. Add Champagne and sherry and heat to boiling. Simmer 4 to 6 minutes, until a skewer can be inserted into them. Drain and cool.</p>
        <p>3. Mash the foie gras with a fork and divide into quarters. Wrap each truffle in one portion.</p>
        <p>4. On a lightly floured surface, roll out the puff pastry into a 16-inch square. With a sharp knife, cut pastry into 4 (4-inch) squares.</p>
        <p>5. Place a slice of ham on each pastry square and top with a prepared truffle. Bring pastry edges up over the truffle and pinch at the top to form a small bundle. Brush with the egg yolk mixture and place on the prepared baking sheet. Bake until pastry is golden brown, about 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Creme Brulee With Truffles  12 egg yolks  6 tablespoons sugar  2 1/4 teaspoons black truffle trimmings tied in cheesecloth  2 1/2 cups double cream  1 cup whipping cream  1 teaspoon chopped black truffle  Soft brown sugar.</p>
        <p>1. In a large bowl, whisk egg yolks and sugar until light and fluffy.</p>
        <p>2. Tie truffle trimmings with a double thickness of cheesecloth to form a small bag. Boil double cream, whipping cream and trimmings in a pan over medium heat.</p>
        <p>3. Whisk half the hot mixed cream into the egg yolks, then whisk this mixture into the remaining cream mixture. Over low heat, stir constantly until it starts to steam (do not boil) and coats the back of a wooden spoon.</p>
        <p>4. Pour through a sieve into a 1 1/2-quart souffle dish and stir in the chopped black truffle. Let cool, cover with plastic and refrigerate until set, at least 3 hours.</p>
        <p>5. Just before serving, sprinkle the custard with a thin layer of brown sugar and place under insanely hot broiler or blowtorch just until sugar melts and is golden brown. Serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
