<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan for Veterans' Monument Stirs Debate</title>
    <meta content="08REP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001105T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mall (Washington, DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE0D9163DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan for Veterans' Monument Stirs Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, D.C.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travel article on controversy over design and planned placement of memorial to World War II veterans on Mall in Washington, DC (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE needle of the Washington Monument pierced an almost cloudless sky and the geese outnumbered the tourists at the far end of the Lincoln Memorial's reflecting pool, but Christine McAdoo still acted claustrophobic when she was asked about plans to build a memorial to the veterans of World War II on this spot.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there would be any air left to breathe,'' said Ms. McAdoo, a tourist from Houston who was strolling around the Mall. ''It would be just so many things to see, and we only have so much time.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE needle of the Washington Monument pierced an almost cloudless sky and the geese outnumbered the tourists at the far end of the Lincoln Memorial's reflecting pool, but Christine McAdoo still acted claustrophobic when she was asked about plans to build a memorial to the veterans of World War II on this spot.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there would be any air left to breathe,'' said Ms. McAdoo, a tourist from Houston who was strolling around the Mall. ''It would be just so many things to see, and we only have so much time.''</p>
        <p>Other tourists, though, expressed support for the project when asked to examine drawings of the imposing plaza ringing a sunken pond at the place where throngs once gathered to hear Martin Luther King say, ''I have a dream.''</p>
        <p>''Definitely I think they should build it,'' said Lynn Hlavaty of Buffalo. ''They fought for our country -- our parents did -- and it's a free country, so yes.''</p>
        <p>''It's nice that everything you can see here is in walking distance,'' said her friend, Doreen Clever, when asked about the objections of some that the plethora of monuments was cramping the Mall.</p>
        <p>The World War II memorial has been under consideration for many years, boosted recently by President Clinton, Bob Dole and Tom Hanks, among others. But it has its opponents, too.</p>
        <p>In recent Congressional testimony, Judy Scott Feldman, an art and architecture historian, objected to the installation. She is a leader of the Committee of 100 on the Federal City, which since 1923 has acted as a watchdog on development in the nation's capital.</p>
        <p>''The Committee of 100 is not opposed to commemorating World War II,'' she said. ''It is the current design at the Mall location that is our concern. The approved design of the proposed memorial will dramatically alter this historic open and green parklike setting and replace it with a solid granite plaza stretching from tree line to tree line across the open central panel of the National Mall.''</p>
        <p>The memorial's design calls for a 7.4-acre granite plaza at the site of a small pool, known as the Rainbow Pool, halfway between the Lincoln Memorial and the Washington Monument. A set of granite pillars would surround the pool, with arches at the eastern and western ends symbolizing the Atlantic and Pacific theaters of the war.</p>
        <p>On Sept. 21, the National Capital Planning Commission voted to approve the basic final design. The vote was 7 to 5, and came after a meeting that lasted 10 hours. The American Battle Monuments Commission, which is sponsoring the memorial, called that step the last formal hurdle and said a groundbreaking could occur on Nov. 11, which is Veterans Day. The memorial is expected to cost $100 million.</p>
        <p>But a few details of the design, by the architect Friedrich St. Florian, were left for further review by the planning commission, one of several agencies that has a say in the memorial. They include such questions as lighting and whether to put a sculpture in the center of the pool.</p>
        <p>Although these matters should be easy for the agencies to agree on, there is no sign that opponents will drop their battle. Members of two coalitions opposing it said that they might still challenge it in court.</p>
        <p>Among those who oppose the changes are some civil rights leaders who object to changes at the scene of Dr. Martin Luther King's famous speech, led by the nonvoting delegate of the District of Columbia in Congress, Eleanor Holmes Norton.</p>
        <p>But many veterans groups argue that more than 1,000 veterans of the war are dying every day and that there has been enough delay.</p>
        <p>This is unlikely to be the last monument added to the area. In September, a design was chosen for a new memorial to Dr. King, to be built a few hundred yards from the Mall on the banks of the Potomac River's tidal basin. And members of Congress are pushing a bill that would lead to a Ronald Reagan memorial, although its prospects are uncertain. Both of these memorials have drawn some opposition, but neither is placed as prominently, or has stirred as much debate, as the war memorial.</p>
        <p>While many passers-by on a recent afternoon were familiar with the general plan for the memorial, few knew until they were told that they were standing on the very spot where it would be built, and none who spoke with this reporter were familiar with the design until they were shown pictures.</p>
        <p>The reviews, if mixed, tended to be favorable.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it would compromise all this at all,'' said Betty Ramaley of Easton, Pa.</p>
        <p>''I think that would be gorgeous,'' said her husband, Donald.</p>
        <p>But Donald Rose and his wife, Peter, of South Salem, N.Y., said they were not so sure.</p>
        <p>They agreed that veterans of World War II deserve a memorial, but their basic reaction summed up the principle objection to the war memorial: its location.</p>
        <p>''It should be someplace else,'' said Peter Rose, gesturing vaguely off toward one side of the Mall. ''How about over there?''</p>
        <p>As it happens, ''over there'' was another memorial to veterans that was controversial when it was installed, in part because its low, sinking design seemed ignoble to some critics. That is the Vietnam Veterans Memorial, now widely acknowledged as one of the most visited of the Mall's monuments.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT  Correction:  November 5, 2000, Sunday  The Correspondent's Report column on Oct. 8, about a proposed memorial on the Mall in Washington to honor veterans of World War II, referred incorrectly to its design. The memorial's granite plaza would be part of a larger 7.4-acre site with trees, grass and fountains; the plaza itself would not occupy 7.4 acres.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 5, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Correspondent's Report column on Oct. 8, about a proposed memorial on the Mall in Washington to honor veterans of World War II, referred incorrectly to its design. The memorial's granite plaza would be part of a larger 7.4-acre site with trees, grass and fountains; the plaza itself would not occupy 7.4 acres.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
