<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bidding For a Trip Online</title>
    <meta content="08CYBE$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/travel/08CYBER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tedeschi, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DD133DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1425" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bidding For a Trip Online</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB TEDESCHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tedeschi, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advice on bidding for trips on-line; drawings (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is good reason why Internet auctions have sapped millions of working hours from businesses and chained otherwise attentive parents to their PC's on evenings and weekends. Not only can auctions yield bargains, but there are few other places where you can compete against a potential pool of hundreds of millions of people and emerge as the winner.</p>
        <p>Given the fact that, like auctions, online travel has been a runaway favorite among Web surfers, it seemed only a matter of time before the two ideas were melded. Now some of the earliest travel-related auction sites are starting to gain momentum among consumers, with one site, BidForVacations .com, securing a spot among the 10 most visited travel sites in August, according to the Internet research company PCData, and others attracting increasing numbers of visitors as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is good reason why Internet auctions have sapped millions of working hours from businesses and chained otherwise attentive parents to their PC's on evenings and weekends. Not only can auctions yield bargains, but there are few other places where you can compete against a potential pool of hundreds of millions of people and emerge as the winner.</p>
        <p>Given the fact that, like auctions, online travel has been a runaway favorite among Web surfers, it seemed only a matter of time before the two ideas were melded. Now some of the earliest travel-related auction sites are starting to gain momentum among consumers, with one site, BidForVacations .com, securing a spot among the 10 most visited travel sites in August, according to the Internet research company PCData, and others attracting increasing numbers of visitors as well.</p>
        <p>The travel auctions on sites like BidForVacations, SkyAuction, AllCruiseAuction and Egghead, among others, closely resemble those on EBay, Yahoo and Amazon -- each of which, incidentally, plays host to travel auctions. Like the general merchandise sites, travel sites offer ''bid tracking'' features, which keep you up to date on the bidding, as well as e-mail notification of new auctions in categories you've expressed interest in. But unlike the general merchandise auction sites, the established travel auction sites, in my experience, don't include offers with messy strings attached.</p>
        <p>On a recent day I found dozens of auctions on EBay for round-trip flights to any destination worldwide on well-known airlines, with bids starting below $30. But in the fine print, bidders are told they must also book a ''minimum number'' of nights at a hotel at prices that cannot be quoted until after the flight is paid for. So you could get a bargain flight but not necessarily a bargain room. The auction pages of both Yahoo and Amazon featured similar offers.</p>
        <p>Experts on Internet security say it makes more sense to visit auction sites that sell the flights or hotel rooms direct, with a customer service staff, rather than the intermediary sites such as Yahoo and Amazon. But that isn't to say the travel auction sites are risk-free -- or stress-free -- environments.</p>
        <p>These sites offer cruises, air fare and hotel and resort vacations at bid prices that start as low as $1. The bidding can last anywhere from one day to one week, but the real action begins a few hours before bidding closes. At that point, bidders -- who have registered in advance -- either sit by their computers and edge the price higher or submit their highest bid and let the site do the bidding on their behalf until the price reaches their limit.</p>
        <p>Marsha Eiben, a school literacy specialist in Rockville, Md., is one who knows well the vagaries of travel auctions. In July she and her boyfriend, Tom Manion, a retired schoolteacher in Silver Spring, Md., decided to return to one of their favorite Caribbean spots, Turks and Caicos. Ms. Eiben clicked onto Bid4Vacations.com, which features vacations without air fare, and SkyAuction, which sells both vacation packages and airline flights. She found a flight on SkyAuction being auctioned at roughly $125 a seat at the time she began tracking it. She then found, on Bid4Vacations, an auction for a five-night, all-inclusive package for two at the Allegro resort in Turks and Caicos, with bids starting at $1.</p>
        <p>A $401 bid won the couple two tickets to Turks and Caicos on SkyAuction, but it also won them a bit of follow-up work. Mr. Manion bought two tickets from Washington to Atlanta for $406 on Delta, then applied himself to the task of winning the Allegro auction on Bid4Vacations. As the auction was about to close, he placed a winning bid for $901. He then had to secure a room with Allegro (through Bid4Vacations) between Aug. 19 and Aug. 26, the dates of the flights.</p>
        <p>Allegro was nearly booked, Mr. Manion said, but five days before he and Ms. Eiben were scheduled to take off, they got notice from Bid4Vacations confirming their room. Because the flight dates were seven days apart and the Allegro auction was for a five-day stay, the couple booked two nights at a Comfort Inn at Turks and Caicos. Total cost for airline tickets and accommodations: over $1,700.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manion and Ms. Eibel both said they had a great time, but they don't think they got a bargain. ''It was just about what you'd pay without the auction,'' Mr. Manion said. ''I wouldn't do it again that way, but it spurred us into action, let me tell you that.''</p>
        <p>Executives and online travel analysts say that one way to ensure a smooth auction experience is to read the terms and conditions of the auctions closely. Most sites add taxes and airport fees to the final bidding price, but they disclose such fees -- generally in the description of the item up for bid.</p>
        <p>Among the travel auction providers, Bid 4Vacations and SkyAuction were particularly easy to navigate, and listed a wide range of items up for bid. But none of the sites was great at packaging air and hotel offers together. So unless you have an abundance of frequent flyer miles or are willing to take a chance on a flight, you could get stuck doing what Mr. Manion and Ms. Eiben did.</p>
        <p>Just like other Internet sites that sell  goods that manufacturers want to get rid of, auction sites often get their inventory from so-called consolidators, who buy blocks of seats from the airlines or from travel providers who realize at the last minute that they have a block of unsold rooms, seats or cabins. Auction sites will either buy the inventory and hope the bids are high enough to make a profit or auction the inventory on behalf of the travel providers and charge them a transaction fee.</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, the value of those seats and rooms at auction is decidedly lower than the ''retail price,'' which sites often list alongside the current bidding numbers. That's because those who bid on these seats and cabins usually face stiff restrictions, including ''no cancellation'' clauses and limited travel itineraries with last-minute departure dates.</p>
        <p>That said, each of the sites boasts numerous auctions in which consumers have walked away with cruise vacations or resort trips for $200 a couple or less. On a recent night I found two auctions in which the winning bidders got great bargains for last-minute travel packages. In one, a bidder won a week's stay in a one-bedroom suite at the Fairfield Orlando for $195, and in another, a couple got a 15-night cruise through Panama and Costa Rica on the Norwegian Sky for about $350 a person. Such steals are the exception rather than the rule, of course, but they are out there. Pamela Bergeson, chief executive of Bid4Vacations, said that all the company's packages sell for 40 to 45 percent off retail.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the best bargains at these sites aren't actually among the auctions. Ms. Bergeson said last month that Norwegian Cruise Lines called and said it had 50 cabins left for a one-week cruise that sailed in three weeks. The retail price was $5,400. Ms. Bergeson said she couldn't put all 50 up for bid, so she sent an e-mail message to some of the site's two million registrants, offering the cruise for $749 for two people.</p>
        <p>Of course, bidders can sometimes lose themselves in the action and end up paying more than they might otherwise. A 32-day Renaissance cruise for two people from Athens to Singapore was recently auctioned on Egghead.com starting at $9. The ''maximum suggested bid'' -- or brochure price -- was $9,594. The bidding was set to close at 12:30 p.m., but because Egghead rules allow it to continue if competing bids come in within 10 minutes of each other, bidders were pushing the price toward $5,150 when bidding closed at 2 p.m. Had the two bidders called Renaissance Cruise Lines earlier  in the day, both could have made the trip, albeit for the slightly higher price of  $5,216. Then again, that wouldn't have been any fun.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
