<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Moon or Bust</title>
    <meta content="08WILFORT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kranz, Gene</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Failure Is Not an Option (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D91E3AF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Moon or Bust</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Noble Wilford</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Noble Wilford reviews book Failure Is Not an Option: Mission Control From Mercury to Apollo 13 and Beyond by Gene Kranz (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Failure Is Not an Option</p>
        <p>Mission Control From Mercury</p>
        <p>to Apollo 13 and Beyond.</p>
        <p>By Gene Kranz.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 415 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Failure Is Not an Option</p>
        <p>Mission Control From Mercury</p>
        <p>to Apollo 13 and Beyond.</p>
        <p>By Gene Kranz.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 415 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $26.</p>
        <p>In the popular image, the early astronauts were brave sons of America who drove fast and lived life to the hilt. Test pilots were like that. But when they wrapped themselves in technology and heard the capsule hatch shut tight, they were studies in coolness under extraordinary pressure: light this candle and get on with it. Test pilots talked that way when they were putting their lives on the line.</p>
        <p>Their confidence stemmed in no small measure from knowing that they had back-seat drivers they couldn't do without -- flight directors and a team of controllers watching every flicker of data crossing their consoles back on the ground. These were young engineers (all men in the beginning) who were earnest, disciplined and unsung. Among them, Gene Kranz was the quintessential flight director of the early space missions and of the first moon flights.</p>
        <p>With crew-cut blond hair and the stern visage of a drill sergeant, Kranz certainly looked the part. (One of his daughters once complained, ''Dad, you scare the boys away.'') He usually dressed for the part, too. While astronauts between flights walked around in short-sleeved Ban-Lon sport shirts, the ''humble ground-pounders wore ties and white shirts and yes, those nerdy pencil-holding pocket protectors.'' One of a select group recruited from government, industry and the armed forces, Kranz found himself in 1960, at 26, developing from scratch all procedures for countdowns, liftoffs and every other step of a space flight. Everything, the rules of flight as well as the hardware, had to be invented fast, and Kranz was an Edison of what became known as Mission Control.</p>
        <p>''Failure Is Not an Option'' is an engaging behind-the-scenes memoir, a welcome contribution to the history of space flight. More than any previous book, it gives the view of that history as lived by the brotherhood of Mission Control. The writing, like Kranz himself, is brisk, unadorned and informative, but warmed from time to time by characteristic expressions of irony and humor. When he noted that his wife, Marta, gave birth to two children in a space of 11 months, Kranz the former Air Force pilot remarked, ''that was a pretty tight formation.'' As a reporter who observed Kranz for years, I can see him saying this in the usual just-the-facts tone, then allowing a brief smile to crack his set professional face before regrouping for the next item on his agenda.</p>
        <p>Some readers may feel the narrative does not really lift off until it comes to the lunar flights, particularly the Apollo 8 Christmas mission in lunar orbit, Neil Armstrong and Buzz Aldrin's first landing on Apollo 11 and the near-loss of Apollo 13. Kranz retells these stories from the flight director's perspective, bringing to light little-known or never-told incidents and offering new insights into critical decisions. If not for a final practice run before the mission, Kranz tells us, the controllers probably would have aborted the historic Apollo 11 landing at the last moment. ''The intercom crackles, the voices diced and chopped, staccato,'' he recalls. ''I listen for any hint of concern or confusion. The voices have the steady, cool response of a well-tuned aircraft engine on a sunny day aloft.'' He gives the ''go'' command for the landing maneuver. In a few minutes, everything seems to be going wrong.</p>
        <p>Alarms sound in the lunar module cockpit and at Mission Control. '' 'It's a 1202 alarm' echoes across the loops for several seconds.'' Then Kranz and others realize that these were the ''same exact alarms that brought us to the wrong conclusion, an abort command,'' in the final simulated training run a week before.</p>
        <p>We know how it all came out. Armstrong could finally be heard over the radio: ''Houston, Tranquillity Base here. The Eagle has landed.'' Kranz for once loses control over his emotions. ''I slam my forearm against the console,'' he writes, but quickly regains command, issuing back-to-business orders. Thanks to the movie ''Apollo 13,'' Mission Control's role in bringing the astronauts safely home after an oxygen-tank explosion is familiar. Yet Kranz, in charge of devising the mission-saving strategy, has much to add on how the problem was identified and a solution improvised. The account captures the can-do spirit of the controllers and engineers in those days and Kranz's leadership style.</p>
        <p>As dramatic as these events were, the book's greatest value may be its evocation of the earliest days of the space program. We are reminded of how little was known about flying in space at the start, how rudimentary were the first control rooms (in a blockhouse at Cape Canaveral the console was little more than an ordinary clock and an intercom panel with a rotary dial phone) and how great were the pressures to get Americans into orbit. Working under Christopher C. Kraft Jr., who organized and trained the control teams, Kranz and his colleagues toiled long hours at low pay with few precedents for guidance in preparing for the first flights of the Mercury astronauts. They were shaken by the launching failure of an unpiloted test flight, ever mindful of the repeated Russian successes. Although no one talked about it openly, Kranz writes, the controllers ''fully expected to lose one or two astronauts in Mercury.'' He learned everything he could about the Mercury spacecraft and sat in on all meetings with the crews, controllers and NASA management. Before the first astronauts flew, Kranz literally wrote the first book on the rules of space flight.</p>
        <p>I was naturally interested in the author's views of reporters. Press conferences for him were an ''ordeal,'' and none more so than one during the Gemini 7 flight in 1965. Reporters exposed a ruse by which the control team had sought to keep certain orbit-to-ground communications from the public, contrary to NASA policy. Put on the spot, Kranz owned up to what had happened. Out of this Kranz said that he developed a grudging respect for the space press corps, and the feeling was mutual. ''We determined never again to try a fast one,'' Kranz writes. ''Personally, I took the attitude that a press conference was like a high-stakes poker game. I loved playing the game with the press, always telling the truth but showing my full hand only when asked the right question.''</p>
        <p>Kranz has succeeded admirably in putting a human face on the indispensable back-seat drivers of early space flight. It is no coincidence -- but altogether appropriate -- that the face bears a strong resemblance to the author.</p>
        <p>John Noble Wilford, a senior science writer for The New York Times, covered early space flights and all the lunar landings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Noble Wilford, a senior science writer for The New York Times, covered early space flights and all the lunar landings.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
