<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Brooklyn to Montauk, One Step at a Time; On a Nine-Day Hike, an Intimate 'Warts and All' Portrait of the Island Emerges</title>
    <meta content="08HIKE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellis, Patty</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toy, Vivian S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1D61E3DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Brooklyn to Montauk, One Step at a Time; On a Nine-Day Hike, an Intimate 'Warts and All' Portrait of the Island Emerges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN S. TOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toy, Vivian S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Patty Ellis, 43, who just completed 150-mile walk for charity from Fort Hamilton in Brooklyn to Montauk Point; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are few things that Patty Ellis enjoys more than walking. She likes to  walk along Jones Beach, and she walks regularly during her lunch hour at work. Walking gives her a chance to think, she says, and to quietly enjoy her surroundings.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis, 43, of Garden City Park, was on one of her walks along the beach when it occurred to her, ''I could just walk all day,'' she said. That thought led to others: Why not walk all day and then some, to walk the entire length of Long Island? And in the process raise some money for charity?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are few things that Patty Ellis enjoys more than walking. She likes to  walk along Jones Beach, and she walks regularly during her lunch hour at work. Walking gives her a chance to think, she says, and to quietly enjoy her surroundings.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis, 43, of Garden City Park, was on one of her walks along the beach when it occurred to her, ''I could just walk all day,'' she said. That thought led to others: Why not walk all day and then some, to walk the entire length of Long Island? And in the process raise some money for charity?</p>
        <p>There is probably no better way to see Long Island, from its western edge in Brooklyn all the way to Montauk Point. Few people even consider Brooklyn and Queens part of Long Island anymore, Ms. Ellis said, and she even thought about dropping them from her itinerary. ''But then I thought that would be like climbing half a mountain,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Plotting a route, though, proved to be much more of a challenge than she anticipated. The actual distance from one end of the Island to the other is about 120 miles, she estimated, but finding roads with sidewalks or at least some protection from automobile traffic was no easy task. She pored over maps for days and drove the length of the Island twice before settling on a 150-mile course along the South Shore, which would take her nine days to complete.</p>
        <p>To prepare, Ms. Ellis embarked on an eight-week training schedule, alternating long hikes of 12 to 18 miles with shorter ones of 3 to 7 miles.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis started her hike on a bike path beneath the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge on Sept. 23 and finished on the rocks of Montauk Point on Oct. 1. She walked from about 8 a.m. until 4 p.m. each day, averaging about 15 miles a day. She stayed with friends or family along the way, and  each morning, her support van took her back to the previous day's end point.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis, who is single, took a week of vacation for the walk, subsisting on cans of tuna and chickpeas, nutrition bars and fruit. After the 150 miles, she was a little disappointed to find that she didn't lose any weight, ''but I did discover some muscles I never knew I had,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A trek like this one produces a snapshot-by-snapshot portrait of Long Island, from the streets of Brighton Beach, where store signs beckon shoppers in Russian, Hebrew, Arabic and Spanish, to the monotonous heart of suburban Long Island, where it's hard to detect where one strip mall ends and another begins, from the faded glory of the beach hotels of Rockaway Park to the sprawling new-money summer estates of Westhampton Beach.</p>
        <p>At the end of her journey, Ms. Ellis contemplated all that she had seen, and her two strongest impressions were of trash and traffic.</p>
        <p>''Some places in the Rockaways, it was like people took garbage pails and flipped them on their sides,'' she said. ''And yes, they even litter in East Hampton.''</p>
        <p>She worried about the continuous bombardment of carbon monoxide she inhaled in the wake of heavy traffic along Montauk Highway.</p>
        <p>The ocean, timeless and serene, provided a counterpoint, glimpsed beyond the marshes along the Belt Parkway, from the Rockaway and Long Beach boardwalks or, finally, from the hills in Montauk.</p>
        <p>But overall, Ms. Ellis said, she was astonished by how much Long Island has changed since she was a child growing up in Copiague. It was as if most of the Island had undergone the same sort of transition she remembered in her hometown, when dozens of towering oak trees that formed a perfect shadowy arch over Great Neck Road were chopped down so the village could widen the road.</p>
        <p>''There's definitely a lot more strip malls and a lot less trees now,'' she said. ''It's just so much more dense.''</p>
        <p>She recalled how in the mid-1970's she and her boyfriend at the time would think nothing of jumping into a car for what they called their ''grand circle drive'': they would cruise west along the Southern State Parkway, head around Brooklyn on the Belt Parkway for the ocean view, admire the Manhattan skyline from the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway and travel home on the Long Island Expressway. ''We'd do it like once a month just to go for a drive,'' she said. ''But you couldn't pay me enough to do that now.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis's walk raised more than  $28,000 for the St. Jude Children's Research Hospital in Memphis. Most of the money came in small donations -- $30 was the average -- from some 250 friends, family members and companies. One of the largest amounts, $1,000, came from the Liberty Maritime Corporation, the steamship company in Lake Success where Ms. Ellis is the controller.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis, whose grandparents immigrated from Lebanon in the late 1800's, said she chose St. Jude's mainly because it was founded by Danny Thomas, the actor who championed his Lebanese roots. ''Plus when I saw what some of these kids have to go through, it broke my heart, and I wanted to do something to help,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The logo for her trek, which she wore pinned to her shirt every day, carried the words ''Take a Hike Patty'' above a map of Long Island with bright yellow footsteps across the South Shore. ''Walking Long Island to help save children's lives'' appeared in smaller letters.</p>
        <p>''This really was a grass-roots effort,'' said Linda Selden, a friend of Ms. Ellis's who trailed her in a support van for eight of the nine days of her hike. ''Just a lot of friends making sure she could do it, and in the end, the kids will benefit.''</p>
        <p>Each day, Ms. Ellis talked by cell phone with a reporter, who drove out to meet her on four of the nine days of her trek. Here are some of the sights and sounds Ms. Ellis encountered on her walk.</p>
        <p>Day 1: Brooklyn</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis and her support team, mainly friends she has met at the Town of Oyster Bay Golf Course, where she plays regularly, gather along a bike path at the foot of the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge in Brooklyn. They momentarily block the path as they pose for a group picture and a biker shouts at them, ''How about opening your eyes?'' Ms. Ellis apologizes and mumbles, ''Getting yelled at in Brooklyn -- what a novel idea.''</p>
        <p>The support van, on temporary loan from a friend, carries water, food, first-aid supplies and a portable toilet, meeting Ms. Ellis every few miles so she can rest and refuel.</p>
        <p>This first day provides some of ''the nicest walking,'' she says, as she travels the Belt Parkway's bike path for most of Brooklyn and along the boardwalk in the Rockaways -- the whole time soaking in a sweeping  ocean view. She passes tidy one- and two-family homes along Cropsey Avenue as she heads toward Coney Island and then gets immersed in the Russian spoken by families in Brighton Beach. In Sheepshead Bay, she walks along the water, passing Italian restaurants and fishing boats.</p>
        <p>Day 2: Jones Beach</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis heads toward Atlantic Beach in Nassau County, but she gets into the van to cross the Marine Parkway Bridge because the bridge is being rebuilt and the pedestrian walkway is gone. This is the first of only two short stints when she does not travel Long Island on her own two feet.</p>
        <p>Once in Atlantic Beach she passes through a area of what she describes as resort homes, Long Island style. Most of them are occupied year-round, but beach clubs line the south shore of this barrier island, and the area exudes a certain seaside feeling.</p>
        <p>After going through Long Beach and Lido Beach, she heads onto the Loop Parkway and then the Meadowbrook Parkway to get to Jones Beach. This is not pedestrian-friendly territory, but she walks on the roads' grassy shoulders. For one treacherous stretch of the Loop that goes over Middle Bay, Ms. Ellis has to walk in a traffic lane because there is no shoulder at all.</p>
        <p>''I'm an outlaw!'' she exclaims by phone. She also has to cross two drawbridges, looking both ways for four-wheeled traffic and then in the other two directions for oncoming boats before proceeding.</p>
        <p>Day 3: The Babylon Line</p>
        <p>She walks along the Jones Beach boardwalk and then heads up the bike path along the Wantagh Parkway to get to Montauk Highway, which will be the main route for most of her journey. A nephew who works at WBAB-FM persuaded the station to promote Ms. Ellis's walk, so its van will meet her for the next five days. Listeners will be encouraged to cheer her on and contribute to her cause.</p>
        <p>One listener named Mike drives up to her this morning to deliver a bagel with cream cheese and some orange juice. ''I brought you breakfast,'' he says. ''I think what you're doing is great.'' Ms. Ellis marvels at the kindness of strangers.</p>
        <p>She crosses into Suffolk County at about midday. ''It only took me three days to do all of Brooklyn, Queens and Nassau, and now Suffolk's going to take me twice as long to finish,'' she says.</p>
        <p>She goes along Montauk Highway, paralleling the Babylon line of the Long Island Rail Road: Wantagh, Seaford, Massapequa, Massapequa Park, Amityville, Copiague, Lindenhurst, Babylon. This is home for her.</p>
        <p>She's a little surprised at how much the automobile exhaust bothers her.  She finds herself repeatedly crossing to the other side of the highway in search of the cleanest air.</p>
        <p>Day 4: Sayville</p>
        <p>Through West Islip, Brightwaters, Bay Shore, Islip, East Islip, Oakdale and West Sayville, she grows tired of the stream of shopping centers, only occasionally broken up by more traditional downtown areas with decorative street lamps. She takes a detour onto South Main Street in Sayville. ''It's going to cost me as much as a mile to go along this residential area, but I just had to get off that Montauk Highway,'' she says.</p>
        <p>It rains most of the day, and she  spends it hopping back from the curb to avoid being splashed by the big trucks spraying rainwater and mud.</p>
        <p>Day 5: Halfway There</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis goes through residential areas in Bayport and Blue Point and then winds up back on the Montauk Highway, walking through Patchogue, Bellport, Brookhaven, Shirley, Mastic and Moriches. The scenery is  more of the same: Strip malls struggling to define themselves with names like Majestic Corners, Garden Plaza, Town Plaza.</p>
        <p>She passes a number of ''pretty little lakes'' and town parks along the way. She reaches the halfway point of her trip in South Haven.</p>
        <p>Day 6: Along Dune Road</p>
        <p>She continues through East Moriches, passes the antique stores in the heart of Eastport, and then goes on to Remsenburg and Speonk. In Westhampton, she gets her first taste of the New England feeling that permeates the East End. Many of the homes predate the rise of suburbia and have a well-worn Colonial look about them.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ellis leaves Montauk Highway to travel along Dune Road, a quiet two-lane byway with lavish waterfront homes on either side. There is no roadside shoulder, but virtually no traffic since most of the houses are vacation homes and no one is out yet for the weekend.</p>
        <p>''Some of these houses are unbelievable,'' she says. ''When I look at them, I think: 'Boy, I really don't have a lot, do I? And I'm not a poor person either.' ''</p>
        <p>Many of the houses are newly constructed in styles that sometimes mimic old New England and sometimes rebel against it with expanses of glass and jagged shapes.</p>
        <p>Day 7: More Traffic</p>
        <p>She crosses the Shinnecock Inlet with the help of Tom Feret, who takes her across the quarter-mile stretch of water in his 20-foot powerboat. To get back to Dune Road on the east side of the inlet, Ms. Ellis has to cross off-limits sand dunes. ''That's the second time I broke the law now,'' she says.</p>
        <p>But, she adds, ''the dunes hurt me more than I hurt them.'' The scrub and burrs scraped her legs badly.</p>
        <p>Rejoining Montauk Highway in Southampton, she's surprised by the bumper-to-bumper traffic all the way to Bridgehampton. Instead of strip malls filled with nail salons and pizza parlors, she sees more roadside farmstands touting sweet corn and piles of perfectly shaped pumpkins. She's amazed at the history here: ''Bridgehampton, Settled 1656.''</p>
        <p>Day 8: East Hampton</p>
        <p>To get away from the congestion, which is much heavier this time of year than she had expected, she continues on Montauk Highway through Sagaponack and Wainscott but decides to take another detour off the main road in East Hampton. ''There have been stretches where it felt like a convoy, and not just cars, but trucks, too,'' she says. ''And if one more truck comes by and nearly blows my hat off again when it passes, I'm going to scream.''</p>
        <p>She turns onto Further Lane, passing the rolling fairways of the Maidstone Club's golf course. An avid golfer, she poses for a picture outside the the club with a sign that says, ''I will dye my blood blue, please just get me a tee time here.'' But she and her friends scurry off before a security guard can ask them what they're up to.</p>
        <p>Day 9: Montauk</p>
        <p>She travels the Montauk Highway through Napeague and Hither Hills State Parks and then heads to the narrower Old Montauk Highway to  get away from traffic.</p>
        <p>When she finally enters the park at Montauk Point, she has added to the back of her shirt the familiar bumper sticker that reads, ''Montauk -- The End.'' About a dozen friends and family members applaud her arrival, and she heads down to the beach and onto the rocks beneath the Montauk Lighthouse. With the vastness of water stretching to the east, she picks up a smooth speckled rock from the ocean. It will join a keepsake pebble picked up at the start of her trip under the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge.</p>
        <p>Day 10: Epilogue</p>
        <p>Before heading back to work, Ms. Ellis goes to the Long Beach boardwalk, where she did much of her training for her walk. She sits on a bench, ''purposefully not walking,'' she says, and stares out to sea. And then a thought occurs: ''You know, I feel like walking,'' she says.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
