<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Streetscapes/307-17 West 80th Street; Six Gothic-Style Row Houses That Date From 1894</title>
    <meta content="08SCAP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236994"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Upper West Side (Manhattan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Bernard S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Israels, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1DD163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1151" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Streetscapes/307-17 West 80th Street; Six Gothic-Style Row Houses That Date From 1894</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gray, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Christopher Gray Streetscapes article on six Gothic-style row houses on West 80th Street between West End Avenue and Riverside Drive, work of developer Bernard S Levy and architect Charles Israels; facades have changed little since they were built in 1894; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE houses at 307-17 West 80th Street are some of the most distinctive on the West Side, built in the last full decade of substantial row-house construction, when builders were seeking variety, not uniformity. The fronts of the buildings have changed little over the last century, but the interiors have continued to evolve with each new generation of owners.</p>
        <p>The six Gothic-style houses, 16 to 18 feet wide, were designed in 1894, between West End Avenue and Riverside Drive, the work of the developer Bernard S. Levy and the architect Charles Israels. An 1894 selling brochure, ''The Beautiful West Side: A Complete List of West Side Dwellings,'' offered the houses for sale at prices ranging from $24,500 to $26,000. The description of the homes gives some idea of what buyers were looking for: ''On the low stoop entrance plan, with dining room, butler's pantry and kitchen on the same floor. Two bathrooms, exposed plumbing, parlors in red mahogany, dining rooms quarter oak, second story oak, third and fourth stories ash, 17 rooms in each house.'' The pointed arches and peaked roofs give the houses a fairy-tale quality quite different from the usual West Side building.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE houses at 307-17 West 80th Street are some of the most distinctive on the West Side, built in the last full decade of substantial row-house construction, when builders were seeking variety, not uniformity. The fronts of the buildings have changed little over the last century, but the interiors have continued to evolve with each new generation of owners.</p>
        <p>The six Gothic-style houses, 16 to 18 feet wide, were designed in 1894, between West End Avenue and Riverside Drive, the work of the developer Bernard S. Levy and the architect Charles Israels. An 1894 selling brochure, ''The Beautiful West Side: A Complete List of West Side Dwellings,'' offered the houses for sale at prices ranging from $24,500 to $26,000. The description of the homes gives some idea of what buyers were looking for: ''On the low stoop entrance plan, with dining room, butler's pantry and kitchen on the same floor. Two bathrooms, exposed plumbing, parlors in red mahogany, dining rooms quarter oak, second story oak, third and fourth stories ash, 17 rooms in each house.'' The pointed arches and peaked roofs give the houses a fairy-tale quality quite different from the usual West Side building.</p>
        <p>In 1895 the new buyers moved in. They included Thomas Brown Jr., chief engineer for the Otis Elevator Company, who bought No. 307. He had already designed elevators for the Eiffel Tower and would later design those in the Woolworth Building. Brown moved from a slightly older row house at 121 West 85th Street.</p>
        <p>THE stockbroker Arthur Niles, 25, moved with his wife, Clara, to 315 West 80th Street, deserting the giant Navarro Flats at Central Park South and Seventh Avenue. The 1900 census taker recorded Arthur and Clara Niles in the house with their son, Arthur Jr., age 3, and three servants of German and Swedish birth.</p>
        <p>Later tenants in the row included George Hellman, a writer and art critic, who moved into 309 West 80th between 1905 and 1910. His son Geoffrey, born in 1907 and later a longtime writer for The New Yorker, spent his early years in the house.</p>
        <p>In June 1919, Arthur Niles Jr. -- by that time a student at Princeton -- let himself into his family's house, which was boarded up for the summer, and shot himself in the head. Later press accounts, offering no explanation for the suicide, said he had been married only the day before.</p>
        <p>By that time the growing crop of apartment buildings was siphoning off single-family homeowners. The 1915 census described 317 West 80th as containing furnished rooms. In 1920, 309 West 80th was a lodging house operated by Irene Jolly, 47, a widow, who had two servants serving six lodgers, all women, including two movie actresses. Despite their family tragedy, the Nileses were the last of the original owners to leave, finally selling their house in 1944.</p>
        <p>The houses were rather small to be cut up into many apartments, a condition that has inadvertently preserved much of their Victorian interiors. In more recent years, the homes have proved attractive to owners seeking to reconvert them to single-family use. The new owner of the Niles house, who works in the publishing industry, said that she and her husband removed two later bathrooms and a fire stair but that many of the original finishes survived. She requested anonymity for reasons of security.</p>
        <p>Working with Allanbrook Benic Czajka Architects and the restoration contractor Preserv, she and her husband have cleaned the facade and created a double-height room in the back. ''I think those houses are very special,'' she said about the entire row. ''I think of them as a little family.''</p>
        <p>Next door, at No. 317, another restoration project is under way at the house of the late Kermit Lansner, a longtime editor at Newsweek who died in May. Workers are cleaning the facade and rebuilding the projecting oriel window, which was built of galvanized iron over wood framing.</p>
        <p>FARTHER up the block, the owner of the old Brown house at 307 said he bought the house in 1994 when he was just beginning his family. The house is a mix of old and new -- much of the oak trim was installed by a previous owner, but the cabinets and fittings of the dressing room are unmistakably 1890's.</p>
        <p>Merilyn Helene Sandin-Zarlengo, who bought the row house at 309 West 80th in 1975, is the senior owner on the block. Soon after she moved in, Ms. Sandin-Zarlengo, a former professor of English at Hunter College, put in full-pane windows that swing in for cleaning. She also remodeled her kitchen -- she said that it used to have specially made oak bins for flour, sugar and other baking supplies, apparently original to the house. Her house is bustling with renovation fever -- a project is under way in almost every room. The dining room is complete -- she stripped the paneling herself about five years ago -- but the front parlor, where the floor has been ripped up, is filled with stained glass and recently stripped doors  awaiting installation.</p>
        <p>She made most of the stained glass in the house herself -- about 10 panels -- after taking a one-year course at Riverside Church. ''It's like sewing -- if you have the right tools, you can do anything,'' said Ms. Sandin-Zarlengo, who worked with other owners to get landmark status in 1985 for the Riverside West 80th-81st Street Historic District, which includes the row houses.</p>
        <p>On the second floor the hallway walls are down to the original primer. A new steambath is being installed, and she is finishing the stripping on intricate door surrounds.  She is going to hire an outside company to strip her intricate stair banister. Her house is in unusually intact condition, with many original light fixtures, mahogany doorknobs and servants' call buttons.</p>
        <p>''The logical thing to do,'' she said, running a hand over an irregular wall surface that was last uncovered a century ago, ''is to drywall it -- but I'll never do that. I like the unevenness, the age.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sandin-Zarlengo has no particular schedule. ''This is fun,'' she said. ''It'll be finished when it's finished.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
