<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Preview Series Offers Sneak Peek at Art Films</title>
    <meta content="08MINO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Key Sunday Cinema Club</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Madison Art Cinemas (Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gorlick, Arnold</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mencher, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minor, E Kyle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D71E3DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Preview Series Offers Sneak Peek at Art Films</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. KYLE MINOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Minor, E Kyle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Key Sunday Cinema Club, film and lecture series, to open at Madison Art Cinemas in Connecticut; cinema owner Arnold Gorlick and club operations director Andrew Mencher comment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ARNOLD GORLICK, owner of the Madison Art Cinemas, prides himself on showing  films on the cutting edge. And in playing host to the Key Sunday Cinema Club, he hopes to sharpen that edge. The seven-part film and lecture series, which starts today at 10:30 a.m., will introduce aficionados to films that have come out of the country's best festivals.</p>
        <p>''Bringing the Key Club to Madison Arts will help shape how the theater is perceived,'' said Mr. Gorlick. ''Most people want to know where the successful main stream films are. I want people to wake up and say, 'What's playing at Madison Art Cinemas?' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ARNOLD GORLICK, owner of the Madison Art Cinemas, prides himself on showing  films on the cutting edge. And in playing host to the Key Sunday Cinema Club, he hopes to sharpen that edge. The seven-part film and lecture series, which starts today at 10:30 a.m., will introduce aficionados to films that have come out of the country's best festivals.</p>
        <p>''Bringing the Key Club to Madison Arts will help shape how the theater is perceived,'' said Mr. Gorlick. ''Most people want to know where the successful main stream films are. I want people to wake up and say, 'What's playing at Madison Art Cinemas?' ''</p>
        <p>The eight-year-old Key Sunday Cinema Club meets annually in Atlanta, Boston, San Diego, San Francisco and Portland, Ore., as well as its native Washington, D.C. The series, which meets on selected Sunday mornings, previews independent American and foreign films before commercial release in the area. In the tradition of several film festivals, the Cinema Club does not reveal film selections before their showing.</p>
        <p>Each film is followed by a one-hour discussion led by a Cinema Club moderator. John MacKay, an assistant professor of Slavic languages and literatures specializing in Russian film at Yale University, will moderate the Madison series.</p>
        <p>''As far as I'm concerned,'' Mr. Gorlick said, ''John is the star of the series. He is extremely knowledgeable. I'm sure he will lead very interesting, lively discussions.''</p>
        <p>At some of the sessions, Mr. MacKay will be joined by an additional film scholar, writer, critic or even the director or actor whose work is being screened. Previous guest speakers in other cities have included the director John Sayles with his film ''Passion Fish,'' the film critic Bob Mondello from National Public Radio speaking on ''Shakespeare in Love'' and the actor Terence Stamp discussing ''Priscilla, Queen of the Desert.''</p>
        <p>Andrew Mencher, director of operations at the Key Sunday Cinema Club, said that Mr. Gorlick tried to land the series after attending a screening in Boston. ''Arnold really wanted it,'' he said from his office in Washington, D.C. ''He called us, very actively lobbying us. He told us the films he was showing and we knew there was potential.'' Madison Art Cinemas has distinguished itself as an art film house with such titles as ''East Is East,'' ''Gods and Monsters'' and ''Saving Grace.'' These are features that the Key Club has introduced to its members in the past.</p>
        <p>''We select our films from various festivals around the country and contact distributors to see if they have any movies they'd be willing to screen before their release,'' Mr. Mencher said. ''They are final cuts but have not yet been reviewed.''</p>
        <p>Some of the independent distribution companies that the Key Club has worked with include Miramax (''East Is East''), October Films (''The Celebration''), and Fox Searchlight (''Waking Ned Devine''). Smaller independent distributors such as Zeitgeist (''Earth'') and Lions Gate have also collaborated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mencher said that the Key Club serves its members, who enjoy seeing new films before the critics, as well as the distributors, who pay the Key Club for its involvement and get advance marketing in return. The Key Club rents the participating theaters.</p>
        <p>''This is not a cash cow for me,'' said Mr. Gorlick. Like most film theaters, Madison Art Cinemas suffered unusually slow business over the summer. ''I want to be a part of the community. I believe that doing a new series like this serves a growing film audience that truly wants to see some of the best movies being made today.''</p>
        <p>The Key Sunday Cinema Club's Premiere Fall 2000 Series begins today at 10:30 a.m., and continues on Oct. 22, Nov. 5 and 12, Dec. 3 and 10, and Jan. 7. The cost of the series is $98 (by credit card) and $95 if paid by check, and people can join after it starts. The number to call to join or for further information is (888) 467-0404. The Madison Art Cinemas is at 761 Boston Post Road in Madison.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
