<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region/New Jersey; Speculative Warehouses Head South on Turnpike</title>
    <meta content="08NJZO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236940"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DB1E3DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region/New Jersey; Speculative Warehouses Head South on Turnpike</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHELLE GARBARINE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE development of big boxy warehouses continues its march southward along the New Jersey Turnpike, most recently arriving at Exit 6A, where an industrial park is under way that will ultimately contain eight million square feet of space.</p>
        <p>Construction is to start this month on two speculative warehouses, totaling 540,000 square feet, at the Haines Industrial Center. It is rising on 700 acres between the Delaware River and Route 130, one mile from the interchange, in Burlington and Florence Townships in Burlington County.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE development of big boxy warehouses continues its march southward along the New Jersey Turnpike, most recently arriving at Exit 6A, where an industrial park is under way that will ultimately contain eight million square feet of space.</p>
        <p>Construction is to start this month on two speculative warehouses, totaling 540,000 square feet, at the Haines Industrial Center. It is rising on 700 acres between the Delaware River and Route 130, one mile from the interchange, in Burlington and Florence Townships in Burlington County.</p>
        <p>The planned buildings join two others, totaling 1.13 million square feet, developed at the center since it was started last October. The earlier structures have drawn National Freight and the B. J.'s Wholesale Club as tenants, according to the developer, the Whitesell Construction Company of Delran, an active commercial builder in South Jersey.</p>
        <p>The project reflects the continuing strength of the state's industrial market, as well as efforts by Burlington County to revive the Route 130 corridor. The corridor, a thriving retail strip that has fallen on hard times, extends from Florence 16 miles south to Cinnaminson. ''It is certainly key to the redevelopment of, and brings a new mix of uses to, the corridor,'' James K. Wujcik, director of the Burlington County Board of Freeholders, said of the project.</p>
        <p>Officials in Florence and Burlington said they supported the development of the Haines center site but noted that it been a long time in coming. For years, the county envisioned the site as a regional food distribution center, which was never realized.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Richards Jr. the president of Whitesell, which bought the site in 1998, said Haines Industrial Center would cost $300 million. ''We expect to complete it in five years, with some luck,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Haines Industrial Center is the new kid on the warehouse distribution block in the state. It competes with the established northerly markets at Exit 8A in Middlesex County and Exit 7A in Mercer County for regional tenants seeking 300,000 square feet or more.</p>
        <p>Such tenants will gravitate to those markets that can accommodate their size, which they need to expand or consolidate scattered operations under one roof as well as to set up central distribution hubs, said Frank V. Caccavo Jr., a senior director at the Iselin office of Cushman &amp; Wakefield, the real estate services concern. His company says that there are at least six tenants with requirements of 300,000 square feet or more currently in the market.</p>
        <p>John Horan, a senior vice president at the Laurence Harbor office of Coldwell Banker Commercial Feist &amp; Feist, another brokerage, added, ''The 6A market does not spell the end of 8A, which will continue to fill up,  first because its centralized location can't be beat, particularly for tenants who want to be closer to Manhattan.''</p>
        <p>Speculative development at Exit 8A continues, as developers put up buildings to meet the demand for large modern warehouse space. Three such buildings are under way, totaling 1.6 million square feet and there are approvals in place for 2 million more square feet.</p>
        <p>IN the last year, however, leasing activity fell to 1.1 million square feet from 2 million. Mr. Caccavo said the decrease ''is due to the lack of completed new buildings in the first half of the year.'' He said activity would bounce back by the first quarter of next year as new buildings come on line. At the same time average asking rents rose by 15 cents, to $4.97 a square foot, a year.</p>
        <p>In the Exit 7A market, where most buildings are being built for specific tenants, production is also brisk. For instance, at the 400-acre Northeast Business Center in Washington Township, three buildings are under way, totaling two million square feet, according to the developer, the Matrix Development Group of Cranbury, which is also among the larger developers in the Exit 8A market.</p>
        <p>Alec Taylor, a partner at Matrix, said users were attracted by the availability of land and the dependability of approvals. Another factor, he said, is timing -- tenants want space ready when they expand or enter a market.</p>
        <p>The question for Exit 6A, Mr. Caccavo said, is how much of a speculative market exists. Mr. Horan of Coldwell Banker Commercial added that Exit 6A ''will snag its share of tenants'' because of price.</p>
        <p>Average rents at the Haines Center are $4.50 a square foot. Mr. Richards said the project offers tenants ''more bang for their buck'' because taxes, housing and labor costs are lower in South Jersey than in North Jersey.</p>
        <p>In addition, he said the roads to the project make it ''as accessible, if not more accessible,'' as an East Coast distribution hub than the more northerly interchanges. Along with the New Jersey Turnpike, where the Exit 6A interchange opened last year and connects to the Pennsylvania Turnpike, the site is accessible to Interstates 95 and 295 as well as Route 130.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Richards said, it is also served by a freight train and is along the path of the 34-mile commuter light rail line from Trenton to Camden, now under way. A station is planned within the center. The $604 million light rail project, financed with state money, is to be completed by early 2003.</p>
        <p>Those transportation links were not always at the Haines site, which sat dormant for nearly two decades. In the 80's, the state selected it for a regional food distribution center meant to spur economic growth in South Jersey.</p>
        <p>Though the state abandoned the plan in 1990, the county pursued it. Under the plan, the county, using public money, would have bought the site, developed the infrastructure and attracted developers to acquire parcels within the center. But the county never finally acquired the site, which Whitesell ultimately bought for $12.5 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wujcik, the freeholder director, said the county supported Whitesell's purchase because attracting a private developer was the ultimate aim. The current project, he added, is expected to generate the same amount of tax revenue as the food distribution center, which was projected at $7 million a year.</p>
        <p>The mayor of Burlington, Joseph Foy, and the mayor of Florence, Michael Muchowski, said the project would help stabilize taxes in their communities.</p>
        <p>It is also proceeding as other sites along Route 130 gain new life. An example is the renovation and expansion of one of 13 shuttered buildings that make up the former Willingboro Plaza, a 514,000-square-foot retail strip that fell into decline in the last decade.</p>
        <p>The 160,000-square-foot building will be refurbished and expanded by 100,000 square feet for reuse as an automated mail-service pharmacy for Merck-Medco Managed Care  of Franklin Lakes, a subsidiary of Merck &amp; Company. It is the first phase of the redevelopment of the former mall into a mixed-use development, with up to 1.2 million square feet.</p>
        <p>The 700 acres where the Haines Industrial Center is taking shape is the only site along the corridor for new development. Mr. Richards of Whitesell said knowing the turnpike exit and the light rail were realities influenced his company's decision to buy the site.</p>
        <p>The company also owns adjacent land where it built 560,000 square feet of industrial space. ''This is another step,'' he said of the current project.</p>
        <p>The first two buildings have attracted tenants relocating from areas farther south. One building, with 504,000 square feet, was started on speculation last year and has been leased to National Freight of Vineland. The second building, with 603,000 square feet, is being built for B. J.'s Wholesale Club, based in Natick, Mass., which is expanding from a 300,000-square-foot warehouse in Bristol, Pa.</p>
        <p>Ray Sareeram, senior vice president of logistics at B. J.'s, said his company had settled on the Exit 6A site after an 18-month search that included looking in the Exit 8A and Exit 7A markets. ''Our president, Jack Nugent, gave a strong directive, 'find the best available location that would enable us to preserve our work force,' '' Mr. Sareeram said. In relocating to the Haines Center, he said, he expects to retain all 200 current employees. The company, which will eventually double that work force, will occupy the building by March 2001.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richards said the center ''is still in its infancy.'' But, he added, with the next two buildings ''the center could begin to take on a life of its own.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
