<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Schools Forced to Deal With Another Fad</title>
    <meta content="08SCOO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scooters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowles, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD91E3DF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Schools Forced to Deal With Another Fad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM BOWLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bowles, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>School districts in Connecticut confront as scooter fad as more and more elementary and middle school children ride them to school; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABOUT 90 percent of the 432 pupils who attend Old Greenwich School walk to the elementary school. So when 200 of them decided to make that trip on scooters on opening day in early September, the principal, Majorie Sherman, was suddenly faced with a problem.</p>
        <p>''This is a congested area,'' Ms. Sherman said. ''There are dogs, cars, and baby carriages. Add to that scooters and it was a dangerous situation. We could not accommodate even the collapsed scooters because there was no place to store them.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABOUT 90 percent of the 432 pupils who attend Old Greenwich School walk to the elementary school. So when 200 of them decided to make that trip on scooters on opening day in early September, the principal, Majorie Sherman, was suddenly faced with a problem.</p>
        <p>''This is a congested area,'' Ms. Sherman said. ''There are dogs, cars, and baby carriages. Add to that scooters and it was a dangerous situation. We could not accommodate even the collapsed scooters because there was no place to store them.''</p>
        <p>So she asked parents to keep the scooters at home.</p>
        <p>Several educators said that scooters, like skateboards and in-line skates before them, have become the preferred mode of transportation for a growing number of students at some schools in Connecticut. The trend has forced districts to decide what to do about these slick two-wheelers, which are a cross between skateboards and bicycles, with upright handlebars and a foot board.</p>
        <p>''This is another example of the marketplace making items that are appealing to young people, but are disruptive to the education process,'' said Thomas W. Murphy, spokesman for the Connecticut Department of Education. ''There were beepers, Pokemon cards and now scooters. There seems to be a succession of these items.''</p>
        <p>Wanda Kowalski, co-president of the Stamford Parent-Teacher Council, said scooters appeared to be more popular among elementary and middle school students than high school students. The good news, she added, is that many of the children in her neighborhood use helmets, a comfort to this registered nurse who has heard the horror stories of scooter riders who have been accidentally hit by cars.</p>
        <p>''It's arrived here big time,'' Ms. Kowalski said. ''You can't turn your back without running into scooters. It's the thing to have.''</p>
        <p>Jessica Shaver of New Haven bought a scooter for her 12-year-old son, Michael.</p>
        <p>''It reminds me of the archetype toys of when I was a kid,'' she said. ''I would like to get one myself. I'm just waiting for the price to go down.''</p>
        <p>The regular scooters cost about $100 or more. Because the scooters fold up and weigh as little as nine pounds, students find it convenient to ride them to school and carry them into class in their backpacks and store them in a closet.</p>
        <p>Michael Shaver takes his scooter to school because he said it is easy to travel with. ''It's faster than taking the bus, so I don't have to get up as early,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And they are great for tricks. Michael is trying to perfect a ''tail-whip'' stunt on his scooter, which involves hopping off the board while in mid-air, keeping the handles straight and kicking the board until it spins 360 degrees before hopping back on.</p>
        <p>Michael is one of about six children who regularly take their scooters to a school building on State Street in New Haven, which temporarily houses the students of the Worthington Hooker and Benjamin Jepson middle schools.</p>
        <p>The school's assistant principal, Kim Johnsky, has given him and five others permission to store their scooters in a corner of her office.</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnsky said that while her district did not have a policy on scooters, she saw no problem with students taking them to school as long as they are not used on the property. Each school district makes its own decision about such matters.</p>
        <p>Patrice McCarthy, deputy director and general counsel for the Connecticut Association of Boards of Education, said boards had not asked the association what to do concerning scooters. She said she expected that most boards will simply add scooters to existing policies forbidding the use of skateboards on school property during school hours.</p>
        <p>That's what Ms. Sherman's school planned to do. Initially, she asked parents in a newsletter not to allow their children to bring scooters to school because it wasn't safe. That was enough to reduce the number of students who took their scooters to school, Ms. Sherman said. But soon the school will formally ban scooters by outlining the prohibition in the student handbook.</p>
        <p>Superintendent Michael Frechette of the Norwich Public Schools, whose district includes about 4,000 students in 10 elementary schools and 2 middle schools, said he had not seen any of his students use a scooter, but added that he would not have a problem with students taking them to school as long as they are not used on the property.</p>
        <p>''We would treat scooters like we do an instrument,'' Mr. Frechette said. ''It's used for an after-school activity.''</p>
        <p>Already about a dozen skateboards are stored daily in each of the two middle schools. Students use them after school in a new skateboard park in town.</p>
        <p>The scooter craze has not taken over the entire state. Several administrators, including Superintendent Patrick Proctor in Windham, said students were not riding them to school.</p>
        <p>''We don't seem to be encountering problems with scooters like our neighbors to the south,'' Mr. Proctor said, ''though Rollerblading certainly has come to Windham. It may be in part that our terrain is less friendly. It's hilly here. The roads in Windham don't lend themselves to scootering.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Proctor, who in-line skates with his wife, oversees about 3,400 students in a high school, middle school, alternative high school, and four elementary schools. Signs posted at each school prohibit the use of in-line skates and skateboards, a ban that Mr. Proctor said would apply to scooters.</p>
        <p>Kathleen Higgins, principal of John B. Sliney Elementary School in Branford, said she had seen many children ride scooters in their neighborhoods but she had not seen any of the 450 students at the K-4th grade school take one into her building.</p>
        <p>''They haven't slipped one by me yet,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
