<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind the Experts' Smoke, There's More Smoke</title>
    <meta content="08ESSA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/business/08ESSA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EFD7163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind the Experts' Smoke, There's More Smoke</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on at least five factors that are weighing on performance of actively managed mutual funds; drawing (M)0</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PLEASE ignore most of what you read in this section.</p>
        <p>And not just here, but in every monthly, quarterly, millennial, latitudinal, astrological or philosophical review of mutual funds that has ever crash-landed on your front doorstep. Skip to sports or the editorial page; scan the weddings or death notices, depending on taste. But save the carefully assembled charts here for fish wrap and kindling. They burn easily, you'll find, though it will be smoky. All that ink.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PLEASE ignore most of what you read in this section.</p>
        <p>And not just here, but in every monthly, quarterly, millennial, latitudinal, astrological or philosophical review of mutual funds that has ever crash-landed on your front doorstep. Skip to sports or the editorial page; scan the weddings or death notices, depending on taste. But save the carefully assembled charts here for fish wrap and kindling. They burn easily, you'll find, though it will be smoky. All that ink.</p>
        <p>Why this contradictory advice? Because the mutual fund business is founded on a myth that is aided and abetted by well-meaning sections like this one. The myth is that actively managed diversified funds, especially those that buy large-capitalization stocks, have much but luck to thank when they outperform the overall stock market.</p>
        <p>Though United States diversified funds have been on a hot streak that continued in the third quarter, big funds face long odds in beating the market in the long run.</p>
        <p>The funds' own growth has made the task that much more difficult. And it is about to become even harder, because of new rules from the Securities and Exchange Commission. Over all, at least five factors are weighing on the performance of actively managed funds:</p>
        <p>A VANISHING EDGE -- Fund managers once received information from companies and  Wall Street analysts weeks before individual investors did, but that gap has now  shrunk to hours or minutes. And in August, the S.E.C. issued its new rules, which aim to make the gap disappear by requiring any piece of material information to be disclosed to all investors simultaneously.</p>
        <p>Sure, big fund companies have tried to keep their edge by hiring more of their own analysts to follow industries and companies and to produce proprietary research. The asset management division of Citigroup, for example, has more than 120 analysts and researchers worldwide, and Citigroup is only the 10th-largest money manager in the United States. But make no mistake. The game has become much more difficult for big fund groups. Getting a tip from a friendly company about sales of a new product was easy. Proprietary research is predicting the future, which is hard.</p>
        <p>THE BULL IN THE CHINA SHOP -- Individual investors can buy or sell most stocks without moving the price of the shares they are trading. But fund companies, especially giants like Janus and Putnam, which have hundreds of billions of dollars under management, lack that luxury. They must spend time and effort concealing their intentions, or smaller traders will jump in front of them, bidding up stocks that the big companies are buying and pushing down shares that they are selling.</p>
        <p>In addition, once a major fund company takes a big position in a stock, it becomes an all-but-permanent holder. Janus, which makes big bets on technology companies, owned more than 260 million shares of Nokia, the Finnish cell phone giant, as of June, according to an S.E.C. filing. That $10 billion stake represented nearly 6 percent of the company. On an average day, about seven million Nokia shares change hands, so Janus's stake would take months to sell without disrupting the market. Along the way, other investors would dump their shares quickly if they learned that Janus's faith in Nokia was flagging. So Janus is wed to Nokia, for better or worse.</p>
        <p>THE WINNER'S CURSE -- A well-marketed, top-performing fund will attract hundreds of millions of dollars in new money looking for the next hot investment vehicle. That forces fund managers into difficult choices. They can load up on the best of the stocks that they already own, increasing the odds that a single negative announcement will ruin returns. They can look for new stocks to buy, at the risk of stretching themselves too thin and neglecting research on companies they already own. Or they can add analysts to cover sectors and companies that they do not. But the new hires may not be as skilled as the managers who have picked them.</p>
        <p>THE DRAG OF FEES -- Don't forget fees and sales charges. For actively managed funds, annual fees usually run 0.5 to 2 percentage points a year, depending on the fund's size; the average is about 1.6 percent. But fees of passively managed funds, which seek only to match the performance of the benchmark they track, are often less than 0.2 percent.</p>
        <p>For any one year, that is only a small difference, which is why in some years, like 1999, the majority of active funds beat the indexes. But over a longer period, beating the market by even one percentage point a year, annualized, is very difficult.</p>
        <p>Yet because of the fees, one percentage point is the minimum level of outperformance required for most actively managed funds to even match a passive fund. Perhaps that is why fewer than one in 10 actively managed funds could equal the performance of the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 over the five years through 1999.</p>
        <p>THOSE HIGHER TAX BILLS -- Taxes are the great hidden cost faced by fund investors. Passively managed funds are very tax efficient, because they do not trade often. They buy stocks only when they receive new money and sell only if they face redemptions. In practice, this means that they almost never sell, since they usually have net inflows, not outflows. So they almost never have to pay capital gains taxes, either long-  or short-term.</p>
        <p>In contrast, active managers have the bad habit of buying and selling stocks. A lot. After all, that is what they are paid to do. And they hardly care about taxes. They and the companies that employ them want to be able to advertise big shiny returns.</p>
        <p>If achieving those returns means accumulating huge capital gains that are distributed to shareholders at year-end, so be it. Never mind that in areas like New York City, the marginal federal and state tax rate on short-term capital gains -- treated as ordinary income -- can be over 50 percent. Though investors are starting to choose funds based on after-tax returns, the top-line returns, not bottom-line gains for shareholders, are still what usually matter to fund companies.</p>
        <p>All of this is, in a word, discouraging. So what can you do about it?</p>
        <p>Aside from investing in passively managed funds, not much. If you choose to buy actively managed funds, try to pick ones that have good long-term records, with long term meaning five years or more, because some academic evidence supports the idea that managers who have beaten the S.&amp; P. 500 for long stretches will continue to beat it. (Unfortunately, this strategy did not hold up well in the late 1990's, as many experienced investors, including legends like Warren E. Buffett and Julian Robertson, were blindsided by the market's sudden turn toward technology stocks.)</p>
        <p>You can also try buying sector funds, like biotechnology or financial services funds.  They have two big advantages over other actively managed portfolios. First, they are usually smaller, so they do not have much trouble trading.</p>
        <p>Second, and more important, sector managers focus on small groups of companies. They can actually do all the things investment professionals are supposed to do, like getting to know the company managers and figuring out which companies have the best products. Research into products is especially important in biotechnology, where many companies never develop anything salable, and in information technology, which has extremely fast product cycles.</p>
        <p>But sector funds' returns show tremendous variation, even though the funds  choose among the same relatively small groups of companies. Over the last four quarters, as biotech funds soared, the Dresdner RCM Biotechnology fund rose 264 percent, making it the best performer in its field and among all funds (Article, Page 17). Yet the Fidelity Select Biotechnology was up 112 percent -- a great gain, but less than half of the Dresdner fund's.</p>
        <p>Buying a few sector-specific funds may offer another way to get the expertise that fund companies are charging so dearly for. But they are not without risk, because they tend to rise and fall with the fortunes of their chosen industries. In terms of risk, they are no substitute for a good diversified fund.</p>
        <p>Like, say, an S.&amp; P. 500 index fund.</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
