<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Down the Years, a Slippery Foe Frustrated the U.S.</title>
    <meta content="08DIPL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/world/08DIPL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237263"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE DIPLOMACY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holbrooke, Richard C (Amb)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5DE133CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Down the Years, a Slippery Foe Frustrated the U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Washington celebrates downfall of Slobodan Milosevic, who for years delighted in defying, befuddling and belittling his far more powerful foes; Clinton administration officials say Milosevic caused as many internal debates and as much anguish in Washington as any opponent; some skirmishes were between Secretary of State Madeleine K Albright, who holds special kinsip to Balkans from her birth, and ambassador to United Nations, Richard C Holbrooke, forceful diplomat who has dealt with Milosevic more than any otehr American official; Holbrooke calls Milosevic 'arsonist' of south-central Europe, and cautions that Milosevic's quick decision to stay on in political life would be 'vastly complicating'; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the mid-1990's, when the United States was trying to end the war in Bosnia and then enforce the peace, Washington's contacts with Slobodan Milosevic were frequent, volatile and very much in person.</p>
        <p>Often, after a shouting match over policy with American diplomats in his palace in Belgrade, Mr. Milosevic would signal a servant to open the doors to a large dining room, where a meal of several courses awaited and where the conversation could be, according to participants, jocular and cordial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the mid-1990's, when the United States was trying to end the war in Bosnia and then enforce the peace, Washington's contacts with Slobodan Milosevic were frequent, volatile and very much in person.</p>
        <p>Often, after a shouting match over policy with American diplomats in his palace in Belgrade, Mr. Milosevic would signal a servant to open the doors to a large dining room, where a meal of several courses awaited and where the conversation could be, according to participants, jocular and cordial.</p>
        <p>Relations with Mr. Milosevic at  that period were never warm, but were at the height of a roller-coaster ride that coursed over a decade from a lack of attention during a Bush presidency distracted first by the fall of Communism elsewhere, and then by fighting Saddam Hussein, to outright war last year under President Clinton. Now, finally, Washington is celebrating the downfall of a man who for years delighted in defying, befuddling and belittling his far more powerful foes.</p>
        <p>As the Clinton administration tries to temper its pleasure, senior officials are looking back at an opponent -- the last of the major East European strongmen -- who has caused as many internal debates and as much anguish in Washington as any other.</p>
        <p>Some of the skirmishes were between the secretary of state, Madeleine K. Albright, who with her Czechoslovak origins and childhood memories of Belgrade holds a special kinship to the Balkans and Eastern Europe, and the ambassador to the United Nations, Richard C. Holbrooke, a forceful diplomat who did the unpalatable deal with Mr. Milosevic to end the war in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>From the beginning, these kinds of diplomatic differences marked Washington's relations with Yugoslavia. In 1990 and 1991, the ambassador to Yugoslavia, Warren Zimmerman, felt that the Bush administration, distracted by the Persian Gulf war, made too little effort, too late, to stop the brewing conflict in Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>Secretary of State James A. Baker said in 1991 that the United States did ''not have a dog in that fight,'' that  Washington's national interest was not centered on the Balkans and that it was unwise to commit American troops there.</p>
        <p>In 1992, while running for the presidency, Mr. Clinton seemed to suggest that he would do more to confront Mr. Milosevic and the Bosnian Serbs, who were besieging Sarajevo, the Bosnian capital, and conducting the worst killing in Europe since World War II.</p>
        <p>Once in power, the Clinton administration wanted little to do with the conflict, which it regarded as Europe's business and which it believed could be contained by United Nations sanctions imposed on Yugoslavia in 1992. In Congressional testimony, Secretary of State Warren Christopher called the killing in Bosnia ''a problem from hell.''</p>
        <p>In a tentative foray into the Balkans in 1993, Mr. Christopher, who never seemed persuaded by what he was trying to sell, went to Europe to persuade the allies to agree to a ''lift and strike'' policy. This called for the lifting of an arms embargo that had been placed on all of former Yugoslavia -- thus giving the well-armed Serbs an automatic advantage over the outgunned Bosnian Muslims -- and the launching of strategic NATO airstrikes at Bosnian Serb targets.</p>
        <p>The British and French, who had troops in Bosnia as part of a United Nations force, objected strongly to airstrikes, and the Clinton White House backed off.</p>
        <p>By 1995, with the killing in Bosnia under way for three years and unpunished, the Clinton administration looked for a way to end the conflict.</p>
        <p>The engagement with Mr. Milosevic turned from sporadic contact to  full-fledged diplomatic involvement.</p>
        <p>First, though, the administration had to make a critical decision. Should it deal with Mr. Milosevic, the mastermind of the war, or with his surrogates, the Bosnian Serbs, led by Radovan Karadzic?</p>
        <p>To decide that question, a diplomat with an uncanny skill for dealing with ugly regimes, Robert Frasure, was dispatched to Belgrade, where he held lengthy talks and had many meals with Mr. Milosevic. Mr. Frasure, who had negotiated with the Marxist dictator of Ethiopia, Mengistu Haile Mariam, who eventually fled his country, and then with the ruling white regime in South Africa, which ultimately collapsed, recommended dealing directly with the boss of the Balkans, Mr. Milosevic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frasure was one of four Americans killed when their armored personnel carrier drove over a mountainside in Bosnia as Mr. Holbrooke, Gen. Wesley K. Clark and other officials took a perilous road into Sarajevo because Bosnian Serb guns made it too dangerous to fly. Mr. Holbrooke then began a dizzying flurry of talks, meeting Mr. Milosevic as NATO launched its first sustained airstrikes against Bosnian Serb targets in September 1995. The negotiations culminated in the Dayton accords, reached at an Ohio air base that November and signed in Paris in December 1995.</p>
        <p>Critics charged that the administration became too close to Mr. Milosevic, treating him as part of the solution to the war, rather than part of the problem.</p>
        <p>At the time, there were arguments within the administration about whether sanctions against Mr. Milosevic should be eased. As ambassador to the United Nations, Dr. Albright was strongly opposed, as was Vice President Al Gore's top foreign policy adviser, Leon Fuerth.</p>
        <p>During this period all kinds of American officials visited Mr. Milosevic, including senators and House members, who would be shown on Serbian television -- lending, for Mr. Milosevic's purposes, authenticity to his reign.</p>
        <p>After the Dayton deal, which resulted in the dispatch of more than 30,000 peacekeeping troops to Bosnia, Mr. Holbrooke, and then the assistant secretary for European affairs, John Kornblum, continued to visit Belgrade. Their purpose was to persuade Mr. Milosevic to get his acolytes in the Serbian part of Bosnia to live up to their commitments at Dayton, including allowing Muslims hounded out of their homes to return.</p>
        <p>On one occasion, however, Mr. Milosevic delivered. In mid-1996, at Mr. Holbrooke's request, he engineered Dr. Karadzic's removal from office.</p>
        <p>By early 1998 Mr. Milosevic, as many feared, began to stir again, this time in the Serbian province of Kosovo, where a large Albanian majority began an armed rebellion against years of repression by the Yugoslav Army and Serbian police. Again, as in Bosnia, Mr. Milosevic's forces committed massacres and drove out thousands of Albanian families.</p>
        <p>In October 1998, Mr. Holbrooke returned to Belgrade to reason with the strongman. The upshot, after more than 10 days of argument and the threat of NATO bombing, was an agreement that allowed outside, unarmed monitors into Kosovo to observe a truce between the Serbian  forces and the growing Kosovo Liberation Army.</p>
        <p>A massacre by Serbs in the Albanian village of Racak in January 1999 decisively broke the truce. By then  Dr. Albright had decided that only force could bring Mr. Milosevic, now in charge of a diminished and isolated Serbia, under control. She argued strenuously at the White House for building a NATO consensus that if Mr. Milosevic did not agree to a NATO peacekeeping force in Kosovo he would be punished with airstrikes.</p>
        <p>She had also concluded that Yugoslavia, where she had walked the streets as a child when her father was the Czechoslovak ambassador to Belgrade, could not be a normal country with Mr. Milosevic at the helm. (Her only encounter with Mr. Milosevic -- in May 1997 in Belgrade as part of a tour of the Balkans as Secretary of State -- was, according to aides, confrontational and blunt.)</p>
        <p>With the war in Kosovo over, Mr. Milosevic remained in power, though indicted for war crimes by the international tribunal in The Hague.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright made no secret of her desire to see him go. She argued that the Serbs, and Europe, needed and deserved better.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Milosevic announced in July that he was holding direct elections for the presidency on Sept. 24, Washington had already prepared some ground by financing civic groups and independent media opposed to his regime. This support was rapidly fortified and an anti-Milosevic operation, intended to keep in contact with the opposition movement, was established under the American ambassador, William Montgomery, in Budapest.</p>
        <p>But the administration had to be careful. The opposition presidential candidate, Vojislav Kostunica, was fiercely independent and critical of American policy in Kosovo and Bosnia. In the end, the sweeping anti-Milosevic election result and the strength of the sentiment on the streets of Belgrade late this week were the work of the people.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Holbrooke, Mr. Milosevic was ''the arsonist of south-central Europe.''</p>
        <p>''As long as he was in power, you couldn't deal with the problems there,'' he said. ''Now he has gone, the real problems will emerge but at least you can deal with them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Holbrooke, who has dealt with Mr. Milosevic more than any other American official, cautioned that Mr. Milosevic's quick decision to stay on  in political life would be ''vastly complicating.''</p>
        <p>For Dr. Albright, the show of people power was a moment of vindication. She learned of Mr. Milosevic's collapse as she flew toward Washington after a disheartening round of Middle East talks.</p>
        <p>She was asked how his departure ranked among her moments in office. ''This is something very personal to me,'' she said, standing in the aisle of the secretary of state's plane. ''I have always felt very strongly that the Serbian people were terrific. They had gotten a lousy deal by being ruled by Milosevic.''</p>
        <p>SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE DIPLOMACY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
