<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Six Figures Add Up to Zero</title>
    <meta content="08MYMY$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/business/08MYMY.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237155"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MY MONEY, MY LIFE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gottlieb, Lori</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3DE153CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Six Figures Add Up to Zero</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LORI GOTTLIEB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gottlieb, Lori</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lori Gottli2</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN I was 10 years old, I would sit at my father's desk in his study, checking my math homework on his adding machine. One day, around tax time, I accidentally came across his pay stubs.</p>
        <p>My parents never talked about money, so I asked my 13-year-old brother what they meant. ''Dad makes six figures,'' he said, matter-of-factly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN I was 10 years old, I would sit at my father's desk in his study, checking my math homework on his adding machine. One day, around tax time, I accidentally came across his pay stubs.</p>
        <p>My parents never talked about money, so I asked my 13-year-old brother what they meant. ''Dad makes six figures,'' he said, matter-of-factly.</p>
        <p>''So?'' I replied.</p>
        <p>My brother rolled his eyes impatiently, explaining, ''We're rich, you moron.''</p>
        <p>Lesson learned: Making ''six figures'' was tantamount to being ''rich.'' So, in 1990, when I took my first job after college, I projected the number of years before I, too, would reach that summit. No matter what  number came first, there was something undeniably magical about those five zeroes interrupted by a comma -- that series of fat, black circles that encapsulated the American dream.</p>
        <p>I don't know at what age my father joined the Six-Figure Club, but I became a member in my late 20's. To commemorate the occasion, I framed that first pay stub and hung it in the back of my closet. ''I've arrived,'' I thought. ''I'm rich.''</p>
        <p>I invested in stocks. I treated my artist friends to movies. I ate a lot of sushi. I stopped getting stomach cramps the night before the rent was due each month. I even felt confident about putting my unborn children through college one day.</p>
        <p>Then, last year, when I was 32, something happened. I moved from Los Angeles to Silicon Valley and learned I wasn't rich at all. In fact, by the valley's standards, some people considered me downright poor.</p>
        <p>Nobody said it outright. They didn't have to. I could see the wealth all around me -- wealth that I most certainly didn't have. I paid $2,000 a month in rent and drove a new Acura, but that was nothing compared with the 20-somethings who were buying million-dollar homes in Pacific Heights and Palo Alto, pulling up to restaurants in their shiny, silver, 7-Series Bimmers.</p>
        <p>If there were people like me around, I didn't see them. No one else seemed to mind that the cheapest grade of gasoline cost more than $2 a gallon, that parking averaged $20 a pop and that women named Nancy, Shelley and Emily shelled out $300 a month for tiny nylon bags emblazoned with the name Kate.</p>
        <p>I USED to compare myself with my peers when it came to career achievement, but I had never felt competitive about net worth. The longer I spent in Silicon Valley, though, the more it became clear that a great fiscal fault line had emerged between me and them.</p>
        <p>They put expensive artwork on their walls, bought bona fide antiques, ordered custom granite tiles for their kitchens and toted sleek Tumi luggage. I, on the other hand, had Pottery Barn sofas, Restoration Hardware throw rugs, kitschy Curious George prints bought on the street and a clunky green suitcase. In the land of Haves, I was a Have Not: I did not have Netscape stock options.</p>
        <p>I knew, of course, that most people my age (heck, most people) weren't worth seven figures, let alone six. Still, it's easy to lose perspective when you go to lunch with a friend who says: ''So I hired this consultant for $12,000 a month. We only get him two hours a week, but it's totally worth it.''</p>
        <p>Suddenly, I found myself struggling to keep up. I joined my friends at restaurants I couldn't afford. I performed calculations in my mind, much like the math problems I used to do in my father's study: ''If Person A makes X, and Person B makes Y, how much more does A need to make so that X equals Y?''</p>
        <p>I hated myself for thinking that way, but I soon learned that the people I was chasing were trying to keep up with everyone else. No matter how much anyone had, it wasn't enough.</p>
        <p>''I'm switching jobs,'' a friend told me. ''I'm the only person in my building who doesn't have a weekend car.''</p>
        <p>That's when I realized that this wasn't just about keeping up with the Joneses. It was about keeping up with the jaded.</p>
        <p>I decided that it was time to get out of town. I visited a friend in the Midwest who told me that when he was granted tenure at his university, he would be making $70,000 a year. Add that to his income from freelance writing, and he could even make six figures. He was debating whether to accept the position.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot of money,'' he sighed, an assessment I found incredibly refreshing.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' I agreed. I meant it, too.  Six figures? Hmm. He'll be rich.</p>
        <p>MY MONEY, MY LIFE The writer, who lives in Palo Alto, Calif., is the author of ''Stick Figure: A Diary of My Former Self'' (Simon &amp; Schuster). Submit your account of struggling or succeeding as a worker, consumer, investor or entrepreneur to My Money, Money &amp; Business, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036, or by e-mail to mymoney@nytimes.com. All submissions become the property of The Times. They may be edited and may be republished in any medium.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">The writer, who lives in Palo Alto, Calif., is the author of ''Stick Figure: A Diary of My Former Self'' (Simon &amp; Schuster). Submit your account of struggling or succeeding as a worker, consumer, investor or entrepreneur to My Money, Money &amp; Business, The New York Times, 229 West 43rd Street, New York, N.Y. 10036, or by e-mail to mymoney@nytimes.com. All submissions become the property of The Times. They may be edited and may be republished in any medium.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
