<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is Jersey City Too Alluring?</title>
    <meta content="08ABAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237038"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE CITIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jersey City (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strunsky, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E2D6163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1079" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is Jersey City Too Alluring?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE STRUNSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strunsky, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>JERSEY CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on growing number of critics who say New Jersey no longer needs to offer tax abatements to lure developers to its once blighted waterfront; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twenty years ago, the word blighted aptly described the Jersey City waterfront.</p>
        <p>To lure developers to the crumbling west bank of the Hudson River, Jersey City took advantage of the state's tax abatement law, and since the 1980's, more than 30 buildings have been completed or are under construction, including over two dozen high-rise offices and apartments, two hotels and a mall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Twenty years ago, the word blighted aptly described the Jersey City waterfront.</p>
        <p>To lure developers to the crumbling west bank of the Hudson River, Jersey City took advantage of the state's tax abatement law, and since the 1980's, more than 30 buildings have been completed or are under construction, including over two dozen high-rise offices and apartments, two hotels and a mall.</p>
        <p>Today, the New Jersey waterfront is increasingly attractive to businesses and residents who want to be near Manhattan -- but not in it -- because of its exorbitance.</p>
        <p>As a result, a growing chorus of critics say there is no longer a need to be as generous. Abatements have become so common that Secaucus, North Bergen and Bayonne are suing Jersey City, claiming they have to make up for more than $4 million in Hudson County taxes that otherwise would have come from properties that have benefitted from this city's abatements. In addition, many homeowners here are fed up with the abatements, which they feel they are subsidizing with their property taxes.</p>
        <p>Spurred by such criticism, Mayor Bret Schundler has recently begun taking steps that he says will open the process by which abatements are granted.</p>
        <p>Apart from New Jersey's relatively low corporate taxes, labor costs lower than those across the river, swaths of vacant land and properties ready to be knocked down and rebuilt, what has also fueled the current boom is a diminishing supply of office space in New York City. Developers, corporate executives and city officials there say the shortage has challenged New York's ability to attract new businesses and stanch the flow of dozens of others -- including some of the leading investment houses -- across the Hudson.</p>
        <p>Against this backdrop, abatements continue unabated.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing left in Manhattan,'' said Mia Scanga, one of 40 homeowners here seeking a referendum to rescind an abatement recently granted to the 43-story Millennium Towers apartment planned at the base of the Palisades. ''And we're giving out tax abatements.''</p>
        <p>Last Tuesday, the group gave City Clerk Robert Byrne a petition with 3,343 signatures -- about 800 more than the number required to hold a referendum.</p>
        <p>''The minute they heard abatement they signed,'' said Robert Duval, vice president of the Sergeant Anthony Neighborhood Association, a member of the coalition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Byrne said that if the petition was certified, the referendum would be the first ever held to repeal an ordinance in the 40-year history of the city's present form of government.</p>
        <p>Currently, there are 89 properties here receiving tax abatements, making payments in lieu of taxes that total $48 million in revenue for the fiscal year 2001, up from $17 million in 1992, said Tom Gallagher, chief of staff to Mayor Schundler.</p>
        <p>Were the abatements not in place, the revenue generated for the same properties in fiscal 2001 would amount to close to $100 million. Of course, proponents of the abatements argue that without the inducements, the properties would not have been developed.</p>
        <p>A common perception is that abatements are mainly granted to waterfront office towers, and indeed, the number of those has grown to 19 from 11 in 1992. Moreover, office abatements generally involve the most money -- and the biggest savings for the recipient. But by far the most common type of abatement is for affordable housing projects, which account for 39 of the 89 abatements, Mr. Gallagher said.</p>
        <p>Despite the rising revenue, critics have complained that while abatements need the approval of the City Council, they are only presented to the full council after terms are negotiated privately by developers and members of the Schundler administration.</p>
        <p>City Councilman Robert Cavanaugh, who plans to run for mayor next year, said that he is not against abatements per se, but ''when you have the hottest economic development area in the country, you've done what the original legislation intended to do.''</p>
        <p>Whether the proposed procedure will be approved by the nine-member council is unclear. Council President Tom DeGise, a probable mayoral opponent of Mr. Cavanaugh in the spring, said he opposes the change because it would weaken the council's role.</p>
        <p>Critics of the waterfront abatements are not limited to political opponents of Mr. Schundler, who plans to enter the Republican race for governor.</p>
        <p>Donald Eisen, exective managing director for New Jersey operations of Cushman &amp; Wakefield, the real estate consulting firm, said that although the abatements had been ''very, very helpful'' in attracting developers, ''it's been such a long time that these abatements have not been necessary.''</p>
        <p>The increased demand for waterfront office space is reflected in several indicators. For example, in the market that includes the Jersey City, Hoboken and Weehawken waterfronts, last week there was only 10,500 square feet of vacant prime office out of an  inventory of more than 9 million square feet, said Mark Field of Cushman and Wakefield.</p>
        <p>In the same market, which is dominated by Jersey City, the current amount of total office space, which includes prime space and less desirable properties, is 12.3 million square feet -- with another 3 million square feet expected to be added within about a year -- as against 9.26 million in 1991, Mr. Field said. During that same period, he added, office rents have increased 40 percent, to about $35 a square foot from $25.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher said in an interview that the administration had toughened its negotiating stance with developers seeking tax abatements in response to the changing market. He cited a new policy limiting the life of an abatement for residential property to 20 years, down from the previous 30 years.</p>
        <p>The Schundler administration has recently begun drafting a plan to revise the abatement process, Mr. Gallagher said.</p>
        <p>Essentially, he said, the plan would create a committee made up of two council members -- including Mr. Cavanaugh -- representatives of the tax collector, the tax assessor and the business administrator's office, the city Department of Housing and Economic Development, the Law Department, the Office of Economic Opportunity, and a member of the public.</p>
        <p>The committee would hold public meetings during which it would question developers and discuss terms of the abatement before making a recommendation to the mayor. If the mayor accepted the arrangement, he would submit it to the full council for approval.</p>
        <p>THE CITIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
