<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Larchmont, an Apollonian Experience</title>
    <meta content="08DINE$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pascal's (Larchmont, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, M H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5DC163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Larchmont, an Apollonian Experience</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. H. REED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, M H</byline>
      <dateline>LARCHMONT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>M H Reed reviews Pascal's restaurant in Larchmont, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST when it seemed that the only restaurants to open were those serving Italian cuisine, Pascal's breezes in and sets up shop in the space last occupied by Hope and Anchor.</p>
        <p>The new restaurant joins a small handful of French spots clustered in the southeast portion of the county, an area that has attracted a sizable French-speaking population, one large enough to encourage a few of the supermarkets in the region to devote a section to French import products.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST when it seemed that the only restaurants to open were those serving Italian cuisine, Pascal's breezes in and sets up shop in the space last occupied by Hope and Anchor.</p>
        <p>The new restaurant joins a small handful of French spots clustered in the southeast portion of the county, an area that has attracted a sizable French-speaking population, one large enough to encourage a few of the supermarkets in the region to devote a section to French import products.</p>
        <p>Grace, clarity, balance -- Pascal's offers to the frazzled post-modern diners a truly Apollonian experience. Nothing is strident or trendy here. This classically serene space has been carefully constructed with high regard for the diner's comfort, aesthetic sensibility and palate.</p>
        <p>Flavorful sauces were applied gently, and arrangements were deliberate, architectural. Exquisitely presented, an amuse-gueule arrived once as a swirl of meltingly delicious chive-flecked salmon mousse and another time as a demitasse cup of creamy gazpacho, the vegetable flavors distinct despite the smoothness created by a food processor and cream.</p>
        <p>This kitchen favors circular constructions, which eventually become wearisome; nonetheless, presentations in no way interfered with the taste of some of the fine dishes concocted here.</p>
        <p>Appetizers were top-notch. Small bits of salmon tartare came beautifully balanced with fresh herbs and decorated, as many of the dishes were, with festive squiggles of color -- here one of lemon, there one of chive.</p>
        <p>A chunk of foie gras terrine topped a frilly green salad set in a remarkable avocado sculpture. A deft hand had cut and splayed the avocado slices to resemble the curve of a bowl; the piece stole the show. Four warm sauteed shrimp and a cool salad of diced tomato and mango brought irresistible counterpoints of hot and cold, and sweet and sour. And wafers of grilled Japanese eggplant came topped with asparagus spears and splashed with gingery vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>Of lesser interest, sweet-crusted vegetable tart of zucchini and eggplant seemed tame in this company. And saffron came on a mite strong in a sauce that moistened somewhat sticky sea scallops ''in a potato shell.'' The ''shell'' was a latticed fried potato lid that capped the dish.</p>
        <p>Generally outstanding appetizers presented a challenge to courses that followed, and most entrees rose to the occasion. Two of them shared first place. On a bed of basmati rice, almost transparent fillets of excellent monkfish were treated to a subtle curry sauce. Tiny cuts of vegetables were simply but notably well prepared and appeared on every plate. Also in the spotlight, under a gloss of olive oil merely hinting of garlic, satin-fleshed tuna rested on a deliciously earthy mushroom blini; it would be hard to say which element was better.</p>
        <p>Almost as good, a classic pairing of duck with fruit brought a virtually fatless breast drizzled with raspberry sauce. And a lovely item called lobster casserole was more an artistic assemblage. A large white bowl held a full tail, claws (shell removed, a thoughtful touch) and heady lobster broth.</p>
        <p>A couple of entrees arrived overdone. Fillet of lamb came more medium than medium rare, but the well-trimmed meat proved wonderfully flavorful nonetheless. Although matched with an exceptionally good fruit sauce, striped bass was poached to death: mealy and shriveled, a surprising gaff for this kitchen.</p>
        <p>Chocolate lovers might want to dig into dense, warm chocolate souffle with molten chocolate oozing from the center of its muffin form. Profiteroles with intensely chocolate sauce were another hit. Except for overly sweet raspberry sauce,  mousse glace Grand Marnier, creamy and subtle, would have been perfect, but tarte Tatin was much too sweet.</p>
        <p>A three-course dinner averages $42 without drinks, tax and tip. Pascal's is near the Larchmont train station and west of Palmer Avenue.</p>
        <p>Pascal's  141 Chatsworth Avenue, Larchmont.  (914) 834-6688.</p>
        <p>VERY GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Glowing, romantic and elegant with formal appointments, comfortable chairs and banquettes, stunning bouquets, perfect lighting. Attentive service.</p>
        <p>SMOKING -- None.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Creamy gazpacho, salmon tartar, shrimp with tomato-mango salad, asparagus and Japanese eggplant salad, avocado and foie gras salad, monkfish with curry, seared tuna with mushroom blini, sauteed duck with raspberry sauce, molten chocolate souffle, profiteroles, mousse glace Grand Marnier.</p>
        <p>PRICES -- Dinner, main dishes, $20 to $33.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS -- Major cards accepted.</p>
        <p>HOURS -- Dinner, Tuesdays through Thursdays, 6 to 9 p.m.; Fridays and Saturdays, 5:30 to 10:30 p.m.; Sundays, 5 to 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>RESERVATIONS -- Accepted.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Street level.  Good, Satisfactory, Poor.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
