<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Reed Puts Past in Past, And Does Job for Mets</title>
    <meta content="Y08BERK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/sports/08BERK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, Rick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5DB133CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Reed Puts Past in Past, And Does Job for Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times column praises play of New York Mets pitcher Rick Reed and notes that he was one of handful of players who crossed picket line when big league players struck in 1994 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the bottom half of the second inning of a scoreless game yesterday afternoon, the Giants were threatening to score against the Mets, gray-suited San Franciscans standing on first and third with one out. It was Game 3 of the National League division playoffs, and a goodly portion of the crowd stood to cheer on the home team pitcher, Rick Reed.</p>
        <p>Reed, the Mets' right-hander, responded by striking out the next two batters, Rich Aurilia and Bobby Estalella, to conclude the inning. It was a sweet bit of hurling, and Mets fans were loudly appreciative.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the bottom half of the second inning of a scoreless game yesterday afternoon, the Giants were threatening to score against the Mets, gray-suited San Franciscans standing on first and third with one out. It was Game 3 of the National League division playoffs, and a goodly portion of the crowd stood to cheer on the home team pitcher, Rick Reed.</p>
        <p>Reed, the Mets' right-hander, responded by striking out the next two batters, Rich Aurilia and Bobby Estalella, to conclude the inning. It was a sweet bit of hurling, and Mets fans were loudly appreciative.</p>
        <p>Of the 56,275 fans who filled Shea Stadium, none of them were Marvin Miller. The former executive director of the Major League Players Association, the man who more than any other was responsible for the players being freed from the restrictive, century-old control of the team owners, didn't come to the game -- wouldn't have. That was because Reed was the starting pitcher for the Mets. It was Miller's quiet, but firm, protest.</p>
        <p>Reed, now 34, is one of the handful of players with previous major league experience and union membership who crossed the picket line when the big league players struck in 1994 seeking to retain the rights they had won. Miller, who retired in 1982 after 16 years as the dynamic, and remarkably effective head of the union, said that he can't forgive a scab.</p>
        <p>The fans, rooting home their team, had little apparent concern for, or memory of, past labor conflicts and decisions.</p>
        <p>Reed became one of what the owners euphemistically called ''replacement players.'' Miller isn't about to use the term -- a term, incidentally, insipidly glorified in the recent Hollywood film, ''The Replacements,'' about strikebreaking football players.</p>
        <p>''A former player said to me one day, 'Aren't you being too hard on guys like Reed?' '' Miller said, from his apartment in Manhattan. '' 'It's been five years already.' And my response is, 'He was trying to take another man's job without having earned it.' ''</p>
        <p>At the time, Reed was not on a major league roster, though he had been a former major leaguer he was then playing minor league ball. ''Reed's excuse for strikebreaking was that he had a sick mother who needed money for medical bills,'' Miller said. ''The union made it clear during the strike that it would make a loan to anyone eligible who needed money. I'm sure he would have qualified.''</p>
        <p>When Reed came to bat to lead off the third inning, the pitcher received a polite patter of applause. He grounded out. The fans were up on their feet again for Reed in the fourth, when he had a runners aboard but this time Estalella singled home a run. Quiet descended on the stadium.</p>
        <p>Reed played briefly as a replacement player with the Reds in the spring of 1995, was in the minors in 1996, came up to the Mets the following season and has been a superb addition to the pitching staff.</p>
        <p>The Mets' player representative to the union, Al Leiter, said of Reed: ''He's a teammate on a team that has a chance to win the world championship. We need Rick Reed. And I like him. He's a hard worker, and respectful. Initially, there was a lot of hatred going on regarding replacement players. And all of us in the union weren't happy with guys coming in to replace us. It cost some of us a lot of money because it was harder to settle the strike.</p>
        <p>''But I'm not one to give a life sentence for someone having done something like Rick did, even if I didn't agree with what he did. There are murderers and rapists who get parole.''</p>
        <p>Reed is earning $4.3 million a year and, as a free agent next season, is reported to be seeking an $18 million contract for three years. In 1966, when Miller became the head of the players' union, the reserve clause was in effect, players had no free agency, and the average salary was $19,000.</p>
        <p>While some players are willing to forgive, it's hard for some to forget. In July, Mets catcher Todd Pratt and Brian Daubach, an infielder for the Red Sox and a former replacement operative, had words on the field. In the clubhouse later, Pratt talked angrily about Daubach, who, he said, ''was nothing but a scab.''</p>
        <p>Reed was aware of such talk, just as when he had to leave the locker room during spring training when the rest of the team went over union matters.  Reed has more than once applied for reinstatement into the union but each time he has been rebuffed.</p>
        <p>''Reed joined with the owners in an attempt to destroy the union,'' Miller said, ''and now he objects to being excluded from the organization he failed to destroy.''</p>
        <p>In the sixth inning, with the Mets still behind by 2-0, the Giants' right-hander Russ Ortiz was working on a no-hitter. He then walked the leadoff batter, Mike Bordick. Reed, who had pitched decently, was due to bat, but Darryl Hamilton was sent in to pinch-hit for him. Hamilton rapped a sharp single to right. The Mets had a rally going. The fans were on their feet and yelling for their darlings to do more damage. The Mets managed to add one run.</p>
        <p>In the eighth, the Mets tied it, 2-2, and Reed, at least for the present, was a thing of the past, but only for some.</p>
        <p>Then, in the 13th, Benny Agbayani, the Mets' other replacement player, hit a home run to win it for the Mets, 3-2. He was mobbed at home plate by his teammates, and the cheering from the fans went on and on and on.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
