<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Monumental Shift In Parental Roles</title>
    <meta content="LTR020723" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tutors and Tutoring</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kapetanakes, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03EEDD123CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Monumental Shift In Parental Roles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>East Ramapo School District psychologist Barbara Kapetanakes letter on September 24 article opposes parents who pay tutors to teach their children how to ride bicycles (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I suppose that in this age of surrogate parenting I should not be surprised that someone like Aresh Mohit has carved out a niche for himself doing a job that parents used to do: teaching a child to ride a bike.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>I suppose that in this age of surrogate parenting I should not be surprised that someone like Aresh Mohit has carved out a niche for himself doing a job that parents used to do: teaching a child to ride a bike.</p>
        <p>Reaching the no-training-wheels milestone is an opportunity for parent-child bonding as much as, or more than, the first steps, first words, etc. Why would any parent pay to have someone else enjoy this milestone with their child? As one parent was quoted as saying, ''Jake would get frustrated and mad if I told him something.'' Is this a reason to pass on parental tasks to a paid stranger? Everyone gets frustrated and mad -- part of growing up is learning to resolve such problems and deal with such negative feelings.</p>
        <p>As a psychologist working both in a school system and in private practice, I see a huge shift in parenting roles, often to the detriment of the child. My colleagues agree that they are seeing a tremendous amount of children with attachment disorders. What is causing this trend? Possibly it is due to early placement in day care and the lack of quality time between parents and children. Any parent can teach a child to ride a bike; this is not true of biology or social studies, where a paid tutor may be necessary.</p>
        <p>We are now living in a society, particularly in upper middle class, professional areas like Westchester, where the values have shifted from what is good for the children and family to what looks good to the neighbors. I see too many two-income households where the second income is used to buy another S.U.V. or take another vacation, while the child has rotating nannies or attends day care for 10 hours or more a day. The consequences of this type of society are far-reaching. I am fearful that we will raise a generation of children who can't handle frustration (after all, you hire someone to ease your discomfort), who will not know how to bond with others (if your au pair leaves at the end of the semester, why trust anyone?) and who will resent their parents.</p>
        <p>A child who has little time to spend with his mother because her double shifts are needed to have basic needs such as food and shelter will understand the sacrifice when he is older. A child who is left with a stranger because his parents have to have the latest BMW is bound to be resentful and angry as an adult, and this will show in his relationships. A child cannot be bought with private lessons and material possessions, nor can parental guilt be eradicated by writing a check. One bike lesson with Mr. Mohit: $40. The memory of my mother letting go of my bike for the first time: Priceless.</p>
        <p>DR. BARBARA KAPETANAKES  Sleepy Hollow</p>
        <p>The writer is a psychologist with the East Ramapo School District.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
