<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Likable Lawyer Buys Local Bowling Alley</title>
    <meta content="08COV2$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tomashoff, Craig</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cavanagh, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beckerman, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burnett, Rob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Letterman, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ed (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E4D9133CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1230" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Likable Lawyer Buys Local Bowling Alley</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG TOMASHOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tomashoff, Craig</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on NBC series Ed, starring Thomas Cavanagh; creators Jon Beckerman and Rob Burnett comment; executive producer is David Letterman; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A couple of years ago, Rob Burnett and Jon Beckerman decided they wanted to create a television show that deconstructed an Everyman's life. They wanted it to capture that moment when he looked at where he'd been and where he was heading, in order to make a midcourse correction and get back on track. They wanted the man to move back to his hometown to regain some real feeling in his life.</p>
        <p>So where else to set their new NBC series, ''Ed,'' than in a bowling alley?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A couple of years ago, Rob Burnett and Jon Beckerman decided they wanted to create a television show that deconstructed an Everyman's life. They wanted it to capture that moment when he looked at where he'd been and where he was heading, in order to make a midcourse correction and get back on track. They wanted the man to move back to his hometown to regain some real feeling in his life.</p>
        <p>So where else to set their new NBC series, ''Ed,'' than in a bowling alley?</p>
        <p>''There's just something about a bowling alley that everybody can relate to,'' says Mr. Burnett, executive producer of both ''Ed'' and ''Late Show With David Letterman.'' ''We all grew up with them. They've always seemed like a happy place.''</p>
        <p>The lanes and pins in question are owned by the show's title character, played by Thomas Cavanagh, a Manhattan lawyer who comes home one day to find his wife in bed with the mailman. This discovery prompts him to move back to Stuckeyville, his tiny hometown, where he gets a kiss from his high school crush and buys the local bowling alley. All in the first couple of minutes of the first episode.</p>
        <p>Considering this off-kilter premise and the fact that David Letterman is one of the executive producers, it's logical to assume ''Ed'' is yet another situation comedy. And one with the same sort of cynical edge that figures in every moment of Mr. Letterman's talk show. However, the series is actually a one-hour drama that strives to combine low-key humor and sympathetic characters.</p>
        <p>''Part of the thing that I think surprises people about the show is that given the source, it has more heart and depth than anyone might expect,'' says Mr. Cavanagh.</p>
        <p>Its creators are more than happy to alter people's expectations.</p>
        <p>''This style of comedy with big laughs and hard jokes in an hour format has not really been done before,'' says Mr. Beckerman, also an executive producer and a former ''Late Show'' writer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burnett adds: ''Other shows take issues and just chat about them in clever ways. We're going to be really grounded in issues, but deal with them in comedic ways. It's a very different kind of comedy, with serious undertones.''</p>
        <p>He has always wondered why television drama hasn't had many characters like the sort Tom Hanks has been known to play, men who are casually funny and sweetly sensitive at the same time. The pilot episode balances goofy moments with sentimental scenes. For instance, Ed shows up in a suit of armor to court the love of his life. Later he seems near tears when he walks her home, realizing it's too soon to accept her invitation to come inside. And by the end of that first show, Ed is both running Stuckey Bowl and practicing law.</p>
        <p>''I think a guy like Ed could exist in the real world, but the world is more cynical than Ed is,'' says Mr. Burnett, who is also head. of Mr. Letterman's production company, Worldwide Pants. ''Cynicism is not a good place for us to get comedy on this show.''</p>
        <p>This isn't the first hourlong show that has tried to combine dramatic situations with quirky characters, but any similarities between ''Ed'' and shows like ''Picket Fences'' and ''Northern Exposure'' are purely accidental. '' 'Northern Exposure' was funny and real, but it didn't take place in a world you felt like you'd ever been,'' explains Mr. Cavanagh. ''You see shows on television that don't mirror what you go through in your own life, but hopefully that's what we'll be doing. We want to write about things that could happen to people, and that have happened to people.''</p>
        <p>It's not unlike the sitcom ''Everybody Loves Raymond,'' which is also produced by Worldwide Pants. That having been said, it's hard to imagine many lawyers who run their practices out of their own bowling alleys. As much as it strives to create real situations, ''Ed'' has a surreal side too. Which is where Mr. Letterman himself enters the picture. According to Mr. Burnett, the ''Late Show'' host has been out to the show's Northville, N.J., set, and offers notes on every script. His wry sensibility has helped several moments in the series, like the one in the pilot in which Ed first meets the eccentric crew of employees he inherits when he buys the bowling alley.</p>
        <p>''A lot of scenes have been polished by Dave,'' says Mr. Burnett. ''With him staying involved, we have somebody who is not involved in the day-to-day operation of the show yet whose opinion Jon and I totally trust.''</p>
        <p>''The presence of Dave is certainly felt,'' adds Mr. Cavanagh. ''He comes on the set and makes suggestions, and when they come from a guy with his track record, he's an asset to have there.''</p>
        <p>Even with Mr. Letterman's involvement, though, it wasn't easy getting ''Ed'' off the ground. The series was originally a pilot for CBS, the home of ''Late Show.'' At the time it was called ''Stuckeyville'' and the bulk of the 45-minute pilot revolved around Ed's life in New York and the discovery of his wife's infidelity. In other words, all the material that is now covered in the first two minutes of ''Ed.''</p>
        <p>''CBS passed on the show, which put us in an odd position,'' says Mr. Burnett. ''The response to the series was overwhelming in the industry, and when we got the show back, NBC was interested.''</p>
        <p>The network swap didn't surprise the star of both versions, Mr. Cavanagh, who says he never felt that it was going to go at CBS. ''It didn't seem like home there,'' he says. ''They did us a favor by not forcing the show to fit somewhere it didn't belong.''</p>
        <p>With a few minor tweaks, like making Ed a lawyer instead of a Wall Street trader (''That way his profession could continue in his new town,'' says Mr. Burnett), the transition to NBC was relatively seamless. The only tough part was getting used to being back at NBC, the network that Mr. Letterman left in 1993 on less than cordial terms.</p>
        <p>''It was certainly odd for us to walk down the hallways at NBC and see all those big posters of their old shows,'' says Mr. Burnett. ''But being there now has a very clean feeling. At least it's very clear that they're not putting our show on the air just because Dave hosts 'The Late Show.' ''</p>
        <p>''Ed,'' it seems, has become something of a lucky charm so far. It's brought Mr. Letterman and NBC back together. It's garnered a lot of critical support. And its approach to one-hour drama could conceivably shake up the genre if the series is a hit. But for Mr. Burnett that's not necessarily the most exciting thing about doing this show.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' he says, ''we get to bowl for free.''</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
