<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Saloon Priest, Keeping an Eye on His Flock</title>
    <meta content="08BARS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Elaine's (Nyc Bar)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Colapietro, Peter (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leduff, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D7143CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Saloon Priest, Keeping an Eye on His Flock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE LEDUFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leduff, Charlie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bending Elbows column describes scene at Elaine's famed bar and restaurant on Second Avenue and 88th Street in Manhattan; Rev Peter Colapietro, who has been frequenting bar for 20 years, comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is a crowd sitting at a table near the window at Elaine's. One man is the port-a-potty prince of New York, the other is a nightclub owner. The club owner's wife is sitting there with him and she looks good. At the adjoining table is the Rev. Peter Colapietro, the saloon priest who, at 275 pounds, fills a chair.</p>
        <p>It's still early in the evening, and already their eyes are glistening. The titan of toilets tells the one about the priest and the rabbi. Then there's the one about the three men looking for a cheap drink. And then the one about the three construction workers who throw themselves to their deaths.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is a crowd sitting at a table near the window at Elaine's. One man is the port-a-potty prince of New York, the other is a nightclub owner. The club owner's wife is sitting there with him and she looks good. At the adjoining table is the Rev. Peter Colapietro, the saloon priest who, at 275 pounds, fills a chair.</p>
        <p>It's still early in the evening, and already their eyes are glistening. The titan of toilets tells the one about the priest and the rabbi. Then there's the one about the three men looking for a cheap drink. And then the one about the three construction workers who throw themselves to their deaths.</p>
        <p>Father Pete hears this one and snorts into his bourbon.</p>
        <p>''Jesus, Father, I'm rotten,'' the toilet titan says.</p>
        <p>''No you're a good man,'' Father Pete reassures. ''You just have to change.''</p>
        <p>The toilet titan wrinkles his nose as if the booze has gone bad. ''I'm talking to a priest, and I'm getting sober.''</p>
        <p>Father Pete claims that he has never had a bad time in the 20 years that he has visited Elaine's, the famous bar, restaurant and gossip stand at 88th Street and Second Avenue that is favored by the city's literati and some celebrities.</p>
        <p>Most recognize Father Pete even when he's out of uniform and dressed in slacks and a blue Oxford shirt. When Catholics walk past his table, they promise him they'll return to church.</p>
        <p>''What they make of the scene here is baloney,'' Father Pete says. ''It's just a bar and restaurant. You can bring your mom, you can bring your wife. I suggest though, that you don't come with your mistress.''</p>
        <p>Father Pete, 52, is the pastor of the Holy Cross Church on West 42nd Street across from the Port Authority Bus Terminal, and his community includes addicts, prostitutes, newspaper photographers, struggling actors, immigrants and the elderly.  He is also chaplain for the Manhattan Restaurant and Liquor Association, the transit police, the Sanitation Department and the state parole officers.</p>
        <p>Raised in the Castle Hill section of the Bronx, this son of an Italian-born saloon owner is as comfortable in the company of the wicked as he is with the wealthy. When Elaine Kaufman, the restaurant's owner, comes by the table, Father Pete swears he loves her with all his heart and half his liver.</p>
        <p>''We're all flawed,'' he says from beneath a cloud of tobacco smoke. ''God loves us all, but maybe he loves some more than others.''</p>
        <p>That's when Tommy Carney walks into the bar to a standing ovation. He takes a chair at Father Pete's table. Tommy's been a barman here for 26 years, and it's his first night out since having a heart attack. It happened on a farm upstate at a wedding in a big tent in a big field.</p>
        <p>He's having his first drink in three weeks.</p>
        <p>''I didn't think 'Oh my Lord' or anything like that while it was happening,'' Tommy says. ''But I'm thinking it now. I know the gift of life, I'll tell you.''</p>
        <p>''Yes, Tommy,'' Father Pete says.</p>
        <p>''And boy, does this drink taste good.''</p>
        <p>CHARLIE LEDUFF</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: BENDING ELBOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
