<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Seducing The Innocent,' The Sequel</title>
    <meta content="08GOOD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/weekinreview/08GOOD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comic Books and Strips</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertham, Frederic</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Walter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comic Books and Strips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EFD6153CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="825" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Seducing The Innocent,' The Sequel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Psychiatrist Frederic Wertham's 1954 book denouncing violence in comic books recalled in light of current criticism of entertainment media; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE evidence was gruesome, the delivery impassioned, the message dire: a generation of American youngsters being lured into crime and psychological troubles by large doses of violence and sex; juvenile crime turning ever more vicious, inspired by the horrendous tales and pictures being peddled to tens of millions of vulnerable children; efforts to safeguard the young being blocked by adult greed, ignorance and politics.</p>
        <p>Sound familiar? That indictment was issued almost 50 years ago in the best seller ''The Seduction of the Innocent'' (Rinehart &amp; Company, 1954) by Frederic Wertham, a psychiatrist who was simultaneously celebrated and debunked in the debate over what to do about decidedly distasteful and reputedly dangerous material.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE evidence was gruesome, the delivery impassioned, the message dire: a generation of American youngsters being lured into crime and psychological troubles by large doses of violence and sex; juvenile crime turning ever more vicious, inspired by the horrendous tales and pictures being peddled to tens of millions of vulnerable children; efforts to safeguard the young being blocked by adult greed, ignorance and politics.</p>
        <p>Sound familiar? That indictment was issued almost 50 years ago in the best seller ''The Seduction of the Innocent'' (Rinehart &amp; Company, 1954) by Frederic Wertham, a psychiatrist who was simultaneously celebrated and debunked in the debate over what to do about decidedly distasteful and reputedly dangerous material.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wertham's target was the comic book, including such favorites as ''Superman'' and ''Wonder Woman'' among less-wholesome specimens, but his call to action has since been applied to movies, television, music videos and other assaults on the nation's sensibilities. And the responses by the latest merchandisers of dubious entertainment to the juvenile market draw on defenses mounted a half century ago.</p>
        <p>Basic to the Wertham crusade and to current attacks on the viciousness and vulgarity that parents have no trouble finding in today's much-enlarged marketplace is the perceived connection between the entertainments that young customers favor and their influence in real life. But, as critics have countered over the decades, such a connection, though worrisome to many and self-evident to some, is exasperatingly elusive.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wertham, who died in 1981, found support from such worthies of the time as Walter Lippmann and Dorothy Thompson, but there were also skeptics. His evidence abounded in examples of the brutal stories and garish images in which many of the comic books traded. Fairly typical was a 1950 story of ''a near rape'' illustrated by 37 pictures of which one in three offered this sort of show: ''The girl falling over, her breast prominent, her skirt thrown up to reveal black net panties, 'the attacker' a black, shadowed figure leaning over her.'' (One bright change over the years is that villainous figures in works for children no longer tend to be swarthy.)</p>
        <p>No one claimed that such tales were edifying, but some, including in Dr. Wertham's profession, challenged his thesis that there was a clear link between what youngsters read or gazed upon and how some of them behaved. Dr. Wertham relied mainly on interviews with juvenile offenders and psychological tests on them, but as his opponents did not fail to point out, his interpretations of his subjects' testimony was subject to reasonable doubt. From an ''association test'' given to a 10-year-old who was accused of pushing a small boy into the water where he drowned, for example, Dr. Wertham concluded, ''Our patient would not have been pushed to the murder if his mind had not been imbued with readiness for violence and murder by his continuous comic book reading.'' Not implausible, but as far from ''proof'' as Dr. Wertham's bald assertion that, ''Our researches have proved that there is a significant correlation between crime comics reading and the more serious form of juvenile delinquency.''</p>
        <p>Faith in psychological test results having declined markedly since the 1950's, today's crusaders, like William J. Bennett, are more likely to play it safe with intimations that popular culture is contributing to a ''coarsening'' of American life, a formulation that evades the pitfalls of specific causality even if it is historically shaky. It echoes Dr. Wertham's contested charge that ''a generation is being desensitized by these literal horror images.''</p>
        <p>The target has moved with the times. In the 1950's, Dr. Wertham expressed hopes for ''good television'' but warned that the new medium was susceptible to ''comic books and the comic book culture in which we force children to live.'' By 1964, he was coming down hard on television as ''a school for violence.''</p>
        <p>But what is to be done a half century after he undertook his campaign? Dr. Wertham scorned the comic book industry's self-serving gestures toward self-regulation. (''We must not chop limbs off characters,'' one such code ruled. ''The same goes for putting people's eyes out.'') Calling for legislation but stopping short of censorship, he expressed a wan faith that ''in some way or other the democratic process will assert itself and crime comic books will go, and with them all they stand for and all that sustains them.''</p>
        <p>The comics that outraged Dr. Wertham have pretty much faded, only to be replaced by the multiheaded creature known as the media, and the fears he raised loom in the nation's consciousness like one of those old comic book nightmares.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
