<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Among Men, It's Bush the Maserati by a Mile</title>
    <meta content="08MEN.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/politics/08MEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: GENDER POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DA133CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Among Men, It's Bush the Maserati by a Mile</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Oct. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore trails Gov George W Bush among men over all by as much as 22 points in one poll, and is not doing well enough among women to be certain to offset that deficit among men; part of problem is that men lean Republican in most presidential races, seeing that party as being more protective of their assets; Gore tries to appeal to men by promoting himself as repository of fiscal responsibility and deficit reduction; political professionals in both parties say Gore's earnest, wonkish personality, and his tendency to lecture, present problems for him; note that Gore may suffer by comparison not with Republicans but with Pres Clinton, who as candidate and president appears often in pop culture forums that helped transform many voters' relationship with president and presidency from paternal one to more of peer-to-peer regard; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Gov. Gray Davis's political advisers want to take Californians' temperatures on the presidential race in voter focus groups, they ask a question that might sound goofy: if Al Gore and George W. Bush were cars, what would they be?</p>
        <p>''Among men, Gore is viewed as a Ford Taurus, a Chevy station wagon, a Volvo, safe and kind of boxy,'' said Garry South, the chief political aide for Mr. Davis, a Democrat. ''With Bush, you get things like Maserati and Mustang convertible, and by no means all of the men who say that are doing it pejoratively. They're saying: 'Wait a minute; that guy's like who I'd like to be.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Gov. Gray Davis's political advisers want to take Californians' temperatures on the presidential race in voter focus groups, they ask a question that might sound goofy: if Al Gore and George W. Bush were cars, what would they be?</p>
        <p>''Among men, Gore is viewed as a Ford Taurus, a Chevy station wagon, a Volvo, safe and kind of boxy,'' said Garry South, the chief political aide for Mr. Davis, a Democrat. ''With Bush, you get things like Maserati and Mustang convertible, and by no means all of the men who say that are doing it pejoratively. They're saying: 'Wait a minute; that guy's like who I'd like to be.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is running comfortably ahead in the polls in California, in part because it is one of the few places where he is holding his own or slightly ahead among men, who tend here to be more liberal than their counterparts in the South and Midwest. But even here, Mr. Gore runs behind Mr. Bush among white men and married men, and the car quiz sums up what may be one of his biggest challenges as the presidential race moves into its final month: how to get guys who may not be like him to like him all the same.</p>
        <p>Since at least 1980, when polls first showed men and women sharply diverging in their presidential preferences, with women leaning Democratic and men Republican, politicians have sought to exploit the gender gap, typically by making special efforts to court the votes of women, who are the greatest share of the electorate and tend to look to government as a supportive partner in challenges from child care to health care and the environment.</p>
        <p>So this year, Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush have gone out of their way to demonstrate their sensitive New Age guyness by gushing with Oprah Winfrey and praising their wives' uplifting influences. In their debate on Tuesday, Mr. Bush, who like most Republicans does worse with women than his Democratic opponent, went so far as to brag about crying with Texas flood victims. ''That's what governors do,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Bill Carrick, a Democratic consultant here, said, ''Neither one of these guys is trying to project himself as John Wayne.''</p>
        <p>But men, especially white men, remain a potent political force, perhaps even more complicated to court. And among this group, Mr. Gore is struggling, trailing Mr. Bush among men over all by 22 points in one recent Los Angeles Times national poll and by smaller but still significant margins in most other surveys. At the same time, Mr. Gore has not been doing well enough among women, especially married women, to be certain he will be able to offset his deficit among men.</p>
        <p>Part of the problem is axiomatic and beyond Mr. Gore's control: men are more likely to be what the Republican pollster Kellyanne Fitzpatrick calls ''congenital Republicans.''</p>
        <p>''If the way to a man's heart is through his stomach, the way to a man's vote is still through his wallet, and men do still see the Republican Party as being more protective of their assets,'' Ms. Fitzpatrick said. ''Even in 1996, with what was sometimes a very inarticulate and uninspired defense of his own tax plan, Bob Dole was still able to secure an advantage among men. It's their default position.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has made his share of efforts to appeal to men. He promotes himself as the repository of fiscal responsibility and deficit reduction. His biographical advertisements are careful to note his Army service in Vietnam. Even his celebrated kiss of his wife, Tipper, at the Democratic convention, pollsters say, could be seen as much as a gesture of solidarity with his fellow family men as an appeal to women.</p>
        <p>But political professionals in both parties say Mr. Gore also faces particular problems growing out of his earnest, wonkish personality, and his tendency to lecture. ''One of the things that I think is happening is that Bush has been able to convey and project a personality type that I think appeals to men,'' Mr. South said, ''a kind of free-wheeling, macho guy, more compatible with where the typical white, middle-aged male voter would be than Gore has.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush may be helped in this regard by his running mate, Dick Cheney, a former high school football captain who made appearances at two athletic events this weekend. On Friday night Mr. Cheney went to a high school football game in Waterloo, Iowa. This afternoon he went to a tailgate party at the Iowa State-Nebraska football game in Ames, Iowa, shaking hands with chilly football fans huddled around beer kegs.</p>
        <p>Oddly, Ms. Fitzpatrick suggested, Mr. Gore may suffer by comparison not with Republicans but with Mr. Clinton, who as a candidate and president appeared often in pop culture forums that helped transform many voters' relationship with the president and presidency from a paternal one to more of a peer-to-peer regard.</p>
        <p>''Before it was always, 'Can he stare down the Soviet Union?' '' Ms. Fitzpatrick said. ''Now it's, 'Is he like me and do I like him?' And with Al Gore the answer to both is no. Clinton is always looked at as having an outstretched hand, and Gore as having a pointing finger.''</p>
        <p>Joel Cook, 32, a milk truck driver in Los Banos, Calif., a swing area in the Central Valley, said it did not matter to him that Mr. Gore was a veteran like himself. He said he thought Mr. Bush would do a better job of building up the military.</p>
        <p>''I don't like the way Gore talks,'' said Mr. Cook, who usually votes Republican. ''I feel like he's trying to put one over on me, and tell me something just for a vote.''</p>
        <p>Robert DeSouza, 60, a disabled former appliance repairman in Sacramento, still calls himself a Democrat but says he has voted Republican since Richard M. Nixon's election in 1968. He is not a big fan of Mr. Bush but says Mr. Gore could not persuade him to vote Democratic.</p>
        <p>''All the big promises he's making, he knows he can't do it,'' Mr. DeSouza said. ''The Democrats had their chance to do all this stuff the first two years of Bill Clinton's administration when they controlled Congress, and they still couldn't do it.''</p>
        <p>In fact, according to the most recent New York Times/CBS News poll, taken late last month, Mr. Gore is doing about the same among men as Mr. Clinton did in 1992 and 1996, drawing the support of about 4 in 10  male voters, though other polls have shown him faring worse.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore is so far not doing as well among women as Mr. Clinton did, drawing the support of just 47 percent of likely female voters in the most recent Times/CBS News poll. When Mr. Clinton was elected in 1996, he won the support of 54 percent of women, surveys of voters leaving the polls found.</p>
        <p>Moreover, before Mr. Clinton's affair with a White House intern and his subsequent impeachment took its toll, the president had managed to make strong inroads of support among the kinds of blue-collar families that the Democrats had been ceding for years. These are among the voters Mr. Gore is trying to reclaim with his oratorical emphasis on ''working families.''</p>
        <p>But here, too, Mr. Gore faces problems caused in part by Mr. Clinton's alienation of these voters, and in part by Mr. Gore's having spent much of the winter running to the left to stave off a primary challenge from Senator Bill Bradley of New Jersey. At the same time, he may suffer in stylistic comparisons with Mr. Clinton, who is a past master at creating connections with his audience, whatever it happens to be.</p>
        <p>''If he was asked about gay marriage, for example, the typical Clinton response lays out right away, 'I do not favor gay marriage,' '' said one Democratic strategist here who has complained to Mr. Gore about this point. ''And then he segues into a sympathetic-sounding response about how we have to uphold everybody's differences and dreams. Gore's tendency is to give the long, sympathetic answer, and then, as an afterthought, add, 'Having said that, I do not favor gay marriage.' ''</p>
        <p>This strategist added that there are few people ''as masterful as Bill Clinton at defining himself in a way that keeps those white male voters in the pen without alienating those female voters that really give you your edge as a Democrat.''</p>
        <p>Mark DiCamillo, director of the statewide nonpartisan Field Poll in San Francisco, said that younger men, in particular, should be a natural demographic target for Mr. Gore, but that Mr. Bush had shown strong appeal among this group.</p>
        <p>''The issues that Bush is raising have a certain appeal for young men, like Social Security, where he says I'll give you the right to invest some of your own funds,'' Mr. DiCamillo said. ''When you poll the attitudes of the young, they basically have much less trust in government to be there when they need it, and the farther you are away from retirement age, the more likely you are to be skeptical about whether the government will deliver. I also think the entrepreneurial spirit, the kind that drives the booming California economy right now, that spirit is more reflected by Bush in his economic proposals. The key question to me nationally is, will these young people go out and vote?''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: GENDER POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
