<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Into the Unknown, by Choice and Otherwise; Battered Crossroads Cancels Its Season</title>
    <meta content="08CROS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237026"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Crossroads Theater Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Woliver, Robbie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E2D7163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Into the Unknown, by Choice and Otherwise; Battered Crossroads Cancels Its Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBBIE WOLIVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Woliver, Robbie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Award-winning Crossroads Theater Company in New Brunswick, NJ, cancels operations and closes while it undergoes financial and operational reorganization; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE curtain -- after looming for some time -- came down Monday on a season that had not yet even begun at the Crossroads Theater Company in New Brunswick, as board members canceled the company's entire season, furloughed its small staff and changed the locks on their building.</p>
        <p>Whether this proves to be the final curtain or merely a long intermission depends on whether the board succeeds in putting together a new financial plan for the Tony Award-winning theater that has been hailed for its African-American repertoire.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE curtain -- after looming for some time -- came down Monday on a season that had not yet even begun at the Crossroads Theater Company in New Brunswick, as board members canceled the company's entire season, furloughed its small staff and changed the locks on their building.</p>
        <p>Whether this proves to be the final curtain or merely a long intermission depends on whether the board succeeds in putting together a new financial plan for the Tony Award-winning theater that has been hailed for its African-American repertoire.</p>
        <p>In the restructuring, Rhinold Ponder, a lawyer who is a former board member for the nearby George Street Theater, took over as interim president of the board, replacing Dale Caldwell, who resigned last Saturday, citing other business commitments and family responsibilities. Mr. Caldwell, who had been in the job since May 1999, was a business consultant with DeLoitte and Touche and is now executive director of the Newark Alliance, a coalition of business executives involved in rebuilding Newark. He did not respond to numerous telephone messages left at his office.</p>
        <p>''It was simply falling apart,'' said Mr. Ponder of the theater organization. ''It was in financial disarray and hemorrhaging money. When we closed it was a very, very sad day. But on the other hand, it was a time of relief.''</p>
        <p>The closing was not a total surprise. Recently the season's opening shows had been canceled, board members had stopped returning calls, and the theater's phones and E-mail were disconnected.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the decision created shock and sadness in the theater world.</p>
        <p>''Oh, my God,'' moaned Ossie Davis, the actor and writer, upon hearing the news. In 1995, he had produced an original play ''Two Ha Has and a Homeboy'' at Crossroads, along with his wife, the actress Ruby Dee, and their musician son, Guy.</p>
        <p>''This is not totally unexpected,'' Mr. Davis said, ''but we deliberately shut our eyes. We took it for granted, this place where the most important works were coming from, this place which spoke for African-Americans in the wider world.''</p>
        <p>Most of the theater's supporters expressed hope  that the closing would provide the opportunity to focus on financial and operational reorganization. Mr. Ponder wants to send a clear message: ''Nothing will happen in this building without it making money.''</p>
        <p>The board was scheduled to meet this weekend to discuss fundraising and the appointment of more board members. One possibility that will be explored is bringing back the theater's co-founder, Ricardo Khan, to help raise money. Mr. Khan, the artistic director, had taken a leave of absence last year, saying he would use the time -- it was never clear how long he intended to be away -- to do fundraising.</p>
        <p>Winner of the 1999 Tony for outstanding regional theater, the Crossroads has been muddling through financially since 1991, when it moved to a new home on Livingston Street, where the rent was $65,000 a year. Last winter, the downward spiral worsened as the theater ran short of money and canceled several performances. The future held promise, however: more than $850,000 was held in reserve in prospective grants while the theater company reorganized financially. Instead, the theater, with an annual budget of $2.9 million, saw its debt rise to $1.7 million.</p>
        <p>''Our debt continues to increase daily as interest mounts on that debt,'' said Mr. Ponder. ''That's a major problem.''</p>
        <p>Three plays were announced for the 2000-2001 season -- including the debut of Samm-Art Williams's ''Conversations on a Dirt Road.'' Mr. Williams was never officially notified by the theater that his play had been canceled. ''I never got a call,'' he said. ''I heard it through the grapevine.'' At this point in the theater season, he has little chance of placing it elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Laura Aden, executive director of the New Jersey Theater Group, an alliance of the state's professional theaters, said of the closing: ''It was certainly dramatic, but I can't say it wasn't expected. People feel fairly optimistic, though. The new people in charge seem right for the task.''</p>
        <p>Secretary of State DeForest Soaries Jr., whose office oversees arts financing, was more cautious, saying, ''When I put on my not-for-profit business hat, I have questions about what really happened this week.''</p>
        <p>The theater company owes ''a substantial amount of money'' to the Internal Revenue Service, he said, adding, ''That's a different kind of threat than money owned for bills.''</p>
        <p>''When I put on my African-American community hat,'' Mr. Soaries continued, ''it is devastating because it was all we had in terms of celebrating African American theater.''</p>
        <p>From the state's point of view, he added, ''We have articulated our willingness to help in whatever way we can. They have not yet submitted a strategic plan that makes sense.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Soaries has asked a task force comprised of members of the New Jersey State Council on the Arts, ''to try to get as much information to determine the most effective and appropriate role for the state.'' He is also studying the possibility that Crossroads, the theater company, could operate operating separately from Crossroads, the physical theater, which is run by the New Brunswick Cultural Center.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, grants from such sources as the state arts council and the Geraldine R. Dodge Foundation are being held in reserve with the expectation that the theater can regroup. Nina Stack, spokeswoman for the arts council, said, ''We are waiting to hear more about the theater's plans for the future, which will help inform the council as it determines what its next steps will be.''</p>
        <p>Ben Cameron, executive director of the Theater Communications Group, a national service organization for not-for-profit theaters, said many arts groups, and especially theaters, encountered problems like those at Crossroads.</p>
        <p>''It's considered a mid-size theater, but it has all the expectations of performing like a large business, but not the ability to do so,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Samm-Art Williams said that the African-American community shares responsibility with Crossroads for the problems.</p>
        <p>''Black Americans have to invest in the theater,'' he said. ''There is enough money in the black community to keep these theaters running.''</p>
        <p>Stephen Richard, the Crossroads' new treasurer, said the theater never got the word out to the right people. ''There's an affluent African-American community out there that was severely undermarketed by the theater,'' he said. ''I was the president of the New Jersey chapter of the National Association of Black Accountants, and they never reached out to me, never solicited me, never even sent me a promo. And there are hundreds like me.''</p>
        <p>Lillian Stroud has financially supported the theater as a 10-year subscriber, even joining the theater's volunteer guild. She spent $250 for two season subscriptions for her and her daughter.</p>
        <p>''I don't care about getting my money back,'' she said, 'I just want the place to reopen.'</p>
        <p>Now, the difficult work has begun for Mr. Ponder, who said he has already secured backing from New Brunswick-based Johnson &amp; Johnson to help organize Crossroads' financial records. ''The Arts Council and others have been very cooperative,'' he said. ''We have very doable requirements and we just need time to address those. Some money, we are told, would be made available when we rehabilitate our plan.''</p>
        <p>A $500,000 federal grant for an after-school educational program might still come through. ''What a perfect time to train interns,'' Mr. Ponder said, with a laugh. ''Now they can really learn everything from the ground up.''</p>
        <p>With all the business ramifications of the closing, Mr. Ponder, the father of a 22-month-old daughter, Jamaica, has a more personal interest in saving the theater. ''I'd be remiss if I would allow the theater to die and not have my daughter exposed to this part of our culture,'' he said. ''It would be a travesty.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
