<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Content With Victory, but Still Find Fault</title>
    <meta content="Y08DEVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/sports/08DEVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237256"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montreal Canadiens</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Montreal Canadiens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1DF133CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Content With Victory, but Still Find Fault</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New Jersey Devils opening season 8-4 victory over Montreal Canadiens (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now that the Stanley Cup banner has been raised to the rafters at the south end of Continental Arena and all the emotion has dissipated, the Devils can go to work at what they do best: allowing as few goals as possible.</p>
        <p>Coach Larry Robinson and players like Bobby Holik were happy about the eight goals the Devils scored against Montreal in the season opener Friday night in East Rutherford, N.J. But they were unhappy about the four goals they yielded to a team that has been so mediocre, it missed the playoffs the last two years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Now that the Stanley Cup banner has been raised to the rafters at the south end of Continental Arena and all the emotion has dissipated, the Devils can go to work at what they do best: allowing as few goals as possible.</p>
        <p>Coach Larry Robinson and players like Bobby Holik were happy about the eight goals the Devils scored against Montreal in the season opener Friday night in East Rutherford, N.J. But they were unhappy about the four goals they yielded to a team that has been so mediocre, it missed the playoffs the last two years.</p>
        <p>''We can't allow four goals in a game, because we're not going to score eight every night,'' Holik said about 20 minutes after Robinson made virtually the same statement in his postgame meeting with reporters. ''I know we were anxious about the festivities and everything, but now it's over and let's move on.''</p>
        <p>The brightest element besides the laser light show on opening night was Alexander Mogilny, the crafty Russian right wing, who scored two goals and assisted on Steve Kelly's goal, which closed the scoring in the trouncing of the once glorious Canadiens.</p>
        <p>Mogilny looked like the player who scored 76 goals for Buffalo in the 1992-93 season and who scored 55 for Vancouver three years later. The 31-year-old Mogilny has shown such offensive gifts that he could very well be the first legitimate sniper in the history of the Devils.</p>
        <p>''I've always been a goal scorer,'' Mogilny said. ''It's just that I was overpassing a little the last few years. Now I can concentrate on shooting more, and the fact I'm playing with good players helps.''</p>
        <p>Mogilny's linemates are Scott Gomez, who may be the best passer on the team, and Sergei Brylin, who is one of Robinson's biggest fans. Gomez made the pass for Mogilny's first goal and Brylin for his second.</p>
        <p>Last season, the line centered by Jason Arnott with Patrik Elias and Petr Sykora, was the Devils' top line. Since Arnott remains unsigned, Mogilny was asked, does he now consider his line the team's best?</p>
        <p>He looked his questioner in the eye and smiled slightly.</p>
        <p>''We don't have a first line here,'' Mogilny said. ''We have four lines. That's the beauty of this team.''</p>
        <p>Player opinions aside, Mogilny, Gomez and Brylin make up the Devils' top combination, and they will continue to until Arnott returns -- if he returns.</p>
        <p>Robinson keeps encouraging Mogilny to shoot more, and he is rediscovering his scoring prowess. Mogilny had five goals in the preseason and seems to be getting his confidence back.</p>
        <p>''That second goal he scored is indicative of the way he can shoot the puck,'' Robinson said. ''I didn't even see it go in.''</p>
        <p>Another pleasant development for the Devils was Sykora's play. He had been limited to just one preseason game because he had a tonsillectomy the day before training camp opened, yet Sykora was effective Friday night.</p>
        <p>Sykora scored to start an explosion of three goals within the first 3 minutes 13 seconds of the second period.</p>
        <p>He also assisted on Sergei Nemchinov's goal, which gave the Devils a 2-0 lead a little more than seven minutes into the game.</p>
        <p>''I still got some work to do,'' Sykora said about his level of fitness, ''but I'm happy with the way I played. With five or six days of practice before the next game, I should be in good shape.''</p>
        <p>The Devils, who staged their skills competition last night at Continental Arena, play their next game on Friday in Ottawa.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
