<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Deathtrap' Revived By Fleetwood Stage</title>
    <meta content="08DEAT$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klein, Alvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arlt, Lewis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Irish, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheeley, Nelson</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Deathtrap (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E6DC163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Deathtrap' Revived By Fleetwood Stage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALVIN KLEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klein, Alvin</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alvin Klein reviews revival of Deathtrap, starring Lewis Arlt and Mark Irish and directed by Nelson Sheeley at Fleetwood Stage in New Rochelle, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOW that Lewis Arlt has had  his way with ''Deathtrap''</p>
        <p>twice in about six months -- perhaps he can get on with the more urgent business of being the producing director of Fleetwood Stage here.</p>
        <p>Television writing aside, the versatile and very busy Mr. Arlt, who lives in Bronxville, is also an accomplished actor, which is how he has had his two recent and entirely different ways with Ira Levin's thriller within a thriller. In February, Mr. Arlt played the minor role of Porter Milgrim, a snoopy lawyer, redundant as that sounds, who doesn't come on until the second act, at the Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn, N.J. Exuding cool in a lamentable production, Mr. Arlt stole the show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOW that Lewis Arlt has had  his way with ''Deathtrap''</p>
        <p>twice in about six months -- perhaps he can get on with the more urgent business of being the producing director of Fleetwood Stage here.</p>
        <p>Television writing aside, the versatile and very busy Mr. Arlt, who lives in Bronxville, is also an accomplished actor, which is how he has had his two recent and entirely different ways with Ira Levin's thriller within a thriller. In February, Mr. Arlt played the minor role of Porter Milgrim, a snoopy lawyer, redundant as that sounds, who doesn't come on until the second act, at the Paper Mill Playhouse in Millburn, N.J. Exuding cool in a lamentable production, Mr. Arlt stole the show.</p>
        <p>It is worth saying that Mr. Arlt had signed on as understudy for the leading role, Sidney Bruhl, the once hot  playwright of the thriller genre who is now suffering an extended bout  with old writers' block and the dangerous envy of emerging young talent. Too bad for New Jersey that Mr. Arlt never went on in that role.</p>
        <p>Given such frustration, it helps to run your own theater and decree theatrical justice. Yes, Mr. Arlt is now playing Bruhl -- a classy, blase, egomaniacal, just plain maniacal, suavely menacing characterization. And he steals the show again, this time more legitimately.</p>
        <p>At this rate, Mr. Arlt may be on the road to claiming exclusive rights to ''Deathtrap,'' perhaps as a one-man show. As a demonstration, or a stretch, of his resourcefulness, he could easily take on the roles of Helga, the neighborhood psychic, and Myra, Sidney's tedious wife. It gives  nothing away to call Myra's a short-lived role. Then there is the young, young other writer, Clifford Anderson, who is very good looking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arlt is good looking too, and a touch of makeup would take care of the rest. And he's already done Porter, to the hilt. Go to it, Mr. Arlt.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, give the play a rest, and that can be taken as advice to regional theater producers in general, if the important distinction between seriously intended professional regional theater and stock or community theater is to be preserved.</p>
        <p>(The Fleetwood show is closing today, a week earlier than originally scheduled. Gene S. Minkow, the theater's managing director, said, ''Our closing was planned for Oct. 15, but we didn't meet our sales goals.'')</p>
        <p>Here, in a substandard supporting cast, Ted Guhl does throwaway work in the role Mr. Arlt previously turned into a splendid display. Mark Irish as Clifford comes off best, being believably competitive, ambitious and obsessed with thriller-itis, as well as  being seductive. Yes, there is sexual tension between the two men, which  is hilariously minimized and amateurishly indicated in Nelson Sheeley's cautious staging, presumably so that audiences won't be shocked by intimations of homosexuality in a  play more than 20 years old.</p>
        <p>If that is a valid presumption, it is too bad Mr. Sheeley did not over do, or at least play up, the reality of Sidney and Clifford as lovers. That could invigorate a worn-out play, and inform it thematically. After all, Mr. Levin writes of murder as an aphrodisiac. And in their subtle performances, Mr. Arlt and Mr. Irish appear to have something going. There are few other moments of titillation here. The Pirandellian aspects of Mr. Levin's intricate plotting and the contrived theatrics and satirical asides  about theater verite are all too familiar while the thunder raging outside is just another sound effect.</p>
        <p>Because the play takes place in an isolated, authentically Colonial house, a handsomely converted stable, with a dagger, an ax, a medieval crossbow, genuine Houdini handcuffs and similar accouterments of crime  on the walls, the ''Deathtrap'' set should send shivers at first sight. Joseph J. Egan's antiseptic prefab room is guaranteed not to. Actually, the only discernible criminal act in Fleetwood's ''Deathtrap'' is show stealing, and that's a merciful one.</p>
        <p>''Deathtrap,'' Fleetwood Stage, 44 Wildcliff Drive, New Rochelle. Last performance today. Information: (914) 654-8949.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
