<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>24-Hour Spots Are Attacked as Inconvenience Stores</title>
    <meta content="08SEVE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: COLLEGE POINT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Convenience Stores</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Michael (Assemblyman)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Sherri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2D7143CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>24-Hour Spots Are Attacked as Inconvenience Stores</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERRI DAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Day, Sherri</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Assemblyman Michael Cohen, responding to College Point residents' complaints about abundance of 24-hour convenience stores in residential neighborhood, authors bill that would prevent new convenience stores within 500 feet of residences from operating between midnight and 6 AM anywhere in New York City; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Residents of College Point say a concentration of 24-hour convenience stores in the neighborhood are more of a nuisance than a convenience.</p>
        <p>The 2.3-square-mile neighborhood has six 24-hour convenience stores within 10 blocks of each other: two 7-Elevens, a Dunkin' Donuts and three bodegas. The newest arrival, a 7-Eleven at 14th Avenue and 127th Street, opened in June.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Residents of College Point say a concentration of 24-hour convenience stores in the neighborhood are more of a nuisance than a convenience.</p>
        <p>The 2.3-square-mile neighborhood has six 24-hour convenience stores within 10 blocks of each other: two 7-Elevens, a Dunkin' Donuts and three bodegas. The newest arrival, a 7-Eleven at 14th Avenue and 127th Street, opened in June.</p>
        <p>''We don't need all these little food stores,'' said Sabina Cardali, president of the College Point Civic and Taxpayers Association. ''I don't think they're adding anything good to the neighborhood. I don't even think they have six 24-hour places in the theater district, where they need them.''</p>
        <p>Residents say rowdy teenagers have turned the businesses into noisy, all-night hangouts, disturbing people who live on the residential streets bordering the stores. They also say some of the stores sell beer and cigarettes to minors and are sites for drug dealing and prostitution. The police said only two stores, 1 Stop Grocery and New Way Supermarket and Deli, have a history of criminal activity. Both bodegas were cited for selling alcohol to minors.</p>
        <p>Fred Mazzarello, president of the College Point Board of Trade, wants the community to have a say about the number of all-night stores that open in the neighborhood, as does Assemblyman Michael Cohen, whose district includes College Point.</p>
        <p>''Essentially, if you're near a convenience store, you're going to suffer from sleep deprivation,'' he said.  ''I'm not willing to accept inflicting misery on people in their homes for the sake of economic expansion.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen is the author of a bill under which new convenience stores within 500 feet of residences could not operate between midnight and 6 a.m. anywhere in the city. The bill requires only city approval since it applies only to the five boroughs.</p>
        <p>Robert Hou, who owns College Point's two 7-Eleven stores, denied that loitering and illegal activity were going on outside his stores and said Mr. Cohen's bill was unfair.</p>
        <p>''I think from midnight to 6 a.m. is a long period of time to be closed,'' Mr. Hou said. ''You're talking about a quarter of our business.''</p>
        <p>But new store owners may not have to worry about the ''7-Eleven Bill'' for some time. Although it was introduced two years ago, the City Council has not voted on it. Mr. Cohen says the City Planning Commission is blocking the bill, and he is considering drafting a statewide measure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cohen said he wrote to the City Planning Commission chairman, Joseph B. Rose, about the bill last winter and later spoke to representatives of the Department of City Planning at a meeting of Community Board 6 but received no response. ''I have never heard a word,'' he said.</p>
        <p>SHERRI DAY</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: COLLEGE POINT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
