<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Betting on the Old Economy Puts Three Managers Ahead</title>
    <meta content="08THRE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/business/08THRE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Alternatives Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Titan Financial Services Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pacific Advisors Small Cap Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Carole</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schoenwald, David J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giordano, Gilbert R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henning, George A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanson, Thomas H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7DE143CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Betting on the Old Economy Puts Three Managers Ahead</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gould, Carole</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fund managers David J Schoenwald of New Alternatives fund, Gilbert R Giordano of Titan Financial Services fund and George A Henning and Thomas H Hanson of Pacific Advisors Small Cap fund comment on what drove their outstanding performances in third quarter; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER a wild ride during the third quarter, many mutual funds ended up about where they started. But some of the smallest and narrowest funds gained more than 20 percent.</p>
        <p>This time, such gains in technology funds were the exception. Instead, several top-performing funds owned shares in old-economy energy companies that benefited from rising energy prices, and in the financial services sector, which was aided by mergers and stabilizing interest rates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER a wild ride during the third quarter, many mutual funds ended up about where they started. But some of the smallest and narrowest funds gained more than 20 percent.</p>
        <p>This time, such gains in technology funds were the exception. Instead, several top-performing funds owned shares in old-economy energy companies that benefited from rising energy prices, and in the financial services sector, which was aided by mergers and stabilizing interest rates.</p>
        <p>Managers of three top-performing funds talked about what drove their outstanding performances -- and they took a stab at predicting the months ahead.</p>
        <p>A Bet on Alternative Energy</p>
        <p>Energy stocks with a green hue propelled the $56.5 million New Alternatives fund, in Melville, N.Y., into first place among 3,635 diversified domestic equity funds for the third quarter, with a return of 32 percent.</p>
        <p>Maurice L. Schoenwald, 80, started this quirky fund in 1982 with his son, David J. Schoenwald. The fund holds shares of 34 companies that the managers say improve the environment and promote clean energy. Their biggest winners were solar power and fuel cell companies, which rose sharply despite measly earnings, if they had earnings at all.</p>
        <p>An example was FuelCell Energy, a Danbury, Conn., maker of fuel cells, devices that use electrochemical reactions to produce electricity without combustion. The company's cells are used to produce power for a single building or as much as an entire community. Its stock rose 179 percent during the quarter.</p>
        <p>''I think there's a sense that this is a new technology that's about to be commercialized,'' David Schoenwald said, ''and it comes at a time of concern about energy, the availability of electricity and the environment.''</p>
        <p>Another holding, the Calpine Corporation of San Jose, Calif., rose 59 percent. Using natural-gas-fired turbines and geothermal energy, Calpine produces electricity that it sells to mainstream power grids.</p>
        <p>''It's an ongoing enterprise with tremendous earnings growth, and it's operating in an environment of energy shortfalls,'' Mr. Schoenwald said.</p>
        <p>The consensus of Wall Street analysts is that Calpine's earnings will grow 81 percent this year.</p>
        <p>The fund also benefited from its shares of El Paso Energy, a natural gas production and distribution company in Houston, up 21 percent. ''The stock price was driven by the sharp increase in the price of natural gas,'' Mr. Schoenwald said, ''and partly by companies like Calpine that use gas to generate electricity.''</p>
        <p>El Paso Energy is acquiring the Coastal Corporation, another natural gas company, in a deal that is expected to be completed by year-end. As for social responsibility, Mr. Schoenwald said, ''it's not Ben &amp; Jerry's, but we think natural gas is a clean fuel.''</p>
        <p>Impressively, the fund achieves its ranking despite an 18 percent cash position, held since January. ''We're not superenthusiastic about the stock market in general,'' Mr. Schoenwald said. ''There's been a huge gap between prices of hot stocks and value stocks that seems absurd.''</p>
        <p>Capitalizing on Mergers</p>
        <p>Mergers and acquisitions among financial services companies pushed the $35 million Titan Financial Services fund into 14th place among the 5,801 domestic equity funds, including sector funds, with a gain of 25  percent.</p>
        <p>''We clearly saw the trends toward consolidation and M.&amp; A.,'' said its manager, Gilbert R. Giordano, 72, who is a former senior executive at First Virginia Bank. ''Now European banks are picking up U.S. brokerages. A few months ago they were steals, but they are still selling at low fundamentals.''</p>
        <p>One of the biggest winners in the sector was FleetBoston Financial, up 15 percent. Unlike most banks, Fleet earns more than half its revenues from continuing fees generated by its brokerage and mortgage servicing businesses, making it much less vulnerable than its competitors to interest rate swings, Mr. Giordano said.</p>
        <p>In addition, acquisitions of Quick &amp; Reilly and Robertson Stephens expanded Fleet's traditional brokerage business into discount brokerage and electronic trading, Mr. Giordano observed. Fleet sells for 12 times earnings, he added, far below his projection of 18 or 20.</p>
        <p>The fund also succeeded with Bear Stearns, up 52 percent for the quarter. ''We think it's an excellent acquisition candidate at $110 a share,'' Mr. Giordano said. ''The board has indicated that it is willing to consider an acquisition at $120. I don't think that's obtainable, but it's just a question of time.''</p>
        <p>Lehman Brothers was another winner, up 57 percent. The company has exceeded earnings estimates for each of the last five quarters, Mr. Giordano said, but still trades at 12 times earnings, well below a peer, Merrill Lynch, at a multiple of 17. He figures that Lehman, widely regarded as a takeover candidate, will increase its book value to $60 a share by year-end, justifying a takeover price of $200 to $220 a share.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giordano remains bullish on financial stocks. ''We're at the beginning of a consolidation that will promote mergers and acquisitions with tremendous speed because of the economies built into one-stop shopping, and because of the demolition of the Glass-Steagall Act,'' which generally kept banks and their affiliates from underwriting securities.</p>
        <p>Return of the Small Caps</p>
        <p>After almost two years in which their investing style could hardly have been less fashionable, George A. Henning, 53, and Thomas H. Hanson, 50, saw their $7 million Pacific Advisors Small Cap fund come back into favor in the third quarter. It gained 22 percent over the period, fourth among domestic diversified funds in a ranking that includes such small funds.</p>
        <p>''After the market correction in March and April, we began to see money flow into the small-cap value market probably for the first time since late 1998,'' Mr. Henning said. ''People began to realize that Internet-related company valuations couldn't be justified on earnings, and a lot of aggressive investors began looking for other sectors where they could get good returns. Small-cap stocks have traditionally fulfilled that role.''</p>
        <p>One winner was East West Bancorp of San Marino, Calif., a full-service regional bank that specializes in the Asian-American market, which gained 36 percent in the quarter. The bank has solid earnings, Mr. Henning said, but its small size and narrow focus had held its share price down before the fund began buying in the spring of 1999. ''Now people are looking beyond that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also made money in Genesco Inc. of Nashville, up 5.5 percent.  Genesco is the parent of Johnston &amp; Murphy, which sells high-end men's shoes; Jarman, which focuses on shoes for a middle-income market; and Journeys, which caters to young men and women. The Journeys brand has been particularly strong, Mr. Henning said, and Genesco has been adding stores around the country. Earnings in the second quarter were up a third from the previous year, he added.</p>
        <p>Another favorite is ITT International Educational Services, in Indianapolis, which offers programs for high school graduates in electronics and computer science in about 30 states. Because growth in the company's programs had slowed, the stock price fell from a high of $42 in 1999 to $10 in February, when the fund bought shares. The stock rose 55  percent during the third quarter, as the success of its new programs became apparent, Mr. Henning said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Henning is cautiously optimistic, about both the market and his favored small-cap value sector. ''I suspect we might have some correction through October, and then see some sort of a year-end rally,'' he said. ''After that, the economy will continue to grow, although at a much slower pace.''</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
