<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fall Classic Meets the Fall Classic</title>
    <meta content="08MISS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DOWN THE SHORE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beauty Contests</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Miss America</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strauss, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty Contests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4D6163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fall Classic Meets the Fall Classic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strauss, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Miss America Pageant, facing competition in September from Summer Olympic Games, has scheduled contest, for first time in its history, in October; will be competing on television with baseball championship series; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Question: Who is this year's Miss America.</p>
        <p>No, the answer is not, ''Who cares?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Question: Who is this year's Miss America.</p>
        <p>No, the answer is not, ''Who cares?''</p>
        <p>Instead of dodging the usual darts, this year the pageant is dodging bullets in the form of televised sports events.</p>
        <p>So rather than singing ''There She Is'' during the second week of September, those who were wandering the Boardwalk in Atlantic City looking for Miss America might have been muttering, ''Where Is She?''</p>
        <p>The answer was, of course, that she was waiting until after the Olympics to get a good spot on the television -- though considering how few people watched the Olympics on NBC, perhaps Miss America reruns might have been a better idea. For the first time in its 80-year history, the Miss America Pageant will be carried in October, at 8 p.m. Sunday on ABC, instead of a week or two after the Labor Day Weekend.</p>
        <p>Aside from worrying about the new Miss America taking her day-after dunk in a  frigid Atlantic, the new chief executive of the Miss America Pageant, Robert Renneisen Jr., says he is not concerned about generating interest in the pageant.</p>
        <p>''The interesting element for us is going to be being on TV in the prime season rather than in a shoulder season,'' said Mr. Renneisen. ''It's a two-sided coin. On the one hand, if you do well, it will be helpful to us in booking future shows. On the other hand, doing well may be hard for us.''</p>
        <p>Still, while Miss America may have dodged the Olympics ratings bullet, it will have to deal with competition from the Major League Baseball League Championship Series on Saturday on Fox and NBC.</p>
        <p>After three consecutive years of declining ratings, Miss America drew 15.2 million viewers last year, an 8 percent jump over the 14.1 million people watched the pageant in 1998. But much of that increase was attributed to running the pageant from 8 to 11 p.m. rather than 9 p.m. to midnight, which had historically been the time slot.</p>
        <p>Robert Beck, the former chief executive of the Miss America Pageant, had suggested the earlier start, saying that the contest was a family broadcast and that it was losing audience by staying on so late.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, despite the ratings jump,  Mr. Beck was unceremoniously fired at the conclusion of last year's festivities and replaced this year by Mr. Renneisen, a former chairman and chief executive of The Claridge Casino Hotel. Mr. Beck says he was dismissed because he warned the board that it was in violation of the New Jersey Law Against Discrimination since the pageant bylaws barred divorcees, mothers or women who had had an abortion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Beck's suggestion to the heads of the state contests for removing the pageant from legal jeopardy went over about as well as an appearance by Andrew Dice Clay, and his ouster was almost immediate.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Beck defended himself by insisting he was trying to bring a little hipness to Miss America without losing its traditional core audience, and in fact filed a suit against the pageant in state superior court -- which is still pending -- claiming that he was wrongfully dismissed and seeking six months severance pay.</p>
        <p>As for the search for hipness, the musical headliner of the telecast this year will be O-Town, the Orlando-based boy band featured on the ABC summer series, ''Making the Band.'' On the other hand, Donnie and Marie Osmond, the epitome of clean-cut middle America, will be back for a second year hosting the pageant.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Renneisen he has been working as hard as any boardwalk pitchman. For example, he organized a contest in conjunction with USA Today for a grass-roots pageant judge in which 76,000 people entered the sweepstakes.</p>
        <p>Then he sued a Philadelphia sports-talk radio host, Howard Eskin, who said in one broadcast that he thought the Miss America contest was fixed. Enter the litigators, followed by the the reporters. Mr. Eskin insisted that he had not meant what he said, adding that he said the pageant was filing the suit for publicity. Mr. Renneisen said that he was merely trying to maintain the pageant's good name.</p>
        <p>In any event, if the move to October becomes a permanent one, it may not be such a bad thing, some say.</p>
        <p>''If it gets better TV ratings, then it will probably stay there,'' said Mayor James Whelan. ''We're long past the point in the casino era where we need an extra week or two to lengthen the summer season, which was the original purpose of Miss America. The driving thing is that it is a positive image associated with Atlantic City and whether it happens in September or October isn't particularly germane to us.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Michael Pollock, publisher of the Gaming Industry Observer, said that a pageant in October might benefit the casinos.</p>
        <p>''October is traditionally a weaker month in the casinos than September, when people still have outdoor things to do,'' said Mr. Pollock. ''And even though it might seem not to be a casino-type thing, it does generate a lot of publicity for the city and the skyline of casinos is always shown in the broadcast. That is an intangible and critical part of casino marketing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Renneisen said that there would be even more changes in future pageants, but that they would be subtle and concentrate on bringing younger people into the fold.</p>
        <p>''What we face,'' he said, ''is not a hard sell at all.''</p>
        <p>DOWN THE SHORE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
