<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Awaits Its Regulator-in-Chief</title>
    <meta content="08POLI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/business/08POLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237159"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Labaton, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simon, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindsey, Lawrence B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E0DE153CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="3109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Awaits Its Regulator-in-Chief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN LABATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Labaton, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US business is awaiting results of presidential election to find out who will be nation's chief regulator; Democratic and Republican campaign advisers say that on wide range of issues a Bush administration would be far friendlier to business than a Gore administration; some advisers say differences between Gore and Bush in regulating businesses are as much product of their careers as anything else; Greg Simon, telecommunications adviser to Gore, and Lawrence B Lindsey, economic advisor to Bush, comment; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is the ritualistic dance that happens here every four years.</p>
        <p>Although neither the Democratic nor the Republican presidential campaign says much publicly about a host of detailed issues of profound importance to corporate America, major companies and industries have been quietly positioning for months in anticipation of the election next month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is the ritualistic dance that happens here every four years.</p>
        <p>Although neither the Democratic nor the Republican presidential campaign says much publicly about a host of detailed issues of profound importance to corporate America, major companies and industries have been quietly positioning for months in anticipation of the election next month.</p>
        <p>Turnover at the top of Washington's powerful regulatory apparatus is inevitable no matter what happens 30 days from now, on Election Day. And while any change in the occupancy of the White House means a change in the way Washington addresses business issues, campaign aides on both sides predict that a move to a Republican president after eight years of Democratic rule would lead to a tectonic philosophical shift in this city's most important agencies, and a major retrenchment in the Rise of the Regulator.</p>
        <p>For all of the populist rhetoric of Vice President Al Gore, who has recently taken on big businesses in his speeches and compared himself to the trust-busting Teddy Roosevelt, no sharp policy shifts are expected if he should move to the larger office down the hall at the West Wing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has played a more prominent role than any other vice president in memory on a wide array of regulatory matters.  He has installed friends and former staff members to be top officials at the Federal Communications Commission and the Environmental Protection Agency, for example, and has directed the administration's response to a variety of legislative proposals that have been adopted or killed over the last eight years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has surrounded himself with campaign aides who had been top lobbyists for many major telecommunications businesses, including regional telephone companies, Internet service providers and software giants like Microsoft. But campaign officials say that if any of them ever joined a Gore administration, they would leave their associations with their former clients behind -- and that such relationships would not translate into policy changes.</p>
        <p>By contrast, corporate executives and lobbyists have been spending months preparing for the possibility of favorable rulings by a Republican administration, and the opportunities it presents for companies are being seen at just about every agency in town.</p>
        <p>''The differences would be dramatic,'' said Floyd Kvamme, a partner at Kleiner Perkins Caufield &amp; Byers, the venture capital firm, who has been advising Gov. George W. Bush on technology issues as a member of the Information Technology Advisory Council, a group of about 250 companies from Silicon Valley and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>To no one's surprise, Democratic and Republican campaign advisers said that on a wide range of issues -- from easing restrictions on computer technology exports to reshaping the nation's tort laws and making corporations more difficult to sue in product liability cases -- a Bush administration would be far friendlier to business than a Gore administration.</p>
        <p>Some advisers say the differences between Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush in regulating businesses are as much a product of their careers as anything else.</p>
        <p>''The place to start is Bush's background as a businessman,'' said Lawrence B. Lindsey, a former Federal Reserve governor appointed by Mr. Bush's father who is now Mr. Bush's top economic adviser. ''Gore has never been a businessman. Bush knows what it is to try to run a company and how frustrating regulation can be. The frustration comes not so much from complying with any particular rule, but from meeting the rules and yet still facing hurdles.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lindsey said the two candidates had fundamentally different views of the role of traditional economic analysis in making policy judgments.</p>
        <p>''To Gore, cost-benefit analysis is a dirty word, and in fact, he once likened such analysis to being a license to pollute,'' said Mr. Lindsey, himself an economist. ''Bush's view is that cost-benefit analysis should play an important role.''</p>
        <p>''Take, as one example, energy,'' Mr. Lindsey said. ''The current administration is opposed to drilling, opposed to pipelines, opposed to constructing new electric plants. For a while in the 1990's, that was a luxury we could afford. We don't have that luxury anymore. The neglect of energy policy is something that has to end.''</p>
        <p>MR. GORE'S advisers respond that Mr. Bush is too close to business interests, that in looking at issues through the lens of cost-benefit analysis he ignores greater public policy concerns, and that he would tend to favor corporate over consumer interests.</p>
        <p>''It's inconceivable that a Bush administration's Environmental Protection Agency would in any meaningful way resemble the current E.P.A., which has been headed by a woman, Carol Browner, who had been on Al's staff and was Al's choice,'' said Reed E. Hundt, a close friend of Mr. Gore who was selected by the vice president to be the administration's first chairman of the Federal Communications Commission.</p>
        <p>''Or turn instead to the Food and Drug Administration,'' Mr. Hundt added. ''It's inconceivable that a Bush F.D.A. would mount the kind of attack on tobacco that the Gore F.D.A. had done, trying as it has to regulate the addictive content of cigarettes.''</p>
        <p>Greg Simon, a top Gore adviser on regulatory and telecommunications issues, said it was naive for the Bush campaign to say the governor understands business issues simply because he was a businessman.</p>
        <p>''George Bush failed in more businesses than he succeeded in,'' Mr. Simon said, a reference to Mr. Bush's time in the oil business. ''And Al Gore has probably spent more time with the leading businessmen than anyone I know. And our economic policies have created the greatest prosperity this nation has seen. The fact that Gore never ran a general store doesn't mean a whole lot.</p>
        <p>''The biggest difference between these two men is that Gore has a long and deep history and that he has done a lot of thinking on these issues, particularly telecommunications,'' he added. ''In a Bush administration, these issues are going to be delegated. No one really thinks that George W. Bush is going to be sitting around the Oval Office thinking about what our nation's telecommunications policy should be.''</p>
        <p>Consumer advocates agree that there would be many differences between the two administrations, although they also say they have been disappointed that Mr. Gore has been less of an ally in recent years than he was earlier in his career.</p>
        <p>''Bush isn't as extreme as the ideologues in his party and wouldn't throw out all antitrust laws, although he would clearly be less aggressive than a Gore administration,'' said Gene Kimmelman, co-director of the Washington office of Consumers Union. ''But the fact is in the last four years, we've had the most enormous consolidation of telephone monopolies, cable monopolies and media companies despite the administration's attack on Republican deregulation efforts that would allow even greater concentration of ownership. It's hard to understand why, in the last four years, Al Gore, who had such a strong history of fighting for consumer pocketbook issues, has suddenly come down with laryngitis on these issues.''</p>
        <p>Still, some industries have been lobbying Washington on the assumption that the election will make a great difference to them.</p>
        <p>The nation's largest accounting firms, troubled by a Securities and Exchange Commission proposal that would sharply curtail their ability to perform consulting work for their audit clients, have lobbied intensely on Capitol Hill and have made hundreds of thousands of dollars in campaign contributions; lawmakers have urged agency officials to delay completing work on the proposal until next year.</p>
        <p>Some of the firms are hoping that, even if Mr. Gore wins, they can run the clock until after Arthur Levitt, the chairman of the S.E.C., steps down. Mr. Levitt has said that the firms' consulting work poses a potential conflict of interest for their audit work.</p>
        <p>IN the broadcasting industry, the major television networks and media companies say they have received word from the Bush campaign that a Republican in the White House would mean scaling back -- and possibly eliminating -- ownership limits that have made it impossible for companies like Viacom's CBS and General Electric's NBC to grow any larger. The changes being floated by the Republicans would also repeal the rules that have made it difficult for a broadcaster to own a newspaper in the same city.</p>
        <p>A few large radio broadcasting companies are hoping for similar relaxation in the rules, and have been working hard with the industry's powerful lobbying group, the National Association of Broadcasters, to prevent the government from beginning to license hundreds of low-power FM radio stations to churches, schools and civic organizations. Large broadcasters say the low-power stations would interfere with signals of existing stations, while the F.C.C. says broadcasters are really just concerned about competition for listeners.</p>
        <p>Telephone companies, too, are gearing up for new battles, particularly among the regional Bell companies, the long-distance carriers and the competitive local companies. There is a widespread view at the F.C.C. that a Republican leading that agency would make it significantly easier for the regional Bells to finally offer long-distance service in many states where they have so far failed to gain regulatory approval. The 1996 Telecommunications Act, which Mr. Gore played a large role in shaping, requires the regional Bell companies to open their local markets to competition before the federal government permits them to enter the $80 billion long-distance market.</p>
        <p>The Republicans have also signaled their intention to reconsider the concentration rules that have made it difficult for wireless telephone companies to expand their operations by getting more licenses for using a greater share of the airwaves.</p>
        <p>Antitrust enforcement, more vigorous under the Clinton administration than at any time since the 1960's, is also expected to undergo fundamental changes, but only if Mr. Bush wins. Both Democrats and Republicans say that the ideological divide between the parties in this area is narrower than at any time in decades, but that there would nonetheless be some major differences.</p>
        <p>''If there is a Gore administration, we're talking about more of the same,'' said Robert Pitofsky, the chairman of the Federal Trade Commission, who in a Democratic administration would likely continue to head the agency at least through next summer. ''We've tried to carve out a middle ground which departs from the ideological warfare of the past. We are vastly more active than the Reagan years and somewhat more active than the Bush years.''</p>
        <p>For most mergers, there will almost certainly be no difference between a Gore administration and a Bush administration. But for some of the larger ones, particularly in the transportation and telecommunications industries, the differences may be stark.</p>
        <p>Moreover, top advisers to Mr. Bush's campaign have been critical of several antitrust enforcement suits brought by the Justice Department and the Federal Trade Commission under the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>At a recent antitrust panel discussion in New York, Timothy J. Muris, a top Bush adviser on economic and competition issues, said the Clinton administration had opened too many cases involving accusations of monopolization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muris, a senior antitrust official in the Reagan administration, was especially troubled by two cases that would likely never have been brought in a Republican administration: the Justice Department's lawsuit against American Airlines, contending predatory pricing, and the Federal Trade Commission for bringing an antitrust case against Intel, contending that it had refused to share technical information with companies that build computers unless those companies also turned over their own technologies in exchange. (The American Airlines case has not yet gone to trial; the Intel case settled last year.)</p>
        <p>A BUSH administration would have powerful allies on the issue in Congress. Republicans lawmakers have vowed to strip the F.C.C. of authority to review corporate mergers, a position also supported by some in the Bush campaign; such a change would make consolidation far simpler among telephone companies, broadcasters and technology concerns.</p>
        <p>''The biggest changes that the F.C.C. would see would be in merger reviews, where there has been so much lobbying to get the agency out of that business,'' said Andrew Jay Schwartzman, president of the Media Access Project, which promotes diversity on the airwaves. ''Bush can be expected to resume the pattern established earlier, in the Reagan and Bush years, of looking at only competitive issues posed by these mergers, and not at the broader public interest questions, as the current administration has.''</p>
        <p>And that says nothing of what might happen in the Microsoft case, which is now on the docket of a Federal appeals court. Experts expect that a Gore administration would approach the case in the same way as the Clinton administration has. Advisers to Mr. Bush's campaign said they do not expect that his administration would do anything before the appeals court makes its decision, which could provide a wide range of opportunities to approach the case. Microsoft executives are hoping that a Bush administration  would dispose of the suit on terms far more favorable to the company than those proposed by the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>For all of the philosophical differences between the two campaigns, the real power over corporate America in Washington rests largely at a handful of Federal agencies that are given broad latitude to interpret both the mandate of the White House and the legislation adopted by Congress.</p>
        <p>While it is impossible to predict precisely who will be heading those agencies next year, there are some telltale indicators of what positions the agencies would take, depending on which party controls the White House.</p>
        <p>It is relatively easy to imagine what those agencies may be like if Mr. Gore wins, because he has already played the primary role in selecting many top regulators.</p>
        <p>In his book, ''You Say You Want a Revolution'' (Yale University Press, 2000), Mr. Hundt, the former chairman of the Federal Communications Commission, wrote that he viewed himself as an agent for realizing Mr. Gore's telecommunications vision.</p>
        <p>Four of Mr. Gore's top campaign advisers -- Thomas Downey, Peter Knight, Roy Neel and Mr. Simon -- all have significant experience working for large telecommunications clients, and one or more of them could play a major role in the next administration, either at the White House or one of the agencies if they are interested in joining the government.</p>
        <p>In a Bush administration, the top contenders for senior regulatory jobs include a handful of Washington officials like Michael K. Powell, a widely respected Republican member of the F.C.C., and Texas regulators like Pat Wood III, chosen by Mr. Bush to run the state's Public Utilities Commission. Neither is viewed as an ideologue. And both have described their roles as reducing regulation while trying to promote competition in markets that have traditionally been controlled by monopolies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell, the son of Gen. Colin L. Powell, has staked out a position as the F.C.C.'s moderate Republican member. He has shown strong political instincts, working well with both Republicans and Democrats. (Before joining the F.C.C., he was the chief of staff to Joel Klein, the former head of the Justice Department's antitrust division.) Mr. Powell also enjoys an unusually close relationship with the leadership of both the House and the Senate, as well as with Senator John McCain of Arizona, the chairman of the Commerce Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wood has been Mr. Bush's top regulator in Texas for more than five years, and he has put into effect state and Federal laws aimed at deregulating both the telephone and utilities industries. Staking out pragmatic and moderate positions on regulatory issues, he has enjoyed good relations with both Democrats and Republicans on the F.C.C.</p>
        <p>IN a recent interview, Mr. Wood said he and Mr. Bush shared the view that there is a need for some regulation in markets that have historically been dominated by a handful of companies, until those markets open up.</p>
        <p>''The governor was clear when he hired me that the old way of regulating did not work for consumers and that market competition is better for the customer than government regulation,'' he said. ''On our best day, we are not nearly as good as the market on prices and competition. But just backing out of regulation will be enough. You have to fix the problems of a century of regulation. So you can't just deregulate. You need competition first, and then deregulation. This is somewhat at variance with the more strident part of the party, which wanted to deregulate first. Then you have a deregulated monopoly. Who wants that?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
