<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barber Hoping the Ball Is Not Such a Stranger</title>
    <meta content="08GIAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/sports/08GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Falcons</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hermoso, Rafael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barber, Tiki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Atlanta Falcons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E5DC133CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barber Hoping the Ball Is Not Such a Stranger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAFAEL HERMOSO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hermoso, Rafael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Giants running back Tiki Barber in view of upcoming game against Atlanta Falcons; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tiki Barber is not one to show his frustration publicly, so when he shrank into an innocent bystander in the first half of the Giants' loss at Tennessee last Sunday, he seethed quietly on the sideline. Days later, while discussing his minor role in the Giants' second straight loss, Barber was again cautious. Yet he was the player who declared in August: ''There's big plays in me. It's just a matter of finding them.''</p>
        <p>Barber is the most dynamic player in the Giants' offense and ranked among the league leaders in rushing through the first three games. The Giants entered last week leading the National Football League in rushing only to abandon the run quickly against the Titans after a few failed attempts and an early deficit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tiki Barber is not one to show his frustration publicly, so when he shrank into an innocent bystander in the first half of the Giants' loss at Tennessee last Sunday, he seethed quietly on the sideline. Days later, while discussing his minor role in the Giants' second straight loss, Barber was again cautious. Yet he was the player who declared in August: ''There's big plays in me. It's just a matter of finding them.''</p>
        <p>Barber is the most dynamic player in the Giants' offense and ranked among the league leaders in rushing through the first three games. The Giants entered last week leading the National Football League in rushing only to abandon the run quickly against the Titans after a few failed attempts and an early deficit.</p>
        <p>The Giants rushed for 24 yards on 12 carries in the loss to Tennessee, and 19 of those were by quarterback Kerry Collins. Barber and Ron Dayne totaled eight carries for 1 yard, numbers that must improve today against Atlanta against a rushing defense that allows 4.5 yards a carry, fifth worst in the league.</p>
        <p>''It was almost helpless,'' Barber said. ''I felt like I wanted to be in the game to make some things happen. I couldn't even get in to return punts. They were driving the field every time. It was frustrating. I think that's the most frustrated I've ever been.''</p>
        <p>Barber rushed and lost 3 yards on the Giants first possession, then did not have another carry until the third quarter. The Giants ran only three plays on each of their first three possessions while running up a 21-0 deficit, but the Giants were quick to abandon the running game, which had carried them the first month of the season.</p>
        <p>Coach Jim Fassel and the offensive coordinator, Sean Payton, have blamed the game situation, the record-low 17 minutes 14 seconds time of possession and the running game's ineffectiveness for switching to the pass. But Barber, the Giants' best weapon, touched the ball only three times in the first half (one carry, one catch, one punt return). And if the Giants had run more, or more effectively, it might have given the defense a rest.</p>
        <p>Barber has not taken his frustrations to his coaches or requested to get more carries. He understands Payton is a first-year coordinator and needs the respect of his players.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I have to,'' Barber said. ''I think he knows.''</p>
        <p>''Certainly, we don't want to get away from our running game and never will,'' Payton said. ''There comes a time in a game where depending on the circumstance you have to get into a no-huddle package because of where you're at. Our philosophy has always been we're going to make every effort we can to find ways to run the football and get the ball into those guys hands. At the same time, that complements what we're trying to do throwing the ball.''</p>
        <p>Barber was one of Payton's greatest campaigners during the season's first three weeks, gushing about his expanded role in the bulging playbook. His confidence in Payton's revamped offense, which relies on multiple formations, personnel groups and last-second shifting, was very high. After running for 144 yards, including a 78-yarder, in the opener, Barber said he expected to have a big game and did not see a defense that could stop the Giants for long.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Barber machine off the field was rolling. His Web site sells T-shirts featuring caricatures of Barber and Dayne and their Thunder and Lightning nickname for $19.99. Another $30 buys you Barber's autograph. The Giants' Web site features a link to a National Football League video of Barber, Greg Comella and Sean Bennett running two miles up a mountain trail in Ramapo, N.J., during the off-season as part of their training.</p>
        <p>Such attention came at a price. Tennessee defensive end Jevon Kearse suggested the Titans were motivated by what they perceived as the Giants' bragging about Thunder and Lightning.</p>
        <p>Barber maintains confidence in the Giants' offense. He referred to last week's game as an anomaly and professed faith that the Giants' plays could work for himself, Dayne and receivers Amani Toomer and Ike Hilliard.</p>
        <p>Barber finished with 2 yards on five carries. Dayne was even less of a factor, carrying three times for minus-1 yard.</p>
        <p>''He didn't hardly play at all and I know that was frustrating,'' Barber said. ''When you have a guy like Ron and me and Amani, guys who are used to making plays, when you're relegated to just watching another team just destroy you, it's like, 'What can I do.' It makes you mad because you're like, What can I do? But it was just a situation where we really couldn't do anything.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
