<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bellport Returns to Form, And East Islip Is the Victim</title>
    <meta content="08SKOL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glickson, Grant</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EEDC133CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bellport Returns to Form, And East Islip Is the Victim</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRANT GLICKSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glickson, Grant</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bellport beats East Islip, 33-13, in high school football; other scores in New York metropolitan area noted</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bellport (3-1), the top-ranked preseason team in Division 2 in Suffolk County on Long Island, rebounded from its first loss of the season last week and defeated its archrival, East Islip (2-2), 33-13, yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Clippers, who lost by 15-7 to North Babylon on Sept. 28, received big-time performances from Sean Manning, Artie Haughey and Jason Fernandez.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bellport (3-1), the top-ranked preseason team in Division 2 in Suffolk County on Long Island, rebounded from its first loss of the season last week and defeated its archrival, East Islip (2-2), 33-13, yesterday.</p>
        <p>The Clippers, who lost by 15-7 to North Babylon on Sept. 28, received big-time performances from Sean Manning, Artie Haughey and Jason Fernandez.</p>
        <p>Manning, the senior quarterback, rushed for touchdowns of 9 and 15 yards and threw for one from 3 yards. Haughey, a senior tailback, carried 17 times for 119 yards and a touchdown. Fernandez, a senior linebacker, had 11 tackles.</p>
        <p>The Commack Cougars (4-0) spoiled Smithtown's homecoming by  beating the Bulls (1-3), 48-14. The senior quarterback Michael Prahalis completed 11 of 19 passes for a career-best 366 yards and 3 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>Prahalis, who also rushed for a touchdown, exploited Smithtown's defense by hooking up with Sean Malone (3 catches for 123 yards, 2 touchdowns) and Bryan Tornee (4 catches for 123 yards and a touchdown).</p>
        <p>''They are the best two receivers on Long Island, it's pretty obvious,'' Commack Coach John Foley said. ''Tornee may be the best receiver in New York State.''</p>
        <p>In a Nassau County Conference III matchup, Bethpage (4-0) knocked off visiting Plainedge (1-3), 35-12. Matt Rewkowski tossed a pair of touchdowns and Chris Britton ran for two others in the victory.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>ELIZABETH (5-0), a perennial offensive power in northern New Jersey, has emerged as one of the top teams in the state this season, thanks to its defense. The Minutemen shut out IRVINGTON (2-3) by 32-0 yesterday. It was the fifth consecutive game in which Elizabeth had not allowed a point.</p>
        <p>Sanyon Lembrick, the senior middle linebacker, registered 16 tackles and Joaquian Colon, a senior two-way lineman, had two sacks.</p>
        <p>Ibrahiam Halsey, a junior tailback, led Elizabeth's offensive charge, gaining 238 yards and 3 touchdowns on 30 carries while catching two passes for 50 yards.</p>
        <p>UNION (4-1) defeated PLAINFIELD (2-3) by 28-14 behind the running of the senior quarterback Jasper Hankins, who carried 18 times for 120 yards and scored two touchdowns.</p>
        <p>Rikki Cook, a highly touted Division I prospect, rushed for 181 yards and 2 touchdowns in MONTCLAIR's 21-7 victory over PARAMUS (3-1). Roberto Cruz's 33-yard fumble recovery helped the Mounties improve their record to 2-2.</p>
        <p>PREPS</p>
        <p>POLY PREP (6-0), behind Marcus Wilson's three-touchdown performance, disposed of WYOMING SEMINARY (3-2) of Wilkes Barre, Pa., 38-8.</p>
        <p>Wilson, a Division I prospect, rushed 12 times for 155 yards, including two touchdowns, and returned a kickoff 85 yards for another score. Defensively, the Blue Devils were led by the senior linebacker John Pannozzo (12 tackles) and John Combs, a junior defensive end, who had eight tackles.</p>
        <p>Rob Schaffer (23 carries for 144 yards) rushed for two touchdowns and Bob Acropolis added two others, including a 74-yard punt return, to help HOTCHKISS (3-0) defeat DEERFIELD (1-2), 29-0.</p>
        <p>HACKLEY (5-0) handed RIVERDALE (3-1) its first loss of the season by defeating the home team, 56-20. Casey Hilbert (4 carries for 160 yards) scored four touchdowns to pace Hackley. Riverdale's touchdowns came on a 16-yard pass from Evan Love to Andrew Berical; a 24-yard pass from Nick Brown, Riverdale's backup quarterback, to Joe Goldschmidt; and E. J. Trundle's 7-yard run.</p>
        <p>Dennis Hicks rushed for 246 yards and 3 touchdowns and Robert Quamily chipped in 111 all-purpose yards, including a 55-yard scoring reception, as CANTERBURY (2-1) humbled visiting SUFFIELD (0-2-1), 33-0.</p>
        <p>WESTCHESTER</p>
        <p>EDGEMONT (5-0), which has defeated its opponents by an average margin of 50 points this season, just missed the mark yesterday in the Panthers' 54-7 dismantling of DOVER (1-4). Matt Bernstein, who has committed to play at Wisconsin, carried much of the offensive load, rushing 17 times for 255 yards, including four touchdowns. Bernstein scored on runs of 16, 35, 40 and 63 yards. Joey Tarasiewicz contributed a 109-yard rushing performance and returned a kickoff 90 yards.</p>
        <p>P.S.A.L.</p>
        <p>Mike Jacob tossed two touchdowns and ran for another as FORT HAMILTON (4-1) made easy work of MIDWOOD (1-4), 32-13. Hakeem Godette contributed a pair of rushing touchdowns in the rout. For Midwood, quarterback Jon Hernandez completed 11 of 21 attempts for 140 yards, including an 8-yard scoring pass to Linus Edghill.</p>
        <p>C.H.S.F.L.</p>
        <p>Matt Rinklin, a senior quarterback, completed 11 of 15 attempts for 156 yards and 2 touchdowns as FORDHAM PREP (4-1) cruised past ST. JOSEPH'S BY THE SEA (2-3), 37-8.</p>
        <p>HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
