<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BENEFITS</title>
    <meta content="08BENE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001015T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D8143CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BENEFITS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Armani at the Guggenheim  WEDNESDAY -- A cocktail party and preview of the Giorgio Armani show at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum will benefit the museum's international exhibition and public outreach programs. Giorgio Armani will be there to discuss the installation, as will Robert Wilson, who designed it. Tickets for the event, which will run from 6 to 8 p.m., are $500, from (212) 935-1033, ext. 202</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Armani at the Guggenheim  WEDNESDAY -- A cocktail party and preview of the Giorgio Armani show at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum will benefit the museum's international exhibition and public outreach programs. Giorgio Armani will be there to discuss the installation, as will Robert Wilson, who designed it. Tickets for the event, which will run from 6 to 8 p.m., are $500, from (212) 935-1033, ext. 202</p>
        <p>Dinner With a Diva  WEDNESDAY -- Roberta Flack will perform at a benefit dinner at the Marriott Marquis for the Association for the Help of Retarded Children. The organization provides services to both children and adults in New York. Jim Watkins, a news anchor on Channel 11, will be the host. Cocktails at 6 will be followed by dinner at 7 and the show. Tickets, $500, from (212) 888-7003.</p>
        <p>Honoring Enablers  THURSDAY -- The International Center for the Disabled will honor a disability rights advocate, John D. Kemp, and others at a black-tie dinner at the Plaza. The evening will benefit the organization's rehabilitation, job-placement and counseling services. Drinks at 6:30 will be followed by dinner at 7:30. Tickets, $500, from (212) 585-6082.</p>
        <p>Sound and Light Ball  FRIDAY -- Helen Keller Services for the Blind will hold its annual Sound and Light Ball at the Crest Hollow Country Club, 8325 Jericho Turnpike, Woodbury, N.Y. The event will raise money for the organization's programs, which include a preschool, a summer camp, senior centers and employment counseling. Cocktails at 6:30 will be followed by dinner and dancing to the music of the Moonglow Swing Orchestra. Tickets, $350, from (718) 522-2122, ext. 201.</p>
        <p>Doo-Wop at the Pierre  FRIDAY -- The Platters will perform at a black-tie dinner at the Pierre to raise money for the National Alliance for Research on Schizophrenia and Depression. Drinks at 6:30 will be followed by dinner, dancing and the show. Tickets, $500, from (516) 829-0091.</p>
        <p>Party on the Pier  OCT. 16 -- Outward Bound will raise money for scholarships and other programs with a dinner at Pier 60 at Chelsea Piers. A cocktail reception at 6:30 will have a climbing wall available for the more adventurous; there will also be a silent auction. Dinner and a live auction will begin at 8. Tickets, $600, from (914) 424-4000.</p>
        <p>For Symphony Space  OCT. 16 -- William Hurt and Cherry Jones, the actors, will read short stories, and Graham Haynes, the cornet player, will be among those performing at a benefit for Symphony Space's programs, which include an educational outreach program in the New York City public schools. The performance will begin at 7 at Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway (95th Street), and will be followed at 8:30 by dinner and dancing at the Latin Quarter, 2551 Broadway (96th Street). Tickets, $300, or $50 for the performances alone, from (212) 864-1414, ext. 223.</p>
        <p>Harvest Meal  OCT. 16 -- City Harvest, which distributes food to more than 500 emergency food programs, will hold a dinner and auction at the Lighthouse at the Chelsea Piers Sports Complex. The evening will begin at 6:30 with a cocktail reception and silent auction. Chefs from Le Bernardin, Lespinasse, Picholine and nearly 30 other restaurants will prepare their signature dishes. At 8, there will be a live auction, with such items as a luncheon with Susan Sarandon and a dinner for 10 prepared by Eric Ripert, the chef of Le Bernadin. Tickets, $150, from (212) 822-8848.</p>
        <p>Spreading the Word About Art  OCT. 16 -- The American Federation of Arts will raise money for its traveling exhibitions and educational programs with a dinner-dance at the Rainbow Room. Jan Cowles, a member of the board, and Serena Rattazzi, the organization's director, will be honored. The black-tie evening begins at 7 with drinks; dinner follows at 8. Tickets, $1,000, from (212) 988-7700, ext. 47.</p>
        <p>A Glimpse of New York History  OCT. 17 -- The galleries of the Museum of the City of New York will be open at a black-tie dinner-dance to raise money for the museum's exhibitions and public education programs. The evening, at 1220 Fifth Avenue (103rd Street), will begin at 7 with a cocktail reception. Dinner is at 8, with dancing to the music of Bob Hardwick Sound. Tickets, $400, from (212) 876-7092.</p>
        <p>For Special Kids  OCT. 17 -- A dinner and fashion show will support programs for children with developmental disabilities at the Elizabeth W. Pouch Center for Special People of the Staten Island Mental Health Society. The event at the Staaten Restaurant, 697 Forest Avenue, West Brighton, Staten Island, will begin with drinks at 6:45. Tickets, $50, from (718) 442-2225, ext. 215.</p>
        <p>Kessler Foundation Gala  OCT. 17 -- Marilyn Horne will perform at a black-tie dinner at the Grand Hyatt for the Henry H. Kessler Foundation, which sponsors rehabilitation research for the physically disabled and community programs throughout the New York metropolitan area. Drinks at 6:30 will be followed by dinner at 7:30. Two ensembles from the Manhattan School of Music will perform. The event will honor Brooke Ellison, the quadriplegic who recently graduated from Harvard University. Tickets, $600, from (973) 243-6818.</p>
        <p>'Full Monty' Preview  OCT. 17 -- A preview performance of ''The Full Monty,'' at the Eugene O'Neill Theater, 230 West 49th Street, will raise money for the AIDS Care Center at New York-Presbyterian Hospital. The evening begins at 5:30 with drinks and a buffet dinner at the Supper Club, 240 West 47th Street; the curtain rises at 8. Tickets, $300, from (212) 685-1095.</p>
        <p>Casita Maria Gala  OCT. 17 -- A black-tie dinner at the Plaza will raise money for the Casita Maria settlement houses in the South Bronx and East Harlem. Agnes Gund and Oscar De La Hoya will be among those honored. Cocktails at 7:30 will be followed by dinner at 8:30 and dancing to the music of Bob Hardwick Sound. Tickets, $500, from (212) 807-7535.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 15, 2000, Sunday  A report in the Benefits column last Sunday about a fund-raiser that offers a preview of the Giorgio Armani show at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum misstated the date. It is this Wednesday; it was not last Wednesday. Information and tickets: (212) 935-1033, ext. 202.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 15, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A report in the Benefits column last Sunday about a fund-raiser that offers a preview of the Giorgio Armani show at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum misstated the date. It is this Wednesday; it was not last Wednesday. Information and tickets: (212) 935-1033, ext. 202.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
