<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Palate-Cleansing Olives</title>
    <meta content="08VINE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WINE UNDER $20"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DB163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="380" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Palate-Cleansing Olives</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD G. GOLDBERG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You've cherry-picked surprisingly low-priced Burgundies at a Zachys-Christie's auction. Wine is about sharing, so you've invited novices and aficionados home to sample a dozen; after an hour, the bottles will hop to the dinner table.</p>
        <p>But frustration lies ahead: your guests will find successive wines harder to appreciate at the tasting as tannins, acidity and alcohol accumulate on their palates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You've cherry-picked surprisingly low-priced Burgundies at a Zachys-Christie's auction. Wine is about sharing, so you've invited novices and aficionados home to sample a dozen; after an hour, the bottles will hop to the dinner table.</p>
        <p>But frustration lies ahead: your guests will find successive wines harder to appreciate at the tasting as tannins, acidity and alcohol accumulate on their palates.</p>
        <p>To solve this age-old problem, wine teachers and sponsors of professional tastings serve sparkling and still water, or baguette slices, or Carr's water crackers, or cheese.</p>
        <p>When James Trezise, president of the New York Wine and Grape Foundation, judged wines this year at the Los Angeles County Fair, he found something new. With the cheese cubes and crackers, he said, were ''the most delightful olives I've ever had,'' which, further, were ''regardless of the wine -- red or white -- the best palate cleanser I've ever had.''</p>
        <p>The foundation, in the Finger Lakes, holds a yearly statewide contest open to all 140 wineries. Mr. Trezise ordered the olives for this year's 16 judges. They were, he said, a hit.</p>
        <p>Intrigued, I fetched cans from the source, the C. C. Graber Company, California olive merchants since 1894. Bull's-eye! Graber's cured olives, tree ripened in the San Joaquin Valley, outrank the choicest Spanish olives I've ever tried with fresh fino and manzanilla sherries, a made-in-heaven marriage.</p>
        <p>Greenish, reddish-green and blackish-green, Graber olives are nutty, smooth, mellow, succulently meaty, but not filling. Paradoxically, eaten warm they not only neutralized the palate but also heightened the pleasures of the next reds and whites sipped. Go figure.</p>
        <p>Graber olives have long been sold in many D'Agostino markets, A. &amp; P.'s and Food Emporiums. Look only for No. 12 size olives in 7.5-ounce cans with a flat 1940's appearance (about $4).</p>
        <p>C. C. Graber is at 315 East Fourth Street, Ontario, Calif. 91764; (800) 996-5483; Web site: www.graberolives.com.</p>
        <p>HOWARD G. GOLDBERG</p>
        <p>WINE UNDER $20</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
