<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What If a McMansion Sprang Up Next Door?</title>
    <meta content="08COLU$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTY LINES/HASTINGS-ON-HUDSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gross, Jane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDD163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What If a McMansion Sprang Up Next Door?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gross, Jane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane Gross County Lines column on discovery that five cookie-cutter mansions are rising near wooded land behind her house in Westchester County, NY; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIVE McMansions, priced between $680,000 and $775,000, are rising from lots that few in my neighborhood knew were available for building. They are unsightly structures, out of scale and out of character with their surroundings, although they will probably look less jarring once the insulating thermal paper is sheathed in wood and the scarred earth is landscaped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIVE McMansions, priced between $680,000 and $775,000, are rising from lots that few in my neighborhood knew were available for building. They are unsightly structures, out of scale and out of character with their surroundings, although they will probably look less jarring once the insulating thermal paper is sheathed in wood and the scarred earth is landscaped.</p>
        <p>But their very existence is every homeowner's nightmare, Nimby in the most literal sense of the word.</p>
        <p>Sure, there are many in this ferociously anti-development county who will protest a proposed Home Depot a few miles away, which might increase traffic or threaten village merchants. But earthmovers and buzz saws right outside the window are a far more personal assault, to say nothing of a huge house -- or worse yet a subdivision -- on wooded land that had seemed an inviolable buffer.</p>
        <p>The cookie-cutter McMansions going up here are just the sort we residents of lower Westchester mock in places like Armonk or Somers. South of I-287, the unofficial dividing line between up-county and down, communities are denser and homes have the patina of age. Sure, we live cheek-by-jowl compared with the horse-farm set. But we are pretty sure that our neighborhoods will look tomorrow as they do today, because they were built out decades ago, to use the jargon of the developers.</p>
        <p>But in these flush times, builders are like eagles flying over the landscape looking for any sliver of property they can find. And buyers want more than the conventional 4BR, 2B; they want Great Rooms, three-car garages and T-1 lines.</p>
        <p>''Money is the bottom line,'' said Susan Maggiotto, the deputy village manager, speaking of both builders and buyers.</p>
        <p>I had called Ms. Maggiotto on a research mission, one I should have conducted when I bought my 200-year-old carriage house three and a half years ago. But I had fallen in love with the cozy bedrooms, the wraparound porch, the wide-plank floors, the brook -- and the deep woods behind the house, which stretched clear through to the next street. I only owned one-fifth of an acre but the woods made it seem like infinity.</p>
        <p>The woods were not mine. For a long while that didn't concern me. The dense trees had been there forever, after all. When roused to curiosity, procrastination set in. Who had time to go to Village Hall and figure out who owned Lot 23 of Sheet 36B of Block 782 in Hastings-on-Hudson? Or whether Lot 23 was ''buildable'' in an R-10 zone, where parcels must measure 100 by 100 feet.</p>
        <p>Then ground was broken for the five new homes, all on my regular hiking or cycling routes. Several were modular pre-fabs, and I watched the four sections of house come together like coupling railroad cars. The thought of one of these going up behind my woodshed, scattering the birds I was just learning to name, sent me racing to the Building Department.</p>
        <p>There, Charles Wucherer, the deputy building inspector, pulled out the big dusty volumes that included maps of the land in question. The good news is that Lots 23, 24 and 25 have a single owner, the Mignogna Family Trust in Springfield, Va. There is one house at the end of the property farthest from the woods.</p>
        <p>The property, with its irregular angles and uneven setbacks, is not large enough to subdivide without a variance. So the wooded section behind my house would be of no use to a developer and unlikely to be severed from the larger parcel if it were sold.</p>
        <p>But what if the three joined lots were to go on the market? The owners, Milt and Mary Mignogna, moved away some 15 years ago, one of their neighbors told me, and the couple has since died. That raised the specter of their heirs, in this over-heated real estate market, selling the property to some dot-com zillionaire who would consider the Mignognas' modest split-level no more than a tear-down. In its place could rise a 5,000-square-foot monstrosity.</p>
        <p>The Mignogna home is currently rented, and the tenants, a young family, tried to reassure me when I phoned. They plan to buy the property when the estate is settled, if the price is right. They might enlarge the current house, but they wouldn't dream of razing the woods.</p>
        <p>Fair enough. But I had one last question for the Building Department. What would it cost to buy Lot 23? More than $100,000, Mr. Wucherer told me, depending on who else wanted it.</p>
        <p>COUNTY LINES/HASTINGS-ON-HUDSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
