<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Business; In This Doctor-vs.-Nurse Debate, Long, Deep Breaths</title>
    <meta content="08NURS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/business/08NURS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Health Care Financing Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Health and Human Services Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Office of Management and Budget</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shalala, Donna E (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nursing and Nurses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E6DA143CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1208" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Business; In This Doctor-vs.-Nurse Debate, Long, Deep Breaths</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interrelated medical professions--physician anesthesiologists and nurse anesthetists--are locked in turf war over who may do what, in what setting, under whose supervision and for what pay; fight has been brewing since 1997, when Health Care Finance Administration, agency that decides what Medicare will and will not pay for, first proposed lifting federal rule requiring nurse anethetists be supervised by physician; proposal has been approved by Health and Human Services Sec Donna Shalala and awaits final administrative clearance, from Office of Management and Budget, before taking effect; argument is over whether shift would affect quality; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY work side by side every day in the high-pressure world of hospital operating rooms -- sedating patients, seeing them safely through intrusive medical procedures and easing their pain. But in the political arena, they are at each other's throats.</p>
        <p>Two interrelated medical professions -- physician anesthesiologists and nurse anesthetists -- are locked in a turf war over who may do what, in what setting, under whose supervision and for what pay.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY work side by side every day in the high-pressure world of hospital operating rooms -- sedating patients, seeing them safely through intrusive medical procedures and easing their pain. But in the political arena, they are at each other's throats.</p>
        <p>Two interrelated medical professions -- physician anesthesiologists and nurse anesthetists -- are locked in a turf war over who may do what, in what setting, under whose supervision and for what pay.</p>
        <p>Such battles have played out before in other pairs of licensed professions -- obstetricians and nurse midwives, for example, or ophthalmologists and optometrists -- and in other walks of life, like the building trades. But this conflict is inflamed by an accelerating flow of regulatory changes from Washington in the last three years, aimed at reining in health care costs.</p>
        <p>Under current rules, these doctors and nurses have no choice but to work as partners in what hospital parlance calls a ''team care'' setting. But the two groups are divided by education, pay and even sex -- most anesthesiologists are men, most anesthetists women.</p>
        <p>The fight has been brewing since 1997, when the Health Care Finance Administration, the agency that decides what Medicare will and will not pay for, first proposed lifting a federal rule requiring that nurse anesthetists be supervised by physicians. The proposal has been approved by Donna E. Shalala, the Secretary of Health and Human Services, and awaits a final administrative clearance, from the Office of Management and Budget, before taking effect.</p>
        <p>But though the issue is now before the budget office -- a decision could come any day -- ''this is really an argument over whether the shift would affect quality; everyone knows it would affect costs,'' said Robert D. Reischauer, president of the Urban Institute in Washington and an expert on health care policy.</p>
        <p>''This is a battle in a larger war -- and a war that could go on for decades,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The ins and outs of Medicare reimbursement have a way of becoming the stuff of political drama, because of their direct effect on older citizens, who punch above their weight at the ballot box. And the remainder of the health care industry tends to follow Medicare's lead. If Medicare thinks it is all right for a nurse anesthetist to treat people over 65 without a doctor's supervision, the argument goes, why not younger patients, too?</p>
        <p>WHAT line of thinking worries Dr. Ann Still, a professor of anesthesiology at the University of Alabama at Birmingham. Dr. Still was a nurse anesthetist before going to medical school and joining the American Association of Anesthesiologists, which has 34,000 members.</p>
        <p>''There's no comparison'' between the two disciplines, she said. Anesthesiologists, she said, typically have eight years of education -- four in medical school and four in specialized training -- while nurse anesthetists usually have a four-year nursing degree plus two years of specialized training. When a crisis brews, Dr. Still said, ''the physician takes control; they're the most qualified person in that operating room.''</p>
        <p>As she sees it, that is how it should be: having an unsupervised anesthetist in such a situation ''definitely could jeopardize a nurse's career while jeopardizing a patient's safety.''</p>
        <p>But the anesthesiologists association is having a difficult time proving the point conclusively. The group cited a University of Pennsylvania study that predicted higher anesthesia-related death rates under nurse anesthetists, but the association acknowledged that the study did not strictly compare supervised versus unsupervised care. A study by the Institute of Medicine, a government agency, commends the field of anesthesiology for its safety record, with just one fatal incident for each 250,000 procedures.</p>
        <p>The nurse anesthetists say arguments about quality of care are a smoke screen. ''This is a game that's been going on for years,'' said Kathy D'Andrea Knipe, president of the North Carolina chapter of the 28,000-member American Association of Nurse Anesthetists. ''The bottom line is money, and we're talking big bucks. The big boys are afraid of losing their cut of the pie.''</p>
        <p>When a Medicare patient has a procedure involving general anesthesia, half the fee paid by Medicare generally goes to the person who administered the anesthesia and monitored the patient in the operating room, most likely a nurse anesthetist.</p>
        <p>The other half goes to the anesthesiologist supervising the nurse, who must examine the patient beforehand but whose involvement thereafter may be minimal. A single anesthesiologist may be supervising, and receive payment for, up to four simultaneous operations in neighboring operating rooms.</p>
        <p>If the supervision requirement is dropped, hospitals and outpatient sites could save substantially; anesthesiologists earn an average of $240,000 a year, compared with the $94,000 or so for nurse anesthetists.</p>
        <p>Scrapping the federal rule would leave the issue in the hands of state regulators; 21 states now echo the Medicare rule in their own regulations. (New Jersey and Connecticut do, New York does not.) If the federal rule changes, states may see a green light to drop their own requirements, to help rein in costs and to allow hospitals more flexibility in staff selection.</p>
        <p>Anesthetists already work without anesthesiologists in some rural and inner-city facilities that cannot afford or cannot attract anesthesiologists. Nurses also work unsupervised in office settings like plastic surgery centers. But anesthesiologists worry that a rule change for Medicare patients in hospitals could create the impression that the federal government endorses the practice across the board, and worsen what some studies indicate is a growing glut of anesthesiologists by causing jobs to be eliminated.</p>
        <p>In contrast, Ms. D'Andrea Knipe said, the job market for nurse anesthetists ''is red-hot right now.''</p>
        <p>CONGRESS may apply the brakes. Many lawmakers are unpersuaded by the nurses' arguments for states' rights and are not ready to let the invisible hand of the market determine operating room staffs.</p>
        <p>The issue cuts across party lines; Senator Jesse Helms, Republican of North Carolina and ordinarily no friend of federal regulation, supports keeping the supervision rule, as does Senator Daniel P. Moynihan, the New York Democrat, while Senator Arlen Specter, the Pennsylvania Republican, has sided with the nurses who want the rule scrapped.</p>
        <p>Lobbying has been intense. The doctors group has contributed more than $1 million to political campaigns in this election cycle; the nurses group has contributed $400,000.</p>
        <p>They may have spent themselves to a stalemate in Washington. There are five bills now in Congress, three calling for more study and two affirming the change. Delay for a new study would keep the anesthesiologists and anesthetists working hand in hand, by law, for at least another year.</p>
        <p>''What you're seeing today will continue,'' Mr. Reischauer predicted, ''in skirmishes and battles'' -- perhaps for decades.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
