<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disgraced Mexican Is Back, With Accusations of His Own</title>
    <meta content="08MEXI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/world/08MEXI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salinas De Gortari, Carlos</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salinas De Gortari, Raul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zedillo, Ernesto (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Colosio, Luis Donaldo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E0D6123CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disgraced Mexican Is Back, With Accusations of His Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>MEXICO CITY, Oct. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Pres Carlos Salinas de Gortari returns to Mexico more than five years afer leaving in disgrace, and brings his 1,380-page memoir written during his Irish exile; book is directed at his hand-picked successor, Ernesto Zedillo, whom Salinas accuses of seeking political revenge by arresting his brother, Raul, and preparing arrest order against former president himself for supposedly obstructing investigation into assassination of Luis Donaldo Colosio, their party's presidential candidate in 1994; Salinas says he never asked his brother, Raul, for accounting of $90 million hidden in Swiss bank accounts; concedes that he has little credibility left among Mexicans; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than five years after leaving Mexico in disgrace, former President Carlos Salinas de Gortari has returned for good -- together with a 1,380-page memoir written during his Irish exile and directed above all at his handpicked successor, Ernesto Zedillo.</p>
        <p>In Mexico, Mr. Salinas's name has come to be commonly connected with corruption and greed, sins that voters also apparently held against his party, the Institutional Revolutionary Party, when they voted it out of the presidency last July after 71 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than five years after leaving Mexico in disgrace, former President Carlos Salinas de Gortari has returned for good -- together with a 1,380-page memoir written during his Irish exile and directed above all at his handpicked successor, Ernesto Zedillo.</p>
        <p>In Mexico, Mr. Salinas's name has come to be commonly connected with corruption and greed, sins that voters also apparently held against his party, the Institutional Revolutionary Party, when they voted it out of the presidency last July after 71 years.</p>
        <p>But the former president returned from exile last Tuesday to publicize his book, in which he accuses Mr. Zedillo, who leaves office on Dec. 1, of waging a campaign of disinformation against him to cover up what Mr. Salinas asserts was Mr. Zedillo's blunder in devaluing the peso and touching off the worst economic crisis in modern Mexican history.</p>
        <p>In his book, which is to be released in Spain on Monday, Mr. Salinas says  that after the devaluation, relations between the two men quickly deteriorated. Mr. Zedillo's ''resentful'' character, he writes, led him to seek political revenge by first arresting Mr. Salinas's eldest brother, Raul, on murder charges and then preparing an arrest order against the former president himself for supposedly obstructing the investigation into the  assassination of the party's presidential candidate in 1994.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for President Zedillo declined to comment at this time. Similarly, the office of the attorney general would not respond to the accusations until it had read Mr. Salinas's book.</p>
        <p>However, a former official in the administrations of both presidents said that Mr. Salinas was merely trying to shift the blame for the problems that he left behind.</p>
        <p>''He makes the devaluation sound like it was a decision plucked out of the air one day, but it wasn't,'' the official said. ''It was discussed over and over and an agreement was reached to do it in November, before Salinas left office. But then he changed his mind.''</p>
        <p>As part of a carefully orchestrated series of events intended to publicize the book and explain his official return, Mr. Salinas made excerpts available to The New York Times and three other publications in the United States and Mexico, on the condition that the material would not be published earlier than in Sunday issues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salinas, who was one of the most powerful and popular presidents in Mexican history before his fall from grace, also agreed to an interview in which, for the first time since he left office, he took all questions. He briefly visited Mexico twice last year but refused to discuss sensitive incidents.</p>
        <p>In a rustic cabin retreat in a corner of the luxurious residential compound of his in-laws in the south of Mexico City, Mr. Salinas, in a dark suit and multicolored tie, talked for almost two hours. He readily discussed everything from the activities of Raul, from whom he said he has never demanded an accounting of some $90 million hidden in Swiss bank accounts, to playing go-between for President Clinton and Fidel Castro.</p>
        <p>In the book, Mr. Salinas says that the reason for the bizarre hunger strike he began in early 1995, just after leaving office, was to stop what he had heard from a high-ranking member of Mr. Zedillo's government was an already prepared order for his arrest.</p>
        <p>''They were going to accuse me of covering up the assassination of Mr. Colosio,'' he said in the interview, referring to Luis Donaldo Colosio, a member of his cabinet whom he had chosen to become the governing party's candidate in the 1994 presidential election. Mr. Colosio was killed at a campaign stop in Tijuana in March 1994 in what remains Mexico's most troubling crime. When Mr. Salinas had to name a replacement presidential candidate a few days later, he selected Mr. Zedillo, who had been Mr. Colosio's campaign manager.</p>
        <p>During the remainder of Mr. Salinas's administration, which ended on Nov. 30, 1994, his government was unable to convince the public that it had solved the murder, even though a lone shooter arrested at the scene had been convicted and sentenced. Mr. Zedillo's new attorney general reopened the case. Within a few weeks he had arrested a second suspect and announced that there had been a conspiracy to kill Mr. Colosio that might be connected to Mr. Salinas's own government.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Zedillo not only put the blame of the economic crisis on me and my administration, but he also did the inconceivable, he put the blame on my administration for the death of Mr. Colosio,'' Mr. Salinas said. His voice dropped to a melodramatic whisper. ''This is inconceivable because Mr. Zedillo knew personally the relationship between Mr. Colosio and myself and Mr. Zedillo was the main beneficiary of the death of Mr. Colosio.''</p>
        <p>After he began his hunger strike in the northern city of Monterrey, Mr. Salinas vowed to take only water until the Zedillo government dropped its plans to arrest him. Within a few days, the attorney general issued an unusual statement saying he had no evidence that Mr. Salinas had tried to obstruct the investigation into Mr. Colosio's killing. Shortly afterward Mr. Salinas left Mexico, voluntarily, he insisted, ''to contribute to the recovery of stability.''</p>
        <p>A few years later, investigators pursuing the Colosio case questioned Mr. Salinas in his exile in Dublin. Although no charges were ever brought or proof given that there had been a conspiracy, let alone one attached to Mr. Salinas, many Mexicans still believe he was in some way involved in Mr. Colosio's death.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salinas's words now are sure to reopen many old wounds and add a further element of uncertainty to the transition of power to President-elect Vicente Fox in December. The triumph of Mr. Fox has made Mr. Zedillo unpopular with many members of his own party, who may therefore be more open to Mr. Salinas's criticism of the departing president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salinas said the opposition won last July because of the effective campaign by Mr. Fox and Mr. Zedillo's bungling. ''The historic defeat of the PRI in the year 2000 is explained not because it was 71 years in power but because of the last six years in power,'' he said. But Mr. Zedillo's popularity among the Mexican people remains high, while Mr. Salinas's mere presence generally elicits outrage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox has said he intends to set up a commission to look into the misdeeds of past administrations. Mr. Salinas said in the interview that  he welcomed such a move.</p>
        <p>The title of his book, which is written in Spanish, means, ''Mexico: A Difficult Step Toward Modernity.'' It will be available in English next year.</p>
        <p>The book reads like an extended state of the union address, though Mr. Salinas said he had received help from Gabriel Garcia Marquez, the  Nobel Prize winner, in loosening up his style.</p>
        <p>In a section on the Zapatista uprising in the poor southern state of Chiapas in 1994, Mr. Salinas writes that the most conservative elements in the Mexican government had pressed strongly to annihilate the rebel movement with military force.</p>
        <p>''In those first days of January 1994,'' he writes, ''Mexico faced the enormous possibility of returning to the epoch of brothers killing brothers. The danger was real.''</p>
        <p>He discusses in detail the conviction of his brother Raul on charges of ordering the murder of a governing party politician who was related to the Salinas family by marriage. The investigation under Mr. Zedillo's attorney general was tainted by a $500,000 payoff to one witness and the planting of a corpse to which investigators were led by a self-styled  witch.</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Salinas insisted that his brother was innocent of those charges. He also discredited the criminal charges that were brought against Raul after more than $90 million was found in his Swiss bank accounts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salinas said he had been unable to ask his brother directly where the money has come from ''because he's subject to terrible conditions of incarceration.'' He said that his brother is under 24-hour observation in prison and that everything he says is taped.</p>
        <p>At one point in his book, Mr. Salinas writes about a telephone call he received from President Clinton after Mexico's 1994 presidential election.</p>
        <p>''He asked me if I could look around with the Cubans and see what was going on,'' Mr. Salinas said. At that time thousands of Cubans on  makeshift rafts were heading for Florida. Mr. Salinas said he called Fidel Castro, ''and what followed were intense communications between President Castro and President Clinton through the mediation of the president of Mexico,'' which led to a compromise agreement that helped end the crisis.</p>
        <p>When asked whether the publication of his book just months before the end of Mr. Zedillo's administration indicated that he planned to return permanently to Mexico, Mr. Salinas replied, ''Yes, very much so,'' then added, ''But I've decided to present this book first.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Salinas conceded that he had very little credibility left among Mexicans and that many might regard the book as a self-serving attempt to rehabilitate his reputation. ''It will be a very difficult and long process, but I have great confidence in the wisdom of the Mexican people,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He also is putting great trust in a people who are notoriously unwilling to spend time reading. Newspapers here tend to have limited circulation, and most books except sexy cartoon comic books languish. Mexicans have not seen anything like Mr. Salinas's 1,380 page tome since 1988, when his predecessor, former President Jose Lopez Portillo, published his own two-volume, 1,279-page memoir.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
