<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Crowded Collection Finds New Space</title>
    <meta content="08ONLINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORK ONLINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of the City of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Denny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E2DD123CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="443" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Crowded Collection Finds New Space</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNY LEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lee, Denny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Museum of City of New York's new Web site described; photos (New York Online column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Museum of the City of New York is taking advantage of free real estate in cyberspace.</p>
        <p>Established in 1923 to preserve the city's artifacts, the museum was originally housed at Gracie Mansion, but moved five years later to a larger building at Fifth Avenue and 103rd Street. Since then, the museum has acquired more than 1.5 million objects, placing enormous pressure on its exhibition space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Museum of the City of New York is taking advantage of free real estate in cyberspace.</p>
        <p>Established in 1923 to preserve the city's artifacts, the museum was originally housed at Gracie Mansion, but moved five years later to a larger building at Fifth Avenue and 103rd Street. Since then, the museum has acquired more than 1.5 million objects, placing enormous pressure on its exhibition space.</p>
        <p>''The Web gives us a whole new outlet,'' said Peter Simmons, the museum's chief information officer. ''We get about 100 exhibition proposals from our staff each year, and maybe a dozen move forward. Many have merit, but we don't have the space or resources.''</p>
        <p>The site appeared in late summer, replacing an earlier version that ''was literally a brochure,'' Mr. Simmons said. It currently has 13 virtual exhibitions. Some were adapted from shows at the museum, but most could not be physically mounted for one reason or another.</p>
        <p>''The 18th-century shoes of New York are too fragile,'' Mr. Simmons said, referring to an online exhibition. ''For conservation reasons, it would have been impossible to display them.''</p>
        <p>Other shows, like a collection of paper fans, were initially considered too esoteric. But its online popularity may lead the museum to install an actual show.</p>
        <p>WHAT YOU SEE -- From the home page, click on ''Features'' to visit the online galleries. Highlights include ''Painting the Town,'' a catalog of cityscape portraits from 1800 to the present; ''New York Before the War,'' a retrospective of photographs commissioned by the Works Progress Administration; and ''New York in Love,'' an assortment of valentines exchanged between long-lost lovers. Other sections offer information about the museum's full archives, coming events and research help.</p>
        <p>LINKS -- To a vast collection of historical resources on the Web, including the Gotham Center at the City University of New York; the Forgotten City, ''the infrastructure of a lost metropolis,'' with images of buildings that no longer exist; and the 1964 World's Fair in Queens. There are also links to the NYC Historical Collections, a compendium of 45 historical societies from the Staten Island Historical Society to the Statute of Liberty National Monument.</p>
        <p>WHAT YOU GET -- Exhibitions from the Museum of the City of New York created for the Web.</p>
        <p>DENNY LEE</p>
        <p>NEW YORK ONLINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
