<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>F.Y.I.</title>
    <meta content="08FYI.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crickets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Holography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Daniel B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFDB143CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>F.Y.I.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schneider, Daniel B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>FYI column answers questions about crickets in Times Square, fate of Museum of Holography and definition of 'New York kiss-off;' drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jiminy, a Real One</p>
        <p>Q.: As we walked along West 44th Street toward Times Square the other night, my 3-year old son, an expert in such matters, said he could hear a cricket chirping. When we paused to listen, beside a scraggly street tree, my wife and I heard it too, amid the din of honking horns and revving car engines. Could there really be . . . a cricket in Times Square?</p>
        <p>A.: It's not impossible, said Louis N. Sorkin, an entomologist at the American Museum of Natural History, though the neighborhood hardly represents a natural habitat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jiminy, a Real One</p>
        <p>Q.: As we walked along West 44th Street toward Times Square the other night, my 3-year old son, an expert in such matters, said he could hear a cricket chirping. When we paused to listen, beside a scraggly street tree, my wife and I heard it too, amid the din of honking horns and revving car engines. Could there really be . . . a cricket in Times Square?</p>
        <p>A.: It's not impossible, said Louis N. Sorkin, an entomologist at the American Museum of Natural History, though the neighborhood hardly represents a natural habitat.</p>
        <p>Adult male crickets chirp by rubbing their wings together, using the sound to attract females and ward off other males, but unlike grasshoppers and katydids, they rarely fly, or even hop, for more than a few feet. Female crickets generally move to locate chirping males, which often stay in one spot their entire lives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sorkin said that since there is at least one street tree in the area, you might have stumbled onto a snowy tree cricket that wandered there, perhaps from a park. The pale green crickets, about a half-inch long, are usually found in gardens, where they are heard but rarely seen.</p>
        <p>Like most crickets they need a water source -- a puddle would suffice -- and eat almost anything organic. After mating, the female deposits her eggs in an incision in the tree bark, so it is at least conceivable that a small population could sustain itself in the area over time.</p>
        <p>In ''The Cricket in Times Square'' (Farrar Straus &amp; Giroux), George Selden's Newbery Medal-winning children's tale of 1960, a common field cricket travels from Connecticut to Times Square inside a picnic basket. Mr. Sorkin said such an event was not out of the question. Field crickets are the familiar inch-long, dark brown ones often heard chirping in pastures or lawns. Given the number of trains, cars and buses pouring into Midtown each day, who is to say that a stowaway from the suburbs didn't just hop out of a briefcase or knapsack and start to chirp?</p>
        <p>''It might be a misidentification,'' Mr. Sorkin said. ''It might have been a katydid.''</p>
        <p>Talk About Ghostly</p>
        <p>Q.: When I took my grandchildren to visit the Museum of Holography this summer, it wasn't there anymore. Where did it go?</p>
        <p>A.: Faced with mounting debt, the erosion of corporate and governmental support and a decline in tourism brought on by a recession, the museum, at 11 Mercer Street, closed in 1992. At a bankruptcy auction the following year, its entire collection of 1,500 holograms -- three-dimensional photographs made with laser beams -- was bought by the M.I.T. Museum for $180,000. It was believed to be the world's largest.</p>
        <p>The collection was moved to Cambridge, Mass., and put in archival storage. ''Now we're cleaning it up and going back though it,'' said Prof. Stephen A. Benton, curator of holography for the museum. Holograms will occupy less than a third of the 10,000-square-foot museum, he said.</p>
        <p>The Museum of Holography opened in 1976, before commercial applications made holograms a ubiquitous part of the consumer environment, and when they were seen as a promising new artistic medium.</p>
        <p>''It had a bit of an identity crisis,'' Professor Benton said. ''It started out as an art gallery, but found out a much bigger constituency was interested in the science of holograms, so it tried to be both things.''</p>
        <p>On Either Coast, Beat It</p>
        <p>Q.: What's a New York kiss-off?</p>
        <p>A.: The Dictionary of American Slang (published in 1975 by Thomas Y. Crowell) says it was a term used in Los Angeles in the 1940's to describe an abrupt brushoff or dismissal.</p>
        <p>But in New York, according to the dictionary, it was supposedly called a ''California kiss-off.''</p>
        <p>DANIEL B. SCHNEIDER</p>
        <p>E-mail: daschn@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: daschn@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
