<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Easing of Some Restrictions By West Could Happen Soon</title>
    <meta content="08SANC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/world/08SANC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE SANCTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Bank for Reconstruction and Development</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Monetary Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DE133CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Easing of Some Restrictions By West Could Happen Soon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton and European leaders, who promised immediate easing of sanctions once Slobodan Milosevic is gone from power, seem likely to remove most sanctions on trade and investment with Serbia in coming week; United States and 15 nations of Eureopan Union are also preparing to restore nation's rights at United Nations, World Bank and International Monetary Fund; some of toughest sanctions will remain in force, including ban on transferring assets out of country and some penalties aimed at Milosevic and his close associates; State Dept says it is important to guard against Milosevic-linked elite fleeing country with looted wealth (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Disastrous civil wars, onerous sanctions and corrupt misrule turned Yugoslavia from the most open and developed nation in the old Communist orbit into the sick man of Central Europe, with a collapsed economy, plummeting living standards and a wretched inventory of bombed bridges, severed electrical lines and outdated factories.</p>
        <p>But President Clinton and European leaders, who promised an immediate easing of sanctions once they feel certain that Slobodan Milosevic is gone from power, seem likely to remove most sanctions on trade and investment with Yugoslavia in the coming week. This will include lifting remaining restrictions of the sale of oil, which have in any case eroded badly. And it seems likely they will eliminate the ban on air travel, currently suspended, to and from Serbia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Disastrous civil wars, onerous sanctions and corrupt misrule turned Yugoslavia from the most open and developed nation in the old Communist orbit into the sick man of Central Europe, with a collapsed economy, plummeting living standards and a wretched inventory of bombed bridges, severed electrical lines and outdated factories.</p>
        <p>But President Clinton and European leaders, who promised an immediate easing of sanctions once they feel certain that Slobodan Milosevic is gone from power, seem likely to remove most sanctions on trade and investment with Yugoslavia in the coming week. This will include lifting remaining restrictions of the sale of oil, which have in any case eroded badly. And it seems likely they will eliminate the ban on air travel, currently suspended, to and from Serbia.</p>
        <p>The United States and 15 nations of the European Union are also preparing to restore the nation's rights at the United Nations, the World Bank and the International Monetary Fund.</p>
        <p>Some of the toughest sanctions will remain in force, at least for now, including a ban on transferring assets out of Yugoslavia and some penalties aimed at Mr. Milosevic and his close associates. State Department officials said that it was important to guard against the Milosevic-linked elite fleeing the country with looted wealth.</p>
        <p>Western nations are also preparing to expand a multibillion dollar reconstruction plan for several Balkan countries to include Serbia, creating what some European officials have referred to as a mini-Marshall Plan for the war-torn region.</p>
        <p>Oil, telecommunications, consumer products and infrastructure companies, some of which operated in Yugoslavia before sanctions began making investments difficult in the early 1990's, also seem likely to explore business opportunities there if the new democratic government proves stable.</p>
        <p>But while General Electric, Foster Wheeler and Procter &amp; Gamble among other companies had significant operations in the old Yugoslavia, several analysts and company officials said that it would take time to attract significant private investment to the largely state-controlled economy. It has fallen more than a decade behind many of its former Communist neighbors, which began economic overhauls after the fall of the Berlin Wall.</p>
        <p>''The problem was Milosevic, Milosevic, Milosevic, now it's economy, economy, economy,'' said Milan Panic, a Serbian-American who runs California-based ICN Pharmaceuticals, which once owned one of the largest private companies in Serbia. ''This will be a major test for the United States and Europe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Panic's pharmaceutical plant in Belgrade was confiscated by the Milosevic government in a bitter political battle after Mr. Panic contested -- and lost -- a race for president against Mr. Milosevic in 1992. He now plans to return to Serbia. But he says reconstruction will be slow.</p>
        <p>''It is still a socialist country and you will have to change the culture,'' he said in an interview. ''It will need aid money -- seed money -- before you will see much private investment.''</p>
        <p>Clinton administration officials said that NATO-led intervention in Kosovo and the campaign to oust Mr. Milosevic will ultimately remain incomplete unless they help reverse the free fall of Yugoslavia's economy, which contracted by 20 percent last year, with 50 percent inflation and 30 percent unemployment.</p>
        <p>''Now is not the time for the United States or our allies to retreat from the Balkans in complacency,'' Mr. Clinton said Friday. ''Now is the time to stay the course and stick with people who have won their freedom; the time to build the economic and civil institutions that will allow democracy to endure.''</p>
        <p>A senior State Department official said Western powers are aiming to channel money and expertise into repairing roads, bridges, schools and hospitals, and to deliver aid quickly.</p>
        <p>''We want to fund projects that will have an immediate impact on people's lives,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>After NATO forced Mr. Milosevic to retreat from Kosovo last year, the United States and the European Union began a joint effort known as the Stability Pact to support democracy and spark economic growth in the Balkans. The European Commission and the World Bank administer the pact. But the United States plays a significant role and sees it as the main vehicle for extending a helping hand to Serbia, the senior State Department official said.</p>
        <p>Participants in the pact, especially the World Bank and European nations, have already made pledges of hundreds of millions of dollars to finance projects like a wastewater treatment plant in Croatia, a new airport terminal in Albania and road improvements in Kosovo.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration recently introduced a bill in Congress that would grant zero-tariff trade status to democratic Balkan nations. And the United States Overseas Private Investment Corporation has set aside $150 million to back companies willing to invest in the Balkans.</p>
        <p>Serbia could use the help. A group of private Yugoslav economists recently estimated that NATO allies inflicted about $4 billion dollars of damage on Serbia during the Kosovo war, while they put the cumulative financial impact of sanctions at $30 billion.</p>
        <p>But several Clinton administration officials said that Europe and the private sector would have to take the lead, citing the reluctance of Congress to fund major international aid programs.</p>
        <p>Theoretically, Serbia should be an attractive market. It has 11 million consumers, slightly more than neighboring Hungary. The Danube, one of Europe's major rivers, runs through it. It is the overland bridge between Western Europe and Greece and Turkey.</p>
        <p>Early investors could include Ericsson, the Swedish telecom company, which has ambitions to resume work on a $210 million mobile phone network. The engineering company, Foster Wheeler, of Clinton, N.J., built oil facilities in Yugoslavia before the Kosovo war and has expressed interest in helping rebuild the nation's largest oil refinery, damaged by NATO bombs.</p>
        <p>But Gary Litman, managing director for Europe and Eurasia at the United States Chamber of Commerce in Washington, said that while many multinationals had expressed interest in Balkan investments, the market could prove unattractive in the short term.</p>
        <p>''There's been almost 10 years with no development there,'' he said. ''There's a big question mark about whether this curiosity will translate into real investments.''</p>
        <p>SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE SANCTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
