<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Tough Contest, Senator Heads Left</title>
    <meta content="08SPAN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spano, Nicholas A (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abinanti, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DB163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1036" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Tough Contest, Senator Heads Left</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on eight-term Republican New York State Sen Nicholas Spano, who, infuriating party conservatives, takes aggressive left-of-center positions aimed at maintaining his popularity in largely Democratic district as he fights challenge from well-known Democrat, Thomas Abinanti; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE evening last month, Nicholas A. Spano, an eight-term Republican state senator from Yonkers, ambled confidently into the heart of what would be hostile territory for most Republicans: a midtown Manhattan fund-raiser held by a prominent abortion rights organization.</p>
        <p>But what would seem like political suicide to many Republicans was just another day's work for Nick Spano, who has always gone out of his way to prove that he is not like other Republicans, if only to maintain his popularity in a district that is largely Democratic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE evening last month, Nicholas A. Spano, an eight-term Republican state senator from Yonkers, ambled confidently into the heart of what would be hostile territory for most Republicans: a midtown Manhattan fund-raiser held by a prominent abortion rights organization.</p>
        <p>But what would seem like political suicide to many Republicans was just another day's work for Nick Spano, who has always gone out of his way to prove that he is not like other Republicans, if only to maintain his popularity in a district that is largely Democratic.</p>
        <p>That task has taken on heightened urgency in recent weeks as Mr. Spano finds himself facing a tough re-election fight against a well-known Democrat, Thomas J. Abinanti, the majority leader of the County Board of Legislators, who contends that the senator is out of touch with voters in the district.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano's response has been decisive and swift. He has aggressively staked out positions that have infuriated conservatives in his party, even as they have delighted gun-control supporters, women's groups, advocates for the poor and other organizations typically wary of, if not hostile toward, Republicans.</p>
        <p>In March, he sponsored a bill requiring safety locks on guns and then successfully lobbied to have the measure included in a new gun-control law passed this summer. He was also one of the few Republicans in the Legislature to urge party leaders to adopt a law that protects abortion clinics from obstruction.</p>
        <p>More than that, though, he has vigorously begun to distance himself from his party's presidential nominee, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, contending that the positions Mr. Bush has taken on issues like gun control and abortion are not only unpopular in his district but also at odds with Mr. Spano's beliefs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano made it clear in an interview that he is seeking not only to draw distinctions between himself and Mr. Bush but also between himself and the Republican Party. ''My intention is to ask voters to look for Nick Spano on the ballot,'' he said. ''The only link I will have in this campaign is with my own record, not with any other candidate.''</p>
        <p>The strategy seems to be paying off. Many groups that are traditional allies of the Democratic Party have not only endorsed him but have also pledged to use their get-out-the-vote operations to help him defeat Mr. Abinanti.</p>
        <p>Kelli Conlin, the executive director of the New York affiliate of the National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League, said it was important that her group do more than simply endorse Mr. Spano, given the heat he has taken in his party for his positions.</p>
        <p>''Senator Spano has a serious challenge, and we feel we must go all out for him,'' said Ms. Conlin, whose group sponsored the Manhattan fund-raiser Mr. Spano attended last month. ''Democrats are not happy about this. But from our perspective, the issues he has supported supersede the question of what party he belongs to.''</p>
        <p>Even some prominent Democrats have praised Mr. Spano, arguing that he should be sent back to Albany for another term. County Executive Andrew J. Spano, a Democrat who is not related to the senator, said that the county could ultimately suffer if Mr. Spano loses, given that county leaders rely on him to push their agenda before the Senate's Republican leadership.</p>
        <p>''You know, Nick has served the county well,'' he said in an interview on WVOX-AM radio in New Rochelle, adding that he gives the county entree to the Senate leadership.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Abinanti argues that a vote for Mr. Spano would be a vote for the same Republican majority in the Senate that has resisted acting on issues like gun control and bias crime in previous years.</p>
        <p>He said the only reason Republican leaders had begun softening their positions on such issues is to protect themselves from election-year challenges. Mr. Abinanti also sought to link his own electoral fate to the Democrats' national ticket, keenly aware of its popularity statewide and in his district.</p>
        <p>''A vote for Nick Spano maintains a philosophy in the state Senate that is inconsistent with the Gore-Lieberman agenda,'' said Mr. Abinanti, who represents Greenburgh in the County Legislature. ''The changes we have seen from Nick Spano and the Senate have been more about image than substance.''</p>
        <p>The contest over Mr. Spano's seat is among a handful of legislative races that could determine the fate of more than 30 continuous years of Republican control of the state Senate. Democrats have targeted Republican incumbents from competitive districts, like Mr. Spano, for challenges this year, hoping for a strong Democratic turnout to tip things in their favor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spano, who is a deputy majority leader in the Senate, represents the 35th Senate District, which begins north of the Bronx and covers Greenburgh, Eastchester and parts of Yonkers and White Plains.</p>
        <p>In addition to adopting positions that reflect the largely moderate attitudes of voters in his district, Mr. Spano has also used his influence in Albany to shore up his support. He has, for example, funneled millions of dollars in state money for pet projects in his district.</p>
        <p>The aid included $300,000 to build a burn unit at the Westchester County Medical Center, $200,000 to buy equipment for the Greenburgh Book Mobile, $250,000 to help build a building for the Westchester Music Conservatory, $50,000 for the Westchester Arts Council and $50,000 for the Westchester County Diabetes Association.</p>
        <p>That came on top of $16 million that he urged state leaders to provide to Yonkers schools to help close a budget gap.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abinanti is serving his fifth term on the Board of Legislators. He is chairman of the Health Committee and co-chairman of the Rules Committee and has promoted laws to impose tougher regulations on guns, to curb mob influence in the trash-hauling industry and to discourage teenage smoking.</p>
        <p>POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
