<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Healthy Quarter for Bonds, So Why Are Investors Leaving?</title>
    <meta content="08BOND$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/business/08BOND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E5DA143CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Healthy Quarter for Bonds, So Why Are Investors Leaving?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investors are fleeing bond funds despite healthy third quarter for bonds, especially Treasuries; nearly $26 billion has flowed out of taxable bond funds since mid-August last year; bond sectors that have suffered most are mortgages and high-yield, or junk bonds; graphs (M)2</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHY are bond funds so unloved?</p>
        <p>Bonds have been doing very well this year, especially Treasuries. The Lehman Brothers Treasuries index returned 8.1 percent through the third quarter. The Lehman aggregate bond index, which includes government, corporate and other bonds, was up 7.1 percent. And with the stock market in a slump that had all three major indexes down for the year through September, bond mutual funds ought to be attractive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHY are bond funds so unloved?</p>
        <p>Bonds have been doing very well this year, especially Treasuries. The Lehman Brothers Treasuries index returned 8.1 percent through the third quarter. The Lehman aggregate bond index, which includes government, corporate and other bonds, was up 7.1 percent. And with the stock market in a slump that had all three major indexes down for the year through September, bond mutual funds ought to be attractive.</p>
        <p>But five years of double-digit returns from the equity market seem to have made it all but impossible for bonds to capture the attention of investors. In fact, money is pouring  out of bond mutual funds at a pace not seen since 1994, when interest rate increases by the Federal Reserve led to one of the worst years ever for bonds.</p>
        <p>Nearly $26 billion has flowed out of taxable bond funds since mid-August last year, according to AMG Data Services, which tracks fund flows. That total is almost two-thirds of the $43.1 billion in net withdrawals from March 1994 to March 1995. The current run on bond funds has drained away 4.6 percent of their assets since last August.</p>
        <p>The bond sectors that have suffered the most are mortgages and high-yield, or junk, bonds. Some $10.7 billion flowed out of high-yield bond funds, according to the AMG data.  Funds concentrating on mortgages lost $5.2 billion, and funds buying both mortgages and Treasuries lost $11.9 billion. There were also outflows of $2.5 billion from funds concentrating just on Treasuries.</p>
        <p>The only sector in favor was corporate bonds, with a net inflow of $4.4 billion.</p>
        <p>Bond portfolio managers can do nothing but shake their heads, knowing that the nation's love affair with stocks has not abated.</p>
        <p>''People are looking at a strong economy that seems to be softening gradually, and they are assuming that in a soft landing there will be no need for an equity correction,'' said Ned Notzon, president of the Spectrum Funds at T. Rowe Price. ''They are prepared to ride it out.''</p>
        <p>So is he. In his personal retirement portfolio, 90 percent of his assets are in stocks, even though he expects some kind of stock market correction in the near future. ''For retirement money, it would be a big mistake to move out of equities and then try to get back in at the right time,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Wayne D. Lyski, chairman and chief investment officer of Alliance Capital Fixed Income Investors, said that changing investor sentiment about bonds ''will take some period of time when returns on stocks are negative, or zero, or close to zero.'' He said he thought that the stock market might be entering such a period, but that it could still take another year to begin changing investors' minds.</p>
        <p>The only good news for bond funds in the AMG data is that the rate of net withdrawals from taxable bond funds has been slowing. Only $495 million flowed out in the third quarter, down from $13.6 billion in the first. ''But it is too early to say this is a turnaround because the only funds attracting investors are corporates,'' said Robert Adler, president of AMG Data Services.</p>
        <p>The moderate scale of bonds' performance adds to the problem. Doing well in bonds just doesn't look like much, compared with the recent performance of stocks and stock mutual funds. Over all, according to Morningstar, taxable bond funds had a return of 1.7 percent in the third quarter and were up 4 percent for the first three quarters of the year. Bond funds concentrating on Treasuries were up 6.4 percent for the three quarters, while corporate bond funds rose 5.7 percent. Those three-quarter returns are a lot better than those of the leading stock indexes, but they still look anemic against the track record of equities during most of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>On top of that, some managers of bond funds think that bonds may be in for some tough going in the months ahead, particularly because of the inflation threat posed by the higher price of crude oil.</p>
        <p>In the long run, said Graham Allen, managing director for global fixed income at Wells Capital Management, interest rates should move lower. ''But in the short run, inflation fears about oil could hold the market up,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Although inflation fears are pushing up some interest rates, signs that the economy is slowing from its breakneck pace of the last year are  helping to pull other rates down.</p>
        <p>The play of these countervailing forces is visible in the performance of Treasury bonds at either end of the yield curve. The yield of the 10-year note rose from 5.68 percent on Sept. 1 to 5.80 percent at the end of the third quarter as crude oil prices finally began to worry some investors.</p>
        <p>But evidence that the Federal Reserve's six interest rate increases since June 1999 are curbing growth has pushed shorter-term interest rates lower. From a May 1999 high of 6.91 percent, the yield on the Treasury's two-year note was down to 5.97  percent at the end of the quarter, significantly below the federal funds rate, the central bank's short-term  rate target, now at 6.5 percent.</p>
        <p>Portfolio managers' recommendations for this type of market are running in the same direction as bond-fund inflows: toward investment-grade corporate bonds.</p>
        <p>Several bond portfolio managers say the spread, or differential, between yields on Treasury securities and corporate bonds offers investors an opportunity, because they can profit in two ways -- from the higher yield on the corporate bonds, and from the capital gain on the price of the corporate bond as its yield declines, narrowing the spread between corporate bonds and Treasuries.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that Treasuries have much farther to go,'' said Kirk D. Hartman, executive vice president at Banc of America Capital Management. ''The real value here is in spread products,'' he added, using the Wall Street term for bonds like corporates that trade at a higher yield than Treasuries.</p>
        <p>He also sees doubts growing among investors that huge government surpluses will be around for long after the presidential election. ''Right now, there is a lot of skepticism about the surplus,'' he said. ''Both candidates are going to spend the surplus. So it makes one wonder if the Treasury market is going to go away'' after all, as would be the case if budget surpluses endure.</p>
        <p>MANY money managers are staying away from high-yield bonds. ''There is a lot of risk aversion,'' said Mr. Lyski of Alliance Capital, explaining the flight from high yield. This sector, several portfolio managers said, is behaving as if the economy were in a  recession. And the rate of corporate defaults has been rising.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lyski is not making any big bets with the money he manages. His most significant move recently was to increase holdings of investment-grade corporate bonds. He has gone from owning fewer of these bonds than are included in the benchmark index he uses to gauge his performance, to being ''slightly overweight.''</p>
        <p>He thinks high oil prices are likely to be a bigger drag on economic growth than is now expected. The market believes that interest rates will stay where they are, or move up or down by only a quarter of a percentage point, he said, but if he is right about oil's extra drag on growth, then ''the risk is greater that interest rates will move down further.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Notzon of T. Rowe Price is also making a small bet on corporates. ''But I am only buying names that I think very highly of,'' he said. ''These are complicated times.''</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
