<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Elderly Living Options, at a Price</title>
    <meta content="08COV.$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retirement Communities and Assisted Living</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oser, Alan S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Luxury and Vacations/Active Adult</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement Communities and Assisted Living</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E6DB163CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="3030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Elderly Living Options, at a Price</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN S. OSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oser, Alan S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on mixed-use luxury assisted-living and independent-living facilities for elderly that are beginning to crop up in New York City which, because of location, are high-priced; variety of services, amenities and personal assistance offered described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER a three-year stint in Stamford, Conn., Ruth Zema is back in Yonkers. A widow in her mid-70's who was living alone at home, Mrs. Zema decided in 1997 that she needed senior housing. She had to go out of state -- to Stamford -- to find a residence she considered acceptable.</p>
        <p>She took a small apartment in an assisted-living project, paying $100 a day under a plan that provided all her meals, housekeeping service and four hours a week of personal service -- in her case help in bathing and the monitoring of the medication she was taking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER a three-year stint in Stamford, Conn., Ruth Zema is back in Yonkers. A widow in her mid-70's who was living alone at home, Mrs. Zema decided in 1997 that she needed senior housing. She had to go out of state -- to Stamford -- to find a residence she considered acceptable.</p>
        <p>She took a small apartment in an assisted-living project, paying $100 a day under a plan that provided all her meals, housekeeping service and four hours a week of personal service -- in her case help in bathing and the monitoring of the medication she was taking.</p>
        <p>But now she is back in Yonkers. In August the Hyatt Corporation opened its first senior residence in New York state, a Classic Residence on Riverdale Avenue just over the line from Riverdale in the Bronx. It has an assisted-living component, but Mrs. Zema moved into a one-bedroom unit on the 12th floor in the independent-living section of the building. Now she pays $3,300 a month under a plan that includes two meals a day and weekly housekeeping but no personal services.</p>
        <p>''Mother no longer needs the level of care she needed when she moved to Stamford,'' said her daughter, Shelley Short, a Yonkers schoolteacher. ''And now what she does need is available close to home.''</p>
        <p>At a time when some producers of assisted-living housing are finding it more difficult to get financing and have had to curb their plans for growth, the arrival of a Hyatt senior residence in Yonkers -- its first in New York state -- stands as a symbol of the emergence of new forms of urban senior housing set in motion by the development surge of the late 90's. Because of a stringent regulatory system and high land, development and operating costs, they have been slow in arriving in the area. And the prices that new arrivals are paying in some of the new developments raise the question of affordability: how many seniors will be able to take advantage of this housing in the high-cost New York City area?</p>
        <p>Hyatt's Classic Residence represents what might be called the mixed-use luxury high-rise for the elderly. Most of the apartments are designed for independent living by active adults. Amid opulently furnished public spaces, the residents get a hotel-like experience. An emphasis is placed on fine food, with breakfast and dinner served in an elegant dining room. Recreational, transportation and housekeeping service -- but no medical services -- are included in the regular monthly charge.</p>
        <p>There are 310 apartments on 17 floors at the Classic Residence, but only 199 of them are for independent living. Rents in these apartments range from $3,400 to $5,500. Around the corner from the main entrance is an entrance to a simpler lobby, from which elevators run to three lower floors with 75 apartments set aside for assisted living -- Hyatt calls it the personal care section -- and one floor with 36 apartments for residents with Alzheimer's disease or other dementia conditions.</p>
        <p>Another mixed-use luxury senior-housing specimen, in Manhattan, puts an even greater emphasis on independent living. At the 14-story Hallmark at Battery Park City, where occupancy began this summer, 198 of the 217 apartments are designed for independent living, with an average rent of $5,500 a month within a range of $4,000 to $8,000. The rent includes two meals a day and weekly housekeeping. Twenty apartments on the second floor are reserved for assisted living.</p>
        <p>In Riverdale, the Hebrew Home for the Aged, the operator of a 1,000-bed nursing home and other senior housing on a 19-acre campus overlooking the Hudson River, has opened a market-rate seniors' residence on Johnson Avenue, in the heart of the community's commercial district.</p>
        <p>There, the lowest rate for an apartment is $3,300 a month, which includes three and a half hours a week of personal assistance and weekly housekeeping; the highest fee is $4,900 a month for tenants needing daily services. All plans provide three meals a day. Although many incoming residents are mobile and still drive, they typically come in prepared to move eventually to the Hebrew Home for a higher level of care. They get priority on the waiting list.</p>
        <p>New developments that emphasize independent living raise another question. As tenants age in place, will they gradually transform their buildings into quasi-nursing homes, with a large number of residents of advanced age needing much personal assistance?</p>
        <p>It was the latter transformation at an assisted-living senior residence on West 86th Street that led Mary Baker to move to the Hallmark at Battery Park City this summer. ''There were so many people there in wheelchairs that it got depressing to me,'' said Mrs. Baker, a retired public-relations executive in her late 70's. ''I don't require anything, but if I need it here, I can get it.''</p>
        <p>Brookdale Living Communities, a Chicago company that owns and manages the Hallmark, has operated a similar project with 341 apartments on North Lake Shore Drive in Chicago since 1993. Mark J. Schulte, the company's chairman, said that residents on average are 78 years old upon arrival and they stay for four or five years.</p>
        <p>On the affordability issue, developers say that retirees typically need an annual retirement income of at least $50,000 from pension benefits, Social Security and personal investments to make new unsubsidized senior housing affordable. At a Manhattan project like the Hallmark, tenants will probably have income of upwards of $75,000 a year, normally with additional assets as well. The projects may receive lower-cost publicly assisted financing, a below-market land-cost benefit or property tax relief, but they get no state reimbursement for the health care they provide.</p>
        <p>THE assumption is that the elderly retirees can pay as much as 80 percent of their income for housing and supportive services -- far more than younger people pay for housing as a percentage of income. Financial support is sometimes available from other family members, although developers say that usually it is the middle-income elderly themselves who are paying. They also say that it is difficult to judge the financial capacity of tenants, who rarely disclose their total assets.</p>
        <p>In New York City, the elderly with incomes under $25,000 -- the upper threshold of ''low income'' in the housing world -- will often be eligible for subsidized senior housing. Although there may not be enough of it, subsidy programs are in place to produce and sustain it.</p>
        <p>The city's Department for the Aging estimates that there are about 26,900 units of low-income senior housing in New York City, plus 8,850 beds in adult homes, mostly with two unrelated low-income seniors in a room. There are also 6,100 units for seniors in middle-income Mitchell-Lama developments. The federal low-income housing production program for the elderly, known as Section 202, is ongoing, but no new Mitchell-Lama production is under way.</p>
        <p>''Judging from inquiries that come to me in a variety of ways, there is an unmet demand for moderate-income senior housing in the city,'' said Herbert W. Stupp, Commissioner of the New York City Department for the Aging. ''There is a gap in availability in the moderate-income group.''</p>
        <p>According to the 1998 census, there are about 182,700 individuals in the city who are over 60 years of age, not institutionalized, with incomes between $25,000 to $50,000 a year. People in this category can normally afford to spend as much as 80 percent of their income for shelter, food and personal services, developers say.</p>
        <p>Since personal services in an urban environment are close at hand, and many of the elderly have housing bargains in rent-regulated apartments or long-owned houses with low property taxes, the city itself is a naturally occurring retirement community -- a ''NORC,'' as the industry calls it. This moderates the need for new housing for city residents, although the market for it includes seniors living out of town and hoping to live closer to their families.</p>
        <p>In any case, developers sense a demand. In testimony at a joint hearing of the City Council's Committees on Aging and on Housing and Buildings last June, Stanley Diamond, chairman of Castle Senior Living, a developer of senior housing based in Teaneck, N.J., called for an ''affordable assisted living'' program that would make it possible for developers to hold monthly assisted-living charges to about $2,500, thereby serving an elderly population with retirement income and assets that can produce $30,000 to $35,000 a year.</p>
        <p>''The cost of assisted living is roughly 60 percent that of nursing homes,'' Mr. Diamond said. ''It is a far more effective alternative for people when skilled nursing is not required.'' He also urged that New York state apply to the federal government for a waiver that would allow people eligible for Medicaid to use this benefit in assisted-living buildings. With a waiver in place, the facility can be reimbursed for each Medicaid-eligible resident at a rate equal to 50 percent of what a nursing home would get as reimbursement for such a tenant. The moderate-income resident whose assets ran down would therefore be covered over time, keeping the development financially viable.</p>
        <p>Castle Senior Living gets no such assistance at its Prospect Park Residence at Grand Army Plaza in the Park Slope section of Brooklyn, which opened in 1997. The 132 apartments, three-quarters of them one-bedrooms, were totally rented in 30 months. Prices range from $2,335 to $4,800 a month (and $4,500 to $5,500 for the 23 dementia residents). The average rent is $3,500 a month, with three meals, housekeeping and a recreational program.</p>
        <p>In some assisted-living developments, personal service is provided by the management's own health-care staff; at the Prospect Park Residence it is available through a home-health care agency as needed.</p>
        <p>Castle Senior Living's newest project, in Manhattan, is an example of the costs in a private Alzheimer's/dementia facility when neither Medicaid reimbursement nor development subsidies are available to the operator. It is a new 60-unit nine-story building at 430 East 80th Street, named the 80th Street Residence. Opened in April, it has 35 tenants so far, served by a full-time staff of 50.</p>
        <p>The cost to residents ranges from $5,100 to $7,900 a month, which covers all expenses except medical treatment. A penthouse rents for $8,900. ''It's all the residents' income, we find, not their children's,'' said Julie Biblowitz, Castle Senior Living's marketing director in the city .</p>
        <p>In Riverdale, a 206-unit project called Atria Retirement Living opened last November alongside Henry Hudson Parkway at 239th Street, developed as a joint venture by Atria Retirement and Assisted Living of Louisville, Ky., and Jeffrey E. Levine, a Queens-based developer. About 50 percent of the units have been rented, at prices ranging from $3,200 for a one-bedroom to as much $4,800 for one of the 28 two-bedrooms. Atria operates about 100 assisted-living projects with 9,600 housing units in 26 states.</p>
        <p>''Affordability has not been an issue for us, because of the demographics of the area,'' Mr. Levine said. ''But unfortunately, people who earn less than $50,000 -- the threshold figure -- are priced out of this product without some form of assistance.''</p>
        <p>An even newer private-pay Riverdale residence for the elderly is Riverdale Terrace, 59 units in a seven-story building in the heart of Riverdale's commercial district, at 3247 Johnson Avenue, near 235th Street. Riverdale Terrace, offering a variety of plans to tenants depending on their personal-care requirements, opened last month and 90 percent of the apartments are spoken for, the management said.</p>
        <p>T HANK God for the teachers' retirement system,'' said Dorothy Kaufman, a 69-year-old widow, who taught for 29 years in the Yonkers system and rents a one-bedroom unit with a kitchenette in the Riverdale residence for $3,300 a month.</p>
        <p>Daniel A. Reingold, executive vice president of the Hebrew Home, said that seniors using this type of private-pay senior housing will need an income of about $50,000 a year. But in contrast to most senior-care residences, Riverdale Terrace assures its residents access to a 1,036-bed nursing home at the Hebrew Home if necessary. ''Access to a full continuum of services is the key benefit that we are able to offer,'' Mr. Reingold said, ''and we are committed to providing it regardless of the tenant's ability to pay for it from private income.''</p>
        <p>In Mr. Reingold's opinion, all new senior housing facilities would ideally be affiliated with an organization that offers full-time long-term care. ''Without this, the danger is that when the residents get too frail to live independently -- and it can happen quickly -- a personal crisis will hit,'' he said. ''The family has to be prepared to deal with this.''</p>
        <p>The Classic Residence in Yonkers has tried to provide this continuum of care within the building, although there is no direct affiliation with a hospital or nursing home. It addresses the cost problem essentially by offering a variety of plans that allow residents to pay only for the services they need, when they need it. Bond financing for the project that was obtained through the Yonkers Industrial Development Agency helped bring its debt costs down. The architect was Perkins Eastman Architects of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Fifty apartments are occupied so far and 50 more are spoken for, said Steven J. Cohen, executive director. Rates for the independent-living units are $3,450 to $4,325 for one-bedrooms; $4,725 to $5,000 for one-bedrooms with dens, and $4,875 to $5,525 for two-bedrooms. The basic rate in the personal-care section is about 20 percent higher, and in the Alzheimer's section it is roughly 30 percent higher.</p>
        <p>''We have applied to the state to establish our own licensed home health-care agency,'' Mr. Cohen said. With a license, Hyatt would offer health care directly so that tenants would not have to obtain it from an outside licensed provider. The company has already received licenses to give health services in both the personal-care and Alzheimer's sections.</p>
        <p>About 40 percent of the tenants have come from New York City, Mr. Cohen said. The company anticipates full occupancy in two to three years, he said.</p>
        <p>Hyatt's development partner at the Classic Residence was Forest City Enterprises, the national developer-builder based in Cleveland, which has a subsidiary known as Forest City Daly Housing, headed by Michael D. Daly and based in Manhattan, to develop senior housing. Forest City has a management arm, Sterling Glen Communities, licensed by the state as an adult-home operator and home health-care agency.</p>
        <p>With long-term hopes of building new projects both in the city and the suburbs, Forest City so far has in construction one assisted-living building in the city: 84 apartments in a nine-story building on the Grand Central Parkway access road at 72d Avenue in the Forest Hills section of Queens.</p>
        <p>''We believe the mixed-use project is more ideal than pure assisted living,'' Mr. Daly said, ''because you can find more people to fill your building. But you need a bigger project -- at least 175 or 200 units. The most promising locations demographically are the Upper East Side and West Side of Manhattan.''</p>
        <p>Senior-housing operators have no easy time competing for land with market-rate housing developers. In assisted living, about 60 cents of every dollar earned in rent goes for labor costs, they say. Put a different way, developers can afford to pay only about $20,000 to $30,000 per developable unit to acquire a site for this right? in a senior-housing project in Manhattan. With current achievable rents in market-rate housing, developers may pay about three times that amount.</p>
        <p>BUT pure assisted-living projects are showing up. Last March Sunrise Assisted Living, based in McLean, Va., an operator of 165 assisted-living properties in 23 states and three countries, opened an assisted-living development with 104 apartments on Emmons Avenue in Sheepshead Bay in Brooklyn. Another went into construction about the same time in Mill Basin, Brooklyn, on Strickland Avenue, with 98 units. These developments. charging between $2,000 to $4,000 a month, probably will be affordable to residents able to pay no more than $50,000 a year for all their expenses.</p>
        <p>''Most of our residents will not require lengthy nursing home stays because of all the services we can provide to the frail elderly ourselves,'' said Paul J. Klaassen, chairman of Sunrise.</p>
        <p>But in Manhattan, subsidies are normally required for the rare new senior housing development. Thus low-income seniors are the principal beneficiaries of the deSales Assisted Living Residence, a new nonprofit project at Fifth Avenue and 108th Street, sponsored by the St. Francis deSales Church at 96th Street and Lexington Avenue. There are 127 units on 14 floors, two outdoor gardens and panoramic views of Central Park. Occupancy began last August.</p>
        <p>About two-thirds of the apartments have been leased at basic rents of $828 for tenants, which are supplemented by Medicaid payments averaging $2,500 a month per apartment. Under a special state program, the Department of Health agreed to license 4,200 beds for assisted living with Medicaid reimbursements in 1995, and the deSales Residence was awarded 127. Qualifying tenants typically derive all their income from Social Security and a modest pension, together amounting to less than $25,000 a year.</p>
        <p>But Terrence Moan, the project's development consultant, said the sponsor was permitted to lease out 10 percent of the apartments irrespective of tenant income. ''The 12 apartments rented for $3,800 a month, and the demand was overwhelming,'' he said. They were gone four months ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
