<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Those Gray Boxes on Poles? Fear Not, the Company Says</title>
    <meta content="08RADI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metricom (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">St Louis, Les</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crow, Kelly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DA143CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="397" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Those Gray Boxes on Poles? Fear Not, the Company Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KELLY CROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crow, Kelly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Les St Louis of Metricom, which has strung up 3,000 shoebox-size radio transceivers on light poles around New York City as part of wireless Internet network called Ricochet, says they will not interfere with other signals or harm anyone; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gray shoebox-sized radio devices are fastened to light poles around the city, and Metricom, a California Internet company, wants you to feel good about them.</p>
        <p>The company recently strung up 3,000 radio transceivers on street lamps and traffic lights across the city as part of a wireless Internet network called Ricochet. Through Ricochet, which began Sept. 21, subscribers can connect to the Internet with portable modems that send and receive signals through the devices instead of through telephone or cable lines. The modem costs $300, and the service costs $79 a month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gray shoebox-sized radio devices are fastened to light poles around the city, and Metricom, a California Internet company, wants you to feel good about them.</p>
        <p>The company recently strung up 3,000 radio transceivers on street lamps and traffic lights across the city as part of a wireless Internet network called Ricochet. Through Ricochet, which began Sept. 21, subscribers can connect to the Internet with portable modems that send and receive signals through the devices instead of through telephone or cable lines. The modem costs $300, and the service costs $79 a month.</p>
        <p>The transceivers, which use low-power microwaves, have left some New Yorkers fascinated and others leery, though, and so Metricom, which has networks in Atlanta and San Diego, spent the last month courting community boards and addressing questions about privacy and safety. The company also hoped to avoid comparisons to cellular phones, which many people love to hate.</p>
        <p>''Most people equate the word 'wireless' with cell phones, but we're completely different,'' said Les St. Louis, the company's director in the metropolitan region, who pitched the product to Upper West Siders at a recent Community Board 7 committee meeting.</p>
        <p>The transceivers use a frequency different from that of cell phones and are not held close to the ear. They are placed 20 feet off the ground on poles spaced every four city blocks. Metricom paid the city $60 to $120 a pole for the space and agreed not to put the devices on any decorative poles.</p>
        <p>Mr. St. Louis said the devices would not pick up or interfere with other signals or harm anyone.</p>
        <p>''We're as safe as a baby monitor or a garage door opener,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some residents, like Barbara Adler, a member of the community board, said they were worried about all the signals whirring overhead.</p>
        <p>''I think the whole concept is fantastic, but as we become more wireless, we have to consider all these waves,'' Ms. Adler said. ''They're invisible, and perhaps one day they'll kill us all.''</p>
        <p>But others, like Kevin Fullam of  West 85th Street, said they liked the idea. ''I'm up for wireless technology as long as it doesn't interfere with my quality of life,'' he said. ''It's just a small box, so it's O.K.''</p>
        <p>KELLY CROW</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: UPPER WEST SIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
