<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Neighborhood Opponents of Milosevic Testify to Wild Abuses by His Son</title>
    <meta content="Y08SCEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/08/world/08SCEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1237264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE HOMETOWN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pozarevac (Serbia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Marko</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5DE133CF93BA35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Neighborhood Opponents of Milosevic Testify to Wild Abuses by His Son</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>POZAREVAC, Yugoslavia, Oct. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Residents of Pozarevac say Slobodan Milosevic's son, Marko, left town at characteristic high speed in convoy of three jeeps, supposedly to flee with his wife and child to Russia; say Marko should have been prevented from leaving so he could stand trial for string of accusations ranging from drug-smuggling and racketeering to physical violence and political repression; local members of student resistance organization tell of being beaten up by Marko and his thugs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Momcilo Veljkovic was one of Marko Milosevic's greatest foes here in his hometown, opposing his thuggish control, even at the cost of two severe beatings from Marko, Slobodan Milosevic's son, and his friends.</p>
        <p>Mr. Veljkovic and his band of friends who had resisted the Milosevic government were in the forefront, he said, of Thursday's attack on the federal Parliament and state television building that finally broke 13 years of misrule. But he took today's report that Marko Milosevic had left for Russia with no surprise and little desire for revenge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Momcilo Veljkovic was one of Marko Milosevic's greatest foes here in his hometown, opposing his thuggish control, even at the cost of two severe beatings from Marko, Slobodan Milosevic's son, and his friends.</p>
        <p>Mr. Veljkovic and his band of friends who had resisted the Milosevic government were in the forefront, he said, of Thursday's attack on the federal Parliament and state television building that finally broke 13 years of misrule. But he took today's report that Marko Milosevic had left for Russia with no surprise and little desire for revenge.</p>
        <p>''Have a nice trip,'' he said at being told of eyewitness reports that Marko, his wife and son had flown to Moscow. ''I am not happy but not sad. Not happy because he should be tried under the law. I can forgive him personally as a Christian and churchgoer, but I cannot take away the responsibility that they all bear for everything that happened.''</p>
        <p>Residents said Marko, a sometime racing driver notorious for his wild behavior, for trashing cars and failing to get more than a high school education, had left Pozarevac, where his parents had grown up and where the family has at least one house, for the last time on Wednesday. He drove out at characteristic high speed in a convoy of three jeeps, shaking loose several people who tried to pursue him, the townspeople said.</p>
        <p>''I am glad he managed to escape them,'' Mr. Veljkovic said, ''because otherwise people would have lynched him and our great victory would be stained.''</p>
        <p>But several residents said Marko should have been prevented from leaving so he could stand trial for a string of accusations ranging from drug-smuggling and racketeering to physical violence and political repression.</p>
        <p>''I feel wonderful -- I am breathing the air of freedom,'' said Dragoslav Micic, an unemployed electrician, sitting across from Marko's  discotheque, Madonna.</p>
        <p>But few applauded the ransacking of the bakery and computer shop that Marko owned here, or the break-in and robbery of equipment from the discotheque.</p>
        <p>''It was unnecessary,'' said Boban Pencic, 30, a power company worker who was walking by the broken windows and smashed glass of the computer shop, Cybernet Communications. ''But I would like to have seen a full judicial procedure. They should have been investigated because there are strong accusations of illegal dealings,'' he said.</p>
        <p>While Marko held sway here, it was the members of the student organization Otpor, or Resistance, and opposition parties who bore the brunt of police harassment and investigation. Mr. Veljkovic, 39, spent two months in jail and still faces charges of attempted murder of one of Marko's bodyguards after a fight in a cafe here on May 2. He says Marko and his bodyguards attacked him and a friend, Radojko Lukovic, when they went to help a third man. The attack, he said, was by the same men who beat him so badly in 1997 that he was hospitalized and lost his upper teeth. That time it was because he was selling opposition newspapers, he said.</p>
        <p>Pozarevac was always a firmly controlled town, an hour's drive south of Belgrade, surrounded by villages whose spacious, neat houses testify to the money earned abroad by the hundreds of thousands of expatriate Yugoslavs.</p>
        <p>Marko Milosevic commanded the loyalty of the police and local authorities and indulged his fancy with various business ventures, including a children's park, called Bambiland, and the Madonna discotheque, both of which closed down recently for apparent lack of customers.</p>
        <p>His opponents say that his main business was selling drugs, and that he also engaged in gasoline and cigarette smuggling. Mr. Veljkovic -- who at one point pulled out the false teeth he said were the legacy of his 1997 beating -- saw the darkest side of his character, close up.</p>
        <p>On the night of May 2, Mr. Veljkovic and a friend went to see if they could help a friend who had been beaten and threatened by Marko and his men, and then told to turn up at a cafe and sign his allegiance to the Yugoslav Left Party run by Marko's mother, Mirjana Markovic.</p>
        <p>''We went there, but we had no intention of fighting,'' he said. ''We would not dare. They all had pistols and security police I.D.'s.'' But when he walked up to the table, the men set upon him, one hitting him on the head repeatedly with a pistol, he said. Others started attacking his friend and a lawyer who was there by chance and tried to intervene.</p>
        <p>Marko arrived soon after as the fight spilled into the street. Mr. Veljkovic said that ''he came by car, with a pistol in his hand, cursing and screaming'' to have Mr. Veljkovic and his friends killed. Marko joined in the beating in the middle of the street, he said, adding: ''When an elderly woman shouted at him to stop, Marko jumped at her face, 'What do you want? They are NATO mercenaries and traitors.' ''</p>
        <p>''He was speeding -- you know they all take cocaine,'' he said. ''We can say it now: They were the main dealers of drugs here; that's why they are so violent.'' That evening, he said, he and his friends were in jail, accused of attempted murder.</p>
        <p>He does not want revenge, Mr. Veljkovic said. Marko actually approached Mr. Veljkovic and Mr. Lukovic last Saturday when it was becoming clear that his father's grip on power was slipping.</p>
        <p>''He told us he would not let anyone touch his workers or endanger his property because he had earned it with his blood,'' he said. ''He had no intention of leaving the country and would not allow anyone to touch his parents.''</p>
        <p>But for all the tough talk, Mr. Veljkovic said Marko was clearly nervous, jiggling his legs constantly in his chair. ''He was acting confident. but it was a false confidence,'' he said. ''He wanted to show who was still the boss. Until the last moment they believed they were strong and could not believe the rage that people were in.''</p>
        <p>SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE HOMETOWN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
