<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Architect Earns the Right to Build the Blues</title>
    <meta content="03HOTE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/03/living/03HOTE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DD1F3DF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Architect Earns the Right to Build the Blues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MUSCHAMP</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gentrification in rapidly transforming Avenue C and its side streets on Manhattan's Lower East Side, alarming longtime residents; many depend on federal rent subsidies, which landlords may now forgo in order to charge market rates; even when subsidies are not involved, some landlords are eager to evict low-income tenants; newcomers are lured to area in large part by its diversity, which is now threatened by their arrival; area's has history of resisting gentrification, sometimes violently; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALONG with a room, the usual luxury amenities and a gift shop stocked with beautiful books on Paris, guests at Sofitel, the new hotel on West 44th Street, are rewarded with an unexpected privilege. They get to participate in the education of an architect. His name is Yann Leroy. He is a partner at the New York firm Brennan Beer Gorman. He is 41. And Sofitel is his solo, stand-alone-building debut in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The hotel, between Fifth Avenue and Avenue of the Americas, is a coltish performance, more promising than accomplished, of interest mainly on account of where it might lead Mr. Leroy in the future and where it sits in relationship to his bad-boy past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALONG with a room, the usual luxury amenities and a gift shop stocked with beautiful books on Paris, guests at Sofitel, the new hotel on West 44th Street, are rewarded with an unexpected privilege. They get to participate in the education of an architect. His name is Yann Leroy. He is a partner at the New York firm Brennan Beer Gorman. He is 41. And Sofitel is his solo, stand-alone-building debut in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The hotel, between Fifth Avenue and Avenue of the Americas, is a coltish performance, more promising than accomplished, of interest mainly on account of where it might lead Mr. Leroy in the future and where it sits in relationship to his bad-boy past.</p>
        <p>It takes most architects half a lifetime to build a stage. Mr. Leroy is not the first to begin by setting up a soapbox in the street. In 1986, soon after moving to New York from Paris, he was like a one man band against the city's architectural establishment. His specialty was distributing leaflets outside lectures by prominent practitioners like Michael Graves and Cesar Pelli. When the Museum of Modern Art opened its ''Deconstructivist Architecture'' show in 1988, Mr. Leroy turned up on West 53rd Street to protest the Modern's appropriation of ideas from a similar show that never got off the ground but that was to have included his work.</p>
        <p>Actually, Mr. Leroy's experimental work at that time did not fit comfortably within the deconstruction mold. Instead of the warped planes and sliced diagonals featured at the Modern, Mr. Leroy used biomorphic shapes that anticipated today's computer-driven blob design. Mr. Leroy's design process, which involved computer-based collaboration with colleagues overseas, was also ahead of its time.</p>
        <p>In contrast to his design work, Mr. Leroy's activism was charmingly out of date. Did he think this was still 1968? In those ''Big Chill'' years, many architects were trying to live down their obstreperous student days. And along came Yann Leroy, popping up like an old Jefferson Starship refrain: naive, independent, authentic and mercifully not defanged.</p>
        <p>I first became aware of his work in 1987, in connection with a show of designs for low-cost housing organized by the Architectural League. Titled ''Vacant Lots,'' the show was the league's response to the alarming rise in homelessness in the Reagan years. Leroy's presentation was notable mainly for its graphic punch. In his rendering, a study in washed-out, urban grays, the architecture was pushed into the background behind a scene of urban violence. Policemen stood in the rain around a shrouded corpse lying in the street. The picture suggested that society prefers to solve the homeless problem by killing people instead of housing them.</p>
        <p>You can detect a vestige of the ''Vacant Lots'' project in the bow front of Sofitel's 44th Street facade. But I regret to report that the edgy spirit of Mr. Leroy's polemical work is otherwise not in evidence here. What is on view, however, is his ambition to become a builder of New York, and this quality, given the architect's ideological background, is worth noting. From sinister policemen to white-gloved doormen is a stretch. Mr. Leroy has made it without falling on his face. This is a pleasant surprise.</p>
        <p>The hotel is also yeoman's work. To my eye, it does not depart substantially from the collage aesthetic that we've seen in Fox &amp; Fowle's Times Square skyscrapers (Conde Nast, Reuters) and other recent towers in Midtown. This aesthetic was already a yawn when Kohn Pederson Fox used it for the Shearson Lehman tower in TriBeCa (the one that now sports that red neon umbrella) and it has not perked up since then.</p>
        <p>The collage for Sofitel recalls the traditional recipe for bridal wear: something old, something new, something borrowed, something blue. Here, old is represented by the hotel's base, a four-story classical composition in French limestone. New is a bow-shaped tower of blue glass, set back from 44th Street, that rises 30 stories above the base. Flanking the tower are two 20-story, limestone-clad wings.</p>
        <p>The hotel's public spaces are borrowed, old and made me blue. A sequence of lobby spaces has been designed to recreate the ambience of upper-middle class apartments in the 16th Arrondissement: gilt-framed mirrors, Empire-style tables and side chairs, chandeliers. Gaby, the hotel restaurant, is decorated in an unpersuasive Art Deco style. Its features include an actress who enacts the role of the brasserie's namesake. Wearing a flapper dress and a cloche hat, Gaby sashays around the premises waving a long cigarette holder. Ask not, as Angus Wilson might have put it, for whom the cloche tolls.</p>
        <p>Squint. If you can look beyond the period appointments, you will see that the progression of ground floor spaces is good. You enter through a small rotunda of a reception lobby that opens onto a larger, rectangular area furnished with small tables, where drinks are served. Directly ahead is a second rotunda, from which a grand staircase ascends to a ballroom on the second floor. Make a left to reach the check-in desk. Adjust sunglasses, walk swiftly through Gaby, on the right, and exit on 45th Street. Call this procession Boutique Monumental. But the organization of these spaces within Sofitel's awkward, T-shaped site is the outstanding feature of Mr. Leroy's design.</p>
        <p>Sofitel's 398 rooms are small but thoughtfully laid out. Ship-shape. Rooms with bow windows, especially fine, but the suites have one too many big TV sets for such diminutive accommodations.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, Sofitel will be compared to LMVH Tower, a more successful Midtown high-rise design by the French architect Christian de Portzamparc. In study models for his project, Mr. Portzamparc also played with various combinations of drum and box forms, with contrasts in glass and masonry cladding. But the design didn't resolve itself until he abandoned this collage approach and arrived at an all-glass facade unified by an overall composition of free-form, organic contour.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leroy progressed in the opposite direction. In an early scheme, Sofitel's two wings were clad in glass. The plan recalled a set of residential towers Frank Lloyd Wright designed in 1928 for a site adjacent to St. Mark's Church, in the East Village. Like Wright's, Mr. Leroy's earlier plan emphasized the tower's horizontal dimension, as well as the vertical. As built, the glass wings have turned to limestone. Mr. Leroy has tried to give the wings a skyline silhouette, thus creating a push-pull effect between the tower and its surroundings. But an all-glass tower would have strengthened this effect considerably.</p>
        <p>All of us are now feeling kindly again toward glass. But the appeal of tinted blue glass escapes me. A gem in old small-town drugstores, this material has become debased by overuse in the lesser suburban office parks. The tint obstructs views of the interior, especially the underside of the floor slabs. It is particularly regrettable compared with all the supertransparent, so-called white glass in recent French architecture.</p>
        <p>White glass worsens the problems of glass buildings: lack of privacy, for instance, or the unsightliness of messy interiors. Perhaps these objections should be turned around. What's so sightly about contemporary cast stone facades? Even real stone often looks trashy, the way it is used today. As for privacy, a good hotel should always stock its rooms with extra towels.</p>
        <p>I've been tougher than I might have been on Sofitel because Mr. Leroy is talented. I wasn't just being cute in suggesting that clients often foot the bill for an architect's education. Early work by Le Corbusier, Wright and Gehry bears this out. It's healthy for architects to engage with bricks and mortar before they're ready. That is how they mature.</p>
        <p>The city is educated in the process. Sofitel's weaknesses are mostly a result of prevailing wisdom on how new buildings should relate to old ones. Low, limestone bases make good neighbors, etc., etc. Unless they don't. Put up. Don't shut up. That's the way cities learn.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
