<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Fires Disrupt Subway Lines In Manhattan And Brooklyn</title>
    <meta content="03SUBW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5D8163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Fires Disrupt Subway Lines In Manhattan And Brooklyn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two underground electrical fires in downtown Brooklyn send thick, black smoke billowing out of manholes and subway entrances and force closing of four of city's busiest subway lines just as evening commute is beginning; tens of thousands of subway riders in Manhattan and Brooklyn are stranded; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two underground electrical fires in downtown Brooklyn sent thick, black smoke billowing out of manholes and subway entrances and forced the closing of four of the city's busiest subway lines yesterday just as the evening commute was beginning, stranding tens of thousands of riders in Manhattan and Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>As subway fires go, the ones that began just before 4:30 p.m. were relatively minor. No one was injured, and transit officials said that all the trains in the area, including three that were traveling beneath the East River, managed to reach stations and discharge their passengers before smoke filled the tunnels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two underground electrical fires in downtown Brooklyn sent thick, black smoke billowing out of manholes and subway entrances and forced the closing of four of the city's busiest subway lines yesterday just as the evening commute was beginning, stranding tens of thousands of riders in Manhattan and Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>As subway fires go, the ones that began just before 4:30 p.m. were relatively minor. No one was injured, and transit officials said that all the trains in the area, including three that were traveling beneath the East River, managed to reach stations and discharge their passengers before smoke filled the tunnels.</p>
        <p>But the blazes, which firefighters battled for more than two hours, forced the Transit Authority to cut power at 4:45 p.m. to miles of subway tracks on the 2, 3, 4 and 5 lines in Lower Manhattan and central Brooklyn. The shutdown closed up to 20 stations until almost 8 p.m. and left herds of baffled commuters bouncing from line to line in Brooklyn and Lower Manhattan, trying to cobble together some way to get home.</p>
        <p>By 6 p.m., parts of downtown Brooklyn looked like the scene of an attack, with smoke pouring from subway grates and manholes and streaming up around Borough Hall from the mouths of subway exits. Traffic was also tied up for miles as dozens of fire trucks streamed into the area and several blocks around the Fulton Mall area were cordoned off.</p>
        <p>Mike Wallace, an accountant, said he left New York University in Greenwich Village at 4 p.m. for a commute to East Flatbush that usually takes him 45 minutes. He took the 6 train to the Brooklyn Bridge stop, where he could not get on the 4, so he took the M to Court Street in Brooklyn and then the N to Pacific Street and got out to try to find a B45 bus.</p>
        <p>''I've been walking ever since,'' he said. ''Can't get that. Can't get nothing.'' He added, more than three hours into his commute: ''I just want to get home.''</p>
        <p>Bob Slovak, a New York City Transit spokesman, said that one fire started when a 600-volt power cable beneath the street near the intersection of Jay and Fulton Streets, near New York City Transit's office building, began to burn, for reasons that were unclear yesterday.</p>
        <p>The fire apparently destroyed some fiber optic cable and other communications lines used by the transit workers to communicate between token booths and between stations.</p>
        <p>The city's director of emergency management, Richard J. Sheirer, told reporters at the scene of the first fire that another fire started near the same location around the same time in a manhole that contained Con Edison cables. It was not known last night whether the fires were related.</p>
        <p>People who worked in the area reported hearing three loud explosions, about a minute apart. And the owner of a women's dress store in the Fulton Mall area said that an electrical fire started in the store above a window display around the time of the explosions.</p>
        <p>Token booth clerks in nearby subway stations said that they knew something was wrong and fled from the stations when the emergency telephones in their booths began to smoke.</p>
        <p>Mr. Slovak said that after the Fire Department ordered the electricity to be turned off, the Transit Authority managed to keep some power on long enough so that the operator of one train that was in a tunnel beneath the river could change cabs -- walking from one end of the train to the other -- and take the train back to the Bowling Green station.</p>
        <p>Two other trains were approaching the Borough Hall station. One train was able to pull into the station and the other one pulled up right behind it so that the passengers in the second train could file into the first train and out onto the platform, without having to descend to the tracks.</p>
        <p>In Manhattan, as far away as 59th Street, transit workers were trying to divert passengers from Brooklyn-bound trains so that stations to the south would not fill up with passengers who could go no further.</p>
        <p>''It's got to be the worst place they could possibly have a fire,'' said a transit supervisor, Patrick Tamborino, as he stood outside the subway station at Borough Hall in Brooklyn, directing weary, angry, overheated commuters.</p>
        <p>Nearby, another transit worker called out to the crowds: ''Take your buses! It's your best way home. Or walk. It's a very nice day.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
