<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News of Arrest Renews Survivors' Pain</title>
    <meta content="03NABE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watkins, Amy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rodriguez, Felix</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jamison, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4DA163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News of Arrest Renews Survivors' Pain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Family and friends of Amy Watkins comment on arrest of David Jamison and Felix Rodriguez in connection with her murder-robbery in March 1999 in Prospect Park section of Brooklyn; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawrence Watkins went through more than a year of tears, condolences, sleepless nights, speeches and letter-writing before his memory began the merciful act of burying his daughter's murder.</p>
        <p>Then yesterday afternoon, a single telephone call unraveled all that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawrence Watkins went through more than a year of tears, condolences, sleepless nights, speeches and letter-writing before his memory began the merciful act of burying his daughter's murder.</p>
        <p>Then yesterday afternoon, a single telephone call unraveled all that.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins stood in silence in his living room as a police officer relayed the news: one man had been arrested in the fatal stabbing of his daughter, Amy Watkins, and two others were being questioned. (Later, one of the other men was also charged.) Mr. Watkins's daughter, a 26-year-old social worker, was robbed and killed on March 9, 1999, in Prospect Heights, Brooklyn, and the police had been looking for the killer since.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watkins, a history teacher at the Dominican Academy on East 68th Street in Manhattan, shared the news with his wife, Gayle, who was standing next to him in their Upper East Side apartment. She left for an appointment. He paced quietly through the rooms. Then he began crying.</p>
        <p>''It was as if it had all happened again,'' Mr. Watkins said hours later. ''What I'm feeling right now is that old wounds are being re-opened.''</p>
        <p>The news that the police had detained several suspects in Ms. Watkins's killing came as a shock to the young woman's family and friends. For some, like Mr. Watkins, it reopened emotional wounds that had been slowly healing for 16 months. Others said they were relieved. On a fundamental level, it raised questions of retribution and human nature.</p>
        <p>''I don't know whether I'll be looking at someone who's pathetic or someone who's malevolent,'' Mr. Watkins said. ''On a certain level, I denied that any human being could be so morally depraved to do something like this.''</p>
        <p>Adam Green, Ms. Watkins's boyfriend, was working at New Settlement Apartments in the Bronx when he heard about the arrest. Ms. Watkins had also worked at the community center, counseling battered women and children. Mr. Green said he walked past a mural on the street that Ms. Watkins had been working on and ''cursed at the world.''</p>
        <p>''I'd already created my own closure, which had to do with not needing a name and a face,'' he said. ''I am hoping this doesn't open up a healed wound. I've done my work already.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Green said the death penalty would be the ''easy way out,'' and that the people responsible should be imprisoned instead.</p>
        <p>For many of Ms. Watkins's friends and family, getting past the killing meant creating memorials to honor her. A mural depicting women at work and at play was painted on the side of a supermarket in the South Bronx. An art student at Hunter College designed a large abstract painting for the student lounge of the School of Social Work, where Ms. Watkins was doing graduate work. Both the painting and a plaque ensured that the young woman's name was remembered in the school.</p>
        <p>In his ninth-floor office, Michael Fabricant, one of Ms. Watkins's professors, leaned back in his chair and mulled over the news of the first arrest. ''Not being able to attach a face and person and story to a crime, a whole lot has gone unsaid,'' he said. ''Hopefully, this will answer some of that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fabricant worked with students at Hunter, as well as Ms. Watkins's family, to raise $50,000 for a permanent scholarship fund in her name. Mr. Watkins said that a committee planned to award the first scholarship in a month, to someone who has been engaged in community organizing. Donors to the fund include residents of Prospect Heights, as well as the artist Yoko Ono, who gave $10,000 after Mr. Watkins wrote her, he said.</p>
        <p>''That's been very helpful to the students and to the school,'' said Bogart Leashore, dean of the School of Social Work. ''But hearing about what happened today, and assuming they might have sufficient evidence, it certainly might help to bring closure.''</p>
        <p>But for Mr. Watkins, that closure came this March, right after the anniversary of his daughter's death. He attended a ceremony at Hunter College where professors and students praised Ms. Watkins's deeds. A reception was held afterward to raise money for the scholarship fund. Mr. Watkins's eyes brimmed with tears, but within weeks his memory began sealing the wounds.</p>
        <p>''The experience is you go back to normal life, and at certain moments you become aware that she's gone,'' he said. ''Then it happens a little less frequently, then a little less frequently, and then you get to a point where you can go whole days or weeks without breaking down.''</p>
        <p>But yesterday afternoon, Mr. Watkins stared down at the message light blinking relentlessly on his answering machine.</p>
        <p>''I think,'' he said, ''we'll have feelings of reawakened grief.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
