<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Jobs in Construction Sought for Minority Workers</title>
    <meta content="03TRAD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tishman Realty &amp; Construction Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koh, Eun Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DB163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Jobs in Construction Sought for Minority Workers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EUN LEE KOH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Koh, Eun Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City's building trade unions strike unusual agreement with private developer Tishman Construction Corp to give at least 10 percent of new construction apprenticeships to graduates of city's vocational high schools (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City's building trade unions have struck an unusual agreement with a private developer to give at least 10 percent of new construction apprenticeships to graduates of the city's vocational high schools, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The program should mean more job opportunities for minority workers in an industry where apprenticeships have traditionally been handed down from father to son and trade union membership is predominantly made up of white men. Blacks and Hispanics represent about 80 percent of the 25,000 students now enrolled in the city's 20 vocational schools, said Edward J. Malloy, president of the Building and Construction Trades Council, one of the participants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City's building trade unions have struck an unusual agreement with a private developer to give at least 10 percent of new construction apprenticeships to graduates of the city's vocational high schools, officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The program should mean more job opportunities for minority workers in an industry where apprenticeships have traditionally been handed down from father to son and trade union membership is predominantly made up of white men. Blacks and Hispanics represent about 80 percent of the 25,000 students now enrolled in the city's 20 vocational schools, said Edward J. Malloy, president of the Building and Construction Trades Council, one of the participants.</p>
        <p>The plan guarantees at least 600 new apprenticeships for the graduates this year, when enrollment in vocational schools is dwindling and the construction industry is facing a shortage of skilled workers during a building boom.</p>
        <p>''There isn't a program like this that exists anywhere else in the country,'' said Louis J. Coletti, chairman of the Building Trades Employers' Association, a group that represents 1,100 construction companies and 22 trade organizations. ''It will provide tremendous opportunities for young people, recent high school graduates, looking for careers in the construction industry.''</p>
        <p>The deal was reached with the Tishman Construction Corporation, one of the city's largest developers.  Mr. Coletti said the unions were now in talks with other developers about the plan, which could ultimately place 1,000 graduates into continuing construction projects over the next year and beyond.</p>
        <p>Building unions have already begun referring the graduates to apprenticeships at three major Tishman-affiliated projects taking shape in and around Times Square: the new Reuters headquarters on Broadway between 42nd and 43rd Streets, the Westin Hotel at 42nd Street and Eighth Avenue, and the Morgan Stanley Dean Witter building at 49th Street and Seventh Avenue.</p>
        <p>Richard Kielar, senior vice president of the Tishman corporation, said the increasing number of minority workers on the company's building projects was already evident from the preliminary referrals made through the program.</p>
        <p>He said, for example, that about 3 to 8 percent of all the construction workers on the Reuters project were members of minorities, while 30 percent of the workers from apprenticeship programs on the project were from minority groups.</p>
        <p>An apprenticeship is an entry-level position; in the construction industry, apprentices train for one to three years or more in their areas of expertise, like plumbing, steel work, electrical work or carpentry, before moving up to full-fledged jobs that union officials say start at about $39,000 a year.</p>
        <p>The new program, Construction Skills 2000, is an expansion of a pilot program that was run by the construction industry groups from 1993 to 1997 for graduates of 10 vocational schools in the city.</p>
        <p>About 85 percent of the more than 1,000 participants in the pilot program were black or Hispanic, and as a result, the total minority participation in apprenticeships in the city rose to 51 percent from 33 percent during the pilot program, Mr. Coletti said. It is not known how many apprentices stayed in construction.</p>
        <p>For industry officials, the program is one way to reinvigorate the sagging interest in construction industry jobs and begin to replace the aging crop of current construction workers, said Mr. Malloy, the president of the Building and Construction Trades Council.</p>
        <p>The program will send representatives of the various trades into vocational schools to recruit junior and senior students.</p>
        <p>''Part of it is to assure young people that it's O.K. if you choose not to go to college,'' Mr. Malloy said. ''Not everyone can afford it, and not everyone can go. But here's a great career that you can go into and be able to make a good living.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
