<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Harris Files Suit Against AOL Over Blocking of E-Mail</title>
    <meta content="Y03SPAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">America Online Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Harris Interactive Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Laurie J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E3DF163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Harris Files Suit Against AOL Over Blocking of E-Mail</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURIE J. FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Laurie J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harris Interactive Inc, nation's largest online market research company, sues America Online and other e-mail service providers charging them with unlawfully blocking e-mail from Harris to its survey participants; service providers subscribe to blocking service in effort to curb unwanted unsolicited mass e-mail, also known as spam; Harris insists it does not send unsolicited e-mail and that all its participants register to take part in surveys (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Harris Interactive Inc., the nation's largest online market research company, has filed a lawsuit against America Online and other e-mail service providers contending that those companies unlawfully blocked e-mail from Harris to its survey participants.</p>
        <p>Harris says the service providers all subscribe to the Realtime Blackhole List, an e-mail blocking service maintained by Mail Abuse Prevention System, or MAPS, a not-for-profit company that tracks e-mail abuse. The service providers subscribe to the Realtime Blackhole List in an effort to curb unwanted unsolicited mass e-mail, also known as spam. MAPS, of Redwood City, Calif., is also named as a defendant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Harris Interactive Inc., the nation's largest online market research company, has filed a lawsuit against America Online and other e-mail service providers contending that those companies unlawfully blocked e-mail from Harris to its survey participants.</p>
        <p>Harris says the service providers all subscribe to the Realtime Blackhole List, an e-mail blocking service maintained by Mail Abuse Prevention System, or MAPS, a not-for-profit company that tracks e-mail abuse. The service providers subscribe to the Realtime Blackhole List in an effort to curb unwanted unsolicited mass e-mail, also known as spam. MAPS, of Redwood City, Calif., is also named as a defendant.</p>
        <p>Harris officials insist that the company does not send unsolicited e-mail, and that all its participants register to take part in its surveys. All survey participants, they said, have several chances to opt out.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit, filed on Monday in United States District Court for the Western District of New York, seeks an injunction removing the block on its e-mail, and unspecified monetary damages. The suit names more than a dozen companies, including the Hotmail operation of Microsoft, BellSouth, Juno Online Services and Qwest Communications. A hearing for a temporary restraining order is scheduled for this afternoon.</p>
        <p>In a statement released yesterday, MAPS officials said they were surprised by the lawsuit.</p>
        <p>''We believe we have every right to keep a list of people we choose not to accept mail from,'' said Kelly Thompson, a spokeswoman for MAPS, which was founded three years ago.</p>
        <p>Ms. Thompson said that MAPS did not itself block e-mail, but rather kept a list that e-mail sservice providers and other companies could use to decide whom they should block. She confirmed that Harris Interactive was on the Realtime Blackhole List, which includes 3,000 names, because the company does not employ a purely ''opt-in'' approach. Harris counters that it gives users several direct and easy opportunities to remove themselves from Harris' participant list.</p>
        <p>The suit is not the first complaint filed against MAPS. Last month, Yesmail.com, an e-mail marketing company, sued MAPS for being included on the Blackhole List, but that suit was put aside after both sides agreed to work together to clarify their approach to mass e-mail.</p>
        <p>America Online, however, insists it does not use the Realtime Blackhole List as part of its anti-spam activities, and said that there was no basis for Harris Interactive to have named AOL in its lawsuit.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, said Rich D'Amato, a spokesman for AOL, ''We are confident our spam-fighting techniques are entirely appropriate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato said ''it was possible'' that AOL was blocking e-mail from Harris, but added that AOL would take such action only if Harris violated AOL's spam-fighting standards, not those of MAPS.</p>
        <p>Gordon S. Black, chairman and chief executive of Harris Interactive, said Harris had no other options but to file a complaint, calling the MAPS actions ''completely arbitrary and capricious.'' MAPS, he said, has no right to ''unilaterally decide'' on appropriate anti-spam standards for the industry. ''The whole thing is absurd, but costly absurd,'' he said. ''We sued in part because we're as offended by the process as we are by the action.''</p>
        <p>The e-mail blocking comes at a particularly bad time for Harris, which is preparing for two major election-related projects in September, including creating a survey site for the Commission on Presidential Debates. ''This will make it difficult to do our Election 2000 Project,'' Mr. Black said, referring to a huge online survey of voter preferences.</p>
        <p>Harris's suit also includes an antitrust complaint against AOL, given that its own online market-research company, Digital Marketing Systems, is a direct competitor to Harris.</p>
        <p>Harris Interactive, based in Rochester, conducts more than 1.5 million surveys every quarter. Of Harris Interactive's 6.6 million registered participants, roughly 2.7 million are affected by the block, Mr. Black said.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
