<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Web Surfing, at the Sound of Your Own Voice</title>
    <meta content="03JPVO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DA1F3DF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Web Surfing, at the Sound of Your Own Voice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE GREENMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS manufacturers of wireless phones, handheld computers and other Internet gadgets scramble to make Web information accessible without the need to boot up a computer, some companies have a different plan. They are adapting the Web to the one device that virtually everyone has: the telephone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS manufacturers of wireless phones, handheld computers and other Internet gadgets scramble to make Web information accessible without the need to boot up a computer, some companies have a different plan. They are adapting the Web to the one device that virtually everyone has: the telephone.</p>
        <p>And they don't mean one of those Web phones that connect you to e-mail and stock quotations after you set up a special wireless-service account and scroll through a series of menus and buttons. All you need is a telephone, even an old-fashioned rotary dial phone. These voice portals - like Tellme, BeVocal and Quack.com - invite you to pick up a phone and let your voice do the surfing. Actually, it's mroe like wading, but you can reach some parts of the Web.</p>
        <p>''The broad view is that we'll eventually offer everything you can get on the Web over the phone,'' said Alex Quilici, chief executive of Quack.com, which began offering its services in April and currently provides, among other things, weather, traffic, movie and restaurant information for most areas of the country. ''You'll see it moving to e-commerce, e-mail and instant messaging.'' Mr. Quilici said the company had reached an agreement with Lycos, a popular search engine, to begin providing voice-activated features to many of its e-commerce partner sites.</p>
        <p>The voice portal is part of the thickening haze blurring the distinctions among computers, cell phones, handheld organizers and the various hybrids on the market. But just as wireless. Web devices can retrieve only limited information from the Web, the voice portals in most cases have limited their phone menus so information can be found easily, either directly from the Web or from a server-like program.</p>
        <p>Most voice portals use speech recognition technology and a computer language that digitizes the spoken word and searches Internet servers based on the commands. In most cases, these services are organized much like basic Internet portals.</p>
        <p>Dial Tellme, for example, and a female voice asks you to select a category like weather, stock quotations, sports, traffic, horoscopes and airlines. Callers can select nearby restaurants according to their Tellme ratings (Tellme automatically determines where the call is coming from) and connect directly to the restaurants. Catchy tunes and R2D2-like computing noises play in the background while the information is fetched. (At Quack.com, a sound like the flip-flop of duck feet - more subtle than an outright quack - fades in and out.) The information retrieved is read to the caller by a recorded or digitized voice.</p>
        <p>Many of the voice portals let users customize their calling menus. A Tellme user, for example, can enter stock ticker symbols onto a list, which is stored on the Tellme site.</p>
        <p>When the user dials the toll-free Tellme number and says, ''Stock quotes,'' the service will read the current price quotations for the stocks on the list.</p>
        <p>The information that goes back to the caller is not limited by the constraints of the small screen found on wireless phones with Web access, say those involved in the voice portal market.</p>
        <p>''The possibilities are far-reaching,'' said Adam Greenhalgh, president of Speaklink, a voice portal that will start operating later this summer. ''A voice portal is the same as an Internet portal, but you have the functionality of talking to it. Speech connectivity is the next evolution of the Internet.''</p>
        <p>Voice portal companies are aiming at computer users who need information but who are away from their computers, and they are also going after the ever-increasing market of cell-phone users. All voice portal services are accessible via cell phones.</p>
        <p>The Kelsey Group, a market research firm in Princeton, N.J., predicts that the  voice portal market will generate $12 billion by 2005 through advertising revenue, e-commerce transactions and related hardware and telephone-service-carrier costs.</p>
        <p>But while analysts agree that advanced speech recognition capabilities and Web development tools are bridging the gap between the phone and the Internet, many wonder about how many people will use these services.</p>
        <p>''Voice will never be the dominant interface because it's so information-poor,'' said John Dalton, an analyst at Forrester Research in Cambridge, Mass. ''When you compare a stand-alone voice interface, you're limited to the amount of information you can distribute. People have a lot more choices, and they can retain a lot more when they're looking at information on a PC.''</p>
        <p>The phone services will not work as effectively as the Internet for research or making buying decisions, Mr. Dalton said, because the average consumer does not remember more than a few bits of audio information at a time and needs to be able to see and compare items before buying.</p>
        <p>Voice portals are competing with some audio services that already have brand recognition.</p>
        <p>Analysts say the voice portals may find it hard to win over people who would otherwise call MovieFone for movie listings or consult another trusted source for restaurant reviews. What is more, the voice portals cannot provide everything that a service like MovieFone can. You cannot buy movie tickets at a voice portal, for example. You can only hear what's playing, where and at what times.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quilici, at Quack.com, said he considered the service to be more of an extension of the Web and other information sources, but one that was easily accessible from  anywhere.</p>
        <p>''Rather than staying late at work figuring out movie and dinner plans, you'll be able to do it on the way home from your phone,'' he said. Mr. Quilici added that Quack.com planned to forge agreements with wireless manufacturers that would allow a consumer to call the service with a request and have any lengthy information sent as a text message to a wireless phone, instead of hearing it recited back.</p>
        <p>One Tellme user, Louise Valente of Palo Alto, Calif., said the service was useful. ''I find that it's handy and frees up my time by not having to go and power up my computer to access information,'' she said. ''I don't know that it's absolutely necessary, but it's a convenience.''</p>
        <p>Most of the voice portals expect to earn money down the road by setting up partnerships with shopping sites and by charging commissions on e-commerce transactions.</p>
        <p>Currently, the phone services are supported by advertising. Each time an option is selected at Tellme or Quack.com, whether it is a request for movie listings or restaurants, callers hear a ''brought to you by'' message reminiscent of early radio shows.  While the service is looking up a request, callers might hear another 10- or 15-second message from a sponsor.</p>
        <p>''You can ignore banner ads on the Web, but you can't ignore the voice,'' said Mr. Greenhalgh, at Speaklink. ''We don't want to frustrate the users.''</p>
        <p>Some voice portals like Tellme and HeyAnita, which plans to start operating in the fall, are focusing on communications services.</p>
        <p>In its Phone Booth section, for example, Tellme offers new users a free, two-minute long-distance call. Before the call is put through, the user will hear a 10- or 15-second advertisement. Yellow and White Pages listings will also be free.</p>
        <p>''The whole telecommunications industry is in the process of changing, and it gives us a great set of opportunities to go after,'' said Mike McCue, chief executive of Tellme. He also said Tellme had received financing  from AT&amp;T and would work on the AT&amp;T network to let callers connect directly to any service they selected while on Tellme.</p>
        <p>Sanjeev Kuwadekar, chief executive of HeyAnita, said the company was partnering with several large Internet service providers to allow consumers with e-mail accounts at the I.S.P.'s to send and receive e-mail with voice commands.</p>
        <p>HeyAnita also has a page on its Web site that lets users store contact information for people they call regularly. When such a user calls the service, says a personal identification number and speaks an individual's name, HeyAnita will read back the phone number or e-mail address. The same can be done with to-do lists and calendar information entered on the HeyAnita site.</p>
        <p>Others, like BeVocal, which opened in June, are focusing on information geared to mobile callers, like driving directions and traffic reports. Through a partnership with Mapquest.com, BeVocal provides callers with driving directions within major metropolitan areas. That part of the service is available only in California, Texas and Michigan at present, but the company says the coverage will be nationwide by September.</p>
        <p>Amol Joshi, founder and vice president of marketing at BeVocal, said the company planned partnerships with wireless phone carriers to provide them with voice-activated dialers and a direct voice link to BeVocal. Wireless phone customers would be able to select that as an optional feature of their monthly calling plans. In addition, BeVocal's strategy is to share commissions with wireless carriers for any business transactions, like hotel reservations or airline ticket purchases, that take place during a call. Commissions would be paid by the business,  not the consumer, he said.</p>
        <p>Voice portals are also working with Web designers to broaden the content the portals can provide. Tellme, for example, is licensing its technology to Web site developers and allowing them to make their sites accessible to Tellme's voice service. ''We'll get to the point where anybody can build a customized phone application,'' Mr. McCue said.</p>
        <p>A completely different approach to Web access via telephone is simply to call other people who will surf and search for you. A company called iNetNow employs actual human beings to retrieve Web information for the people who call the service. The service is free for a promotion period that ends in the fall. After that, iNetNow will offer monthly plans of $4.95 for five calls and $21.95 for unlimited use.</p>
        <p>The company provides service around the clock; it has 50 operators who work eight-hour shifts. Complicated questions are handled by a research department that culls data and links from the Web and puts them into information packets that can be sent to the callers via e-mail or faxes.</p>
        <p>''The voice portal companies are all kind of jockeying to figure out what people want most and deliver that,'' said Lenny Young, president of iNetNow. ''We're trying to be much broader. It requires more people, but we think it's the most satisfying way to get the information.'' Mr. Young said the company planned to add voice recognition features in the future to cut down on overhead  costs.</p>
        <p>Harry Kelso, an environmental consultant in Richmond, Va., used iNetNow to look up articles about the military's role in the westward expansion of the United States, and he was impressed by the results. ''I thought this was a pretty big request to ask of anyone,'' he said, ''but they came back with things I wouldn't have dreamt would be around. If it means that you can speed up finding facts, then that goes a really long way toward helping.''</p>
        <p>Site-Seeing: Voice Portals  The voice portals below are functioning or available in trial versions.</p>
        <p>SPEAKLINK: www.speaklink.com  (877) SPEAKLINK, or (877) 773-2554.  TELLME: www.tellme.com  (800) 555-TELL, or (800) 555-8355.  BEVOCAL: www.bevocal.com  (800) 4BVOCAL, or (800) 428-6225.  HEYANITA: www.heyanita.com  (800) 44-ANITA, or (800) 442-6482.  QUACK: www.quack.com  (800) 73-QUACK, or (800) 737-8225.  INETNOW: www.inetnow.com  (888) INETNOW, or (888) 463-8669.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
