<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Clock Is Ticking for the Class of 1998</title>
    <meta content="03JETS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219742"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E6DA163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Clock Is Ticking for the Class of 1998</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes scene at New York Jets training camp; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Groh has a calendar. And if you read it carefully, you know the significance of the Jets' preseason game at Lambeau Field in Green Bay on Friday night for at least two of his players.</p>
        <p>Dorian Boose, a defensive end, and Scott Frost, a free safety, were the first two players chosen by the Jets in the 1998 draft. Each is at a critical point in his career, for Groh believes what Tom Landry once told Bill Parcells: ''If they don't make it by their third year, get rid of them.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Groh has a calendar. And if you read it carefully, you know the significance of the Jets' preseason game at Lambeau Field in Green Bay on Friday night for at least two of his players.</p>
        <p>Dorian Boose, a defensive end, and Scott Frost, a free safety, were the first two players chosen by the Jets in the 1998 draft. Each is at a critical point in his career, for Groh believes what Tom Landry once told Bill Parcells: ''If they don't make it by their third year, get rid of them.''</p>
        <p>Thus, during the off-season, Groh and Frost had a talk, Frost recalled today. ''He basically told me it was a fresh start, and to come in to camp and ask myself, 'Why not me?' '' Frost said. ''I ask myself that every day.''</p>
        <p>Frost will not start against the Packers. That honor goes to Kevin Williams. But Frost will start eight days later at Baltimore. Groh has been giving Williams, Frost and Omar Stoutmire equal opportunity; each performs for eight plays, and then sits out so the other two can get in eight plays. The point is, Groh does not know who his free safety will be. And that is good for Frost.</p>
        <p>For Frost, this is the best -- and perhaps only -- chance he has had at being a starter in the pros. He was quarterback of Nebraska when it was national co-champion. That was in 1997. But he was 6 feet 3 inches and weighed 215 pounds, so Bill Parcells saw him as a dominating free safety, drafting him in the third round.</p>
        <p>The Jets, who were without a first-round pick in 1998, chose Boose of Washington State as a future pass-rusher with their opening pick, in the second round.</p>
        <p>Each can show off Friday night against a dangerous Packers offense overseen by quarterback Brett Favre.</p>
        <p>''I looked at this coaching staff as a fresh start,'' said Boose, who felt that the former defensive coordinator, Bill Belichick, was often surly and used putdowns to motivate him instead of constructive criticism.</p>
        <p>''When I came in as the first pick, there was the burden, pressure to do well,'' he said. He never truly did.</p>
        <p>''I felt they were kind of giving up on me,'' he admitted. ''It can downplay your maturation, your self-worth.''</p>
        <p>Then the Jets used their first selection in the first round this spring to pick a pass-rusher, Shaun Ellis, and followed that up with another quarterback chaser, linebacker John Abraham.</p>
        <p>''I took that as a challenge,'' said Boose, who will start at right end on Friday night.</p>
        <p>Ellis appears to be moving up on the depth chart, and he lined up today as the No. 2 left end.</p>
        <p>Frost declined to comment on his relationship with Belichick. But he did say of this training camp, ''It's the first time I feel I've had a shot.''</p>
        <p>In the Jets' preseason opener last Saturday against the Saints, Frost made a game-saving interception on the goal line with 10 seconds remaining. In limited play, he also produced a pair of tackles.</p>
        <p>Frost says he does not think of being a quarterback any more. He said that ''hasn't crossed my mind since I've been here.''</p>
        <p>Frost objected to Landry's belief in cutting players who have not developed by their third year. ''I don't like being lumped in there like that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Frost has been working hard. He worked to strengthen his upper body during the off-season, did agility drills to improve his footwork and paid attention to detail in the film room. He has become an equal among free safeties, at least for now.</p>
        <p>''To make it would be a dream come true,'' he said. ''I want to be a football player.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>If you get thirsty listening to the Jets' radio broadcast, you will not hear an ad for beer, at least not until the team moves to its new home on WABC. The Jets' interim radio station, WQEW, is part of the Disney Network, and Disney does not allow beer advertising on its stations. The Jets last year were on WFAN, which does air beer ads. The team will move to WABC when the Yankees' season is over. . . . Coach AL GROH scrutinized the special teams during the afternoon workout, especially looking at kick returns. He scolded punter ANDY RUSS: ''Throw the damn thing if you can't kick!'' . . . Three mothers showed up for practice: those of quarterback CHAD PENNINGTON, center DENNIS O'SULLIVAN and running back VAUGHN SANDERS. . . . Three Jets did not practice because of injuries: defensive linemen ANTHONY COOK and RICHARD SEALS and cornerback BUDDY CRUTCHFIELD.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
