<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Watch Your Back, Harry Potter; A Wizardly Comuter Game, Diablo II, Is a Hot Seller</title>
    <meta content="Y03DIA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/03/business/03DIAB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blizzard Entertainment</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowling, J K</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Harry Potter (Book Series)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2DF163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Watch Your Back, Harry Potter; A Wizardly Comuter Game, Diablo II, Is a Hot Seller</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>IRVINE, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Diablo II, Dungeons and Dragons-like computer game for older teenagers and adults from Blizzard Entertainment, sells more than million copies worldwide and is within striking distance of popular Harry Potter books in terms of revenue; is on track to be one of top selling computer games but has won little attention in media; unlike Potter books, which have won praise for drawing videogame-crazed and television-besotted children back to reading, Diablo II has drawn condemnation for ensnaring players in morbid world view and gluing them antisocially to computer screen; photos; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It came out just recently, a highly anticipated sequel to a best seller filled with stories of wizards and sorcerers. Revenue has topped $50 million so far, reviews have been good, and fans, who waited impatiently for their new heroes to arrive, are thrilled.</p>
        <p>''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire,'' right?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It came out just recently, a highly anticipated sequel to a best seller filled with stories of wizards and sorcerers. Revenue has topped $50 million so far, reviews have been good, and fans, who waited impatiently for their new heroes to arrive, are thrilled.</p>
        <p>''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire,'' right?</p>
        <p>Right -- and wrong.</p>
        <p>The fourth installment of the Harry Potter series is not the only fantasy-filled hit this summer. On July 3, five days before Harry Potter arrived in stores, Blizzard Entertainment, which is based here, released Diablo II, a Dungeons and Dragons-like computer game in which players battle a demon to save the world.</p>
        <p>So far, even though Blizzard marketed Diablo II only to serious game players, it has sold more than a million copies worldwide, at an average retail price of more than $50. The 70,000 copies of the $70 collectors' edition, which was offered before the game was officially released, have sold out.</p>
        <p>In terms of revenue, that puts Diablo II within striking distance of the Potter book, which sold nearly three million copies in its first weekend in stores, according to Scholastic, its publisher, but those sales were often at deep discounts to the cover price of $25.95. Diablo II is on track to be one of the top-selling computer games.</p>
        <p>Yet Diablo II, which is intended for older teenagers and adults, has hardly registered on the media radar screen.</p>
        <p>And while Potter and his creator, J. K. Rowling, have won praise around the globe for drawing videogame-crazed and television-besotted young people back to reading, games like Diablo II draw condemnation for ensnaring players in a morbid worldview and gluing them antisocially to a computer screen.</p>
        <p>''A medal should be struck for Rowling,'' said the novelist Sidney Sheldon, the former national spokesperson for the Coalition for Literacy, in a typical observation. ''For this woman to come along and excite millions of children about reading today is a miracle.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheldon, whose sometimes steamy books have sold more than 300 million copies worldwide, said he believed that video games were ''getting so dark and so cruel; the object is to kill somebody, and I think that is dreadful.''</p>
        <p>Diablo II is rated ''mature'' by the Entertainment Software Rating Board, the equivalent of an R rating for a movie; few games receive more restrictive ratings. A rating of mature means Diablo II is supposed to be sold only to players who are 17 or older. But many children and younger teenagers play the game as well, according to Mike Morhaime, president of Blizzard, a subsidiary of Vivendi, the French company that is buying Seagram and its Universal Studios operation in Hollywood.</p>
        <p>Still, while the game is hardly nonviolent, it is ''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire,'' not Diablo II, that opens with the murder of a 76-year-old man. And it is Diablo II, not ''Harry Potter,'' that gives young people worldwide the opportunity to interact with each other in real time over the Internet, solving problems and battling monsters together.</p>
        <p>Indeed, many Diablo II players say they are also avid readers of science fiction and fantasy. And like Harry Potter, the characters in Diablo II are ultimately fighting evil.</p>
        <p>''Harry Potter'' and games like Diablo II may have more in common than many people realize, said Robert Coover, a Brown University English professor and experimental novelist who is among the leaders of efforts to find new ways to write on the Internet. ''I don't like the sense that book reading is good and computer game playing is not,'' Mr. Coover said.</p>
        <p>In Diablo II, players pick one of five character types and then try to complete increasingly difficult quests assigned to them by computer-controlled characters in the game. There are four worlds to conquer, and along the way, players must strengthen their characters, finding better weapons and armor and learning new skills they will need to battle ever more sinister creatures. In practice, players spend much of their time killing or dodging skeletons, zombies and other monsters, and many of the quests are themselves nothing more than hunting expeditions for evil creatures.</p>
        <p>But in contrast to ''first-person shooter'' games like Doom, in which players feel as if they are looking through the eyes of a character whose sole purpose is to kill as many other players and characters as possible, Diablo II is what video game experts call a third-person game. In these, players view their characters and the game's world from above, as if watching from a low-flying plane, and the violence is not particularly graphic.</p>
        <p>''Harry Potter'' and Diablo II ''are both fantasy -- it's an escape for people,'' said Bill Roper, a producer at Blizzard who helped lead the development of the game.</p>
        <p>Diablo takes at least 50 hours to solve, according to Mr. Morhaime, Blizzard's president. ''People take a lot of pride in their characters,'' he said. ''There's a big sense of accomplishment.''</p>
        <p>In e-mail interviews, several players of Diablo II echoed that view.</p>
        <p>''For me, the hook is character development, and in Diablo's case, hunting for items,'' wrote Caton Little, a 27-year-old player from New Zealand. ''The story's not too important, although hackneyed back-stories turn me right off.''</p>
        <p>As a measure of the seriousness with which some players treat their characters, Blizzard's manual offers a special warning to gamers who play Diablo in ''hard core'' mode, in which they cannot revive characters killed during the game. As a result, one mistake in hard-core mode can end weeks or months of effort.</p>
        <p>''Blizzard Entertainment is in no way responsible for your hard-core character,'' the manual tells players. ''Blizzard will not and does not have the capability to restore any deceased hard-core characters. Don't even ask. La-la-la-la-la, we can't hear you.''</p>
        <p>Like many games, Diablo allows players to interact with each other over the Internet, another part of its appeal, players said. At Blizzard's Battle.net Web site, Diablo players can interact or compete at no cost, joining each other's quests or battling for supremacy.</p>
        <p>''One of the assumptions that often gets made with computers is that they alienate and isolate people,'' said Robert Nideffer, a professor at the University of California at Irvine who specializes in the study of art and computer science. ''In fact, players are actively participating with other people in a very social space.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nideffer is one of a small but growing group of academics, including Mr. Coover of Brown, who argue that games are worthy of study for what they tell about how people interact with computers and the future of technology.</p>
        <p>The game market remains small compared with other media. About 170 million game cartridges and compact discs were sold last year, compared with more than 1.5 billion general-interest books, according to PC Data and the Book Industry Study Group.</p>
        <p>But while book sales are flat or declining and movie admissions are barely rising, sales of games are surging. The number of games bought for PC's tripled between 1993 and 1999, and for the first five months of 2000, computer game sales are more than 10 percent higher than last year, according to PC Data, a research firm in Virginia.</p>
        <p>The growing game market has not escaped the attention of Warner Brothers, which is working to develop a game based on the Harry Potter series. At the same time, Blizzard is working with Pocket Books to release a three-part series of books based on the Diablo games.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
