<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unusual Setting, But Fish Still Bite</title>
    <meta content="03OUTD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219751"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bass (Fish)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island Sound</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sautner, Stephen C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E1DA163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unusual Setting, But Fish Still Bite</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen C. Sautner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sautner, Stephen C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Outdoors column discusses bass fishing from shore of Long Island Sound (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thoughts of hungry striped bass hung in the air, bright as the nearly full moon rising in the afternoon haze over Long Island. Though not a swirl or splash could yet be seen, Rob Maass and John Waidman stood supremely confident, casting bucktails from shore into a quiet backwater.</p>
        <p>They had lured me here with tales of wild fishing they had stumbled upon only two days earlier. Between them, they landed nearly 60 fish, all stripers in the 3- to 6-pound range.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thoughts of hungry striped bass hung in the air, bright as the nearly full moon rising in the afternoon haze over Long Island. Though not a swirl or splash could yet be seen, Rob Maass and John Waidman stood supremely confident, casting bucktails from shore into a quiet backwater.</p>
        <p>They had lured me here with tales of wild fishing they had stumbled upon only two days earlier. Between them, they landed nearly 60 fish, all stripers in the 3- to 6-pound range.</p>
        <p>They told me how the bass had pinned schools of young-of-the-year spearing against the shoreline, gulping them down by the dozen and swiping at nearly any lure tossed their way.</p>
        <p>What made the invitation even more tempting was the odd-ball location: an utterly urbanized shoreline of Queens, along a dead-end cove of western Long Island Sound.</p>
        <p>Directions included parking near some garden apartments, then wandering under a highway overpass while keeping a low profile so as not to tip off any potential commuter/anglers as they zipped home. Catching a fish under such conditions seemed downright illicit -- in a playing hooky sort of way.</p>
        <p>More than anyone I know, Waidman and Maass have assembled a formidable cache of equally funky spots. Waidman, a scientist for the Hudson River Foundation, recently chronicled New York Harbor's prolific wildlife in his book ''Heartbeats in the Muck.'' Maass has spent the better part of the last two years filming anglers in New York City for an coming documentary on the subject.</p>
        <p>The two men have even wet their lines in the Gowanus Canal in Brooklyn, which Waidman describes as ''punched senseless by man.'' Even there, they have caught fish.</p>
        <p>Perhaps a trip to the Gowanus was now in order as the three of us continued to cast with no results. Maass theorized that the tide may to be to blame, since it would flood nearly two hours later than the other night. Waidman, on the other hand, silently fired cast after cast into the cove until, finally, he yielded two small stripers around 14 inches each.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, I had switched to a surface popper, if for no other reason than to watch it slowly chug along the glassy surface of the cove. With the light spinning rod and 6-pound line I brought to match up with the schoolie bass, I could send the weighted lure a few hundred feet.</p>
        <p>As the popper began another slow, gurgling retrieve, a large swirl suddenly appeared behind it. I thought for a moment that a striper may be following, when all at once the lure and everything around it seemed to explode in a wild shower of spray. Reflexively, I lifted the rod and 100 feet of line instantly dumped off my reel, the telltale sign of a big bluefish. The fish stopped, briefly shook its head and stripped off another 100 feet for good measure.</p>
        <p>Now, clutching a doubled-over fishing rod that seemed as inadequate as a stick and some old string, I remembered that Waidman and Maass had warned me that a few large blues had been patrolling the cove, probably in pursuit of the small striper. Hooking into one on such light tackle, and the barroom brawl that would surely follow, must have seemed foolhardy enough that I had blocked it out of my mind.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the fish held deep, shaking its head repeatedly like a dog that refuses to give up its favorite sock. Tremors shot up the line, down the rod, and into my upper arms. Large blues, with their sickle-shaped tails and thick, muscular bodies, can do this indefinitely.</p>
        <p>And so it went for the next 10 minutes. The bluefish would sometimes turn, if only for a moment, allowing me to gobble a few yards of line back on the reel, only to resume its head-shaking routine once more. At one point the fish actually rose to the surface and its gaping mouth looked as if it could chomp a small striper clean in half.</p>
        <p>By now even Waidman and Maass had wandered over. I continued to draw the fish closer with my strained rod. Finally I steered it into the shallows, where it kicked its tail one last time and beached itself.</p>
        <p>On the shore lay a bluefish that Waidman estimated at 36 inches and easily 14 pounds. I slipped the barbie's popper from its huge mouth, then grabbed it by its tail and slipped my other hand under its prodigious belly to hold up for an imaginary photo. But the big blue would have none of it. It wrestled from my grip and thrashed back into the water, pushing a torpedo wake as it sped away.</p>
        <p>Thankfully, no more big blues came that night. And though the stripers never did show up either, by the next day a satisfying twinge of stiffness had settled into both arms.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
