<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plunging Ratings Touch Off Debate on Why Public Is Losing Interest</title>
    <meta content="Y03RATI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: ON TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brokaw, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E2DB163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plunging Ratings Touch Off Debate on Why Public Is Losing Interest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Broadcast television networks have cut back on hours devoted to presidential conventions, holding viewers are uninterested; low ratings for first two nights of Republican National Convention seem to back up stand; Tom Brokaw, NBC anchor, blames parties for eliminating all semblance of suspense or debate; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1984, ABC shocked news purists by inserting a rerun of a canceled series, ''Hart to Hart,'' in the middle of one night's convention coverage. The same year an ABC News executive, Jeff Gralnick, labeled the conventions ''dying dinosaurs.''</p>
        <p>In 1992, CBS skipped one night entirely to cover the baseball All-Star game. In 1996, Ted Koppel of ABC yanked his ''Nightline'' crew from the Republican convention one night early, declaring there was too little news.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1984, ABC shocked news purists by inserting a rerun of a canceled series, ''Hart to Hart,'' in the middle of one night's convention coverage. The same year an ABC News executive, Jeff Gralnick, labeled the conventions ''dying dinosaurs.''</p>
        <p>In 1992, CBS skipped one night entirely to cover the baseball All-Star game. In 1996, Ted Koppel of ABC yanked his ''Nightline'' crew from the Republican convention one night early, declaring there was too little news.</p>
        <p>For two decades, the amount of convention coverage has been a testy issue. This year, the debate has only increased as the broadcast networks have further cut back on the hours devoted to the convention, saying that viewers are uninterested. Over the first two nights of this year's convention, the ratings seem to back them up.</p>
        <p>But whether the falloff in audience is a result of viewers losing interest or the broadcast networks simply offering them less to be interested in is a matter of some debate.</p>
        <p>The chairmen of both parties confronted network executives at a panel discussion in Philadelphia on Sunday accusing them of shirking their civic duty by drastically curtailing the number of hours of live coverage and argued that by de-emphasing coverage, they were sending the message that the conventions were not newsworthy.</p>
        <p>Network executives dismissed that accusation.</p>
        <p>''I reject that chicken and egg theory,'' said Andrew Heyward, the president of CBS News. ''I do not think people are less interested because we're covering less but because they find the conventions less compelling.''</p>
        <p>For Tom Brokaw, the NBC anchor, who has covered every political convention since 1968, the blame lies squarely with the decisions made by the parties to eliminate all semblance of suspense or debate.</p>
        <p>''We are covering them differently because there's no there there,'' he said. ''The parties have drained all the drama out of the proceedings.''</p>
        <p>With network coverage reduced at a time when the number of cable news channels has expanded, exact comparisons of this year's audience with the past audiences are difficult.</p>
        <p>But there are signs of lack of interest. Even though CBS and NBC tried a bait-and-switch technique the first two nights to try to lure viewers -- by folding the coverage inside its news magazines -- the audience defected in huge numbers as soon as convention coverage started. ABC, the one network duplicating its coverage from 1996, saw its ratings fall about 25 percent, compared with the first two nights four years ago.</p>
        <p>On CBS, the program ''60 Minutes II'' offered a repeat segment on dot-com millionaires for the first half-hour and drew a 4.6 rating. That fell to a 4.1 once the convention coverage came on. (Each rating point represents just over 1 million homes.)</p>
        <p>The falloff was more drastic at NBC, where a ''Dateline'' segment on nursing homes drew a 7.2 rating in the first half-hour. The second half-hour of convention coverage lost almost half that audience, falling to a 3.8 rating.</p>
        <p>''Here you had John McCain, one of the heroes of the campaign, speaking and, zowie, half the audience is gone,'' Mr. Heyward said.</p>
        <p>He also cited CNN's falloff in viewers from 1996 -- a decline of 35 percent the first night and 17 percent the second night. This is partly due to increased competition from Fox News and MSNBC.</p>
        <p>CNN executives argued that they had been totally satisfied with the ratings so far. ''We got a big bounce over our normal ratings,'' said Susan Binford, the spokeswoman for CNN. ''And we increased our numbers from the first night to the second. We think the networks are engaging in a self-fulfilling prophecy in sending out the message that the conventions are boring.''</p>
        <p>Money is not at the heart of the network decisions to cut back, Mr. Heyward said, though he said network expenses in covering the event, put at $15 million each in the 1980's, were now down to single digit millions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heyward said, ''If things don't change, I could see a scenario where the candidates' acceptance speeches become the only events covered live in 2004.''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: ON TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
