<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rather Be in Philadelphia? G.O.P. Convention's Online</title>
    <meta content="03CONV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DC1F3DF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rather Be in Philadelphia? G.O.P. Convention's Online</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE WAYNE</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Aug. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Internet is a new presence at this year's Republican National Convention, and it is blurring barriers between those who are at convention and those who are not; Webmasters say Internet has ability to encourage grass-roots political involvemnt and can challenge ability of parties and pundits to set political agenda; Web surfers are able to pull up candidates' speeches, videos of proceedings and party position papers, share political opinions, participate in opinion polls, and scan and zoom in on convention floor via 360-degree cameras; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the media tents off the floor of the Republican National Convention here, in a corner dubbed Internet Alley, the crowd is young, the style is geek chic and the latest in computer gadgetry is on display. It's all part of a not-so-quiet Internet revolution, say those who work here, that has the potential to shake up the world of politics.</p>
        <p>Just as television made its political debut at the Republican convention in Philadelphia in 1948 -- and politics has never been the same -- the Web has made its way to the convention here. Whether it is a way of connecting delegates and building party loyalty or a means of promoting grass-roots political activism among those not present, a wired world has been constructed here to  link the convention floor to cyberspace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the media tents off the floor of the Republican National Convention here, in a corner dubbed Internet Alley, the crowd is young, the style is geek chic and the latest in computer gadgetry is on display. It's all part of a not-so-quiet Internet revolution, say those who work here, that has the potential to shake up the world of politics.</p>
        <p>Just as television made its political debut at the Republican convention in Philadelphia in 1948 -- and politics has never been the same -- the Web has made its way to the convention here. Whether it is a way of connecting delegates and building party loyalty or a means of promoting grass-roots political activism among those not present, a wired world has been constructed here to  link the convention floor to cyberspace.</p>
        <p>There are ''dot-com delegates'' participating in a virtual convention. Politicians who once never knew the difference between e-mail and eBay are now lining up to participate in political chat rooms with ''e-jockeys'' as hosts. One Web site, with five 360-degree cameras, offers streaming video that allows site visitors to scan the convention floor, zooming in and out for close-ups of individual delegations and delegates.</p>
        <p>Polls are being taken online while speakers are on the podium, providing a real-time reaction to their speeches. And there are chat rooms, feedback forums, discussion groups and ways for Web users to talk back and talk about politicians.</p>
        <p>The goal is to break down the physical barriers between those who are at the convention and those who are not.</p>
        <p>''We're not replacing any medium -- we are a new medium,'' said David Borhman, chief executive of Pseudo.com, which offers the 360-degree cameras and online chats with politicians. ''We are going to have a role in politics, but we don't know what it will be. This convention is a test for us, just as the first television cameras here 52 years ago were a test.''</p>
        <p>The Webmasters here say their sites are superior to television because they are interactive while television is not. Television provides viewers with a set body of information at a set time that is selected by the network. Web surfers, not bound by the same constraints, are able to turn to these sites to pull up candidates' speeches, videos of the proceedings and party position papers or to engage in political chat rooms when and for as long as they want. Television networks have tapped into the Web world, too, offering live video and audio from the convention and message boards.</p>
        <p>Those in Internet Alley say that the Web has the ability to encourage grass-roots political involvement at a time when voter participation is declining and that it can challenge the ability of parties and pundits to set the political agenda.</p>
        <p>Of course, it is hard to determine the exact impact these sites are having. Their audience is still small -- none of the sites are on any list of the 100 most popular sites. But Pseudo.com says its chat rooms are filled with people saying they are new to the political process. And on MTV's Choose OrLose.com, the most heavily visited part of the site is its SpeakUp section, where Web users share political opinions.</p>
        <p>Steve Schneider, a research fellow at the Annenberg Public Policy Center at the University of Pennsylvania, said: ''Can we measure the impact on this election? Not at this time. But what we are seeing is political junkies turning to the Web for information,  and Web junkies turning into these political sites.''</p>
        <p>Robert B. Vanasse, vice president for programming at Voter.com, said, ''What we are doing is not just chats and message boards.'' The site offers text and video of the convention floor proceedings, comparisons of the candidates' records, chat rooms with politicians and a daily topic for political debate with an interactive poll.</p>
        <p>Not wanting to miss an opportunity, the Republican Party has also jumped on the Web bandwagon. Its convention site, www.gopconvention.com, not only provides information on daily events to delegates, but also connects the activities here to some 15,000 dot-com delegates who are participating online.</p>
        <p>Dot-com delegates -- anyone who wants to be one can register -- receive daily e-mail messages telling them the ''talking points'' the party gives to every delegate each morning in case they run into reporters. The online delegates can submit questions to be answered each day by Republican leaders here, receive daily news reports about their state's delegation and participate in surveys.</p>
        <p>For the party, it's a way of capturing e-mail addresses for future mailings in the fall campaign and a way of building enthusiasm. ''E-mail, e-mail, e-mail,'' said Lawrence J. Purpuro, deputy chief of staff for the Republican National Committee, explaining the site's purpose. ''We are out to build relationships with the party. For us, the Web is a powerful medium. We can give folks the information we want; we can ask them what issues they care about. Because it is interactive, it is essentially the best focus group money can buy.''</p>
        <p>Of course, many in Internet Alley see information flowing in the other direction,  from ordinary voters and to the parties. SpeakOut.com, a nonpartisan site designed to increase political activism, has the ability to record a visitor's response to a convention speaker during the speech on something called, informally, a ''mood meter.'' Once signed in, a person watches the speech on MSNBC and then continually scrolls along an online bar recording reactions, favorable or less favorable, to each line of the speech.</p>
        <p>SpeakOut.com puts these analyses online. For instance, of 1,200 people using the mood meter to judge the first convention night speeches, Laura Bush scored particularly well among women who were undecided. Colin L. Powell scored as high as George W. Bush's taped presentation among Bush voters, but he was outscored by Mr. Bush among undecided voters.</p>
        <p>''I explained to one congressman what was going to be happening during his speech,'' said Rekha Chalasani, director of public affairs for SpeakOut.Com. ''He just looked at me and said, 'You've got to be kidding.' But we aren't. Conventions are so scripted. This gets beyond the pundits and prognosticators and shows how people are really reacting.''</p>
        <p>Todd Vitale, director of political programs for Voter.com, said: ''We were able to use our site as a channel to give the Republican party input on the platform. The Web is making it hard for those in Washington to be so isolated.''</p>
        <p>There are computer kiosks put up by Voter.com in the hotels where delegates are staying to provide information on daily convention events. Congressional Quarterly and Motorola are distributing pagers with e-mail capability and access to news stories to anyone asking for them. (The Republican Party turned down an offer to provide every delegate with one, but the Democrats will be giving them to all delegates at their convention in Los Angeles, Aug. 14 to 17.)</p>
        <p>Where will this all lead? ''I could see the day,'' said Burton Pines, director of Internet operations for the Republican National Committee, ''when we have a three-day virtual convention and a one-day real one.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
