<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once-Towering Figure Is Focus of Irish Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="Y03IRE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/03/world/03IREL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ireland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haughey, Charles J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3D71F3DF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once-Towering Figure Is Focus of Irish Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <dateline>DUBLIN, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Irish Prime Min Charles J Haughey, once dominant political figure, is being questioned by tribunal probing suspected corruption; tribunal has estimated he got as much as $10 million in contributions from businessmen to cover his huge debts and expensive tastes and seeks to determine whether he used public office to benefit donors; probe will join other efforts to tighten relatively new public ethics laws; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Each weekday morning, he is chauffeured in a pale blue Mercedes to the doors of Dublin Castle. It would seem a fitting mode of travel for a former prime minister of Ireland, a man of regal bearing whose very face, with those hooded eyelids and that dramatic sweep of silvery hair, is as identifiable in this country as the castle itself.</p>
        <p>But Charles J. Haughey comes to discuss the state of his financial affairs rather than affairs of state -- from the witness stand, at a tribunal that is exploring the relationship between this once-dominant political figure and various businessmen who, over the years, handed him and his subordinates hundreds of thousands of dollars in checks and cash.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Each weekday morning, he is chauffeured in a pale blue Mercedes to the doors of Dublin Castle. It would seem a fitting mode of travel for a former prime minister of Ireland, a man of regal bearing whose very face, with those hooded eyelids and that dramatic sweep of silvery hair, is as identifiable in this country as the castle itself.</p>
        <p>But Charles J. Haughey comes to discuss the state of his financial affairs rather than affairs of state -- from the witness stand, at a tribunal that is exploring the relationship between this once-dominant political figure and various businessmen who, over the years, handed him and his subordinates hundreds of thousands of dollars in checks and cash.</p>
        <p>The tribunal has estimated that Mr. Haughey (pronounced HAW-hee) received as much as $10 million in contributions to cover his huge debts and expensive tastes, and it is poring over his personal banking records to determine whether he used his public office to benefit his benefactors. Mr. Haughey and his lawyers have not yet addressed the central thrust of the inquiry, but they are expected to maintain that he did nothing untoward for the money, which they will argue totaled no more than $7.5 million.</p>
        <p>The seamiest allegations center on a fund that Mr. Haughey established in 1989 to send his political ally and close friend, Brian Lenihan, who has since died, to the United States for a liver transplant. About $100,000 from the fund covered the transplant and related costs, but the whereabouts of at least another $125,000 is unclear -- although there is evidence that some was spent on Mr. Haughey's personal expenses.</p>
        <p>The tribunal will ultimately present a report to Parliament that probably will join other efforts to tighten relatively new public ethics laws. Michael Moran, a government spokesman, said that revelations regarding Mr. Haughey and other politicians have already contributed to legislation seeking further reform.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the daily proceedings of the tribunal [which began a summer recess on July 28 and will reconvene in September] feed a growing list of allegations of public corruption. There are 9 sitting tribunals and 11 other inquiries, investigating everything from the contamination of blood products to decades-old allegations of child abuse in public institutions.</p>
        <p>But the most prominent investigation centers on offshore bank accounts, cozy public-private relationships and blurred lines between political donations and personal gifts -- all of which lead inexorably back to this 74-year-old man twirling his gold-rimmed glasses as he ponders embarrassing questions posed in public.</p>
        <p>''He is a Nixon figure in Irish public life,'' said Dermot Keogh, an author and professor of Irish history at National University of Ireland in Cork. ''He is a flawed talent.''</p>
        <p>An accountant from Dublin and the son-in-law of former Prime Minister Sean Lemass, Mr. Haughey rose quickly within the dominant political party, Fianna Fail (FEE-na FALL) to serve in various ministerial capacities in the 1960's. He is credited with several progressive measures, from ensuring that widows and children were included in estate matters to providing free electricity and public transportation to the elderly.</p>
        <p>He spent several years in political isolation -- charged with, and then acquitted of, conspiring to import guns to be used in Northern Ireland. But in 1979 he returned, gaining control of Fianna Fail and emerging as prime minister, a position he held, on and off, for nine years. He was both blamed and praised for economic ebbs and flows and is generally credited with jump-starting the Northern Ireland peace efforts.</p>
        <p>He seemed larger than life, with a stiletto-sharp intellect, a ruthless political instinct and an imperious nature. While visiting Galway one day in the early 1980's, he tried to scrape a campaign sticker from his shoe. When he failed, one of his ranking cabinet ministers bent down low to remove the annoyance.</p>
        <p>''He has this Napoleonic thing; he fancies himself as quite a bit of an emperor,'' said Ryle Dwyer, a historian who has written several books about Mr. Haughey. ''But I would argue that he had this real charisma in the true sense of the word, used for politicians who seem capable of superhuman feats. In Haughey's case, he kept escaping.''</p>
        <p>Throughout, the matter of his wealth vexed and amused the nation. Mr. Haughey earned a modest salary as a member of the Parliament, yet lived on a Dublin estate, owned a small island off the southern coast, and relaxed on a yacht called the ''Celtic Mist.''</p>
        <p>By 1992, various controversies had become too much for even Mr. Haughey's allies to countenance, and he was forced to step down as prime minister. With characteristic flourish, he said farewell to public life with a quote from ''Othello'': ''I have done the state some service, they know't; no more of that.''</p>
        <p>But just as Mr. Haughey was settling into his role as elder statesman, the Dunne family, owners of the country's largest department-store chain, became concerned with the spending habits of the company's chief executive, Ben Dunne. Inquiries led to the discovery that over the years Mr. Dunne had given Mr. Haughey a sum now estimated at $2.5 million.</p>
        <p>At first Mr. Haughey told an investigating tribunal in 1997 that he knew nothing of the matter and that a close adviser had handled his financial affairs to free him ''to devote my time and ability to public life.'' But the accumulated evidence forced Mr. Haughey to concede that he had misled the tribunal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunne's testimony of an incident in 1991 was particularly damaging. He said he visited the prime minister and found him looking depressed. To cheer the leader up, he said, he handed him checks totaling $260,000. His recollection of Mr. Haughey's response has since entered national lore: ''Thank you, big fella.''</p>
        <p>Although the tribunal found no evidence that Mr. Haughey had assisted Mr. Dunne in exchange for the gifts, it expressed great doubt about the former leader's testimony. ''It is quite unacceptable,'' the tribunal said in its final report, for an elected official -- particularly a prime minister -- to be ''supported in his personal lifestyle by gifts made to him personally.''</p>
        <p>A criminal charge of obstruction was lodged against Mr. Haughey, and he was forced to pay more than $1 million in back taxes and penalties.</p>
        <p>Now another panel is digging deeper into his murky finances to determine whether the showers of money influenced the performance of his public duties.</p>
        <p>And so, for the last 18 months, some of Ireland's best-known public figures -- from multimillionaire businessmen to Bertie Ahern, a former Haughey lieutenant and current prime minister -- have made their way up the cobblestone path to Dublin Castle to share their tantalizing pieces of the puzzle.</p>
        <p>Even the Haughey faithful have found the revelations unsettling. Testimony has shown that when he was elected prime minister in late 1979, Mr. Haughey and his aides spread the word that he needed money, fast: he owed more than $1.3 million to Allied Irish Bank. Within weeks, he was able to give more than $930,000 to the bank, which charged off most of what was still owed.</p>
        <p>A property developer, in typical testimony, testified that he contributed $475,000 to the cause after being summoned by the prime minister to his estate. Another developer testified that in 1989 he handed Mr. Haughey four checks for about $31,000 each -- one for the Lenihan transplant fund and the three others for Fianna Fail. But according to the tribunal, the party received only a portion of the money, and none of it was deposited in the transplant fund.</p>
        <p>In fact, testimony has shown that contributions to the Lenihan fund went into a so-called leader's account that Mr. Haughey used for such personal needs as tailor-made shirts from Paris and dinners at an exclusive French restaurant in Dublin. Evidence that Mr. Lenihan's medical costs were fully covered has not created a groundswell of support for Mr. Haughey, no more than have reports that he has prostate cancer.</p>
        <p>Professor Keogh, who has written several books on modern Ireland, said the revelations of the tribunal demonstrate the extent to which Mr. Haughey and his allies corrupted the values of a government founded a generation earlier by people who believed in a ''communitarian democracy.'' The country needed to be modernized, he said, ''but he did it in a way that weakened and undermined the state of governance, and the citizens' confidence in the government.''</p>
        <p>Professor Dwyer said, though, that Mr. Haughey is not the first leader to believe that he should focus on public affairs while others tend to his finances. Mr. Dwyer also said that, given the many other cases of political scandal, Mr. Haughey's indiscretions are more symptomatic than causal -- and that Irish politicians have long had the power to enact reform.</p>
        <p>''If he has done wrong he should be nailed and, I rightly feel, jailed,'' Mr. Dwyer said. ''I just don't like the hypocrisy.''</p>
        <p>As others contemplate his legacy, Mr. Haughey comes daily to Dublin Castle and tries when possible to contain the harm already done. At times he has claimed to be overwhelmed by all the paperwork. At other times he demonstrates the acumen for which he was once famous, quibbling with the nuances of certain words -- even the nuances of punctuation -- that appear in old bank memoranda portraying him as an unrepentant debtor who was not above mentioning his station in national politics.</p>
        <p>Then, when two hours have elapsed -- a time limit established in deference to his age and illness -- Mr. Haughey is excused. A few minutes later, the blue Mercedes carrying a small man in the passenger seat pulls away from Dublin Castle, whose refurbishment he oversaw when once in power.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
