<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parched U.S. Faces Worst Year for Fires Since Mid-80's</title>
    <meta content="Y03FIR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Western States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forest and Brush Fires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5DC163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parched U.S. Faces Worst Year for Fires Since Mid-80's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, Aug. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prolonged hot and dry weather this summer, especially in West, is resulting in unsually large number of wildfires around nation; 61,400 fires have burned nearly 3.6 million acres so far, mostly in West, with many more fires expected before fall; two military battalions of 500 each have been called to assist overburdened firefighters; map; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prolonged hot and dry weather this summer, especially in the West, has made this the worst year since the mid-1980's for wildfires around the country. And with no major meteorological changes in sight, many more fires are expected before temperatures drop in the fall.</p>
        <p>The National Interagency Fire Center in Boise, Idaho, this year has recorded 61,400 fires, which have burned nearly 3.6 million acres, the vast majority in Western states. The fires include 17 new wildfires reported overnight, bringing to 47 the number of large wildfires now burning on more than 707,200 acres in Arizona, California, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, Texas, Utah and Wyoming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prolonged hot and dry weather this summer, especially in the West, has made this the worst year since the mid-1980's for wildfires around the country. And with no major meteorological changes in sight, many more fires are expected before temperatures drop in the fall.</p>
        <p>The National Interagency Fire Center in Boise, Idaho, this year has recorded 61,400 fires, which have burned nearly 3.6 million acres, the vast majority in Western states. The fires include 17 new wildfires reported overnight, bringing to 47 the number of large wildfires now burning on more than 707,200 acres in Arizona, California, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, Texas, Utah and Wyoming.</p>
        <p>''This year has been much worse than average,'' said Dennis Pendleton, the center's director, judging the severity by the number of acres burned. ''With the number of acreage burned, the number of fires and the drought, it's the worst we've had in 15 years and it could become one of the worst years we've ever had.''</p>
        <p>Complicating matters for firefighters is a wildfire season made unusually long by the unchanging weather patterns. The season typically ends in June in many Southern states and in July through the Southwest, when heavy rains materialize. But persistently dry weather has left many forest regions brittle and easily set ablaze by a lightning strike or a discarded cigarette, which is how many fires are started.</p>
        <p>In its daily assessment of conditions around the country, the fire center said today that 11 states in the West were reporting ''very high to extreme fire danger indices,'' with hot and dry weather expected to continue.</p>
        <p>The cumulative effect of an ever-growing number of fires has placed such a high demand on firefighting personnel and equipment this summer that two military battalions of 500 each have been called to assist, a normal procedure when wildfires have overwhelmed local and state resources and firefighters have tired.</p>
        <p>An Army battalion from Fort Hood, Tex., arrived in Boise on Tuesday to begin field training today for action later this week, fighting the Burgdorf Junction fires in central Idaho. A Marine battalion from Camp Pendleton in Southern California is scheduled to arrive for training on Saturday for deployment to the Clear Creek fires in northern Idaho.</p>
        <p>''The demand has been unusually high,'' Mr. Pendleton said of the need for added firefighters and equipment. ''The same people have been chasing a good deal of the fires around the country since early April. Just in California, we've problems since January.''</p>
        <p>The fire center measures the severity of wildfires in a variety of ways: by the number of fires, by the number of acres burned and by how many military battalions have been summoned to help.</p>
        <p>Over the last 50 years, 1981 was the worst for the number of fires, with 249,370; 1950 was the worst for number of acres burned, with 17.5 million; and wildfires in 1988 demanded the largest number of battalions, 8.</p>
        <p>Many times, wildfires cause deaths, and by that measure this year has been relatively safe. Only one death has been attributed to firefighting efforts, that of a smoke-jumper from Alaska whose parachute failed to open while he was training.</p>
        <p>Records kept by the fire center indicate that the worst years for deaths were 1871, when wildfires in Wisconsin and Michigan caused the deaths of 1,500 people, and 1894, when wildfires in Minnesota killed 418.</p>
        <p>Fewer deaths have been recorded in recent years, largely because of the ability to warn people far in advance of spreading fires so they can evacuate the area and because of improved firefighting equipment.</p>
        <p>Another measure is the cost of fire suppression, although it is difficult to put a final price on overall damage caused by wildfires in a given year because the accounting would take into consideration costs to the federal government, as well as state and local agencies and individuals through property damage.</p>
        <p>Among the five federal land agencies over the six years through 1999, the largest costs, by far, have been borne by the Forest Service, $2.1 billion, according to figures compiled by the fire center. The overall federal cost for the six years was $2.9 billion.</p>
        <p>While the fires that burned in Los Alamos, N.M., in May received widespread national attention for the danger they posed to the national laboratories, other fires have caused equally troublesome problems for local residents.</p>
        <p>Among those now burning, fires south of Hamilton, Mont., have closed a state highway and forced evacuations in four towns. Abandoned mineshafts around fires burning 12 miles north of Helena, Mont., are hampering firefighting efforts there. Wildfires east of Phoenix are threatening summer homes, recreation areas and endangered habitats. Residents of several Utah towns southwest of Provo have been warned that spreading fires might come their way.</p>
        <p>Among the most challenging wildfires still burning out of control are those spreading across 5,100 acres of Cleveland National Forest, northeast of San Diego, where officials with the Forest Service say the rugged and inaccessible terrain, combined with limited resources, could leave the fire burning another week or more.</p>
        <p>Even with seven helicopters assisting 1,000 firefighters, the wildfires today were only 15 percent contained.</p>
        <p>''We're about a month early, how dry it is,'' said Elliott Graham, a Forest Service spokesman at the site. ''This one is different; a lot of it is in a wilderness area.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
