<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Journalists Are Making Very Much Of a Little</title>
    <meta content="Y03SURF" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE NEWS MEDIA -- POLITICAL SURFING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, Gerald Rudolph Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George Prescott (Former Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EEDB163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Journalists Are Making Very Much Of a Little</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Carefully scripted Republican National Convention had given journalists little actual news to cover until former Pres Gerald R Ford was hospitalized with stroke, former Pres Bush attacked Pres Clinton for deriding his son and Dick Cheney was nominated for vice presidency (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Perhaps it was when the musician Kenny Gamble stepped to the microphone and yelled -- ''Peace, everybody!'' -- and then, dissatisfied with the lackluster response from the Republican delegates, forcefully added: ''Did you hear me? I said, peace!''</p>
        <p>Or perhaps it was when Representative Joe Scarborough of Florida brought his rock band, the Regular Joes, to the stage at the Republican National Convention and warmed up the crowd with a little poetry, ''Unite, not divide, so once again we can look at the White House with pride.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Perhaps it was when the musician Kenny Gamble stepped to the microphone and yelled -- ''Peace, everybody!'' -- and then, dissatisfied with the lackluster response from the Republican delegates, forcefully added: ''Did you hear me? I said, peace!''</p>
        <p>Or perhaps it was when Representative Joe Scarborough of Florida brought his rock band, the Regular Joes, to the stage at the Republican National Convention and warmed up the crowd with a little poetry, ''Unite, not divide, so once again we can look at the White House with pride.''</p>
        <p>Or maybe it was when Fox News tracked down a giddy delegate wearing a hat that had a live plant on its crown and a slender chain hanging from the brim along with a four-inch ''E.'' What did it mean? ''Bush,'' she said, pointing to the plant. ''And chain-E, Cheney.''</p>
        <p>But surely CNN's Bernard Shaw was not alone when he shook his head with disbelief, asking, ''The Republican convention?''</p>
        <p>Television reporters and Internet correspondents seemed energized, if a little startled, yesterday by the prospect of actual news to report from the convention. Until yesterday, as has been endlessly pointed out, the convention had been a carefully scripted infomercial punctuated by scattered protests and pundits on autopilot.</p>
        <p>But suddenly there was the disclosure that former President Gerald R. Ford had gone to the hospital with what was thought to be a sinus infection but was actually a stroke. That followed the beginning of a whiff of a semi-controversy about former President George Bush attacking President Clinton for attacking Mr. Bush's son. And then there was an actual event that took place, with the Republicans getting an official vice presidential candidate.</p>
        <p>The all-news channels and streaming Web sites suddenly had something to cut back to regularly (correspondents standing outside the hospital, promising updates on Mr. Ford's condition), a fresh bone to gnaw on (whether former President Bush should have kept quiet) and a convention floor that at long last began to go a little wacky around the edges.</p>
        <p>Some news outlets that had done interviews with Mr. Ford on Tuesday, before he was hospitalized, replayed the tapes throughout the afternoon, so viewers could watch the 87-year-old former president slurring his words. At the same time, the pundit class was making much of former President Bush's remark that he was growing irritated with President Clinton's attacks on Mr. Bush's son. This allowed Democrats and some pundits to argue that Gov. George W. Bush of Texas apparently needed his daddy to protect him.</p>
        <p>Yesterday morning, when former President Bush and his wife, Barbara, appeared on ''Good Morning, America,'' he was promising to be good. ''They're making a federal case about it,'' he said. ''It's better to say nothing about it, future, now, nothing, period.'' The show's host, Charles Gibson, however, knew raw meat when he saw it and prodded once more. ''Not going to talk about it,'' former President Bush insisted.</p>
        <p>Then Mrs. Bush leapt to her husband's aid, saying that his was not really a personal attack, just an observation about the state of the presidency. Again, Mr. Gibson detected sirloin. Oh, is there something wrong with the state of the presidency? Has it been sullied? And who might have been responsible for that? ''You know who I mean,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Former President Bush tried to shush his wife. ''They're going to get all over your case,'' he warned.</p>
        <p>''I don't care,'' she said.</p>
        <p>There they were, working it out, on television. It was like being a fly on the wall in Kennebunkport, Me.</p>
        <p>By the end of the day, though, the pundits seemed to have gnawed all the meat off the bone. Besides, Governor Bush had finally arrived in Philadelphia and was himself criticizing President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Lewis Black, a political humorist reporting for the Comedy Central cable network, complained that he and his colleagues had been refused floor credentials and had been reduced to covering the event from a college dormitory miles away. ''If we had any brains, we could have been on a cruise ship, watching it on television and sipping cocktails,'' Mr. Black said.</p>
        <p>Peace!</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE NEWS MEDIA -- POLITICAL SURFING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
