<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; The Orioles Pack Up The U-Haul</title>
    <meta content="03CHAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Orioles</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trades (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0DC163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; The Orioles Pack Up The U-Haul</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murray Chass Sports of The Times column discusses numerous trades made by Baltimore Orioles aimed at reducing club's payroll; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIKE BORDICK was the first to go. He was sent away last Friday. Mike Timlin followed him out the door the next day, and so did Charles Johnson and Harold Baines. Last Monday Will Clark and B. J. Surhoff joined them. In 75 hours, a long weekend, the Baltimore Orioles chopped 74 years of major league service from their roster.</p>
        <p>Not to mention nearly $25 million in salaries for the rest of this and future seasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIKE BORDICK was the first to go. He was sent away last Friday. Mike Timlin followed him out the door the next day, and so did Charles Johnson and Harold Baines. Last Monday Will Clark and B. J. Surhoff joined them. In 75 hours, a long weekend, the Baltimore Orioles chopped 74 years of major league service from their roster.</p>
        <p>Not to mention nearly $25 million in salaries for the rest of this and future seasons.</p>
        <p>''I was a little surprised that they got rid of B. J.,'' Bordick, the Mets' rental shortstop, said Tuesday, the day after the Orioles traded Surhoff to Atlanta. ''I guess it came to the point where they had to do something drastic. Unfortunately, the last few years they haven't been very successful. They had to make some drastic changes, and they certainly did that.''</p>
        <p>The Orioles won the American League East in 1997, marking the second successive season they had reached the playoffs. But in the two subsequent seasons they spent nearly $1 million per victory in player payroll and had nothing to show for it. Their payroll for those two seasons totaled $147 million, and they won 157 games while finishing fourth both years, a total of 55 games from first.</p>
        <p>When Peter Angelos, the Orioles' owner, awoke last Friday, he again found his team in fourth. It was baseball's version of ''Groundhog Day,'' and Angelos was Bill Murray.</p>
        <p>''The results speak for themselves,'' Angelos said by telephone of the Orioles' subsequent moves. ''There was an interest in reconstructing the team, with the stress on younger players. With so many teams in contention for the wild card as well as division championships, there was a great opportunity to make beneficial trades to further that goal.''</p>
        <p>The Orioles are no longer the team Bordick thought he would continue to play for, beyond the free agency he can have after this season.</p>
        <p>''We had been talking about that, being there,'' Bordick said. ''The one thing about myself is you start something and you hope to finish it. There was some excitement there going to the postseason in '97. Then obviously the frustrating time came after that.''</p>
        <p>What happened to the Orioles in the last three seasons? ''That's what makes it so frustrating,'' Bordick said. ''We had so much talent. Not to do what we hoped to do there was very frustrating.'' Bordick didn't feel the frustration any more deeply than Angelos, who pays the large salaries. ''We had some great players,'' the owner said, ''but the years go by. The years take their toll on players who have done very well but who eventually aren't at the performance level they once were.''</p>
        <p>The half-dozen players the Orioles traded have 2000 salaries totaling $24 million. In the management and union method used to compute season payrolls, the trades left the Orioles with a $61 million payroll, down considerably from the opening-day figure of $81.5 million. In reality, the Orioles will save $7.2 million for the rest of this season and avoid having to pay $17 million that had been committed to future seasons for some of the traded players.</p>
        <p>''Money wasn't a consideration up front,'' Angelos said. ''It's a consequence. We save substantial dollars in making the changes, but those moneys will be invested back into the recruitment of additional players in order to present a competitive team next season. These aren't dollars that are going into anyone's pockets, except the players. That's the inevitable destination of all the dollars.''</p>
        <p>In other words, the Orioles weren't following in the grand tradition of the San Diego Padres of the early 1990's and the Florida Marlins of the 1997 World Series championship in decimating the team just to slash the payroll.</p>
        <p>''There will be a substantial number of first-rate players in the forthcoming free agency group,'' Angelos said. ''We intend to be involved heavily though carefully.''</p>
        <p>Angelos was quick to explain the difference, as he sees it, between the personnel actions of the 2000 Orioles and the 1997 Marlins.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the Marlins had any choice but to do that,'' he said, ''because their attendance and subsequent revenues have always been sparse. We're in a totally different position. We're a high-revenue franchise. Having those dollars available, we intend to invest them in a team worthy of the fan support we get every year. We're not in this game for profit. We provide entertainment and make a statement for the city and the state.''</p>
        <p>Despite their noncontending status, the Orioles lead the major leagues in attendance.</p>
        <p>''The support absolutely is unequaled and we are obliged to respond in a similar fashion,'' Angelos said. ''We have to give them a winner,  and we are going to give them a winner.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
