<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Colin Powell's Critique: Part II</title>
    <meta content="03LEWI$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219693"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Center for Public Integrity</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE0DF163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="695" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Colin Powell's Critique: Part II</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Charles Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Charles</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Center for Public Integrity founder Charles Lewis Op-Ed article notes government largess played key role in business success of both Dick Cheney and Gov George W Bush, while Vice Pres Al Gore remains closely tied to Washington lobbyists; holds affirmative action for special interests scored by Colin Powell is likely to continue (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some in our party miss no opportunity to roundly and loudly condemn affirmative action that helped a few thousand black kids get an education,'' Colin Powell told the Republican convention this week, ''but you hardly hear a whimper when it's affirmative action for lobbyists who load our federal tax code with preferences for special interests.''</p>
        <p>His defense of affirmative action got all the attention, but his challenge was twofold because he was also criticizing politicians' giveaways to corporations, which, in turn, contribute to those politicians' campaigns. Though this challenge could have been leveled at both Democrats and Republicans, let's start with the G.O.P.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some in our party miss no opportunity to roundly and loudly condemn affirmative action that helped a few thousand black kids get an education,'' Colin Powell told the Republican convention this week, ''but you hardly hear a whimper when it's affirmative action for lobbyists who load our federal tax code with preferences for special interests.''</p>
        <p>His defense of affirmative action got all the attention, but his challenge was twofold because he was also criticizing politicians' giveaways to corporations, which, in turn, contribute to those politicians' campaigns. Though this challenge could have been leveled at both Democrats and Republicans, let's start with the G.O.P.</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney, the party's vice presidential nominee, complained throughout his political career about the oppressive, wasteful, inefficient role of big government. But while he has been the chief executive of Halliburton, a Dallas oil services company, few businessmen have benefited more from federal help.</p>
        <p>In the five years that Mr. Cheney has run Halliburton, the company and its subsidiaries have received $2.3 billion in federal contracts, up from $1.2 billion during the five years preceding his tenure. Halliburton also received  $1.5 billion in guaranteed or direct loans from the Export-Import Bank and the Overseas Private Investment Corporation. In the five years before Mr. Cheney joined the company, it received only $100 million from these government institutions.</p>
        <p>How did Halliburton double its federal contracts and increase, by a factor of 15, the amount of direct or government-guaranteed loans? The company may attribute its success to other factors, but is it a coincidence that in the past five years, Halliburton gave $1.2 million to the two political parties and individual members of Congress? According to the Center for Responsive Politics, the company also increased its Washington lobbying: its costs mushroomed from $280,000 in 1996 to $600,000 last year. As Halliburton's fortunes have risen, so, too, have those of Mr. Cheney, who after five years at the helm is worth about $50 million.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Cheney, Gov. George W. Bush talks of the importance of self-reliance and getting government out of the way of private initiative -- unless, of course, there is a little ''affirmative action'' for your company.</p>
        <p>His success in business was also famously tied to government largess. Mr. Bush made $14.9 million from the sale of the Texas Rangers, a 25-fold return on his investment of $606,302. The team's phenomenal rise in value was directly tied to a new stadium financed by more than $200 million in public subsidies and tax incentives. Taxpayers didn't get a return from the Rangers' surging new revenues. The profits went almost exclusively to the team's owners.</p>
        <p>The Republicans hold no monopoly on hypocrisy. Despite the move of his campaign operation from Washington to Nashville, Vice President Al Gore is still close to the lobbyists on K Street. His closest confidants and campaign advisers are lobbyists for all kinds of corporate interests. His $30 million in 1999 contributions, a Democratic  record for fund-raising in a year before a presidential election, didn't come from backyard barbecues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore says that as president he would reform the campaign finance system. Yet he has clung steadfastly to legalistic evasions about the nature of both the notorious White House coffees, which collected $26.4 million for the Democratic Party from 1,544 people who sought face time with the president and vice president, and the Buddhist monastery event, which he has said was nothing more than ''community outreach.'' Such sustained sophistry is tiresome and does not speak well for a candidate who claims to want to clean up the system.</p>
        <p>So while I hope that both Democrats and Republicans take the second half of Colin Powell's message seriously, I won't hold my breath. Certain kinds of ''affirmative action'' are not going change much anytime soon.</p>
        <p>Charles Lewis is the founder and executive director of the Center for Public Integrity, a nonpartisan research group.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Charles Lewis is the founder and executive director of the Center for Public Integrity, a nonpartisan research group.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
