<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russia Trying To Get Assets Of Top Critic</title>
    <meta content="Y03RUS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/08/03/world/03RUSS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gazprom (Russia)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Media-Most (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tavernise, Sabrina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Surkov, Vladislav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gusinsky, Vladimir A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berezovsky, Boris A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E7DD163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russia Trying To Get Assets Of Top Critic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRINA TAVERNISE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tavernise, Sabrina</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Aug. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Senior Russian official Vladislav Surkov confirms government-controlled company Gazprom seeks to take over Media-Most from Vladimir Gusinsky, government's most outspoken critic, interview; Media-Most has hired foreign auditors in bid to show that company is worth far more than it owes Gazprom, which argues that it should get all of company; journalists and analysts see government trying to assert control over Russia's three biggest television networks; government has also begun talks with Boris A Berezovsky on his 49 percent stake in biggest network, ORT (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A senior Russian official said today that the government-controlled company Gazprom is in negotiations to acquire the entire media empire of Vladimir V. Gusinsky, the Kremlin's most outspoken critic.</p>
        <p>Speaking in an interview, Vladislav Surkov, deputy head of the presidential administration, confirmed what had been a matter of speculation for days, that the gas giant Gazprom may take over Mr. Gusinsky's company, Media-Most.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A senior Russian official said today that the government-controlled company Gazprom is in negotiations to acquire the entire media empire of Vladimir V. Gusinsky, the Kremlin's most outspoken critic.</p>
        <p>Speaking in an interview, Vladislav Surkov, deputy head of the presidential administration, confirmed what had been a matter of speculation for days, that the gas giant Gazprom may take over Mr. Gusinsky's company, Media-Most.</p>
        <p>Media-Most owes hundreds of millions of dollars to Gazprom, and they have been haggling over its own value. Media-Most, which has hired foreign auditors, wants to establish that  it is worth a great deal, so that  Gazprom would be entitled to only a small percentage of the company. Gazprom argues otherwise, that the debt should be exchanged for all of Media-Most.</p>
        <p>Though the talks are inconclusive so far, journalists and political analysts said the Kremlin is trying to assert control over Russia's three biggest television networks.</p>
        <p>The government has begun talks with the magnate Boris A. Berezovsky on his 49 percent stake in the biggest television network, ORT. He has mentioned a willingness to sell.</p>
        <p>In the case of the gas company, ''talks are being conducted, they are already drawing to a close,'' Mr. Surkov said. ''It s possible that in exchange for these debts the entire holding will be transferred to Gazprom.''</p>
        <p>Gazprom's apparent move against Media-Most shows that though President Vladimir V. Putin has promised the country's richest men that the state won't take away their assets, he may have specific goals to reduce their influence. The government owns 38 percent of Gazprom.</p>
        <p>Today's statement highlights the conflict between the Kremlin and Mr. Gusinsky, who has been under pressure since May, when masked law enforcement officers raided his offices in central Moscow. He was jailed for a while in June, though the criminal case against him was dropped last month.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the struggle is control over Mr. Gusinsky's assets, which include NTV, a large television network, and a new, American-made satellite, as well as the newsmagazine Itogi, Echo Moscow radio station and the newspaper Sevodnya. The current talks will determine how much of the holding Mr. Gusinsky is left with, whether some or none.</p>
        <p>Control of the media holding might not extend to NTV, however, as it is registered as a separate legal entity.</p>
        <p>''Though their political interests may not be made public, de facto they exist,'' said Boris Makarenko, deputy director of the Center for Political Technologies, an independent Moscow-based research institution. ''When a company friendly to the government acquires a controlling interest in Media-Most, the government accomplishes its goal. Media-Most as a hotbed of political opposition will cease to exist.''</p>
        <p>Media-Most denied that the talks focus on handing control to Gazprom, and said it is striving in the talks to agree to a valuation for the company. Media-Most puts its value at more than $2 billion, while Gazprom says the figure is much lower.</p>
        <p>Gazprom has extended loan guarantees totaling about $380 million to Media-Most, and already owns, directly and indirectly, just under half of the media company. Media-Most is also holding talks with foreign investors, which could reduce government pressure.</p>
        <p>In June, Gazprom asked Media-Most to pay the debts after Mr. Putin, on a trip to Europe, wondered aloud why Gazprom had become a creditor in the first place. In the same month, Mr. Putin reasserted control over the gas monopoly, installing a close adviser, Dmitri Medvedev, as chairman of the board.</p>
        <p>Despite the state's rocky relations with Mr. Gusinsky, recent attacks on some of the country's most powerful businessmen are not a systematic state policy, said Mr. Surkov, of the presidential administration. Law enforcement authorities have acted too rashly in the recent spate of investigations, he said.</p>
        <p>''Putin has said there won't be any review of privatization, and the law enforcement agencies now understand that,'' Mr. Surkov said. ''It's the role of the government to hold back these unhealthy tendencies.''</p>
        <p>One powerful business leader said Mr. Putin has not distanced himself entirely from big business, as he has not yet pushed out Roman Abramovich, a close friend of Boris N. Yeltsin's family.</p>
        <p>''There's not equal distance from all of the oligarchs yet,'' said the executive, who attended a meeting of Mr. Putin and the company's top business leaders on Friday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
