<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Prosperous Lunch With a Purpose, a Salad and Rubber Chicken</title>
    <meta content="Y03DIA$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: PHILADELPHIA DIARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuczynski, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdy, Matthew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gingrich, Newt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1D8163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1076" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Prosperous Lunch With a Purpose, a Salad and Rubber Chicken</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX KUCZYNSKI AND MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdy, Matthew; Kuczynski, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Diary of happenings at Republican National Convention: Gov George W Bush makes his public party debut at convention's biggest fund-raiser, which raises $10 million; former House Speaker Newt Gingrich attends convention, but does not have leading role; protesters fail to disrupt convention; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is your decision, America.</p>
        <p>Dinner at Alain Ducasse for two might set you back $500, but lunch with Gov. George W. Bush and 3,099 of his best friends on Wednesday ran to at least twice that at the Pennsylvania Convention Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is your decision, America.</p>
        <p>Dinner at Alain Ducasse for two might set you back $500, but lunch with Gov. George W. Bush and 3,099 of his best friends on Wednesday ran to at least twice that at the Pennsylvania Convention Center.</p>
        <p>But who needs foie gras poached in pepper court bouillon when you can get soggy Caesar salad and a glass of bathtub-warm pinot grigio (if you were one of the lucky ones)?</p>
        <p>Governor Bush chose to make his  public party debut yesterday at the Republican convention's biggest fund-raiser, which seemed in step with last night's convention message of ''prosperity with a purpose.'' The lunch certainly added to the party's prosperity, raking in $10 million, according to party officials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and his wife, Laura, attended; so did brother Gov. Jeb Bush of Florida and Dick Cheney. One of Mr. Bush's nephews, George P. Bush, the thinking woman's Ricky Martin, flashed his extremely white teeth and spoke heart-melting Spanish with one woman.</p>
        <p>The lunch had the feeling of any fund-raiser: rubber chicken, an earnest children's chorus (to which no one listened) and lots of schmoozing. But there was one big difference for most of the donors at the lunch, at least according to the wife of a governor who pleaded for anonymity.</p>
        <p>Safely ensconced in the ladies' room, she peered excitedly into her plastic goody bag, the donor's version of a child's birthday party bag. The contents: a notepad with a Republican National Committee logo, a T-shirt and a Kit Kat bar.</p>
        <p>''You would think for that much money, you'd at least get a bottle of  perfume,'' she complained.</p>
        <p>Prosperity, alas, has its limits.</p>
        <p>A Familiar Face Returns</p>
        <p>With his familiar mop-top and full face, he could have been Pete Rose at an old-timers' game the way fans angled for autographs and snap shots with yesterday's hero.</p>
        <p>Newt Gingrich may be out, but he's not down.</p>
        <p>He's a member of the convention's overcrowded chattering class, yakking online, on radio, on television. ''I'm back to where I was before I was speaker, walking around spreading new ideas,'' Mr. Gingrich said.</p>
        <p>The recent Gingrich idea that got the most attention was registering online (at Web sites for Macy's and Williams-Sonoma) for gifts for his coming wedding. But Mr. Gingrich said he and his soon-to-be third wife were simply doing ''what most modern couples do.''</p>
        <p>The ideas that really excite him these days are about science and technology. He's studying and writing about technology, advising corporations on strategic planning and, this week, providing commentary on Fox Television.</p>
        <p>The former speaker of the House  wasn't invited to the convention podium. First off, as he says, ''the Republican Party hardly needs to build its strength among white males.'' His brand of conservatism, even within the Republican Party, often seemed as compassionate as a nail gun. And since he used his 1996 convention speech to talk most memorably about beach volleyball, apparently none of this convention's theme nights seemed like a perfect fit.</p>
        <p>So what if he doesn't have a leading role in the convention he calls the beginning of ''chapter four of the modern conservative movement.''</p>
        <p>After all, the third chapter was entitled ''The Contract With America,'' he said with a satisfied smile.</p>
        <p>Minor League Protests</p>
        <p>Pity the protester.</p>
        <p>The crowds weren't overwhelming. The convention flowed smoothly. Philadelphians actually cheered when the police arrested them. Philadelphia, so far, doesn't compare with the protests over world trade issues in Seattle, or even in Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>''Seattle was like a 9, because they declared martial law,'' said Henry Schwab, 27, a self-described traveling activist. ''Philadelphia's like a 4. D.C. was like a 5.5.''</p>
        <p>Bush Family Values</p>
        <p>One of Governor Bush's first stops in Philadelphia on Wednesday was the Philadelphia Museum of Art for what was billed as a Hispanic welcome event. Latin music blared. But while Hispanic children were up on the stage and Hispanic supporters up front, the crowd was filled out with a sizable contingent of blond College Republicans waving ''Viva Bush'' signs.</p>
        <p>One of them, David Standness, 21, said he was part of a bunch of College Republicans who came by bus from Minnesota.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was introduced by his  Hispanic-American nephew, George P. Bush, who said, ''Are you excited about electing a president who represents the diversity of our society?''</p>
        <p>About 60 Bush family members -- all the siblings, the parents, most or all of the siblings' kids -- planned an early dinner at the Ritz Carlton. For the Bushes, national political conventions have become family reunions. One campaign aide who is staying near the family ay the Wyndham Hotel described the scene as ''very exuberant, with lots of children running up and down the hall.''</p>
        <p>''It's a lot of fun for the cousins,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Taking On the Rock</p>
        <p>It ain't easy being mean.</p>
        <p>Dwayne Johnson, a k a the Rock, introduced J. Dennis Hastert, the speaker of the House, at last night's convention session. Why?</p>
        <p>It seemed appropriate that the World Wrestling Federation's most celebrated wall of meat, Mr. Johnson, would introduce Mr. Hastert, who was once a wrestling coach.</p>
        <p>Not everyone was happy about the invitation. As the Rock was practicing his recitation on the convention floor (''Can you s-m-e-l-l what the Rock is cooking?'' he wailed into the microphone, flexing his shoulders so the seams on his white dinner jacket swelled), L. Brent Bozell, the president of the Parents Television Council, was steaming.</p>
        <p>''This will hurt the Republicans in more ways than they can possible imagine,'' Mr. Bozell said. ''Any time a Republican gives a speech about raunch or violence, the bottom-of-the-barrel stuff, people will be able to point to the Rock, and his introduction of Hastert, and they will be able to say that the Republicans sponsored and approved of and celebrated the biggest superstar of raunch and violence. How vastly stupid can they be?''</p>
        <p>On CNN, the Rock slammed back at Mr. Bozell, calling him ''an extremist who represents a radical organization.'' And he stared into the camera and chewed out Mr. Bozell. ''Grow up,'' he said. ''What we do is entertainment.''</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: PHILADELPHIA DIARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
