<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mrs. Clinton Criticizes Lazio on 'Multiple Choice' Abortion Stance</title>
    <meta content="03HILL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Planned Parenthood Federation of America</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5DB163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mrs. Clinton Criticizes Lazio on 'Multiple Choice' Abortion Stance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>OLD WESTBURY, N.Y., Aug. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton receives endorsement of Planned Parenthood and uses occasion to exhaustively criticize her Senate opponent, Representative Rick A Lazio, for his position on abortion and for what she implies is his petulant reaction to her attacks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton received the endorsement of Planned Parenthood today and used the occasion to exhaustively criticize her Senate opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio, for his position on abortion and for what she implied was his petulant reaction to her attacks.</p>
        <p>''When you say something that's accurate about someone's record, if they don't want anybody to know about it, they say it's negative,'' Mrs. Clinton told a group of several hundred people at the State University of New York here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton received the endorsement of Planned Parenthood today and used the occasion to exhaustively criticize her Senate opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio, for his position on abortion and for what she implied was his petulant reaction to her attacks.</p>
        <p>''When you say something that's accurate about someone's record, if they don't want anybody to know about it, they say it's negative,'' Mrs. Clinton told a group of several hundred people at the State University of New York here.</p>
        <p>''So for weeks now, I have said that he sided with the insurance companies and voted for the Republican patients' bill of rights instead of a patients' bill of rights that will hold H.M.O.'s accountable,'' she added. ''And I mean, my goodness, he just has gone crazy about that. He had everybody saying that that was so negative, and so mean. I don't understand it. He's either going to accept his record, or he's going to have to continue to try to run away from it and avoid accountability for it.''</p>
        <p>Last year Mr. Lazio opposed a Democratic version of a so-called patients' bill of rights that would give patients the right to sue health maintenance organizations for mistreatment. Mr. Lazio supported a Republican bill that instead would provide tax deductions to help people pay their medical premiums.</p>
        <p>The Planned Parenthood endorsement, from both the national organization and the New York state chapter, was hardly unexpected for the first lady. But Gloria Feldt, the president of the national Planned Parenthood organization, said that the group would have stayed neutral if Mrs. Clinton's former opponent, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, had remained in the race. Mr. Giuliani is a strong supporter of abortion rights.</p>
        <p>''Once Lazio got in the race, it was an easy decision,'' Ms. Feldt said.</p>
        <p>On her second day of a three-day campaign swing through the heart of Long Island, Mr. Lazio's home territory, Mrs. Clinton also said in an interview that she thought she would win at least ''parts of'' the area. ''I have no illusions about how difficult it is for a Democrat or for me to do well in the suburbs,'' she said, ''but I'm not going to concede one vote.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton said she was startled by the favorable reception she received this morning at the Hicksville station of the Long Island Rail Road, where she greeted commuters. ''You know, I've been in lots of different settings politically for a long time,'' she said. ''And when people really aren't interested in you, or really don't like you, they let it be known.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton made her remarks about Mr. Lazio during a speech on women's issues, when she said, as she has in the past, that Mr. Lazio is not pro-choice on abortion rights but ''multiple choice.'' Mr. Lazio generally supports abortion rights, but he opposes the use of government money to pay for abortions. ''I believe in choice for all women, not just some women,'' Mrs. Clinton said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton was accompanied again today by her daughter, Chelsea, who is taking a leave from Stanford University to campaign with her mother and experience the last months of her father's presidency.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
