<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH-CHENEY TICKET NOMINATED AND THE ATTACKS ON GORE BEGIN</title>
    <meta content="03CONV$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000804T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219821"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS: THE NOMINEE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE5D7163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1845" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH-CHENEY TICKET NOMINATED AND THE ATTACKS ON GORE BEGIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Aug. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican Party nominates Gov George Walker Bush for president and Dick Cheney for vice president at National Convention, Philadelphia; Cheney warns election of Vice Pres Al Gore would perpetuate what he calls Pres Clinton's misguided policies, speech; delegates hail his taunts at Democrats after three nights of sunny, even apolitical speeches; campaign showcases Cheney by breaking tradition and giving him own night to speak; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Burning to reclaim the White House after eight years on the outside, the Republican Party tonight nominated George Walker Bush for president and sent forth his running mate with the most stinging and unabashedly partisan assault of the convention.</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney, Mr. Bush's No. 2, said the election of Al Gore would perpetuate what he called the misguided policies of President Clinton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Burning to reclaim the White House after eight years on the outside, the Republican Party tonight nominated George Walker Bush for president and sent forth his running mate with the most stinging and unabashedly partisan assault of the convention.</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney, Mr. Bush's No. 2, said the election of Al Gore would perpetuate what he called the misguided policies of President Clinton.</p>
        <p>''We are all a little weary of the Clinton-Gore routine,'' Mr. Cheney said. ''But the wheel has turned.'' [Excerpts, Page A28.]</p>
        <p>Then, appropriating Mr. Gore's 1992 campaign slogan as his own, he said, ''It is time for them to go!''</p>
        <p>In the ritual roll call, the 22 votes from Mr. Cheney's home state, Wyoming, cast at 10:04 p.m. gave Mr. Bush more than the 1,034 votes needed to grasp the nomination. The hall erupted in a prolonged ovation as jubilant delegates, many of them dancing, were awash in a sea of beach balls, confetti and balloons.</p>
        <p>The delegates, who had heard three nights of sunny, even apolitical, speeches, roared in delight as Mr. Cheney directed full-throated taunts at the Democrats. But with Mr. Cheney's mild and even-toned delivery, his punch lines did not carry the same weight on television.</p>
        <p>Casting aside the high-minded oratory that had marked this convention, Mr. Cheney portrayed Mr. Gore as mean-spirited by reviving former Senator Bill Bradley's pungent dismissal of him six days before the New Hampshire primary: ''A thousand promises. A thousand attacks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, defense secretary under former President George Bush, said he was lured back into public service because of his belief in Governor Bush and his fear that Mr. Gore's election would perpetuate everything that he believed was wrong with Mr. Clinton's stewardship.</p>
        <p>Drawing a contrast with Mr. Bush's achievements as governor of Texas, Mr. Cheney contended that the Clinton administration had made no headway on Social Security, taxes or military readiness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's address capped Mr. Bush's night of triumph, which had been honed for weeks, if not months. It was a political and emotional peak for the two-term governor, one-time baseball team owner and son of a former president who did not appear on the public stage until he first won election in 1994.</p>
        <p>Just eight years ago, Republicans nominated Mr. Bush's father for a second term, only to have their president ousted by Bill Clinton. But tonight, Mr. Cheney told the 2,066 delegates that the era of Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore had been one of dashed hopes and squandered opportunities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney depicted Mr. Gore as intimately connected to an administration mired in scandal, and he sought to turn Mr. Gore's attacks on Mr. Bush's ''risky tax scheme'' back against the vice president.</p>
        <p>''In this election, they will speak endlessly of risk,'' Mr. Cheney said. ''We will speak of progress. They will make accusations. We will make proposals. They will feed fear and we will appeal to hope. They will offer more lectures and legalisms and carefully worded denials. We offer another way -- a better way -- and a stiff dose of truth.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's comments left no doubt that despite his mild-mannered demeanor, the Bush campaign intended to employ him in the somewhat traditional role of running-mate-as-attacker. In his acceptance speech four years ago as Bob Dole's No. 2, Jack F. Kemp was far more restrained; he mentioned Mr. Clinton only once, and his sharpest words were casting Democrats as ''elitist.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cheney picked up a mantle that has been carried in the past by Bob Dole and Mr. Gore himself.</p>
        <p>The speech by the vice-presidential nominee is typically delivered on the closing night of the convention -- and is usually overshadowed by the one delivered by the head of the ticket. But by giving Mr. Cheney his own night, the campaign was able to showcase Mr. Bush's running mate.</p>
        <p>And though Mr. Bush had planned the break with tradition well before Mr. Cheney was chosen, the move offered the public an opportunity to take a measure of a man who has been out of the public eye since leaving the Pentagon eight years ago after playing a crucial role in the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's speech provided delegates with yet another reason to revel in a quadrennial gathering that has been remarkably devoid of controversy, in public at least.</p>
        <p>After his defeat to Mr. Clinton, former President Bush was shunned at many Republican events. But this week, delegates expressed supreme confidence that his son was their best hope to retake the White House.</p>
        <p>For the third night in a row, the former president sat through the proceedings, logging more time there than many delegates. At the very end of the night, he smiled and sang along as Lee Greenwood appeared on stage to sing what had been Mr. Bush's campaign anthem, ''I'm Proud to Be an American.''</p>
        <p>The one somber note on what was the most festive night thus far was the health of former President Gerald R. Ford.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford, who had delighted party loyalists on Tuesday night when he appeared on the floor as part of a tribute to past Republican presidents, was admitted to a hospital here today after suffering at least one minor stroke.</p>
        <p>At the start of his speech, Mr. Cheney, who had been Mr. Ford's chief of staff at the White House, passed on his wishes for ''a quick and speedy recovery.'' After serving with Mr. Ford, Mr. Cheney was elected as a congressman from Wyoming, rising to the rank of Republican whip.</p>
        <p>While acknowledging that Mr. Cheney's speech was the most hard-edged of the convention, Mr. Bush's aides insisted that it did not violate their pledge to keep the discourse from Philadelphia largely high-minded and positive.</p>
        <p>''The secretary's speech sets a new tone,'' said Ari Fleischer, a spokesman for Mr. Bush. ''It draws contrasts with Vice President Gore, but far more respectfully than typical politicians.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush had said to expect some barbs aimed at Mr. Gore. Yet some passages in Mr. Cheney's speech veered closely to the personal, especially those that linked Mr. Gore to Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''As the man from Hope goes home to New York,'' Mr. Cheney said, ''Mr. Gore will try to separate himself from his leader's shadow, but somehow we will never see one without thinking of the other.''</p>
        <p>Then he added, ''Does anyone, Republican or Democrat, seriously believe that under Mr. Gore the next four years would be any different from the last eight?''</p>
        <p>Several delegates welcomed Mr. Cheney's speech as crucial to counter the Democrats. ''After putting up with the president and his lies for eight years, this was a breath of fresh air,'' said John Enriquez, a delegate from California.</p>
        <p>Carolyn Shinke, a delegate from Dayton, Ohio, put it this way: ''Mr. Cheney had to say the things that had to be said tonight. We all know the details, and it is not easy to listen to. But the record had to be set straight at this convention; this aggressive message had to come out.''</p>
        <p>In the eight days since Mr. Bush named him as his running mate, Mr. Cheney has found himself largely on the defensive, fighting off attacks by Democrats that his voting record was too conservative for most voters. They concentrated on his opposition to the Head Start preschool education program and his votes against a ban on armor-piercing bullets.</p>
        <p>Yet in his speech tonight, Mr. Cheney did not even allude to the controversy -- or his own ideology -- and instead took the opportunity to say glowing things about his former boss, then-President Bush, and about the president's son.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush -- who arrived in Philadelphia today after a six-day tour through six states carried by Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore in 1992 and 1996 -- took to the sprawling stage at the convention hall this afternoon to run through his acceptance address for Thursday night.</p>
        <p>Expressing, perhaps, Mr. Bush's disdain of long-winded addresses -- and perhaps his own self-assuredness -- his aides said that his acceptance speech might well be the shortest in years.</p>
        <p>Karen Hughes, the campaign's communications director, told reporters that, allowing for applause, Mr. Bush's speech would last roughly 38 minutes. In contrast, acceptance speeches by President Bush in 1992 and Bob Dole in 1996 each ran 57 minutes.</p>
        <p>Beyond the effort tonight for Mr. Cheney to extol Mr. Bush's virtues, the program was intended to highlight the Republican Party's signature economic issue: tax cuts.</p>
        <p>As throughout the convention, the focus was on portraying the party not as one of plutocrats -- as Democrats have long sought to label it -- but as a party of working people.</p>
        <p>To drive home the point, speakers included a Hispanic small-business owner, Hector Barreto, who spoke of how Mr. Bush would help entrepreneurs by cutting the burden of taxation and regulation, and Kim Jennings, a single mother, who discussed how the tax plan would help her edge toward the middle class.</p>
        <p>Democratic officials countered that the Republicans were trying to obscure the fact that Mr. Bush's tax-cut proposals would disproportionately benefit the wealthy.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Gore's aides pressed their case that the Republican tax cuts passed this year by Congress and those proposed by Mr. Bush would both endanger the nation's newfound fiscal health and the economy's long-term prospects.</p>
        <p>The very theme of the Republicans' evening, ''prosperity with a purpose,'' contained a tacit acknowledgment that the economy is hardy, a fact that could ultimately be expected to help Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bush arrived at the airport here this morning, he received a red-carpet welcome, replete with a fife and drum corps and a replica of the Liberty Bell, which he gonged. Then he was off to the Philadelphia Museum of Art for what was billed as a Hispanic welcome event.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was introduced by his Hispanic-American nephew, George P. Bush, who asked the crowd, ''Are you excited about electing a president who represents the diversity of our society?''</p>
        <p>The governor and his wife, Laura, then appeared with Senator John McCain and his wife, Cindy. Mr. Bush praised his once-bitter foe -- who had paid tribute to him at the convention on Tuesday -- as a ''living example of duty, honor and country.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''Senator, I can't wait to campaign with you all across our country.''</p>
        <p>TV Coverage Today</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush will deliver his acceptance speech to the Republican National Convention tonight at 10. It will carried live on ABC, CBS, CNN, C-Span, Fox News Channel, MSNBC, NBC and PBS.</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS: THE NOMINEE  Correction:  August 4, 2000, Friday  A chart yesterday tracing the decline in television viewing of Republican conventions since 1960 referred incompletely to the networks that were excluded from the ratings for this week. Monday's ratings did not reflect CBS and NBC, which both showed convention coverage as a part of regular programs. Tuesday's ratings did not include CBS. PBS, which does not report ratings overnight, was not the only network excluded from the ratings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 4, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>A chart yesterday tracing the decline in television viewing of Republican conventions since 1960 referred incompletely to the networks that were excluded from the ratings for this week. Monday's ratings did not reflect CBS and NBC, which both showed convention coverage as a part of regular programs. Tuesday's ratings did not include CBS. PBS, which does not report ratings overnight, was not the only network excluded from the ratings.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
