<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y03BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1219703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000803T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DE163CF930A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeanne Moore</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>CROATIA: MISSION TO WASHINGTON  The new, democratic leaders of Croatia have been granted the official visit to Washington that the late president, Franjo Tudjman, was never allowed. President Stipe Mesic and Prime Minister Ivica Racan, opposition leaders elected this year, arrive on Monday for meetings with President Clinton and other administration officials. They have moved Croatia away from Mr. Tudjman's strident nationalism and closer to Western aims in the Balkans, but face huge fiscal problems and unemployment.</p>
        <p>Steven Erlanger (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: GOOD NEWS FOR PETS  Fifteen rabies-free islands -- including Australia, Japan and Hawaii -- will be added to the ''pet passport'' program that allows cats and dogs to enter Britain without being quarantined for six months. The program got under way in February, beginning with 22 rabies-free European countries. Each passport certifies the pet has a microchip implant verifying its identity and that it has been vaccinated and tested. Other regions will be considered for inclusion in the program in the near future, including the continental United States.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>CROATIA: MISSION TO WASHINGTON  The new, democratic leaders of Croatia have been granted the official visit to Washington that the late president, Franjo Tudjman, was never allowed. President Stipe Mesic and Prime Minister Ivica Racan, opposition leaders elected this year, arrive on Monday for meetings with President Clinton and other administration officials. They have moved Croatia away from Mr. Tudjman's strident nationalism and closer to Western aims in the Balkans, but face huge fiscal problems and unemployment.</p>
        <p>Steven Erlanger (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: GOOD NEWS FOR PETS  Fifteen rabies-free islands -- including Australia, Japan and Hawaii -- will be added to the ''pet passport'' program that allows cats and dogs to enter Britain without being quarantined for six months. The program got under way in February, beginning with 22 rabies-free European countries. Each passport certifies the pet has a microchip implant verifying its identity and that it has been vaccinated and tested. Other regions will be considered for inclusion in the program in the near future, including the continental United States.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>POLAND: WALESA UNDER SCRUTINY  Lech Walesa, founder  of the Solidarity movement that toppled Polish Communism, was in court for the second time in a week fighting allegations by a political opponent that he lied about past ties with the secret police. Mr. Walesa is among a dozen contenders in presidential elections who, under a new law, must file statements disclosing whether they collaborated with the Communist-era police. Anyone caught lying can be barred from running. Mr. Walesa has repeatedly denied the allegations.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>FRANCE: CONCORDE INQUIRY  Transport Minister Claude Gayssot called a meeting for today to update all parties involved in examining last week's Concorde crash on progress of the investigation and to look at new safety measures that might enable Air France Concorde flights to resume. French Concordes have been grounded since the July 25 crash, which killed 113 people, but British flights have continued.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>VENEZUELA: PROTESTS EASE  Disturbances over disputed regional election results died down despite continued vote-rigging allegations by candidates opposed to President Hugo Chavez. Mr. Chavez, who won re-election in Sunday's vote, sent troops to quell protests after his alliance won governorship races in most of the country's states. But there was no sign of a repetition of the violent clashes between pro- and anti-Chavez groups that left one person dead and nine injured on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAN: REBEL CLASHES  Two Iranian soldiers were killed in clashes with the outlawed opposition People's Mujahedeen, which also left several rebels dead and wounded, the official IRNA news agency said. It said the Iraq-based rebels mounted a mortar attack along the region of Dehloran bordering Iraq and tried to send fighters into Iranian territory.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>CHINA: U.S. PORT CALL  A United States Navy cruiser  arrived in Qingdao for the first port call by an American warship in China since NATO bombed the Chinese Embassy in Yugoslavia last year. The visit by the cruiser Chancellorsville is part of a gradual revival of military ties, which has included a visit to Beijing last month by William S. Cohen, the U.S. defense secretary.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>HONG KONG: MIGRANT PROTEST  Angry migrants from mainland China set a fire inside Hong Kong's immigration headquarters after being refused papers that would have allowed them to remain in the former British colony. Forty-six people were injured in the blaze, which erupted after the migrants doused the 13th floor with a flammable liquid. The right of mainland Chinese to live in Hong Kong has been a volatile issue since Beijing overturned a local court ruling that granted residency to some migrants.</p>
        <p>Mark Landler (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>NIGERIA: HOSTAGE DEAL  Royal Dutch/Shell officials said that armed youths agreed to free the 165 hostages they had been holding on two oil rigs since Monday. The oil company said it would meet with representatives of the youths on Aug. 15 to discuss their demands, which included jobs.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>NIGERIA: ISLAMIC LAW WIDENS  A sixth northern state, Jigawa, has decided to introduce strict Islamic law later this year. The move to extend Shariah has divided the mostly Muslim north from the strongly Christian areas in central Nigeria, and created political problems for President Olusegun Obasanjo, a Christian.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>BURUNDI: CAMPS SHUT  Authorities have finished dismantling 30 ''regroupment camps'' into which 350,000 civilians were moved last year, according to the governor of Bujumbura Rural Province. Older camps in other parts of the country housing more than half a million people displaced by Burundi's seven-year-old civil war were not included in the operation. The government justified the camps by saying they would allow the military to better deal with the rebels, but international aid agencies said their aim was to cut off villagers from the rebels.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>ERITREA, SUDAN: UNEASY BORDER  Eritrea's defense minister moved to calm tensions with Sudan during a visit to Khartoum, dismissing claims that Eritrean troops were massing at their common border. Relations between the countries have been tense in recent months after accusations by officials in eastern Sudan that Eritrea was sending troops to the border in preparation for an attack.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
