<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Journal; Tomorrow Is Another Day</title>
    <meta content="15RICH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rich, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Frank Rich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4DA143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Journal; Tomorrow Is Another Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rich, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Ga.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Rich Op-Ed column says that if Gov George W Bush's 'compassionate conservatism' is more than a campaign slogan, it must reside in someone like Dylan Glenn, a black Republican and unabashed Bush supporter, who is challenging Rep Sanford Bishop, a black Democrat, in Georgia's Second Congressional District (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Wolfe set some of his last novel near here but even he couldn't make this scene up:</p>
        <p>In the packed, sweltering living room of the tiny house that serves as the Dylan Glenn for Congress headquarters, a Louis Farrakhan acolyte is brandishing The Final Call, the Nation of Islam newspaper, and ranting about a Washington conspiracy to rob Georgia's peanut farmers. Listening to him are a couple of dozen angry and weather-beaten black farmers, lifelong Democrats, as well as Mr. Glenn, who wants their vote. Looking down on them all is a regal poster-size photograph of a starchy Barbara Bush, replete with pearls -- but it's not there as a gag. Mr. Glenn is a 31-year-old black Republican, an unabashed George W. Bush cheerleader, who believes he can be elected to Congress by a white-majority district that has never sent any Republican to Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Wolfe set some of his last novel near here but even he couldn't make this scene up:</p>
        <p>In the packed, sweltering living room of the tiny house that serves as the Dylan Glenn for Congress headquarters, a Louis Farrakhan acolyte is brandishing The Final Call, the Nation of Islam newspaper, and ranting about a Washington conspiracy to rob Georgia's peanut farmers. Listening to him are a couple of dozen angry and weather-beaten black farmers, lifelong Democrats, as well as Mr. Glenn, who wants their vote. Looking down on them all is a regal poster-size photograph of a starchy Barbara Bush, replete with pearls -- but it's not there as a gag. Mr. Glenn is a 31-year-old black Republican, an unabashed George W. Bush cheerleader, who believes he can be elected to Congress by a white-majority district that has never sent any Republican to Washington.</p>
        <p>''That's the first Black Muslim I've ever seen in southwest Georgia,'' the candidate muses after the meeting, in which he seems to win over his audience, Muslim included, just as I'd seen him win over the all-white staff of a small local telecom business a few hours earlier. Such cross-cultural incongruities abound in Mr. Glenn's race: his campaign coordinator, Lizanne Clay, is a white Jewish Democrat gung-ho for Al Gore. The district itself, Georgia's Second, is one big anomaly. Because Mr. Glenn's opponent, the Democratic Congressman Sanford Bishop, is also black, this is that rare white-majority district in the South, let alone the country, that offers no white choice in its House race. ''The race card is more or less removed from the table,'' says Mr. Glenn.</p>
        <p>The district is also unusual in having missed out entirely on the New Economy that has showered spectacular growth on Atlanta, 150 miles and a world away. Though Georgia's Second encompasses some of the South's most spectacular old hunting plantations -- the prototypes for the fictional spread owned by the hero of Mr. Wolfe's ''A Man in Full'' -- it is among the nation's poorest precincts. The poverty level in some of its 31 counties is three times the national average, and unemployment in Albany, the largest town (pop. 80,000), nears 8 percent. Functional illiteracy levels approach 40 percent in some counties -- giving the local chain outlet's midnight party for Harry Potter a special poignancy. While Jimmy Carter may still live in Plains, young people flee faster than such past native sons as Ray Charles and Jackie Robinson.</p>
        <p>Dusty, deserted storefronts are common; billboards heralding dot-coms are absent. Ms. Clay, a fourth-generation ''Albanian,'' doubts her own daughter will return after college. ''It's like a third world country down here,'' she says.</p>
        <p>So what's an ambitious young black middle-class Republican doing in a place like this?</p>
        <p>I first met Dylan Glenn a few months ago and was curious to watch him for a simple reason: If Governor Bush's ''compassionate conservatism'' is more than a campaign slogan, it must reside in someone like Mr. Glenn, a smart candidate blessed with charisma and a sense of humor who is taking on a seemingly quixotic political mission. No black Republican has ever defeated a black Democrat in a modern Congressional race; his opponent is a formidable incumbent whom Mr. Glenn himself regards as ''a decent man.'' As Mr. Glenn's strategist, Ron Jensen, explains, Mr. Glenn can win only by holding on to the all-white G.O.P. base (with no defections from any racists who might want to abstain altogether), peeling off some conservative white Democrats and, most crucially, winning some 15 percent of the heretofore monolithically black Democratic vote.</p>
        <p>If the potential crossover black Democrats I met are any indication, they won't leap easily. One such Glenn enthusiast, a 71-year-old county commissioner and 60's civil-rights veteran named James Mays, regards both George W. Bush and his father as among ''the most evil people in the world.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Glenn, who was a young aide in President Bush's White House, hammers in the George W. message -- the classic Republican mantra of ''growth, lower taxes, opportunity, individual responsibility, jobs.'' In essence, he sands down any ideology beyond a faith in free enterprise. The son of educators, he presents himself as an educational reformer and as an energetic, well-connected rainmaker more likely than Mr. Bishop to attract new businesses to an area in desperate need. Like the Texas governor in his address before the N.A.A.C.P. this week, Mr. Glenn doesn't pretend that his party has a distinguished record with minorities. ''There's a perception that the Republican Party is intolerant -- against immigrants, gays, blacks,'' he says, ''and we play into that.''</p>
        <p>To put it mildly. In primary season, Mr. Bush and John McCain both lacked the courage to take on South Carolina's Confederate flag. Last month Colin Powell, who is a Glenn contributor, went on Fox to say that the G.O.P. is ''certainly not seen as the black guy's party'' and to dissent strongly from its opposition to affirmative action. This week the Bush campaign made light of a Washington Post reporter who dared bring up the hard-line white supremacist past of its ally Strom Thurmond. Meanwhile, even as Mr. Bush appeared before the N.A.A.C.P., the news media feasted on a 1996 photo of a Republican governor, Christine Todd Whitman, broadly grinning while frisking a black man. Whatever Governor Whitman's intentions, the image was a bizarre echo of antebellum porn.</p>
        <p>Unlike the white compassionate conservatives in his party, Mr. Glenn can speak with some moral authority. He is a sharecropper's grandson and the great-grandson of emancipated slaves. When pressed, he can cite instances of experiencing discrimination, and he recalls being the sole black person at a White House meeting a decade ago where he had to speak up to challenge other Bush ites' derisive views of welfare recipients.</p>
        <p>In between campaign stops that ranged from a diesel-scented drag strip populated equally by blacks and whites to a watermelon festival parade in Cordele (''Watermelon Capital of the World''), I asked Mr. Glenn if the latent, tentative G.O.P. embrace of minorities is more spin than action, more election-year packaging than substance. He unsurprisingly asserted that Governor Bush is ''100 percent sincere'' and is intent on moving beyond the ''outreach programs and window dressing'' that have often constituted the G.O.P.'s attempt to woo minorities. ''I know the party isn't seen as motivated by the right reasons,'' he adds. ''It's seen as the party of the rich, white country club and doesn't have a lot of credibility.'' He argues that if he can bring economic relief to those left behind in Clinton-era prosperity he can help turn the page. As the first black Republican elected to Congress from a Confederate state since 1901, he would certainly be a highly watched test case of whether there can be results to back up his party's compassionate rhetoric.</p>
        <p>Whether Mr. Glenn wins or not, there's no doubt he is on the edge of a generational shift. The Albany area was the site of the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'s biggest, and legendary, defeat on the road to Montgomery. It's where a sheriff told the New York Times reporter Claude Sitton, in a famous 1962 front-page story, ''We want our colored people to go on living like they have for the last hundred years.'' But while such events may have helped forge Mr. Glenn's opponent -- who, as Morehouse College student president, sang at King's funeral in 1968 -- they happened before Mr. Glenn was born. Now they are history: the Albany Movement is documented in a new museum at the old Mount Zion Baptist Church, once the site of overflow civil-rights rallies led by the Freedom Singers but today a quiet refuge in a somnolent town segregated in its entirety from the American boom.</p>
        <p>''My generation and younger didn't live through the civil-rights movement,'' says Mr. Glenn. ''We know and understand it and respect what it did, but we want to go on to the next step.'' If the Republican Party is really to be a credible part of that next step, it will not be enough for its presidential candidate to pose incessantly with black schoolchildren and boast about his ''heart.'' It will need someone like Dylan Glenn to make good on his promise to lift up both black and white Americans in a patch of the country as ripe for change as this.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
