<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Takeover Of Reliance Falls Through</title>
    <meta content="Y15SAUL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reliance Group Holdings Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Leucadia National Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E3DF143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Takeover Of Reliance Falls Through</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Planned takeover of Saul Steinberg's insurance venture, Reliance Group Holdings, collapses amid worries that Reliance may be unable to pay debts which come due in August; Leucadia National, which agreed to purchase Reliance for $295 million in stock, is unwilling to proceed; Reliance's financial condition continues to deteriorate (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A planned takeover of Saul Steinberg's Reliance Group Holdings collapsed yesterday amid worries that Reliance may be unable to pay debts that come due next month.</p>
        <p>Leucadia National, which had agreed in May to buy Reliance for $295 million in stock, said it was unwilling to proceed with the transaction, but left open the possibility that it might reach another deal with the struggling insurance company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A planned takeover of Saul Steinberg's Reliance Group Holdings collapsed yesterday amid worries that Reliance may be unable to pay debts that come due next month.</p>
        <p>Leucadia National, which had agreed in May to buy Reliance for $295 million in stock, said it was unwilling to proceed with the transaction, but left open the possibility that it might reach another deal with the struggling insurance company.</p>
        <p>The Leucadia deal had valued Reliance shares at $2.55 each, but the stock has fallen well below that price as Reliance's financial condition has continued to deteriorate. Yesterday, the shares fell 6.25 cents, to 50 cents. Reliance bonds that are due to mature in November were quoted at 30 cents on the dollar.</p>
        <p>Reliance was the centerpiece of Mr. Steinberg's empire, which he took over in a daring corporate raid in 1968 when he was 29 years old. He used it in a failed attempt to take over Chemical Bank, a New York giant, the next year, and in 1984 made $60 million in a failed effort to buy Walt Disney.</p>
        <p>As an insurance company, Reliance was moderately successful, but it suffered major losses in workers compensation insurance in recent years and began to decline.</p>
        <p>In the last month, as insurance rating agencies cut Reliance's rating to very low levels, Reliance has had to sell some subsidiaries whose products, like insurance for corporate directors and officers, can be sold only by companies with relatively high ratings.</p>
        <p>''The company is in a fire sale right now,'' said Matthew Coyle, a director of insurance ratings for Standard &amp; Poor's. ''It has to sell key businesses or lose them.''</p>
        <p>While the remaining insurance subsidiaries do not appear to be in financial distress, most of the company's debt is at the holding company level, including nearly $240 million of bank debt that matures in August and $290 million of bonds maturing in November.</p>
        <p>S.&amp; P. cited ''increasing concerns that Reliance will fail in its efforts to refinance'' those debts as it lowered its rating of the company's bonds to CCC, the lowest rating the agency has for bonds that are not in default. It also lowered its rating of the insurance companies' ability to pay to B, a weak level.</p>
        <p>Leucadia, whose shares rose 31.25 cents, to $24.50 yesterday, said it was continuing to talk to Reliance and would not say what had led it to back away from the previously agreed transaction. Along with property and casualty insurance, Leucadia has a wide range of businesses and is known for snapping up undervalued companies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steinberg owned 29 million shares of Reliance at last report, but most of them were pledged to secure debts from three financial institutions, which are not fully covered at the stock's current price. Some other shares have been sold to meet margin calls. Reliance shares peaked at $19.8125 in the summer of 1998 and traded above $6 as recently as February.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steinberg has also sold other assets, including shares in other companies and his Park Avenue apartment, which fetched more than $30 million, and his antiques collection, which brought $12.5 million in a Sotheby's auction in May.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steinberg got his start in 1961, when he was 22 and just out of the University of Pennsylvania. He identified opportunities in computer leasing, a business that was in its infancy. I.B.M., which made the computers, was not interested in long-term leases, but there was a demand for them. He started Leasco, which grew rapidly.</p>
        <p>The company went public in 1965 and quickly became a hot stock as reported profits grew rapidly. There was criticism that the profit growth reflected aggressive accounting, but the criticism was largely ignored, and Leasco stock provided Mr. Steinberg with the currency to take over Reliance, an old-line company that had assets worth more than Wall Street realized.</p>
        <p>Through the years, Mr. Steinberg became known for a lavish life and for an ability to sniff out value. The companies he raided often were undervalued, but he generally was unable to make significant acquisitions.</p>
        <p>Moreover, as an operating executive, he was less successful. He took Reliance private in 1982, when stocks were cheap, and sold shares in it to the public again in 1986. Those shares were issued at $10 each, or about 20 times their current market price.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
