<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MSG Files Suit to Block Yankees' Network Plans</title>
    <meta content="15MSGG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yankeenets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trans World International</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Msg Network</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Madison Square Garden</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D8143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MSG Files Suit to Block Yankees' Network Plans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Madison Square Garden sues New York Yankees in Manhattan Supreme Court, charging that team's plan to form new network, created by YankeeNets and Trans World International, violates MSG Network's right to match outside offers to carry team's game after this season when contract expires (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Madison Square Garden sued the Yankees in Manhattan Supreme Court yesterday, charging that the team's plan to form a new network violates the MSG Network's right to match outside offers to carry the team's games after this season.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit creates a massive rift between the Yankees and the MSG Network, which agreed in 1988 to pay $486 million for 12 years to carry Yankee games, the largest local television rights deal in sports history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Madison Square Garden sued the Yankees in Manhattan Supreme Court yesterday, charging that the team's plan to form a new network violates the MSG Network's right to match outside offers to carry the team's games after this season.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit creates a massive rift between the Yankees and the MSG Network, which agreed in 1988 to pay $486 million for 12 years to carry Yankee games, the largest local television rights deal in sports history.</p>
        <p>The relationship has been symbiotic. MSG's cash has fueled the Yankees' payroll, the highest in Major League Baseball. Yankee games helped propel MSG's 1999 revenues to $219 million, from $39.6 million in 1988.</p>
        <p>But the end of the Yankees' deal with MSG has ignited speculation that the network may lose the team's games and has created the prospect of MSG competing in the spring and summer against a Yankee-anchored network.</p>
        <p>But in its filing, the Garden said it could not match the outside Yankee offer, a network formed by the YankeeNets, the parent of the Yankees, and Trans World International, the television arm of the International Management Group.</p>
        <p>''The so-called 'offer' is a sham,'' the Garden charged, ''and is designed to prevent MSG from availing itself of its right of last refusal -- a right MSG bargained for carefully and paid for handsomely.''</p>
        <p>Howard Rubenstein, a spokesman for the YankeeNets, said: ''The YankeeNets carefully followed all the terms and conditions of the agreement. The plaintiffs are way off base.''</p>
        <p>Barry Watkins, a spokesman for the Garden, refused to comment.</p>
        <p>The YankeeNets informed the Garden on July 5 that it was forming the New York Sports Network, a 10-year partnership with T.W.I., which would own 5 percent of the venture and produce all Yankee games and, eventually, Nets and Devils games. It would also contribute programming from its vast archives.</p>
        <p>Newco would be a separate company, producing games and selling advertising and sponsorships for sports and other entertainment programming.</p>
        <p>The Yankees would receive $65 million in 2001, with 7 percent increases each year, which would amount to $119.5 million in the 10th season.</p>
        <p>The Nets would be paid $7 million a year, with 7 percent annual increases. The financial terms of a Devils television deal were not outlined.</p>
        <p>In its court papers, the Garden says that the Yankees-T.W.I. venture is unmatchable because it contemplates a significantly different commitment than simply buying the rights to carry games on MSG.</p>
        <p>The Garden said the Newco offer was not an offer to transfer the rights to exploit Yankee games on televisions, which such traditional contracts grant.</p>
        <p>Rather, the Garden charged, ''T.W.I. would merely become a vendor of television production services with a small equity interest in a new company.''</p>
        <p>But the Garden alleged yesterday that the Yankees ''concocted an 'offer' designed to defeat MSG's right of last refusal, in a flagrant breach of the Yankees Partnership's obligations to MSG.''</p>
        <p>The Garden said numerous other terms of the Newco deal circumvent what it believes is a valid offer it would try to match, including paying the Yankees 25 percent of the net income or equity of any cable sports networks it may operate outside the New York area. The Garden called that term ''bad faith.''</p>
        <p>YankeeNets officials have in recent months described their own network as the ultimate exploitation of its teams' television rights and true market value, especially those of the Yankees.</p>
        <p>Cablevision, the principal owner of the MSG Network, was one of the companies talking to the YankeeNets about becoming a partner in a new network. Time Warner was also mentioned.</p>
        <p>Cablevision is believed to have discussed a deal that bore some similarities to the one the YankeesNets have with T.W.I. One industry report said that Cablevision was willing to convert one of its existing networks to the YankeeNets' venture.</p>
        <p>In its lawsuit, the Garden seeks a judgment that the Yankees-T.W.I. deal is not a valid offer, and to enjoin the Yankees from consummating the agreement.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
