<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Manners Still Matter</title>
    <meta content="15PYLE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hats and Caps</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kansas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pyle, George B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs, Etiquette and Manners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7DF143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Manners Still Matter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By George B. Pyle</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pyle, George B</byline>
      <dateline>SALINA, Kan.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by George B Pyle, editorial page editor of Salina Journal, says Kansas and rest of nation's heartland have not been infected with the rudeness now rampant in the country because they do not adhere to a strict code of etiquette; says the only two times people there have been rude to him is when they have admonished him for wearing a hat indoors (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From complaints about impolite cell-phone users to gripes over bad service at restaurants, it seems that everyone's gotten a bit prickly over everyone else's manners -- or lack thereof. This perception that civility is on the decline has taken hold not only in places often associated with rudeness, like busy Eastern cities, but also in the supposedly more mannerly cultures of the South and Midwest.</p>
        <p>I can't comment on conditions elsewhere, but I would argue that this so-called rash of incivility has not pervaded the country completely. Civility in Kansas and the rest of the heartland, for example, remains intact. It has endured because it comes not so much from any strict code of etiquette but from a comfortable lack thereof.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From complaints about impolite cell-phone users to gripes over bad service at restaurants, it seems that everyone's gotten a bit prickly over everyone else's manners -- or lack thereof. This perception that civility is on the decline has taken hold not only in places often associated with rudeness, like busy Eastern cities, but also in the supposedly more mannerly cultures of the South and Midwest.</p>
        <p>I can't comment on conditions elsewhere, but I would argue that this so-called rash of incivility has not pervaded the country completely. Civility in Kansas and the rest of the heartland, for example, remains intact. It has endured because it comes not so much from any strict code of etiquette but from a comfortable lack thereof.</p>
        <p>In my 43 years living in the heartland, I can think of only two instances in which I was the victim of what I consider overt rudeness. Both were perpetrated by people who were trying to enforce their own brand of etiquette. Both ran against the relaxed, live-and-let-live attitude that to me has always seemed the gentle core of Plains culture.</p>
        <p>Both involved my hat.</p>
        <p>In third grade, in my hometown of McCook, Neb., I wore my Cub Scout uniform, cap and all, to school. I was pretty proud of it. But the principal had only one thing to say: ''Do Cub Scouts wear their hats in the house?''</p>
        <p>It was the only sentence I remember her speaking to me in the five years I attended that school. I took the hat off, stifling the urge to tell her we were not in a house.</p>
        <p>The second time was in 1984. I was having an early dinner in a bookstore-coffee shop in the artsy Westport neighborhood of Kansas City, Mo. It was a warm day, and I was wearing a white Panama hat. I thought it looked quite jaunty.</p>
        <p>A pair of older women rose to leave from a nearby table. As they passed me, one leaned over and said: ''I must say, I remember a day when a gentleman would never wear his hat inside a building.''</p>
        <p>I left it on, stifling the urge to tell her she was no lady for insulting a perfect stranger.</p>
        <p>Heartland men like John Wayne (from Winterset, Iowa) and Henry Fonda (from Omaha) would be more likely to have said something like, ''Well, you do as you please -- just don't get in my way,'' than tell someone that what he or she was doing was impolite -- even if they generally took their hats off to say it.</p>
        <p>Out here in the Plains, we don't get in each other's way much. As long as that standard is met, friction stays at a minimum. Road rage is not the rage here -- we don't have to fight for parking spaces and spend as much time on crowded freeways as other Americans do.</p>
        <p>So here's the Kansas solution to those who are worried about a decline in civility: Don't worry so much. It only makes you cranky.</p>
        <p>George B. Pyle is the editorial page editor of the Salina Journal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">George B. Pyle is the editorial page editor of the Salina Journal.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
