<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: A Dot-Com Revolution in China; Venture Capital Backs Talented Young Entrepreneurs</title>
    <meta content="Y15NET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Startup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Venture Capital</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E1DF143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: A Dot-Com Revolution in China; Venture Capital Backs Talented Young Entrepreneurs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hundreds of millions of American investment dollars fatten bank accounts of China's Internet entrepeneurs, causing singular vibrancy in fledgling, struggling Chinese private sector; venture capitalists say that $1 billion more hovers eagerly overhead, waiting to pounce onto China's rapidly growing Internet industry; photos; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>China's economy is throwing millions of people out of work each year, but an unemployed Internet journalist, Shao Ying, says she can get a job whenever she wants among the hundreds of Internet companies opening offices here.</p>
        <p>Her eyes widened when asked how she could be certain to find one that pays if so few Chinese Internet companies have any revenue. The answer, to her, is as obvious as the mole on Mao Zedong's chin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>China's economy is throwing millions of people out of work each year, but an unemployed Internet journalist, Shao Ying, says she can get a job whenever she wants among the hundreds of Internet companies opening offices here.</p>
        <p>Her eyes widened when asked how she could be certain to find one that pays if so few Chinese Internet companies have any revenue. The answer, to her, is as obvious as the mole on Mao Zedong's chin.</p>
        <p>''America,'' she replies. ''Didn't you know?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Shao is right: hundreds of millions of American investment dollars have fattened the bank accounts of China's young Internet entrepreneurs over the last year, making dot-com companies the most vibrant part of the country's fledgling but still struggling private sector. And despite the high-technology stock slump in the United States, as much as $1 billion more in venture capital, most of it from America, is hovering overhead waiting to dive into China's fast-developing Internet industry, venture capitalists say.</p>
        <p>The torrent of cash into private hands is without parallel here under Communist Party rule. It also is particularly conspicuous given the enormous financing difficulties that many budding Chinese entrepreneurs confront in a society that still officially discourages real capitalism.</p>
        <p>The money also could quickly vanish or move elsewhere if foreign venture capitalists decide China is not worth the risk, leaving people like Ms. Shao stranded.</p>
        <p>But if the money keeps coming, the impact could be as big as the breakup of the country's Maoist communes 20 years ago. A capital-backed private sector may be the economy's best hope for survival as hundreds of millions of workers spill from sinking state-owned enterprises, and foreign competitors eagerly await China's market opening after it joins the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>For the first time since a fledgling private sector reappeared in the late 1970's, a group of private businesses here are accumulating capital.</p>
        <p>''China is seeing a core entrepreneurship being established that is different from the old one, which never really grew because it didn't have access to capital,'' says Dong Tao, an economist with Credit Suisse First Boston in Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>The new entrepreneurs, many with American educations or American companies on their resumes, are outrunning China's ideologically hobbled bureaucracy not only because of their youth but because they are supported by a powerful constituency abroad: men and women often times not much older who represent millions of dollars in investment capital and are not intimidated by China's authoritarian government or its byzantine rules.</p>
        <p>On a sultry night in June, more than 200 young men and women crowded into a fashionable Shanghai restaurant, wearing colored stickers on their lapels identifying them as either someone looking for money (red) or someone with money to give (green). Rapid-fire volleys of industry jargon were part of conversations around the room. One Chinese man told a Silicon Valley banker that his Web site would handle transactions next year worth 1 billion yuan, about $120 million.</p>
        <p>''Who here would like Goldman, Sachs to underwrite their Nasdaq I.P.O.?,'' a young man in a white-collared blue shirt shouted from atop a chair in an effort to get the crowd's attention for the evening's speaker from the American investment bank.</p>
        <p>Like their counterparts in the United States, men and women in their 20's have emerged from such evenings to find themselves deploying millions of dollars, in some cases tens of millions of dollars, almost overnight.</p>
        <p>The money is not yet sinking very deeply into China's economy. Buses and bus stops in most major cities have been taken over by dot-com advertising. And interior design firms are doing a booming business. At the Internet auctioneer Eachnet.com's sleek offices in a new Shanghai bank building, visitors are greeted by an orange-tiled wall bearing the company's logo -- recently redesigned by a Japanese firm. Against the glass wall of the chief operating officer's office lean presentations from a handful of interior design companies showing various high-tech versions of the company's new offices soon to be built in another building a few doors away.</p>
        <p>But as China's old Marxists know, capital is power and if the country's young Internet entrepreneurs can hang onto their assets and make them grow, they could emerge as a potent force shaping the country's economic -- and political -- future.</p>
        <p>So far, the big capital formation is limited mostly to Internet companies, though China is exploring ways to make it easier for a business's original investors to cash out when it goes public. China's regulators are considering a second board on the country's stock exchanges that might allow share sales by companies before they are profitable, for example. And Chinese start-ups can, in theory, list their shares on a second board already operating in Hong Kong. Several domestic venture capital funds have even appeared, though they are mostly government controlled.</p>
        <p>If that model takes hold, it could fundamentally alter economic life in China, where, despite 20 years of changes that have made the economy more flexible and market-driven, the ever-present state still decides how resources are allocated.</p>
        <p>''Many good mechanisms have been introduced to China, such as venture capital and stock options, which will help trigger the restructuring of industries throughout the country,'' says Wang Zhidong, chief executive of Sina.com, one of the few  mainland Chinese Internet companies to list shares on Nasdaq so far. He says the success of those private businesses will also influence the country's attitude toward its educated youth, who remain suspect in the eyes of many Chinese officials.</p>
        <p>But China's notoriously slow government must act quickly or the dot-com phenomenon might disappear as quickly as it came without having made much of an impression on the country's economic landscape. Venture capitalists, despairing of any easy exit through which to sell their investments, may move on, leaving China's fledgling Internet industry gasping for cash. The Ministry of Information Industries already estimates that most of the country's 16,000 Web sites will be gone by year-end for lack of financing.</p>
        <p>For now, few of China's Internet companies are seriously considering raising capital at home. Current listing requirements make that impossible and the approval to go public is a political favor that private companies rarely win.</p>
        <p>And most of the foreign investment in China's Internet sector remains technically illegal under rules barring foreign ownership of value-added telecommunications services. In June, China's stock market regulators issued a new rule requiring companies that want to list abroad to first submit to Beijing documents detailing their ownership structure and showing that the structure adheres to Chinese law.</p>
        <p>Even Sina.com had to strip its primary asset -- the mainland China Sina.com Web site -- from its Cayman Islands shell company to get Beijing's approval to list on Nasdaq. Investors in the United States stock own a stake in the shell and its ancillary Chinese-language Web sites in Hong Kong, Taiwan and North America, but not in the Chinese operations.</p>
        <p>Rivals angling for a Nasdaq listing are having to do the same, but acknowledge that China's changing rules could make even the restructured operations illegal. Sohu.com, one of the China's most popular Internet portals, stated in a recent Securities and Exchange Commission filing that ''relevant P.R.C. authorities could, at any time, assert that any portion or all of our existing or future ownership structure and businesses, or this offering, violate existing or future P.R.C. laws and regulations.''</p>
        <p>Yet, with China expecting to join the World Trade Organization later this year, a feeling of invincibility -- some say hubris -- has permeated the industry. ''The same deference isn't being paid to the ministries and bureaucrats as was paid in the past,'' says Greg Shea, an American who is working for a venture capital fund sponsored by Siemens A.G. and one of China's own investment companies, the China International Trust and Investment Corporation. The money Mr. Shea's company is investing comes from a telecommunications-equipment-leasing business that was unwound last year after China declared that the structure violated Chinese law.</p>
        <p>Even if the current trend does die without transforming China's economy, it has taught a group of bright, ambitious young people the basic tools of capitalism. And not all of those people are likely to go away. Michael Brownrigg of the San Francisco-based Chinavest, one of the first venture capital firms to invest in China, said, ''The Internet shows that young people can run businesses here and that will resonate for a long time to come.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
