<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Piazza Erases Any Doubts With 2 Homers</title>
    <meta content="15METS$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Red Sox</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Boston Red Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6D6143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1089" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Piazza Erases Any Doubts With 2 Homers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, July 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Boston Red Sox, 6-4; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Mets came back to beat the Boston Red Sox tonight, but a more significant comeback took place. Mike Piazza, it turns out, is just fine.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the Mets' catcher played for the first time after sustaining a concussion from a Roger Clemens fastball to the head last Saturday. He went 1 for 4, and faced countless questions about whether he had feared anything or felt awkward in the batter's box.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Mets came back to beat the Boston Red Sox tonight, but a more significant comeback took place. Mike Piazza, it turns out, is just fine.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, the Mets' catcher played for the first time after sustaining a concussion from a Roger Clemens fastball to the head last Saturday. He went 1 for 4, and faced countless questions about whether he had feared anything or felt awkward in the batter's box.</p>
        <p>He answered no on Thursday, and his bat talked for him tonight. Piazza blasted two home runs, the second one a game-winner that lifted the Mets to a 6-4 victory in a game delayed 62 minutes at the start because of a power outage at Fenway Park.</p>
        <p>''Mike's the M.V.P.,'' Mets catcher Todd Pratt said. ''I don't know how far we're going to go, but right now, he's doing everything we've always known he could do. It's incredible.''</p>
        <p>After blowing the lead to the Boston Red Sox in an ugly seventh inning, the Mets needed a jolt in the eighth. Red Sox reliever Hipolito Pichardo had retired all eight batters he faced, but with two outs in the eighth, Red Sox Manager Jimy Williams called on Derek Lowe, his All-Star closer, to face the Mets' two offensive All-Stars.</p>
        <p>Edgardo Alfonzo singled, and Piazza, who missed the All-Star Game because of the concussion, came to the plate. He drove a 1-1 curveball from Lowe off a giant cola bottle mounted on the light tower above the high left-field wall, giving the Mets a 5-4 lead.</p>
        <p>''For myself personally, I didn't really worry about any sort of questions,'' Piazza said. ''I was happy about myself, health-wise, that I'm O.K. That sort of has a way of mediating my expectations.''</p>
        <p>The homer earned a victory for Pat Mahomes (3-1), who got the last out in a seventh inning in which the Red Sox took the lead with two runs off three Mets relievers.</p>
        <p>The Mets' starter, Glendon Rusch, has not walked a batter in his last 33 2/3 innings. But as soon as he was removed, the Red Sox drew their first walk, by Jose Offerman off Turk Wendell to lead off the seventh. After a sacrifice, Dennis Cook relieved and faced Brian Daubach, who won Thursday's game with a two-out, two-run double in the ninth inning. Cook had struck out Daubach on a nasty slider on Thursday, and Williams -- a former Atlanta Braves coach -- had the ball checked before Cook's first pitch. Cook got ahead in the count, 0-2, and Williams came onto the field to complain about the way Cook was rubbing the baseball with his hands between pitches.</p>
        <p>''I've been checked probably 50 times between these guys and the Braves, and every time I get the ball back,'' Cook said. ''I've been rubbing the ball up for 15 years the same way, and the only teams that seem to have a problem with it are the Braves and Red Sox.''</p>
        <p>Cook stepped off the rubber and backed away from the mound, then got back on and stared in for several seconds. It was gamesmanship, and Daubach did not like it. Annoyed, he stepped out of the batter's box and walked away from Todd Pratt, who became irate and confronted Daubach, with the umpire Marty Foster coming between them.</p>
        <p>''He told me to 'Save it,' '' Pratt said. ''I just said, 'Who are you to tell me to save it?' I couldn't believe a guy who's got one year in is telling me to save it. I told him how I felt about it.''</p>
        <p>The benches and bullpens emptied, but no punches were thrown and several Red Sox and Mets players joked with each other. Foster still warned both benches, and on the next pitch, Daubach lined a single to right, scoring Offerman to tie the score, 3-3.</p>
        <p>Cook then walked Nomar Garciaparra, and two pitches later, he hit Carl Everett in the back of the shoulder with a pitch. Foster ejected Cook, who was livid and stalked to the plate pointing, claiming Everett was crowding the plate.</p>
        <p>It got worse one pitch later. The left-hander Rich Rodriguez came in, and in his first game back from a five-game assignment to Class AAA Norfolk, Rodriguez allowed a bloop single to Troy O'Leary that scored Garciaparra to put the Red Sox ahead, 4-3. It was the third time in the game that O'Leary singled home Garciaparra.</p>
        <p>Garciaparra had kept Rusch in trouble for much of his six innings. The Red Sox shortstop entered the game with a major league-leading .391 average, and he was 4 for 4 in the game, pulling his average to .400.</p>
        <p>Rusch had left with a 3-2 lead, courtesy of Piazza's first homer -- which he sent onto Landsdowne Street beyond the left-field wall in the fourth -- and a two-run homer by Mora, in the fifth.</p>
        <p>Mora's error on Thursday prolonged the ninth inning and made possible the Red Sox' comeback victory. Mora was shaky at shortstop again tonight, losing the ball on a transfer from his glove to his hand as he tried to throw to first on a potential double-play grounder in the second.</p>
        <p>Ventura Is Sent Home for Tests</p>
        <p>Third baseman Robin Ventura, who has struggled to regain his offensive form after surgery on his right shoulder last winter, will return to New York Saturday for a magnetic resonance imaging test on the shoulder. Ventura will meet with the Mets' team doctor, David Altchek.</p>
        <p>Ventura lifted his average to .251 on June 25, the day he tweaked the shoulder while sliding headfirst into second base, and he has eight hits in 50 at-bats since, dropping his average to .235. . . . With General Manager Steve Phillips watching, the Class AAA Norfolk right-hander Grant Roberts struggled Friday night, allowing four runs on nine hits in six innings against Scranton-Wilkes Barre and raising his earned-run average to 4.58. The 22-year-old Roberts has been an enigma for the Mets, who are losing faith in the idea that he can help them this year. ''He seems to have stalled right now,'' said Jim Duquette, the Mets' assistant general manager.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
