<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economy May Not Be Cooling To the Satisfaction of the Fed</title>
    <meta content="Y15ECO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve Bank</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D8143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economy May Not Be Cooling To the Satisfaction of the Fed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Government reports reveal that shoppers kept spending heavily through spring, despite increases in interest rates and gasoline prices; this indicates that economy may not be slowing sufficiently to satisfy Federal Reserve officials; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nation's shoppers kept spending through the spring despite an uninspiring stock market and increases in interest rates and gasoline prices, according to government reports issued yesterday.</p>
        <p>As a result, analysts said, a superheated American economy may not be cooling to the satisfaction of the Federal Reserve, which over the last year has raised the cost of borrowing money on six occasions as it seeks to keep prices in check.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The nation's shoppers kept spending through the spring despite an uninspiring stock market and increases in interest rates and gasoline prices, according to government reports issued yesterday.</p>
        <p>As a result, analysts said, a superheated American economy may not be cooling to the satisfaction of the Federal Reserve, which over the last year has raised the cost of borrowing money on six occasions as it seeks to keep prices in check.</p>
        <p>''You've got an economy that's slowing but that may not be slowing enough,'' said Diane Swonk, chief economist for the Bank One Corporation in Chicago. She said the risks were still very high that the Federal Reserve would decide it needed to raise interest rates again.</p>
        <p>The bond market's reaction to yesterday's economic data was swift: prices fell, raising yields, as traders and investors decided that a bigger-than-expected rise in retail sales last month -- on top of a hefty upward revision for May -- outweighed a relatively market-friendly report on June producer prices.</p>
        <p>A third survey, on industrial output for June, showed the smallest increase in nine months.</p>
        <p>Retail sales, according to the Commerce Department's initial estimate, climbed 0.5 percent last month, to $269.3 billion, with about 70 percent of the gain spent at automotive dealers and about half the rest at gasoline stations.</p>
        <p>While the increase was not much more than had been expected, analysts said, it was from a base in May that was considerably higher than first reported as the department's statisticians, using more complete data, transformed what had been a decline of 0.3 percent in retail sales into a gain of 0.3 percent. Retail sales, which account for about half of consumer spending and one-third of all economic activity, are widely watched for clues to current conditions.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department's report on prices paid to producers, which excludes both services and imported goods, showed a 0.6 percent advance for finished goods; the rise was largely driven by oil and natural gas. While this matched expectations, economists said they were surprised that the so-called core rate, which excludes energy and food, edged down 0.1 percent after rising 0.2 percent in May, the first drop since January.</p>
        <p>James E. Glassman, an economist and a managing director of Chase Securities, went so far as to call it ''stunning'' that the long run-up in energy prices has spilled over so little into other sectors. ''Underlying inflation remains well behaved,'' he said, adding that an enormous, continuing corporate appetite for high-technology equipment implies further anti-inflation pressure by rising productivity.</p>
        <p>Goods at the intermediate stage of production, like a sack of flour, climbed 0.9 percent last month while raw materials jumped 5.8 percent, in both cases reflecting the surge in energy costs. Recently, Ms. Swonk said, gasoline prices have dropped very sharply in the Midwest, where they had risen the most.</p>
        <p>The industrial production report, compiled by the Federal Reserve, showed that the nation's factories, mines and utilities raised output 0.2 percent last month, a little less than expected, compared with a 0.5 percent rise in May.</p>
        <p>Automobiles, semiconductors and business equipment were the main contributors to the gain, with output slackening for appliances, clothing, steel and electricity.</p>
        <p>The next scheduled meeting of Federal Reserve policy makers, who last month found signs of economic slowdown ''still tentative and preliminary,'' is Aug. 22.</p>
        <p>In another development yesterday, the National Association for Business Economics published a survey that found one-third of businesses were able to offset higher costs by raising prices during the second quarter, the highest proportion since the first quarter of 1995.</p>
        <p>''Pricing power has improved,'' said Ms. Swonk, who is currently the association's president. ''It makes the Fed awfully cautious.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
