<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vote by Board of General Mills On Pillsbury Deal Is Expected</title>
    <meta content="Y15FOO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Mills Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pillsbury Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Diageo Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7DA143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vote by Board of General Mills On Pillsbury Deal Is Expected</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Board of directors of General Mills will meet July 16 to consider company's proposed acquisition of Pillsbury brand from Diageo PLC for $10.5 billion in cash and stock (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The board of General Mills is meeting tomorrow to consider the company's proposed acquisition of Pillsbury from Diageo P.L.C. for $10.5 billion in cash and stock, according to executives close to the negotiations.</p>
        <p>If approved by the board, the companies could announce the deal on Monday, the executives said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The board of General Mills is meeting tomorrow to consider the company's proposed acquisition of Pillsbury from Diageo P.L.C. for $10.5 billion in cash and stock, according to executives close to the negotiations.</p>
        <p>If approved by the board, the companies could announce the deal on Monday, the executives said.</p>
        <p>The sale would follow a rash of consolidations in the consumer food industry as food makers battle with grocery retailers for more leverage in pricing products. The deal would also immediately make General Mills an attractive takeover target because it would diversify its product line, which now includes cereal brands like Cheerios and Cocoa Puffs, to include Pillsbury's stable of brands like Haagen-Dazs ice cream and Green Giant frozen food and would give it annual sales of nearly $1.7 billion.</p>
        <p>According to the executives, General Mills has offered to pay Diageo about $4.5 billion in cash and about $6 billion in stock for Pillsbury, giving Diageo a stake in the combined concern of about 33 percent. As part of the agreement, Diageo, which is based in Britain, would also get two seats on the board of General Mills. Both General Mills and Pillsbury are based in Minneapolis.</p>
        <p>Diageo, which has historically acted like a holding company of sorts for a variety of food and spirits companies, is quickly abandoning the food business to focus on its much more profitable spirits business, which includes Smirnoff vodka, Johnnie Walker whiskey and Guinness stout.</p>
        <p>Diageo recently announced that it planned to spin off 20 percent of Burger King, signaling its intention to eventually sell the entire fast food chain.</p>
        <p>Analysts say that with the proceeds from the sale of Pillsbury, Diageo might go on its own acquisition binge, buying rival spirits makers like Seagram liquor business, which is being put up for sale as part of Vivendi's recent plan to acquire that company.</p>
        <p>Though General Mills is expected to acquire Pillsbury's entire stable of businesses, executives close to the company have indicated that it may seek to sell brands like Green Giant and possibly several others that do not strategically fit the company's brand portfolio.</p>
        <p>General Mills products include the Betty Crocker line of cake mixes, Hamburger Helper, Pop Secret microwave popcorn, Gold Medal flour, and Yoplait and Colombo yogurt. It recently scored a major hit with Go-Gurt, a yogurt aimed at children that is packaged in a slender portable tube that requires no spoon. So successful is Go-Gurt, in fact, that an adult version is being planned.</p>
        <p>Pillsbury's product lineup also includes the Old El Paso line of Mexican food and Progresso soups.</p>
        <p>There are overlaps in several areas, particularly flour and cake mixes.</p>
        <p>Jaine Mehring, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, recently wrote in a report to investors, ''We believe General Mills would be most interested in the Pillsbury Doughboy businesses and the refrigerated-foods technology.'' She added, ''However, it's hard to imagine Mills taking on Green Giant.''</p>
        <p>Shares of Diageo dropped 2 pence each, to 597 pence, or $8.95, in London yesterday. Shares of General Mills slumped 68.75 cents each, to $36.3125, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>The sale of Pillsbury follows Unilever's proposed $20.3 billion acquisition of Bestfoods and Philip Morris's planned $14.9 billion buyout of Nabisco Holdings.</p>
        <p>Analysts said a General Mills-Pillsbury combination would put even more pressure on companies like Campbell Soup, H. J. Heinz and Kellogg to consider their own own acquisitions.</p>
        <p>A merger would probably mean job cuts in Minneapolis. ''As with any merger there will be some consolidation of jobs and things like that, and I assume some executive-level jobs will be lost,'' said Thomas Stinson, the Minnesota state economist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
