<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reliving Childhood as They Dwell on Children Lost</title>
    <meta content="15DEWI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewitt, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carner, Charles Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belushi, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hines, Gregory</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Who Killed Atlanta's Children? (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E5D6173BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reliving Childhood as They Dwell on Children Lost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID DeWITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewitt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>television review: relivin</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One at a time they cascade across the screen, face after face, lives cut short and deaths not explained.</p>
        <p>Set against a dark background and accompanied by haunting gospel music, the opening moments of ''Who Killed Atlanta's Children?'' suggest a film that will have a focused appeal and a subtle integrity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One at a time they cascade across the screen, face after face, lives cut short and deaths not explained.</p>
        <p>Set against a dark background and accompanied by haunting gospel music, the opening moments of ''Who Killed Atlanta's Children?'' suggest a film that will have a focused appeal and a subtle integrity.</p>
        <p>The movie's good intentions, however, are undercut by the bulk of this fact-based drama, which compresses a painful, complex tale into a plodding, sketchy screenplay that, sadly, is not enlivened by either direction or performances.</p>
        <p>''Who Killed Atlanta's Children?'' -- on Showtime tomorrow night at 8 -- is based on a 1986 investigation by Spin magazine, which reported on the doubts that remained in the wake of a frightening series of murders in Atlanta between 1979 and 1981. Known as ''the Atlanta child murders,'' the case was declared closed after the 1982 conviction of Wayne Williams, who was a suspect in the  murders, for killing two of the victims, who at 21 and 27 were adult men.</p>
        <p>''Who Killed Atlanta's Children?'' covers explosive territory. The case prompted fear in the Georgia capital and across the nation, because of the victims' youth, because of their numbers (the official total was 29) and because of their race: all were black.</p>
        <p>As depicted in the film, mothers of some slain children remain unconvinced that Mr. Williams, who is black, was responsible for all the deaths. Ron Larson (Gregory Hines) and Pat Laughlin (James Belushi) are the journalists who step in to help their cause. They find evidence of a confused investigation and desperate investigators. An insider source (played with crusty authenticity by Sean McCann) points the reporters to suspects allied to racist groups. Worse, the source offers documentation of an inquiry into those suspects, one not made public because, the film suggests, the authorities were more concerned about smoothing racial tensions than about solving crimes.</p>
        <p>That secret investigation and its disturbing context were the crux of Spin's report. The film, written and directed by Charles Robert Carner, has an even broader reach. One short but evocative scene is dominated by a portrait of President Reagan, with a man in the foreground giving telephone assurance to an unidentified someone that the authorities had settled the Atlanta child murders.</p>
        <p>Such conspiracy material, coupled with the families' grief and desire for closure, offers plenty to occupy ''Who Killed Atlanta's Children?'' So it is disappointing that the film wastes most of its energy on the journalists' professional issues and domestic worries. Imagine ''All the President's Men''; make the investigative focus more somber and grisly; now envision a black Woodward and a white Bernstein talking about their childhood, or swapping advice on balancing family and work. The mix makes an unwieldy whole.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hines gives Larson a nicely reticent dignity, but he can't lift dialogue that locks his character, an editor, into obvious professional conflicts with the freewheeling writer played by Mr. Belushi.</p>
        <p>Also conventional is the revelation that Larson feels distant from his lower-income relatives as well as from his less sophisticated Southern sources. (The film's portrait of Atlanta is visually and socially unappealing.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Belushi as Laughlin is saddled with even more generic material. ''Everyone wants to blame others for their own failures,'' Laughlin says of the Atlanta murders, a provocative attitude that is diluted because it is used to reveal the reporter's boyhood more than it is to enrich his current situation. Mr. Belushi's few muted moments add more to the film than his typical bluster.</p>
        <p>''Who Killed Atlanta's Children?'' does not try to answer its titular question. The movie does not exonerate Mr. Williams (given a creepy edge by Cle Bennett). And it makes no declaration of blame, though it examines possibilities of several killers tied to several motives: urban prostitution, political hypocrisy and organized racism.</p>
        <p>Instead, the movie calls attention to a set of killings that were never given as fair and thorough a hearing as they deserved. The streamlined tale of ''Who Killed Atlanta's Children?'' proves no more satisfying a hearing.</p>
        <p>WHO KILLED ATLANTA'S CHILDREN?  Showtime, tomorrow night at 8</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Charles Robert Carner; produced by Rudy Langlais; Michael Grais and Mark Victor, executive producers; Michael Goi, director of photography. A Showtime presentation.</p>
        <p>WITH: James Belushi (Pat Laughlin), Gregory Hines (Ron Larson), Sean McCann (Melton), Aidan Devine (Jack Johnson), Shawn Doyle (Royal McCullough), Cle Bennett (Wayne Williams) and Kenneth Welsh (Wayne Williams's lawyer).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
