<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Portland's Grant Savors Taste of Life in the Big City</title>
    <meta content="15KNIC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Portland Trail Blazers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grant, Brian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Portland Trail Blazers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EED7143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Portland's Grant Savors Taste of Life in the Big City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, July 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Portland Trail Blazers Brian Grant comes to New York to meet with New York Knickerbockers; Grant wants to play for Knicks but there are salary cap problems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Wednesday afternoon, Brian Grant and his wife, Gina, arrived at Newark International Airport like other harried tourists, setting their itinerary for New York City. But between the usual attractions, Grant found himself being courted by the Knicks. By the time he was eating a final piece of New York cheesecake as he waited for his flight home to Portland, Ore., he was ready to turn the two-night stay into a permanent home.</p>
        <p>''Coming out, I was all Portland,'' Grant said as he signed autographs for fans who lined up to tell him to stay. ''But coming back, it's a toss-up, 50-50. I could come to New York or I could stay in Portland. New York sold me.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Wednesday afternoon, Brian Grant and his wife, Gina, arrived at Newark International Airport like other harried tourists, setting their itinerary for New York City. But between the usual attractions, Grant found himself being courted by the Knicks. By the time he was eating a final piece of New York cheesecake as he waited for his flight home to Portland, Ore., he was ready to turn the two-night stay into a permanent home.</p>
        <p>''Coming out, I was all Portland,'' Grant said as he signed autographs for fans who lined up to tell him to stay. ''But coming back, it's a toss-up, 50-50. I could come to New York or I could stay in Portland. New York sold me.</p>
        <p>''If they work something out, then I will come to New York.''</p>
        <p>More difficult than the recruiting process for the Knicks is actually figuring out a deal to get Grant to New York. Although he opted out of his contract with the Portland Trail Blazers, the Knicks are over the salary cap and can only offer him a $2.25 million midlevel exception. The way the deal can be done is through a sign-and-trade agreement between the Blazers and the Knicks. But until the Knicks can figure out a package that will appease the Blazers, the pursuit of Grant is just beginning.</p>
        <p>''Even though we may say, 'Yeah, we want to come to New York,' they don't have to trade me,'' Grant said of the Trail Blazers. ''It's up in the air. Just because I say I want to be in New York, doesn't mean necessarily that they would bring me to New York.''</p>
        <p>Grant's agent, Mark Bartelstein, said his client would not try to pressure Portland.</p>
        <p>''Brian is not one to go around issuing ultimatums,'' Bartelstein said. ''He just doesn't work that way. The Blazers are a great opportunity for Brian, and the Knicks are a great opportunity.''</p>
        <p>Referring to the Knicks' general manager and the Blazers' general manager, respectively, Bartelstein said, ''Scott Layden and Bob Whitsitt are going to talk, and they'll see if they have something to talk about.''</p>
        <p>Grant did see some of the typical attractions, like the Statue of Liberty, during his New York stay. But unlike the tourists who crowd onto the Circle Line, he saw it from the yacht of James L. Dolan, the president of Cablevision. Rather than taking in a show, he was solicited by the stars of the shows. But it was the pastoral country homes of Westchester County and Connecticut and discussions with Charlie Ward and Allan Houston, who share his religious beliefs, that convinced Grant he could adjust to life in New York.</p>
        <p>''I'm from a small town of 2,500 people,'' Grant said. ''Portland is a smaller city, and it's easier to get adjusted to. So I never thought I'd be able to adjust to living in New York City.''</p>
        <p>While the National Basketball Association rules prohibit teams from negotiating until Aug. 1, the Knicks accomplished their goal of proving to Grant that he could be a vital piece of the team and town.</p>
        <p>''It's a recruiting process and I know that,'' he said. ''But it just feels good to have all that going on.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
