<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Defends the Death Penalty to a Religious Audience</title>
    <meta content="Y15BUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garlic, Joseph H (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DB143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Defends the Death Penalty to a Religious Audience</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush appears at a Presbyterian meeting hall in Elizabeth, NJ, where he is challenged on his support to death penalty by Rev Joseph H Garlic; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of Gov. George W. Bush's campaign events unexpectedly turned into a debate over the death penalty yesterday when a black minister raised questions about the governor's compassion and told him that a recent execution in Texas was ''not a moral decision.''</p>
        <p>The surprise exchange, in what is usually a highly scripted campaign, took place at a Presbyterian meeting hall in Elizabeth, N.J., where Mr. Bush had come to highlight his belief in using religious institutions to provide social services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of Gov. George W. Bush's campaign events unexpectedly turned into a debate over the death penalty yesterday when a black minister raised questions about the governor's compassion and told him that a recent execution in Texas was ''not a moral decision.''</p>
        <p>The surprise exchange, in what is usually a highly scripted campaign, took place at a Presbyterian meeting hall in Elizabeth, N.J., where Mr. Bush had come to highlight his belief in using religious institutions to provide social services.</p>
        <p>The presumed Republican presidential nominee sat with a mostly black and Hispanic panel of church leaders, community organizers and local officials who had been assembled by his campaign to discuss how churches provide services. But halfway through the event, the Rev. Joseph H. Garlic, seated immediately to Mr. Bush's right, changed the subject.</p>
        <p>He said he had to ask a sensitive question. ''It is one I could not live with myself if I did not ask or bring up,'' he said, ''and that's about Gary Graham.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham, who had been convicted for the 1981 murder of a man outside a Houston supermarket, was executed in Texas last month, with Mr. Bush proclaiming that ''justice is being done.''</p>
        <p>Pointing to the questions that swirled around the case, including the competency of Mr. Graham's lawyer and the fact that only one witness testified against him, Mr. Garlic said the case had given Mr. Bush ''an opportunity to show some compassion and love in a way that had not been shown before.''</p>
        <p>''I think that when you chose protocol and not setting a precedent over a decision about a man's life,'' Mr. Garlic said, ''you missed an opportunity to show some of this compassion, and to show some of this new Republican spirit that you talk about.''</p>
        <p>''You and I must differ on the death penalty,'' a surprised Mr. Bush replied, speaking softly. ''I support it because I think it saves lives when it's administered fairly and justly and surely.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''My job is to uphold the laws of my state. That's what I was sworn in to do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said of his refusal to intervene in the execution, ''It's not an easy decision to make, as I'm sure you can understand.'' He added, ''But it isn't a political decision for me, Reverend.'' He said he would continue to ''uphold the law'' and ''if it costs me votes, so be it.''</p>
        <p>Dissatisfied, Mr. Garlic persisted. ''With all due respect, sir, that is not an answer,'' he said. ''That is not a good enough answer for me.'' He said the issue was whether or not Mr. Graham was guilty. ''And while you say to me that it was not a political decision, it definitely was not a moral decision.''</p>
        <p>''We just disagree on that case,'' Mr. Bush said, and the group returned to talking about services for children and to a proposal by him for a $400 million program to help lower-income parents pay for after-school activities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has made a concerted effort throughout his campaign to prove he is a ''different kind of Republican'' by appearing in minority neighborhoods. He began his week at the N.A.A.C.P. convention. And he told the small crowd of invited guests today that he hoped his appearance before the civil rights organization would cause black voters to think, ''Hey, there might be a little different cut to this man.''</p>
        <p>''I don't know how many Republican presidential candidates have come to this neighborhood before,'' he said. ''I hope it tells people I care.''</p>
        <p>And by the end of the event, he had the crowd laughing, when he raised the question of whether he would remember his visit. ''I think it's safe to say I might,'' Mr. Bush said with a smile. Then the governor turned to Mr. Garlic, former director of the Elizabethport Presbyterian Center, where Mr. Bush spoke, and shook his hand.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Garlic said afterward that he ''was absolutely not'' satisfied by Mr. Bush's response, he said Mr. Bush ''handled himself very well in the total situation.''</p>
        <p>Several others in the audience said the governor had left them more comfortable with the idea of a Bush presidency and even willing to consider voting for him.</p>
        <p>''He was a little bit more down to earth than I thought,'' said William Ward, a board member of the center. ''He's more impressive than I thought. Now I've got to listen to the other guy.''</p>
        <p>''He had a sense of humor,'' said Vera Atkinson, an assistant director of an organization that builds low-income housing in the neighborhood. ''I thought he was uncomfortable but answered the best he could.''</p>
        <p>Later in the day, Mr. Bush traveled to more traditional Republican turf -- a reception of New York's Conservative Party in a Manhattan hotel ballroom. But the Gary Graham issue followed him, as two protesters rose in the back of the room and began chanting. They were quickly evicted.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
