<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After 8 Years in Office, Unfamiliar in Michigan</title>
    <meta content="Y15GOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Michigan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D8143BF936A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After 8 Years in Office, Unfamiliar in Michigan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>SAGINAW, Mich., July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore campaigns in Michigan, where for many voters he remains an unknown quantity despite his nearly eight years as vice president and a yearlong presidential campaign; Ralph Nader and his anti-corporate third-party candidacy are also siphoning votes from what should be Gore's constituency; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sheila Redman, director of the Saginaw Art Museum, put it best. ''I feel kind of bad in asking this,'' she said to the vice president of the United States. ''But where have you been for the past eight years?''</p>
        <p>This is a solidly Democratic, heavily unionized area, the buckle of Michigan's industrial belt. But as in the rest of this state, and much of the industrial Midwest, voters here are skeptical about Al Gore's presidential candidacy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sheila Redman, director of the Saginaw Art Museum, put it best. ''I feel kind of bad in asking this,'' she said to the vice president of the United States. ''But where have you been for the past eight years?''</p>
        <p>This is a solidly Democratic, heavily unionized area, the buckle of Michigan's industrial belt. But as in the rest of this state, and much of the industrial Midwest, voters here are skeptical about Al Gore's presidential candidacy.</p>
        <p>And tonight, for three and a half hours, Mr. Gore stood under the hot lights in the sweltering gymnasium of Arthur Hill High School here, patiently answering questions from 200 voters -- many of them undecided -- on the economy, jobs, trade and the insurgent campaign of Ralph Nader.</p>
        <p>But it was Ms. Redman's questioning that seemed to strike at the heart of the issue. Noting that she was only suddenly aware of his campaign, she told Mr. Gore: ''I wasn't sure I would vote for you. I didn't know if you were strong enough to compete.''</p>
        <p>This is one of the areas where Mr. Nader and his anti-corporate third-party candidacy is siphoning votes from Mr. Gore. It may seem odd that Mr. Nader, author of ''Unsafe At Any Speed'' and the longtime nemesis of the auto industry, could make a dent in the support of the A.F.L.-C.I.O.-backed Democratic candidate here. But Mr. Gore, who as Republicans like to say, once proposed elimination of the internal-combustion engine, carries a heavily anti-automobile reputation, too.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Nader in the race, according to the latest statewide poll by The Detroit Free Press, Mr. Gore trails Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, his likely Republican rival, by 12 percentage points. The poll gave Mr. Bush 46 percent, Mr. Gore 34 and Mr. Nader 8.</p>
        <p>In the same poll two months ago, before Mr. Nader became a factor, Mr. Gore was leading Mr. Bush. The Democrats have spent $1.2 million in television commercials here since then to try to raise Mr. Gore's stock, but to little avail.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Nader is only part of the problem. Gore backers and analysts say that as the election heats up after Labor Day and Mr. Nader's bare-bones campaign competes for news media attention and on the airwaves, he may become less of a factor.</p>
        <p>For voters like Ms. Redman, the main concern is that despite Mr. Gore's nearly eight years as vice president and his yearlong presidential campaign, he is still an unknown quantity.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign is fully aware that the vice president ''hasn't broken through'' with voters, as one Gore adviser put it. And tonight, he revived one of his favorite campaign venues, the town hall meeting, an open-ended give-and-take with voters that allows Mr. Gore to display his grasp of issues and, more important, to try to convey to voters who he his.</p>
        <p>While Ms. Redman did not mention President Clinton, Mr. Gore immediately interpreted her concern as one about his toiling in the shadow as a No. 2. He told her that the job of vice president was a ''mixed blessing.'' The ideal person for the job, he told her, was someone who would not care about receiving press attention and who would help ''carry the load when the load gets heavy.''</p>
        <p>But, he added: ''You may not always notice that man. And if you do, he may be just standing there stiffly behind the president, not saying a word.''</p>
        <p>He pressed on: ''Well, is it like the woman behind the man? Well, you know, actually, I've learned a lot about some of those issues because a vice president who does the job correctly is somebody who pitches in and does everything that can help out the country by strengthening the team and moving the ball down the field.''</p>
        <p>Ed Sarpolus, who is a longtime political analyst in Lansing and who conducted The Free Press polls, said that despite Mr. Bush's lead across the state, Mr. Gore still leads heavily in this region. But he added that Ms. Redman had given voice to the central obstacle that Mr. Gore had to overcome.</p>
        <p>''Gore's problem in Michigan is not the China issue, it's not the labor issue,'' he said of some union concerns. ''It's personality and character because it's tied to Bill Clinton.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''When I look at people's angst with Gore, it's not the policies'' that give them pause, but Mr. Clinton's ''moral turpitude,'' he said. ''They will punish Bill through Al. And until Gore separates himself from Clinton, it's the sins of the father being visited on the son.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarpolus said that Mr. Gore needed eventually to make a clean break with Mr. Clinton, probably after the convention, even though he was relying on the Clinton economy as his biggest selling point.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore seems more comfortable training the national discussion on the economy.</p>
        <p>''You put your finger on the problem,'' he told a man in a tank top who implored the vice president to ''get more manufacturing jobs back into Michigan.'' But even that man, a union worker who said he earned $23,000 a year, shared a more personal reaction to the vice president as he addressed him. ''You look a lot like my older brother,'' he told Mr. Gore, approvingly.</p>
        <p>The Gore strategy at this point is to create the chance for the vice president to make these personal connections, which he invariably comes away from successfully, but also to hammer away at his differences with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Chris Lehane, Mr. Gore's press secretary, said that Mr. Gore would not be distracted by Mr. Nader, whose name Mr. Gore never uttered during the meeting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sarpolus said that Mr. Gore's reference to being ''the woman behind the man'' was probably a useful way to convey his role and his sensibilities to women, who make up the majority of Democratic voters -- even if it did not appeal to male voters, who polls show favor Mr. Bush over the vice president.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't change the way he communicates that,'' Mr. Sarpolus said. ''He has to reach women, and this helps him do that, by being a man who is willing to admit that,'' he said. ''And if he doesn't get the women's vote, it doesn't matter what happens with the men.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
