<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Freshness and Fire In a Tanglewood Idyll</title>
    <meta content="11TANG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tanglewood Music Festival (Lenox, Mass)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oestreich, James R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFD71238F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Freshness and Fire In a Tanglewood Idyll</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES R. OESTREICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Oestreich, James R</byline>
      <dateline>LENOX, Mass., July 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James R Oestreich reviews opening weekend of concerts at Tanglewood Festival; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For decades, the Tanglewood Festival was a reliable retreat. Not that the big business of classical music is ever without problems, but what better place to ponder or -- grudgingly -- deal with them than the idyllic summer home of the Boston Symphony, nestled here in the Berkshire Hills?</p>
        <p>Then came the recent wars over the Tanglewood Music Center, a venerable training ground for young musicians and a force for contemporary music. Awkwardly at best, after a quarter-century of relative neglect, Seiji Ozawa began some three years ago to assert his prerogative, as the orchestra's music director, to determine the center's direction. After an upheaval in personnel, a new regime was consolidated under the direction of Ellen Highstein in 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For decades, the Tanglewood Festival was a reliable retreat. Not that the big business of classical music is ever without problems, but what better place to ponder or -- grudgingly -- deal with them than the idyllic summer home of the Boston Symphony, nestled here in the Berkshire Hills?</p>
        <p>Then came the recent wars over the Tanglewood Music Center, a venerable training ground for young musicians and a force for contemporary music. Awkwardly at best, after a quarter-century of relative neglect, Seiji Ozawa began some three years ago to assert his prerogative, as the orchestra's music director, to determine the center's direction. After an upheaval in personnel, a new regime was consolidated under the direction of Ellen Highstein in 1998.</p>
        <p>Then, shortly before the festival last year, Mr. Ozawa announced that he would leave Boston in 2002 to take over the Vienna State Opera. So, as the Boston Symphony opens its season here this year, how stands his belated commitment to the center?</p>
        <p>It remains as strong as it was two years ago if not stronger, Ms. Highstein suggested. ''It's hard to be more than 100 percent,'' she said.</p>
        <p>A major focus of his commitment this summer is Verdi's opera ''Falstaff,'' which he is to conduct in late July with two casts and two orchestras, spreading the pedagogical wealth. He offers a preview on Saturday evening, leading the Music Center Orchestra in Act III in the Leonard Bernstein Memorial Concert.</p>
        <p>By all accounts from battle-scarred survivors, a productive calm has finally returned. And Mr. Ozawa, as his tenure approaches an end, may at least have established a solid precedent for active involvement by his successor as well as by the orchestra. (Fifty players now take part in the center's activities as opposed to a handful a few years ago.)</p>
        <p>The festival's patrons, who were probably never much concerned with such issues anyway, turned out in droves for the opening weekend of Boston Symphony concerts despite an unseasonable chill on Friday evening and rain on Sunday afteroon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ozawa conducted the opening concert, on Friday, the orchestra's first outing together in eight weeks (after a run of Boston Pops concerts, involving most of the players, and vacation). The layoff partly told, though the woodwinds, in their blatancy and unevenness, and the brasses, with their periodic blurs, may have suffered from the cold.</p>
        <p>As exceptions, Robert Sheena gave a lovely lift to the English horn solo in Copland's ''Quiet City,'' and Richard Svoboda was a fine bassoonist in Stravinsky's ''Firebird'' Suite. The brasses and percussionists were aptly stentorian in Copland's ''Fanfare for the Common Man.''</p>
        <p>But the occasion belonged largely to Yo-Yo Ma, who played both Haydn's C major Cello Concerto and Edgar Meyer's Double Concerto for cello and double bass. However often he may have played the Haydn over the years, Mr. Ma gave it a remarkable freshness, finding full scope for his ebullient musical personality.</p>
        <p>He seemed to find no such thing in the Meyer work, from 1995, despite a committed performance along with Mr. Meyer's own virtuosic effort on double bass. For all the piece's extroverted gestures -- a funky main theme in the first movement, a bit of jazz in the second, an Appalachian flavor in the third -- the soloists' conversation seemed crabbed rather than expansive, and their interaction with the orchestra poorly knit.</p>
        <p>Other new music -- not all of it yet intended for public consumption -- impressed more. On Saturday evening, Mr. Ma's bruited Silk Road Project was put on semipublic display in a workshop for concert presenters. Extended discussion of this venture (named for the ancient trade route between Asia and Europe), which variously combines Eastern and Western performers, instruments or idioms in contemporary compositions, must await a public airing in the fall, but these glimpses proved tantalizing.</p>
        <p>John Williams's new ''TreeSong,'' a concerto for violin and orchestra in the symphony concert that followed, seemed almost an extension of the Silk Road aesthetic. Inspired by a Chinese redwood in the Boston Public Garden, it combines Western lyricism in the violin with fine, subtle Orientalizing in the orchestra, owing partly, no doubt, to Mr. Williams's cinematic sense.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams conducted the program, which also included his early Essay for Strings, Prokofiev's Violin Concerto No. 2 and Tchaikovsky's ''Francesca da Rimini.'' Gil Shaham, the violinist, was as sensitive in his finespun lines in ''TreeSong'' as he was clever and brilliant in Prokofiev's quirks and pyrotechnics.</p>
        <p>Garrick Ohlsson rounded out a cast of superb soloists on Sunday, showing his familiar mastery of Beethoven's ''Emperor'' Concerto. Roberto Abbado, a rising Italian, conducted deftly there and in Debussy's ''Printemps,'' and theatrically in Respighi's ''Feste Romane,'' reveling in the circus atmosphere and ruckus.</p>
        <p>Is Mr. Abbado a candidate to succeed Mr. Ozawa, as he is said to be a candidate to succeed Wolfgang Sawallisch as music director of the Philadelphia Orchestra? ''Everyone is a candidate, and no one is a candidate,'' Mark Volpe, managing director of the Boston Symphony, said in the classic lingo of search committees, ever mindful that no one wants to be seen eventually as a failed candidate or a consolation winner.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
