<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Challenging Work in Search of Appreciative Listeners</title>
    <meta content="11AUTH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="OPERA REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Opera Festival of New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisgall, Hugo (1912-97)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Six Characters in Search of an Author (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E0D71238F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Challenging Work in Search of Appreciative Listeners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON, N.J., July 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Tommasini reviews Hugo Weisgall opera Six Characters in Search of an Author as performed by Opera Festival of New Jersey at McCarter Theater in Princeton; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Long before the American composer Hugo Weisgall died at 84 in 1997, he was regarded by many musicians and critics as a major figure in 20th-century opera. General audiences have been slower to catch on. Although Weisgall's operas are the products of a skilled dramatist, his musical language, steeped in fitful Expressionism and spiked with elements of 12-tone writing, is craggy and challenging.</p>
        <p>The composer and his supporters were heartened when his 10th opera, ''Esther,'' was ecstatically received at its premiere in 1993 as part of the 50th-anniversary celebrations of the New York City Opera. Now the Opera Festival of New Jersey has revived Weisgall's ''Six Characters in Search of an Author,'' based on the play by Pirandello. And the enthusiastic response to the opening performance at the McCarter Theater at Princeton University should encourage Weisgall's champions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Long before the American composer Hugo Weisgall died at 84 in 1997, he was regarded by many musicians and critics as a major figure in 20th-century opera. General audiences have been slower to catch on. Although Weisgall's operas are the products of a skilled dramatist, his musical language, steeped in fitful Expressionism and spiked with elements of 12-tone writing, is craggy and challenging.</p>
        <p>The composer and his supporters were heartened when his 10th opera, ''Esther,'' was ecstatically received at its premiere in 1993 as part of the 50th-anniversary celebrations of the New York City Opera. Now the Opera Festival of New Jersey has revived Weisgall's ''Six Characters in Search of an Author,'' based on the play by Pirandello. And the enthusiastic response to the opening performance at the McCarter Theater at Princeton University should encourage Weisgall's champions.</p>
        <p>''Six Characters,'' commissioned by the Alice Ditson Fund at Columbia University in the mid-1950's, was given its premiere at the New York City Opera in 1958 and repeated successfully the following season. Then, inexplicably, it languished unproduced until 1990, when the resident training company of the Lyric Opera of Chicago presented an acclaimed performance, later released on New World Records.</p>
        <p>Pirandello's remarkable 1921 play shatters the boundaries between illusion and reality by boldly manipulating the play-within-a-play convention. A company of actors is rehearsing ''Mixing It Up,'' a new play that none of them like, by this pretentious modern playwright named Pirandello. As they work, six strangers walk onstage from out of nowhere: a father, a mother in mourning dress, a surly adult son, a volatile stepdaughter and two silent, sullen young children. They are, they say, characters from a play left unfinished by its author and are searching for someone to complete their story. In creating an operatic version of Pirandello's play, Weisgall and his librettist, Denis Johnston, an Irish playwright, turned the actors into singers who were rehearsing an overly complex new opera, ''The Temptation of St. Anthony,'' by Hugo Weisgall. The six strangers are characters from an incomplete opera. While generally adhering to the events of the original, the librettist wisely cut, altered and rewrote the material to produce an effective libretto.</p>
        <p>Weisgall's score is brilliant and haunting. Born in Bohemia, the son of a cantor, he immigrated as a child to the United States, where he received his musical education. Yet his works are imbued with Central European Expressionism. Weisgall ably fashioned the pungent atonal and thickly chromatic elements of his harmonic language into music of gritty power and affecting lyricism. Though not conventionally tuneful, the score is richly melodic.</p>
        <p>For example, in Act I the stepdaughter, to audition for the director, sings a melancholy soliloquy about her life. It's a mystery why this ravishing solo has not achieved independent life as a recital work. The soprano Michaela Gurevich sang it here with dusky sound and sensitivity, though her diction was not always clear. And if you can't understand the words in a Weisgall opera, it's not the composer's fault, for his skills at prosody were first-rate.</p>
        <p>In general, the production was admirable. The bare look of the rehearsal stage, by the set designer Ron Kadri, and the 1950's-style costumes, by Patricia Hibbert, created the right effect.</p>
        <p>Only one aspect of the director Albert Takazauckas's work seemed miscalculated. Though there is bleak humor in Pirandello's ''Six Characters,'' which the author subtitled ''A Comedy in the Making,'' the opera does not quite capture it. The opera singers are comic stereotypes, like the Coloratura (here sung by Alicia Berneche), a diva with a thick German accent and a little dog named Toto that she carries in a straw handbag.</p>
        <p>If anything, Mr. Takazauckas exaggerated the caricatures, turning the Tenore Buffo (Douglas Perry) and the Basso Cantante (Scott Altman) into stock figures.</p>
        <p>But his handling of the six rootless characters was very compelling. They were grim, unnerving figures, ageless and bound forever to their creator's conception.</p>
        <p>On opening night the musical performance, conducted by Barbara Day Turner, was not completely solid. But this was essentially a strong and sensitive account of the score.</p>
        <p>Several singers were standouts. The Accompanist, Kent Smith, sang with crisp diction and bright sound, and played the difficult onstage piano part himself. Robert Orth as the Father, Dominic Inferrera as the Son, and Ryan Allen as the crusty Stage Manager were all memorable. And it was good to see the veteran mezzo-soprano Rosalind Elias, 71, make the tormented Mother a riveting figure.</p>
        <p>There will be two more performances, on Sunday and on July 22. With luck, this revival will prod other companies into presenting this important work. How about the New York City Opera, where it received its premiere?</p>
        <p>OPERA REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
