<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Firefighter to the Rescue Is Uneasy in the Spotlight</title>
    <meta content="11FIRE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flynn, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hurley, James (Lt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Tiffany F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0D71338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Firefighter to the Rescue Is Uneasy in the Spotlight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN FLYNN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flynn, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lt James Hurley, off-duty firefighter who came to aid of Tiffany F Goldberg after she was attacked on Manhattan street with concrete block, is uneasy with attention he is getting; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Yesterday, as Tiffany F. Goldberg sat recovering in her hospital bed, the memory of the misfortune that had befallen her remained blurry and confusing. But she clearly remembered the first thing she had seen when she opened her eyes after being hit with a five-pound piece of concrete.</p>
        <p>''Some gentleman was kneeling over me, trying to wake me up,'' she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Yesterday, as Tiffany F. Goldberg sat recovering in her hospital bed, the memory of the misfortune that had befallen her remained blurry and confusing. But she clearly remembered the first thing she had seen when she opened her eyes after being hit with a five-pound piece of concrete.</p>
        <p>''Some gentleman was kneeling over me, trying to wake me up,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The gentleman was an off-duty fire lieutenant, James Hurley, 44, who happened to have attended the same 10:30 a.m. service at Marble Collegiate Church on West 29th Street. After the service, Lieutenant Hurley had stopped for coffee at a doughnut shop. He was driving home to his apartment several blocks away in Stuyvesant Town when he spotted Ms. Goldberg being assaulted on East 29th Street.</p>
        <p>Initially, Lieutenant Hurley said, he thought of chasing in his car as the attacker sprinted east toward Lexington Avenue and disappeared. But he found himself unable to leave Ms. Goldberg, 25, who was lying motionless on the sidewalk, face down, with an open, bleeding wound on her head.</p>
        <p>''I shook her but she wasn't moving,'' Lieutenant Hurley said. So he rolled her onto her back and she began to come around. A passer-by gave him a shirt and he used it to stanch the bleeding. Someone else gave him a cardboard box to use as a pillow.</p>
        <p>''She asked me, 'Who are you and what happened to me?' I told her, 'I'm a fireman and my name is Jimmy,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>''Please stay,'' she said. Lieutenant Hurley replied: ''I'm not going anywhere. It looks like you're going to be O.K.''</p>
        <p>With one hand, he held hers. With the other, he kept the shirt pressed firmly against her head to slow the loss of blood as he went through the questions he had been trained to ask: What is your name? What day is it? Who is the president of the United States?</p>
        <p>She gave the right answers, and soon Lieutenant Hurley, a 17-year veteran, was able to turn her over to crew members of an ambulance that others in the gathering crowd had flagged down as it passed.</p>
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani said doctors believe that the lieutenant, who has training in cardiopulmonary resuscitation, helped greatly to stabilize Ms. Goldberg after the attack. He called to tell him so yesterday morning. Lieutenant Hurley spent the short moment of the phone call telling the mayor that his praise was unwarranted. He spent most of the afternoon telling reporters that his efforts were not worth the fanfare.</p>
        <p>''He is the quiet man,'' said Lt. James Walsh, a colleague. ''He never blows his own horn.''</p>
        <p>So, at Ladder Company 41 in the Morris Park section of the Bronx, where Lieutenant Hurley works, firefighters were preparing to create the perfect annoyances for a man who disdains attention: huge blow-ups of any article that proclaims his acts those of a good Samaritan. ''They can't wait to rub it in,'' Lieutenant Walsh said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
