<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Africa Faults Critics of Its President on AIDS Stance</title>
    <meta content="Y11MBE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mbeki, Thabo (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swarns, Rachel L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E2DE1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Africa Faults Critics of Its President on AIDS Stance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHEL L. SWARNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Swarns, Rachel L</byline>
      <dateline>DURBAN, South Africa, July 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>South African government, striking defiant and combative tone, lashes out at critics at 13th international conference on AIDS in Durban who expressed disappointment with Pres Thabo Mbeki for opening conference by describing extreme poverty, rather than AIDS, as biggest killer in Africa (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Striking a defiant and combative tone, the South African government today lashed out at its increasingly vocal critics at the 13th International AIDS Conference, saying there was no need for President Thabo Mbeki to affirm that the human immunodeficiency virus, H.I.V., causes AIDS.</p>
        <p>The government was responding to the chorus of criticism from prominent scientists, physicians and activists here who today expressed their disappointment with Mr. Mbeki. He opened this conference on Sunday night with a speech in which he described extreme poverty, rather than AIDS, as the biggest killer in this country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Striking a defiant and combative tone, the South African government today lashed out at its increasingly vocal critics at the 13th International AIDS Conference, saying there was no need for President Thabo Mbeki to affirm that the human immunodeficiency virus, H.I.V., causes AIDS.</p>
        <p>The government was responding to the chorus of criticism from prominent scientists, physicians and activists here who today expressed their disappointment with Mr. Mbeki. He opened this conference on Sunday night with a speech in which he described extreme poverty, rather than AIDS, as the biggest killer in this country.</p>
        <p>In recent months, Mr. Mbeki has consulted with two American researchers who argue that poverty and malnutrition -- and not H.I.V. -- cause AIDS, an argument that most established scientists say was debunked years ago. Today, in panel sessions and interviews, several participants said the president had squandered an opportunity to clarify his position and to take a leadership role in fighting the disease and preventing the spread of the virus, which has infected four million people here.</p>
        <p>Health Minister Manto Tshabalala-Msimang dismissed the criticism and accused the news media of distorting Mr. Mbeki's message. ''The president of this country has never denied either the existence of AIDS nor this causal connection between H.I.V. and AIDS,'' she said at a news conference today. ''But we reiterate our view that it is inappropriate to blame everything around this epidemic on the H.I.V. virus.''</p>
        <p>She added that ''clearly, the relationship between H.I.V. and other social ills afflicting our society such as poverty and disease'' is complex.</p>
        <p>But in the corridors and halls of the conference here, many participants remained perplexed and confused by the president's reluctance to say what so many people wanted to hear. Some wondered whether he was too proud to back down. Others wondered whether Mr. Mbeki, who is an economist and an intellectual, simply remains unconvinced of the links between H.I.V. and AIDS.</p>
        <p>No one disputes the link between poverty and H.I.V. and AIDS. Prostitutes, migrant laborers, the uneducated and victims of sexual violence are more vulnerable to infection. And poor people typically lack access to drugs that might prolong their lives.</p>
        <p>But scientists and researchers fear that Mr. Mbeki's heavy emphasis on poverty may confuse people and cause them to continue risky sexual behavior.</p>
        <p>Mark Wainberg, the president of the International Aids Society, the co-organizer of this conference, described Mr. Mbeki's speech, which was broadcast live on national television, as a ''lost opportunity.'' American officials said privately that they feared that Mr. Mbeki had raised broader questions about the quality of his leadership.</p>
        <p>A South African judge, Edwin Cameron, received a standing ovation after he delivered the conference's opening speech today and condemned Mr. Mbeki for wasting time on discredited theories while people were dying.</p>
        <p>''This has shaken almost everyone responsible for engaging the epidemic,'' Judge Cameron, who is infected with H.I.V., said of Mr. Mbeki's stance. ''It has created an air of unbelief among scientists, confusion among those at risk of H.I.V., and consternation among AIDS workers.''</p>
        <p>The health minister emphasized today that Mr. Mbeki was committed to combating the disease vigorously by encouraging safe sex and by sponsoring research on drug therapies and a possible vaccine, which has been applauded by researchers here.</p>
        <p>Dr. Awa Coll-Seck, the director of the United Nations' department of aids policy, said she was encouraged to hear Mr. Mbeki mention the program in his speech on Sunday night. But Dr. Coll-Seck, who is from Senegal, said she feared that the safe-sex message might get lost in the emphasis on poverty.</p>
        <p>''I was discouraged,'' Dr. Coll-Seck said. ''We were expecting him to be a leader.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
