<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In His Own Words</title>
    <meta content="Y11BWO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Assn for the Advancement of Colored People</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E5DC1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="635" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In His Own Words</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Text of address by Republican presidential candidate Gov George W Bush before annual conference of NAACP in Baltimore (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GEORGE W. BUSH  Speaking yesterday to delegates at the N.A.A.C.P. annual convention in Baltimore:</p>
        <p>'' For our nation there is no denying the truth that slavery is a blight on our history and that racism, despite all the progress, still exists today. For my party there is no escaping the reality that the party of Lincoln has not always carried the mantle of Lincoln. Recognizing and confronting our history is important. Transcending our history is essential. We're not limited by what we have done or what we have left undone. We are limited only by what we're willing to do.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GEORGE W. BUSH  Speaking yesterday to delegates at the N.A.A.C.P. annual convention in Baltimore:</p>
        <p>'' For our nation there is no denying the truth that slavery is a blight on our history and that racism, despite all the progress, still exists today. For my party there is no escaping the reality that the party of Lincoln has not always carried the mantle of Lincoln. Recognizing and confronting our history is important. Transcending our history is essential. We're not limited by what we have done or what we have left undone. We are limited only by what we're willing to do.</p>
        <p>Our nation must make new a commitment to equality and upward mobility to all the citizens. This is a great moment of national prosperity. But many still live in prosperity's shadow. The same economy that is a miracle for millions is a mystery to millions as well. From the beginning of this campaign I have said that prosperity must have a purpose. The purpose of prosperity is to ensure the American dream touches every willing heart. And we cannot afford to have an American segregated by class, by race or by aspiration. America must close the gap of hope between communities of prosperity and communities of poverty. . . .</p>
        <p>There is a higher and older tradition in my party. Lincoln argued that every poor man should have a chance. He defended a clear path for all. He financed colleges and welcomed immigrants, promoted railroads and economic development. Through the Homestead Act he gave countless Americans a piece of land, a start in life.</p>
        <p>I propose a new prosperity initiative that reflects the spirit of Lincoln's reforms. A plan to remove obstacles on the road to the middle class. You see, instead of helping people cope with their need, we will help them move beyond it.</p>
        <p>And here are some of the ideas of the new prosperity initiative, just some of the thoughts:</p>
        <p>We must provide a family health credit that covers 90 percent of the cost of basic health policy for low-income families in America.</p>
        <p>We must make it possible for more people to become homeowners in this great land, to own a part of the American dream. So we allow low-income families to use up to a year's worth of Section Eight rental payments to make a down payment on their own home. Then use five years of those payments to help with the mortgage.</p>
        <p>We will start an American dream down payment fund, matching individual savings to the down payment for a home.</p>
        <p>Behind these last two proposals is a simple belief. I believe in private property. I believe in private property so strongly, I want everybody to have some. . . .</p>
        <p>These are some of my goals for America. To help make opportunity not only a hope and a promise but a living reality. The N.A.A.C.P. and the G.O.P have not always been allies. I know that. But recognizing our past and confronting the future with a common vision, by doing that I believe we can find common ground. It won't be easy work. But a philosopher once advised, 'When given a choice prefer the hard.' We will prefer the hard because only the hard will achieve the good. That's my commitment. And that is our opportunity.''</p>
        <p>A full transcript of Mr. Bush's remarks is available from The New York Times on the Web: www.nytimes.com/politics</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
