<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poll Finds Optimistic Outlook But Enduring Racial Division</title>
    <meta content="11POLL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elder, Janet</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E2D81338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poll Finds Optimistic Outlook But Enduring Racial Division</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK with JANET ELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elder, Janet; Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nationwide poll by New York Times finds 35 years after dismantling of legalized segregation, majority of Americans say race relations in America are generally good, even though blacks and whites still have starkly divergent perceptions of many racial issues and remain relatively isolated from each other in everyday lives; both groups are most in agreement in perceptions of racial hostility; 39 percent of whites and 45 percent of blacks say they believe that almost all white people dislike blacks; 45 percent of whites and same percentage of blacks say many or almost all black people dislike whites; findings of poll detailed; charts (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thirty-five years after the dismantling of legalized segregation, a majority of Americans maintain that race relations in the United States are generally good, but blacks and whites continue to have starkly divergent perceptions of many racial issues and they remain largely isolated from each other in their everyday lives, according to a nationwide poll by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>The poll reflected some of the same complex tensions that have surfaced in The Times's six-week examination of contemporary race relations, ''How Race is Lived in America.'' The series has portrayed a stubbornly enduring racial divide, and the poll suggested that even as the rawest forms of bigotry have receded they have often been replaced by remoteness and distrust in places of work, learning and worship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thirty-five years after the dismantling of legalized segregation, a majority of Americans maintain that race relations in the United States are generally good, but blacks and whites continue to have starkly divergent perceptions of many racial issues and they remain largely isolated from each other in their everyday lives, according to a nationwide poll by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>The poll reflected some of the same complex tensions that have surfaced in The Times's six-week examination of contemporary race relations, ''How Race is Lived in America.'' The series has portrayed a stubbornly enduring racial divide, and the poll suggested that even as the rawest forms of bigotry have receded they have often been replaced by remoteness and distrust in places of work, learning and worship.</p>
        <p>The poll, which surveyed 2,165 adults, detected some signs that both blacks and whites believe race relations are improving. The proportion of those surveyed who said race relations in the country were generally good -- 57 percent -- was at its highest mark in 10 years, a full 16 percentage points higher than in 1990. Large majorities of both races -- 63 percent of whites and 79 percent of blacks -- said they approved of interracial marriage, compared with only 44 percent of whites and 70 percent of blacks who said so in a 1991 poll.</p>
        <p>And the percentage who said the country had made real progress in reducing racial discrimination -- 74 percent, including 78 percent of whites and 58 percent of blacks -- was about 25 percentage points higher for each group than in May 1992, just after the deadly rioting that followed the acquittal of four white Los Angeles police officers in the beating of a black motorist, Rodney G. King. The percentage of blacks who see progress has doubled in that period.</p>
        <p>But in question after question the poll also revealed a core of blacks -- about 4 in 10, many of them college-educated -- who find little to celebrate even today. Those blacks, for instance, said they thought that race relations in the country were generally bad and that there had been no real progress in eliminating racial discrimination since the 1960's.</p>
        <p>On many questions, particularly those related to whether blacks are treated equitably and whether race plays too large a role in the national discourse, blacks and whites seemed to be living on different planets. Blacks were roughly four times more likely than whites to say they thought blacks were treated less fairly in the workplace, in neighborhood shops, in shopping malls and in restaurants, theaters, bars and other entertainment venues.</p>
        <p>Indeed, one of the few areas where blacks and whites were most in agreement was in their perceptions of racial hostility. Similar percentages -- 39 percent of whites and 45 percent of blacks -- said they thought that many or almost all white people disliked blacks. And 45 percent of whites and the same percentage of blacks said they thought that many or almost all black people disliked whites.</p>
        <p>The continuing complexity of racial attitudes, and the awkwardness of discussing them forthrightly, came through clearly in the poll results. Taken as a whole, the respondents' answers offered a far more nuanced view of race than was apparent during the height of the civil rights struggle, when battle lines were more clearly drawn and bigotry was more clearly expressed.</p>
        <p>Befitting the subject matter, the poll was rife with seeming contradictions. Most striking, perhaps, was a telescopic pattern in which people of both races depicted themselves as far more sanguine about race relations in their own communities, and far more sensitive in their own views, than they believed to be the case elsewhere. Susceptible perhaps to the pressures of political correctness, they seemed to strive to depict themselves and their neighbors as open-minded and accepting while projecting less enlightened views on the rest of the country. And the farther from home, the worse things seemed.</p>
        <p>For instance, 88 percent of whites and 82 percent of blacks said race relations were generally good in their neighborhoods. Similarly large majorities of whites and blacks said race relations were generally good where they worked and at their children's schools.</p>
        <p>But the numbers dropped when people were asked to characterize race relations in their communities, and they dropped more precipitously when they were asked about race relations in the country. Fifty-eight percent of whites and 51 percent of blacks said race relations in the country were generally good, while 30 percent of whites and 40 percent of blacks said they were generally bad.</p>
        <p>Similarly, nearly all respondents -- 93 percent of whites and 95 percent of blacks -- said they would vote for a qualified black presidential candidate if one was nominated by their political party. And yet, most of those surveyed -- 55 percent of whites and 62 percent of blacks -- agreed that the country was not ready to elect a black president.</p>
        <p>In another example, 85 percent of whites said they did not care whether they lived in an area where most of their neighbors were white or where most were black. But two-thirds of the whites said they thought most white people preferred to live in white areas. And perhaps most telling, 85 percent said they actually live in areas where they have no or few black neighbors, the same percentage that said they had no preference.</p>
        <p>The poll, which was conducted June 21-29, surveyed 1,107 people who said they were white and 934 who said they were black. It has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus 3 percentage points for each racial group.</p>
        <p>To determine the views of the country as a whole, the responses of blacks were weighted to equal 11 percent of the total, the proportion used by the Census Bureau. According to the Current Population Survey, 11 percent of Americans are black and 89 percent are nonblack. With the exception of the prevailing pessimism expressed by college-educated blacks, the poll turned up few variations in responses based on geography, education, age or income among blacks.</p>
        <p>All in all, blacks and whites seem to feel that these times of relative peace and prosperity are good ones. Seventy-three percent of those questioned, including 73 percent of whites and 80 percent of blacks, said their opportunities for success in life were better than those of their parents. And 40 percent, including 39 percent of whites and 44 percent of blacks, said they thought the next generation of Americans would have a better future than their own. The proportion who said they believed things would get worse -- 31 percent, including 30 percent of whites and 35 percent of blacks -- was substantially lower than in past polls by The New York Times.</p>
        <p>But when questions focused more specifically on racial issues, a schism quickly emerged. Asked whether whites or blacks had a better chance of getting ahead, for example, 58 percent of whites said the playing field was now level, a view shared by only 39 percent of blacks. Fifty-seven percent of blacks said whites still had advantages, compared with only 32 percent of whites.</p>
        <p>There were similar gaps in black and white perceptions of how blacks are treated in various circumstances.</p>
        <p>Two-thirds of blacks, for example, said blacks were treated less equitably by the police, a view shared by only a quarter of whites. Forty-two percent of blacks said they felt they had been stopped by the police simply because of their race, compared with only 3 percent of whites.</p>
        <p>''Blacks are still having the same problems,'' said a 79-year-old retired black woman from Long Beach, Calif., who responded to poll questions and a follow-up interview but did not want her name published. ''Being black, you're discriminated against when you try to buy something you want unless you assert yourself. If the store is crowded, you're pushed aside because the sales clerks would rather wait on someone else. Progress means being considered on the same level with any other race.''</p>
        <p>Predictably, the variation in attitudes about equal opportunity and treatment gave rise to differing views about programs that make special efforts to help minorities get ahead. Blacks favored such programs 76 percent to 11 percent, while whites were ambivalent, with 46 percent saying they favored them and 44 percent saying they opposed them.</p>
        <p>The poll detected a surprising degree of social interaction between blacks and whites. Large proportions of both races said they had close friends of another race, 76 percent of whites and 84 percent of blacks. Similarly large numbers -- 69 percent of whites and 84 percent of blacks -- said they had socialized with someone of another race outside their homes in the last month. Forty-three percent of whites and 58 percent of blacks said people of another race had visited their homes socially in the last month.</p>
        <p>George Norris, 44, a black man from Baltimore, said he gets together every other month or so with colleagues from the moving company where he works. ''We shoot pool, have some drinks, have a cookout or watch some movies,'' Mr. Norris said. ''It's basically the same group of folks, white and black. They come over to my house or I go to theirs.''</p>
        <p>And yet the poll made it clear that most Americans do not live, work or worship with those of other races. Eighty-three percent of whites said they worked with only a few blacks or none at all. Ninety percent of whites who attended religious services at least once a month said that none or only a few of their fellow congregants were black, while 73 percent of blacks said that almost all of their fellow congregants were black.</p>
        <p>In general, whites expressed a certain fatigue with racial issues. More than half -- 54 percent -- said the news media devoted too much time to race. But 44 percent of blacks, by contrast, said that the media talked too little about race, while 28 percent said the media talked too much about it and 23 percent said the media devoted an appropriate amount of attention to it.</p>
        <p>Two-thirds of blacks also said that politicians talked too little about race, and the same number of blacks said that improving race relations was one of the most important challenges facing the country. Only one-fourth of whites said it was one of the most important challenges, while 65 percent said it was important, but so were other issues. And whites were more than three times as likely as blacks -- 33 percent to 10 percent -- to say that too much has been made in recent years of the problems facing black people.</p>
        <p>How the Poll Was Conducted</p>
        <p>The latest New York Times Poll is based on telephone interviews conducted June 21 through 29 with 2,165 adults from throughout the United States.</p>
        <p>Black Americans were sampled at a higher rate than normal to permit analysis of black attitudes in greater depth. From all national polls completed by The Times and CBS News since October 1998, every household in which a black respondent had been interviewed was recalled for the poll, as well as one-twelfth of the households in which a nonblack respondent had been interviewed earlier.</p>
        <p>Of the total in the new poll, 1,107 said they were white and 934 said they were black. There were too few respondents of other races to show their results separately.</p>
        <p>The original samples of telephone exchanges had been randomly selected by a computer from a complete list of more than 42,000 active residential exchanges across the country. Within each exchange, random digits had been added to form a complete telephone number, thus permitting access to both listed and unlisted numbers.</p>
        <p>Within each household, both in the original polls and the new poll, one adult was designated by a random procedure to be the respondent for the survey.</p>
        <p>The results of the new poll have been weighted to account for household size and number of telephone lines into the residence and to adjust for variations in the sample relating to geographic region, sex, age, marital status and education. Blacks and nonblacks were then weighted back to their proper proportion of the overall population.</p>
        <p>In theory, in 19 cases out of 20, the results based on such samples will differ by no more than three percentage points in either direction -- for blacks or whites -- from what would have been obtained by seeking out all American adults.</p>
        <p>For smaller subgroups, the margin of sampling error is larger.</p>
        <p>In addition to sampling error, the practical difficulties of conducting any survey of public opinion may introduce other sources of error into the poll. Variations in the wording and order of questions, for example, may lead to somewhat different results.</p>
        <p>Chart:''Differing Perceptions''  Has too much been made of the problems facing black people, has too little been made, or is it about right?</p>
        <p>BLACK:  Too Much -- 10%  Too Little -- 51%  Just Right -- 34%</p>
        <p>WHITE:  Too Much -- 33%  Too Little -- 18%  Just Right -- 42%</p>
        <p>Who has a better chance of getting ahead in today's society -- white people or black people? Or do they both have about an equal chance of getting ahead?Respondents who did not know or had no answer are not included. Respondents who did not know or had no answer are not included.</p>
        <p>BLACK  White people -- 57%  Black People -- 1%  People Equal -- 39%</p>
        <p>WHITE  White People -- 32%  Black People -- 6%  People Equal -- 58%  (Source: The New York Times poll)(pg. A1)</p>
        <p>Chart: ''Measuring Race Relations in America''  Black and white Americans remain largely isolated from each other in daily life and have starkly divergent views on many racial issues, according to The New York Times poll. That poll interviewed 934 blacks and 1,107 whites throughout the country between June 21 and 29.</p>
        <p>Thinking About Race</p>
        <p>In order to make up for past discrimination, do you favor or oppose programs that make special efforts to help minorities get ahead?</p>
        <p>How important do you think improving race relations is to the future of the United States -- do you think it's one of the most important things we need to do for the future, or it is important, but so are other issues, or it's not that important to the future of the U.S.?</p>
        <p>Do you think the future of the next generation of Americans will be better, worse or about the same as life today?</p>
        <p>Compared to your parents' generation, do you think in general your opportunities to succeed in life are better than theirs, about the same as theirs, or worse than theirs?</p>
        <p>Some people say that since the 1960's there has been a lot of real progress in getting rid of racial discrimination against blacks. Others say that there hasn't been much real progress for blacks over that time. Which do you agree with more? Would you say there's been a lot of real progress getting rid of racial discrimination or hasn't there been much real progress?</p>
        <p>Do you think race relations in your neighborhood are generally good or generally bad?</p>
        <p>Do you think race relations in the United States are generally good or generally bad?</p>
        <p>Talking About Race</p>
        <p>How comfortable do you personally feel when you have a conversation about race with someone of another race -- very comfortable, somewhat comfortable, somewhat uncomfortable or very uncomfortable?</p>
        <p>How comfortable do you think most people feel when they do have conversations about race with someone of another race -- very comfortable, somewhat comfortable, somewhat uncomfortable or very uncomfortable?</p>
        <p>Living With Race</p>
        <p>These days, do you think the media talk too much about issues of race, too little, or about the right amount?</p>
        <p>These days, do you think ordinary people talk too much about race, too little about race, or about the right amount about race?</p>
        <p>Think about the people who have visited your home in the last month for social reasons. Have any of those people been of another race?</p>
        <p>Do you personally know any white people who dislike blacks?</p>
        <p>Do you personally know any black people who dislike whites?</p>
        <p>Do you think that no white people dislike blacks, only a few white people dislike blacks, many white people dislike blacks or almost all white people dislike blacks?</p>
        <p>Do you think that no black people dislike whites, only a few black people dislike whites, many black people dislike whites, or almost all black people dislike whites?</p>
        <p>Leadership and Race</p>
        <p>If your political party nominated a black for president, would you vote for that person if he or she were qualified for the job?</p>
        <p>Thinking about black business-people who head large companies, would you say that there should be more or fewer, or is</p>
        <p>the number about right?</p>
        <p>About how many of the people who live in the immediate area around your home are black -- none, a few, about half or almost all?</p>
        <p>About how many of the people you work with are black -- none, a few, about half or almost all?</p>
        <p>About how many of the people at your church or synagogue are black -- none, a few, about half or almost all?</p>
        <p>About how many of the other customers at the places you usually go shopping, such as grocery stores or pharmacies, are black -- none, a few, about half or almost all?</p>
        <p>How much black history do you think public schools in this country teach -- too much, too little or about the right amount?</p>
        <p>Do you think most white people prefer to live in areas where most of their neighbors are white or most of their neighbors are black, or don't you think most white people have a preference?</p>
        <p>What about most white people you know personally? Do you think most of the white people you know prefer to live in areas where most of their neighbors are white or most of their neighbors are black, or don't you think most white people have a preference?</p>
        <p>What about you? Do you prefer to live in an area where most of your neighbors are white or most are black, or don't you have a preference?</p>
        <p>How much do you feel you know about the history of blacks in America -- a lot, some, not much, or nothing at all?  Graphs show percentages of blacks and whites to questions.</p>
        <p>(Percentages do not add up to 100 because Don't know/No answer is not shown)(pg. A23)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
