<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ezer Weizman, Under a Cloud, Resigns as President of Israel</title>
    <meta content="Y11WEIZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Joel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weizman, Ezer (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DD1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="732" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ezer Weizman, Under a Cloud, Resigns as President of Israel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenberg, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, July 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Ezer Weizman of Israel resigns, lowering curtain on public career that spanned more than half century of war and peacemaking but ended tainted by scandal; steps down amid report by state prosecutors harshly criticizing him for financial misdealings and warning from speaker of Parliament that legislature could move to dismiss him (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Ezer Weizman of Israel resigned today, lowering the curtain on a public career that spanned more than half a century of war and peacemaking but ended tainted by scandal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weizman's letter of resignation was delivered to the speaker of Parliament, Avraham Burg, who will fill the largely ceremonial post until Parliament chooses a new president on July 31.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Ezer Weizman of Israel resigned today, lowering the curtain on a public career that spanned more than half a century of war and peacemaking but ended tainted by scandal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weizman's letter of resignation was delivered to the speaker of Parliament, Avraham Burg, who will fill the largely ceremonial post until Parliament chooses a new president on July 31.</p>
        <p>Shimon Peres, a former prime minister and a Nobel Peace Prize laureate, is the candidate of the governing One Israel Party. His opponent, representing the rightist Likud Party, is Moshe Katzav, a former cabinet minister and a longtime legislator.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weizman, 75, whose second term as president was to have ended in three years, stepped down early after a report by state prosecutors that harshly criticized him for financial misdealings and a warning from Mr. Burg that the legislature could move to dismiss Mr. Weizman.</p>
        <p>The report by the attorney general, issued in May, found that Mr. Weizman had acted improperly when he accepted more than $300,000 in unreported cash from two executives from 1985 to 1993.</p>
        <p>The report said insufficient evidence and the statute of limitations prevented prosecution for suspected bribery, fraud and breach of trust. But it asserted that Mr. Weizman, who was a minister and a lawmaker when he received the money, had violated disclosure rules for officials.</p>
        <p>Although he is leaving under a cloud, Mr. Weizman, crusty and outspoken, enjoyed wide popularity in his seven years in office. He often stepped beyond the bounds of his apolitical post to dispense advice on peace efforts and to sound off on matters like homosexuality and the role of women, setting off lively debates.</p>
        <p>A hawk-turned-dove who is a former air force chief and defense minister, Mr. Weizman was an architect of the Camp David peace accords with Egypt in 1978. He advocated talks with the Palestine Liberation Organization years before the Oslo accords of 1993.</p>
        <p>A nephew of Chaim Weizmann, Israel's first president, and a member of Israel's pioneer generation, Mr. Weizman served in the British Air Force in World War II and helped organize the air wing of the Haganah, the Jewish armed force during the British Mandate in Palestine. He commanded the Israeli air force from 1958 to 1966, building the squadrons that destroyed Egyptian air power on the first day of the Arab-Israeli war in 1967.</p>
        <p>After leaving the army, he joined the rightist Herut Party, a forerunner of Likud. As the Likud's campaign manager in 1977, he directed Menachem Begin's upset victory, ending 29 years of Labor Party government.</p>
        <p>The landmark visit to Israel of President Anwar el-Sadat of Egypt in 1977 was the start of Mr. Weizman's conversion from hawk to dove. As defense minister in Mr. Begin's cabinet, Mr. Weizman played a pivotal role in the Camp David talks, establishing a quick rapport with Mr. Sadat and prodding fellow Israeli ministers to show more flexibility in the talks, which led to a formal peace treaty in 1979.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weizman left Mr. Begin's government in 1980, dissatisfied with what he considered the slow pace of peace efforts, particularly talks on planned Palestinian autonomy in the West Bank and Gaza Strip. In 1984, he ran in elections at the head of a small party that merged with the Labor Party two years later.</p>
        <p>As a minister in a Labor-Likud government in 1989, Mr. Weizman clashed with Prime Minister Yitzhak Shamir over meetings that he reportedly held abroad with the P.L.O., and he was stripped of his membership in the decision-making ''inner cabinet.''</p>
        <p>In 1992, Mr. Weizman announced his retirement from politics, saying that he could ''no longer contribute'' to peace efforts and that the Likud government was leading the country toward war. He was chosen as president a year later.</p>
        <p>Today, hours before he sent off his resignation letter, Mr. Weizman dispensed one last piece of political advice, urging Prime Minister Ehud Barak to forge ahead with the summit meeting this at Camp David, Md., with the Palestinians, despite the collapse of Mr. Barak's governing coalition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weizman, a former fighter pilot, described peacemaking as a battle. ''The prime minister,'' Mr. Weizman said, ''is acting like a commander in the field who knows that he may not have enough troops, but he has a goal to achieve, and he runs forward.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
