<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; The Classic That Lost Its Meaning</title>
    <meta content="11CHAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214053"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">All Star Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DD1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; The Classic That Lost Its Meaning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murray Chass Sports of The Times column holds baseball All-Star Game has lost its meaning now that leagues exist in name only, without presidents; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY will play baseball's 71st All-Star Game here tonight, and it will be the first played without league presidents. Sort of makes one wonder why they're even bothering.</p>
        <p>As in the first 70 games, from 1933 through last season, the game at Turner Field will match the American League against the National League, but it won't be the same. The leagues exist in name only. The baseball offices in Manhattan still have signs designating the league offices, but if summer tourists want to see them just to confirm their understanding of what the baseball structure used to be, they better visit soon. Neither the signs nor the offices will be there much longer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY will play baseball's 71st All-Star Game here tonight, and it will be the first played without league presidents. Sort of makes one wonder why they're even bothering.</p>
        <p>As in the first 70 games, from 1933 through last season, the game at Turner Field will match the American League against the National League, but it won't be the same. The leagues exist in name only. The baseball offices in Manhattan still have signs designating the league offices, but if summer tourists want to see them just to confirm their understanding of what the baseball structure used to be, they better visit soon. Neither the signs nor the offices will be there much longer.</p>
        <p>The league presidents have already disappeared. Their absence creates a void at the All-Star Game. Chub Feeney's old heart would ache if he were still with us, knowing there was no one left to carry on his practice of delivering a pregame pep talk, his version of win-one-for-the-Gipper, except in this case, the Gipper was an entire league.</p>
        <p>Katy Feeney, Chub's daughter and a high-ranking baseball official herself, explained that the old president's All-Star intensity had its roots in his longtime executive role with the Giants. ''He came from a team, and he lived and died by the team,'' she said. ''When he became National League president and had to be neutral, the All-Star team and the World Series team were his teams. He felt very strongly that the National League was the best.''</p>
        <p>Feeney urged the N.L. All-Stars to ''show our pride.''</p>
        <p>''We have a long history,'' he told the players. ''Let's show what we can do. Don't think this is an exhibition game. You guys are the best.''</p>
        <p>Feeney presided at 17 All-Star Games during his tenure, 1970 through 1986. The National League won 14 of the games, including 11 in a row from 1972 through '82, giving the senior league a run of 19 victories in 20 games.</p>
        <p>For 10 of the Feeney years, Lee MacPhail was the American League president. A forthright and gentlemanly executive, MacPhail didn't have Feeney's fire when it came to the game. ''I never gave them any speeches,'' MacPhail said the other day from his retirement home on Long Island.</p>
        <p>MacPhail rooted hard for his A.L. All-Star teams, but rooting obviously wasn't enough because the American lost the first nine games under his stewardship. ''I did lose a few,'' said MacPhail, no revisionist of history. He made a comeback briefly two years ago at the game in Denver. ''When they picked me to be honorary captain,'' he related, ''I said someone had failed to look up my record or else they figure the law of averages would catch up with me.''</p>
        <p>Leonard Coleman, the last N.L. president, and Gene Budig, the last A.L. chief, limited their pregame clubhouse visits to handshakes and hellos. But they at least were in position where if they ever felt the urge to erupt with verbal fire and brimstone, they would have had the players' attention.</p>
        <p>No one in either league is in that kind of position today because the leagues no longer have officials. Katy Feeney, in the N.L., and Phyllis Merhige, in the A.L., could be viewed as the highest-ranking league officials, which they became after the departure of Coleman and Budig. But they don't work for the leagues any more; they work for Major League Baseball. So even though each has taken care of her ''league's'' team here, neither was inclined to offer a pep talk tonight.</p>
        <p>''I don't have my father's erudition and charm,'' Feeney said.</p>
        <p>''I can't and I won't,'' Merhige said.</p>
        <p>Bud Selig could speak to the teams. But he's the commissioner of all of baseball. What's he supposed to do, go into the N.L. clubhouse and tell the players there to beat the bejabbers out of the other guys, then go to the A.L. clubhouse and urge the players there to do the same thing to the players he spoke to five minutes earlier?</p>
        <p>Maybe the managers could assume the role. On second thought, their credibility might be strained. Bobby Cox, the N.L., manager, played in the American League, and Joe Torre, the A.L. manager, played in the National League.</p>
        <p>What the game needs is a league lifer like Feeney. But the leagues are on the wane, too. In the first 67 All-Star Games, when a pitcher faced a batter, fans knew they were seeing the matchup for the first time that season. When David Wells pitches against Chipper Jones and Andres Galarraga in the first inning or two tonight, the encounters will look familiar. Jones and Galarraga batted against Wells only five weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Interleague games come, league presidents go.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
