<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Turn of the Tide, Bloodshed Rises in Los Angeles</title>
    <meta content="Y11ANG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gangs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Terry, Don</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5DA1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Turn of the Tide, Bloodshed Rises in Los Angeles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DON TERRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Terry, Don</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, July 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Violent crime resurfaces in Los Angeles at time when it has declined nationwide; city has experienced 7.5 percent increase in violence so far this year, compared with same period in 1999; resurgence attributed mainly to youth gangs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the middle of a sound sleep a few weeks ago, John W. Mack, the president of the Los Angeles Urban League, was awakened by a sound he had hoped had vanished from the night here:  the unmistakable rattle of gunfire echoing through the streets. The next morning, he awoke to learn that a man had been fatally shot 50 feet from his home. Several blocks away, a woman who had witnessed the shooting was ''blown away, too,'' Mr. Mack said.</p>
        <p>''For a while, it looked like we had turned a corner on this kind of thing,'' Mr. Mack said today before the start of another neighborhood anti-crime meeting here. ''But this violence issue is really, really out of control.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the middle of a sound sleep a few weeks ago, John W. Mack, the president of the Los Angeles Urban League, was awakened by a sound he had hoped had vanished from the night here:  the unmistakable rattle of gunfire echoing through the streets. The next morning, he awoke to learn that a man had been fatally shot 50 feet from his home. Several blocks away, a woman who had witnessed the shooting was ''blown away, too,'' Mr. Mack said.</p>
        <p>''For a while, it looked like we had turned a corner on this kind of thing,'' Mr. Mack said today before the start of another neighborhood anti-crime meeting here. ''But this violence issue is really, really out of control.''</p>
        <p>A seeming resurgence in violent crime has struck Los Angeles in recent months, at a time when, with only a few exceptions, violent crime is down nationwide. Compared with this time last year, the city has had a 7.5 percent increase in violent crime, including 58 more homicides, 97 more rapes, 106 more robberies and 1,437 more aggravated assaults, Los Angeles Police Deputy Chief Maurice Moore said.</p>
        <p>One of the most publicized cases was the killing of the 20-year-old granddaughter of the city's chief of police. She was shot as she sat in a car with a childhood friend. The friend, the intended target, was a gang member. He escaped.</p>
        <p>But the violence has been more widespread than was generally known. Out of the city's 18 police areas, 15 report increases in violent crime, with several stations experiencing what officials consider an alarming increase in homicides. The hardest hit, the Newton station, which includes parts of South-Central Los Angeles, has had 24 more homicides than a year ago, followed by the 77th police area, with 14 more killings. The Wilshire police area, where Mr. Mack lives, was actually one of only three areas that reported a slight decrease in violent crime.</p>
        <p>''That just goes to show that there is no sanctuary, no safe haven from violence,'' Mr. Mack said. ''Everybody needs to wake up and help.''</p>
        <p>The police blame much of the increased violence on the city's 65,000 ''identified gang members.''</p>
        <p>''What we're seeing is multiple gang frictions throughout the city,'' Deputy Chief Moore said, adding that there appeared to be no one reason for the increased violence. ''A lot of it has to do with turf and of course drugs.''</p>
        <p>But neighborhood advocates, like Najee Ali of Project Islamic HOPE and Earl Ofari Hutchinson of the National Alliance for Positive Action, say it is too easy to just blame the gangs. And police statistics seem to back them up. So far this year, according to the police, 42 percent of the city's homicides were gang-related, meaning the majority were not. Their causes included arguments, robberies, domestic disputes or the myriad reasons people kill.</p>
        <p>''There's a deep sense of hopelessness out there,'' Mr. Hutchinson said. ''We spend more money on prisons than on schools. And the leadership, particularly the African American leadership, has abandoned the inner city. All these factors are coming together, and I don't think this increase in the violence is just an up-tick. I think it's a long term trend.''</p>
        <p>Violence has certainly been part of the city's past. In the 1980's and early 1990's, street gang violence was almost as much a part of Los Angeles' image as sunshine and palm trees. There have been countless meetings of politicians, ministers, neighborhood advocates, gang members and grieving parents searching for ways ''to stop the violence and increase the peace.'' Those efforts led eight years ago to a well publicized truce among gangs. That and the improvement of the economy contributed to a lowering of the crime rate here and across the country.</p>
        <p>Now, though, some experts say, the coming of age of younger gang members is at least partly responsible for a resurgence of violence.</p>
        <p>Whatever the cause, the drive-by shootings, the meetings and the funerals are happening more often again. Dozens of people turned out today for an antiviolence meeting at the First A.M.E. Church, which became a shelter for hundreds of people during the civil unrest of 1992. The meeting was one of two held today to search for new and old ways to stop the killing. It was convened by Los Angeles County Supervisor Yvonne Brathwaite Burke and the speaker emeritus of the California State Assembly, Antonio R. Villaraigosa, a candidate for mayor in next year's election. The Los Angeles city attorney, James K. Hahn, another mayoral candidate, also attended.</p>
        <p>''We were patting ourselves on the back six months ago about crime going down,'' Mr. Hahn said. ''We have to recognize the work is not over.''</p>
        <p>The violence is not confined to Los Angeles. Mary Simmons, a 43-year-old home care worker, lives in Long Beach and she said she was ''scared everyday.''</p>
        <p>''I try to get into my home before 9 every night,'' she said. ''I've lost two nephews. We can't go to school because we got to work all the time to survive on almost no money. My son is 23. He's tired of struggling. He can't put shoes on his feet. I can't help him. I don't have any money.'' A tear fell down her cheek. ''We can't take care of our kids,'' she said. ''That's why we're losing our children to these gangs.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
