<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frisking Photo Puts Whitman On Defensive</title>
    <meta content="11WHIT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Camden (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Philadelphia (Pa)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Black Ministers Council of NJ</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharpton, Al (Rev)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Al Sharpton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania/Philadelphia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00EFD71338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1157" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frisking Photo Puts Whitman On Defensive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, July 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Photo of New Jersey Gov Christine Todd Whitman frisking black man as she patrolled Camden with state troopers in 1996 renews concerns about racial profiling by police and Whitman's sensitivity to inner-city residents; man was stopped for 'suspicious activity' but not arrested or found to be violating law; photo was subpoenaed by two troopers who sue state for discrimination; Whitman reportedly says she regrets taking part in frisk and was trying to learn dangers officers faced in Camden; Rev Al Sharpton and Black Ministers Council of NJ plan demonstrations around state and at opening ceremonies of Republican National Convention, which will be held across river from Camden in Philadelphia (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After enduring two years of criticism for the racial profiling practices of state troopers, Gov. Christine Todd Whitman is suddenly struggling with a self-inflicted public relations problem: a picture of the governor herself, grinning as she frisks a black man.</p>
        <p>The photograph, which was subpoenaed by two New Jersey troopers who have filed a discrimination suit against the state, was taken by a trooper during a trip Mrs. Whitman made with officers as they patrolled in Camden one night in 1996. The picture was obtained by The Associated Press and published in several New Jersey newspapers over the weekend (and on Page 1 in The New York Times on Tuesday).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After enduring two years of criticism for the racial profiling practices of state troopers, Gov. Christine Todd Whitman is suddenly struggling with a self-inflicted public relations problem: a picture of the governor herself, grinning as she frisks a black man.</p>
        <p>The photograph, which was subpoenaed by two New Jersey troopers who have filed a discrimination suit against the state, was taken by a trooper during a trip Mrs. Whitman made with officers as they patrolled in Camden one night in 1996. The picture was obtained by The Associated Press and published in several New Jersey newspapers over the weekend (and on Page 1 in The New York Times on Tuesday).</p>
        <p>It shows the governor in a baseball cap, dungarees and black Kevlar gloves, patting down a man whose arms are splayed against a graffiti-covered wall.</p>
        <p>The symbolism of the photo and the facts of the frisking -- the man was stopped for ''suspicious activity'' but not arrested or found to be violating the law -- have drawn criticism from civil rights leaders who have long questioned Mrs. Whitman's sensitivity to inner-city residents, and from the governor's political foes.</p>
        <p>The governor was at the National Governors' Association meeting today in State College, Pa., and her press office did not make her available to discuss the issue. But she told the A.P. that she regretted taking part in the frisk, and was simply trying to learn firsthand about the dangers that officers encountered in Camden, the state's most impoverished and crime-ridden city.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman said she hoped that the shock value of the photo -- which was taken  two years before racial profiling became the state's most consuming issue -- would not overshadow the fact that in 1999 she became the first state official to acknowledge that state troopers were singling out minority drivers for traffic stops, and went on to overhaul the force to discourage discriminatory practices.</p>
        <p>''That worries me, and for that I am deeply sorry,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The timing of the photo's release -- three weeks before the Republican National Convention in Philadelphia, just across the Delaware River from Camden -- could hardly be worse for the governor. Some of her supporters still hold out hopes that Gov. George W. Bush might choose her as a running mate, but Mrs. Whitman's close advisers say she is trying to position herself for a cabinet position or ambassadorship.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Al Sharpton and the Black Ministers Council of New Jersey are scheduled to meet this week to plan a series of protests around the state, and they said they would also hold a demonstration after the opening ceremonies of the convention.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it needs any explanation why it took her so long to understand the outrage over racial profiling -- she herself engaged in it,'' Mr. Sharpton said. ''You're not talking about speculation. You're not talking about interpretations. Here you clearly have a governor engaged in this and caught in the act.''</p>
        <p>Civil rights advocates and Mrs. Whitman's political opponents have pounced on the issue in the days since the photo first surfaced, calling the frisking a sign of her callousness toward minorities. Deborah Jacobs, executive director of the New Jersey chapter of the American Civil Liberties Union, said the search was also illegal because the troopers had apparently searched the man -- and found no contraband -- before turning him over to the governor.</p>
        <p>State Senator Wayne Bryant, a Democrat from Camden, said the photo would set back attempts to heal the state's racial divisions.</p>
        <p>''This would never have happened in white suburbia,'' said Mr. Bryant, who is black. ''In a state with a profiling problem, it sends a signal that you can do things to young African-Americans -- the kind of things that you wouldn't think of doing to other people. They reduced this individual to something less than a human being.''</p>
        <p>The photo was taken in the spring  of 1996, a year before Mrs. Whitman ran for re-election. Mrs. Whitman, who went on to take credit for bringing down New Jersey's crime rate during the 1997 campaign, enjoyed good relations with the state's law enforcement community at the time and said she wanted to spend a few nights working alongside the state troopers she had sent to roust Camden's violent drug gangs.</p>
        <p>In April 1998, however, the climate changed when two troopers shot three unarmed minority men on the New Jersey Turnpike, and the complaints of racial discrimination by troopers grew to dominate the state's political agenda.</p>
        <p>Details that have begun to emerge about the governor's midnight tour of Camden recall some of the serious discrimination allegations against the state police.</p>
        <p>Phil Moran, the lawyer who subpoenaed the photos, said a state police supervisor had offered an extra week of paid vacation to the troopers who were escorting the governor if they brought back a photo of Mrs. Whitman frisking a black suspect.</p>
        <p>The supervisor used a racial slur to refer to blacks, Mr. Moran said, and apparently thought it was funny to harass black civilians.</p>
        <p>The officer told Mrs. Whitman about the bonus vacation time, apparently without mentioning the racial element of the supervisor's request, and she agreed to be photographed, Mr. Moran said.</p>
        <p>But Jayne O'Connor, a spokeswoman for Mrs. Whitman, said today that the governor never knew that the trooper planned to exchange her photo for vacation time. The governor wanted to frisk a suspect, Ms. O'Connor said, because she wanted to take part in the same experiences as the troopers.</p>
        <p>In a May 1996 interview with The Courier-Post, Mrs. Whitman described her travels through Camden with the troopers and said the visit had helped her better understand the challenges facing inner-city parents. She did not mention taking part in a frisk. The governor also recounted the tale of one man who was searched, but was released after officers found he had $100 in his pocket. She told the paper that the man had told her: ''Not everyone you find with a lot of cash on them in Camden is a criminal, governor.''</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether the man she described was the man she frisked.</p>
        <p>Under New Jersey law, it is illegal for officers to conduct a search unless they believe a suspect is armed or has committed a crime, said Ms. Jacobs, of the civil liberties union.</p>
        <p>''It's disheartening that the war on drugs can lead some elected officials to trample on people's rights, to use people as props and to carry out searches as photo opportunities,'' Ms. Jacobs said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
