<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>K2 Design branches out into the risky realm of wireless services with acquisition of SilverCube.</title>
    <meta content="Y11ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paging Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SilverCube Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">K2 Design</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Unwired Ventures I</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paging Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0DE1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>K2 Design branches out into the risky realm of wireless services with acquisition of SilverCube.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>K2 Design, which handles Internet marketing for advertisers like Hewlett-Packard and IBM, will join with Uniwired Ventures I, a venture capital partnership, to indirectly acquire for $14.8 million a majority interest in SilverCube Inc; Silvercube is a wireless professional services company that specializes in strategy and content development for the new generation of cellular telephones, pagers, hand-held computers and other devices that deliver text in form of news headlines, e-mail and advertisements (Advertising column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A LEADING agency in the interactive services field is branching out with its first acquisition, entering the potentially lucrative but risky realm of wireless services.</p>
        <p>K2 Design Inc. in New York, which handles Internet marketing for advertisers like Hewlett-Packard, I.B.M., Philips and Standard &amp; Poor's, plans to announce today that it will join with a venture capital partnership to indirectly acquire for $14.8 million in stock and cash a majority interest in SilverCube Inc. A wireless professional services company, Silvercube works for marketers like General Motors and Edmunds, a clearing house for automotive data.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A LEADING agency in the interactive services field is branching out with its first acquisition, entering the potentially lucrative but risky realm of wireless services.</p>
        <p>K2 Design Inc. in New York, which handles Internet marketing for advertisers like Hewlett-Packard, I.B.M., Philips and Standard &amp; Poor's, plans to announce today that it will join with a venture capital partnership to indirectly acquire for $14.8 million in stock and cash a majority interest in SilverCube Inc. A wireless professional services company, Silvercube works for marketers like General Motors and Edmunds, a clearing house for automotive data.</p>
        <p>SilverCube, based in Rochester, Mich., specializes in strategy and content development for the new generation of cellular telephones, pagers, hand-held computers and other devices that deliver text in the form of news headlines, e-mail -- and yes, advertisements. K2 and Unwired Ventures I, a partnership of Emerald Ventures Capital in King of Prussia, Pa., will join forces for the deal and will operate four offices under the SilverCube name.</p>
        <p>The deal is indicative of the growing interest in the wireless Internet among agencies that were founded in the 1990's to capitalize on the boom in its wired counterpart. The ability to gain access to the World Wide Web through, say, a display panel on a cellular telephone or a personal digital assistant is appealing to marketers that want to aim sales pitches at consumers based on geography or demographics, as evinced by the formation of the Wireless Advertising Association.</p>
        <p>But there are daunting challenges associated with m-business (dial ''m'' for mobile) that range from technical shortcomings to disparate formats to the costs of gaining wireless access to the Internet.</p>
        <p>''Everybody is doing what they did with the Internet in '94, saying 'Here are the limitations of the current technology, therefore it won't be a component of everyday life,' '' Matt de Ganon, executive chairman at K2, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>''A pure-play wireless professional services company will help companies sort out the morass of competing issues,'' said Mr. de Ganon, who was joined by executives of SilverCube and Emerald Ventures in a telephone interview as they provided a preview of the coming deal.</p>
        <p>After the deal goes through, K2 will own 38.2 percent of SilverCube; Unwired Ventures I will own 35.3 percent; and current shareholders of SilverCube will own 26.5 percent.</p>
        <p>''What we saw in the people at K2 was their embrace of wireless technologies,'' said Greg Guidice, chief executive at SilverCube.</p>
        <p>''The devices will continue to change,'' he added, ''but as everyone becomes more and more familiar with the wired Web, we're finding they want to take information where they want, when they want, with wireless.''</p>
        <p>For instance, Mr. Guidice said, ''our Edmunds clients say they get phone calls on the weekend'' from car shoppers in metropolitan Detroit, where auto dealerships are closed on Saturdays, ''who want to compare the Oldsmobile Aurora to the Toyota Camry.''</p>
        <p>''They have to tell the callers to check out the Web site,'' he added. ''But with wireless, we give that ability to do comparisons by phone.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Guidice will serve as chief operating officer at SilverCube after the deal goes through; a search for a chief executive is under way. Mr. de Ganon and Lynn Fantom, president and chief executive at K2, will most likely join the SilverCube board. Gary W. Brown, chief operating offer at K2, will serve as interim chief financial officer at SilverCube.</p>
        <p>''I've been scouring the market for potential acquisitions,'' said Mr. Brown, who joined K2 in April from units of UBS, the Swiss banking company. ''SilverCube has done some pretty significant business in the unwired segment already with G.M., among others.''</p>
        <p>For G.M., SilverCube designed and introduced a way for users of personal digital assistants to visit a condensed version of the Oldsmobile Web site to obtain data like model specifications and dealer addresses. That is being expanded to the rest of the G.M. domestic divisions.</p>
        <p>Perhaps SilverCube could persuade Leo Burnett, the Oldsmobile agency, to revive a familiar ad slogan and promote the new wireless access as ''not your father's wired Internet.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
