<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="Y11DIG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214090"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DA1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Religious Organizations Seeking Radio Licenses  For months, Republicans in Congress have sought to block a Federal Communications Commission program to license hundreds of new low-power radio stations. About half of the first batch of applications are from religious organizations, mostly the sorts of fundamentalist churches active in conservative, Republican politics.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of evangelical churches are asking for space on the airwaves to spread the Gospel. Some simply want to read Scripture verbatim; others want to preach against abortion. They will not get the chance, however, if the Republican Congressional leadership gets its way. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Religious Organizations Seeking Radio Licenses  For months, Republicans in Congress have sought to block a Federal Communications Commission program to license hundreds of new low-power radio stations. About half of the first batch of applications are from religious organizations, mostly the sorts of fundamentalist churches active in conservative, Republican politics.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of evangelical churches are asking for space on the airwaves to spread the Gospel. Some simply want to read Scripture verbatim; others want to preach against abortion. They will not get the chance, however, if the Republican Congressional leadership gets its way. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>The Demise of a Celebrity Charity  After seven years, the writer Tom Clancy is scuttling a foundation that he set up to help children who had cancer and other grave illnesses use the Internet to talk with one another and learn about their diseases. Despite spending more than $5 million on travel, salaries, fund-raising and furniture, the foundation did not even have a Web site to show for its efforts. The legal fight that has broken out over the collapse of the foundation offers a rare glimpse at the inner workings of a celebrity charity. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Alcoa Profit Beats Forecasts  Alcoa said that its second-quarter profit rose 57 percent, beating Wall Street forecasts by two cents, as aluminum prices rose and productivity improved. Revenue rose 38 percent, to $5.62 billion. Shares of Alcoa increased 7 percent, or $2.0625, to $29.6875. They had dropped 33 percent this year. [C25.]</p>
        <p>Dow Rises as Other Gauges Decline  Stocks ended mixed in subdued trading, with blue chips pulling ahead and technology issues slipping. The Dow Jones industrial average rose 10.60 points, or 0.10 percent, to 10,646.58. The Nasdaq composite index dropped 42.91 points, or 1.1 percent, to 3,980.29, while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 3.28 points, or 0.2 percent, to 1,475.62. [C12.]</p>
        <p>President to Establish Fuel Reserve  Reacting to widespread concern over climbing heating oil prices and low inventories, President Clinton announced a plan to establish a fuel reserve for the Northeast, where most of the country's heating oil is consumed. [C2.]</p>
        <p>ICO-Teledesic Receives $300 Million  ICO-Teledesic Global Limited, the satellite telecommunications venture controlled by Craig O. McCaw, said it had received commitments for nearly $300 million from influential investors, including William H. Gates, chairman of Microsoft, and the private investment firm Clayton, Dubilier &amp; Rice. [C14.]</p>
        <p>Honeywell Issues Earnings Warning  Honeywell International warned that its second-quarter profit would be 75 cents a share, about 3 cents less than it had predicted earlier this year. Honeywell also lowered its earnings estimates for the full year and for 2001. [C8.]</p>
        <p>U.S. Sues Toysmart.com Over Data  The Federal Trade Commission sued to prevent toysmart.com, a bankrupt Internet toy retailer, from selling its database of customer information, asserting the company had assured hundreds of thousands of online visitors their personal data would never be shared with a third party. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Chilly Reception to EADS Offering  The European Aeronautic Defense and Space Company, or EADS as the new conglomerate that controls Airbus Industrie is known, received a chilly response from investors in its long-awaited initial stock offering as shares dropped more than 9 percent. Philippe Camus, a co-chief executive, responded by saying: ''You must be humble with the market. The market indicated to us the price it was ready to pay. End of story.'' [C4.]</p>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom Seeks a Partner  Deutsche Telekom of Germany, which is seeking an American partner, has made overtures to VoiceStream Wireless, a person close to the companies said. [C4.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
