<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Beanballs, Clemens, Piazza and Medwick</title>
    <meta content="11ANDE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Piazza, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clemens, Roger</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E3D71338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Beanballs, Clemens, Piazza and Medwick</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column on beaning of New York Mets' Mike Piazza by New York Yankees pitcher Roger Clemens recalls Clemens' reputation for throwing knockdown pitch; notes teammates suspect he may have been trying to hit Piazza, but not in head; holds helmet may have saved Piazza's life; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIS name is Clemens, not Clemency. When Roger Clemens first pitched batting practice in spring training a year ago, Derek Jeter stepped into the cage with his bat while wearing a catcher's mask, chest protector and shinguards. Off to the side, Chuck Knoblauch was dressed the same way.</p>
        <p>On the mound, Clemens laughed. So did the other Yankees who knew his reputation for ''throwing inside,'' the current politically correct euphemism for the beanball, the knockdown pitch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIS name is Clemens, not Clemency. When Roger Clemens first pitched batting practice in spring training a year ago, Derek Jeter stepped into the cage with his bat while wearing a catcher's mask, chest protector and shinguards. Off to the side, Chuck Knoblauch was dressed the same way.</p>
        <p>On the mound, Clemens laughed. So did the other Yankees who knew his reputation for ''throwing inside,'' the current politically correct euphemism for the beanball, the knockdown pitch.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees had never laughed when Clemens was an opposing pitcher. In a 1998 incident, Clemens, then with the Toronto Blue Jays, plunked Scott Brosius, prompting a scrum. Knoblauch had always wondered if his Texas A&amp;M background had provoked Clemens, from the rival University of Texas, to throw inside just for the fun of it.</p>
        <p>Clemens even drilled his former Boston Red Sox teammate, Mo Vaughn, for digging in too close to the plate. When the Mets repeatedly tried to pick Clemens off second base a year ago, he told their infielders, ''Do that once more and I'll put one in your ear'' -- a throwback line similar to the old ''stick it in his ear'' expression.</p>
        <p>So when Clemens's fastball smashed into Mike Piazza's helmet Saturday night at Yankee Stadium, Clemens's intentions were instantly suspect.</p>
        <p>Early last week Clemens had even predicted that he would be ''more aggressive'' in pitching to Piazza, who in 12 at-bats against Clemens had seven hits, including three home runs. And suddenly the Mets' catcher was sprawled in the dirt, dizzy with a concussion.</p>
        <p>The next day, Piazza branded the pitch ''definitely intentional.'' Clemens repeated that he was just ''trying to pitch him inside.''</p>
        <p>If the Mets thought they could prove in court that Clemens had intentionally tried to hit Piazza in the head with a weapon (a 90-plus-mile-an-hour fastball), the 37-year-old Yankee could be charged with assault; the hockey player Marty McSorley of Boston is now awaiting trial in Vancouver for assault with a weapon in flattening Donald Brashear of the Canucks with his stick.</p>
        <p>But only Clemens knows if he was intentionally trying to hit Piazza on the helmet or in the head.</p>
        <p>Considering Clemens's reputation, the belief here is that, yes, he was trying to intimidate Piazza by firing a flaming fastball near his head, just as the 6-foot-4-inch, 238-pound right-hander has intimidated so many other batters.</p>
        <p>But was he trying to hit Piazza in the helmet? No.</p>
        <p>Was he really aiming lower, hoping to hit Piazza in the back or the ribs and the pitch sailed a little higher? Maybe.</p>
        <p>Would he have done it over the weekend in Shea Stadium, where a pitcher has to bat? Maybe not.</p>
        <p>Whatever his intentions, if Clemens's fastball had somehow hit Piazza in the head, especially the temple, he could have killed the Mets' catcher. In 1920, another Yankee right-hander with a knockdown reputation, Carl Mays, fired a fastball that struck Ray Chapman, a Cleveland Indians shortstop, in the head. He died 14 hours later -- baseball's only fatality.</p>
        <p>But there's no way to tell yet if Piazza, scratched from tonight's All-Star Game, will be the same slugger who was batting .348 with 24 homers and 72 runs batted in. He knows it will take time for him to be completely comfortable in the batter's box.</p>
        <p>Joe Medwick was never completely comfortable after being beaned in the era before batters wore helmets. With the St. Louis Cardinals in 1937, Medwick had a triple crown season: .374, 31 homers, 154 R.B.I., and he's in the Hall of Fame. But soon after Larry MacPhail, the Brooklyn Dodgers boss, obtained him in a 1940 trade, he was beaned by the Cardinal right-hander Bob Bowman.</p>
        <p>The police and the umpires stopped Leo Durocher, the Dodger manager, and several players from charging the mound. When Bowman later departed through the Dodger dugout, MacPhail, with a swing from his Ebbets Field box seat, knocked his cap off.</p>
        <p>Medwick returned to bat .301 with 17 homers and 86 R.B.I. that season, followed by .318 with 18 homers and 88 R.B.I. in 1941 (when the Dodgers won the pennant) and .300 with 96 R.B.I. but only 4 homers in 1942. But he never led the league again. He never was the same hitter.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, Mike Piazza was wearing a helmet with an ear flap. It may have saved his career, if not his life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
