<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New China Flights Put Old Foes at Odds; New York, Chicago and 3 Airlines Lobby Hard for Lucrative Market</title>
    <meta content="Y11FLY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kennedy International Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">O'Hare International Airport (Chicago)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beijing (China)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shanghai (China)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Transportation Department (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Delta Air Lines Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Airlines</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Parcel Service of America Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Shanghai</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E1DC1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New China Flights Put Old Foes at Odds; New York, Chicago and 3 Airlines Lobby Hard for Lucrative Market</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City and Chicago are lobbying hard over which city will become take-off point for lucrative set of new flights to China scheduled to begin next April; in New York's corner is Delta Air Lines, which wants to fly to Beijing from John F Kennedy International Airport; American Airlines wants to fly from O'Hare International Airport in Chicago to Shanghai; bickering between Delta and American may help open door to another well-connected contender: United Parcel Service, since bilateral aviation agreement with China forces Transportation Department officials to choose between passenger and cargo carriers, rather than allocating routes to each separately; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For more than a century, New York and Chicago have alternated outdoing each other by building the tallest skyscraper in the United States. Their art museums have long competed for some of the world's great paintings. And their sports teams -- be it the Giants and Bears in the early days of professional football or the Knicks and Bulls in basketball more recently -- have repeatedly battled for championships.</p>
        <p>Now comes the latest skirmish in a long civic rivalry: the behind-the-scenes struggle over which city might become the take-off point for a lucrative set of new flights to China scheduled to begin next April. The decision -- due this summer from the Transportation Department amid a flurry of subtle lobbying from members of Congress and former top Clinton administration officials -- has added importance because of the increase in travel that is expected to follow China's entrance to the World Trade Organization.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For more than a century, New York and Chicago have alternated outdoing each other by building the tallest skyscraper in the United States. Their art museums have long competed for some of the world's great paintings. And their sports teams -- be it the Giants and Bears in the early days of professional football or the Knicks and Bulls in basketball more recently -- have repeatedly battled for championships.</p>
        <p>Now comes the latest skirmish in a long civic rivalry: the behind-the-scenes struggle over which city might become the take-off point for a lucrative set of new flights to China scheduled to begin next April. The decision -- due this summer from the Transportation Department amid a flurry of subtle lobbying from members of Congress and former top Clinton administration officials -- has added importance because of the increase in travel that is expected to follow China's entrance to the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>In New York's corner is Delta Air Lines, which wants to fly to Beijing from John F. Kennedy International Airport. With support from Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and much of the state's Congressional delegation, Delta executives are arguing that New York's size and economic importance so outweigh Chicago's as to make the decision an easy one.</p>
        <p>''New York is the most important aviation market on the planet,'' Leo F. Mullin, Delta's chief executive, said.</p>
        <p>American Airlines, which would fly from O'Hare International Airport in Chicago to Shanghai, responds that geography trumps demographics. The Midwest's unofficial capital is an excellent gathering point for passengers and offers a shorter trip to China, via the North Pole, American and its supporters say. New York, important as it is, is isolated from the rest of the country, they say -- a complaint New Yorkers have heard before.</p>
        <p>But even as the Big Apple and the Second City highlight each other's flaws, the bickering between Delta and American may help open the door to another well-connected contender: United Parcel Service. The bilateral aviation agreement with China, unlike any other in memory,  forces Transportation Department officials to choose between passenger and cargo carriers, rather than allocating routes to each separately.</p>
        <p>''We're sort of in new territory, in terms of the department trying to make an analysis,'' said Will Ris, American's senior vice president for government affairs.</p>
        <p>U.P.S. wants the same right to fly to China that its chief competitor, Federal Express, already enjoys. With the help of the Teamsters, its largest union, U.P.S. -- one of the biggest campaign contributors in the country -- has lined up a list of supporters that includes more than 300 members of Congress. ''This is our No. 1 international priority,'' said Tom Weidemeyer, the president of U.P.S. Airlines.</p>
        <p>The company's allies have inundated the Transportation Department with letters saying that the cargo business needs a new entrant much more than the passenger business does. Currently, Federal Express is the only American cargo company to fly directly to China, although U.P.S. flies to Hong Kong and its partners distribute packages from there. Northwest Airlines and United Airlines both now carry passengers to Beijing and Shanghai.</p>
        <p>''There has not been a more important carrier-selection case before D.O.T. since deregulation,'' more than two decades ago, American wrote in its official filing. It ''transcends aviation.''</p>
        <p>The passenger airlines argue that opening up their market to greater competition will promote travel between the two countries and accelerate the kind of political change the United States wants to see in China. U.P.S. says it can lower the price of shipping goods between the world's biggest economy and its most populous nation, thus increasing global trade.</p>
        <p>The carriers' deadline for making their official case has recently passed. A decision is due soon, but it already has taken longer than other cases because of the complexity of the filings, analysts say.</p>
        <p>''Frankly, nobody really knows quite what's going on right now,'' said Dale Bumpers, the former senator from Arkansas whom American has hired to help its case.</p>
        <p>President Clinton and Zhu Rongji, China's premier, negotiated the new aviation treaty at their April 1999 summit meeting here, when Mr. Zhu was willing to make concessions in an effort to persuade the Clinton administration to support China's entry into the World Trade Organization. The pact did not go as far as American officials and airline executives would have liked, but it allowed for the doubling of flights, to about eight each day -- split equally between American and Chinese airlines. And it gave each country the right to designate one more airline to fly between the countries.</p>
        <p>Even the airlines that already serve the market have become involved in the political maneuvering. Currently, Northwest flies to Beijing and Shanghai from Detroit. United flies from San Francisco to Beijing and, via Tokyo, to Shanghai. But in a move that most analysts consider an effort to ward off American's bid for the new flights, United has announced that it will switch the Shanghai flights to Chicago next April and no longer make a stop in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>The incumbents, including Federal Express, a unit of the FDX Corporation, have also applied for some of the 10 new weekly round trips that the Transportation Department will hand out. Still, lobbyists expect the new entrant to get most of them so it can establish itself. In addition, Polar Air, a small cargo carrier, has filed to become the new entrant, but it has little support in Washington.</p>
        <p>All along, federal law has barred the companies from directly lobbying A. Bradley Mims, the Transportation Department official who oversees the process. At a recent meeting of an international airline industry group in Sydney, Australia, for instance, Mr. Mullin of Delta said he had a long discussion with Mr. Mims, all about rules on how much noise airplanes can make. ''I didn't mention China once,'' Mr. Mullin said. (Through a spokesman, Mr. Mims declined to comment.)</p>
        <p>Instead, the airlines have hired some of Washington's best-connected lobbyists. Mickey Kantor, the former commerce secretary and top trade representative in the Clinton administration, has sent written testimony on behalf of U.P.S. And Mr. Bumpers helped American, a unit of the AMR Corporation, write its application.</p>
        <p>The companies have also asked their outside supporters to write letters to the Transportation Department, though executives are barred from asking the politicians to lobby Clinton administration officials more directly. Hundreds of mayors, governors and members of Congress have weighed in, breaking down along predictable geographic lines. Richard M. Daley, the mayor of Chicago and the brother of Vice President Al Gore's campaign chairman, backs American. Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, supports Delta. For either city, a victory would mean new jobs, more trade with China and a bigger tax base.</p>
        <p>One of the New Yorkers' biggest advantages is the imbalance that currently exists between the Midwest and East Coast. Detroit is already the take-off point for all of Northwest's flights to China. Once United makes its change, Chicago will have direct flights, too.</p>
        <p>''That makes American's bid redundant,'' said Jon F. Ask, the managing director of Global Aviation Associates, a Washington consulting firm not working for any of the applicants. Meanwhile, no airline flies between the East Coast and China.</p>
        <p>American's executives and their Midwestern supporters respond that Delta's flight would not actually help many eastern cities other than New York. Delta flies from only 29 domestic cities to Kennedy Airport, some 60 fewer than American and its regional partner, American Eagle, do at O'Hare. As a result, many passengers would have to make two flights just to get to Kennedy, the Chicagoans say.</p>
        <p>For example, a resident of Syracuse who wanted to travel to China only on Delta would have to fly first to Atlanta and then north to New York. In its filing, U.P.S. argued that many people would instead choose to fly Northwest through Detroit because it would be a shorter trip. The congestion in the skies above New York could hurt Delta's case, too.</p>
        <p>The more fundamental decision facing Mr. Mims and his colleagues at the Transportation Department, however, is whether they should award the new route to a passenger airline or a cargo carrier. Analysts say that decision is a close call.</p>
        <p>U.P.S.'s strongest argument is that it would become only the second American shipper to fly to China, while two passenger airlines based in the United States already do so. The company is supported by Northwest and United, which say they currently lose money on their flights to China. ''The market is terribly overserved,'' Gary Wilson, Northwest's chairman, said. ''I know everybody views China as a great new market, but it's been viewed as a great new market for 500 years.''</p>
        <p>U.P.S. does already fly to Hong Kong, however, and Chinese partner companies pick up and drop off packages there. According to an Arthur Andersen study commissioned by American, that service allows U.P.S. and DHL, which also lacks direct service, to get packages to the United States about as fast as Federal Express. U.P.S.'s shipments to China were somewhat slower, though DHL's were not.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Weidemeyer, the head of U.P.S.'s airline division, said the carrier's broad support, from politicians in every region in the country, indicates that it has the best application. Even some members of the New York House delegation whom Delta calls supporters -- Representative Louise M. Slaughter, a Democrat, for example, -- actually back U.P.S., according to letters they have written. They say Delta should receive the new rights only if the administration decides to select a passenger airline.</p>
        <p>The Teamsters have also written letters on behalf of U.P.S. and with Mr. Gore looking to shore up the support of labor leaders angered by his position on other trade issues, the union could be an important voice. Even American and Delta acknowledge that U.P.S. has built the strongest base.</p>
        <p>''They do have, probably, a political advantage because of the number of people they employ and because of the members of Congress they've signed up,'' Mr. Bumpers said. ''They operate not only in every state, but in every village of every state.''</p>
        <p>With all three airlines presenting strong cases, a host of considerations beyond the purely technical are bound to influence the decision. American and Delta officials hope that their backers in Chicago and New York will cancel out some of U.P.S.'s support and that the administration will decide new passenger service is simply more important. But only one can win.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing wrong with U.P.S.'s proposal or Delta's,'' said Mr. Ris, the lobbyist for American. ''The real problem is that we have been able to negotiate only one new carrier with China.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
