<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Response Polite As Bush Courts The N.A.A.C.P.</title>
    <meta content="11BUSH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Assn for the Advancement of Colored People</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Gary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Gary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5D81338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Response Polite As Bush Courts The N.A.A.C.P.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, July 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican presidential candidate Gov George W Bush addresses NAACP annual convention in Baltimore; admits that Party of Lincoln has been derelict in its treatment of blacks in latest bid to show he is different kind of Republican; pledges strong civil rights enforcement will be cornerstone of his administration; is given polite reception; is also jeered by opponents of death penalty protesting execution of Gary Graham by State of Texas (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush told the nation's largest civil rights organization today that ''the party of Lincoln has not always carried the mantle of Lincoln,'' and he pledged that ''strong civil rights enforcement will be a cornerstone of my administration.''</p>
        <p>In his latest bid to show that he is a different kind of Republican, the Texas governor quoted Abraham Lincoln's warning to a divided nation that ''we cannot escape our history.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush told the nation's largest civil rights organization today that ''the party of Lincoln has not always carried the mantle of Lincoln,'' and he pledged that ''strong civil rights enforcement will be a cornerstone of my administration.''</p>
        <p>In his latest bid to show that he is a different kind of Republican, the Texas governor quoted Abraham Lincoln's warning to a divided nation that ''we cannot escape our history.''</p>
        <p>''One hundred and forty years later, that is still true,'' Mr. Bush added. ''For our nation there is no denying the truth that slavery is a blight on our history. And that racism, despite all the progress, still exists today.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, to a large extent, simply retailored his stump speech for the thousands of delegates to the annual convention of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, and he won a polite reception. He did not cover several topics of interest to the delegates, including the death penalty, Supreme Court nominees and affirmative action.</p>
        <p>But his appearance provided a contrast with four years ago when Bob Dole, the Republican nominee, refused to speak to the group and accused its president, Kweisi Mfume, of ''trying to set me up.''</p>
        <p>Just as Mr. Bush was about to be introduced, four demonstrators rose in the Baltimore Convention Center and began protesting the execution last month of Gary Graham.</p>
        <p>''Remember Gary Graham,'' the protesters shouted. ''An innocent man was murdered by Governor Bush.''</p>
        <p>Frank Humphrey, the presiding officer, ordered the protesters removed as hymns were played.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham, the 135th inmate to be executed in Texas since Mr. Bush became governor five and a half years ago, went to his death proclaiming his innocence. The N.A.A.C.P. has called his execution a ''gross travesty of justice'' and wants a national moratorium on executions.</p>
        <p>When he began speaking, Mr. Bush quickly drew laughter by remembering how Jackie Robinson, upset by something John F. Kennedy once did, called the president a fine man but said he reserved the right to change his opinion.</p>
        <p>''For those of you who support me,'' Mr. Bush said, ''I see a couple here, maybe more than a couple: I hope you won't change your opinion. And for those of you who don't, I hope that at least you take Jackie's opinion as your own and give me a chance to tell you what is in my heart.''</p>
        <p>He made implicit reference to Mr. Dole and drew another round of applause when he said: ''I recognize the history of the Republican Party and the N.A.A.C.P. has not been one of regular partnership. But our nation is harmed when we let our differences separate us and divide us. So while some in my party have avoided the N.A.A.C.P. and while some in the N.A.A.C.P. have avoided my party, I'm proud to be here.''</p>
        <p>Black Americans represent one of the Democratic Party's strongest constituencies, and those Republicans who have appeared before the N.A.A.C.P. have not had an easy time. Mr. Bush's father, who was then the vice president, faced a chorus of boos and hisses in 1983 when he tried to portray the Reagan administration as sensitive to blacks.</p>
        <p>A year later both Mr. Bush's father and President Reagan cited scheduling conflicts in declining invitations to the convention and sent Elizabeth Dole, then the secretary of transportation. She was received politely but not enthusiastically. Mr. Bush's father did speak to the group as a presidential candidate in 1988.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush's reception today was polite, but he did not appear to have changed many minds. After his speech, a few listeners spoke of his courage in addressing a skeptical crowd. But many more listeners complained about the lack of specifics in the speech.</p>
        <p>''He's speaking to a moderate element of the Republican Party more than he's talking to us,'' said Thomas L. Jackson, a retired police officer from Ohio. ''The things he outlined are pretty vague.''</p>
        <p>Gary Bledsoe, the president of the Texas branch of the civil rights organization, said Mr. Bush, ''reduced some barriers today, but I don't think he won any support.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bledsoe praised the governor's tone and self-deprecation but said, ''people were crying out for specifics and substance.''</p>
        <p>Eleanor Holmes Norton, the nonvoting House delegate from the District of Columbia and a Democrat, said: ''Look, it is too late in American history for us to give any candidate points for showing up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush spoke of expanding opportunity and said, ''this begins by enforcing the civil rights laws.''</p>
        <p>''Discrimination is still a reality even when it takes different forms,'' Mr. Bush said. ''Instead of Jim Crow, there's racial redlining and profiling. Instead of 'separate but equal,'  there's separate and forgotten. Strong civil rights enforcement will be a cornerstone of my administration.'' He did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush put his usual emphasis on education and ending what he called ''the soft bigotry of low expectations'' for minority children. He promoted his plan to give parents in low-income areas vouchers that they could use for private schools if their children attend poor schools that failed to improve.</p>
        <p>The Texas governor said he wanted his party and the N.A.A.C.P. to find some common ground. ''This will not be easy work,'' he said. ''But a philosopher once advised, 'When given a choice, prefer the hard.' ''</p>
        <p>He has campaigned often in black and Hispanic neighborhoods, to underscore his theme that he is a ''compassionate conservative.'' And his campaign media strategist was on hand today filming the governor's speech, though Mr. Bush's aides said they had no plans, for now, to use the speech in commercials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush still has significant differences with the N.A.A.C.P., and not just over the death penalty. The group has been leading a boycott of South Carolina over the Confederate battle flag. During the Republican primary in South Carolina, Mr. Bush declined to take a stand on whether the flag should fly over the Capitol.</p>
        <p>As a tax-exempt group, the N.A.A.C.P. cannot endorse a presidential candidate. But the evening before Mr. Bush's appearance, the group's leaders urged members to mount an ambitious voter registration drive. Julian Bond, the group's chairman, argued that one more conservative vote on the Supreme Court could result in a setback for civil rights causes.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore and Ralph Nader, the Green Party candidate, are scheduled to speak to the group.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
