<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Honeywell Warns That Profit Will Fall Short for Second Quarter and Year</title>
    <meta content="Y11HONE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honeywell Inc</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDC1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Honeywell Warns That Profit Will Fall Short for Second Quarter and Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Honeywell International says second-quarter profit will be 75 cents a share, about 3 cents less than it predicted earlier this year; also lowers its earnings estimates for full year and for 2001 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Honeywell International, citing high raw material costs in some businesses, slow growth in others and high interest rates in all of them, told investors yesterday that its second-quarter profit would be 75 cents a share, about 3 cents less than the company had predicted earlier this year. The company also lowered its earnings estimates for the full year and for 2001.</p>
        <p>On June 19, Honeywell, a diversified industrial manufacturer, warned analysts that the quarter's earnings would fall short of their earlier expectations. That time, surprised and angry investors sent Honeywell's shares plummeting by more than 25 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Honeywell International, citing high raw material costs in some businesses, slow growth in others and high interest rates in all of them, told investors yesterday that its second-quarter profit would be 75 cents a share, about 3 cents less than the company had predicted earlier this year. The company also lowered its earnings estimates for the full year and for 2001.</p>
        <p>On June 19, Honeywell, a diversified industrial manufacturer, warned analysts that the quarter's earnings would fall short of their earlier expectations. That time, surprised and angry investors sent Honeywell's shares plummeting by more than 25 percent.</p>
        <p>This time, however, investors seemed to simply shrug. Honeywell fell 25 cents, to end at $34.75.</p>
        <p>''Investors priced their disappointments into the stock on June 19, and now they want to take a breather and see what happens,'' said David A. Kiefer, a portfolio manager at Prudential Global Asset Management.</p>
        <p>Indeed, most analysts kept their strong buy recommendations on the company, in part because the stock is now so cheap. ''Given where earnings are, and the company's ability to generate results, the shares should be trading in the mid-40's,'' said Howard A. Rubel, an analyst at Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>The earnings shortfall and lagging stock come at an unpropitious time for Michael R. Bonsignore, Honeywell's chief executive. Honeywell International was formed last year when Honeywell Inc., the Minneapolis company that Mr. Bonsignore ran, merged with Allied Signal Inc. Part of the deal was that Mr. Bonsignore would run the merged company when Lawrence Bossidy, Allied's well-regarded chief, retired.</p>
        <p>''Our fundamentals are strong, but yes, this has been a hell of a way to get started,'' said Mr. Bonsignore, who became chief executive in December and chairman in April.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bonsignore inherited many of the company's problems. Mr. Bossidy invested heavily in pharmaceutical and chip-packaging businesses, both of which have been bottom-line disasters.</p>
        <p>But the merged company has also had disappointing growth in industrial controls and fire security systems, two businesses that the old Honeywell brought to the party. And it has not been able to offset tripling oil prices with price and volume increases in its chemicals businesses.</p>
        <p>''There are problems on both sides of the portfolio,'' Mr. Bonsignore acknowledged yesterday. ''And if we hadn't been so distracted by melding cultures and otherwise making this merger work, we might have reacted more quickly to oil prices.''</p>
        <p>Analysts are giving him the benefit of the doubt, at least for now. ''We aren't ready to hang him yet,'' said David Bleustein, an analyst with PaineWebber. ''But if problems surface in 2001, they will clearly be on Michael Bonsignore's watch.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Bonsignore described several plans to keep that from happening. He said he would close the chip operation, taking a charge of $59 million, and would shed pharmaceuticals and friction materials. Most analysts think he is already negotiating sales of both.</p>
        <p>He said he might spin off part of Honeywell's new microturbine business to shareholders, a move that could generate a huge amount of cash. Last month Capstone Turbine, which also makes microturbines -- small, clean-burning power generators -- went public at $16; it closed yesterday at $59.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bonsignore also promised to reduce costs by an additional $100 million a quarter over the next two to three years and to use attrition to trim 5,000 jobs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bonsignore would use the resulting cash to reduce Honeywell's debt-to-capital ratio, now a troubling 42 percent. He would like to flesh out the company's core aircraft parts and industrial controls businesses with more acquisitions. And he wants to buy back stock.</p>
        <p>''At this price, a share buyback would certainly be a compelling, high priority use of our cash,'' Mr. Bonsignore said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
