<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Web Hardware Maker Buys Digital 'Plumber' for $41 Billion</title>
    <meta content="Y11TEC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jds Uniphase Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sdl Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EEDD1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Web Hardware Maker Buys Digital 'Plumber' for $41 Billion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>JDS Uniphase, maker of optical components, will buy SDL Inc, maker of lasers, for $41 billion, strengthening its position as provider of components for optical communication networks; graph; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mention ''new economy'' and just what comes to mind? For many people, dot-com companies, fancy Web sites, piles of cash.</p>
        <p>Those are all fine images, but these days, the big money in the new economy is being made not by dot-coms but by the digital plumbers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mention ''new economy'' and just what comes to mind? For many people, dot-com companies, fancy Web sites, piles of cash.</p>
        <p>Those are all fine images, but these days, the big money in the new economy is being made not by dot-coms but by the digital plumbers.</p>
        <p>Most people probably never heard of the company that makes the valves inside the pumps at their local water treatment plant. And they probably never heard of SDL Inc., either. But that can hardly bother SDL's investors, because the company announced yesterday that it had agreed to be acquired by the JDS Uniphase Corporation for $41 billion in stock.</p>
        <p>That is more than the market values of Amazon.com, the At Home Corporation, eBay and Priceline.com combined.</p>
        <p>Modern cities are not possible without plumbing, and the wildfire spread of data communications and the Internet is not possible without the sort of arcane components for fiber optic networks (think lasers and amplifiers) made by companies like JDS Uniphase and SDL.</p>
        <p>That is not an original thought; over the last year, investors have bid up the price of JDS Uniphase fivefold. But beside the stock levitation, the financial muscle of the new economy's plumbers has been felt in explosive initial public offerings and in rich acquisitions of private companies.</p>
        <p>But SDL, based in San Jose, Calif., is publicly traded, on Nasdaq. And now the plumbers have announced what may just be the biggest technology takeover yet.</p>
        <p>Under the deal, each share of SDL would be exchanged for 3.8 shares of JDS Uniphase. JDS Uniphase's shares closed on Friday at $116.1875, making the transaction worth $441.5125 for each share of SDL. SDL's shares, meanwhile, closed Friday at $295.3125, giving the company's investors a takeover premium of almost 50 percent.</p>
        <p>By the time trading was over yesterday, the value of the deal had declined substantially. With such a wide spread between the implied value of the deal, as announced, and where SDL's shares had been trading, the arbitrage opportunity was obvious. Shares of JDS Uniphase fell $15.0625, to $101.125, while SDL jumped $25.375, to $320.6875.</p>
        <p>But even with those moves, shares of SDL did not end up close to JDL Uniphase's bid. With the slide yesterday in shares of JDS Uniphase, the deal is now worth $384.275 for each share of SDL, which means that SDL could still be described as undervalued by more than 19 percent.</p>
        <p>What that probably represents is uncertainty among arbitragers and institutional investors that the deal will be completed. After all, it must be reviewed by the Justice Department, which imposed some conditions on JDS Uniphase's last big acquisition, of E-Tek Dynamics Inc., for about $20 billion earlier this year.</p>
        <p>But what is almost certain is that optical networking technology will in some ways remain the technical foundation of the communications revolution. That is because optical networks are generally the most cost-effective way to transmit gargantuan amounts of two-way information from one point to another, especially in the industrialized world.</p>
        <p>Copper wires like those used to connect most homes to the telephone network also used to be employed for regional and transcontinental networks. But optical networks, which transmit information using pulses of light modulated by lasers, can be much more efficient than copper networks that use pulses of electricity.</p>
        <p>Big communications carriers like the AT&amp;T Corporation and WorldCom Inc. buy optical communications systems from big equipment vendors like Lucent Technologies Inc. and the Nortel Networks Corporation of Canada. This is like a city turning to a water treatment company for a water treatment plant. In turn, companies like Lucent and Nortel assemble their systems from components and modules often bought from companies like JDS Uniphase. This is like the water treatment company turning to another concern for advanced pumps.</p>
        <p>Companies like JDS Uniphase then buy more specialized parts from companies like SDL. This is like the pump company contracting with another company for specialized valves.</p>
        <p>But imagine that only a few companies could make the valves needed. And imagine that the overall capacity of the water treatment plant was closely linked to the performance of those valves. Then it becomes clear that the valve company is quite valuable.</p>
        <p>''Let me put it to you in a simple way,'' Anthony R. Muller, JDS Uniphase's chief financial officer, said in a telephone interview yesterday. ''Think of Amazon and eBay and any number of other companies that are of this genre. They all require bandwidth to deliver their products and services. And we and our competitors make the fundamental underlying technology that provides the amount of bandwidth that is required for the Internet.''</p>
        <p>In a statement, Don Scifres, SDL's chairman, said, ''This combination brings together world-class technical and manufacturing teams that promise to deliver best-in-class products at increased volumes for today's systems while developing solutions for tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>Jozef Straus, the co-chairman and chief executive of JDS Uniphase, said in a statement, ''JDS Uniphase and SDL share a common vision to provide customers with the most innovative and technologically advanced products that enhance their ability to deliver next-generation optical systems.''</p>
        <p>SDL specializes in a laser known as a pump laser and in components that are used to make laser systems. JDS Uniphase is hoping that by acquiring the company, it will be able to direct SDL's research in ways that are more complementary to its own technical plans.</p>
        <p>As that happens, the dot-com companies will continue to be the most visible element of this new economy. And that will not trouble the plumbers one bit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
