<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Edgy City Series</title>
    <meta content="11TUE3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2DC1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Edgy City Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Setting aside the frightening fact that one of Roger Clemens's 90-mile-an-hour fastballs beaned and concussed Mike Piazza, the New York Mets' All-Star catcher, the rousing four-game series between the Yankees and Mets was everything that organized baseball had hoped for when it introduced midseason interleague play in 1997. New York, of course, is unusual. There is only one other major league city, Chicago, with two teams in different leagues, and one would expect more interest in a crosstown rivalry than, say, an intrastate rivalry like St. Louis and Kansas City. Even so, the excitement reached World Series levels from the very first pitch, and when the last out had been recorded at Shea Stadium on Sunday night, New Yorkers had been treated to some sterling baseball and a few memorable moments.</p>
        <p>Wearing a Yankee uniform, Dwight Gooden made an emotional return to Shea, where, as a Met, he enjoyed his greatest triumphs during the 1980's before his personal life spiraled out of control. Gooden was unemployed in late May when George Steinbrenner, with the benevolence he often shows to former employees, reached out and gave him a minor league contract. Gooden responded by pitching five strong innings in the front end of an unusual home-and-home doubleheader, with the first game at the Mets' ballpark in Queens, the nightcap at Yankee Stadium in the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Setting aside the frightening fact that one of Roger Clemens's 90-mile-an-hour fastballs beaned and concussed Mike Piazza, the New York Mets' All-Star catcher, the rousing four-game series between the Yankees and Mets was everything that organized baseball had hoped for when it introduced midseason interleague play in 1997. New York, of course, is unusual. There is only one other major league city, Chicago, with two teams in different leagues, and one would expect more interest in a crosstown rivalry than, say, an intrastate rivalry like St. Louis and Kansas City. Even so, the excitement reached World Series levels from the very first pitch, and when the last out had been recorded at Shea Stadium on Sunday night, New Yorkers had been treated to some sterling baseball and a few memorable moments.</p>
        <p>Wearing a Yankee uniform, Dwight Gooden made an emotional return to Shea, where, as a Met, he enjoyed his greatest triumphs during the 1980's before his personal life spiraled out of control. Gooden was unemployed in late May when George Steinbrenner, with the benevolence he often shows to former employees, reached out and gave him a minor league contract. Gooden responded by pitching five strong innings in the front end of an unusual home-and-home doubleheader, with the first game at the Mets' ballpark in Queens, the nightcap at Yankee Stadium in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>The Yankees won three of the four games and local bragging rights, at least for now. It is conceivable that the two teams will meet again in October, since both have the talent to win their respective league championships. Perhaps by then both teams will have forgotten the ugly beaning incident. Clemens insists that he did not throw deliberately at Piazza. The Mets suspect the worst, however, because historically Piazza has treated Clemens's pitching roughly, and also because Clemens had good control of his pitches when facing all the other Mets. Players have long memories, and at least for the remainder of this season, the Mets-Yankees rivalry is likely to be characterized by good baseball and bad blood.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
