<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Untimely Turbulence in Israel</title>
    <meta content="11TUE1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E2DC1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Untimely Turbulence in Israel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial calls unfortunate decision by center-right parties in Israeli Prime Min Ehud Barak's coalition to desert him on eve of crucial Camp David peace summit with Pres Clinton and Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat; says summit can only succeed if both leaders are ready to deal, and that Barak appears ready to do so despite collapse of cabinet majority (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is unfortunate that the center-right parties in Prime Minister Ehud Barak's coalition have deserted the Israeli leader just as peacemaking in the Middle East reaches a critical juncture this week at Camp David. Had they not resigned from the cabinet Sunday, and voted against him in a failed no-confidence vote yesterday, the parties could have helped shape the agreement Mr. Barak hopes to negotiate with the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Barak will have to proceed on his own considerable authority. Just over a year ago 56 percent of Israeli voters elected him prime minister on a platform of negotiating peace with the Palestinians. Under recent changes in Israeli election law, prime ministers are directly elected, making them less dependent on Parliament's shifting coalitions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is unfortunate that the center-right parties in Prime Minister Ehud Barak's coalition have deserted the Israeli leader just as peacemaking in the Middle East reaches a critical juncture this week at Camp David. Had they not resigned from the cabinet Sunday, and voted against him in a failed no-confidence vote yesterday, the parties could have helped shape the agreement Mr. Barak hopes to negotiate with the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat.</p>
        <p>Instead, Mr. Barak will have to proceed on his own considerable authority. Just over a year ago 56 percent of Israeli voters elected him prime minister on a platform of negotiating peace with the Palestinians. Under recent changes in Israeli election law, prime ministers are directly elected, making them less dependent on Parliament's shifting coalitions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak heads to Camp David rightly determined to rise above party politics and work hard for an honorable peace.</p>
        <p>The main issues awaiting him and Mr. Arafat are delineating borders between Israeli- and Palestinian-ruled territory, resolving competing claims over greater Jerusalem and defining the rights of Jewish settlers and Palestinian refugees. Mr. Barak has long promised Israelis that there are clear ''red lines'' beyond which he will not compromise on these issues. He insists, for example, that the city of Jerusalem will remain united and under Israeli sovereignty, and he has promised that a majority of Jewish settlers will be able to stay in the West Bank.</p>
        <p>But within these parameters, Mr. Barak has wisely left room to negotiate with Mr. Arafat. If the Palestinians are prepared to make compromises on these sensitive issues, a fair agreement can be reached. Should he come home with an honorable deal, Mr. Barak will have a good chance of getting it approved by a majority of voters, either in a special referendum or through new national elections. It is a reasonable assumption that many of the Russian immigrants and Sephardic Jews whose party leaders quit the government this week would themselves welcome a realistic peace agreement.</p>
        <p>President Clinton summoned Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat to Camp David because lower-level negotiations had reached a dangerous impasse. The unresolved questions are the hard ones, and only the top leaders have the authority to make the necessary compromises. Mr. Clinton should be ready to back them up with American guarantees, promises of financial aid and even draft diplomatic language. But this summit meeting can succeed only if the two leaders themselves are ready to deal. Mr. Barak appears ready to do so, despite the untimely collapse of his cabinet majority.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
