<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Syrians Vote To Confirm Assad's Son As President</title>
    <meta content="Y11SYR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Assad, Bashar Al-</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kifner, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DD1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Syrians Vote To Confirm Assad's Son As President</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN KIFNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kifner, John</byline>
      <dateline>BEIRUT, Lebanon, July 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Syrians vote in referendum to confirm Bashar al-Assad, sole candidate, as president; swearing-in scheduled for July 13 (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Syrians lined up to vote today in a referendum to confirm Bashar al-Assad as president.</p>
        <p>It was hardly a cliffhanger. Indeed, Mr. Assad was the sole candidate, and the swearing-in was already scheduled for Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Syrians lined up to vote today in a referendum to confirm Bashar al-Assad as president.</p>
        <p>It was hardly a cliffhanger. Indeed, Mr. Assad was the sole candidate, and the swearing-in was already scheduled for Thursday.</p>
        <p>He is the son of Hafez al-Assad, who ruled with an iron fist for 30 years. The election today was part of a programmed process by the governing Baath Party and an inner circle of the late president to provide the trappings of legitimate succession. Portraits of Bashar al-Assad, once a little-known eye doctor, flooded Damascus today.</p>
        <p>In quick tempo after President Assad's death on June 10, the Constitution was amended to make the minimum age for the presidency 34, Bashar al-Assad's age. He was also promoted to lieutenant general and commander of the army, named head of the Baath Party Regional Command and endorsed for president by acclaim in a parliamentary session that ran an extra day because so many people wanted to be recorded in support.</p>
        <p>As Prime Minister Muhammad Miru, who was appointed in March with Bashar al-Assad's backing, voted, he said, ''The people gave their opinion before the referendum by choosing Bashar as president.''</p>
        <p>A long-serving previous prime minister, Mahmoud Zubi, committed suicide on May 21 as security forces arrived to arrest him in what was generally described as an anticorruption drive spearheaded by Bashar al-Assad that purged a number of formerly powerful officials.</p>
        <p>The voting today -- extended, officials said, for popular demand -- consisted of marking a ballot in a green circle signifying approval of Mr. Assad or a negative gray circle.</p>
        <p>Several polling places offered an unusual accessory, an array of safety pins or sewing needles with which voters could prick their thumbs and mark the circles in blood.</p>
        <p>Basil Hassan, 18, voting at a school where he was taking a free 15-day computer course sponsored by Bashar al-Assad in his only previous official role as head of the Syrian Computer Society, marked his ballot with a bloody thumbprint.</p>
        <p>''We already sacrificed a lot of blood for our country in peace and war,'' Mr. Hassan said. ''We will sacrifice more of our blood and our country for Dr. Bashar. He is a student in his father's school, and he will continue in his footsteps.''</p>
        <p>Officials in one voting place open to foreign reporters looked shocked when a women marked her ballot in blood in the gray ''no'' circle instead of the green approval circle. She quickly realized her error, however, and was given another ballot to commend the new government.</p>
        <p>In the polling place where Mr. Miru voted, an official assured reporters that not 1 of the 435 votes cast in the first four hours of the referendum had been negative.</p>
        <p>Foreign Minister Farouk al-Shara said to reporters after casting his ballot: ''There has been a lot of betting on the succession, that the absence of Assad would lead to instability and ambiguity. We thank God that all these bets have failed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
