<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="11TRN.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5D61338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>National League  METS -- Optioned RHP Eric Cammack to Norfolk of the International League. Recalled LHP Rich Rodriguez from Norfolk.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association  WNBA -- Fined Utah coach Fred Williams $1,500 for verbally abusing the referees and failing to leave the court in a timely manner following his ejection in a game against Detroit July 7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>National League  METS -- Optioned RHP Eric Cammack to Norfolk of the International League. Recalled LHP Rich Rodriguez from Norfolk.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association  WNBA -- Fined Utah coach Fred Williams $1,500 for verbally abusing the referees and failing to leave the court in a timely manner following his ejection in a game against Detroit July 7.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  BUFFALO BILLS -- Signed WR Avion Black to a three-year contract.  CLEVELAND BROWNS -- Agreed to terms with DE Eric Chandler, DB Rashidi Barnes, OL Manuia Savea and OL Brad Bedell, on four-year contracts.  GREEN BAY PACKERS -- Signed LB Eugene McCaslin to a multiyear contract. Placed QB Ben Sankey on waivers.  KANSAS CITY CHIEFS -- Agreed to terms with TE Rickey Brady on a two-year contract.  JETS -- Signed DE Shaun Ellis and LB John Abraham to five-year contracts.  SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS -- Announced that S Tim McDonald has retired.  TENNESSEE TITANS -- Signed RB Mike Green.  WASHINGTON REDSKINS -- Signed CB Lloyd Harrison to a four-year contract.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  ATLANTA THRASHERS -- Acquired F-D Steve Staios from the New Jersey Devils for future considerations.  CAROLINA HURRICANES -- Signed F Ian McNeil to a multiyear contract.  MINNESOTA WILD -- Named Chris Hansen president and Jim Ibister vice president of the St. Paul Arena Company.  NEW YORK RANGERS -- Signed D Vladimir Malakhov to a four-year contract plus an option year.</p>
        <p>AUTO RACING</p>
        <p>NASCAR -- Fined crew chief Jimmy Fenning $25,000 for having his car under the required height and crew chief Gary DeHart $7,000 for improperly attaching added weight to his car for the thatlook.com 300 held on July 9.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  NEW ENGLAND REVOLUTION -- Signed F Jose Luis Morales.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>ALABAMA-BIRMINGHAM -- Announced the retirement of Gene Bartow, athletic director.  BROWN -- Announced the resignation of Peter Lasagna, men's lacrosse coach, so he can take the same position at Bates.  IOWA -- Named Garland O'Keefe women's swimming coach.  NORTH CAROLINA -- Named Todd Cavallaro men's assistant lacrosse coach and Nunzio Esposto diving coach.  NORTHERN KENTUCKY -- Announced the retirement of Mary Biermann, women's volleyball coach, effective at the end of the 2000 season.  OKLAHOMA STATE -- Named Tanya Ray women's assistant basketball coach.  PORTLAND -- Named Lemont Daniels and Bob Lowe men's assistant basketball coaches.  PROVIDENCE -- Named Phil Seymore men's assistant basketball coach.  TEMPLE -- Named Ervin Monier women's assistant basketball coach.  VILLANOVA -- Named Vince Nicastro athletic director.  VIRGINIA TECH -- Named Lisa Hart women's tennis coach.  WAKE FOREST -- Named Larry Leonard women's assistant basketball coach.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
