<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conseco Chief Got Big Bonus For Signing On</title>
    <meta content="Y11CONS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conseco Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wendt, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bonuses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE7DB1338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conseco Chief Got Big Bonus For Signing On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Conseco Inc says it paid George C Wendt signing bonus of $45 million when he was hired in June as chairman and chief executive; Wendt was also given 3.2 million shares of stock, now worth $31.2 million, as well as options to buy 10 million more shares; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gary C. Wendt took the cash up front when he agreed to become chairman and chief executive of Conseco Inc., the company disclosed yesterday.</p>
        <p>Conseco, the troubled insurance and financial services company, said that it paid Mr. Wendt a signing bonus of $45 million when he joined the company last month. He was also given 3.2 million shares of stock, now worth $31.2 million, as well as options to buy 10 million more shares.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gary C. Wendt took the cash up front when he agreed to become chairman and chief executive of Conseco Inc., the company disclosed yesterday.</p>
        <p>Conseco, the troubled insurance and financial services company, said that it paid Mr. Wendt a signing bonus of $45 million when he joined the company last month. He was also given 3.2 million shares of stock, now worth $31.2 million, as well as options to buy 10 million more shares.</p>
        <p>''Clearly, he is getting a significant sum of money up front,'' said Kathy Shanley, a fixed-income analyst with Gimme Credit, an institutional research firm. ''He's not taking any risk by taking this assignment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wendt, the former chief executive of GE Capital, a unit of General Electric, will  not get a salary for the first two years he runs Conseco, but he will get a bonus of no less than $8 million, and as much as $50 million, at the end of the two-year period, depending on how high the stock price is.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wendt, 58, gained a wide following at GE Capital, but he faces very different challenges at Conseco, whose bonds are rated as speculative, or below investment grade, and whose insurance operations have a relatively low rating as well. At GE Capital, he benefited from that company's top-notch credit rating, which meant it could usually raise capital at a lower cost than competitors had to pay.</p>
        <p>Conseco pays substantially higher costs, which is one reason the company has said it needs to sell its Conseco Finance subsidiary. Buyers have not been willing to pay Conseco's asking price, however, leading to speculation that Mr. Wendt may decide to keep the operation.</p>
        <p>Conseco was once a highflying stock, but since the spring of 1998 it has fallen from a high of $58.125 to a low of $4.50 in May. The stock price was at $5.875 on June 20, 10 days before Mr. Wendt's hiring was announced, and that will be the exercise price for the options he is being issued. Yesterday, in trading before the pay package was announced, Conseco shares ended at $9.75, up 12.5 cents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wendt will get the maximum bonus of $50 million in two years even if he does not come close to restoring Conseco's stock price to its former glory. The top amount will be paid if the stock price averages $20 a share -- less than 35 percent of the stock's previous high -- over a period before the end of the two years. The minimum bonus of $8 million will be paid if the share price is under $10, with payments between those figures if the stock price is higher than $10 but less than $20.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wendt was hired after the company's board ousted Steven Hilbert, the founder of the company, who received $53 million when he departed in April. Mr. Hilbert remains deeply in debt on company-guaranteed loans that he took out to buy shares at prices far above the current level.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wendt's employment contract covers five years and calls for the final three years to have an annual  salary of $1 million, a bonus of up to $2.8 million, a grant of shares worth $1.5 million at the time and annual grants of options to buy 500,000 shares.</p>
        <p>In addition, the agreement provides for some smaller benefits for Mr. Wendt. The company, based in Carmel, Ind., will pay all travel costs for the executive and his family for up to a year, until they move to Indiana. It will also reimburse him for up to $10,000 a year to cover any medical expenses not covered by the company's health plan, pay him an automobile allowance of $600 a month plus the cost of gasoline, and pay up to $125,000 a year for the cost of Mr. Wendt's life insurance.</p>
        <p>General Electric agreed to release Mr. Wendt from a noncompete agreement in return for a warrant allowing it to buy 10.5 million shares of Conseco at a price of $5.75 a share at any time through June 28, 2005.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
