<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Victim Leaves Hospital, Police Press Hunt for Her Assailant</title>
    <meta content="11ATTA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Tiffany F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">fountain, john w</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D71338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1215" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Victim Leaves Hospital, Police Press Hunt for Her Assailant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS and JOHN W. FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">fountain, john w; Chivers, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tiffany F Goldberg, who was attacked with concrete block on Manhattan street in what police call botched robbery attempt, leaves hospital, sounding upbeat and expressing some understanding for attacker; police conduct intensive search but fail to turn up assailant; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A young woman who was attacked with a concrete block on a Manhattan street left the hospital yesterday, sounding upbeat and expressing a measure of understanding for her attacker. Simultaneously, dozens of detectives participated in an intense manhunt but failed to turn up the assailant.</p>
        <p>The woman, Tiffany F. Goldberg, 25, was discharged from Bellevue Hospital Center at 4:45 p.m. just one day after a man rushed up to her from behind on East 29th Street and, in what the police described as a botched robbery attempt, slammed her head with a five-pound shard of concrete, fracturing her skull. The attack occurred minutes after she had left services at Marble Collegiate Church, where she is a member of the gospel choir.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A young woman who was attacked with a concrete block on a Manhattan street left the hospital yesterday, sounding upbeat and expressing a measure of understanding for her attacker. Simultaneously, dozens of detectives participated in an intense manhunt but failed to turn up the assailant.</p>
        <p>The woman, Tiffany F. Goldberg, 25, was discharged from Bellevue Hospital Center at 4:45 p.m. just one day after a man rushed up to her from behind on East 29th Street and, in what the police described as a botched robbery attempt, slammed her head with a five-pound shard of concrete, fracturing her skull. The attack occurred minutes after she had left services at Marble Collegiate Church, where she is a member of the gospel choir.</p>
        <p>Sitting up in her bed before leaving the hospital, Ms. Goldberg said she had been lucky to survive the assault but remembered little of it, other than the image of the man who came to her aid, Lt. James Hurley, an off-duty city firefighter.</p>
        <p>''I was walking down 29th Street, and the next thing I remember I was waking up,'' she said. ''Some gentleman was kneeling over me, trying to wake me up.''</p>
        <p>Lorinda Klein, a hospital spokeswoman, said that in addition to a skull fracture, Ms. Goldberg had a large cut on the back of her head, a black eye and two shattered front teeth, injuries that apparently occurred when she pitched face first onto the sidewalk after she had been struck.</p>
        <p>But two CAT scans revealed no neurological damage, Ms. Klein said, and Ms. Goldberg was expected to recover without complications. She was treated with antibiotics and mild pain relievers. She walked from the emergency ward accompanied by Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's community assistance aides, bound for an undisclosed location. Her spirits were high.</p>
        <p>''She's a very together person,'' Ms. Klein said. ''She has a good outlook and a lot of inner strength. She has no animus at all.''</p>
        <p>The attack on Ms. Goldberg, with its striking similarities to the brick attack on another young woman, Nicole Barrett, in Midtown last fall, spurred an intense and wide-ranging police investigation.</p>
        <p>Late Sunday night, the Police Department began circulating a sketch of the attacker, whom they described as a chubby and unkempt black man with a crooked nose. They said he was about 5 feet 7 inches tall, weighed 180 to 200 pounds and was believed to be homeless.</p>
        <p>Detectives were canvassing locations where homeless people gather. ''We have a full-court press on to find him,'' Commissioner Howard Safir said.</p>
        <p>One investigator said a witness, a homeless man, told detectives that he had seen the assailant running down the street after the attack and recognized him as a familiar street person. But the investigator said the police had not corroborated this account, and had not narrowed their search to a specific individual.</p>
        <p>At the Holy Apostle Soup Kitchen in Chelsea, which serves hundreds of homeless people each day, a security guard said two detectives questioned him at 2:15 p.m. yesterday, but did not seem to have detailed information about Ms. Goldberg's attacker. ''They are seeking assistance,'' the guard said. ''But I don't think they have a clue who he is other than his description.''</p>
        <p>The police also set up a mobile command post on East 29th Street at Lexington Avenue, near where the attack occurred, and uniformed officers stood in fixed posts on nearby streets. The heavy police presence appeared to keep transients away.</p>
        <p>''There's no homeless people here today,'' said Javed Keen, owner of Naghma House, a discount appliance store on Lexington Avenue. ''There hasn't been any at all.''</p>
        <p>By nightfall, the police said they had no clear suspects. They detained a few men based on their resemblance to the sketch, they said, but released them all after interviews.</p>
        <p>Police officials also discounted speculation that the man who had attacked Ms. Goldberg was the same man who had attacked Ms. Barrett.  Paris Drake, a street hustler with an extensive criminal record, has been charged with attempted murder in connection with that attack and is being held at the Queens House of Detention. Police officials said the latest attack had not given them any doubts about their case against Mr. Drake, who has pleaded not guilty.</p>
        <p>''We have no reason to believe that these incidents are connected,'' said Marilyn Mode, the department's spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>As the investigation continued, Ms. Goldberg's friends clustered around her in the hospital or waited for news of her condition. From her hometown in Madison, Wis., to her apartment building in Spanish Harlem to the Bryant Park Grill, where she works,  her friends all described a responsible young woman with a charitable streak.</p>
        <p>Alfred Colucci, a retired principal of Madison West High School, from which she graduated in 1992, remembered her as someone who ''never, ever caused anyone any problems.''</p>
        <p>One friend, Rachael Blair, supervised Ms. Goldberg in February when she was part of a 13-woman team of volunteers that traveled to Coban, Guatemala, and built three homes for Habitat for Humanity International. The work was grueling. Like the other volunteers, Ms. Goldberg paid her own way. She impressed Ms. Blair as a collegial and hard worker. ''She never complained; she was an absolute delight,'' Ms. Blair said. ''I'm so relieved that she's O.K.''</p>
        <p>The Rev. Robert D. Williams, an associate minister at Marble Collegiate Church, a Presbyterian church, said Ms. Goldberg -- whose father is Jewish and whose mother is Christian -- was not officially a member of the congregation, but attended services regularly and sang in the choir. He said church members prayed for her yesterday, but also expressed concerns for the man who wielded the slab of concrete.</p>
        <p>''There have been special prayers for her, and members of our staff have been over to the hospital,'' he said. ''We're really upset for her to be injured in such a pointless way. I guess the implication is that it was done by someone with mental disabilities. It is our concern that he receive some type of treatment.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Goldberg expressed a similar thought. A 1996 graduate of Sarah Lawrence College, she has been accepted for fall enrollment in a master's program in clinical social work at Columbia University. She said yesterday that she herself had struggled academically as a child, but succeeded with the help of adults, and that the man who attacked her might have needed similar attention.</p>
        <p>''The guy who attacked me, 20 years ago, was probably a struggling kid,'' she said. ''If anyone had reached him when he was younger, maybe he wouldn't have done what he did.''</p>
        <p>Reflecting on the attack in her bed in the emergency ward, clad in a floral-print hospital gown and a seersucker robe, she said she counted herself among the lucky. ''This is a very cup-half-full situation,'' she said. ''If he would have been a little mightier or struck me in a different way, I might have been more seriously hurt or even killed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
