<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Once Again Callas's Fans Can Bid Her Farewell</title>
    <meta content="11ARTS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS ABROAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Drouot-Montaigne (Paris Auction House)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Callas, Maria (1923-77)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riding, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7D61238F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Once Again Callas's Fans Can Bid Her Farewell</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riding, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, July 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Belongings of Maria Callas, including her own collection of memorabilia on her life and career, will be auctioned at Drouot-Montaigne in Paris and Dec 2, and they will be exhibited in Monaco, Tokyo and New York before the sale; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is a miniature by the 18th-century Italian painter Giandomenico Cignaroli, there are a couple of sketched portraits by the movie director Pier Paolo Pasolini and there are furs and haute couture dresses as well as shoes and gloves galore. Yet when these and other even more personal items come up for auction here in December, the point of interest will not be their intrinsic value but their provenance.</p>
        <p>All belonged to Maria Callas, arguably the 20th century's most famous operatic diva.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is a miniature by the 18th-century Italian painter Giandomenico Cignaroli, there are a couple of sketched portraits by the movie director Pier Paolo Pasolini and there are furs and haute couture dresses as well as shoes and gloves galore. Yet when these and other even more personal items come up for auction here in December, the point of interest will not be their intrinsic value but their provenance.</p>
        <p>All belonged to Maria Callas, arguably the 20th century's most famous operatic diva.</p>
        <p>When she died at 53 in Paris on Sept. 16, 1977, her unlikely heirs were her estranged husband, Giovanni Battista Meneghini, whom she left for the Greek shipping magnate Aristotle Onassis in 1959, and her mother, Evangelia, with whom she had not spoken in 25 years. They sold the furniture and paintings in her apartment on the Avenue Georges Mandel and then divided up the personal objects, with Meneghini's half going to Italy and Evangelia's share sent to Greece.</p>
        <p>Now, after passing into other hands, these collections of Callas memorabilia are coming together again for a pre-auction exhibition that will open in Monaco on July 28 and travel to Tokyo and New York before returning to Paris for display prior to the auction at Drouot-Montaigne on Dec. 2 and 3. After that, they will be dispersed, bringing to a close sporadic efforts to create a Callas museum in both Greece and Italy.</p>
        <p>''The logic of the auction is the continuation of the dispersal of Callas's belongings since the time of her death,'' explained Frederic Chambre, a partner in the French auction house Calmels Chambre Cohen. ''Many things have been sold or were lost, but these are the two largest extant collections.'' He added: ''This is an auction in the spirit of the Marilyn Monroe auction. It's an intimate, private affair.''</p>
        <p>But it is also one that Mr. Chambre and his colleagues are eager to have noticed, in the conviction that legions of Callas devotees dream of possessing something that brings them closer to the legendary Divina, anything that she once owned, touched, wore. Many of the items on sale will be on view in New York from Nov. 7 to 13 at the showroom of Leftbid.com at 1016 Madison Avenue, near 78th Street. The auction itself will also be open to Internet bidders using the site www.leftbid.com.</p>
        <p>Among the 400 or so lots on sale, a number stand out for their close association with Callas. Cignaroli's ''Holy Family,'' for instance, was given to her by Meneghini, who was then courting her, when she sang the title role in Ponchielli's ''Gioconda'' in her first performance in Verona in 1947. The painting, kept in a red velvet case, traveled with her everywhere and can be seen in many photographs taken in her dressing rooms around the world.</p>
        <p>The auction also includes Callas's chinchilla coat, made for her in the 1950's by her couturiere friend Biki Milan, who was Puccini's granddaughter. Among the many photographs of the fiery soprano in this coat is one in which both Meneghini and Onassis can be seen holding onto her, as if wrestling for possession. In the 1960's the coat was covered by emerald green silk, with the chinchilla becoming its lining, and that is how it now looks. The other fur to be sold is a white mink bolero jacket with the word Maria woven into its lining.</p>
        <p>The two Pasolini portraits as well as a heavy amethyst-colored glass necklace date from 1969, when Callas played Medea in a nonoperatic film of Euripides' play. The film was not a commercial success but established a close friendship with Pasolini that lasted until the Italian director's own death in 1975.</p>
        <p>Callas herself was a collector, not of valuable paintings or furniture (although she owned copies of a Cycladic statue and of a Greek tomb, also to be sold) but of anything linked to her life and career. Thus the auction will be offering three of her personal photo albums (which not only show her before and after her famous crash diet in 1954 but also as a blonde and as a brunette), envelopes full of newspaper cuttings, letters from friends and admirers, and many of her contracts, including those for her first and last performances at La Scala in Milan, in 1951 and 1958.</p>
        <p>The tape recorder that Callas used to practice her roles will also be for  sale, along with a collection of large-spool tapes of recordings of her favorite music. These include one of her recordings of ''Tosca'' and a surprising amount of nonvocal classical music, like symphonies by Saint-Saens and Sibelius, Chopin waltzes and Vivaldi's ''Four Seasons.'' Among the many scores that she kept are those for Richard Strauss songs and a piano version of Verdi's ''Don Carlo.''</p>
        <p>But most of the auction lots are decidedly more personal. There is an array of colorful party dresses, handbags, shoes, hats and wigs, but also slips, stockings, a black girdle, two brassieres and an embroidered blue corset of the kind known in French as a ''guepiere.'' Callas, renowned for her long slim hands, owned drawers full of elbow-length kid gloves in many colors; 14 pairs of gloves are in the auction. Nothing, though, could be more personal than three plaits of the diva's hair, all in slightly different tones of brunette.</p>
        <p>Many of these items have until now been on loan to a traveling exhibition organized by the International Maria Callas Association of Venice that drew crowds to Tokyo's Opera City in 1997 and to the Hotel de Ville in Paris in 1998. While that exhibition also showed what Callas wore in ''La Traviata'' at the Metropolitan Opera of New York in 1958 and in ''Tosca'' at Covent Garden in 1965, however, the auction includes none of her stage costumes or jewelry, most of which are still owned by opera houses.</p>
        <p>Today it is hard to divine how Meneghini and Evangelia divided up the  belongings, although it is said that Meneghini refused to take anything linking his wife to Onassis. (As it happens, the auction includes nothing associated with Onassis, for whom Callas felt great bitterness after he abandoned her to marry Jacqueline Kennedy in 1968.). After the collections left Paris, though, they had very different lives.</p>
        <p>Meneghini, whose marriage to Callas was never annulled, is reported to have proposed creating a Callas museum, but nothing had come of this by the time he died in 1986, leaving his entire estate to his housekeeper, Emma Roverselli-Brutti. She is believed to have sold most of Callas's private archives in Italy before selling the rest of her belongings to an Italian collector, Ilario Tamassia, who then created a sanctuary to Callas in his home in Modena. He also lent items for the traveling exhibition.</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Tamassia who first contacted Mr. Chambre late last year with a view to selling his collection. ''He no longer wants to hold the memory of Callas all alone,'' Mr. Chambre explained. ''He too wanted to create a museum, but he had no response from the authorities and decided to sell. I then set out looking for other objects here and there, but the only other big collection was in Greece.''</p>
        <p>In 1982, upon the death of Callas's mother, the singer's sister, Jackie, inherited the collection, which included an 18th-century console that had been in Callas's Paris apartment and was offered for sale through an Athens dealer in 1989. It was bought by a Greek journalist, Nicolas Petsalis-Diomidis, who happened to be preparing a biography about Callas and who met Jackie Callas through the dealer. Between 1989 and 1995 he bought most of her collection.</p>
        <p>In an essay prepared for the auction catalog, Mr. Petsalis-Diomidis said that when his biography, ''The Unknown Callas,'' was published in Greece in 1998, he too tried to interest the mayor of Athens in creating a Callas museum. The mayor showed enthusiasm, he said, and even proposed naming a central plaza in Athens after the diva. ''But two years later, I have seen no name on a square and no interest in a museum,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>Finally, he said, having been contacted by Mr. Chambre, he decided to sell the collection and obtained Jackie Callas's ''moral approval'' for the auction. ''Perhaps the Callas myth is better served by dispersing her last personal belongings,'' he said. ''After all, who will buy these objects if not people who truly love and admire Callas, who respect her memory and cultivate her legend? I said to myself, why a museum and not 100, 150 or 1,000 ardent defenders of her glory who can perpetuate her memory?''</p>
        <p>And so Callas's last physical vestiges -- her ashes were scattered in the Aegean Sea -- were packed up in Italy and Greece and transported to Paris, where they were sorted out, in some cases (like her wigs) cleaned and restored and then kept locked in the basement of an art security firm barely a mile from where they were taken 23 years earlier. Now, much like the international recitals that preceded Callas's last public performance on Nov. 11, 1974, the relics are preparing for a final tour.</p>
        <p>ARTS ABROAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
