<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justice Dept. Details Its Case Against Former Starr Spokesman</title>
    <meta content="Y11CON$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1214133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Times</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Kenneth W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bakaly, Charles G 3d</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4D71338F932A25754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justice Dept. Details Its Case Against Former Starr Spokesman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Justice Department details case against Charles G Bakaly III, former spokesman for independent prosecutor Kenneth W Starr who is accused of lying when he denied leaking information to New York Times about possible indictment of Pres Clinton relating to affair with Monica Lewinsky; says his false answers to government lawyers obstructed justice by delaying federal judge's investigation into news leaks and causing unnecessary work and costs for court and others; Bakaly's lawyers deny allegations; say Bakaly discussed subject with reporter for Times, but nothing that was not already public knowledge (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Justice Department detailed its case against the former spokesman for Kenneth W. Starr, the independent counsel, today, accusing Charles G. Bakaly III of lying when he denied leaking information last year to The New York Times about a possible indictment of President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakaly will go on trial here on Thursday on charges of criminal contempt of court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Justice Department detailed its case against the former spokesman for Kenneth W. Starr, the independent counsel, today, accusing Charles G. Bakaly III of lying when he denied leaking information last year to The New York Times about a possible indictment of President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakaly will go on trial here on Thursday on charges of criminal contempt of court.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department's brief said Mr. Bakaly's false answers to government lawyers obstructed justice by delaying a federal judge's investigation into the news leaks and causing ''unnecessary work and costs'' for the court and others.</p>
        <p>In the investigation, Judge Norma Holloway Johnson of Federal District Court had been trying to determine the source of reports by The Times and other news organizations, specifically a January 1999 article in The Times, that said Mr. Starr had concluded that a sitting president could be indicted.</p>
        <p>In a brief filed in response to the charges, Mr. Bakaly's lawyers insisted that his statements were not false and that in any case, they were not relevant to an investigation of possible leaks of grand jury evidence.</p>
        <p>In their brief, defense lawyers conceded that Mr. Bakaly had discussed the subject with a reporter for The Times, but had not discussed anything that was not already public knowledge.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the lawyers argued, guilt can only be established in a criminal contempt case by actions that amounted to ''a public wrong against the court,'' not against others.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakaly's lawyers said in the brief that Congress wrote the contempt law ''specifically to preclude a judicial power to hold a witness in criminal contempt any time the court believes that the witness has testified falsely and thereby prolonged or complicated proceedings.''</p>
        <p>While accusations of improper leaks had plagued Mr. Starr's investigation of President Clinton's relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky from its start in early 1998, the Jan. 31, 1999, article in The Times caused a particularly intense response.</p>
        <p>The article by Don Van Natta Jr. was published during the president's impeachment trial by the Senate.</p>
        <p>It said Mr. Starr had decided that he had the authority to seek an indictment of Mr. Clinton before he left office. It said he had not decided whether to do so.</p>
        <p>The article also said: ''Inside the independent counsel's office, a group of prosecutors believes that not long after the Senate trial concludes, Mr. Starr should ask the grand jury of 23 men and women hearing the case against Mr. Clinton to indict him on charges of perjury and obstruction of justice.''</p>
        <p>The report was attributed to ''several associates of Mr. Starr.'' It said Mr. Bakaly had ''declined to discuss the matter.''</p>
        <p>Judge Johnson sought to prosecute Mr. Bakaly for leaking grand jury material in violation of federal rules.  But last September, a federal appeals court here said that the rule barred prosecutors from publicly discussing ''matters occurring before the grand jury,'' and that the views of Mr Starr and his associates about a possible indictment of a president did not fit that definition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakaly was accused of lying three times in a sworn statement to Judge Johnson, specifically when he said that he had refused ''to discuss nonpublic matters'' with both Mr. Van Natta and Jill Abramson, a reporter who is now the Washington editor of The Times; that he had ''refused to confirm or comment'' on what Mr. Starr ''was thinking of doing''; and that Mr. Van Natta had ''assured me that his sources were outside'' the independent counsel's office and that the reporter ''intended to make it clear'' in his article.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakaly was also accused of withholding information from outside lawyers hired by Mr. Starr's office to investigate the leak to The Times.</p>
        <p>Because he withheld the information, the Justice Department brief said, ''Mr. Bakaly knowingly caused a materially false and misleading statement to be made in a brief filed by the O.I.C. with this court, as follows: 'Mr. Van Natta further told Mr. Bakaly that all his information came from sources 'outside' the O.I.C..' ''</p>
        <p>In their defense, Mr. Bakaly's lawyers accused the lawyers who prepared the statement of ignoring much of what Mr. Bakaly told them about his dealings with Mr. Van Natta.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakaly acknowledged, they said, that he had dealt with Mr. Van Natta on the story and had even sent him portions of an internal memorandum on the constitutional issues.</p>
        <p>They insisted that when Mr Bakaly confirmed to Mr. Van Natta that Mr. Starr had the four options -- indicting the president, not indicting him, indicting him under seal or indicting him after he left office -- the spokesman was in fact revealing nothing but merely acting to ''confirm a truism.''</p>
        <p>Editors at The Times have said they do not and will not discuss the sources for the article.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakaly won some public support from a consistent, intense critic of Mr. Starr and his investigations, Julian Epstein, the chief Democratic lawyer on the House Judiciary Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Epstein called the case ''a terrible prosecution.''</p>
        <p>Since the appeals court had found that no offense against grand jury secrecy had been committed, making this case against Mr. Bakaly amounted to no more than ''a semantical game of gotcha,'' Mr. Epstein said today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
