<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First Winner Is Ruled Out Of an Award</title>
    <meta content="Y23CON$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201751"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PEN/Amazon.com Short Story Award</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amazon.com Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Dinitia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nair, Meera</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wetzel, Marlene</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DD1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First Winner Is Ruled Out Of an Award</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DINITIA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Dinitia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amazon.com is publishing short story by Meera Nair on its Web site despite some complaints over graphic descriptions of sex and discovery that writer is ineligible for PEN/Amazon.com Short Story Award because her fiction was previously published in national magazine with circulation of over 10,000; judges give $10,000 prize to runner-up, Marlene Reed Wetzel; Nair had told Amazon about previous publication, but neither she nor Amazon initially realized magazine's circulation; Nair will also keep $10,000 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last Monday, the first PEN/ Amazon.com Short Story Award was announced and Meera Nair of Brooklyn won the prize. It was one of the largest prizes for an undiscovered writer -- for her work entitled ''Video,'' about the havoc wrought on a young Indian couple's marriage by the sexually explicit culture of the West. With a disclaimer, Amazon is running the full text of the story despite some complaints over the graphic descriptions of sex -- and despite the fact that the story was found to be ineligible for the award.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Amazon and PEN rescinded the prize, which includes $10,000 and publication on Amazon and in The Boston Book Review, and gave it to someone else when it was discovered that Ms. Nair's fiction had been published previously in a national magazine with a circulation of more than 10,000. This made her ineligible for the prize.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last Monday, the first PEN/ Amazon.com Short Story Award was announced and Meera Nair of Brooklyn won the prize. It was one of the largest prizes for an undiscovered writer -- for her work entitled ''Video,'' about the havoc wrought on a young Indian couple's marriage by the sexually explicit culture of the West. With a disclaimer, Amazon is running the full text of the story despite some complaints over the graphic descriptions of sex -- and despite the fact that the story was found to be ineligible for the award.</p>
        <p>On Friday, Amazon and PEN rescinded the prize, which includes $10,000 and publication on Amazon and in The Boston Book Review, and gave it to someone else when it was discovered that Ms. Nair's fiction had been published previously in a national magazine with a circulation of more than 10,000. This made her ineligible for the prize.</p>
        <p>The judges gave the $10,000 prize instead to one of the runners-up, Marlene Reed Wetzel, of Bixby, Okla., for ''A Map of Tripoli, 1967,'' a love story about an American woman and a Jewish-Italian man, set in Libya just before the Six-Day war. It is the first published work of fiction for Ms. Wetzel, who is 63, and has lived and worked in the Middle East. Up to now, Ms. Wetzel has only published articles in local papers in the Oklahoma area, she said.</p>
        <p>Amazon.com ruled Ms. Nair ineligible because one of her previous stories had appeared in The Threepenny Review, which violated the competition's rules that entrants' must not have published a work of fiction in a nationally distributed magazine with a circulation over 5,000.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nair had told Amazon about The Threepenny Review story, but neither she nor Amazon initially realized the magazine's circulation.  The decision was made after someone called Amazon's attention to the Review's circulation figures.</p>
        <p>Still, Ms. Nair will be allowed to keep the $10,000 and her story remains on the Amazon Web site, said Patty Smith, an Amazon spokeswoman. In the story, an Indian husband watches a pornographic video and tries to persuade his wife to perform the acts he sees.</p>
        <p>''Some of them did object to the sexual nature'' of the piece, Ms. Smith said of the customers. ''Some people did not share the judges' enthusiasm for this wonderful story.'' But the customers' reaction had nothing to do with the prize's withdrawal, she said.</p>
        <p>''I think Amazon was very fair,'' Ms. Nair said. ''I don't think they had any qualms'' about publishing the story.</p>
        <p>Amazon said 12,000 people entered the contest. The submissions ranged from apocalyptic fantasies to stories about children and horses. The other runners-up are Thomas Cockrell, Holiday Reinhorn, and Paul Rusconi, whose stories are available on Amazon.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
