<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress Reviewing Use Of Evidence Kept Secret</title>
    <meta content="Y23SEC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DE1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress Reviewing Use Of Evidence Kept Secret</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM WEINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiner, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congress weighs bill that could alter or abolish practice of using secret evidence to send people to jail in wake of findings by federal judges that it may be unconstitutional, except in immigration courts where foreigners or immigrants have been imprisoned for years on the basis of classified hearsay; bill would restrict use of evidence kept secret from defendants and lawyers; nearly 100 sponsors in House have backed measure, which is subject of upcoming hearing by House Judiciary Committee (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Using secret evidence to send someone to jail may be unconstitutional, except in immigration courts, where foreigners or immigrants have been imprisoned for years on the basis of classified hearsay, federal judges have found.</p>
        <p>Now Congress is considering a bill that could alter or abolish the practice. The bill would restrict the use of evidence kept secret from a defendant and his lawyers. Nearly 100 sponsors in the House have backed the measure, the subject of a hearing  scheduled before the House Judiciary Committee on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Using secret evidence to send someone to jail may be unconstitutional, except in immigration courts, where foreigners or immigrants have been imprisoned for years on the basis of classified hearsay, federal judges have found.</p>
        <p>Now Congress is considering a bill that could alter or abolish the practice. The bill would restrict the use of evidence kept secret from a defendant and his lawyers. Nearly 100 sponsors in the House have backed the measure, the subject of a hearing  scheduled before the House Judiciary Committee on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Secret evidence has been used to jail about 100 foreigners and resident aliens in the last decade, the Immigration and Naturalization Service says. The detainees are held on the basis of evidence introduced by the government, which they cannot see or challenge, at immigration hearings. Court records show that such evidence has included rumor and innuendo -- the unsubstantiated accusations of an ex-wife, or hearsay from foreign intelligence services.</p>
        <p>One case involved Hany Kiareldeen, a Palestinian married to an American. He was freed from a New Jersey jail last year, after a federal district judge ruled that ''the government's use of secret evidence violates the due process'' that the Constitution guarantees, even to resident aliens.</p>
        <p>The secret evidence accusing Mr. Kiareldeen of links to terrorists, largely compiled and classified by the Federal Bureau of Investigation, was partly revealed on appeal. It proved untrue. A primary source of the accusations, court records show, was his ex-wife, who was fighting him in a custody battle.</p>
        <p>Congressional testimony suggests that a new secret-evidence case takes place about once a month. The numbers are hard to confirm, in part because of poor recordkeeping by the immigration courts, which often make no formal record of hearings, and in part because of the secrecy surrounding the cases.</p>
        <p>The immigration service says 11 people are detained in the United States today on the basis of secret evidence. Opponents of the process say the number is higher.</p>
        <p>One of those detained is Mazen al-Naijar, a professor at the University of South Florida. A Palestinian, Mr. al-Naijar has been in jail for three years. Neither he nor his lawyers have ever seen the evidence against him, which has been used to accuse him of associating with terrorists.</p>
        <p>Another detainee is Dr. Ali Yasin Mohammed Karim, an Iraqi Kurd who worked with the Central Intelligence Agency against Saddam Hussein. He was evacuated to California after one of the C.I.A.'s covert operations collapsed in 1996 -- and then was arrested. He has been jailed for nearly four years because of secret evidence against him, provided by the C.I.A. and the F.B.I.</p>
        <p>That evidence was ''hearsay'' and ''nonsense,'' said R. James Woolsey Jr., a former director of central intelligence, who volunteered to defend Dr. Karim and had the security clearances needed to see the evidence.</p>
        <p>Now that the evidence has been declassified, largely through Mr. Woolsey's work, the judge has indicated that she may release Dr. Karim this week.</p>
        <p>David Cole, a Georgetown University law professor who will testify on Tuesday in favor of the bill, said,  ''Secret evidence is something we associate with totalitarian regimes, not with free democratic nations.''</p>
        <p>''The best test for truth is an adversarial process in which both sides get tested by cross-examination,'' Mr. Cole said. ''Secret evidence makes that impossible. We've seen innocent people locked up for years on evidence which, once revealed, would not justify their being locked up for a day.''</p>
        <p>For the last two years, the I.N.S. has been considering revising its rules on the use of secret evidence, at the request of Attorney General Janet Reno. But an immigration service official said the agency opposed the proposed limits on secret evidence.</p>
        <p>''It will make us choose either between requesting an agency to declassify national security information, or going ahead and letting a benefit be granted to an alien who is a danger to national security,'' the immigration official said.</p>
        <p>David A. Martin, a former general counsel for the immigration service, said that secret evidence should be used sparingly.</p>
        <p>''There is an argument for maintaining the use of secret evidence in some cases,'' Mr. Martin said, citing, for example, a case of a suspected terrorist entering the country illegally. But, he added, ''whenever it's used, it makes for bad procedure.''</p>
        <p>''You lose a lot of protections you count on'' under the Constitution, he said. ''If you don't know the evidence you're confronting, you're not in a good position to defend against it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
