<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israeli High Court Rules for Women's Services at Western Wall</title>
    <meta content="Y23ISR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Women of the Wall (Israel)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0DF1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israeli High Court Rules for Women's Services at Western Wall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL GREENBERG</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli Supreme Court changes rules of worship at Wailing Wall, Judaism's most revered shrine, decreeing that women can worship there--holding group services, wearing prayer shawls and reading aloud from Torah scrolls; legal ban on services at shrine, in keeping with strict Orthodox Jewish tradition, was challenged by Women of the Wall, group that demanded right to hold services in same way men worship at site (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Israeli Supreme Court changed the rules of worship at Judaism's most revered shrine today when it ruled  that women can hold group services at the Western Wall, wear prayer shawls and read aloud from Torah scrolls.</p>
        <p>A legal ban on women's services at the shrine, in keeping with strict Orthodox Jewish tradition, was challenged in court by Women of the Wall, a group that demanded the right to hold services in the same way men worship at the site.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Israeli Supreme Court changed the rules of worship at Judaism's most revered shrine today when it ruled  that women can hold group services at the Western Wall, wear prayer shawls and read aloud from Torah scrolls.</p>
        <p>A legal ban on women's services at the shrine, in keeping with strict Orthodox Jewish tradition, was challenged in court by Women of the Wall, a group that demanded the right to hold services in the same way men worship at the site.</p>
        <p>Under the rules in force at the Western Wall, which follow Orthodox custom, men and women worship in separate areas divided by a partition, and only the men hold services while the women worship individually. Today the court gave the government six months to arrange for group services for women at the shrine, complete with prayer shawls and chanting from the Torah.</p>
        <p>''We've come out of the Middle Ages,'' said Anat Hoffman, a leader of the women's group. ''Today the Western Wall became part of the State of Israel.''</p>
        <p>The ruling was condemned by Orthodox officials and rabbis, who called it a divisive assault on Jewish law and practice. It was the latest in a series of Supreme Court rulings that have been criticized by Orthodox leaders as anti-religious.</p>
        <p>The Deputy Religious Affairs Minister, Yigal Bibi, a member of the National Religious Party, said the Supreme Court had issued yet another ruling that would ''nullify the State of Israel as a Jewish state and turn it into a state of all its citizens.''</p>
        <p>The case, thrashed out over 11 years in the courts and in three government committees, raised the question of whether the Western Wall is a religious site where worship must follow strict Orthodox practice, or a national place of pilgrimage where Jews of all persuasions can hold services in different ways.</p>
        <p>The shrine of huge stones, venerated by Jews for centuries, is a remnant of a wall that surrounded a plateau where the ancient Jewish temple stood before it was destroyed by the Romans in A.D. 70.</p>
        <p>Attempts by Women of the Wall to hold prayer services there, and by Conservative and Reform Jews to hold mixed services, have drawn verbal abuse and sometimes violence by strictly Orthodox Jews.</p>
        <p>Women of the Wall, made up of more than 100 liberal Orthodox, Conservative and Reform women backed by a few hundred abroad, did not challenge the segregation of men and women but sought to hold traditional services in the women's area.</p>
        <p>Such group worship was outlawed by a regulation governing Jewish holy places that barred ''holding a religious ceremony that is not according to local custom.'' That was interpreted by the Chief Rabbinate and the Religious Affairs Ministry as Orthodox custom. Violating the regulation carried a penalty of up to six months in prison.</p>
        <p>Government committees ruled against changing standing practice on the ground that it might provoke violence, and suggested alternative sites for women to hold services adjacent to the Western Wall.</p>
        <p>But in today's ruling, a three-judge panel rejected such alternatives, saying they failed to uphold the women's right to prayer at the shrine.</p>
        <p>''The petitioners have the right to pray according to their custom in the Western Wall plaza as well,'' Judge Eliahu Matza wrote in his opinion, endorsed by the two other judges. ''It is unacceptable that concern about a violent reaction by any sector of the public will lead to denial of the exercise by another sector of its right.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hoffman, who is a Jerusalem city council member from the liberal Meretz Party, said the ruling ''is moving the Western Wall out of the complete monopoly of the ultra-Orthodox,'' and will make it possible for the first time to hold bat mitzvah services there for girls.</p>
        <p>''The voices of women, who are half of the Jewish people, were silenced in the holiest place to Jews,'' she said. ''This was a stain on the State of Israel and Jerusalem. Today that stain has been removed.''</p>
        <p>But Moshe Gafni, a legislator form the strictly Orthodox United Torah Judaism Party, called the court decision a ''shocking blow to observant and traditional Jews around the world, and a stab in their back.''</p>
        <p>He warned that the ruling would ''turn the holiest place to the Jewish people into a place where none of us will be able to pray, because it will be the site of the worst kind of sacrilege, against all the rules of Jewish law and the entire Jewish tradition.''</p>
        <p>The religious affairs minister, Yitzhak Cohen, from the strictly Orthodox Shas Party, said he would submit a bill to Parliament that would counter the ruling by specifying what forms of worship are permitted at the Western Wall.</p>
        <p>A religious moderate, Rabbi Michael Melchior, the minister of diaspora affairs, also criticized the ruling, warning that it could lead to ''terrible and violent dispute.'' He urged a compromise.</p>
        <p>But the ruling caused hardly a ripple this morning at the Western Wall, where hundreds of worshipers paid no attention to Ms. Hoffman and four other women who arrived from the Supreme Court to celebrate.</p>
        <p>As they draped arms around one another and read a psalm, Rivka David, an Orthodox school principal  from Tel Aviv, looked at them as if they were from another planet.</p>
        <p>''Prayer is a personal thing,'' she said. ''This is a show.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
