<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jays' Grebeck Produces</title>
    <meta content="AL23.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="AMERICAN LEAGUE: YESTERDAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toronto Blue Jays</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago White Sox</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D71F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jays' Grebeck Produces</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Toronto Blue Jays defeat Chicago White Sox, 4-3 (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Craig Grebeck has the role of a utility player all figured out.</p>
        <p>Grebeck hit a game-winning single in the ninth inning yesterday as the Toronto Blue Jays beat the visiting Chicago White Sox, 4-3, to stop a four-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>The 5-foot-7-inch utility player went 3-for-5 with two runs batted in, playing in place of Homer Bush, who is in an 0-for-11 skid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Craig Grebeck has the role of a utility player all figured out.</p>
        <p>Grebeck hit a game-winning single in the ninth inning yesterday as the Toronto Blue Jays beat the visiting Chicago White Sox, 4-3, to stop a four-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>The 5-foot-7-inch utility player went 3-for-5 with two runs batted in, playing in place of Homer Bush, who is in an 0-for-11 skid.</p>
        <p>''I know my role,'' said Grebeck, who is hitting .383 in 47 at-bats. ''A lot of teams have utility players, but they don't have a true utility player. The key in doing this job is working. You have to practice like you're playing, and if you do that you'll be OK.''</p>
        <p>Chicago overcame a 3-1 deficit in the ninth on a two-out single by Jeff Abbott off Billy Koch (3-0) on a 3-2 pitch and Herbert Perry's second home run of the season, an opposite-field shot to right.</p>
        <p>But Bob Howry (0-1) walked the pinch-hitter Darrin Fletcher with one out in the bottom half, Shannon Stewart hit a ground-rule double and Grebeck grounded a single under the glove of shortstop Jose Valentin, who was playing in.</p>
        <p>Toronto Manager Jim Fregosi knows he can count on Grebeck being ready when he is called upon.</p>
        <p>''Craig knows what his job is, and he keeps himself ready to play,'' Fregosi said. ''That's what experience on the bench means.''</p>
        <p>Toronto's Pete Munro, making his first start of the season, did not allow a hit until Chris Singleton doubled with two outs in the fourth and gave up just four hits and one run in seven and one-third innings. Valentin's run-scoring single tied the game, 1-1, in the fifth.</p>
        <p>Grebeck's solo homer off Jim Parque put Toronto ahead in the fourth.</p>
        <p>VISIT TO THE RAWLINGS FACTORY: A day after a record six grand slams and 56 home runs were hit in the majors, a van full of baseball executives showed up at the Rawlings factory in Turrialba, Costa Rica, yesterday for a long-scheduled look at how big league baseballs are made.</p>
        <p>Their conclusion: It's not the balls' fault.</p>
        <p>''We came away very impressed with the operations here,'' Sandy Alderson, the majors' executive vice president for operations, said after a two-and-a-half-hour tour of the plant where all major and minor league baseballs are made.</p>
        <p>With Rawlings balls flying out of major league parks at a record-setting pace, Alderson said he took a tour of the factory to get more familiar with what goes into making a baseball.</p>
        <p>Alderson said he thought stronger hitters, smaller ballparks and a pitching talent pool thinned somewhat by expansion all contributed to 2000's homer-happy season.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN LEAGUE: YESTERDAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
