<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rebels Free Half of Force From the U.N. In Africa War</title>
    <meta content="Y23LEO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sankoh, Foday</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hostages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE1DE1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rebels Free Half of Force From the U.N. In Africa War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rebels in Sierra Leone release 29 more hostages or nearly half of 500 UN peacekeepers who were seized; officials voice optimism releases will continue in coming days; rebels call for release of leader Foday Sankoh, raising concern that they may continue to hold troops while bargaining for his freedom; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nearly half the peacekeepers seized in Sierra Leone this month have been released, the United Nations said today. Officials added that they hoped that releases would continue in coming days.</p>
        <p>With the freeing of 29 additional troops today, 233 of the 500 hostages have now been turned over, United Nations officials said here.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nearly half the peacekeepers seized in Sierra Leone this month have been released, the United Nations said today. Officials added that they hoped that releases would continue in coming days.</p>
        <p>With the freeing of 29 additional troops today, 233 of the 500 hostages have now been turned over, United Nations officials said here.</p>
        <p>But as more hostages have been released, rebels have also been calling for their leader, Foday Sankoh, to be freed, raising concerns that the rebels may continue to hold the troops while bargaining for their leader's freedom.</p>
        <p>Also today, Secretary General Kofi Annan proposed strengthening the United Nations force, to 16,500 from the authorized 13,000. He also said in a report to the Security Council that even more soldiers might be needed later.</p>
        <p>In his report and in comments to reporters, Mr. Annan blamed Mr. Sankoh, who is in the custody of the Sierra Leone government, for the crisis in the country. Mr. Annan recommended that the council consider imposing new sanctions on Mr. Sankoh and his Revolutionary United Front, adding that the guerrilla leader had no future role in government.</p>
        <p>''I believe by his behavior he has excluded himself from the process,'' Mr. Annan said. The Secretary General said Sierra Leone's diamonds, which financed Mr. Sankoh, should be taken out of rebel hands and turned over to the government and people of the country. The diamonds are one of Sierra Leone's few natural resources.</p>
        <p>In Freetown this morning, two Nigerians on duty were killed when armed men described as former Sierra Leone army soldiers entered the Nigerians' barracks and demanded the release of a fellow soldier who was apparently being detained there.</p>
        <p>A gun battle erupted, and the Nigerians and a former soldier died. Several former Sierra Leone soldiers were reportedly injured.</p>
        <p>In another incident, about six mutilated bodies wearing peacekeepers' uniforms were found northeast of Freetown. United Nations officials said they did not have enough information to know victims' identities.</p>
        <p>Jordanian soldiers were sent to the area to examine the site and the bodies. But the group does not have a forensic expert, according to a spokeswoman for the United Nations here, Marie Okabe. Uniforms of Nigerian and Zambian troops were stolen a few weeks ago, so the presence of just uniforms would not necessarily identify the men, she said.</p>
        <p>The victims appear to have been shot in the head at close range.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
