<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Mideast Reality Check</title>
    <meta content="23FRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Thomas L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E5DF1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Mideast Reality Check</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Friedman, Thomas L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas L Friedman Op-Ed column says final Israeli-Palestinian peace talks are turning out to be more explosive and shocking than either side anticipated because for three decades both sides evaded hard compromises with 'stock answers' without ever having to give ground but are finally talking to each other about concrete compromises required to make actual deal possible; says it is almost as though they are discussing issues for first time, and that their people and coalitions are not fully prepared (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After all these years of Israelis and Palestinians talking about the core issues -- Jerusalem, refugees, prisoners, territory -- you'd think there would be no surprises left now that we have reached the endgame. But in fact the final peace talks are turning out to be more explosive and shocking then either anticipated. Why?</p>
        <p>Because for three decades whenever issues such as Jerusalem, territory or Palestinian refugees returning to Israel were raised, Israelis and Palestinians had their stock answers ready: ''The [other side] is simply going to have to accept our demand for [fill in the blank] because we can't possibly compromise on that issue. Sorry.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After all these years of Israelis and Palestinians talking about the core issues -- Jerusalem, refugees, prisoners, territory -- you'd think there would be no surprises left now that we have reached the endgame. But in fact the final peace talks are turning out to be more explosive and shocking then either anticipated. Why?</p>
        <p>Because for three decades whenever issues such as Jerusalem, territory or Palestinian refugees returning to Israel were raised, Israelis and Palestinians had their stock answers ready: ''The [other side] is simply going to have to accept our demand for [fill in the blank] because we can't possibly compromise on that issue. Sorry.''</p>
        <p>In other words, although both sides have talked about all the issues involved in this endgame for decades, when it came to the hard compromises they were usually talking to themselves. And what's great about negotiating with yourself is that you never have to really give ground, so your public is never surprised.</p>
        <p>But now that the Israelis and Palestinians are talking through various secret channels (talks that Israel temporarily froze Sunday due to the recent violence in the West Bank) about the concrete compromises that are required to make an actual deal possible, it is almost as though they are talking about these issues for the first time -- and their people and coalitions are not fully prepared.</p>
        <p>So many Israelis are shocked at news leaks suggesting that a final deal with the Palestinians will require Israel to give up 90 to 92 percent of the West Bank, not 60 or 75, which was the working assumption all these years. Many Israelis are going to be shocked to hear that despite their insistence on retaining a united Jerusalem, the Palestinians will have their own administrative capital on the outskirts, in Abu Dis, with some access to and oversight of Palestinian areas in East Jerusalem. Many Israelis are going to be surprised to learn that despite all these years of insisting there be no return of Palestinian refugees to pre-1967 Israel, some Palestinians will be returning under the guise of ''family reunifications.'' Without these compromises, there will be no deal.</p>
        <p>As for the Palestinians, after 30 years of declaring that they will not cede to Israel one inch of the West Bank, they will be ceding 8 to 10 percent, on which 80 percent of the Jewish settlers live; Jerusalem will remain the unified capital of Israel, and, while there will be a symbolic return of some Palestinian refugees to pre-1967 Israel, it will only be symbolic. Without these compromises, there will be no deal.</p>
        <p>And these are just the hard compromises that have leaked. There will be more surprises. This whole thing reminds me of a couple who for years have suffered through a bad marriage. They are now meeting secretly with their divorce lawyers to work out the separation and the only question is: When do we tell the kids? Israeli and Palestinian negotiators are working on all the details in Stockholm, but they haven't told the kids yet (although many are getting inklings).</p>
        <p>This helps explain the current surge of Palestinian-Israeli violence. The Palestinians are enraged at Yasir Arafat because their fathers and sons are still in Israeli prisons for committing violent acts against Jews that Mr. Arafat ordered. But Mr. Arafat is now negotiating with the Israelis about a deal that might not result in all the prisoners getting out, and he has not made their release his top priority. Meanwhile, you have Israeli families that are upset because they have had loved ones killed by these Palestinian prisoners, and some of them are going to be released as part of a deal.</p>
        <p>''And the problem,'' says the Middle East expert Stephen Cohen, ''is that no one in either society can say to his neighbor to just forget about this prisoner issue for now -- even though they know that to get a final deal that could ensure that more people are not killed, and more prisoners not taken, there is going to have to be a compromise in which some Palestinians who killed Israelis are going to stay in jail and others are going to be freed.''</p>
        <p>The paradox of peace is that the more separated you want to be, the more cooperation and cutting of slack is required to get a deal. That is why the endgame is going to require a whole new set of compromises, a whole new politics really, for both Palestinians and Israelis. But when will they tell the kids?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
