<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Chicago exchanges feel some heat to step up merger talks.</title>
    <meta content="Y23PLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000525T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Board of Trade</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Board Options Exchange</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barboza, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DC1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MARKETS: Market Place; Chicago exchanges feel some heat to step up merger talks.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Barboza</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barboza, David</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago Board of Trade and Chicago Board Options Exchange have stepped up merger talks in face of bill that would allow sale of futures contracts on individual stocks; Chicago Board Options Exchange fears change could undercut sales of options on individual stocks; table of data on exchanges; graphs of trading volume (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MERGER talks between the Chicago Board of Trade and the Chicago Board Options Exchange have intensified in recent weeks as a Congressional proposal threatens to put them in more direct competition.</p>
        <p>The two exchanges announced early last month that they were weighing a merger, but have stepped up negotiations in light of a proposal to repeal an 18-year ban on the trading of futures contracts on individual stocks, according to executives close to the talks. The futures proposal is backed by two Republican Senators, Phil Gramm of Texas, and Richard G. Lugar of Indiana.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MERGER talks between the Chicago Board of Trade and the Chicago Board Options Exchange have intensified in recent weeks as a Congressional proposal threatens to put them in more direct competition.</p>
        <p>The two exchanges announced early last month that they were weighing a merger, but have stepped up negotiations in light of a proposal to repeal an 18-year ban on the trading of futures contracts on individual stocks, according to executives close to the talks. The futures proposal is backed by two Republican Senators, Phil Gramm of Texas, and Richard G. Lugar of Indiana.</p>
        <p>If enacted, it would pit the two exchanges against one another in the trading of stock derivatives. It would also put them into competition with the Chicago Mercantile Exchange, at a time when all three are bracing for increased competition from electronic systems.</p>
        <p>The two futures exchanges -- the Chicago Board of Trade and the Chicago Merc -- support the lawmakers' proposal. The Chicago Board Options Exchange is opposed, and its officials cite differences in how options and futures markets are regulated.</p>
        <p>The products are similar. In the futures market, an investor is obligated to buy or sell a certain commodity by a set date. In the options market, an investor pays a set amount for the right, but not the obligation, to buy a commodity. But the futures market is regulated by the Commodities Futures Trading Commission, while the options markets is overseen by the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>If the futures exchanges are allowed to trade futures on single stocks, the options exchanges officials worry that investors may view the new products as cheaper alternatives to their products, options on individual stocks.</p>
        <p>William J. Brodsky, the chairman of the Chicago Board Options Exchange, said Monday that the Congressional proposal was not pushing his exchange into a merger, but it could make one more likely.</p>
        <p>''The stock futures matter is a factor,'' he said in an interview. ''It adds to the synergies of a potential merger.'' The two exchanges are trying to determine whether they can pool their resources to upgrade their electronic trading platforms and offer trading in both futures and options. By merging, they would create the nation's first futures and options exchange.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Board of Trade declined to comment on the discussions.</p>
        <p>The prospect of a merger is just the latest twist in this city's struggle to defend its position as the world's primary derivatives market. For more than a year, the Chicago Board of Trade has been struggling with how to restructure and meet the challenge of low-cost electronic trading. And now, despite strong growth over the last four years, the Chicago Board Options Exchange is feeling the heat from its sister exchanges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brodsky says the proposal to allow futures on individual stocks could put his exchange at a competitive disadvantage. He says he is not opposed to the introduction of single-stock futures, but he would like regulations to be harmonized.</p>
        <p>''My thesis is these things should be regulated on a level playing field with the same referee,'' he said. ''What we have now is a proposal that could create regulatory arbitrage.</p>
        <p>''Only in the U.S. do we have this governmental distinction between a futures exchange and a stock exchange,'' Mr. Brodsky continued. ''In Europe, they're all one.''</p>
        <p>For years, the Chicago Mercantile Exchange and the Chicago Board of Trade have lobbied to repeal the Shad-Johnson Accord, which separated the regulation of futures and options and banned the trading of single-stock futures and futures on narrow stock indexes. The ban was intended as a temporary measure to resolve regulatory issues, they say, but has stood for nearly two decades.</p>
        <p>Ellen G. Resnick, a spokeswoman for the Chicago Merc, said the exchange was in favor of regulations that would allow fair competition among the various Chicago exchanges, but the Merc did not want to be weighed down by having to answer to the S.E.C., which would mean answering to two regulators.</p>
        <p>''We'd be happy to have equivalent regulations, but we don't want more regulators,'' she said. ''There's no reason to have another regulator, it would be costly and subject us to more bureaucracy.''</p>
        <p>Tiffany Steele, a spokeswoman for Mr. Lugar, said regulators and lawmakers were working to resolve the regulatory differences in the trading of stock options and futures. She said that members of the Senate Agriculture Committee planned to meet with officials from the S.E.C. and the C.F.T.C. to come up with a workable plan to permit trading in single-stock futures.</p>
        <p>For the Board of Trade and the Merc, offering single-stock futures could be a way to tap into the public enthusiasm for trading stocks. Until now, the futures exchanges have been able to trade futures on only a basket of stocks, say the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index.</p>
        <p>The Board of Trade, which has been overtaken by Eurex, the merger of the German and Swiss derivatives exchanges, as the world's largest derivatives market, has been searching for ways to strengthen its offerings and to prepare for electronic challenges. It is now seeking membership approval to split into two companies, one devoted to floor trading and the other to electronic trading.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the C.B.O.E., which was spun off from the Board of Trade in 1973 as the world's first options exchange, is facing competition from the International Securities Exchange, the first entirely electronic options exchange, which begins operating later this week. To encourage competition in a market where there has been little, the S.E.C. has also put pressure on all the options exchanges to depart from their past practice of listing a futures contract for a specific stock only on one exchange.</p>
        <p>As a result, the C.B.O.E. is facing some of its stiffest challenges. Mr. Brodsky, the chairman, says the exchange is moving aggressively toward electronic trading and trying to protect its stock products.</p>
        <p>''Equity products have been the brightest lights over the past few years,'' he said, noting the futures industry's interest in trading stock futures. ''Now they want to peddle our trade.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 25, 2000, Thursday  A chart in Business Day on Tuesday with an article about merger talks between the Chicago Board of Trade and the Chicago Board Options Exchange mislabeled the scales showing trading volume in the number of contracts for futures and options. The figures are in the hundreds of millions, not the millions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 25, 2000, Thursday</p>
        <p>A chart in Business Day on Tuesday with an article about merger talks between the Chicago Board of Trade and the Chicago Board Options Exchange mislabeled the scales showing trading volume in the number of contracts for futures and options. The figures are in the hundreds of millions, not the millions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
