<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rusch Finds Good Pitching Is Not Enough</title>
    <meta content="23METS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Diego Padres</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7D71F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rusch Finds Good Pitching Is Not Enough</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>San Diego Padres defeat New York Mets, 1-0; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Glendon Rusch's game is control. He has impeccable control, staying around the plate, giving hitters no option but to go after his pitch. The Mets left-hander has the look of a pitcher who is finally understanding himself after three years in the majors, and when the Mets slot him in as their fifth starter, they now know he will given them a chance to win.</p>
        <p>But the one thing Rusch cannot control is how his teammates hit in the games he starts. For that reason, Rusch has only one victory this year. Tonight he again pitched well enough to win. But again, the Mets lost the game, falling to the Padres, 1-0, at Qualcomm Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Glendon Rusch's game is control. He has impeccable control, staying around the plate, giving hitters no option but to go after his pitch. The Mets left-hander has the look of a pitcher who is finally understanding himself after three years in the majors, and when the Mets slot him in as their fifth starter, they now know he will given them a chance to win.</p>
        <p>But the one thing Rusch cannot control is how his teammates hit in the games he starts. For that reason, Rusch has only one victory this year. Tonight he again pitched well enough to win. But again, the Mets lost the game, falling to the Padres, 1-0, at Qualcomm Stadium.</p>
        <p>Rusch threw seven shutout innings, but his counterpart, Matt Clement, threw eight. Clement was rewarded with a victory -- his second against the Mets this year -- because the Padres scored off John Franco in the eighth inning when Ruben Rivera singled home Eric Owens.</p>
        <p>In the ninth, the Mets loaded the bases against the Padres closer, Trevor Hoffman, on singles by Edgardo Alfonzo and Mike Piazza and an intentional walk to Matt Franco. But Jay Payton popped to second and Mark Johnson, batting for Rey Ordonez, flied out softly to center for the final out. Payton has one hit in his last 30 at-bats, and Johnson is 0 for 6 this year.</p>
        <p>Owens, who has been among the National League leaders in hits this season, was held without a hit in three at-bats against Rusch. But with one out in the eighth, he singled off Franco and stole second despite a strong throw from Piazza. Owens became the 36th successful base stealer against Piazza, who has caught only five runners this year. Rivera singled to left, and Owens slid in before Joe McEwing's throw.</p>
        <p>The Mets were shut out twice in Rusch's first six starts; in two others, they scored only one run. Their dismal offensive output in those games has been a major disappointment for the Mets, who could not have expected such consistency from their fifth starter when they initiated a competition for the job among Rusch, Bill Pulsipher, Bobby M. Jones and Dennis Springer.</p>
        <p>Rusch was the only one in that group who did not win a major league game last year; he was 4-7 in the minors for the Kansas City Royals, who dealt him to the Mets for pitcher Derek Wallace. Rusch had inexplicably lost confidence in his changeup, and he was drifting.</p>
        <p>But a late-season lesson in the two-seam fastball from the former Met Kenny Rogers helped make Rusch's other pitches better, and he has rediscovered his changeup. Not many pitchers succeed with Rusch's mix of changeups, sinking fastballs and curveballs.</p>
        <p>Rusch began the game by striking out Owens, but the ball got away from Piazza and Owens was safe at first on the wild pitch. No matter -- before throwing his next pitch, Rusch picked off Owens.</p>
        <p>But the bases did not stay empty for long. The next hitter, Rivera, tripled to the gap in right-center, the ball going all the way to the wall as Rivera dashed to third.</p>
        <p>Again, a Padres threat fizzled. Tony Gwynn sent a broken-bat grounder to third, where Robin Ventura fielded it as Rivera scrambled to get back to the base. He swerved out of the baseline, and Ventura tagged him anyway for the second out.</p>
        <p>That brought up Phil Nevin, one of only two Padres who had ever faced Rusch, a career American Leaguer before joining the Mets last September. Nevin singled, putting runners at first and second for the other Padre with experience against Rusch, Ed Sprague.</p>
        <p>Sprague, a longtime American Leaguer before last season, had a .400 career average against Rusch (6 for 15) but flied out to end the inning. Rusch, a control specialist, pitched carefully to Sprague all night, throwing a first-pitch ball all three times he faced him and walking Sprague the second time up.</p>
        <p>That walk was just the fourth Rusch allowed this season, and it came in his 45th inning. He was removed for a pinch-hitter in the top of the eighth, having pitched seven innings of three-hit shutout ball. When the Mets went down that inning, 1-2-3, it ensured Rusch of another successful day of work without reward.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>MELVIN MORA, who has a cut right index finger, is eligible to come off the disabled list on Sunday. He began a rehabilitation assignment for Class AAA Norfolk Monday night, going 1 for 4 as a designated hitter. Also in that game, BILL PULSIPHER made his first start since returning to Norfolk last week, and he was the losing pitcher, allowing five runs in four and two-thirds innings. . . . MATT FRANCO made his fourth start of the year, giving first baseman TODD ZEILE a day off. Franco, who had only 5 hits in 37 at-bats before the game, singled in the second and fourth innings. . . . The left-hander JOHN FRANCO had treatment on his sore right ankle before the game, and he was still experiencing soreness from a play at first base on Saturday. But Franco entered the game in the eighth inning, his first appearance since the minor injury.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
