<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="23FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EEDA1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Hezbollah Advances As Israeli Zone Collapses  The center of Israel's buffer zone in southern Lebanon collapsed as Israeli-backed Lebanese militias abandoned villages, command posts and arms to advancing guerrillas, and the Israeli Army early today hurriedly evacuated a major Lebanese base. The rout followed the start of a quiet withdrawal of Israeli forces in advance of a July 7 deadline set by Prime Minister Ehud Barak.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Hezbollah Advances As Israeli Zone Collapses  The center of Israel's buffer zone in southern Lebanon collapsed as Israeli-backed Lebanese militias abandoned villages, command posts and arms to advancing guerrillas, and the Israeli Army early today hurriedly evacuated a major Lebanese base. The rout followed the start of a quiet withdrawal of Israeli forces in advance of a July 7 deadline set by Prime Minister Ehud Barak.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush accused the Clinton administration of taking sides in last year's Israeli election and of pressing Israel to meet American ''plans and timetables.''</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Women and the Western Wall  The Israeli Supreme Court changed the rules of worship at the Western Wall, ruling that women may hold group services, wear prayer shawls and read aloud from Torah scrolls at Judaism's most revered shrine.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Maneuvering on China Trade  Administration officials said they still needed six to eight undecided Democrats and a similar number of uncommitted Republicans to vote their way if the China trade bill is to pass the House, where a vote is set for tomorrow.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore expressed perfunctory support for the China trade agreement, reading a statement in front of a labor group that opposes the China bill.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>In Defense of Globalization  Secretary General Kofi Annan, hoping to dissuade demonstrations against a United Nations millennium assembly in September, told independent groups that the solution to global inequalities was not confrontation but cooperation.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>More U.N. Peacekeepers Freed  The United Nations said nearly half the 500 peacekeepers seized in Sierra Leone this month had been released. But the rebels have been calling for the release of their leader, Foday Sankoh, raising concerns that they may hold on to hostages .</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Haitian Election in Question  The results of an undetermined number of legislative races from voting on Sunday may have to be voided because ballots were either damaged, lost or left susceptible to fraud when tired and poorly trained poll workers dumped huge piles of ballot boxes outside electoral offices.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-23</p>
        <p>Court Voids Law Limiting Sex Channels on Cable TV  The Supreme Court, voting 5 to 4, struck down a federal law that required many cable systems to limit sexually explicit channels to late-night hours. Both sides agreed that shielding children from sexually explicit material, the purpose of the law, was a legitimate goal but differed on the extent of the problem and on the degree of constitutional ''flexibility'' that is allowed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>In rulings on arson and fraud cases, the court stepped back from a continuing confrontation with Congress over limits on federal authority.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>The justices agreed to hear a clean-air case that casts a constitutional shadow over the ability of federal agencies to administer programs within broad grants of authority from Congress.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Disbarment Is Recommended  A disciplinary committee in Arkansas recommended that President Clinton be disbarred for ''serious misconduct'' -- his false testimony about his relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky -- in the Paula Jones sexual harassment case. A judge must approve it, and the president can appeal to the state's Supreme Court.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>General Loses Appointment  The Army has rescinded the appointment of Maj. Gen. Larry G. Smith as the Army's deputy inspector general in the wake of accusations by the Army's highest-ranking woman, Lt. Gen. Claudia J. Kennedy, that he made an unwanted sexual advance toward her in 1996, officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Doctors vs. Big Drug Maker  Hundreds of doctors have been boycotting drug products made by Merck in a political fight over the collective bargaining rights of doctors, pharmacists and other health care professionals.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Complicating Crash Inquiry  The cockpit voice recorder was not working in the twin-engine turboprop that crashed near Scranton, Pa., on Sunday and apparently never worked, because it was the wrong model for that airplane, the National Transportation Safety Board said. And the plane did not carry a flight data recorder, the other kind of ''black box.'' All 19 people aboard were killed.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-9</p>
        <p>Speaker Silver Survives A Revolt in the Assembly  Democrats engaged in a rare public struggle over the future of their leader, Speaker Sheldon Silver, who with his allies held off a coup attempt.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Conservatives Back Lazio  The Republicans' new Senate candidate, Representative Rick A. Lazio, received the backing of the state's Conservative Party, which could deliver as many as 300,000 votes.</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Tour Bus Kills Actor  Randolph Walker, 71, who was known for dozens of off-Broadway roles, was struck by a double-decker bus on West 45th Street.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>New Vision for CUNY  Trustees approved a plan calling for elite colleges and research groups, higher standards for admission and graduation and possibly a core curriculum across campuses.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Harvard President Leaving  Neil L. Rudenstine, 65, said he would step down next spring.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-14</p>
        <p>Easing Hot Flashes  A researcher said hot flashes among women with breast cancer were quickly eased in frequency and severity by relatively small amounts of antidepressant drugs.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>Lincoln Center Jazz Complex  Jazz at Lincoln Center will present plans today for its new home, including what are billed as the world's first concert halls built for jazz.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B10-11</p>
        <p>Sir John Gielgud  One of the great actors of the English stage, who enthralled audiences for more than 70 years, he was 96.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-28</p>
        <p>Industrial Espionage Case  A federal indictment accuses Jose Ignacio Lopez de Arriortua, a former senior executive at General Motors, of defrauding the automaker by taking boxes of its confidential documents with him when he moved to a top job at Volkswagen in 1993.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Taking Literary Market Online  Time Warner Trade Publishing is expected to announce today the creation of a separate online publishing venture. And Microsoft is teaming up with Simon &amp; Schuster and Random House for online publishing.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Consumer Privacy on the Net  Clinton administration officials disagreed with the F.T.C on what the commission's chairman said was a need for legislation to protect consumer privacy on the Internet.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Devils Hang On  The Devils beat Philadelphia, 4-1, to avoid elimination.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Portland Evens Series</p>
        <p>The Trail Blazers evened their best-of-seven series with the Los Angeles Lakers, 106-77.</p>
        <p>D3</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A24-25</p>
        <p>Editorials: Israel's volatile border; the lesson for the speaker; cable shows and free speech; new rhetoric at City Hall.  Columns: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E8  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
