<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is It a Plane? No, It's a Bird And a Very Rare Bird Indeed</title>
    <meta content="23ALBA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Albatrosses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Penikese Island (Mass)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buzzard's Bay</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laux, E Vernon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E6DA1E3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1242" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is It a Plane? No, It's a Bird And a Very Rare Bird Indeed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By E. VERNON LAUX</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Laux, E Vernon</byline>
      <dateline>PENIKESE ISLAND, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>E Vernon Laux article reports on rare sighting of a yellow-nosed albatross on Penikese Island in Buzzard's Bay, thousands of miles off course; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The weather was hot and sunny with a stiff southwest wind blowing at about 30 knots on Tuesday, May 9, when a large seabird, an albatross, came flying in off Buzzard's Bay at 11:45 a.m. and buzzed researchers hunkered down in a blind here.</p>
        <p>The researchers, Gina Reppucci of North Chelmsford, Mass., and Carolyn Mostello of West Kingston, R.I., were on the island to study terns and gulls for the Massachusetts Division of Fisheries and Wildlife. The last thing they expected to see was an albatross.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The weather was hot and sunny with a stiff southwest wind blowing at about 30 knots on Tuesday, May 9, when a large seabird, an albatross, came flying in off Buzzard's Bay at 11:45 a.m. and buzzed researchers hunkered down in a blind here.</p>
        <p>The researchers, Gina Reppucci of North Chelmsford, Mass., and Carolyn Mostello of West Kingston, R.I., were on the island to study terns and gulls for the Massachusetts Division of Fisheries and Wildlife. The last thing they expected to see was an albatross.</p>
        <p>But both had prior experience with albatrosses in the Pacific Ocean and had spent time observing these birds on Midway Island, a major breeding area for laysan (Phoebastria immutabilis) and black-footed (Phoebastria nigripes) albatrosses, two widespread Pacific Ocean species.</p>
        <p>Ms. Mostello has even seen the rarest species of albatross in the world, the short-tailed albatross (Phoebastria albatrus), at Midway.</p>
        <p>So they were well aware that these large, soaring birds, whose wingspans reach six or seven feet, were virtual strangers -- accidentals, in the language of ornithology -- in the North Atlantic Ocean. One can scarcely hope to see a member of this family in a lifetime of venturing offshore in this part of the world.</p>
        <p>As Ms. Reppucci recalled, they were ''hysterical, our eyes popping out of our heads,'' when this adult yellow-nosed albatross (Thalassarche chlororhyncos) came soaring in off the bay and zoomed by their blind, passing about 15 feet away.</p>
        <p>They were so awestruck when they realized what it was that they did not even grab their binoculars on the bird's first pass. They did not need them as it came in at eye level, then flared up and over the blind.</p>
        <p>The black bill with yellow upper ridge, underwing pattern, the exquisite eye shadow and overall pattern and coloration of this fabulous bird were etched into instant memory. ''It was the most exciting thing we had ever seen,'' Ms. Mostello said.</p>
        <p>While observing endangered terns is worthwhile and satisfying, there is nothing like a big-time rarity, a bona fide off-the-wall vagrant seabird.</p>
        <p>Penikese Island is a small grass-covered island in the sparsely inhabited Elizabeth Island chain that juts westward into Buzzard's Bay. The researchers are camping here from April through August, monitoring a federally endangered species, the roseate tern (Sterna dougallii). There are large numbers of nesting herring gulls (Larus argentatus) and great black-backed gulls (Larus marinus) on the island and a small rookery of black-crowned night-herons (Nycticorax nycticorax) and a few snowy egrets (Egretta thula).</p>
        <p>For a small island, Penikese has its share of ornithological items of note. The first breeding record of the manx shearwater (Puffinus puffinus) in North America was discovered when a nest containing a chick was found here in 1973, the first time this species had been found nesting on the western side of the North Atlantic. It has not been found breeding in Massachusetts since.</p>
        <p>Penikese is also the southernmost known nesting location for a small seabird called the Leach's storm-petrel (Oceanodroma leucorhoa) in the Atlantic Ocean. These nocturnal birds arrive in the middle of the night to return to nesting burrows in old stone walls on the island. There are only a handful of pairs on the island.</p>
        <p>But the albatross was an even rarer bird. The ''gooney'' bird made several passes over the grassy island hillsides at relatively slow speed, treating the researchers to great views at close range.</p>
        <p>The nesting great black-backed gulls took offense at its presence and three or four adults gave chase. The beleaguered albatross headed back to the north into Buzzard's Bay with several ''angry'' great black-backs in pursuit.</p>
        <p>Albatrosses come to land for only one reason: to find a mate, lay an egg and raise another albatross. Were Penikese Island located in the southern Atlantic Ocean, it would be ideal albatross nesting habitat. It fills the bill nicely with strong winds and wide open grassy hillsides to serve as runways for these heavy birds to take off on. Most important, it is free of mammalian predators. The bird was in all probability prospecting for a nest site.</p>
        <p>But it was 180 degrees out of sync from the Southern Hemisphere. While it is spring here, it is fall where the rest of its species lives. It seems the bird's compass and internal clocks have all been reset for the Northern Hemisphere. If it could only find a mate, there could be a staggering range expansion into a whole new hemisphere. This kind of thing could happen -- the Penikese albatross is not the first to turn up in the wrong place at the wrong time.</p>
        <p>Last summer an adult yellow-nosed albatross visited Matinicus Rock in Maine on July 6. The bird remained for about two hours, was photographed and then it flew off never to be seen again, unless the bird that visited Penikese was the same individual. The sighting in Maine last summer was the third for this species in Maine ornithological history.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the North Atlantic, there have been some remarkable albatross sightings. A black-browed albatross (Thalassarche melanophris) returned to the same huge Northern Gannet (Morus bassanus) rookery on Hermaness Island in the Outer Hebrides from 1967 until 1987.</p>
        <p>The albatross courted these large, sea-going gannets to no avail. It built a nest each year from 1972 until 1987 but never attracted a mate as the rest of its species were well south of the Equator. This bird exhibited extreme site fidelity, but it was the only one of its kind, so its efforts were genetically in vain.</p>
        <p>There are two other records for this species in Massachusetts. Amazingly, the first record was of a bird on almost the exact same date, on May 7, 1971, seen over Bird Island, off of Marion, Mass., also in Buzzard's Bay. This bird was spotted by Dr. Ian Nisbet, an authority on roseate terns who has been active in research and conservation efforts on their behalf for more than 40 years. Bird Island is really no distance at all as the albatross flies from Penikese across Buzzard's Bay.</p>
        <p>Yellow-nosed albatrosses have also been spotted from the Gulf of St. Lawrence in Quebec, the Bay of Fundy in New Brunswick, twice in New York State, once in Freeport on Long Island and one was seen flying up the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>As more and more birders go afield armed with excellent optics and first-rate field guides, the species is being detected more frequently. But the birds are still very rare.</p>
        <p>Albatrosses are extraordinarily long-lived. This is known from recoveries of birds wearing bands or rings that were attached at a known time  and place. The longevity record is of a giant royal albatross (Diomedea  epomohora) banded in New Zealand and recovered as a breeding adult 58 years later. Theoretically they could live to be more than 80 years old.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the recently sighted bird has not reappeared at Penikese Island or been seen anywhere else for that matter.</p>
        <p>E. Vernon Laux is the birding columnist for The Vineyard Gazette. His book, ''Bird News,'' was published last year by Four Walls Eight Windows.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E. Vernon Laux is the birding columnist for The Vineyard Gazette. His book, ''Bird News,'' was published last year by Four Walls Eight Windows.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
