<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Union Welcomes Gore, Despite China Views</title>
    <meta content="Y23GOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Food and Commercial Workers Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEFDC1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="774" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Union Welcomes Gore, Despite China Views</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore addresses members of United Food and Commercial Workers Union in Washington, where he voices perfunctory support for China trade agreement, which union opposes; receives warm welcome; is given standing ovation after pledging to ban use of permanent striker replacements and is applauded at several other points; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore voiced perfunctory support today for the China trade agreement, reading a statement in front of a labor group that opposes the China bill and is rallying in Washington against it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's appearance before about 175 members of the United Food and Commercial Workers was preceded by a videotape of his acceptance speech last fall after winning the endorsement of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. He began his speech today by mentioning a few of the issues on which they agreed, like raising the minimum wage, instituting new standards for workplace safety and passing a patients' bill of rights.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore voiced perfunctory support today for the China trade agreement, reading a statement in front of a labor group that opposes the China bill and is rallying in Washington against it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's appearance before about 175 members of the United Food and Commercial Workers was preceded by a videotape of his acceptance speech last fall after winning the endorsement of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. He began his speech today by mentioning a few of the issues on which they agreed, like raising the minimum wage, instituting new standards for workplace safety and passing a patients' bill of rights.</p>
        <p>''On all these issues and on many many more, some of which I'm going to discuss here today, we agree,'' Mr. Gore said. ''But in candor, I do have to begin here by saying something about an issue where we differ.</p>
        <p>''I know that one of your legislative priorities is to urge members of Congress not to support permanent normal trade relations with China,'' he went on, referring to the vote scheduled for Wednesday. ''I respect your view. You know that I do not share that view. I strongly support normal trade relations with China, because I believe it is right for America's economy and right for the cause of reform in China,'' he said.</p>
        <p>After another sentence or two, he eased back into the many points of agreement between himself and labor, and the audience appeared to be as forgiving of his pro-China position as they were relieved that he did not make much of an issue of it. Still, the food workers union, which represents numerous service workers, has less at stake in the trade issue than the industrial unions have.</p>
        <p>The workers gave him a standing ovation when he pledged to ban the use of permanent striker replacements and applauded him at several other points.</p>
        <p>''We're not naive,'' David Mertz, 32, a political worker for the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union, which is affiliated with the food workers, said after the speech. ''But on the vast majority of issues, we'll stand with him and he'll stand with us.''</p>
        <p>Labor's endorsement of Mr. Gore and opposition to the China bill has tied one hand behind Mr. Gore's back as he has stood with the Clinton administration on urging passage of the bill.</p>
        <p>Still, the degree to which he has pressed for passage is unclear. He did attend and speak at a White House pep rally on the bill recently, but his comments were overshadowed by those of former presidents and other notables. He has said that he has personally lobbied some members of Congress, but he would not name them.</p>
        <p>The Republicans have been quick to say that Mr. Gore's support has been tepid, and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, his Republican rival, has suggested that he has been more enthused about the matter than has Mr. Clinton's own vice president.</p>
        <p>''So far, Al Gore has only paid lip service to his position'' on permanent normal trade relations for China, Mindy Tucker, a spokeswoman for Mr. Bush, said in a statement today. ''He may offer tepid support for China P.N.T.R. in a room full of former secretaries of state and ambassadors, but before union audiences, his support disappears.''</p>
        <p>But others, like George Becker, president of the United Steelworkers of America, have said that Mr. Gore has been lobbying hard for the measure and would suffer for that in November because labor would not work hard for him.</p>
        <p>''We are not going to be forgiving on this,'' Mr. Becker said earlier this month.</p>
        <p>Two of the biggest unions in the labor federation -- the Teamsters and the United Auto Workers -- withheld their endorsements of the vice president because of the China deal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore began his day with breakfast with Thabo Mbeki, president of South Africa, and concluded his evening by attending a state dinner at the White House for him.</p>
        <p>But Gore aides were circumspect about their discussions. Mr. Gore has come under continuing protest from AIDS activists -- as recently as last week -- for administration policy that had the effect of blocking cheaper anti-AIDS drugs to South Africa.</p>
        <p>A Gore spokesman said today only that Mr. Gore and Mr. Mbeki discussed the matter of AIDS in Africa. An administration official said Mr. Mbeki discussed the matter with President Clinton but was uncertain of Mr. Gore's involvement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
