<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Former G.M. Executive Indicted On Charges of Taking Secrets</title>
    <meta content="Y23AUT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industrial Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Volkswagen Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lopez De Arriortua, Jose Ignacio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extradition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6D91F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Former G.M. Executive Indicted On Charges of Taking Secrets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former General Motors purchasing vice president Jose Ignacio Lopez de Arriortua is indicted on charges of defrauding GM by taking boxes of its confidential papers with him when he jumped to top Volkswagen job in 1993, federal court; Justice Department says it will seek his extradition from Spain; his lawyer says Lopez, who left Volkswagen in 1996, denies charges, but will not come to United States and cannot be extradited against his will; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former senior executive at General Motors has been indicted on charges of defrauding the company by taking boxes of its confidential documents with him when he jumped to a top job at Volkswagen in 1993, reviving one of the most celebrated cases in recent years involving accusations of industrial espionage.</p>
        <p>The six-count indictment by a federal grand jury here accuses Jose Ignacio Lopez de Arriortua, G.M.'s former vice president for worldwide purchasing, of wire fraud and the interstate transportation of stolen property. The Justice Department asserted that Mr. Lopez copied extensive G.M. computer files on auto parts costs and future car models and took them to VW when he took the top purchasing job at the German automaker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former senior executive at General Motors has been indicted on charges of defrauding the company by taking boxes of its confidential documents with him when he jumped to a top job at Volkswagen in 1993, reviving one of the most celebrated cases in recent years involving accusations of industrial espionage.</p>
        <p>The six-count indictment by a federal grand jury here accuses Jose Ignacio Lopez de Arriortua, G.M.'s former vice president for worldwide purchasing, of wire fraud and the interstate transportation of stolen property. The Justice Department asserted that Mr. Lopez copied extensive G.M. computer files on auto parts costs and future car models and took them to VW when he took the top purchasing job at the German automaker.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez's longtime lawyer, Plato Cacheris, said that Mr. Lopez denied breaking any American laws but would not come to the United States to defend himself. Mr. Lopez lives in Spain.</p>
        <p>And while the Justice Department said today that it would seek Mr. Lopez's extradition, Mr. Cacheris said that Spain's extradition treaty with the United States does not allow Spanish citizens like Mr. Lopez to be extradited against their will.</p>
        <p>''This is a case that is a waste of time and money -- he will never be tried,'' Mr. Cacheris said.</p>
        <p>The State Department and the Spanish Embassy had no comment this evening on how or whether the two countries' extradition treaty might apply to Mr. Lopez. Many such treaties limit the extradition of a country's own citizens to stand trial, particularly on charges of nonviolent crimes, for which countries' laws may differ considerably.</p>
        <p>The United States on rare occasions has been able to persuade foreign governments to extradite individuals even if their cases are not clearly covered by an extradition treaty. But such a move would be politically difficult for Spain.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez left Volkswagen in 1996 and has been working ever since as an auto consultant in Bilbao, the industrial center of Spain's economically depressed Basque region. Mr. Lopez has tried with little success to start his own auto company in his Basque hometown of Amorebieta, partly as a way to reduce unemployment there.</p>
        <p>Soon after Mr. Lopez's surprise resignation and departure to Volkswagen on March 15, 1993, G.M. executives became concerned about the large volume of confidential documents which he and his assistants had requested in the four preceding months. G.M. ended up suing VW, accusing it of having used the documents. VW settled the civil case in January 1997, agreeing to pay G.M. $100 million, but not admitting any wrongdoing; Mr. Lopez had resigned from VW two months earlier.</p>
        <p>German prosecutors had also filed charges against Mr. Lopez accusing him of having stolen G.M. documents, but dropped the charges in July 1998 after he agreed to make charitable contributions totaling 400,000 marks, or $224,000.</p>
        <p>G.M. cautiously welcomed today's announcement of the indictment, which came after a prolonged investigation. ''Obviously, these are decisions with which we agree and we will continue, as we have in the past, to provide support to the Justice Department in connection with their handling of this matter,'' G.M. said in a statement. VW officials did not return calls for comment.</p>
        <p>In today's announcement, the Justice Department revealed that the grand jury had actually returned the indictment last October under seal. The Justice Department did not reveal why the indictment was unsealed today, other than to note the planned extradition request.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez now faces up to five years in jail on each of 4 wire-fraud counts and up to 10 years on the two interstate transportation counts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez's exertions to cut costs were legendary in Detroit. When G.M. was teetering at the edge of financial disaster in the early 1990's, he and his aides, and even their spouses, made a point of wearing their wristwatches on their right wrists and vowing not to move them back to their left until G.M. was once again earning record profits. In a city that still reveres red meat and junk food, Mr. Lopez turned heads by requiring that his aides live on a ''warrior's diet'' of fruit, whole-grain products, as little meat as possible and no alcohol except an occasional glass of wine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez wrung somewhat lower prices from the companies worldwide that sell the auto parts from which G.M. assembles its cars. The legal wrangling has centered on whether he took G.M.'s prices to VW, which would have allowed VW to compare what it was paying the same suppliers for the same or similar parts, and then demand lower prices in every case in which G.M. had negotiated a better deal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez tried to persuade G.M. to build a low-cost factory in the Basque region at which suppliers would play an unusually large role, sometimes sending their employees to help install parts at the assembly line. He went to VW when G.M. rejected the idea, but VW ended up not building a factory in the region either. VW has since opened an experimental factory on Mr. Lopez's model in Brazil, while G.M. and Ford are also building such factories in Brazil.</p>
        <p>Only adding to Mr. Lopez's mystery has been the car accident in which he was involved two years ago. Mr. Cacheris said that his client had suffered brain damage and significant memory loss in the accident and would be unable to assist his counsel. But Mr. Lopez has continued to promote his dream of a Basque auto factory over the last two years.</p>
        <p>In an interview last autumn, Mr. Lopez voiced regret that he had ever left G.M., given that VW never built his dream factory. ''If I had known that, I wouldn't have changed'' jobs, he said. ''It was my error.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
