<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California's Governor Plays Tough on Crime</title>
    <meta content="23DAVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201823"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nieves, Evelyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Gray (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E2D81F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California's Governor Plays Tough on Crime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nieves, Evelyn</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Calif Democratic Gov Gray Davis is establishing himself halfway into second year in office as more conservative on criminal justice issues than his Republican predecessors or any other elected state, or even national, official; some of his criminal justice initiatives discussed; he continually cites polls showing his approval rating at more than 65 percent as proof that voters endorse his stance on law and order; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the height of the bitterly fought 1998 campaign for governor of California, and Gray Davis, a Democrat, was trying to prove that he would be tougher on crime than the Republican attorney general, Dan Lungren, who was running on a record of two decades in law enforcement.</p>
        <p>As governor, Mr. Davis -- then the state's lieutenant governor, with a record as a moderate -- insisted he would be harder on crime than anybody. He would give judges discretion to sentence 14-year-olds to death; he would let them consider supporting nonunanimous jury verdicts. Indeed, Mr. Davis said in a televised debate, on issues of law and order, he considered Singapore -- a country that executes drug offenders -- ''a good starting point.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the height of the bitterly fought 1998 campaign for governor of California, and Gray Davis, a Democrat, was trying to prove that he would be tougher on crime than the Republican attorney general, Dan Lungren, who was running on a record of two decades in law enforcement.</p>
        <p>As governor, Mr. Davis -- then the state's lieutenant governor, with a record as a moderate -- insisted he would be harder on crime than anybody. He would give judges discretion to sentence 14-year-olds to death; he would let them consider supporting nonunanimous jury verdicts. Indeed, Mr. Davis said in a televised debate, on issues of law and order, he considered Singapore -- a country that executes drug offenders -- ''a good starting point.''</p>
        <p>No one took that remark literally. But these days, Democratic lawmakers say it sometimes seems as though Mr. Davis was only slightly exaggerating. Halfway into his second year in office, the governor is establishing himself as more of a conservative on criminal justice issues than his Republican predecessors, or any other elected official in California -- if not the nation.</p>
        <p>The governor has essentially removed the ''time off for good behavior'' incentive that makes inmates model prisoners by refusing any recommendation the parole board has made to grant a release. He has announced that any judge he appoints should reflect his sentiments ''or resign.''</p>
        <p>He has blocked efforts to soften the state's ''three strikes'' law, which can put someone in prison for life for stealing a bicycle if it is his third felony conviction. He has vetoed a modest bill that would grant reporters greater access to inmates in the state's closed-door prison system, which has been rocked in recent years by corruption scandals and has indicated he will veto a similar bill introduced this year.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the governor -- who broke with the Democratic Party and endorsed Proposition 21, the youth crime initiative passed in November that allows 14-year-olds convicted of felonies to be locked up in adult prisons -- has stocked the parole board and other posts with ex-law enforcement officials who are considered hard-liners, very much like his Republican predecessor, Pete Wilson, had done. Mr. Gray has also sided with police groups against civil rights groups in refusing to approve a bill to track racial profiling by police agencies.</p>
        <p>California, already in a class by itself in terms of crime and punishment because of the ''three strikes'' law, continues to be one of the strictest states in the nation -- if not the strictest, on law and order -- said Frank Zimring, director of the Earl Warren Legal Institute at the University of California at Berkeley.</p>
        <p>Governor Davis, through a spokesman, has declined repeated requests over several weeks for an interview, saying he was too busy. But the governor has continually cited polls showing his approval rating at more than 65 percent as proof that voters endorse his stance on law and order.</p>
        <p>His spokesman, Michael Bustamante, says that the governor campaigned as a centrist, made moderation a theme of his first two State of the State speeches and told Democrats at last year's state convention exactly how he planned to lead.  ''Governor Davis laid out how he intended to govern from the center,'' Mr. Bustamante said then.</p>
        <p>As a calculation, political observers say, the governor's move to the far right on crime and punishment is a safe bet. California is rather conservative when it comes to crime issues, with voters consistently approving initiatives that strengthen laws against offenders. In fact, California, which has the biggest court and prison system in the country, led the prison-building boom, and Governor Davis is expanding it.</p>
        <p>Both his supporters and critics regard the governor's stand as a political buffer against potential challengers who might fault him for being soft on crime. But to the state's Democratic leaders -- eager for change after 16 years of Republican governors who made hard lines on law and order the benchmarks of their administrations -- Mr. Davis's inflexibility on criminal justice issues is becoming the defining characteristic of his administration as well.</p>
        <p>Former Governor Wilson, who started the Proposition 21 youth crime initiative that Governor Davis endorsed, praised his successor as ''a pleasant surprise on the stance he has taken on criminal justice, both in terms of his appointments and his support of tough standards as well as prevention.''</p>
        <p>California is enjoying a drop in its crime rate, though there is no way to tell if it is attributable to such policies. Most other states, including those with less stringent stands on criminal justice, have experienced declines in their crime rates as well.</p>
        <p>Even so, the governor's critics -- almost all of them from within his own party -- say that in these good times, when the public is content and the state coffers are flush, any governor would receive similar high approval ratings.</p>
        <p>In fact, they say, it is precisely during these times that the governor can afford to show some independence rather than plod along the politically safe path to a second term.</p>
        <p>''The thing that has been somewhat surprising is the kind of iron-clad approach he has,'' State Senator Tom Hayden said. ''Absolutism is something that you expect from an ayatollah, but it's surprising in a governor in a state that's very complex and diverse.</p>
        <p>''It's O.K. to lay down the rules, but there's been any number of occasions when flexibility is called for,'' he added. ''I've seen any number of his appointees who share the same approach, but who display routine flexibility. He's not bending to them. He's the hard-liner in their ranks.''</p>
        <p>After a year in which the governor's stance on crime caused barely a ripple of attention, except for regular scoldings in newspaper editorials, his stance has received greater scrutiny and political disapproval in recent weeks. Or, as an editorial in The Los Angeles Times put it, ''the honeymoon is over, brought to an end partly by his prickly, controlling style and partly by his aversion to taking political risk.''</p>
        <p>In March, the governor suffered his first major political defeat when the State Senate blocked a conservative Republican from serving another term as chairman on the state parole board, a consequence of a federal court ruling that the board had violated the Americans with Disabilities Act.</p>
        <p>James W. Nielsen, a former Republican state senator, had been named to the board of prison terms, as the parole board is called, by Governor Wilson in 1991 and re-appointed in 1995. Mr. Davis re-appointed him to fill out the remaining nine months of a term last May and tried to extend it.</p>
        <p>But the Senate leader, John Burton, a Democrat from San Francisco considered the state's most powerful legislator, refused to hold a confirmation hearing on the appointment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burton, increasingly vocal about disagreements with the governor over law and order, said he was outraged by a federal judge's ruling criticizing Mr. Nielsen -- who actively campaigned against Mr. Davis in 1998 -- as ''callous'' to the rights of disabled inmates seeking full access to parole hearings. Some wheelchair-bound prisoners had to crawl up stairs to attend hearings; deaf inmates who used sign language had their hands shackled at hearings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis turned the defeat into a victory of sorts by naming Mr. Nielsen to head the state youth parole board.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, Mr. Burton said that Mr. Davis's inflexibility -- ''because he thinks a Democrat becomes a moderate by being tough on crime'' -- ignored the possibility that people could be ''redeemed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burton was referring to the high-profile parole case of Robert Rosenkrantz, who has served 15 years in prison for second-degree murder. In June 1985, Mr. Rosenkrantz, who is now 34, killed the man who revealed his homosexuality to Mr. Rosenkrantz's at a high school graduation party; he was sentenced to 17 years to life.</p>
        <p>Prison officials have said he is a model inmate; numerous psychologists, as well as the prosecutors, trial judge and detective who worked on the case all recommended that Mr. Rosenkrantz be released.</p>
        <p>Last month, a state appellate court took the unprecedented step of ruling that the parole board had abused its discretion when it found Mr. Rosen krantz unsuitable for parole.</p>
        <p>Under the order of a state court judge, who sided with Mr. Rosenkrantz when he challenged the board's denial, the board reluctantly set a release date for Mr. Rosenkrantz last year. But the governor stepped in and rejected the parole, saying Mr. Rosenkrantz ''was not currently suitable'' for release. The appellate court, ruling against the board's appeal, upheld the lower court's order.</p>
        <p>The case came up concerning another appointment to the board Mr. Davis has made. The appointee, Leonard G. Munoz, a former Los Angeles police officer who had been serving on the board since last year without confirmation by the State Senate, was a member of the panel that rejected Mr. Rosenkrantz's bid for release.</p>
        <p>[On Thursday, the State Senate confirmed the Munoz appointment 30-4, after hard lobbying by Governor Davis. Senator Burton, who voted against the appointment, warned in a floor speech that unless the governor loosened his parole policies, the Senate might abolish the board.]</p>
        <p>John Vasconcellos, a Democrat from San Jose who is chairman of the State Senate's Public Safety Committee, said that the board, under the governor's edict to never approve the release of anyone convicted of murder, ''have held Kafkaesque hearings in which conclusions have nothing to do with the facts.''</p>
        <p>The governor, through a spokeswoman, declined to comment on the Rosenkrantz case.</p>
        <p>In recent days, the governor has had to confront reporters who want to know why he continues to reject a bill that would grant journalists greater access to inmates.</p>
        <p>The bill, which is similar to one he rejected last year, would restore the ability to conduct interviews with inmates, a policy changed in 1995 by the California Corrections Department after a series of scathing articles in The Orange County Register about conditions in state prisons.</p>
        <p>Carole Migden, a Democratic assemblywoman from San Francisco who wrote both bills, said it was important to keep the issue alive even if the governor vetoed it again, though she added that she did not think his law-and-order stance was out of line with the voters.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure he wants to get re-elected,'' she said, ''just as you want to keep your job. Everybody wants to keep their job.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, a politician, especially a Democrat, faces few repercussions in gaining a reputation as a hardliner on law and order, said Mr. Zimring, the University of California professor. ''He loses nothing except if someone were writing the next 'Profiles in Courage,' '' he said. ''I don't think Davis would make it into that. But politically? There is no serious downside.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
