<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With an Ear For Baroque Passions</title>
    <meta content="23BARO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">I Musici di San Cassiano (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brookshire, Bradley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E2D81E3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="472" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With an Ear For Baroque Passions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allan Kozinn reviews concert by harpsichordist Bradley Brookshire and his period instrument ensemble, I Musici di San Cassiano, at Merkin Concert Hall (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As part of the Baroqueworks series at Merkin Concert Hall, the harpsichordist Bradley Brookshire and his period instrument ensemble, I Musici di San Cassiano, offered works by Handel and the two Scarlattis last Tuesday evening.</p>
        <p>Stylistically, this was a diverse assembly: in Alessandro Scarlatti's cantata ''Perche tacete, regolati concenti,'' one hears the seeds of Handel's dramatic style, but also the echoes of Monteverdian text setting. Domenico Scarlatti, son of Alessandro, is known for his hundreds of short but meaty harpsichord sonatas, many of them full of eccentric but striking effects. Handel was represented here by music that distanced him from both father and son: the cantata ''Dolce pur d'amor l'affanno,'' which is a generation more modern than Alessandro Scarlatti's cantata, and a harpsichord suite, notably more conservative than the works of Domenico Scarlatti, Handel's exact contemporary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As part of the Baroqueworks series at Merkin Concert Hall, the harpsichordist Bradley Brookshire and his period instrument ensemble, I Musici di San Cassiano, offered works by Handel and the two Scarlattis last Tuesday evening.</p>
        <p>Stylistically, this was a diverse assembly: in Alessandro Scarlatti's cantata ''Perche tacete, regolati concenti,'' one hears the seeds of Handel's dramatic style, but also the echoes of Monteverdian text setting. Domenico Scarlatti, son of Alessandro, is known for his hundreds of short but meaty harpsichord sonatas, many of them full of eccentric but striking effects. Handel was represented here by music that distanced him from both father and son: the cantata ''Dolce pur d'amor l'affanno,'' which is a generation more modern than Alessandro Scarlatti's cantata, and a harpsichord suite, notably more conservative than the works of Domenico Scarlatti, Handel's exact contemporary.</p>
        <p>What drew these composers together, Mr. Brookshire said in a pre-concert talk, was that all three  worked in Rome at some point in their careers and were influenced by its esthetic atmosphere. That's fairly flimsy as thematic links go, but the program itself had ample attractions, thematic or not.</p>
        <p>One was Bejun Mehta, a countertenor with a strong voice, a firm command of color and vibrato, and an ear for the passions of the text. Mr. Mehta sang both cantatas, and was fully attuned to the distinctions between them. Both works are the plaints of wounded lovers, but Handel's is fiery and outgoing and Scarlatti's alternates between melancholy and agitation. Mr. Mehta's brisk rendering of the Handel drew on the music's drive and seemed to amplify it. In the Scarlatti, he adopted a darker vocal hue and moved gracefully through the ornamented line.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brookshire is a fine harpsichordist and a thoughtful musician, and he played nine of Scarlatti's Sonatas and Handel's ''Harmonious Blacksmith'' Suite with vitality, a good sense of color and some unusual but effective phrasing ideas. The Variations that close the Handel were especially lively. That said, his endings -- a pause followed by a pounced-upon final note -- came to seem slightly mannered and predictable, if never really objectionable. And perhaps it's not too much to expect these works to be played from memory. In the first group of Scarlatti sonatas in particular, there were moments of tentativeness that made the performance seem sight-read rather than fully internalized.</p>
        <p>Besides Mr. Brookshire, I Musici di San Cassiano includes Sybille Johner, a cellist, and Claire Jolivet and Karl Kawahara, violinists. The ensemble bears watching: its playing in the Scarlatti had both an admirable transparency and the slightly tart edge that makes Baroque playing so inviting.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
