<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>French Can Pursue Polish Phone Company</title>
    <meta content="Y23POLA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Poland</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">France Telecom</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kulczyk Holding</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Telekomunikacja Polska Sa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EFD71E3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>French Can Pursue Polish Phone Company</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>France Telecom and Polish partner, Kulczyk Holding, get exclusive rights to negotiate purchase of 35 percent stake in former Polish phone monopoly, Telekomunikacja Polska, for some $4 billion and right to lift stake to 51 percent by 2001; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>France Telecom and a Polish partner, Kulczyk Holding, received exclusive rights today to negotiate the acquisition of a 35 percent stake in the former Polish phone monopoly, Telekomunikacja Polska, for roughly $4 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal signals what could be the final steps in the sale of Poland's state phone company, one of the largest privatizations in the formerly Communist-ruled Eastern Europe. The award brings with it the right to lift the stake to 51 percent by 2001.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>France Telecom and a Polish partner, Kulczyk Holding, received exclusive rights today to negotiate the acquisition of a 35 percent stake in the former Polish phone monopoly, Telekomunikacja Polska, for roughly $4 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal signals what could be the final steps in the sale of Poland's state phone company, one of the largest privatizations in the formerly Communist-ruled Eastern Europe. The award brings with it the right to lift the stake to 51 percent by 2001.</p>
        <p>The deal also opens up Eastern Europe to France Telecom, which has been struggling to regain momentum after stumbling badly earlier this year in its international expansion plans.</p>
        <p>The pace is expected to accelerate, because France Telecom is also considered the front-runner to acquire Orange P.L.C., a big British cellular phone provider, which Vodafone AirTouch agreed to sell when it reached a deal to acquire Mannesmann of Germany in February.</p>
        <p>Emil Wasacz, the Polish treasury minister, said the deal provided Telekomunikacja Polska with a partner with ''the knowledge, know-how and technology necessary to assume a leading market position.''</p>
        <p>If France Telecom and Kulczyk, which is controlled by the Polish entrepreneur Jan Kulczyk, complete the negotiations by June, they will have an option to acquire a further 16 percent later, giving them full control of the Polish phone company.</p>
        <p>In 1998, the Polish treasury sold 15 percent of Telekomunikacja Polska on the stock market and another 15 percent to company employees. It plans to retain 45 percent of the company after the full entry of France Telecom and Kulczyk.</p>
        <p>The move is a gamble for France Telecom because Telekomunikacja Polska is a lumbering dinosaur in a market rapidly shifting to wireless phones and the Internet. Telekomunikacja, stymied for decades by Poland's former Communist rulers, has 71,000 employees and faces growing competition from an array of fresh and nimble wireless companies.</p>
        <p>But the Polish government, fearful of heavy job reductions and eager to preserve a national phone business, has shielded the giant former monopoly by taking a slow path toward deregulation, issuing licenses that allow only a single rival in each of Poland's major cities and reserving lucrative long-distance lines to Telekomunikacja Polska until 2002 and international service until a year later.</p>
        <p>Additionally, the government has assured Telekomunikacja Polska one of four potentially lucrative licenses for a new generation of wireless phones that will provide users with basic Internet services.</p>
        <p>Still, because of government hesitation over the sale, overhauling Telekomunikacja Polska has proceeded fitfully, and only recently has it begun major investments to enhance its wireless and Internet services. On Friday, it announced a $1 billion bond offering to help accelerate the financing of those investments.</p>
        <p>France Telecom's sole competitor in the bidding was the Italian carrier, Telecom Italia. Michel Bon, the chief executive of France Telecom, has been trying to hasten development of international activities ever since France Telecom abandoned a partnership with Deutsche Telekom, its German counterpart, early this year in a venture known as Global One. Deutsche Telekom already owns a 51 percent share of the Hungarian phone company, Matav, and a 22 percent share in Poland's No. 2 cell phone provider.</p>
        <p>Telekomunikacja Polska says it has about 9 million customers in a country of 42 million people. In the first quarter, it said net profit rose 450 percent, to the equivalent of $109 million, on a 25 percent revenue increase, to $760 million.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
