<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Andrew Choa, 76, Former Bank Executive</title>
    <meta content="Y23CHOA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">303 words</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E4D61E3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="303" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Andrew Choa, 76, Former Bank Executive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew Choa, an international banker and professional adviser, died on May 17 in a hospital in Mount Vernon, Va. He was 76. His family said he had had vascular disease for a year.</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Andrew Choa, an international banker and professional adviser, died on May 17 in a hospital in Mount Vernon, Va. He was 76.</p>
        <p>His family said he had had vascular disease for a year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Andrew Choa, an international banker and professional adviser, died on May 17 in a hospital in Mount Vernon, Va. He was 76.</p>
        <p>His family said he had had vascular disease for a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Choa came to New York City from Hong Kong in 1945 with a scholarship to attend Fordham University. He earned a bachelor's degree there in 1949 and went to the Harvard Business School, where he received an M.B.A. in 1951.</p>
        <p>Mr. Choa became a United States citizen in 1959 by a special act of Congress in a bill introduced by John V. Lindsay, the former mayor of New York who was then a Republican congressman.</p>
        <p>In 1967, he became president of the First National City Bank's overseas division, which handled nonbanking investments.</p>
        <p>In 1972 he became director of Citicorp Investment Bank Ltd. and led its first initiative in global investment banking.</p>
        <p>He advised two Citicorp chairmen, George Moore and Walter Wriston, in the early stages of the bank's expansion overseas.</p>
        <p>In 1980, Mr. Choa joined Russell Reynolds Associates, an executive recruiting firm, and established its Hong Kong office as the managing director.</p>
        <p>In Hong Kong, he was chairman of the Harvard Business School Alumni Association and president of the International Rotary Club.</p>
        <p>Mr. Choa retired in 1999 and returned to New York. He is survived by his wife, France Berveiller Choa; two sons, Christopher and Gregory, both of Manhattan; a daughter, Veronique Pittman of Great Falls, Va.; and five grandchildren.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
