<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Developing Nation on the Frontiers of Space</title>
    <meta content="Y23ROC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alcantara (Brazil)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EED91F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Developing Nation on the Frontiers of Space</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>ALCANTARA, Brazil</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brazil and other nations in satellite launching business are hoping boom in telecommunications satellites will boost their spaceports; Brazil's Alcantara launching center's site near Equator, where Earth's rotation speed is greatest, allows rockets launched from there to carry relatively heavy payloads and use less fuel; map; tables of launches from various sites; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the satellite launching business, as in real estate, location is everything. Because of that simple fact, the spaceport the Brazilian government has built here on the eastern edge of the Amazon basin, and is now making available to foreign companies and governments, may soon become a very valuable piece of property.</p>
        <p>Situated 2 degrees south of the Equator, the Alcantara launching center, built by the Brazilian military two decades ago, has become the focal point of what is perhaps the most ambitious unmanned space program in any developing country. But it is the boom in telecommunications satellites that is likely to ensure it a prosperous future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the satellite launching business, as in real estate, location is everything. Because of that simple fact, the spaceport the Brazilian government has built here on the eastern edge of the Amazon basin, and is now making available to foreign companies and governments, may soon become a very valuable piece of property.</p>
        <p>Situated 2 degrees south of the Equator, the Alcantara launching center, built by the Brazilian military two decades ago, has become the focal point of what is perhaps the most ambitious unmanned space program in any developing country. But it is the boom in telecommunications satellites that is likely to ensure it a prosperous future.</p>
        <p>''At the end of 1998, we calculated there were going to be 800 satellites launched around the world between 2000 and 2004, and that billions of dollars were going to be spent,'' Ronaldo Sardenberg, Brazil's science and technology minister, said in an interview in the capital, Brasilia. ''We decided that we wanted to take advantage of those favorable circumstances and that Alcantara could and should be an important player on the international market.''</p>
        <p>Because of Alcantara's proximity to the Equator, rockets launched here can carry relatively heavier payloads than those launched elsewhere. The rotation speed of the Earth is greater at the Equator than in zones north and south, and the spin pushes rockets and satellites into orbit faster and with the use of less fuel. That translates into substantial savings for users and a longer useful life for the satellites. Brazilian officials estimate that a launching from Alcantara can be as much as 30 percent more efficient than one from Cape Canaveral, at 28 degrees north latitude.</p>
        <p>In addition, the areas north and east of here are largely jungle or ocean, meaning that in case of an accident, debris is unlikely to fall on populated areas. As a result, Alcantara, about 2,500 miles southeast of Miami, is able to offer clients a choice of polar or equatorial orbits or any trajectory in between.</p>
        <p>''The world needs a greater availability of launch sites,'' Luiz Gylvan Meira, the Brazilian Space Agency director, said in an interview, ''and while the niche that Alcantara finds will be dictated by the market, it is a launch site that is both good and cheap. It is good because of both its location and its availability, and it will be cheap because the Brazilian government has already put in the necessary infrastructure.''</p>
        <p>The Brazilian effort to turn Alcantara into a leading spaceport got significant help in April, when the United States and Brazil signed an accord that permits the launching of American satellites on American launchers from the base here. In return, Brazil agreed to a series of safeguards intended to prevent it from acquiring the technology of its American clients or passing that information on to other countries.</p>
        <p>The site here, its privileged geographic position notwithstanding, is not the only one seeking a share of any satellite wealth. Many European nations use a site at Kourou in French Guiana, 5 degrees north of the Equator. [On May 19, Guyana signed a deal with a Texas company, Beal Aerospace Technologies, to build a launching site there.]</p>
        <p>Various proposals have also been floated to build spaceports on the east coast of Africa and the east coast of Australia; because of the earth's rotation, a site permitting a launch eastward over water is always preferred. There have also been efforts to launch satellites from a sea platform in the Pacific, as well as from high-altitude aircraft.</p>
        <p>But since American companies account for about 80 percent of the satellite market, April's accord gives Brazil an advantage over rivals. There are 17 other sites operating around the world, but only Brazil is now authorized to launch both rockets and satellites of American make.</p>
        <p>The Alcantara agreement, said Anthony Harrington, the United States ambassador to Brazil, ''is symbolic both of the strength of the U.S.-Brazil relationship and the level of trust that is developing between the two governments.'' He predicted that several American companies would soon begin operating here, adding, ''Cape Canaveral has many advantages, but being right next to the Equator is not one of them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sardenberg, the technology minister, said ''8 of the top 15 aerospace firms in the United States'' had been at the site here, including, according to the visitors' logbook at the space center, Lockheed Martin, Orbital Sciences, Rockwell International and Boeing. He noted that both Cape Canaveral and Kourou ''have their schedules full,'' adding, ''Our objective is that this base be a profit center that can accommodate many users at the same time.''</p>
        <p>Last November, Brazil signed a wide-ranging agreement with Ukraine. It permits a consortium also including Fiat Avio of Italy to use Ukrainian-made Tsyklon-4 rockets, a liquid-fuel, three-stage rocket based on the Soviet SS-9 ballistic missile, to launch as many as 60 satellites here over five years, starting in 2001.</p>
        <p>''There is space for everyone here,'' said Col. Jose Campos Lobato, commander of the base here, with about 400 military personnel and 200 civilians. ''We have almost 250 square miles of land, so we can easily install four additional launch pads here and still have some room left over.''</p>
        <p>Construction of the base began in 1983, with the first satellite launching six years later, after nearly $300 million had been spent on roads, electricity, a command center, an airport and other infrastructure. Since then, 276 satellites or rockets have been launched from Alcantara, including 36 by NASA, though the great majority of these were suborbital rockets.</p>
        <p>Brazilian officials have made it clear that their space ambitions go far beyond offering a launch site for others' use. They hope to supply some of the satellites and rockets that will be sent up, and have maintained a wide-ranging research and development effort with that aim.</p>
        <p>The center of that program is in Sao Jose dos Campos, nearly 2,000 miles south of here. The National Institute for Space Research has its headquarters there, engaging in activities ranging from weather forecasting to industrial testing, and on an adjoining campus is the Center for Aerospace Technology, controlled by the Brazilian Air Force.</p>
        <p>The importance that Brazil attaches to its space program can be seen by looking at the institute's budget: as other government agencies tighten their belts, it has received a 36 percent increase this year. The government intends profits from future launchings to go to research and development.</p>
        <p>''In a country like this, with all the problems we have, you cannot do science just for the sake of doing science,'' said Marcio Nogueira Barbosa, the director of the space institute. ''You have to show results.''</p>
        <p>The pride of the Brazilian space effort is the Cbers satellite, which has been jointly developed with China in a $300 million program. The first of these satellites, which carry three high-resolution cameras to study environmental and agricultural conditions, was launched from Taiyuan, a Chinese base, in October, and a second is being assembled at the Brazilian institute's campus in Sao Jose dos Campos, with launching tentatively scheduled in the second half of next year.</p>
        <p>Brazilian officials said that at least two more satellites are likely to be launched with the Chinese, in an effort to turn the program into a money-making operation that can compete with NASA's Landsat program. ''Since we are a big buyer of satellite images,'' Mr. Sardenberg said, ''it is only natural that we would also want to supply high-definition photographs to a market that is so large and constantly in search of images from different angles.''</p>
        <p>Brazil is also a member of the consortium building the international space station, the only developing country to be invited to join the 15-nation group. A Brazilian astronaut is being trained in the United States for that mission, and Brazilian companies have been awarded about $120 million in construction contracts for the space vehicle.</p>
        <p>The weak link in the country's space program has been its rocket program, which aims at building a reliable launching vehicle that is cheaper than American or European rockets. An initial attempt to launch a four-stage, solid-fuel missile in 1997 failed, as did a second attempt in December, which led to widespread criticism and mockery in the press.</p>
        <p>Still, officials say they intend to go ahead with the rocket program. ''These things happen, it goes with the territory,'' said Mr. Meira, the space agency's director, ''and there is no indication that our rocket has a fundamental structural flaw. It's just that other aspects of our space effort have developed and advanced more rapidly.''</p>
        <p>Both the rocket and satellite programs began in the 1970's, when Brazil was ruled by a military dictatorship. At that time, the government encouraged the founding of companies to manufacture jet aircraft for military use and another to make tanks and armored personnel carriers, both of which were also based in Sao Jose dos Campos. These quickly found markets in Latin America, the Mideast and Asia.</p>
        <p>As a result, there were uncertainties at first whether the objectives of Brazil's space effort were scientific and commercial or primarily military. Those concerns lingered after the military handed over power to a democratic civilian government in 1985 and saw many of its other pet projects, like a costly nuclear program, mothballed.</p>
        <p>As late as 1990, in the months before the Persian Gulf war, Washington expressed concern about Brazil's supplying satellite and rocket technology to Iraq, a longtime buyer of Brazilian armored vehicles. Gen. Hugo Piva, a former director of the Center for Aerospace Technology, who was a strong advocate of a Brazilian nuclear program, has acknowledged that he sought rocket parts on the black market in an effort to accelerate the rocket program.</p>
        <p>But United States officials say that all such concerns have been eliminated in recent years. Brazil, after refusing to do so during the years of military rule, has signed a series of international agreements, including ones on nonproliferation, that paved the way for April's accord.</p>
        <p>''This is an evolutionary process in which they have moved in the right direction,'' Mr. Harrington, the American envoy, said. ''We don't have those concerns. On the other hand, the agreement is a safeguards agreement, and it involves mutual assurances'' to American companies likely to launch from here that ''there is no risk of their technology being broadcast in an unauthorized manner.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
