<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks and Pacers in the Conspiracy Series</title>
    <meta content="23KNIC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indiana Pacers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Indiana Pacers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EED81F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="988" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks and Pacers in the Conspiracy Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for NBA Eastern Conference championship playoff series between New York Knickerbockers and Indiana Pacers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The conspiracy theories were spilling out of the Miami Heat locker room Sunday evening and seeping into the public consciousness in places as far away as Indiana. But it does not matter to Jeff Van Gundy if a fan in the farmland nodded in agreement when Tim Hardaway accused the officials of cheating the Heat in Game 7.</p>
        <p>And he is not going to fret any more than usual if a Pacers zealot in Muncie puts stock in Jamal Mashburn's assertion that the Knicks had the three referees ''in their pocket'' and that the big-market fix is in by a league sensitive to nervous ticks in the ratings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The conspiracy theories were spilling out of the Miami Heat locker room Sunday evening and seeping into the public consciousness in places as far away as Indiana. But it does not matter to Jeff Van Gundy if a fan in the farmland nodded in agreement when Tim Hardaway accused the officials of cheating the Heat in Game 7.</p>
        <p>And he is not going to fret any more than usual if a Pacers zealot in Muncie puts stock in Jamal Mashburn's assertion that the Knicks had the three referees ''in their pocket'' and that the big-market fix is in by a league sensitive to nervous ticks in the ratings.</p>
        <p>If a perception becomes reality in the wheat belt, so be it.</p>
        <p>But Van Gundy does worry about any effect the referee-bashing will have on the three officials who step onto the floor of Conseco Fieldhouse tonight for Game 1 of the four-of-seven-game Eastern Conference finals between the Knicks and the Indiana Pacers.</p>
        <p>''My concern is that by the constant belaboring of such foolish points, somehow it will have a subconscious effect on both the league office and the officials, and that it will affect the upcoming series,'' Van Gundy said yesterday during a conference call nearly 24 hours after the Knicks eliminated the Heat, 83-82, in Game 7. ''Last year, it went without any repercussions. I don't know what it'll be like this year.''</p>
        <p>Last year, the Pacers were the ones looking suspiciously at the officials when their season was ended by the Knicks in the conference finals. They were devastated when the official Jess Kersey called Antonio Davis for a foul that resulted in a miracle 4-point play by Larry Johnson to win Game 3 of the series.</p>
        <p>This year, in here-we-go-again fashion, they bemoaned a call the official Joe Crawford missed in a Knicks-Pacers game on April 10; after the game, Crawford admitted that the crew blew the offensive goaltending that Patrick Ewing committed to help Johnson's 3-pointer fall with 21.7 seconds remaining.</p>
        <p>It is not surprising that the Pacers became semisympathizers with the frustration emanating from Miami's main stars on Sunday: the Heat players were incredulous over a no-call when Alonzo Mourning rescued a loose ball turned jump ball in the final minute and were irate at a mix-up by the referees on whether Latrell Sprewell stepped out of bounds or called time out with 2.1 seconds remaining.</p>
        <p>''I can understand where Miami was coming from, but Miami had their shot to win it,'' Reggie Miller said after the Pacers practiced yesterday in Indianapolis. ''If they make a couple of free throws, we're talking about Miami. But I can see where they are coming from.</p>
        <p>''We don't need no mysterious 4-point plays or no tip-ins or nothing like that. Let the best team play. I've said that from Day 1. Come playoff time, as long as they let the best team win and play, I'll handle that. If there is some funny business going on we can't control, so be it.''</p>
        <p>There is something humorous about all this to Rod Thorn. Merely the thought, as Van Gundy suggested, that the league would be influenced by the Heat's pouting or that the National Basketball Association's brain trust is somehow the Svengali over the outcome to every game left Thorn, the league's vice president for operations, chuckling at the absurdity of it all.</p>
        <p>''If the league ever overtly or tacitly suggested that the referees favor a particular team or player, it would take about 24 hours to be in every newspaper in the country,'' said Thorn, who is investigating the remarks made by the Heat to see if fines should be levied. ''That doesn't happen. We couldn't care less who wins or loses. It's not right to say there is a conspiracy, but that seems to be the popular thing to do today.</p>
        <p>''For whatever reason, as more teams are eliminated, they want to blame outside forces for why they lost. You don't see nearly enough of X team played well, or X team did a good job. It's become sort of the popular thing to blame someone else for the loss. This past series between the Heat and Knicks was hotly contested. Every game could have gone either way. It just so happens the Knicks prevailed. The conspiracy theories and other reasons regarding why a game was won or lost are ludicrous.''</p>
        <p>Van Gundy might believe this. But it was good politics to bring up the officiating angle with a series coming up against an Indiana team that went to the free-throw line 113 times during its four-game regular-season split with the Knicks, while the Knicks went only 52 times. Van Gundy is well aware that Miller's whipsaw reactions to contact on the floor often land him at the free-throw line. Maybe, with that in mind, it was not such a bad idea to wring his hands over Miami's bluster.</p>
        <p>''Every time we shoot more free throws, it's a league conspiracy,'' Van Gundy said. ''When Miami shoots 21 free throws in the first half of Game 6, that's hard driving to the basket. It's not my fault they're a jump-shooting team.</p>
        <p>''You know, we were 8-9 with that same officiating group this year. The year before, with those same three guys we had in Game 7, we were 10-12. If we had them 'in our pocket,' we had them in the wrong pocket. I just find it unfortunate. I can understand Miami's disappointment. But certainly, with Mashburn and Hardaway, I really believe they should be just as disappointed in themselves going 9 of 35 from the field as they are in the free-throw discrepancy.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
