<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An MTV Prankster Gets (Mostly) Serious About His Cancer</title>
    <meta content="23JAME$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Green, Tom</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Tom Green Cancer Special, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EFD81E3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An MTV Prankster Gets (Mostly) Serious About His Cancer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James reviews The Tom Green Cancer Special, on MTV, on Green's treatment for testicular cancer; Green photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This is so different from ''E.R.'' In fact, though ''The Tom Green Cancer Special'' takes place largely in a hospital, following its star as he is treated for testicular cancer, this stomach-churning, affecting, original special is different from anything that has ever been on television.</p>
        <p>The cult star of his own MTV series, in which his camera captures reactions to practical jokes that delight 15-year-olds, Mr. Green is just beginning to emerge as a mainstream personality. Last week on the ''Tonight'' show he put a squirming white mouse in his mouth, re-enacting a scene from his current movie, ''Road Trip,'' and horrifying Judge Judy, sitting next to him on the couch. With a wide-eyed gaze and a goatee, he looks both innocent and devilish, a style that perfectly expresses his personality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This is so different from ''E.R.'' In fact, though ''The Tom Green Cancer Special'' takes place largely in a hospital, following its star as he is treated for testicular cancer, this stomach-churning, affecting, original special is different from anything that has ever been on television.</p>
        <p>The cult star of his own MTV series, in which his camera captures reactions to practical jokes that delight 15-year-olds, Mr. Green is just beginning to emerge as a mainstream personality. Last week on the ''Tonight'' show he put a squirming white mouse in his mouth, re-enacting a scene from his current movie, ''Road Trip,'' and horrifying Judge Judy, sitting next to him on the couch. With a wide-eyed gaze and a goatee, he looks both innocent and devilish, a style that perfectly expresses his personality.</p>
        <p>However adolescent his humor, though, it can be serious and revealing as it shatters cultural assumptions. He turned a corner with his recent special in which he took Monica Lewinsky to Canada, where he grew up, ostensibly to buy fabric for her line of handbags. He took her to dinner with his parents, the beleaguered victims of so many of his pranks. The tone was poignant simply because he was nice to her, neither fawning nor rude. (Think of how different that attitude is.) Gradually, deeper resonances emerged: of course he was making fun of her, but they were both making more fun of the people who came out to gawk at her; and it was a bit sad to see how willing she was to go along.</p>
        <p>His ''Cancer Special'' is another breakthrough. It deserves its viewer's warning; the show is excruciating to sit though because it includes a long, unflinching look at the operation (no one except a surgeon should ever get that close to human intestines) and a visit to the pathology lab where we see the mashed-up testicle that had been removed in a previous operation. Yet beyond its shock value, the show is also a bizarre television landmark, willfully erasing all boundaries between narcissism and art, black humor and gross-out comedy, private and public lives, good taste and bad.</p>
        <p>''I was going to live this secret life with one testicle,'' he says here, explaining his reaction after the cancerous testicle was removed. When he needed a second operation to remove and test lymph nodes in his abdomen, he decided to take the cameras along. His special is the video generation's equivalent of the confessional memoir, a kind of public therapy in which self-revelation becomes a survival strategy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green is so known for pranks that the immediate reaction to the news he had cancer was that he must be joking. The special is no joke. A large part was filmed at the University of Southern California, where he was treated. The chairman of the urology department explains that while testicular cancer accounts for only 1 to 2 percent of male cancers, it is the most common form among 15- to 35-year-old men. (Mr. Green is 28.)</p>
        <p>Such informative moments are not the point, though. The special is shaped by nervous laughter. Mr. Green recruits those closest to him and they gamely try to adopt his defensive, mocking attitude. He goes to dinner with his parents, his girlfriend Drew Barrymore and his two regular sidekicks from his show, Glenn Humplick and Phil Giroux. He gives the waitress an elaborate, uncomfortable explanation of his disease, and she replies, ''You want to see a wine list?''</p>
        <p>This particular kind of cancer gives him plenty of opportunities for jokes that would never make it on network television. Yet there are also moments that seem unintentionally touching. Being fitted for what he calls his burial suit (actually the suit he wore to the Oscars), he asks for ''a last picture of me alive with my mother, in a nice suit.''</p>
        <p>''Tom, you're going to live,'' his mother says, sweetly and as cheerfully as she can, kissing him on the cheek. ''What did the doctor tell you today? He said, 'Tom, you're going to be fine.' ''</p>
        <p>He looks close to tears, though he recovers by saying, ''You're wrinkling my suit, Mom.''</p>
        <p>In the hospital he asks the doctor, ''Is it possible I'm going to wake up screaming?''</p>
        <p>Seeing the operation is the price viewers pay for the rest of the special. Even Mr. Green says, with his deadpan delivery, ''I was kind of hoping it would have been funnier inside my body.''</p>
        <p>After that, there are some genuinely funny moments, including a singalong ditty about the value of self-examination, complete with lyrics on screen and a bouncing testicle over the words.</p>
        <p>Appearing to a cheering crowd at the University of Florida, he has turned his terrifying experience into comedy, helped by the fact that the doctors found no trace of cancer during the second operation. Still, he ends the special by saying, ''Hopefully, my cancer won't come back and I won't die.'' Performers are rarely so chilling, blunt or honest.</p>
        <p>FRONTLINE  The Battle Over School Choice  PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 10)</p>
        <p>To flip back and forth between the taboo-shattering Tom Green and the staid ''Frontline'' would be to invite an extreme case of cultural whiplash. Despite its eye-glazing title, though, ''The Battle Over School Choice'' turns out to be a smooth, humanizing primer on an issue that is both central to the presidential campaign and deadly dull in the abstract. The main subject is vouchers, with which the government pays for students to attend private schools.</p>
        <p>Focusing on Cleveland, the evenhanded special presents voucher students whose futures have been salvaged by the opportunity, as well as others who attended a school whose founders absconded with the government's money. There are interviews with Vice President Al Gore, who opposes vouchers, and Gov. George W. Bush, who supports them, but the documentary makes the point that there is less difference between the candidates' views than their ads contend. (And really, who is against higher standards and better education?)</p>
        <p>The failure of this otherwise lucid, engaging documentary is in its modest ambition: it offers only glancing references to a profound, underlying issue it is easier to ignore: how much the battle over school choice is really about race and class.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
