<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Was the Day That Time Stood Still</title>
    <meta content="23SAND$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFD81F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Was the Day That Time Stood Still</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Sandomir TV Sports column discusses NBC television coverage of seventh and final game of New York Knickerbockers-Miami Heat Eastern Conference semifinal playoff series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Speed had no place Sunday in the fourth quarter of Game 7 of the Knicks-Miami grudge match. You could call it timeless basketball if you were serving time. The quarter lasted 48 minutes 56 seconds.</p>
        <p>The last two minutes -- the only part of a Knicks-Heat playoff game that requires your undivided attention -- needed 16:46 to complete.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Speed had no place Sunday in the fourth quarter of Game 7 of the Knicks-Miami grudge match. You could call it timeless basketball if you were serving time. The quarter lasted 48 minutes 56 seconds.</p>
        <p>The last two minutes -- the only part of a Knicks-Heat playoff game that requires your undivided attention -- needed 16:46 to complete.</p>
        <p>What took so long? The quarter did not have an excessive number of free throws -- 16 were attempted -- or fisticuffs. NBC's Ahmad Rashad did not conduct Coors Light pouring clinics during timeouts with his commercial bud, Bill Russell.</p>
        <p>The slowdown did not commence until 1:33 remained on the clock. A Tim Hardaway 3-pointer, putting Miami up, 82-81, prompted a Knicks timeout. Two minutes of commercials followed. Another timeout with 26.3 seconds left led to two more minutes of commercials. A jump ball following a wild shot by Hardaway needed 32 seconds to set up. Having won the jump, Miami called time. More commercials.</p>
        <p>All this resembled a baseball game, minus the dirt kicking, meandering around home plate, wandering around the mound and shaking off catchers' signs.</p>
        <p>A scramble after Clarence Weatherspoon's missed jumper with six seconds left required 48 seconds of deliberation by the officials before they determined that Latrell Sprewell (or another Knick) had called a timeout. Another 90 seconds of spots ensued. A recapitulation of the frantic sequence cost 40 seconds.</p>
        <p>When Charlie Ward could not pass the ball in, he called time. So NBC sneaked in a 30-second spot. NBC returned before the timeout ended with 48 seconds of players' backs. Finally, the nearly 50-minute quarter ended with Ward's inbounds pass.</p>
        <p>The elasticized fourth quarter did not bother viewers much. The game generated an 8.7 overnight Nielsen rating, up 16 percent from the comparable game last year. So far, it is NBC's highest-rated playoff game this postseason. The last half-hour produced an 11.8 rating.</p>
        <p>NBC's Bill Walton and Steve Jones never acknowledged the creeping pace of game time. Had he noted it, Walton would have surely pronounced it ''horrible.'' And Walton, especially, offered a characteristically provocative performance in Game 7.</p>
        <p>Regarding the struggling Knicks forward Marcus Camby, Walton said, ''The effort is there, but never mistake activity for achievement.''</p>
        <p>When the Knicks' Kurt Thomas picked up a foul, then a technical foul, Jones said his lack of control ''is his Waterloo.'' Walton, however, is too enamored of Thomas, often praising him as if he were Charles Oakley.</p>
        <p>Walton rarely let up on his idea that Miami Coach Pat Riley should not rest Alonzo Mourning at all. Riley subsequently rested Mourning, who scored 14 points in the first quarter, plus Dan Majerle and Jamal Mashburn, and all at once, early in the second. When the Knicks tied the game at 29-29, after a 9-0 run, Walton said: ''Riley only has himself to blame. He takes three guys out, they lose the lead.''</p>
        <p>When Jones raised the notion later in the game that Riley should rest Mourning again, Walton loudly said, ''Don't give him any ideas!''</p>
        <p>Walton railed when Knicks Coach Jeff Van Gundy sat Sprewell. ''You can't do that,'' he said. ''You're down 4 points in the fourth quarter.''</p>
        <p>Jones, who exists to refute Walton's world view, said: ''You've got 10 minutes to play. You know Miami will go on another drought.''</p>
        <p>Walton said: ''I have never seen Latrell Sprewell need a rest. Ever.''</p>
        <p>Jones persisted, saying Van Gundy saw a need to refocus Sprewell, who was in a scoring drought, rather than give him a rest. Trumped, Walton did not reply.</p>
        <p>In close games, Walton has toned down his extreme analyses -- which often sound contemptuous -- and his verbal excesses. Still, he is blunt about unintelligent play, and impatient when great players foul up.</p>
        <p>When Mourning risked stealing a pass to Ewing, who dunked it to put the Knicks up for good, 83-82, with 1:20 to go, Walton said: ''He's blocking every shot coming at him. Ewing hasn't had a go-to move all day, and Alonzo Mourning makes an ill-advised decision to come over his back.''</p>
        <p>Walton, Jones and Tom Hammond will call the Eastern Conference finals between the Knicks and Indiana on NBC, while Bob Costas and Doug Collins are describing the Portland-Los Angeles Lakers Western finals.</p>
        <p>Where is Marv Albert, who will replace Costas in NBC's top play-by-play slot next season? His deal with the MSG Network, which employs him to call Knicks games on WFAN and be the host for ''MSG SportsDesk,'' keeps him from calling any Knicks games during the week, so Dick Stockton will call the Knicks-Indiana games on TNT tonight and Thursday. Meanwhile, NBC would not put Albert on the series, out of loyalty to Hammond. When his laryngitis clears up, Albert will call some of the games on WFAN. Gus Johnson is assigned to call Games 1 and 2.</p>
        <p>Limbaugh Makes the Call</p>
        <p>Rush Limbaugh, the conservative radio talk show host, told WMAL-AM radio in Washington yesterday that he auditioned for ABC's ''Monday Night Football,'' in Los Angeles on a recorded game with Al Michaels and said the results were ''excellent.'' By speaking publicly about the audition -- during a process run as secretly as the Manhattan Project -- Limbaugh may have blown his chance.</p>
        <p>TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
