<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accounting Standards Committee Named</title>
    <meta content="Y23ACC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201733"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Accounting Standards Committee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levitt, Arthur Jr (Chmn)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Volcker, Paul A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Roy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Biggs, John H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crockett, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Teixeira da Costa, Roberto</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ferraini, Guido A (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fortier, L Ives</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fukuma, Toshikatsu</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herkstroter, Cornelius</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kopper, Hilmar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Laskawy, Philip A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Charles Yeh Kwong</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipworth, Sydney (Sir)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pineau-Valencienne, Didler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roder, Jens</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ruder, David S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spencer, Kenneth H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steere, William C Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tajika, Koji</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EEDF1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accounting Standards Committee Named</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Panel led by Securities and Exchange Commission Chmn Arthur Levitt Jr names Paul A Volcker, former Federal Reserve chairman, to head new body, International Accounting Standards Committee, that will choose people who will set international accounting standards; names 16 other trustees; Levitt and Volcker comment, interviews; list of trustees; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The long-range goal of establishing worldwide accounting standards -- making it possible for companies to compile one set of books for investors everywhere -- may be moving closer to reality with new efforts to put together an international standards setter that will be accepted in both the United States and Europe.</p>
        <p>Paul A. Volcker, the former Federal Reserve chairman, was named yesterday to head a new body that will choose the people who will set the international standards. The 14 people they select will replace the current International Accounting Standards Committee, which has been dominated by accounting professionals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The long-range goal of establishing worldwide accounting standards -- making it possible for companies to compile one set of books for investors everywhere -- may be moving closer to reality with new efforts to put together an international standards setter that will be accepted in both the United States and Europe.</p>
        <p>Paul A. Volcker, the former Federal Reserve chairman, was named yesterday to head a new body that will choose the people who will set the international standards. The 14 people they select will replace the current International Accounting Standards Committee, which has been dominated by accounting professionals.</p>
        <p>The path to truly international accounting standards has been a rocky one because standards vary widely among nations and because the United States, with the most comprehensive standards and in some ways the most restrictive, has been loath to accept international standards.</p>
        <p>But that has begun to change as American regulators conclude that their principal advantage in forcing large companies to comply with American standards may lose its effectiveness in coming years. That weapon is the requirement that any foreign company that wants to list its stock on an American market like the New York Stock Exchange or Nasdaq, must reconcile its books to American accounting rules.</p>
        <p>Technology has opened the possibility of international stock markets that span national boundaries and make it easy for an investor in the United States to buy shares in a foreign company that has no American listing. ''I worry about what happens in an electronic market, where the value of a listing is likely to be diminished,'' Arthur Levitt, the chairman of the Securities and Exchange Commission, said in an interview yesterday. In a round of international negotiations last year and early this year, Mr. Levitt held out the prospect of possible American acceptance of international standards to prompt a change in the way those standards are set. He became the chairman of a body that chose Mr. Volcker and 16 other trustees of the new organization. The trustees' job will be to pick the standard setters and then raise money to keep the body in business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Volcker said he hoped the board would be appointed by the end of this year. The 14 people are to be chosen based on technical expertise. At least five of them are to have experience as practicing auditors.</p>
        <p>Seven of the 14 board members are to be liaisons with national accounting standards bodies, like the Financial Accounting Standards Board in the United States.</p>
        <p>There is still no assurance that the S.E.C. or any other country's market regulator will accept international standards.</p>
        <p>But the progress makes it more likely that the S.E.C. will at least gradually move toward international standards, possibly by certifying that accounts that comply with a particular international standard will not have to reconcile that part of the books with United States standards, even though other parts must be so reconciled.</p>
        <p>The politics of accepting international standards in the United States have shifted somewhat in recent years.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, much of corporate America was pushing for it, in some cases because they hoped international standards would be looser than American ones. But some of that support has vanished because more recent international standards have been more rigorous.</p>
        <p>One of the most emotional battles in accounting covers merger accounting rules. The F.A.S.B., citing in part the fact that international standards do not allow a form of merger accounting known as pooling, has proposed ending that type of accounting. That move, which would hurt reported profits of many companies that make acquisitions, has touched off complaints to Congress and could lead to legislation aimed at reversing the F.A.S.B. decision.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Volcker, the other trustees for the International Accounting Standards Committee are:</p>
        <p>Roy Andersen, chief executive of Liberty Life, a South African company; John H. Biggs, the chairman of TIAA-CREF, an American money management firm; Andrew Crockett, general manager of the Bank for International Settlements; Roberto Teixeira da Costa, former chairman of the Comissao de Valores Mobiliarios of Brazil; Guido A. Ferrarini, a law professor at the University of Genoa in Italy; L. Yves Fortier, chairman of Ogilvy Renault, a Canadian law firm; Toshikatsu Fukuma, chief financial officer of Mitsui &amp; Company; Cornelius Herkstroter, former president of Royal Dutch Petroleum; Hilmar Kopper, chairman of the supervisory board of Deutsche Bank; Philip A. Laskawy, the chairman of Ernst &amp; Young International; Charles Yeh Kwong Lee, chairman of Hong Kong Exchange and Clearing Ltd.; Sir Sydney Lipworth, the chairman of the U.K. Financial Reporting Council; Didier Pineau-Valencienne, chairman of Association Francaise des Enterprises Privees; Jens Roder, a senior partner of PricewaterhouseCoopers; David S. Ruder, a former chairman of the S.E.C.; Kenneth H. Spencer, the chairman of the Australian Accounting Standards Board; William C. Steere Jr., chairman and chief executive of Pfizer Inc.; and Koji Tajika, co-chairman of Deloitte Touche Tohmatsu.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
