<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israel's Volatile Border</title>
    <meta content="23TUE1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Syria</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hezbollah</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barak, Ehud (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E0D91F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israel's Volatile Border</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial comments on Israel's withdrawal from security zone in southern Lebanon, sudden disentegration of large sections of pro-Israel Southern Lebanon Army and quick advance by Hezbollah guerrillas into area; says quick move by Hezbollah seems to have caught Israel unprepared but that Prime Min Ehud Barak must nevertheless respond to new dangers in way that allows Israeli withdrawal to proceed without delay; says Syria must guarantee that Hezbollah does not use new position to launch attacks against Israeli territory (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israel's hopes for an orderly withdrawal from its security zone in Southern Lebanon this summer were jolted yesterday by the sudden disintegration of large sections of the Southern Lebanon Army, a pro-Israeli militia. With Syria's blessing, Lebanese Hezbollah guerrillas quickly moved into the vacuum left by the militia's collapse, seizing fortified positions laden with Israeli munitions and occupying a slice of the zone reaching to the Israeli border.</p>
        <p>Hezbollah's advance, which seems to have caught Israel unprepared, has increased the danger to Israeli troops still in Lebanon and to Israeli civilians across the border. Prime Minister Ehud Barak must respond to these dangers in a way that allows the Israeli withdrawal to proceed without delay. Overnight his security cabinet authorized him to speed the withdrawal timetable, to minimize the chance for further chaos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Israel's hopes for an orderly withdrawal from its security zone in Southern Lebanon this summer were jolted yesterday by the sudden disintegration of large sections of the Southern Lebanon Army, a pro-Israeli militia. With Syria's blessing, Lebanese Hezbollah guerrillas quickly moved into the vacuum left by the militia's collapse, seizing fortified positions laden with Israeli munitions and occupying a slice of the zone reaching to the Israeli border.</p>
        <p>Hezbollah's advance, which seems to have caught Israel unprepared, has increased the danger to Israeli troops still in Lebanon and to Israeli civilians across the border. Prime Minister Ehud Barak must respond to these dangers in a way that allows the Israeli withdrawal to proceed without delay. Overnight his security cabinet authorized him to speed the withdrawal timetable, to minimize the chance for further chaos.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Syria, as the dominant military power in Lebanon, must see to it that Hezbollah does not use its new positions to launch rocket attacks on Israeli territory. Any such shellings could bring Israeli reprisals that could spread beyond the immediate border area and involve both Lebanon and Syria.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak promised during his election campaign last year to withdraw Israeli troops from Lebanon within a year of his taking office. That deadline runs out in early July. Most Israelis oppose maintaining the 22-year-old security zone. It has left Israeli troops exposed to constant guerrilla attack without significantly increasing Israel's security.</p>
        <p>But carrying out the withdrawal became a lot harder after peace talks between Israel and Syria broke down in March. Syria's president, Hafez al-Assad, hoped to see the Lebanese border issue resolved as part of a package deal that would also returned the Golan Heights to Syria. With no such bargain in sight, Damascus seems to feel little incentive to assure a smooth Israeli withdrawal.</p>
        <p>For years the Arab world demanded that Israel withdraw from Lebanon as provided under the terms of a United Nations resolution. But now that Israel has begun doing so, the Syrian and Lebanese governments are undermining a smooth transition. Syria ought to be arranging for Lebanese Army units to move into areas vacated by Israel and its militia allies. By instead permitting Hezbollah guerrillas to move up to the Israeli border, Syria jeopardizes Lebanon's chances for future peace and adds a dangerous new element of instability to the Middle East.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
