<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Joining the Club: Like Others, China Will Try to Protect Its Own Industries</title>
    <meta content="Y23SHAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Trade Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EEDE1F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1245" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Joining the Club: Like Others, China Will Try to Protect Its Own Industries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis of China's possible entry into World Trade Organization, focusing on many loopholes behind promises of free trade (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sun Guomin, a poor farmer in a village west of here, represents an example of why American business executives and government officials may be disappointed once China enters the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>While American businesses have been dreaming of the vast potential markets for their goods and services in China, the government is unlikely to allow the West the kind of access those dreams are made of. For if Beijing immediately did everything the trade organization requires, Mr. Sun and millions like him could be driven out of business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sun Guomin, a poor farmer in a village west of here, represents an example of why American business executives and government officials may be disappointed once China enters the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>While American businesses have been dreaming of the vast potential markets for their goods and services in China, the government is unlikely to allow the West the kind of access those dreams are made of. For if Beijing immediately did everything the trade organization requires, Mr. Sun and millions like him could be driven out of business.</p>
        <p>And with droves of laid-off workers already mounting sporadic protests across the country, giving foreign competition a hand in wiping out whole industries could amount to political suicide for China's governing Communist Party.</p>
        <p>Agriculture is one of the most vulnerable areas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sun, 68, is struggling to get by on his six and a half acres of land in the village of Nansong, west of Shanghai, where he lives in a mud house on a dirt path with his wife, Chen Baonan.</p>
        <p>He has already stopped growing barley, once a major crop in this part of the flat Yangtze River delta, because it does not pay. He and his neighbors still grow rapeseed, the source of canola oil, and the plant's brilliant yellow flowers carpet the delta with color each spring.</p>
        <p>But the price the government pays for rapeseed has fallen so low, Mr. Sun says, that he is better off pressing the seeds himself and using the cooking oil at home. He would gladly lease his field to a factory, but the government will not let him, citing a need to preserve farmland. He and his wife have opened a small store in the front of their house, where they make about five cents a day selling cigarettes and beer.</p>
        <p>Joining the W.T.O. threatens to make China's agricultural economics even worse.</p>
        <p>Last year China imported record quantities of rapeseed and soybeans, because foreign oilseed production is cheaper and the quality often higher than that of domestically grown crops. But to enter the trade group, China has agreed to lift quotas that it now uses to restrict the import of edible oils. A surge in imports would further dampen demand for seeds from people like Mr. Sun.</p>
        <p>The problem exists pretty much across the board.</p>
        <p>The Chinese Academy of Social Sciences, a top government research institute in Beijing, recently estimated that prices for Chinese grain and other agricultural products would continue to exceed those of the global market for the next 20 years.</p>
        <p>Thanks to huge mechanized farms, the American cost of production is often lower than that in China, where farming employs as many as 600 million people, fields are fragmented and transportation is slow.</p>
        <p>And many other labor-intensive industries are in the same boat.</p>
        <p>Many of the country's 100-plus automobile assembly plants face extinction if imports surge as tariffs fall, and chemical plants could be crippled by foreign competition. The Chinese government wants to reform the economy, but it favors a cautious, go-slow approach rather than risk widespread unrest that could undermine its rule.</p>
        <p>''It's important to think about stability,'' said Zhou Hanming, a lawyer who advises the government about the W.T.O.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhou says that the two to five years in which the organization requires members to put most of its mandated measures into effect is too short a time, and that China will do what it must to shelter industries until they are ready to face global competition.</p>
        <p>''We're working very hard on a large number of new laws and regulations that will offer protection of national industries, vulnerable industries, infant industries,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zhou, one of dozens of experts Beijing has enlisted to prepare the country to defend its industries, is studying ways to use anti-dumping rules. Under China's trade deal with the United States, Washington insisted that it be allowed to levy punitive duties against imports that it deems to be sold below cost. Washington wanted the clause to protect the American textile industry from cheap Chinese imports, but China has seized on the provision to protect its own threatened industries.</p>
        <p>''We're going to learn how to use the same weapon,'' Mr. Zhou said.</p>
        <p>The country will also use other means to give threatened industries an edge, including preferential bank loans and tax breaks. And Beijing may end longstanding tax breaks for foreign companies that were intended to encourage investment.</p>
        <p>But China does hope to use its membership in the trade group as a lever to move moribund state industries toward real reform.</p>
        <p>Take the pharmaceutical industry, which still relies largely on copies, often illegal, of Western compounds. China will come under pressure from the group to enforce the intellectual property rights of foreign drug makers. To survive, Chinese pharmaceutical firms will have to invest in research and development and begin producing original drugs.</p>
        <p>''The pressure will help force us to depend on ourselves,'' said Wang Li, general manager of the Shanghai Joy Biopharm Company, a state-owned drug laboratory started five years ago to develop commercially viable pharmaceuticals for the domestic industry.</p>
        <p>And China hopes that membership in the group will spur foreign investment, which fell last year for the first time since investors withdrew after the crackdown on pro-democracy protesters at Tiananmen Square in June 1989.</p>
        <p>Multinational corporations have already begun signaling their willingness to pump more money into China after it joins. Nonetheless, protection is high on Beijing's agenda.</p>
        <p>China is not known for its strict adherence to trade agreements. In 1995, Trade Minister Wu Yi signed a deal with the United States trade representative, Charlene Barshefsky, that promised to protect American intellectual property rights. But counterfeiting of computer software and movies on compact disks is now more common than ever. Street hawkers sell the latest Hollywood blockbusters in most Chinese cities, and the police ignore the activity.</p>
        <p>Nor has China proven a progressive member of another trade club. As a member of the Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation forum, it has resisted moves to speed the liberalization of financial services.</p>
        <p>The opening of China's market is more likely to mirror that of Japan's. Tokyo agreed to open its tightly closed rice market starting in 1995 with a so-called minimum access program. But thanks to various protectionist measures, imports still account for less than 7 percent of the rice consumed in Japan.</p>
        <p>China may take its cue from other members of the trade group as well. Despite pressure from the group, for example, the European Union continues to protect its farmers from imported bananas and hormone-treated beef.</p>
        <p>And even if China does follow the organization's rules, there is plenty of room for interpretation. As a member, the country has agreed to import 20 foreign-made films a year. But it can reduce the competitive impact on its own film industry by picking films from, say, other Asian countries instead of Hollywood.</p>
        <p>''Behind the promise there are related mechanisms and measures to restrict what is promised,'' one of China's trade negotiators told Hua Sheng Monthly, a state-owned newspaper. For example, China promised to let foreign insurance companies operate in 15 cities in two years' time, up from the 3 cities to which they are now limited. ''But 'allow' does not necessarily mean that companies can enter the market,'' the official was quoted as saying. ''They will still need approval.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
