<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tension And Tragedy As Traveling Companions</title>
    <meta content="23CAB.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Anita</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glesser, Mark R</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hansen's Cab (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1D81E3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tension And Tragedy As Traveling Companions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANITA GATES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gates, Anita</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anita Gates reviews Mark R Glesser play Hansen's Cab, directed by Glesser, at Jose Quintero Theater (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you passed Florence and Arthur Gateman on the road, you probably wouldn't give them a second look. Dressed nicely in the fashions of their time, 1958 -- she in a fashionable brown suit, he in jacket, tie and fedora -- they might be any middle-aged American couple on a motoring vacation. But some people might run if they knew that the Gatemans' passenger, an attractive but distressed young woman, had Hansen's disease (more commonly known as leprosy). In Mark R. Giesser's drama ''Hansen's Cab,'' the Gatemans (Melissa Hart and Avrom Berel) make their living transporting patients from their homes to leprosariums, in this case United States Military Hospital No. 66 in Carville, La.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Talavera (Heather Randall), the patient, did not leave her home and her two small children willingly. So there is serious tension between her and the Gatemans. Luckily she takes a walk where they've parked, somewhere in the Guadalupe Mountains of Texas, and meets a helpful archaeologist (John Wayne Shafer) who is one-quarter Apache and knows a lot about American Indian healing ceremonies. There is also a chance that they are standing on what was once considered sacred ground. Mr. Shafer doubles in the role of an Indian dancer -- or perhaps just Jennifer's vision of one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you passed Florence and Arthur Gateman on the road, you probably wouldn't give them a second look. Dressed nicely in the fashions of their time, 1958 -- she in a fashionable brown suit, he in jacket, tie and fedora -- they might be any middle-aged American couple on a motoring vacation. But some people might run if they knew that the Gatemans' passenger, an attractive but distressed young woman, had Hansen's disease (more commonly known as leprosy). In Mark R. Giesser's drama ''Hansen's Cab,'' the Gatemans (Melissa Hart and Avrom Berel) make their living transporting patients from their homes to leprosariums, in this case United States Military Hospital No. 66 in Carville, La.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Talavera (Heather Randall), the patient, did not leave her home and her two small children willingly. So there is serious tension between her and the Gatemans. Luckily she takes a walk where they've parked, somewhere in the Guadalupe Mountains of Texas, and meets a helpful archaeologist (John Wayne Shafer) who is one-quarter Apache and knows a lot about American Indian healing ceremonies. There is also a chance that they are standing on what was once considered sacred ground. Mr. Shafer doubles in the role of an Indian dancer -- or perhaps just Jennifer's vision of one.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giesser, whose 1998 play, ''The Night They Burned Washington,'' was an antiwar drama set in 1814, still has a talent for dialogue (''What myth did you base your marriage on?'' Florence asks Jennifer pleasantly). And he has something to say; the possible quarantine of people with AIDS is clearly the analogy. But Mr. Giesser is still guilty of making his plots a little too eventful and not having a sure hold on the personalities he has created.</p>
        <p>It seems completely out of character when Florence shows Jennifer a .38 handgun and suggests that if Jennifer wants to kill herself, she can ''provide the means.'' It's even more jarring (but funny) when Jennifer, complaining about being treated like a criminal, says, ''Friends don't use handcuffs,'' and Florence replies, ''You've never been to Greenwich Village.'' Sacrificing character for a one-liner is a common temptation for writers, and Mr. Giesser yields.</p>
        <p>There is a complicated back story about Arthur's having lost his medical license and about the Gatemans' meeting and courtship in Liverpool, England (''Cleveland without the charm''), during the war. If this information is supposed to make an emotional connection with the rest of the play, it isn't clear.</p>
        <p>There is a temptation to say that the director doesn't understand the playwright's work, but Mr. Giesser is directing his own play. It continues at the Jose Quintero Theater through Sunday.</p>
        <p>HANSEN'S CAB  Written and directed by Mark R. Giesser; sets by John C. Scheffler; costumes by Melanie Ann Schmidt; lighting by Aaron Meadow; choreography by Sharon Halley; assistant director, Steven Ditmyer; stage manager, Marcos Dinnerstein; assistant stage manager, Kim Marie T. Jones. Presented by Alces Productions. At the Jose Quintero Theater, 534 West 42nd Street, Clinton.</p>
        <p>WITH: Avrom Berel (Arthur Gateman), Melissa Hart (Florence Gateman), Heather Randall (Jennifer Talavera) and John Wayne Shafer (Clay Mitchell).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
