<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chancellor's Political Ability Balances His Outsider Status</title>
    <meta content="23LEVY$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1201806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O (Chancellor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartocollis, Anemona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E5D81F3AF930A15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2370" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chancellor's Political Ability Balances His Outsider Status</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANEMONA HARTOCOLLIS and ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hartocollis, Anemona; Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harold O Levy's pragmatic approach to management explains how as high-level corporate lawyer with no experience running single school he became chancellor of New York City school system, nation's largest; in his first 125 days, he has surprised even savviest insiders by going from dark horse for interim chancellor, with Mayor Rudolph Giuliani opposing him, to unanimous choice for permanent job, with mayor instructing his appointees to support him; he is remembered by friends and colleagues, from his earliest days as student government president at Bronx High School of Science to ascension as international corporate trouble-shooter, as consummate politician with shrewd strategic intelligence, honed by his experience as courtroom litigator; with knowledge acquired from three years on State Board of Regents, he has passionate sense of how to improve schools; has promised to hire better teachers, crack down on superintendents and principals whose students perform poorly and lobby aggressively for more city and state aid; as father of young schoolchildren he has sense of what parents want, and has moved quickly to reach out to groups that have felt shut out; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week, as Harold O. Levy pulled off the improbable feat of becoming chancellor of the New York City schools, he announced at a cabinet meeting that 30 volumes of chancellor's regulations -- accumulating since 1958 -- had been slashed to 9 volumes. Gone were vestiges like how to help students deal with the assassination of President John F. Kennedy.</p>
        <p>Yes, a staff member fretted in a reporter's presence, but shouldn't he run the changes past the 43 district and other superintendents first? ''No,'' Mr. Levy replied. ''Just do it. If we have to restore some, we can do that later.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last week, as Harold O. Levy pulled off the improbable feat of becoming chancellor of the New York City schools, he announced at a cabinet meeting that 30 volumes of chancellor's regulations -- accumulating since 1958 -- had been slashed to 9 volumes. Gone were vestiges like how to help students deal with the assassination of President John F. Kennedy.</p>
        <p>Yes, a staff member fretted in a reporter's presence, but shouldn't he run the changes past the 43 district and other superintendents first? ''No,'' Mr. Levy replied. ''Just do it. If we have to restore some, we can do that later.''</p>
        <p>''Just do it'' could be Mr. Levy's motto. As much as anything, his pragmatic approach to management explains how a high-level corporate lawyer with no experience running a single school became the chancellor of the country's largest school system. In his first 125 days, he has surprised even the savviest insiders by going from dark horse for interim chancellor -- with Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani opposing him -- to unanimous choice for the permanent job, with the mayor instructing his appointees to support him.</p>
        <p>From his earliest days as student government president at the Bronx High School of Science to his ascension to international trouble-shooter for Sanford I. Weill, the chairman and chief executive of Citigroup, Mr. Levy is remembered by friends and colleagues as a consummate politician with a shrewd strategic intelligence, honed by his experience as a courtroom litigator.</p>
        <p>With knowledge acquired from three years on the State Board of Regents, he has a passionate sense of how to improve the schools, and has promised to hire better teachers, crack down on superintendents and principals whose students perform poorly and lobby aggressively for more state and city aid. As the father of young schoolchildren, albeit children attending private school, he has a sense of what parents want, and has moved quickly to reach out to groups that have felt shut out.</p>
        <p>But there may be a flip side to Mr. Levy's cunning, charm and admitted love of the limelight. He has a tendency, associates say, to assume that he knows the answers, even when he may not. And he can be as imperious as he is seductive, sometimes letting his drive to get things done blind him to the distress or disagreement of those around him.</p>
        <p>''He could be a chancellor to reckon with,'' said one longtime superintendent, ''if he learns to listen.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy's background as a corporate lawyer with no formal credentials in education, and his skill in making quick decisions, may give him the fresh perspective and brashness needed to make radical changes. But his outsider status could also be a liability. He is the first white full-time chancellor since 1983, in a system that is 84 percent black, Hispanic and Asian, and only 16 percent white.</p>
        <p>Indeed, race was in the air as he attended a forum led by the Rev. Al Sharpton in Harlem two Saturdays ago.</p>
        <p>''The schools are killing fields,'' a woman in a turquoise satin turban, calling herself Mother Franklin, boomed into the microphone as Mr. Levy sat on a platform in the storefront auditorium, decorated with paintings of Malcolm X and James Brown. ''The school system is nothing but an industry.'' Another likened Mr. Levy's going to Harlem to talk about public schools to Hitler's defending the Holocaust, a particularly raw remark given Mr. Levy's background as the son of Jewish refugees from Nazi Germany.</p>
        <p>But what may have been more telling about Mr. Levy's management style was simply that he was there to visit Mr. Sharpton's headquarters, something, as Mr. Sharpton noted, that the previous chancellor, Rudy Crew, had never done.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy, 47, is the self-made son of a hardware store owner in the Bronx. His father, Hugo, a textile merchant, and mother, Alice, fled Germany in 1939, settling in Washington Heights, then a middle-class neighborhood of German-Jewish immigrants. His grandparents were killed in concentration camps. A sister, Marion, died of kidney disease at age 12 before he was born, but her photo was always prominent in the Levy home and the family visited her grave throughout Mr. Levy's childhood.</p>
        <p>Despite his modest roots, Mr. Levy is the product of Cornell and Oxford Universities and has worked his way into New York's corporate and cultural elite. Six feet and 200 pounds, in pinstriped suits, gold cuff links, tasseled loafers and eggheady wire-rim glasses, he works to project a down-to-earth image with a conversational style that is breezy and direct, free of pandering in public, rife with expletives in private.</p>
        <p>He works hard to dispel the image of a patrician dabbling in public service out of noblesse oblige. ''I have tried to be sensitive,'' he said. ''My way of dealing with it is to say I am going to do the best job I can. I am not going to change my race.''</p>
        <p>Derided as a Henry Higgins for sending poetry to board members and arranging violin lessons for superintendents, Mr. Levy said he was trying to build teamwork and boost morale, standard practice in business.</p>
        <p>''I believe that education is an opportunity for social mobility, me included,'' he said.  ''That was a way out, a way up. Children in public school have an absolute right to experience the finer things in life, just as much as everybody else. That's not elitism. That's being a democrat, small d.''</p>
        <p>As for his pursuit of the chancellorship, he said: ''It's not a lark. We've come to the point in our society where unless you explain why you're doing something on a monetary, mock-rational basis, you can't be serious. Our society has lost the ability to encourage people to be altruistic, adventuresome, to submerge themselves at least for a moment in the greater good.''</p>
        <p>Unlike the last two chancellors, Mr. Levy is a confirmed New Yorker, living with his wife, Patricia Sapinsley, and two children, Noah, 6, and Hannah, 9, on Riverside Drive near Columbia University. Ms. Sapinsley, whose mother, Lila, is a prominent Republican in Rhode Island, gave up her architecture practice when her son was born.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy has drafted two Upper West Side friends and neighbors to be his top deputies: Jonathan Levi, a novelist, and David Klasfeld, a former mid-level City Hall cabinet member.</p>
        <p>As a father, the new chancellor tells poignant stories of wrestling with phonics and the ache of a bad fit between child and teacher. He talks about schools in a jargon-free way that every New Yorker can understand. But while he is proud of his own public school education, Mr. Levy sends his children to Dalton, one of the city's most selective and expensive private schools.</p>
        <p>He and his wife looked at public and private schools, but chose Dalton because it was the best fit, he said. (Reminded that most New Yorkers of his means reject public school on the assumption, right or wrong, that private schools are simply better, he said their decision was more complicated than that.)</p>
        <p>Some say Mr. Levy's lack of on-the-job experience in education could hurt him. At a recent teachers' union convention, Mr. Levy offended guidance counselors by suggesting that historically, their job had been a hiding place for inept teachers.</p>
        <p>''It's going to be important for Harold to understand what he knows well and what he still needs to learn,'' said Ann Marcus, dean of New York University's education school.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy is working hard to woo skeptics. When Diane Ravitch, the acerbic historian of New York City schools, wrote an Op-Ed page article in March attacking Mr. Levy's summer-school program, he called her at 8 the same morning to invite her over, and they talked for an hour about religion, books and education. By contrast, Chancellor Crew refused to shake her hand after she criticized him. ''I found his lack of defensiveness impressive,'' she said of Mr. Levy.</p>
        <p>He has also used his candor to cultivate reporters and editors. (He admits to two hours of media training.)</p>
        <p>As for his relationship with Mayor Giuliani, Mr. Levy, who so far has tried hard to be conciliatory, would not make any predictions. ''I'll make judgments as we go,'' he said. ''There are a lot of things we agree on and a lot of things I can work with him on, but I can't change who I am.''</p>
        <p>Being chancellor is a dream job for Mr. Levy, friends say. As Citigroup's director of global compliance, he was in charge of ensuring that employees in 100 countries followed proper policies and laws. But in the banking industry, deal makers rule the roost. Lawyers -- no matter how highly paid (his financial disclosure form says more than $500,000 a year, far more than his chancellor's pay of $245,000) -- are on the margins of power. Though he had risen to the top, he was restless.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weill, recognizing his political skills, assigned him to special projects like negotiating between the Rev. Jesse Jackson's Rainbow/PUSH Coalition and Wall Street over investment in the inner city and in hardscrabble rural areas.</p>
        <p>His prowess as chancellor has amazed and tickled some former colleagues, but others see a pattern. While his college classmates organized antiwar protests, Mr. Levy, at 20, won a seat on Cornell's board of trustees. Three years after being appointed to the board of the University Settlement Society, a social service agency on the Lower East Side, he became chairman.</p>
        <p>Over the years, working with chancellors like Ramon C. Cortines, Mr. Levy said he fantasized about what he would do if he were chancellor, but never imagined such a thing could come true. But friends and associates have no doubt that when Mr. Levy put his name forward as interim chancellor in January, he was already angling for the permanent job. ''It was like letting the fox into the henhouse,'' Meryl Tisch, who served with him on the Board of Regents, said affectionately.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy's drive was evident early on. Growing up in Washington Heights, he attended Public School 189, Junior High School 52 and Bronx Science, one of the city's most selective high schools. He got his undergraduate and law degrees at Cornell, and a master's in politics, philosophy and economics at Oxford.</p>
        <p>Hired by the civil rights division of the Justice Department, he left in 11 months, he said, because he disapproved of Reagan-era policies. He moved on to some of the city's most competitive legal and investment banking firms: Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher &amp; Flom; Philipp Brothers; Salomon Brothers, the Travelers Group and then Citigroup.</p>
        <p>At Philipp Brothers, Mr. Levy tracked down thousands of tons of coffee that had disappeared from Mexican warehouses; wrested back Pizza Hut franchises that the company had lost in Taiwan, and cracked down on lawyers who were spending too much and taking too long to settle a huge international case.</p>
        <p>''Harold is used to cleaning things up and getting things back under control,'' said Donald Feuerstein, the chief legal officer at Salomon at the time. ''He is good at going into unknown territory, identifying the problem and fixing it without delay.''</p>
        <p>He was a playground monitor in elementary school, supervising his classmates with a whistle in his mouth.</p>
        <p>''Harold was always more controlled and adult than the rest of us,'' said Ilene Guralnick, who was Mr. Levy's classmate from elementary through high school.</p>
        <p>As a high school student in the 60's, he was antiwar, but not an activist. ''He was never the guy with the bullhorn or the one who would get into a confrontation with the principal,'' said Arthur Schwartz, another high school classmate. ''He wanted to work through the proper channels to get something accomplished.''</p>
        <p>As one of 220 associates at Skadden, Arps, as a litigator working on mergers and acquisitions, Mr. Levy got into the habit of rising at 4:30 a.m., a practice he said he maintains to this day. Nearly 20 years later, after becoming interim chancellor, he was introduced to Lewis E. Lehrman, a founder of the Rite Aid Corporation. ''Nice to meet you,'' Mr. Lehrman said, according to witnesses. ''I've been with you many times,'' Mr. Levy replied. ''I used to go to the Brasserie at 4:30 in the morning to do paperwork. You came in at 5:15 to read the papers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy inherited what he calls a familial tremor from his father, which sometimes causes his hands to shake, and is worsened, he said, by fatigue and caffeine. To combat the tremor during grueling exams at Oxford, he began using fountain pens, which require less hand pressure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy has cultivated powerful mentors.</p>
        <p>As chairman of a commission to investigate the city's crumbling school buildings, he forged ties with Jack Rudin, the builder, James S. Tisch, chief executive and co-president of Loews, and Sheldon Silver, speaker of the State Assembly. Two years later, those connections helped him become a regent, where he became close to Richard Mills, the state education commissioner, and Randi Weingarten, president of the teachers' union. Ms. Weingarten lobbied for him as chancellor, but Mr. Levy denies Mr. Giuliani's accusations that he is too cozy with the union and he has pushed for changes in the union, like letting principals demand lesson plans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy is not given to self-reflection. But in a visit to Bronx Science in April, he indulged in a rare meditation on his life, describing his 25th reunion in 1995. Looking at his middle-aged classmates, he was struck at how many of them had become doctors, lawyers and accountants, professionals like him. Beware of losing your passion, he warned, or ''you wind up being disappointed in yourself in later life.''</p>
        <p>Now he will never be just another lawyer, doctor or accountant again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
