<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dialogue From Auschwitz</title>
    <meta content="19BOOK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/arts/19BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239940"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MAKING BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Martin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinberg, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levi, Primo (1919-87)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Speak You Also: A Survivor's Reckoning (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Survial in Auschwitz (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Making Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DC153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dialogue From Auschwitz</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martin Arnold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin Arnold Making Books column on Speak You Also: A Survivor's Reckoning, Paul Steinberg's account of what he did to survive at Auschwitz, which have already been described with appalled harshness in Primo Levi's Survival in Auschwitz; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Books are still man's greatest invention, despite the nonsense so often published between their covers. But their singular marvelousness, I guess, is that there will never be a Harry Potter movie that can reveal the wonder of the story the way the books do. Nor will there ever be a movie, no matter how skillful, that can capture the horror of the concentration camp the way a book can.</p>
        <p>I am reminded of the power of this wondrous conception once again by the recent publication of yet another book that gives witness to life in the  camps. It's a slim volume, but in reality it is one-half of a conversation across the decades between two men now dead who survived Auschwitz in quite different ways. The unfriendly partners in this dialogue are really discussing, in their separate books, a weighty, barbarous question: How much of one's humanity can a person give up to save his own life? And still be called human?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Books are still man's greatest invention, despite the nonsense so often published between their covers. But their singular marvelousness, I guess, is that there will never be a Harry Potter movie that can reveal the wonder of the story the way the books do. Nor will there ever be a movie, no matter how skillful, that can capture the horror of the concentration camp the way a book can.</p>
        <p>I am reminded of the power of this wondrous conception once again by the recent publication of yet another book that gives witness to life in the  camps. It's a slim volume, but in reality it is one-half of a conversation across the decades between two men now dead who survived Auschwitz in quite different ways. The unfriendly partners in this dialogue are really discussing, in their separate books, a weighty, barbarous question: How much of one's humanity can a person give up to save his own life? And still be called human?</p>
        <p>The new book is ''Speak You Also: A Survivor's Reckoning'' (Metropolitan Books) by Paul Steinberg, who in 1943, at 16, was gathered up in Paris and sent to Auschwitz. It is a disturbing, honest and unapologetic self-examination in response to those questions. This book would never have been written, and indeed no one would ever have heard of its author, had he not been written about by a fellow prisoner, Primo Levi, the Italian novelist, poet, nonfiction writer and chemist, and perhaps the most articulate and literate survivor of the camps.</p>
        <p>Here is how he described Steinberg: ''inhumanly cunning and incomprehensible like the Serpent in Genesis.'' That harsh declaration is in Levi's heroic book, ''Survival in Auschwitz: The Nazi Assault on Humanity'' (Collier, 1961), first published in the United States in 1959 as ''If This Is a Man'' (Orion Press).</p>
        <p>Levi gives Steinberg the name Henri, a young man who was ''eminently civilized and sane, and possesses a complete and organic theory on the ways to survive in Lager.'' Henri saw ''three methods open to man to escape extermination which still allow him to retain the name of man: organization, pity and theft.''</p>
        <p>Henri, Levi wrote, practiced all three. He gained favors (food and cigarettes) from the relatively well-treated English P.O.W.'s. ''Seducing'' them (not sexually), Levi called it; ''cultivating'' was Henri's word. Levi explained: ''In exchange for a single English cigarette you can make enough in Lager not to starve for a day. Henri was once seen in the act of eating a real hardboiled egg.''</p>
        <p>Levi wrote that Henri's ability to sympathize with and flatter a person who could help him, be it an English soldier or a German guard, was so natural a gift that ''there is no heart so hardened that Henri cannot breach it.''</p>
        <p>So Henri's protectors were English soldiers, French, Ukrainian and Polish civilian workers, German ''politicals,'' a cook, an SS man, inmate camp leaders, and doctors who, ''immediately before selections, and in periods of most laborious work,'' take him in the hospital ''whenever he wants and with the diagnosis he wants.'' Henri called these hospitalizations periods of ''hibernation.''</p>
        <p>Levi conceded that ''to speak with Henri is useful, and pleasant . . . even affection seems possible,'' but reminds himself that ''the next moment his sad smile freezes into a cold grimace . . . and here he is again, intent on his hunt and his struggle; hard and distant, enclosed in armor, the enemy of all.''</p>
        <p>Now all this seemingly mundane characterization takes place within a world so horrific that among picture makers perhaps only Goya could have captured its charnel house essense.</p>
        <p>In such conditions, what is a man's responsibility? To survive, Steinberg says in his own book. He was a tough teenager in that Lager who decided from the first that he was going to live. ''I've withdrawn inside my shell; all the vital energy I have left is mobilized for my own survival,'' he wrote. ''I'm at the age where one adjusts, and I economize on everything by getting rid of moral suffering, emotions, memories -- and regrets as well, a crucial imperative.''</p>
        <p>He goes on: ''It's wasteful to give your affection to ghosts on reprieve. Why set yourself up for tears the next day?'' Levi does not accuse Steinberg of betraying prisoners, but Steinberg tells of reaching his nadir when, at 18, he was made a camp trusty and one of his duties was to inspect a row of beds to see if they had been properly made up.</p>
        <p>He records this scene: An elderly Polish Jew is lying on his bunk. Steinberg orders him out of the bed, but the man cannot move. Steinberg wrote: ''Furious, I raise my hand without thinking and slap him. At the last moment, I hold back and my hand grazes his cheek. In that fraction of a second, I sound the abyss.'' He adds, ''If only I could get rid of this memory, sweep it away with my hand.''</p>
        <p>Primo Levi died in 1987 at 67 in what is generally believed to be a suicide. Paul Steinberg died last December at 73, having lived to see his book published in French, German, Italian and Spanish but not in English. Levi had written: ''I know that Henri is living today. I would give much to know his life as a free man, but I do not want to see him again.''</p>
        <p>Steinberg's editor, Riva Hocherman, said that the writer ''actually started trying to write his story as fiction in the 60's, but couldn't do it.''</p>
        <p>''He underwent some sort of breakdown when he started to confront it,'' she said. It wasn't until later that he learned of Levi's book when another survivor directed him to it, she said. Ms. Hocherman said that Steinberg's family believes that finally there was correspondence between Levi and Steinberg. Either the family could not find it or has declined to make it public, she said.</p>
        <p>It's an unsettling book, from the first page showing Steinberg's fierce will to survive. ''He doesn't apologize,'' Ms. Hocherman said, ''but then there's a line he did not cross. He did not betray his own people; he did not send anyone to their death.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Steinberg concedes that  Levi was probably right about him, and says, ''I'll never know whether I have the right to ask clemency of the jury.'' He asks, ''Can one be so guilty for having survived?''</p>
        <p>MAKING BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
