<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rupert Murdoch lends his voice to those worried about a cooling of television ad spending.</title>
    <meta content="Y19ADC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/business/19ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239995"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">News Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murdoch, Rupert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DF123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rupert Murdoch lends his voice to those worried about a cooling of television ad spending.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bill Carter</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Television advertising marketplace is cooling; some network executives dispute some earlier reports of weakening in ad marketplace, but News Corp chairman, Rupert Murdoch, predicts at shareholders meeting in Australia that advertising sales for his television company in US, Fox Entertainment Group, look a little uncertain; Murdoch attributes weakness in advertising marketplace over next couple months to falloff in spending by Internet businesses (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER years of white-hot intensity, most recently driven by a media buying frenzy by start-up dot-com companies, the television advertising marketplace is cooling by almost all accounts.</p>
        <p>While some network executives have disputed some earlier reports of weakening in the ad marketplace, Rupert Murdoch, the chairman of the News Corporation, openly acknowledged that the issue was becoming a problem when he predicted yesterday at a shareholders meeting in Australia that advertising sales for his television company in the United States, the Fox Entertainment Group, ''look a little uncertain.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER years of white-hot intensity, most recently driven by a media buying frenzy by start-up dot-com companies, the television advertising marketplace is cooling by almost all accounts.</p>
        <p>While some network executives have disputed some earlier reports of weakening in the ad marketplace, Rupert Murdoch, the chairman of the News Corporation, openly acknowledged that the issue was becoming a problem when he predicted yesterday at a shareholders meeting in Australia that advertising sales for his television company in the United States, the Fox Entertainment Group, ''look a little uncertain.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch also said that the sale of shares in the News Corporation's satellite-TV unit, Sky Global Networks, originally scheduled for next month, would be delayed at least several more months. American depository receipts of the News Corporation fell $2.81 yesterday, to $40.69.</p>
        <p>As for the advertising marketplace, Mr. Murdoch said, ''There are signs of weakness in the next couple of months,'' and he openly attributed that to a falloff in spending by Internet businesses.</p>
        <p>The remarks illustrated a concern that has spread throughout the television industry over the last several weeks as network television, coming off a record selling spree last spring, began picking up signs that advertisers were beginning to look for ways to temper spending going into the first quarter of next year and even to cut back on some commitments made for the fourth quarter this year.</p>
        <p>Those concerns have been presumed to be behind a sharp sell-off in shares for some media companies this week, including Viacom and Time Warner. But many of the media companies, and specifically those two, rebounded impressively yesterday.</p>
        <p>Network executives will be scrutinizing what advertisers decide in the next few weeks during what is called the option period, when advertisers have an opportunity to pull back some of the money they pledged to the networks last spring during the upfront buying season.</p>
        <p>''The marketplace right now is in a wait-and-see position,'' said Alex Wallau, the president of ABC. ''People may start looking to make better deals for themselves down the road, but that happens all the time.''</p>
        <p>This year, however, a record amount of ad money was committed upfront at record prices. A significant factor in that heavy spending was the implied threat to some advertisers that if they did not snap up the time being offered by the networks it might be gobbled up by dot-com companies at even higher prices later in the year -- as happened last year.</p>
        <p>Jack Myers, the chief economist for The Myers Report, an industry newsletter, noted that, ''up to 50 to 70 percent of the money put up by venture capitalists to start up these new- media companies got passed through in spending on traditional media.'' He added, ''That's over now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Myers said he was forecasting a downturn in growth in ad revenue for the broadcast networks in 2001, falling from growth of 9 percent this year to just 3 percent next year. He called it ''reality setting in.''</p>
        <p>Jessica Reif-Cohen, a media analyst at Merrill Lynch, said, ''Of course there is a slowdown in the overall ad market.'' But she said that slowdown should be regarded as a return to more normal levels of ad spending after a period inflated by the dot-com businesses. ''This was like a special event, like the Olympics. Nobody in their right mind would expect that to happen again.''</p>
        <p>She argued that other circumstances, like the Olympics on NBC, the presidential election and the delayed start to the fall television season were all having a negative effect on advertiser spending. ''I think when all that clears out, we'll see a better picture,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But some executives said the advertising falloff might be tied to specific performance of companies in the stock market and their desire to present strong earnings reports to protect their stock prices. Traditionally, if a company sees a potential earnings problems, it may seek to improve its bottom line by cutting advertising costs, at least temporarily.</p>
        <p>One longtime senior advertising executive said, ''Tell me what the earnings reports are going to be in the next few months and I'll tell you what shape the advertising market is going to be in.''</p>
        <p>Tom Wolzien, a media analyst with Sanford C. Bernstein, said any pullback in advertising commitments would most likely not be felt first at the network level. ''This stuff usually cracks up from the bottom,'' he said. ''I would expect local stations and small cable networks to be hit first.''</p>
        <p>There have been enough hints of some cracks in recent weeks to stir at least some concerns at the network level, Mr. Wallau said. ''We are not at Defcon-4 mode or whatever the horrific Defcon number is. But we're definitely not comfortable.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
