<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romping Inside a Dolphin's Skin in a 3-D Undersea Playground</title>
    <meta content="19GAME$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/technology/19GAME.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sega Gameworks Llc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olafson, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7D7143EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1104" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romping Inside a Dolphin's Skin in a 3-D Undersea Playground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER OLAFSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olafson, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Olafson Game Theory column reviews Ecco the Dolphin, published by Sega of America, a tranquil computer game; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DON'T bother me. I'm swimming.</p>
        <p>I know I should get on about the business of playing Ecco the Dolphin: Defender of the Future, the sequel to the celebrated Sega Genesis (and later, Windows) game from the mid-1990's. My dolphin has already been offered a range of small tasks. A baby whale is missing, and in the game's first region, its great gray mother implores me (as Ecco) to find him. My fellow dolphins have invited me to take part in a game called Fish Fetch. And in the second region, two others want to race me. Success in each of these ventures will open new areas of the game or opportunities to improve my character.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DON'T bother me. I'm swimming.</p>
        <p>I know I should get on about the business of playing Ecco the Dolphin: Defender of the Future, the sequel to the celebrated Sega Genesis (and later, Windows) game from the mid-1990's. My dolphin has already been offered a range of small tasks. A baby whale is missing, and in the game's first region, its great gray mother implores me (as Ecco) to find him. My fellow dolphins have invited me to take part in a game called Fish Fetch. And in the second region, two others want to race me. Success in each of these ventures will open new areas of the game or opportunities to improve my character.</p>
        <p>But the simple business of moving through the sumptuous undersea realms of this unusual action-adventure game for the Sega Dreamcast is so beguiling that progress in the story and advances in Ecco's repertory of skills have become secondary concerns. I am not ''doing'' so much as ''being.''</p>
        <p>The little lost whale, the race, the fish-fetching game and the glimmering crystals that dot the ocean floor will all have to wait. I am swimming happily -- exploring, jumping and performing stunts -- and I do not know when I will stop.</p>
        <p>This three-dimensional game succeeds in some measure because of this very openness and because the experience is so convincing.</p>
        <p>When Ecco is under water, I feel as though I am under water. When he breaks the surface and his sleek, silvery body curves through the air, I can almost feel that air against my skin.</p>
        <p>It's a consummate illusion that is a product of a range of evocative visual and aural effects.</p>
        <p>Shadows play across the rocks on the bottom of Aquamarine Bay. When the dolphin (seen from behind) skims the ocean floor, sand is churned up in the wake. Ocean plants wave vaguely with the current, and schools of small fish dart across my path. (In the distance, sharks circle angrily.) Ornate rock formations wind upward toward a bright surface, then lure me down into a murky darkness. Even the flat textures of stone and plants on the rocky boundaries of these pools seem three-dimensional when seen from a distance.</p>
        <p>And the score, while beautiful as music, somehow manages to suggest the filtered way we hear sounds under water. One of the first things I usually do when playing a game is turn off the music. (Games should speak to our emotions in their content, not manufacture them with scores, as movies do.) But I left it on this time. It is such a natural extension of the game that I seem to be hearing it as a character, not as a player.</p>
        <p>But these are only effects. More to the point is the freedom the developer, Appaloosa Interactive, has given me to experience this exquisite world.</p>
        <p>The game elements are charming, to be sure, but Ecco is one of the very few action games that allow me to enjoy myself by simply existing within the game. In Ecco, it's as though I were really living as a dolphin. In most games, you are mostly doing something, taking steps that further the objectives of the game, either because such steps are forced on you by circumstance or because the game environment isn't rich enough to reward you for mere exploration.</p>
        <p>In Ecco, I can do nothing. I can waste time being a dolphin and enjoy it mightily.</p>
        <p>I am dealing not with Defending the Future, as the blustery title proposes, but with how many full somersaults Ecco can do in the air. (Almost three, if I time his final surge toward the surface just right.) Inspired by the ''Free Willy'' movies, I'm trying (with mixed success) to vault over necks of land that separate bodies of water. I am poking around in out-of-the-way places. I am learning various little stunts, like suspending Ecco's body above the water while his tail lashes below it -- just like the dolphins I've seen perform at theme parks. (And yes, you can make Ecco chirp and smile, too.)</p>
        <p>To do that, all I really have to do is monitor two on-screen meters, one that measures the damage Ecco sustains in encounters with enemies like sharks, jellyfish and moray eels, and another that shows his remaining air supply. (Since dolphins are not fish, but mammals, Ecco has to surface every so often to take in oxygen.) I can also draw a map of my surroundings by holding down the sonar button, but I haven't yet felt the need to do that. I have always felt at home in Ecco.</p>
        <p>In short, while building a delicious spin on the old jump-and-run arcade game, Appaloosa has effectively created a dolphin simulator.</p>
        <p>There are limits to Ecco's open-endedness. This is a game, after all, and the ocean doesn't extend into the infinite distance. For instance, in Aquamarine Bay, the tide on the seaward side is so strong that plants lie parallel to the sea bottom. Ecco cannot pass, and I, running out of things to explore and experience, eventually had to swim into the story. (As man and dolphin step into space, an enemy from space destroys the Guardian, which the dolphins had created to protect the planet. Are you dolphin enough to save Earth?)</p>
        <p>There is a raft of missions, which Ecco can undertake by communicating with other creatures. (He does that by pointing his nose at them and using his sonar.) Along the way, the dolphin can acquire songs, which will allow him to influence the movements of other creatures; gifts, which extend his abilities; and crystal shards of the Guardian's power, which extend his health.</p>
        <p>But it turns out that doing nothing in Ecco has a constructive purpose. In most action games, you learn the ways of the world on the job or in a crash-course tutorial. When I finally set about performing missions in Ecco, they came so naturally to me it was as though I'd been born to them, like a dolphin to water. I was swimming. In some sense, I was really swimming.</p>
        <p>Ecco the Dolphin: Defender of the Future; developed by Appaloosa Interactive and published by Sega of America for the Sega Dreamcast; $39.95; for all ages.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
