<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Topkapi Treasures Find Friends in South Florida</title>
    <meta content="19ARTS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/arts/19ARTS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS IN AMERICA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Museum of Art (Fort Lauderdale, Fla)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Topkapi Palace (Istanbul)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parnes, Amie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFDF153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="907" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Topkapi Treasures Find Friends in South Florida</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Amie Parnes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Parnes, Amie</byline>
      <dateline>FORT LAUDERDALE, Fla., Oct. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arts in America column on exhibit at Museum of Art in Fort Lauderdale, Fla, of art treasures from Topkapi Palace in Istanbul, Turkey; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years the Greater Fort Lauderdale Convention and Visitors Bureau has wanted something else to lure the tourists, something other than the golden sun and its sparkling, deep-blue portion of the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>This month perhaps the postcard-perfect sandy beaches will face some competition from the treasures of a  distant and far more legendary place by the sea .</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years the Greater Fort Lauderdale Convention and Visitors Bureau has wanted something else to lure the tourists, something other than the golden sun and its sparkling, deep-blue portion of the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>This month perhaps the postcard-perfect sandy beaches will face some competition from the treasures of a  distant and far more legendary place by the sea .</p>
        <p>On Sunday an exhibition opened at the Museum of Art here with such exotic items as a dagger adorned in emeralds and diamonds and a 16th-century throne made of ebony, ivory and mother-of-pearl. The show, ''The Palace of Gold and Light: Treasures from Topkapi, Istanbul,'' runs through Feb. 28.</p>
        <p>Topkapi is the palace begun by Sultan Mehmed II (Mehmed the Conqueror), who took the city from the Byzantines in 1453 and established the Ottoman Empire. The building, which sits at the end of a peninsula and is known for its extraordinary views of Asia and Europe, remained home to the Ottoman sultans until the middle of the 19th century and was the center of the vast empire's administration, military, educational and cultural activities.</p>
        <p>Thousands of people from every corner of the empire, of many ethnic backgrounds and religions, lived and worked there. The most talented artists and craftsman were employed by the palace and created the highest-quality Ottoman imperial objects.</p>
        <p>Today the palace is a museum, home to artifacts of the once-powerful empire. Until this tour in the United States, which also included stops in Washington and San Diego, the more than 200 works of art and Ottoman artifacts had never left the their home.</p>
        <p>The tour underlines the growth in ties between Turkey and South Florida, as many people of Turkish descent have settled in the Fort Lauderdale area and other sections of Broward County, north of Miami. Their number has more than doubled in the last 10 years to well over 5,000 as younger immigrants have arrived to work in engineering and tourism. Entrepreneurs have also opened restaurants and businesses importing rugs, ceramics and other works of art.</p>
        <p>''In South Florida we've become much more diverse in every regard,'' said Michael Kenny, the vice president for cultural tourism at the visitors' bureau. ''We're a composite of cultures. And the tourists that come here are also very well traveled. They don't come for just the beach anymore. They have begun to come for the arts.''</p>
        <p>To complete their Ottoman education and see the rest of the palace's treasures, Mr. Kenny said, museum patrons can now fly nonstop flight from Miami to Istanbul, a route established just last year.</p>
        <p>The museum in Fort Lauderdale is almost dominated by Sultan Mehmed's presence. His portrait is the first work a visitor sees, looking proudly into the distance as he holds a long-stemmed rose. A few steps farther along are the centuries-old book he read about his hero, Alexander the Great, and the objects the sultan would have taken to battle: a water canteen made of rock crystal, silver, ruby and gold and a saddle made of leather, velvet and metallic thread.</p>
        <p>There are carefully stitched royal robes, silk embroidered carpets and fairy-tale-like armor. But it is the glistening Topkapi dagger, made famous by the 1964 film ''Topkapi,'' that appears to wow the crowds the most from behind its protective glass. Visitors have to remind themselves that the diamonds on both sides of the dagger's handle and its three large emeralds are real.</p>
        <p>The dagger, certainly the best-known attraction in this exhibition and in the palace in Istanbul, was intended to be a gift from the sultan to the Nadir Shah of Iran. But the shah was killed in an uprising in 1747, and it went back to the royal treasury.</p>
        <p>Near other cases full of emeralds and rubies, some of them three times the size of a quarter, is an ornament covered in diamonds, rubies, emeralds and sapphires that sat on top of a turban and soared a foot into the air.</p>
        <p>''Their goal was to look larger than life,'' explained Kathleen Harleman, the director and chief executive officer of the Museum of Art. ''They wanted to appear almost mythical in a way.''</p>
        <p>The other hit attraction is the ebony and ivory throne inlaid with mother-of-pearl that is thought to have been used by Sultan Suleyman I in the 16th century on his travels in Europe and Asia. A visitor might almost sense the presence of the powerful man who once sat there.</p>
        <p>Even the genuinely useful objects  are impressive enough to be works of art. Pen boxes are studded with more jewels. Spoons are made of tortoise shell, rhinoceros horn and coconut. Children's underwear is embroidered.</p>
        <p>There is a row of intricate small, vibrant, carpets used only for praying, and a large bookstand, said to have been used for reading the Koran, made of wood, tortoise shell, ivory and mother-of-pearl. The 17th-century sterling silver candlesticks are each the size of a human. ''Imagine what the palace itself was like, said Ms. Harleman. ''It must have been an absolute dream of a place.''</p>
        <p>ARTS IN AMERICA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
