<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Last-Minute Congressional Mischief</title>
    <meta content="19THU2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/opinion/19THU2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E6D7153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Last-Minute Congressional Mischief</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial scores Congress for failing to complete work on several key appropriations bills, three weeks into new fiscal year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is now nearly three weeks into the new fiscal year, and Congress still has not finished work on several key appropriation bills, including measures to finance foreign operations and the departments of Commerce, Justice, State, Labor, Health and Human Services and Education. At this point it seems likely that most of these measures will be rolled into a giant omnibus bill loaded with riders and other surprises that neither the public nor even most members of Congress will have understood or digested before they become law. End-of-session chaos has become the norm in recent years, and the picture this year seems no better.</p>
        <p>Several of the bills are hung up as Congressional Republicans struggle to negotiate compromises with President Clinton. Some disputes involve spending levels, others involve policy matters. The spending bill for the Commerce, Justice and State departments, for example, has properly drawn a veto threat for several reasons. Congress has failed to include a provision giving limited amnesty for illegal immigrants who have been in the United States since 1986. Mr. Clinton is right to insist on this provision given that so many longtime immigrants were left in legal limbo after the 1986 immigration reform. The bill does not include $23 million sought by the administration to finance federal litigation against the tobacco industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is now nearly three weeks into the new fiscal year, and Congress still has not finished work on several key appropriation bills, including measures to finance foreign operations and the departments of Commerce, Justice, State, Labor, Health and Human Services and Education. At this point it seems likely that most of these measures will be rolled into a giant omnibus bill loaded with riders and other surprises that neither the public nor even most members of Congress will have understood or digested before they become law. End-of-session chaos has become the norm in recent years, and the picture this year seems no better.</p>
        <p>Several of the bills are hung up as Congressional Republicans struggle to negotiate compromises with President Clinton. Some disputes involve spending levels, others involve policy matters. The spending bill for the Commerce, Justice and State departments, for example, has properly drawn a veto threat for several reasons. Congress has failed to include a provision giving limited amnesty for illegal immigrants who have been in the United States since 1986. Mr. Clinton is right to insist on this provision given that so many longtime immigrants were left in legal limbo after the 1986 immigration reform. The bill does not include $23 million sought by the administration to finance federal litigation against the tobacco industry.</p>
        <p>Finally, the bill is likely to be saddled with a rider pushed by commercial broadcasters that would hinder the Federal Communications Commission from approving low-power radio licenses for groups like schools and churches that want to reach communities underserved by commercial radio. The administration has said it would oppose such an amendment.</p>
        <p>The education bill has major problems. It fails to include money for tax credits to help school districts finance school construction. It places money for class size reduction and school repairs into block grants that do not allow sufficient accountability from local districts, and it does not adequately finance teacher training or after-school programs.</p>
        <p>The foreign aid bill is blocked by a dispute over unacceptable language that would bar international family planning groups from receiving American aid if they perform abortions or lobby foreign governments on abortion policy, even if they use their own money. Mr. Clinton should veto the bill if this language is not stripped out.</p>
        <p>Two insidious environmental riders bear watching. One, drafted by the snowmobile industry and sponsored by Senator Craig Thomas, Republican of Wyoming, would effectively overturn an Interior Department plan to ban snowmobiles from Yellowstone National Park. It would also block the department from issuing new regulations banning snowmobiles in national parks generally. This rider deserves a veto should it somehow find its way to the president's desk. The other rider, attached to the veterans and housing appropriations bill, seeks to throw unnecessary obstacles in the way of a decision by the Environmental Protection Agency on how best to deal with toxic sediments in the Hudson River. That decision has been too long in coming as it is.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
