<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Milan, Steam Power</title>
    <meta content="19FIRS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/living/19FIRS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FIRST LOOK: COBAN ESPRESSO MACHINE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sapper, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pearlman, Chee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E4DC153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1906" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Milan, Steam Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHEE PEARLMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pearlman, Chee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Richard Sapper, designer, who discusses his latest work, Coban, a stove-top espresso machine, as well as his classic designs for Tizio lamp and IBM ThinkPad; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR Richard Sapper, there is no such thing as a simple cup of coffee. Twenty-one years ago, he won the gratitude of caffeine connoisseurs everywhere with a stove-top espresso maker that has sold 1.2 million copies. And now Mr. Sapper, a Munich-born honorary Italian -- he lives in Milan -- is back in the kitchen again.</p>
        <p>Coban is his new espresso and cappuccino machine for the Italian housewares maker Alessi -- and for Americans, who have been preconditioned by Starbucks to spend serious money for a serious cappuccino. The company's first electrical kitchen appliance, which it is manufacturing in collaboration with Philips, recalls high-performance machines Mr. Sapper helped design in the 1950's at Daimler-Benz, including the Mercedes 300SL. Like any other espresso maker, Coban uses scalding steam to coax flavor out of roasted beans, but it lifts the veil of mystery off the process. As water is heated and pumped through -- at 116 pounds of pressure per square inch -- the Pantheon curve of Coban's transparent dome fills with condensation to signal the coffee's progress.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR Richard Sapper, there is no such thing as a simple cup of coffee. Twenty-one years ago, he won the gratitude of caffeine connoisseurs everywhere with a stove-top espresso maker that has sold 1.2 million copies. And now Mr. Sapper, a Munich-born honorary Italian -- he lives in Milan -- is back in the kitchen again.</p>
        <p>Coban is his new espresso and cappuccino machine for the Italian housewares maker Alessi -- and for Americans, who have been preconditioned by Starbucks to spend serious money for a serious cappuccino. The company's first electrical kitchen appliance, which it is manufacturing in collaboration with Philips, recalls high-performance machines Mr. Sapper helped design in the 1950's at Daimler-Benz, including the Mercedes 300SL. Like any other espresso maker, Coban uses scalding steam to coax flavor out of roasted beans, but it lifts the veil of mystery off the process. As water is heated and pumped through -- at 116 pounds of pressure per square inch -- the Pantheon curve of Coban's transparent dome fills with condensation to signal the coffee's progress.</p>
        <p>Even the beans have been relentlessly designed. Alessi's other partner, Nespresso, a division of Nestle, has imported its mess-proof system of premeasured ground coffee in vacuum-sealed capsules (Eric Asimov's review is on Page 4). The result? Fresh dinner-party espressos in less than 20 seconds each.</p>
        <p>In this country, Mr. Sapper's name is barely known. But anyone who has come in contact with the Tizio lamp or the I.B.M. ThinkPad has seen his gift for reducing form and line to pure essence. (For better or worse, credit Mr. Sapper with the concept of a designer tea kettle; a sensorial creation in 1983 sang in two keys.) Over a lunch of mussels and quail at Quilty's in SoHo before Coban's coming-out party at Moss, Mr. Sapper critiqued the espresso: too much water. ''Americans just don't know how to make espresso,'' he said, taking pity. (The mussels he rated four stars.)</p>
        <p>Q: Why did you choose to call this new espresso maker Coban?</p>
        <p>RICHARD SAPPER:  Coban is a little town in Guatemala, in the middle of the coffee growing region that produces one of the best coffees in the world. My grandfather was a coffee planter there, and my father was  born there. In Germany, my father would get bags of coffee from Guatemala, and once a month we roasted it ourselves.</p>
        <p>Q: So coffee, if not in your DNA, is in your blood.</p>
        <p>A: It is. And I had made a stove-top espresso machine -- the 9090 -- that has sold for more than 20 years and is one of Alessi's most successful products.</p>
        <p>Q: What was the breakthrough of the 9090?</p>
        <p>A: The 9090 was a revolutionary project because in 1979 only one espresso maker existed, which was the one invented by Mr. Alessi's uncle, Mr. Bialetti. Every Italian  household had one.</p>
        <p>Q: The slim-waisted Bialetti is still a fixture of Italian life. It's such an unusual idea today, that only one model of anything could reside in every home.</p>
        <p>A: No, even in Italy, where markets are less global, it's rare. Alessi asked me to design one in stainless steel, which had not been done before. An espresso maker is really a little steam engine. It has a tank, where the water is transformed into steam and then rises and extracts the aroma from the coffee. I wanted to show the character of the steam engine in this design.</p>
        <p>Q: There is a streamlined, machinelike quality to its design, with the ''boiler'' as its base.</p>
        <p>A: There were also some practical reasons that came with the design. One had to do with safety. My first objective was to make it impossible to explode, because it is made of two parts that are screwed together. If the safety valve becomes clogged it can be very dangerous. I solved this by making the 9090 in one piece. The other issue was materials and planned obsolescence. I am a great enemy of planned obsolescence. I think producing a product so that it will break down and you have to buy a new one is  criminal. I think it's betraying your client.</p>
        <p>Q: It betrays your culture, too.</p>
        <p>A: Yes. And one of the things we learned about the Bialetti, which is made of cast aluminum with a plastic handle, is that if you put this whole thing on your fire, the handle will be destroyed.</p>
        <p>Q: You spent over a year designing the Coban. Why did it take so long?</p>
        <p>A: This is a sophisticated, highly complex machine, and there are only a few companies in the world that can make them, and most of them are in Switzerland.</p>
        <p>Q: I wouldn't have thought that the Swiss were such espresso connoisseurs. They're known for water decaffeination.</p>
        <p>A: No, Switzerland is certainly not the homeland of espresso. But it is the homeland of the espresso maker because they are specialists in doing small, highly complex, precise mechanical processes. Every other coffee maker in the world starts with a mechanism that has been predesigned by the manufacturer and then has a plastic box designed around it.</p>
        <p>Q: The engineers have always called the shots.</p>
        <p>A: I refuse to make a machine like that. I wanted to make an object that transmits its character to anyone who looks at it. The normal espresso maker could be a Coca-Cola dispenser. It doesn't tell you anything about its inner self. I also have other espresso makers, and if I want to know if there is water in the machine, I have to open a cover and look in it, or pull the tank out. That's ridiculous. You should see when to refill.</p>
        <p>Q: What strikes me about the Coban is that it has a blunt, no-nonsense appeal, like early kitchen appliances -- the old Waring blenders, for example, which told you exactly what they were and what they do. But why does directness have to cost $599?</p>
        <p>A: It is going to be more expensive than just putting a plastic box around a premade mechanism, but it will also be definitely better, and definitely longer lasting.</p>
        <p>Q: It's interesting that the Coban is coming to America from Europe if only because Americans generally think we are the kingpins of convenience. We're the ones who invented fast food, after all.</p>
        <p>A: I can't argue with that! But coffee is an extremely messy material, and it is somewhat risky, because it is not easy to make a good coffee. It is fun, but it is also work. You have to select the beans, grind them not too fine, but not too coarse. And some people don't have time to do that. So Nestle said: What if we prepare all this before, and then we put that result into a capsule? You will get a coffee that is not of your choice, it's of our choice. But it will be always the same quality.</p>
        <p>Q: Is this progress? Isn't there something to honor about complexity? Has some essential ritual been removed?</p>
        <p>A: (Laughing.) My wife thinks so. She refuses to drink Nespresso. She wants everything handmade. She says we pay for convenience with a loss of individualism. The first thing I do at home in the morning is make fresh espresso with another version of the Coban, which hasn't been made for the American market yet, that includes a coffee grinder. So, we stick with the messy stuff at home because my wife wants to select the coffee and mix it herself. But in the office, if I want a coffee, or if someone comes to visit, I make a Nespresso and that's it!</p>
        <p>Q: Do you mind if I complain about the design of the capsules? They are rather cheap and disposable looking.</p>
        <p>A: I had nothing to do with that. Though I suppose I'd have to agree.</p>
        <p>Q: Is your design control more difficult in a huge corporation like I.B.M.?</p>
        <p>A: It depends on how well the development team works. We had a party recently celebrating the 10 millionth ThinkPad sold by I.B.M. There is no other company in the world that can sell 10 million computers of the same design. And naturally there have been many versions. Each computer lives only six months, and then it's replaced by a machine that has a better chip in it, or something. But we have conserved the character of that design.</p>
        <p>Q: Do you think it's hard to make that kind of a breakthrough in something? What about Apple Computer's iMac?</p>
        <p>A: The iMac is like a piece of candy. It's not new at all. It's a form that has existed for I don't know how many times. And the fact that it's transparent -- it's not so terrific that you actually want to see what's inside it.</p>
        <p>Q: What do you think of all the colors?</p>
        <p>A: Candy. (Laughs)</p>
        <p>Q: Does that mean trivial?</p>
        <p>A: That means trivial, yes.</p>
        <p>Q: But do you think the attempt to appeal to the home market, to make it a little bit more friendly, is valid?</p>
        <p>A: I wouldn't sit in front of a pink iMac, not for even 10 minutes. I would get mad. Colors are wonderful. But you must have good colors. Not horrendous colors. And beautiful colors in Western culture are rare to come by. But also, Apple has corrected this. The new computer, the Cube, is transparent. I think it is interesting that they have shown two completely different faces of design. I appreciate the Cube very much.</p>
        <p>Q: You've been responsible for creating a number of products that have achieved classic status. Do you know a design icon when you've created it?</p>
        <p>A: No. Absolutely not. I also don't know if I'm designing a successful product or not. I'm convinced it has nothing to do with the design of this product or even the quality but with how it's marketed and presented to the public.</p>
        <p>Q: What are some of the qualities that make something classic?</p>
        <p>A: It's when the form of an object establishes contact with you, and you have to interact with it. I am very interested in objects that move and change character. That's the main theme of the Tizio, for example, or even the ThinkPad, which opens and reveals itself like a box of cigars. The Coban also has this nature -- it makes noise, steam comes out of it, you see the condensation drops form. It starts to live.</p>
        <p>Q: That actually is the power of great design, because it's a form of communication.</p>
        <p>A: Absolutely. And this is probably the essence of an icon. Like a great sculpture, you want to touch it. You can't resist.</p>
        <p>FIRST LOOK: COBAN ESPRESSO MACHINE First Look is a monthly conversation with design innovators. Chee Pearlman is the former editor in chief of I.D. magazine. E-mail: Chee2000@aol.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">First Look is a monthly conversation with design innovators. Chee Pearlman is the former editor in chief of I.D. magazine. E-mail: Chee2000@aol.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
