<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On the London Scene, Practicality Is Radical</title>
    <meta content="19LOND$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DESIGN NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamilton, William L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Design Notebook</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E5DC153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1911" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On the London Scene, Practicality Is Radical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM L. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hamilton, William L</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Britain's premier design exhibition, 100% Design, is held at Earls Court in London, showcasing design that is radical in it applicability as much as in its forms or materials; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HERE'S an idea. Design innovative furniture. Make it useful. Sell it.</p>
        <p>At London's recent 100% Design, which is Britain's premier design exhibition and now a required stop on the Paris, Cologne, Milan and New York show circuit, there were trends, and there was a new, potential take-away factor, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HERE'S an idea. Design innovative furniture. Make it useful. Sell it.</p>
        <p>At London's recent 100% Design, which is Britain's premier design exhibition and now a required stop on the Paris, Cologne, Milan and New York show circuit, there were trends, and there was a new, potential take-away factor, too.</p>
        <p>The bratty British design scene, co-opted by the Blair government in 1997 with its ''Cool Britannia'' campaign, didn't drop out. It grew up. The raw thinking and uncommercial energy of newcomers like Inflate, a company that in 1995 showed lights blown up like beach toys, is showing responsibility as well. Inflate has spent five years investing in manufacturing machinery. This year it showed up at the sixth annual British show with an inventive, inexpensive bed, as in, try to get a mass market to lie in it.</p>
        <p>London's student princes are like all people you know in their 30's -- a few years on, still fun, working on commitment. The city's four-day calendar of design events was more like a proud new house tour, home by 10, than like the old late-night clubbing.</p>
        <p>From architectural tilework to tabletop ceramics, from living room lounge seating to workplace desks and chairs, the new design was radical in its applicability, as much as in its forms or materials.</p>
        <p>Even at Designersblock2000, an off-site event staged in St. Pancras Chambers, a derelict 19th-century Gothic railway hotel, the newest designers were showing things that looked more like furniture than ideas -- pragmatic, original updates of the everyday with little nostalgia for the uncommon or conceptual. What was revolutionary was their confidence that design was now viable with the public.</p>
        <p>At the official exhibition at Earls Court 2, which ran from Oct. 5 to 8, British designers and their European colleagues were translating excitement into maturity: a new practical wisdom about what people want and how to get it to them. Maybe, wisely, they understand that designers who want to stay in the profession have no choice.</p>
        <p>Even the conceptual work -- and it was strong -- had its feet on the ground. There were several collections of furniture for children, including Biscuit for Oreka Kids (www.orekakids.com), a new company, whose 10 designers were a virtual roundup of the avant-garde names of five years ago. And babies and children were the big vogue everywhere, including a 7-year-old girl in a silver shag-rug A-line dress with matching shag pillbox hat leaving the Christopher Farr party in Notting Hill. How much realer can you get?</p>
        <p>The exhibition, a trade show open to the public, was largely of prototypes or new products being previewed for manufacturers, the interior design trade and retailers. (And the actress Charlotte Rampling, who walked by during the kickoff cocktail party, tawny as a prize cat in a leather jacket and ankle-high plaid pants, and froze Sir Terence Conran in his tracks.)</p>
        <p>But in great evidence at 100% Design was the fact that the designers and companies, especially the new names, have Web sites to visit and to shop at -- with collections, not selections, of their work. You don't have to wait for a local design store shopping the show to pick it up and bring it back. In addition, the shipping and handling on a direct order could be less expensive than a shop's markup.</p>
        <p>The satisfaction expressed by exhibitors this year was the same as the dissatisfaction: the show, which is now five times the size it was in 1995, included major companies like Ligne Roset and Wedgwood, and lacked the unholy rudeness and punkish presence of the unpolished, independent designs that gave it its reputation.</p>
        <p>''I see excitement now very differently,'' Nick Crosbie, 29, a founding partner in Inflate, said. ''I look at the stands of the big companies, and I can really appreciate what they've done to construct that credibility. Five years ago, I would have looked and thought, 'That's really boring.' ''</p>
        <p>Inflate's big product introduction, Snoozy, a plastic, pop-apart bed, easy to ship and store, is manufactured with a process used for making highway cones. It is intended as a midprice alternative ($:585, or about $850) to the low-end futon and the high-end designer bed. It will be available at Inflate's Web site (www.inflate.co.uk).</p>
        <p>''Production is as important as design,'' Mr. Crosbie said. ''To make a real product, rather than just being on magazine pages. If you can't buy something, then it doesn't actually perform its task.''</p>
        <p>ANDREAS ENGESVIK, a partner in Norway Says (www .norwaysays.com), a young Norwegian design collective, showed a tiny, upholstered armchair called Tennis that looked like a space-saving Muppets version of Harry Bertoia's classic Diamond wire chair for Knoll. Mr. Engesvik's colleague, Frode Myhr, who was still in design school when Norway Says exhibited in Milan in April, sat in Birce, his red flying carpet of a seat on steel, voicing concern that the traffic was too light. Though tender in age, Norway Says means business -- it sold a half-dozen designs shortly after showing in Milan, to Herman Miller, Saporiti and other companies.</p>
        <p>Down the dank hall at Designersblock2000, Thomas Winkel and Tobias Jacobsen, Danish designers, displayed Tatami, a dining table that folds down, like a horse kneeling, into a low bed.</p>
        <p>''It's a new way of giving furniture an expression,'' Mr. Winkel (thomas@winkel.com) said, speaking of utility. ''I feel that when there's a lot of furniture in your apartment, it takes away your freedom.'' Mr. Winkel, who lives in a small apartment in Copenhagen, demonstrated by pressing his back against a crumbling wall.</p>
        <p>At 100% Design, there was much of the same practical-minded versatility -- a kind of suggestiveness in objects that was smart and fresh. ''Not prescriptive, but multifunctional and playful,'' said Michael Marriott, who organized the designers for Oreka Kids.</p>
        <p>''We thought about how kids use adult furniture as toys,'' Mr. Marriott said. ''Playing under the table, or in a box.'' His Nice steps-and-storage design ($:270, or about $390) also rolls and has a crawl-in cabin at the back -- the cockpit for a rocket ship or a racing car. It also makes a handy television and VCR stand.</p>
        <p>''It isn't going to be cheap, like Ikea, so we wanted to give the pieces longevity,'' Mr. Marriott said. ''They don't end life as children's furniture.''</p>
        <p>Schmidingermodul's storage system, designed by Harri Koskinen, is built upon modular, molded birch plywood cases with the rounded corners, liftable lids and carrying grips of suitcases -- baggage for the house. They also stack as pedestals or sit squatly in a sequence, to make benchlike seating (www.Schmidingermodul.at).</p>
        <p>Like much that was seen at the exhibition and elsewhere that week, the designs were startlingly low-tech. The best technological innovations involved explorations with traditional materials. Lubna Chowdhary (lubna.c@virgin.net) showed ceramic tiles with the color fields and surface relief of Abstract Expressionist painting.</p>
        <p>Foundation 33, the London-based team of Daniel Eatock, an English graphic designer and Sam Solhaug, an American architect, displayed simple plywood tables. Their concept is in the investigation of the material in their construction: a basic 4-by-8-foot sheet of plywood is cut into thin strips, then glued, sanded and laminated into a minimal but beautifully striated surface. There is no waste of wood; the tables are 33% lighter than the sheets they are constructed from, because of the sawdust lost in cutting -- hence the team's moniker (www.foundation33.com).</p>
        <p>Mari-Ruth Oda (Mari</p>
        <p>DESIGN NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
