<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europeans Buy 2 U.S. Money Managers</title>
    <meta content="Y19FUN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/business/19FUND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239961"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Allianz Insurance Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nicholas-Applegate</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abn Amro</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Allegheny Asset Management</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Danny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EFD9153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europeans Buy 2 U.S. Money Managers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANNY HAKIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hakim, Danny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allianz, German company that is Europe's second-largest insurer, agrees to pay up to $2.2 billion to acquire Nicholas-Applegate, privately held firm that manages $45 billion in institutional accounts and mutual funds; ABN Amro, largest Dutch bank, agrees to pay $825 million for Allegheny Asset Management, firm that manages about $45 billion, mostly for institutional clients (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European appetite for American money management firms continued apace yesterday as two European financial firms struck deals to buy two domestic asset management firms. The deals are part of a trend that has Europeans shopping for American investment firms to help them capitalize on a shifting pension landscape at home.</p>
        <p>Allianz, the German company that is Europe's second-largest insurer, agreed to pay up to $2.2 billion to acquire Nicholas-Applegate, a privately held firm that manages $45 billion in institutional accounts and mutual funds. The purchase included an upfront payment of $980 million and an additional $1.2 billion largely contingent on Nicholas-Applegate meeting growth and performance targets over the next five years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The European appetite for American money management firms continued apace yesterday as two European financial firms struck deals to buy two domestic asset management firms. The deals are part of a trend that has Europeans shopping for American investment firms to help them capitalize on a shifting pension landscape at home.</p>
        <p>Allianz, the German company that is Europe's second-largest insurer, agreed to pay up to $2.2 billion to acquire Nicholas-Applegate, a privately held firm that manages $45 billion in institutional accounts and mutual funds. The purchase included an upfront payment of $980 million and an additional $1.2 billion largely contingent on Nicholas-Applegate meeting growth and performance targets over the next five years.</p>
        <p>In a second deal, ABN Amro, the largest Dutch bank, agreed to pay $825 million for Alleghany Asset Management, a firm that like Nicholas-Applegate, manages about $45 billion, mostly for institutional clients. Alleghany is a subsidiary of the Alleghany Corporation, a New York holding company.</p>
        <p>In a third deal that is in the offing, Amvescap, a British money management firm that owns the Invesco and AIM fund groups, confirmed yesterday that it was in talks to buy Perpetual, a British money manager.</p>
        <p>What is driving the deals?</p>
        <p>With many pension systems underfunded, Europeans are beginning to look to private investments to supplement government pensions. American investors have shown the potential of the retirement market. In 1990, Americans had $207 billion in retirement mutual fund assets. By the end of last year, that had swelled to $2.4 trillion, according to the Investment Company Institute.</p>
        <p>''It's a great opportunity for European banks,'' said Jocelyn Hamlar, a spokeswoman for ABN Amro's domestic subsidiary.</p>
        <p>Joachim Faber, chief financial officer of Allianz, said the dilapidated state of the pension systems was part of the motivation. ''All our rotten state pension systems, going forward, will have to be funded,'' Mr. Faber said. ''There's no way around it, whether the governments want to or not.''</p>
        <p>The flurry of activity yesterday follows several major deals earlier this year involving European financial firms acquiring American asset managers. In June, a subsidiary of AXA, a French financial holding company, paid $3.5 billion for Sanford C. Bernstein, a privately held money management and research firm based in New York. In July, UBS, a giant Swiss bank, spent $10.8 billion to aquire the PaineWebber Group, an American asset manager that caters to the wealthy.</p>
        <p>Guy Moszkowski, an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, said the European pension system had driven many of these deals.</p>
        <p>''European individuals are going to be realizing more and more that the local retirement programs, the local equivalent to Social Security, simply aren't going to be able to provide for them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moszkowski said European insurers and banks were taking a lesson from American insurers and banks over the last decade and trying to avoid an exodus of their assets to money management firms. European banks and insurers, he said, ''don't want to see something similar happen.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
