<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Media Meets An Old Medium In the Phone Book</title>
    <meta content="19LIST$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/technology/19LIST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Directories</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Joyce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronic Mail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Directories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E4DC153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1176" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Media Meets An Old Medium In the Phone Book</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>2001 telephone books distributed by Verizon Communications will list subscribers' e-mail and Web page addresses in addition to home telephone listings for annual fee of $36 for each item appearing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''WHAT'S your e-mail address?'' may soon have a new answer: ''It's in the book.''</p>
        <p>In the phone books that will be distributed next year by Verizon Communications, people will be able to include their e-mail addresses, as well as personal Web page addresses, along with their home telephone listings, for an annual fee of $36 for each additional item.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''WHAT'S your e-mail address?'' may soon have a new answer: ''It's in the book.''</p>
        <p>In the phone books that will be distributed next year by Verizon Communications, people will be able to include their e-mail addresses, as well as personal Web page addresses, along with their home telephone listings, for an annual fee of $36 for each additional item.</p>
        <p>The little-heralded change, which the company says is a first for the New York area, is being advertised in the 2000-2001 white pages of all New York City boroughs. (Businesses have been able to include e-mail and Web addresses for several years, in both their listings and their yellow-page ads.) The residential service is being rolled out by Verizon, Bell Atlantic's corporate successor, in former Bell Atlantic territory -- New York, New England and the mid-Atlantic states -- as the new phone directories are printed.</p>
        <p>The idea, part of a new ''personalized listings'' offering, has been under consideration for several years. ''This is the first time we've finally decided to go with it,'' said MaryBeth Masterson, product manager of white pages for Verizon. Other phone companies have offered the service but with limited response.</p>
        <p>Verizon's research showed that people wanted to be located easily. ''It's a great way to give people the opportunity to contact you in ways other than by telephone,'' Ms. Masterson said. ''E-mail is how people are communicating now.''</p>
        <p>The inclusion of a cyberpresence with a phone listing represents a convergence of high and low technologies, said Dr. James Katz, a communication professor at Rutgers University. ''We are having this jumbling of communication tools,'' he said. People can find ''old-style information'' like phone numbers online, he said, even as they find e-mail addresses in a low-tech print directory.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people are not very Internet-savvy,'' Dr. Katz said, ''so for them, being able to use a familiar technology to look up an e-mail address is great.''</p>
        <p>The personalized-listing option is intended to promote the directory as  ''a print resource for the Internet,'' said Melissa Leach, group manager of consumer products for Verizon. It is advertised in New York City only with a small highlight on the cover of the new Manhattan and Bronx white pages. The personalized-listing option will be highlighted in other areas as the covers are printed and will be mentioned in bill inserts.</p>
        <p>The next step will be to borrow a technique from Web design, highlighting e-mail adresses and U.R.L.'s in blue ''so they pop off the page at you,'' Ms. Leach said.</p>
        <p>Assorted directory publishers nationwide offer various residential  listing options, Ms. Masterson said. ''Across the country, you will come across companies that have different residential products, including a logo, like a horse in front of your name, or a sports insignia.''</p>
        <p>The major phone companies whose white pages blanket the United States are all considering an e-mail listings option. In a very few cases, they offer it already. Qwest, for example, began offering the service in January 1997 but does not advertise it; fewer than 400 residential customers have signed up. Bell Canada has offered the service since November 1996.</p>
        <p>Verizon is offering several kinds of personalized home listings for next year's phone books, as touted in a one-page advertisement in the current white pages. People can highlight their listing with bold or italic type, add identifying information (''your local selectman'' is given as an example) or include an e-mail address or personal Web site address.</p>
        <p>As it happens, the example given for the mythical Donna Waters in the ad includes a mistake. Her Web site's U.R.L. is given in an e-mail format: donnawaters@baweb.com, rather than www.donnawaters.com. The error will be corrected in next year's book, Ms. Masterson said.</p>
        <p>Currently, people will not be able to list e-mail or Web addresses if their phone numbers are unlisted -- though that policy might change. But a listing can include multiple e-mail addresses, like one for each spouse.</p>
        <p>''I think it's going to take off great,'' said Jean Carroll, a supervisor for DDA, the telemarketing company that distributes Verizon's phone directories and answers the  personalized-listings number, (888) 550-1222. Still, there's a time lag that makes many people postpone ordering. The next Manhattan phone book, for example, does not come out until early fall of 2001.</p>
        <p>The e-mail address, which Verizon calls an ''e-dress,'' is by far the most popular feature offered, said Cedric Brown, the only operator currently assigned to the listings line. People also like to add a reference to a listing for a small business, like a tailor's or seamstress's shop, he said.</p>
        <p>Right now, with just a few dozen calls a day, Verizon isn't worried that fervid interest in e-mail listings will fatten its phone books. ''It's just  starting, and people are just becoming aware of it,'' Ms. Masterson said.</p>
        <p>What's more, publicizing it has not been a priority, Ms. Leach said. Compared with business listings, the service generates little revenue. Even an ordinary Manhattan business listing costs $15.25 a month. Each extra line of type, like an e-mail or Web address, is an extra  $13.75 each month.</p>
        <p>An e-mail listing will be a boon for those who want to be reached, Dr. Katz said. ''A lot of people hunger for contact -- look how often they check their e-mail. This promotes that kind of contact in a positive way. Sometimes people want to send a message but don't want to bother you.''</p>
        <p>In some ways, paying for an e-mail listing is the flip side of the unlisted-number phenomenon, where people pay ($1.95 a month in New York) not to be listed.</p>
        <p>''People in the phone book do get more telemarketing and obscene phone calls than those who are unlisted,'' Mr. Katz said. ''But a lot of people hope their long-lost friends or old flame will get in touch with them, and this increases the possibility of that.''</p>
        <p>Though people might worry that listing an e-mail address is an open invitation to spammers, such a listing would be unlikely to generate more spam than even one visit to a  chat room, Dr. Katz said.</p>
        <p>But just in case, he suggested using a Web-based e-mail address, like those offered by Hotmail or Yahoo, for a phone-book listing. ''Most people already have many e-mail addresses -- a real one they look at many times a day, and a 'public' one they don't check all that often,'' he said.</p>
        <p>What's more, a Web-based address will not become outdated if the user changes Internet service providers or moves.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
