<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fighting in Colombia Stops Commerce and Creates Refugees</title>
    <meta content="19COLO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/world/19COLO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Colombia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Putumayo Province (Colombia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forero, Juan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EED8153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fighting in Colombia Stops Commerce and Creates Refugees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUAN FORERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Forero, Juan</byline>
      <dateline>BOGOTA, Colombia, Oct. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fierce fighting in southern Colombia halts commerce and makes hundreds of people seek refuge in Ecuador and elsewhere in Colombia; guerrillas of largest rebel organization are controlling roads throughout area; chaos has gripped Putumayo Province since heavy fighting began last month; roadblocks prevent deliveries of food and other necessities (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fierce fighting in southern Colombia has halted commerce and made hundreds of people seek refuge in Ecuador and elsewhere in Colombia, officials said today.</p>
        <p>Guerrillas of the largest rebel organization here, the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, are controlling roads throughout the area. As a result, isolated towns and hamlets have seen supplies of food, gasoline and drinking water dwindle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fierce fighting in southern Colombia has halted commerce and made hundreds of people seek refuge in Ecuador and elsewhere in Colombia, officials said today.</p>
        <p>Guerrillas of the largest rebel organization here, the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, are controlling roads throughout the area. As a result, isolated towns and hamlets have seen supplies of food, gasoline and drinking water dwindle.</p>
        <p>More than 1,000 people have left their houses this month, said Gloria Echeverry, a spokeswoman for the Network of Social Solidarity, a government agency that is shipping food to the region.</p>
        <p>Of the refugees, 225 have reportedly crossed the San Miguel and Putumayo Rivers into Ecuador, fleeing the chaos that has gripped the Putumayo Province since heavy fighting began last month. Several hundred Ecuadoreans who work in Putumayo are reportedly stranded in its capital, Mocoa.</p>
        <p>The people who remain are said to subsist on whatever food and water they had stored since roadblocks all but ended the deliveries.</p>
        <p>''Now the people are hungry,'' said Francisco Segura, director of the Association of Municipalities of Putumayo, a nongovernment group that has been in contact with elected officials. ''They are not allowing any food in or out through any route, not through Ecuador or anywhere else. What the government is doing is not much. They are helping people in the cities. But what about the people in the little communities and farms?''</p>
        <p>The confrontations between left-wing guerrillas and right-wing paramilitary forces are in a region the size of New Hampshire, an area of steamy jungles and coca fields where an ambitious American-backed effort at eradicating 135,000 acres of coca fields is widely expected to go into high gear by early next year. Two counternarcotics battalions trained by American soldiers are beginning operations.</p>
        <p>The training, along with helicopters and other assistance to help them operate, is part of $1.3 billion in United States aid that is meant to curtail the northbound flow of cocaine.</p>
        <p>Critics have said the program, which is top-heavy with military spending, will lead to increased fighting and displaced farmers.</p>
        <p>The rebel group, known as FARC, has long been involved in the cocaine trade in the region, where half the Colombian coca is grown, American officials say. The paramilitary groups, privately financed groups that human rights workers say have often operated with tacit support from elements of the military, have in recent weeks engaged the guerrillas for control of the lucrative business.</p>
        <p>One result, Colombian officials say, has been a series of skirmishes that has left scores of guerrillas, paramilitaries and farmers dead.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Interior Ministry here, Raul Gutierrez, said: ''In these zones, 50 percent of Colombian coca is produced. And now there is a dispute between the paramilitaries and the guerrillas for the territory, for the business.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gutierrez said the government had not foreseen ''the blockade and the isolation of the people and, much less, that the blockade would stop the flow of food.''</p>
        <p>The government has flown 120 tons of rice, milk, beans, cooking oil and other food items to the region. A 100-ton shipment is to be sent beginning on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gutierrez said, ''We have only gotten the food to the big towns.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
