<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Theater's Uptown 'Party' Leaves a Hangover</title>
    <meta content="19WILD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/arts/19WILD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="MUCH ADO ABOUT A VISION -- Second of two articles." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Papp, Joseph, Public Theater/new York Shakespeare Festival</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wild Party, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Joseph Papp Public Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E5DE153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Theater's Uptown 'Party' Leaves a Hangover</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Second article in series, Much Ado About a Vision, on commercial failure of The Wild Party, musical produced by Joseph Papp Public Theater, which closed shortly after opening in April; failure raises questions about Public and Broadway's capacity to handle unorthodox fare, and highlights issues and problems that can arise in increasingly frequent partnerships between nonprofit theaters and commercial producers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Jan. 26, just three weeks into rehearsals for the Broadway musical ''The Wild Party,'' the Hollywood producer Scott Rudin wrote a letter to George C. Wolfe, the producer of the Joseph Papp Public Theater, to tell him that he was pulling his money out of the show.</p>
        <p>''When we agreed to go forward together, I fully understood that you guys were going to be the lead producers on the venture, which I never had a problem with, provided that the criteria we agreed upon were put in place and adhered to,'' Mr. Rudin wrote. ''To be told yesterday 'George is an artist and doesn't have time for producing issues' so contravenes the understanding, that I feel it is pointless to try and continue.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On Jan. 26, just three weeks into rehearsals for the Broadway musical ''The Wild Party,'' the Hollywood producer Scott Rudin wrote a letter to George C. Wolfe, the producer of the Joseph Papp Public Theater, to tell him that he was pulling his money out of the show.</p>
        <p>''When we agreed to go forward together, I fully understood that you guys were going to be the lead producers on the venture, which I never had a problem with, provided that the criteria we agreed upon were put in place and adhered to,'' Mr. Rudin wrote. ''To be told yesterday 'George is an artist and doesn't have time for producing issues' so contravenes the understanding, that I feel it is pointless to try and continue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rudin was ultimately persuaded to stay on, a decision he later said he regretted. Although the show opened in April and went on to receive nominations for seven Tony Awards, it won none and quickly closed.</p>
        <p>The commercial failure of ''The Wild Party'' raised broad questions both about the Public and about Broadway's capacity to handle unorthodox fare. An examination of the musical's short, troubled life highlights those issues and the problems that can arise in the increasingly frequent partnerships between nonprofit theaters and commercial producers.</p>
        <p>Although many say ''The Wild Party'' might have had an easier time starting at the Public rather than  high-stakes Broadway, the Public Theater wanted to produce it uptown from the beginning. The production, which Mr. Wolfe wrote with the composer Michael John LaChiusa and also directed, was the season's second adaptation of the 1928 poem by Joseph Moncure March, which chronicles a debauched evening of orgies, shared misery and murder. Manhattan Theater Club did the first ''Wild Party,'' written and composed by Andrew Lippa, in January.</p>
        <p>The Public considered the Wolfe-LaChiusa version to be Broadway-caliber material, particularly because Vanessa Williams had initially agreed to star.</p>
        <p>The Public's board chairman, Kenneth B. Lerer, said that going straight to Broadway also made economic sense because the Public planned to put up just $2.4 million, or half the cost of the show, only $900,000 more than it would have cost to produce it downtown at the Public on Lafayette Street.</p>
        <p>And to do the show justice, Mr. Wolfe and Mr. LaChiusa said, they needed an orchestra pit and sizeable proscenium stage. (In addition, they said, their female star, Toni Collette, who replaced Ms. Williams when she became pregnant, would agree to appear only on Broadway. Ms. Collette's agent, Adam Isaacs, however, said this was ''totally untrue.'')</p>
        <p>To help bring the show to Broadway, everyone working on it agreed to work for below-Broadway rates, said John Breglio, the Public's lawyer. The Public knew it could not afford to produce ''Wild Party'' on Broadway without outside financial help, given that musicals usually cost from $5 million to $10 million these days and that the Public spent $8 million on a failed revival of ''On the Town'' last year. So Mr. Wolfe approached Mr. Rudin, who in turn invited three other commercial producers to take part: Roger Berlind, Elizabeth Williams and Anita Waxman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rudin's team put up half of the show's $4.8 million cost while the Public provided the other half and agreed to cover any overruns, which ultimately amounted to more than $1 million. The Public agreed to split the profits almost evenly with the commercial producers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rudin said that he was initially enthusiastic about the project and that he expected Vanessa Williams's name to sell tickets. ''I thought it had great artistic promise, although the subject matter made it a tough bet,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Those present at the show's first rehearsal remember the excitement in the air. Still, board members say they were realistic about the show's financial prospects. ''We never thought of 'The Wild Party' as another 'Chorus Line,' never thought it would be a commercial hit,'' Mr. Lerer said. ''In my wildest dreams I thought it would break even.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rudin saw the Public's attitude toward potential losses as cavalier, which is partly what soured him on the partnership. ''George Wolfe invited me and my colleagues into this project because he said he wanted a partner in producing this show with the Public Theater,'' Mr. Rudin said. ''In fact what he wanted was investors to hand over the money and walk away and not care where it was spent, how it was spent or whether there would ever be even the possibility of a return.''</p>
        <p>More than a clash of nonprofit and commercial cultures, Mr. Wolfe said, it was a clash of personalities. ''The theater is fundamentally about collaboration,'' he said. ''It was not a good collaboration with Scott because Scott is not a good collaborator. He needs to be in charge. If he is not in charge, it tends to color his passion and his generosity of spirit.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rudin said that over time he came to feel that the show was badly managed because Mr. Wolfe closely guarded all decisions on elements like marketing, advertising and publicity, disregarding the commercial partners' expertise and stretching himself thin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rudin said he became exasperated with Mr. Wolfe's unavailability and wrote the letter after he  tried to plan a promotional event for the show at Joe's Pub and was told over the phone by a Public executive that Mr. Wolfe did not have time for such things. . In response Mr. Lerer, a senior vice president of America Online, together with Michael Lynton, another board member, went to see Mr. Rudin and assured him that his concerns would be addressed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfe conceded that there were ''unquestionably times when the artistic demands of the show were all-consuming,'' but he said he felt that it was important for the Public to hold the reins as part of its mandate.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately the producer of 'The Wild Party' was the Public Theater,'' Mr. Wolfe said. ''And we had agendas that are informed by fiscal realities. But we also have an unbelievable number of agendas that are about the mission of this institution, that are about our relationship with artists, that are about our sense of responsibility to the communities of this city.''</p>
        <p>Despite the assurances from Mr. Lerer and Mr. Lynton, Mr. Rudin said, the situation remained unchanged, and soon there were other flash points. High among them, he said, was the erratic behavior onstage of the show's male lead, Mandy Patinkin, who also regularly missed performances, more than 20 over all.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rudin said that Mr. Wolfe abdicated responsibility. ''Decisive action needed to be taken to make the other 15 actors onstage feel they were as important as Mr. Patinkin,'' Mr. Rudin said. Mr. Patinkin declined to comment. Mr. Wolfe would only say he believed he acted appropriately.</p>
        <p>With conflicts far from resolved, ''The Wild Party'' opened on April 13 to mixed reviews. John Lahr wrote in The New Yorker, ''The enormous energy that comes across the footlights feels more like theatrical hyperventilation than revelation.'' Linda Winer, in Newsday, described the show as ''explosive and entertaining, if not completely satisfying.'' Ben Brantley of The New York Times, called it ''a cause for sorrowful head-shaking,'' in a review that many at the Public blame for the show's demise, given the influence of the newspaper's chief theater critic.</p>
        <p>Even though he was no longer obligated financially, Mr. Rudin said he felt that the producers should close the show. He said he sent a strong message to Mr. Lerer through a colleague. ''I told him, every cent you spend two weeks after the show opened you're going to lose,'' Mr. Rudin said. ''You're throwing money in the street.''</p>
        <p>But the Public's board said it had a duty to keep the show running until the Tony nominations were announced on May 8. After ''Wild Party'' received seven nominations, including one for best musical, the Public hunkered down to hang on until the awards ceremony on June 4.</p>
        <p>To the extent that it is financially possible, Mr. Lerer and other board members say, a nonprofit theater must stick by its artists, particularly its leader. In deciding to keep the show open, the Public had the support of at least one of Mr. Rudin's fellow commercial producers.</p>
        <p>''I thought we were all pretty unified in feeling -- after we received mixed reviews, some raves and some not good reviews -- to let word of mouth build,'' said Elizabeth Williams, who also produced ''The Real Thing'' and ''A Moon for the Misbegotten'' last season. ''We needed to make the commitment, financial and otherwise, to stay open through the Tonys when we got so many nominations.''</p>
        <p>People involved in the show agreed to take salary cuts. Mr. LaChiusa, the composer, waived his royalty fee. And Mr. Lerer appointed a committee of three board members to oversee the show's finances: himself, Larry E. Condon and Ken Auletta.</p>
        <p>The Public says it ultimately put up an additional $1.1 million to cover the costs of keeping the show open. That included $200,000 Mr. Lerer raised from private investors -- including Robert W. Pittman, the president of America Online and the Public's former board chairman -- and from Mr. Lerer himself.</p>
        <p>The Public's board members say that the project fulfilled their artistic expectations. ''I think George completely lived up to his side of the bargain,'' said Mr. Lynton, the president of AOL International. ''He put on a good production. It was cast well, well produced. Whether people came or not is a separate issue.''</p>
        <p>As far as Mr. Rudin is concerned, however, whether people come or not is decisive. And they were not coming in large enough numbers; the show, which cost $450,000 a week to run, was losing $150,000 a week, he said.</p>
        <p>On June 6, two days after ''Wild Party'' was shut out at the Tony Awards, the producers announced that the musical would close on June 11. Soon afterward Mr. Lerer invited Mr. LaChiusa down to the Public to meet with the board.</p>
        <p>''He said, speaking for the board, how much they believed in this piece, that it was the type of show they wanted to do, and I always had a home there,'' Mr. LaChiusa recalled. ''It was one of the most moving things I've ever been through in my life.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolfe said he had no regrets, that he believed in ''The Wild Party'' and felt it belonged on Broadway, although he said he was left asking himself, ''Can challenging work happen in that landscape?''</p>
        <p>Tonya Pinkins, one of the show's lead actors, said, ''Sometimes you have to be taking an audience to the next level.''</p>
        <p>The comments point up the divide between the nonprofit theater world and many entrepreneurs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rudin, still irritated by the experience, said it was ''childish and amateurish'' to hold the notion that a show is ''too good for Broadway.''</p>
        <p>''The Broadway environment raised an expectation for the show that the show simply did not deliver,'' he said. ''And despite the fact that there was tremendous talent involved in it on- and offstage, audiences simply didn't like it in large enough numbers to keep it running.''</p>
        <p>In Mr. Wolfe's view, ''The Wild Party'' might have taken off had it had more time to find an audience. ''We lost the commercial battle,'' he said. ''But I firmly believe this show is going to have a future life because it's a good piece.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
