<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In America; Mr. Gore in Top Form</title>
    <meta content="19HERB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/opinion/19HERB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E1D8153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In America; Mr. Gore in Top Form</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herbert, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Herbert Op-Ed column says Vice Pres Al Gore was clear winner in final debate with Gov George W Bush; says Gore was best he has been since acceptance speech at Democratic National Convention (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This time Al Gore got it right, and not a moment too soon.</p>
        <p>People were starting to say of George W. Bush: Well, he might not know the Middle East from the Big East, but he's a nice guy. He might not know subliminal from subliminable, but he's likeamable. And, hey, I can't locate Yemen on a map, either.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This time Al Gore got it right, and not a moment too soon.</p>
        <p>People were starting to say of George W. Bush: Well, he might not know the Middle East from the Big East, but he's a nice guy. He might not know subliminal from subliminable, but he's likeamable. And, hey, I can't locate Yemen on a map, either.</p>
        <p>Turned off by Al Gore's performance in the first two debates, a fair number of voters began moving toward Mr. Bush, making excuses and weird rationalizations along the way. Some argued that if Mr. Bush were to become president and the country found itself in a tight spot, he'd have plenty of experienced people available to bail him out -- his dad; his vice president, Dick Cheney; his secretary of state, Colin Powell, etc.</p>
        <p>Talk about the soft bigotry of low expectations! Why should anyone be afraid to set high standards for Mr. Bush or Mr. Gore, and demand that they meet them? They're running for president.</p>
        <p>At the debate Tuesday night, Al Gore was the best he's been since his acceptance speech at the Democratic convention. He was knowledgeable and comfortable discussing a wide range of complex issues, including health care, Social Security and tax cuts. You can agree or disagree with his position on any issue, but you cannot argue that Mr. Gore does not understand the issue. With Mr. Bush, you're never quite sure.</p>
        <p>The tone of the debate was set early. Mr. Gore was much better prepared than Mr. Bush to discuss a so-called patients' bill of rights. ''Doctors are giving prescriptions, they're recommending treatments, and then their recommendations are being overruled by H.M.O.'s and insurance companies,'' said Mr. Gore. ''That is unacceptable.''</p>
        <p>He said he supports bipartisan legislation -- sponsored by Representative John Dingell, a Michigan Democrat, and Representative Charlie Norwood, a Georgia Republican -- to establish a national patients' bill of rights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he, too, supports a patients' bill of rights. But though he was asked twice if he supported the Dingell-Norwood bill, he never answered. Instead, he scoffed at the whole governmental process, saying, ''There's this kind of Washington D.C. focus -- well, it's in this committee, or it's got this sponsor.''</p>
        <p>Well, yes, governor. That's how the federal government works. And it will continue to work that way, even if you are elected president.</p>
        <p>Time and again during the debate Mr. Bush appeared baffled by the specifics of one issue or another. During a discussion of affirmative action, Mr. Gore asked, ''Are you for what the Supreme Court says is a constitutional way of having affirmative action?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush turned to Jim Lehrer, the moderator, his facial expression and body language all but begging Mr. Lehrer to save him by declaring there was no time left for him to answer.</p>
        <p>''Jim --'' said Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lehrer said, ''Let's go onto another --''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said, quietly and devastatingly, ''I think that speaks for itself.''</p>
        <p>The governor's worst moment came in response to a woman who asked, ''How will your tax proposals affect me as a middle-class, 24-year-old single person with no dependents?''</p>
        <p>The answer was bizarre. It meandered this way and that until it lost any semblance of coherence. Mr. Bush said everyone would get tax relief under his plan. He went on to say, ''I think also what you need to think about is not the immediate but what about Medicare?'' He said, ''You get a plan that will include prescription drugs, a plan that will give you options.'' He talked about Medicare people being stuck in a time warp. He said, ''You're going to live in a peaceful world.'' He said, ''You'll be in a world, hopefully, that's more educated, so it's less likely you'll be harmed in your neighborhood, seeing an educated child is one much more likely to be hopeful and optimistic.'' And so on.</p>
        <p>It was astonishing. When he finally reached the end of this positively Olympian feat of convolution, I wondered what could possibly come next. Surely someone would comment.</p>
        <p>But no one seemed fazed. Mr. Lehrer said, ''Governor, the next question is for you and Leo Anderson will ask it. Mr. Anderson.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush smiled. ''Hi, Leo,'' he said. ''You want a mike?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
