<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chase, Nearing J. P. Morgan Merger, Reports Profit Shortfall</title>
    <meta content="Y19CHAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/business/19CHAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chase Manhattan Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan, J P, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Atlas, Riva D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7D8153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="843" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chase, Nearing J. P. Morgan Merger, Reports Profit Shortfall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RIVA D. ATLAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Atlas, Riva D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chase Manhattan announces third-quarter operating earnings of $905 million, down 26 percent from prior year; J P Morgan reports net income of $514 million, 25 percent increase over same period last year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chase Manhattan, whose stock had already fallen 34 percent since it announced its $31 billion merger with J. P. Morgan last month, gave investors more bad news yesterday. Chase announced third-quarter operating earnings of $905 million, or 68 cents a share. That was down 26 percent from the prior year, and far below the 93 cents analysts had expected.</p>
        <p>In contrast, Chase's prospective merger partner, J. P. Morgan, reported net income of $514 million, or $2.77 a share. That was 25 percent above what the bank earned in the quarter a year ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chase Manhattan, whose stock had already fallen 34 percent since it announced its $31 billion merger with J. P. Morgan last month, gave investors more bad news yesterday. Chase announced third-quarter operating earnings of $905 million, or 68 cents a share. That was down 26 percent from the prior year, and far below the 93 cents analysts had expected.</p>
        <p>In contrast, Chase's prospective merger partner, J. P. Morgan, reported net income of $514 million, or $2.77 a share. That was 25 percent above what the bank earned in the quarter a year ago.</p>
        <p>Much of Chase's earnings disappointment was linked to its Chase Capital Partners division, a $20 billion investment portfolio with large holdings in technology and telecommunications. Chase also suffered from an industry-wide downturn in high-yield bond underwriting and leveraged lending.</p>
        <p>Still, Chase worked hard to persuade investors that the earnings shortfall was a result of short-term cyclical problems. Chase's stock price gyrated wildly during the day. In the morning, it was down as much as $4.30 a share, and by late afternoon it was actually up 20 cents, before closing at $36.88, down $1.06. J.P. Morgan's shares dropped $3.38, to $134.25.</p>
        <p>''The nature of the earnings disappointment shouldn't have been a surprise to investors,'' said Judah Kraushaar, an analyst at Merrill Lynch who maintains a buy recommendation on Chase's stock. Investors had anticipated that Chase Capital Partners would show losses on a number of its investments, given the downturn in technology stocks. Since 20 percent of Chase Capital's portfolio is in public equities, with the holdings listed on Chase's Web site, investors had been tracking the losses.</p>
        <p>Chase Capital Partners had been a big money maker for the bank in previous quarters, particularly with technology stocks booming. But in its earnings release, the company made a point of reporting its profits with and without Chase Capital Partners. Without the investment portfolio, results looked slightly better: operating earnings were 77 cents a share.</p>
        <p>One unexpected problem for Chase in the third quarter was a rise in cash expenses in its investment banking division, up 47 percent from the prior year. Even before its merger with Morgan was announced, Chase had been aggressively building its deal-making team. In the third quarter alone, it acquired the Beacon Group, a merger advisory boutique, and Robert Fleming Holdings, an investment bank based in London.</p>
        <p>''I want to assure all of you that we are exceedingly focused on the expense issue,'' said Geoffrey Boisi, head of investment banking at Chase, at a meeting with analysts yesterday. He said the division had already been evaluating its personnel needs, and hoped to accelerate that process in the course of completing the merger with Morgan.</p>
        <p>Marc Shapiro, vice chairman of Chase, added: ''We have 600 M &amp; A bankers. We do not need 600 M &amp; A bankers to have a first-class platform.''</p>
        <p>He said the companies' investment bankers have already been working together to solicit new business. In the last three weeks, J. P. Morgan and Chase have probably won business worth an additional $50 million in fees that they would not have earned on their own, he said. ''We looked at 2,400 clients and the overlap was 10 percent,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One bit of good news for Chase came in its loan portfolio. Despite concerns about credit problems in the banking industry, Chase's nonperforming assets have actually declined 10 percent since last year. ''That's rather remarkable,'' said David Berry, head of research at Keefe, Bruyette &amp; Woods, a brokerage firm focused on the financial services industry. ''I cannot think of another bank that has had a decline year over year.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Shapiro stressed that the merger with J. P. Morgan was very much on track, despite the decline in Chase's stock since the deal was announced. ''We are expecting to close in the first quarter,'' he said, ''but we are preparing ourselves to close by year-end if we can do that.''</p>
        <p>The dip in Chase's stock yesterday was viewed by many investors as an opportunity. ''We thought given the underlying fundamentals, this was an opportunity to step up,'' said Frank Barkocy, head of research at Keefe Managers in New York, which runs a $200 million hedge fund specializing in bank stocks. Keefe bought shares of Chase when it was down heavily in the morning.</p>
        <p>''I think there's more than a double in the stock over the next two years,'' Mr. Kraushaar of Merrill said. Chase is trading at just 9.5 times his estimate for 2001 earnings, taking into account the merger with Morgan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
