<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WorldCom Might Issue New Stock</title>
    <meta content="Y19PHON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/technology/19PHON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Worldcom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mci Worldcom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Telecom Usa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D9153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WorldCom Might Issue New Stock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Worldcom Inc intends to issue new stock to track its consumer and wholesale long-distance units; new stock would track unit that generally sells long-distance service to consumers under MCI and Telecom USA brands and has annual revenue of about $12 billion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frustrated by the price wars and slow growth that have come to characterize much of the long-distance telephone business, WorldCom Inc. intends to issue a new stock to track its consumer and wholesale long-distance units, people close to the company said yesterday.</p>
        <p>One person close to the company said that the units could still be sold or spun off but that the possibility of such a move was small, for now. Yesterday, the plan was to announce the new stock soon after the company announced its quarterly financial results next Thursday. AT&amp;T, the No. 1 long-distance carrier, is considering a similar move.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frustrated by the price wars and slow growth that have come to characterize much of the long-distance telephone business, WorldCom Inc. intends to issue a new stock to track its consumer and wholesale long-distance units, people close to the company said yesterday.</p>
        <p>One person close to the company said that the units could still be sold or spun off but that the possibility of such a move was small, for now. Yesterday, the plan was to announce the new stock soon after the company announced its quarterly financial results next Thursday. AT&amp;T, the No. 1 long-distance carrier, is considering a similar move.</p>
        <p>A WorldCom spokesman declined to comment.</p>
        <p>It was unclear yesterday whether WorldCom intended to offer the tracking shares directly to investors through an initial public offering or whether the company would simply distribute the new shares to its existing stockholders.</p>
        <p>The new stock would track a unit that generally sells long-distance service to consumers under the MCI and Telecom USA brands and has annual revenue of about $12 billion. The unit would probably have a market value of $10 billion to $15 billion, at least initially.</p>
        <p>Even as many investors have focused on the turmoil at AT&amp;T, the nation's biggest phone company, the downdraft in the consumer long-distance market has caught other big long-distance carriers including WorldCom and Sprint. Consumers can now choose among multiple calling plans with rates of less than 10 cents a minute.</p>
        <p>For WorldCom, the long-distance pressure is doubly vexing. Not only is it a problem on its face, but WorldCom has never really concentrated on retail consumers in the first place. Rather, WorldCom has focused on serving business customers; WorldCom's decision to buy MCI was based more on the value of MCI's network and MCI's data business than on the value of MCI's consumer unit.</p>
        <p>And even as the consumer long-distance business has deteriorated, the wholesale business has become a lot less attractive than it used to be. There are hundreds of long-distance phone companies in the nation, and most of them buy network capacity or long-distance minutes from the bigger carriers.</p>
        <p>The rise of new long-distance carriers with networks of their own, like Qwest Communications International Inc. and Level 3 Communications Inc., has increased competition in that market, driving down prices.</p>
        <p>And so, WorldCom's consumer and wholesale operation grew only about 1 percent in the second quarter compared with figures in the period a year earlier, to revenue of about $2.9 billion. Meanwhile, the company's overall revenue from communications services grew about 14 percent.</p>
        <p>''By separating the segments that are dragging revenue growth down, the remaining company will have top-  and bottom-line growth rates more appealing to public market investors,'' said Daniel P. Reingold, chief telecommunications services analyst at Credit Suisse First Boston, who expects WorldCom to announce that the consumer and wholesale units actually shrank in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>But what might the new unit be worth?</p>
        <p>For the second quarter, WorldCom announced that the combined consumer and wholesale unit had revenue of about $2.9 billion and that the entire company had earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortization, or Ebitda, that came to about 36 percent of overall revenue.</p>
        <p>If the consumer and wholesale unit has annual revenue of $11.6 billion, or four times the second-quarter figure, and if the Ebitda margin is the same for that unit as for the rest of the company (WorldCom has not released that figure), then the new unit will have annual Ebitda of about $4.2 billion.</p>
        <p>Now, according to people close to AT&amp;T, that company has shopped its consumer long-distance unit to various leveraged buyout shops, offering it for four times Ebitda. The buyout firms have reportedly said they would pay no more than two times Ebitda.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T's consumer unit is somewhat less attractive than WorldCom's consumer and wholesale operation, not least because the AT&amp;T unit is already shrinking. So perhaps the WorldCom unit would be worth three times Ebitda, rather than two, assuming that the AT&amp;T and WorldCom units carry proportional debt loads. In that case, the Worldcom unit would be worth about $12.6 billion.</p>
        <p>Many analysts, however, think that the Ebitda margin for WorldCom's consumer and wholesale operation is not as high as 36 percent, or at least would not be after the new stock is issued. If that figure is instead 30 percent, then the same analysis yields an overall value of about $10.4 billion.</p>
        <p>In the future, of course, the unit could grow into a multiple higher than three times Ebitda. Mr. Reingold, for instance, thinks the unit is worth six times Ebitda, though he cautioned that he would not expect public investors to lend such a valuation right away.</p>
        <p>So under a rosy outlook, that of 36 percent Ebitda margins and an Ebitda multiple of six, the unit could be worth $25 billion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
