<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Office Renovated For Mac</title>
    <meta content="19STAT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/technology/19STAT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1239925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STATE OF THE ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Apple Computer Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Biersdorfer, J D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/State of the Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EFDE153EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1262" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Office Renovated For Mac</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J. D. Biersdorfer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Biersdorfer, J D</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Microsoft releases Word 2001, word processing software program for Macintosh operating systems; article evaluates new program, finds it impressive and innovative; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MICROSOFT WORD 2001 for the Macintosh just came out this month, and as someone whose first choice for word processing is Word on a Mac, I am apprehensive.</p>
        <p>Like many writers, I still have fond memories of Word 5.1, which was released in the early 90's and was a straightforward, yet powerful word-processing program that didn't complicate the task of writing. I found the next version, Word 6.0, to be a wheezing, bloated mess of recycled Windows code that was confusing to use and took no advantage of the built-in elegance of the Macintosh operating system. I still have the 13 or so floppies that it came on, though, because they do make a nice set of matching coasters for parties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MICROSOFT WORD 2001 for the Macintosh just came out this month, and as someone whose first choice for word processing is Word on a Mac, I am apprehensive.</p>
        <p>Like many writers, I still have fond memories of Word 5.1, which was released in the early 90's and was a straightforward, yet powerful word-processing program that didn't complicate the task of writing. I found the next version, Word 6.0, to be a wheezing, bloated mess of recycled Windows code that was confusing to use and took no advantage of the built-in elegance of the Macintosh operating system. I still have the 13 or so floppies that it came on, though, because they do make a nice set of matching coasters for parties.</p>
        <p>Luckily, Word 98 was a vast improvement, but I fear that with Word 2001, Microsoft may have once again tinkered with a good thing. After watching the software develop, I have begun to feel that many of the iterations of Word are like Beethoven symphonies: only every other one stands out. (I do, however, love listening to the Fifth and the Sixth back to back.)</p>
        <p>Word 2001 is part of Office 2001 for Mac, which includes new versions of the Excel spreadsheet program and the popular PowerPoint program for creating presentations and slides. The Office suite costs about $450. Sold separately, the three programs cost around $360 apiece; upgrades from the previous versions cost around $140 per program.</p>
        <p>The Office suite also comes with a fresh addition: an application called Entourage, an e-mail and desktop personal organizer program that lets you link your Office programs together.</p>
        <p>I was quite curious as I loaded up the Microsoft Office 2001 CD-ROM into my Mac at home. Users of older Macs that didn't have enough power to handle Office 98's beefy system requirements are out of luck here as well. To use Office 2001, you need a Power Macintosh with at least Version 8.1 of the operating system (OS 8.5 is preferred), a 120-megahertz processor and at least 32 megabytes of RAM. For the standard versions of the programs, you need 160 megabytes of hard disk space. Fortunately, iMacs, iBooks and the machines in Apple's G3 series of computers can easily meet those requirements.</p>
        <p>After I put in the CD, a window popped up showing the Office folder, along with the instructions ''To install Office, just copy this folder to your hard disk.'' Internet Explorer 5 and a selection of additional Office components called the Value Pack can also be installed in a similar fashion from the Office CD. It took less than five minutes for the entire Office suite (almost 900 individual files) to be copied to the hard drive of my beige G3, which has 128 megabytes of RAM and a 266-megahertz processor. In fact, it took longer to register the software online than it did to install it.</p>
        <p>As soon as I was registered, I started with Entourage, the new app around the Office. The program let me easily import my address book, contact list, memos and task list from the desktop program that works with my Palm organizer. Entourage will also work with files imported from other personal-information management programs like Now Contact and Claris Organizer.</p>
        <p>Entourage encourages you to use it as your default e-mail program. It pestered me twice to let it import all the files from my Eudora e-mail program, but I ignored it, and it finally left me alone. Entourage can handle mail and address-book files from Eudora, as well as those from Outlook Express, Claris E-Mailer and Netscape Messenger. The Entourage e-mail program incorporates many of the features found in recent versions of Word, like instant corrections for typing and spelling mistakes and some automatic formatting functions, including those for numbering and making bullets in text.</p>
        <p>The main Entourage window can be divided into panes displaying various types of information. You can click down a list on the side to have your calendar, e-mail, contact list and daily tasks all pop up on screen. There is a Flag for Follow-Up feature that you can apply to any document in the Office 2001 suite. A file that has been flagged will nag you with an on-screen alert box that reminds you to finish your work on that  e-mail note, Word file or Excel spreadsheet.</p>
        <p>Excel 2001 itself has some nice features, some available so far only in this Mac version. One of them is the  Calculator. It is intended to help people like me, who turn white at the word spreadsheet, understand the concept of working with simple formulas in cells. The List Manager function in Excel 2001 makes it easier to manage long lists of items, as in an inventory. And the program offers users a variety of ways to import files from a FileMaker Pro database into an Excel worksheet.</p>
        <p>PowerPoint pros will find some helpful new capabilities in 2001. Different styles of design templates can coexist within one presentation now, and text can be automatically resized to fit when you are fussing around with a slide. Multimedia treats like animated GIF's can be used in the slides, and even QuickTime movies can be added by dragging them into place. There is a Make Movie memo option that will allow users to save their PowerPoint presentations as QuickTime movies, which can be viewed on any computer, Mac or Windows, that has the QuickTime software installed.</p>
        <p>Word 2001 -- surprise -- truly functions like a Macintosh program. Many of the hallmarks of Word 98 are still there, like automatic spelling-checking and more intuitive tools for adding graphic elements to pages. Word 2001 has a floating Formatting Palette that puts many of the document-adjusting functions, like font size and line spacing, right next to the open file -- that feature saves countless frustrating minutes wading around in menus. Those who still long for the days of Word 5.1 should take note that the familiar, no-frills Word 5.1 toolbar is still available as an option in Word 2001.</p>
        <p>There is a Contact toolbar that you can click on to fetch any name and address from the Entourage program to be moved into a document, a shortcut that saves scads of time when doing business letters. And like Excel and PowerPoint, Word comes with a Project Gallery that contains a selection of templates for different document types, and most files in the programs can be quickly saved as serviceable Web pages by using an option under the File menu.</p>
        <p>All in all, I was quite impressed  with Office 2001, and a little relieved. This robust set of business programs can let Mac users work with tools that are just as good (or even better) than the ones available to their Windows co-workers -- just what one needs in a cross-platform world.</p>
        <p>One of my favorite new features in Word 2001 is the Live Word Count area of the document window, which automatically tells me how long my article is. I expect that will become a valuable inspirational tool, especially on nights when I have to finish an assignment and it's almost time for ''Buffy the Vampire Slayer'' on TV.</p>
        <p>STATE OF THE ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
