<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Close Race Both Parties Think Is Theirs</title>
    <meta content="19CONN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/politics/19CONN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maloney, James H (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nielsen, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EEDB123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Close Race Both Parties Think Is Theirs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <dateline>WESTON, Conn., Oct. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses bitter rematch between Representative James H Maloney, two-term incumbent Democrat, and his Republican challenger, Mark Nielsen, for Congressional seat in Connecticut's fifth district; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are moments when the bitter rematch between Representative James H. Maloney, a two-term incumbent Democrat, and his Republican challenger, Mark Nielsen, actually seems to live up to its billing as one of the most important Congressional races in the country.</p>
        <p>President Clinton has come here to Connecticut's Fifth District to campaign for Mr. Maloney, and Senator John McCain of Arizona and Elizabeth Dole have campaigned for Mr. Nielsen. Money and resources are pouring in from both major national parties. And the candidates have serious disagreements on education, taxes, health care and other key issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are moments when the bitter rematch between Representative James H. Maloney, a two-term incumbent Democrat, and his Republican challenger, Mark Nielsen, actually seems to live up to its billing as one of the most important Congressional races in the country.</p>
        <p>President Clinton has come here to Connecticut's Fifth District to campaign for Mr. Maloney, and Senator John McCain of Arizona and Elizabeth Dole have campaigned for Mr. Nielsen. Money and resources are pouring in from both major national parties. And the candidates have serious disagreements on education, taxes, health care and other key issues.</p>
        <p>But there are also days when this race seems more like a nasty scrap for control of the student council at a local college. Last Thursday, for instance, two carpenters supporting Mr. Maloney were pulled over in their pickup truck, arrested and charged with stealing Nielsen campaign signs in broad daylight. (The Maloney campaign said it had no connection to the men.)</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Mr. Nielsen crashed a news conference where Mr. Maloney proposed ending the use of soft money in the race. Mr. Nielsen stood off in a corner and then spoke to reporters after Mr. Maloney finished, making both men look like actors in an amateurish parody of the soft-money dispute in the Clinton-Lazio Senate race in New York. (No agreement was reached, and the soft money spending continues.)</p>
        <p>The reason for this free-for-all is that the seat is one of the few in the country that is considered so close that both parties have made winning it part of their strategy for controlling the House. In 1998, Mr. Maloney barely survived Mr. Nielsen's first challenge, defeating him by fewer than 2,400 votes, less than 2 percent of those cast.</p>
        <p>In this year's sequel, Mr. Nielsen is presenting himself as a fresh choice while deriding Mr. Maloney as a man beholden to special interests who failed to bring home sufficient pork. ''Connecticut ranks dead last in the country, 50th of all 50 states, in return on our dollars from Washington,'' he told voters at a recent forum.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maloney is trying to remind constituents what he has done for them on the House Banking and Armed Services Committees, presenting himself as a centrist while painting Mr. Nielsen as a right-wing attack dog with no agenda. ''I think he has failed the voters of this district by failing to offer a program as to what he stands for,'' Mr. Maloney said in an interview.</p>
        <p>There have been angry words and angrier advertisements. One Nielsen commercial portrays the husky Mr. Maloney as a fat, red-faced marionette whose strings are pulled by labor interests. A Maloney advertisement calls Mr. Nielsen ''shameless,'' adding: ''But that's Mark Nielsen. Personal attacks, questionable ethics, anything to get elected.''</p>
        <p>The Fifth District stretches across the gently rolling hills of western Connecticut, from Danbury near the New York border to Meriden 15 miles south of Hartford. It has a mix of wealthy suburbs, like Ridgefield and Weston in Fairfield County, and blue-collar towns like Derby and Naugatuck in New Haven County.</p>
        <p>Registered Democrats and Republicans are almost equal in number, and nearly all of the remaining 43 percent of voters are unaffiliated. The district supported George Bush in 1992 and Bill Clinton in 1996, and has been known to throw out incumbent congressmen in either party,  having done so in 4 of the last 14 elections. Mr. Maloney was first elected to Congress in 1996 by defeating Gary Franks, a Republican incumbent.</p>
        <p>A poll conducted for the Maloney campaign in late September had him ahead by 25 percentage points. But that could mean the race is closer than the contest in 1998; a late October independent poll in that race had him up by 30 points. A poll by the Nielsen camp, also in September, showed Mr. Maloney ahead by just 7 points.</p>
        <p>As if to guarantee an unpredictable outcome, there is a potential third-party spoiler: Joseph Zdonczyk of the conservative Concerned Citizens Party. In 1998, Robert Strasdauskas, of the same party, won about 2,700 votes, which is larger than Mr. Maloney's margin of victory.</p>
        <p>Despite the close race in 1998, Mr. Nielsen, who has been in private law practice while preparing to run again, worries that he has little name recognition. ''This is still a race between someone who is universally known and someone who is not yet on the radar screen,'' he told supporters at a forum here in Weston, urging them to tell friends and neighbors about his candidacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nielsen has run a persistent grassroots campaign, knocking on doors, attending high school football games and standing near Interstate 84 entrance ramps to wave to drivers headed for work. Mr. Maloney has had to limit most of his politicking to weekends, because Congress has remained in session in Washington.</p>
        <p>Tethered to the Capitol, Mr. Maloney has had to rely on sporadic events to publicize the legislation he is working on, and on marquee supporters like President Clinton and the state's popular senators, Joseph I. Lieberman and Christopher J. Dodd.</p>
        <p>As the House session has dragged on, it has put pressure on Mr. Maloney at home. The crunch was evident Tuesday after he visited Naugatuck to announce new federal aid for local fire stations. Pressed to make one more stop before catching the shuttle back to Washington, his driver raced 20 miles above the speed limit down Route 8 to their next event in Derby.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Maloney, 52, and Mr. Nielsen, 36, are residents of Danbury. Both graduated from Harvard College and are lawyers and former state legislators. Both are married, and both have children. But on a personal level, the similarities end there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maloney, bear-sized with a bushy white mustache, looks older than his years. Mr. Nielsen, slim and clean-shaven, looks fresh out of school.</p>
        <p>For the most part, their politics also clash. Mr. Nielsen advocates aggressive Republican-style tax cutting, while Mr. Maloney favors smaller tax cuts.</p>
        <p>On education, Mr. Nielsen advocates ending tenure for public school teachers; Mr. Maloney disagrees.  Mr. Nielsen favors allowing citizens to put some Social Security taxes in a private account for mutual funds or other investments; Mr. Maloney calls that proposal risky. Both favor abortion rights. But issues are not the focus of this race.</p>
        <p>Instead, there has been a vicious exchange of accusations. Mr. Nielsen has hammered at Mr. Maloney over the 1997 conviction of his brother, Robert Maloney, on 17 counts of violating federal election laws, suggesting that the congressman let his brother ''take the fall'' for him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maloney has repeatedly noted that he was cleared of wrongdoing in his brother's case. In turn, he has attacked Mr. Nielsen for putting his campaign headquarters in Watertown, just outside the Fifth District, and accused him of getting an illegal rent subsidy from the landlord, who is also a Nielsen contributor.</p>
        <p>There have been bizarre moments, like the day Dick Cheney, the Republican vice-presidential nominee, came to the Fifth District and Mr. Nielsen started broadcasting a commercial that held up Mr. Cheney's opponent, Mr. Lieberman, as a model of integrity to contrast with Mr. Maloney.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nielsen, whose campaign had trumpeted his joint appearance with the Republican vice-presidential nominee, was shunned. Mr. Cheney did not acknowledge him and left without shaking his hand.</p>
        <p>There is also Mr. Nielsen's tendency to crash Maloney campaign events. He turned up at the rally with President Clinton, on the campus of Western Connecticut State University in Danbury, and talked to reporters in the press area until a Maloney campaign aide asked him to leave.</p>
        <p>There are times when the vitriol  seems to undermine plain old-fashioned electioneering. Steve Hutchins, a statistician who recently moved to the district, was on his way to work when he saw Mr. Nielsen near the entrance ramp to Exit 11 on I-84. A supporter held a sign advertising a voter forum in Newtown that evening, and Mr. Hutchins made a mental note to attend.</p>
        <p>That night, as local Republicans gathered at the Town Hall in Newtown, a half-dozen Maloney supporters carrying campaign placards posted themselves outside. Fearing infiltration by the opposition, Mr. Nielsen's driver and aide, Jay Garrity, accosted Mr. Hutchins, who was perhaps the one person in the meeting room not affiliated with the local Republican machine.</p>
        <p>''You are going to have to leave,'' he told Mr. Hutchins, who seemed stunned. ''You need an invitation to the event.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hutchins, clearly bewildered, muttered something about Exit 11.</p>
        <p>''You are not with the Maloney campaign, are you?'' Mr. Garrity asked quickly. ''Don't work for any Democratic organizations? No plans to disrupt the meeting or anything?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hutchins was allowed to stay.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
