<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Death Inquiry Resumes After New Accusations in Auto Lawsuit</title>
    <meta content="19AIRB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/nyregion/19AIRB.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haley, Stephanie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Eric (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6DC123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Death Inquiry Resumes After New Accusations in Auto Lawsuit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prosecutors reopen case of Stephanie Haley, New Jersey woman whose 1997 death behind wheel of Ford Explorer was ruled accidental; decision to reopen case came after lawyers for Ford Motor Company argued in civil suit that she was strangled and that her husband, Dr Eric Thomas, was having an affair at time (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prosecutors have reopened the case of a New Jersey woman whose 1997 death behind the wheel of a Ford Explorer was ruled accidental. The decision to reopen the case came after lawyers for the Ford Motor Company argued in a civil suit that she was strangled and that her husband was having an affair at the time.</p>
        <p>David Blaker, the acting Cape May County prosecutor, said he sent a letter yesterday to lawyers for Ford requesting records they had obtained listing 140 telephone calls from a home in Austin, Tex., to three phones belonging to the husband, Dr. Eric Thomas, around the time of his wife's death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prosecutors have reopened the case of a New Jersey woman whose 1997 death behind the wheel of a Ford Explorer was ruled accidental. The decision to reopen the case came after lawyers for the Ford Motor Company argued in a civil suit that she was strangled and that her husband was having an affair at the time.</p>
        <p>David Blaker, the acting Cape May County prosecutor, said he sent a letter yesterday to lawyers for Ford requesting records they had obtained listing 140 telephone calls from a home in Austin, Tex., to three phones belonging to the husband, Dr. Eric Thomas, around the time of his wife's death.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blaker said he decided to request the records after reading local newspaper accounts of assertions by Ford's lawyers that the calls came from the home of a married woman, Stephanie Haley, with whom Dr. Thomas, a dentist, was having an affair. The two are now married to each other.</p>
        <p>''The medical examiner determined that the death was accidental, and we had no reason to believe otherwise,'' Mr. Blaker said. ''The purpose of looking at these phone records is to see where else they might lead.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blaker's decision to reopen the case was first reported by The Press of Atlantic City yesterday.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas's previous wife, Tracy Rose Thomas, 37, a former ballerina, died on Feb. 9, 1997, after the couple's Explorer sport utility vehicle struck a utility pole on a back road not far from their home in Middle Township, N.J.</p>
        <p>According to court documents, Dr. Thomas told the police that the couple were taking their sick 18-month-old daughter to the hospital on that snowy night, and that his wife, who was six months' pregnant, had insisted on driving.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas, who was in the passenger seat, and the girl, who was strapped into a child safety seat in the back seat of the Explorer, survived the crash.</p>
        <p>On Feb. 1, 1999, Dr. Thomas filed a wrongful death suit against Ford in Federal District Court in Camden, charging that his wife was killed by the force of an air bag opening at 200 miles per hour. He is seeking unspecified compensatory damages for the loss of his wife.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thomas passed a lie detector test administered by the prosecutor's office at his lawyer's request.</p>
        <p>The accident is listed among some 60 low-speed traffic deaths among all vehicle makes and models since 1990 in which the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration has reviewed official reports and found to have been caused by air bags.</p>
        <p>But a report by a pathologist hired by Ford concluded that Ms. Thomas was not killed by the air bag.</p>
        <p>''In my opinion, Mrs. Thomas died of compression of the neck by the hands of another,'' wrote the pathologist, Dr. Michael M. Baden.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas did not respond to  phone messages left at his office and on an after-hours pager. His lawyer in the civil suit, Tom Mellon, did not return messages.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mellon said in an interview in July that Ford was trying to intimidate Dr. Thomas into dropping his civil suit by asserting that he murdered his wife and blamed the air bag.</p>
        <p>The suit is not yet scheduled for trial, and Dr. Thomas has been granted a motion to expand the suit to include defamation charges against Ford, although the company has appealed the motion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
