<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debates Leave Instant Analysts Hedging Their Bets</title>
    <meta content="Y19CRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/politics/19CRIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK -- ON TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EEDE123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debates Leave Instant Analysts Hedging Their Bets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Most political commentators adopt wait-and-see attitude after third presidential debate, mindful that after first debate, when they declared Vice Pres Al Gore the easy winner, Gov George W Bush gained in polls (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Doing the post-mortems after Tuesday night's debate, Peter Jennings on ABC referred to ''the sink-in factor'' that would develop over the next days and George Stephanopoulos said people in the Gore camp ''believe they will win the second-day spin.''</p>
        <p>On CNN, Bernard Shaw compared the debate to yeast that needs time to rise, and on CBS, Gloria Borger chimed in with the night's most unfortunate, unctuous metaphor. ''This has to marinate,'' she said, as if waiting for the Gore and Bush kabobs to be ready for the grill. (Substituting food for sports metaphors suits the cozy Oprah-to-Regis circuit the candidates have been prancing through, but they are no improvement.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Doing the post-mortems after Tuesday night's debate, Peter Jennings on ABC referred to ''the sink-in factor'' that would develop over the next days and George Stephanopoulos said people in the Gore camp ''believe they will win the second-day spin.''</p>
        <p>On CNN, Bernard Shaw compared the debate to yeast that needs time to rise, and on CBS, Gloria Borger chimed in with the night's most unfortunate, unctuous metaphor. ''This has to marinate,'' she said, as if waiting for the Gore and Bush kabobs to be ready for the grill. (Substituting food for sports metaphors suits the cozy Oprah-to-Regis circuit the candidates have been prancing through, but they are no improvement.)</p>
        <p>Though most commentators gave the edge to Vice President Al Gore, their wait-and-see caveats showed that they had learned something after the first debate, when pundits declared Mr. Gore the easy winner but Gov. George W. Bush gained in the polls. Yet the longer view points to a more fundamental question: why have debates diminished as major television events?</p>
        <p>Ratings were weak and the three debates failed to galvanize viewers because television itself has changed. Debates are now simply one part of a process that includes snap polls and focus groups, clips and interviews on morning shows the next day and pundits dissecting each camp's spin for days. Unless a candidate makes a catastrophic blunder (the flub-prone Mr. Bush might have but did not, everyone agreed) it is hard to argue for a debate's singular importance when viewers are bombarded with 24-hour cable news and candidates popping up in daytime, prime time and late night.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the television coverage was visibly struggling with this change. After the debate, on CNN Mr. Shaw introduced viewers to Wolf Blitzer ''in a one-room schoolhouse in Michigan,'' where he spoke to a focus group of undecided voters. There was the television trend of the moment: down-home people rather than experts, a move that speaks to the closeness of this race and also creates a mild echo of the interactive Internet culture creeping up on everyone.</p>
        <p>Yet it led to a futile question. ''Was there a defining moment for you in the course of the debate?'' Mr. Blitzer asked, searching for a turning point that may not materialize until historians view this race in hindsight.</p>
        <p>Over the next 24 hours, the debate's true significance revealed itself, as clips and interviews demonstrated the difference between watching in real time and seeing the debate shaped by repeated snippets. One clip instantly became the most frequently shown: Mr. Gore marching into Mr. Bush's space as if he were a bull ready to charge. In context, the sudden move reeked of contrivance, begging to be the clip of the day. Snipped out of context, the contrivance disappears and the visual image of strength takes over, as was intended.</p>
        <p>The reverse happened with Mr. Bush's closing statement, when he raised his hand and mimed taking the presidential oath. The gesture was also clearly planned, an image meant to be lifted as a news bite. But each time it was replayed afterwards, Mr. Bush looked less presidential and more like a Star Trek character offering a greeting.</p>
        <p>Both candidates appeared on the ABC, CBS and NBC morning shows, in separate interviews taped soon after the debate. Each man reinforced the night's message in miniature.  Mr. Bush's code words were ''smaller government'' and Mr. Gore's ''fight for you.'' And on both CNN and ABC, Mr. Gore repeated what he called his Goldilocks interpretation of his debate performance. In the first he was too hot, in the second too cold and this time just right, he said. (It is a solid assessment but not original; after the second debate Ted Koppel had wondered how Mr. Gore could find a ''Goldilocks solution.'')</p>
        <p>The formats of the debates themselves fostered a Three Bears difference. Stiffly tied to their lecterns in the first, the candidates gave programmatic answers. Seated at an awkward distance from each other at a table in the second, they were vague.</p>
        <p>Tuesday night's so-called Town Hall format was not really that. The candidates could not engage each other in conversation or address the questioners in the audience. Though Mr. Bush once chastised Mr. Gore for breaking the rules and speaking out of turn, it was when the candidates stepped outside the lines that the debate came to life.</p>
        <p>Despite those drawbacks, the near theater-in-the-round perspective allowed television viewers more intimate access than in previous debates. As the men walked across the floor, playing to the crowd, they were able to look directly into cameras and address viewers without seeming too stagey. They were performing, but they were acting the role of your friendly president, not an imperious, distant one. The form suited the close-up nature of television.</p>
        <p>Yet in the end, the format seemed less influential than the campaign strategists' orders. ''They came out fighting,'' as Bill Plante reported on the CBS ''Early Show'' the next morning. Mr. Gore's energetic display was meant to counter criticism that he had been too timid last time; Mr. Bush's demeanor, which several commentators called ''sleepy,'' seemed intended to play it safe and protect his slight lead.</p>
        <p>The debates were lackluster, yet the Bush campaign's rejected proposals would have been worse. Imagine those meetings, moderated by Larry King (the king of softball questions) and Tim Russert (whose self-aggrandizement at the Hillary Clinton-Rick Lazio debate made him a performer rather than a moderator.) With Mr. King too cool, Mr. Russert too hot and Mr. Lehrer too lukewarm, where is Goldilocks when you need her?</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK -- ON TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
