<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; The Popular Pariah</title>
    <meta content="19DOWD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/opinion/19DOWD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DC123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; The Popular Pariah</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column speculates about Pres Clinton's reaction to debates between Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush, noting Clinton has become somewhat of 'pariah' in Gore's presidential campaign (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Gore has said he would consider putting a 24-hour-a-day Webcam, or Alcam, in the Oval Office.</p>
        <p>Tipper, of course, immediately intimated to friends, with her sly, our-love-life-is-groovy smile, that there would be times when that Webcam would have to be turned off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Gore has said he would consider putting a 24-hour-a-day Webcam, or Alcam, in the Oval Office.</p>
        <p>Tipper, of course, immediately intimated to friends, with her sly, our-love-life-is-groovy smile, that there would be times when that Webcam would have to be turned off.</p>
        <p>But this just proves you can never get a Webcam where you want one.</p>
        <p>I have zero desire to see President Gore round the clock, putting comely interns to sleep with charts and lectures on gaseous reduction.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, I would have loved to have a Webcam trained on Bill Clinton during the debates.</p>
        <p>I wonder if the president, who is a pariah in his own vice president's campaign, chewed on his cigar and shouted comebacks at the screen as the Three Faces of Al flickered.</p>
        <p>What an exquisite dilemma for a man who always wants things both ways! He needs his partner to excel so that Al can defeat W. and secure Mr. Clinton's legacy. But if Mr. Gore falls short, Mr. Clinton can comfort himself with the belief that ''if only I were out there, the election would be over. I'm still the best. If you find a turtle on a fencepost, it didn't get there by accident.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, some close to him say, is bewildered and hurt by the way Mr. Gore keeps erasing him from his  White House photo album. The president thinks Mr. Gore should run as his vice president, bragging on their record of economic growth, welfare reform and fiscal (if not personal) discipline.</p>
        <p>I would much rather have the master pol's debate commentary than those ''doofus-heavy focus groups assembled by the networks,'' as The Washington Post's TV critic Tom Shales calls them, which deemed the governor more specific and straightforward than the vice president even when W. was offering generic and incoherent bromides.</p>
        <p>As W. bit the inside of his lip and looked hunched, vacant and played-out, you just had an image of a head full of sawdust as he sniffled, snorted and sifted through his brain trying to remember if the situation called for ''I trust people, not government'' or ''Leave no child behind'' or ''The partisan bickering has to stop'' or ''Governors lead. That's what we do.''</p>
        <p>In a 1996 debate with Bob Dole, Mr. Clinton used sidling and staring to intimidate his rival. Mr. Gore attempted the same maneuver Tuesday. Lithe as a lawn mower, subtle as a subpoena, Alpha Al clomped right up beside Mr. Bush, who rewarded him with a disdainful double take that brought chuckles from the crowd. Mr. Gore kept right on striding up to the crowd, like an Olympic diver about to do a three-and-a-half-somersault pike.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's points often had a subtext of tattling. He said his four children had come to the debate. (W.'s didn't, nyah, nyah!) He said he had gone to Vietnam, even though there were ''fancy ways to get out of going.'' (W. got a cushy spot in the Texas Air National Guard, nyah, nyah!) He had ''not spent the last quarter-century in pursuit of personal wealth.'' (W. was using family connections to get rich, nyah, nyah!)</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's erratic and sometimes arrogant debate demeanor, which has caused some Gore focus groups to violently turn on the Democratic nominee, has surely confirmed Mr. Clinton's belief, which he once confided to a friend, that Al would have been happier in academia.</p>
        <p>After being slighted by the Gorites, the president would certainly be gratified to see them come beg him for an 11th-hour rescue -- to do last-minute stumping with minorities and in hard-fought states.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore, who has not appeared publicly with the president since their awkward passing of the torch in Monroe, Mich., two months ago, resents Mr. Clinton so much he might rather lose than reattach himself. He has paid all the dues he intends to. He frets over polls that show lingering anger at Mr. Clinton that might drag him down.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore cannot even bring himself to use the word ''Clinton.'' In the debate, he was boasting of his role in planning ''the president's'' summit meeting in the Mideast. He caught himself using the ''P'' word and you could practically hear the klaxon go off as he switched to praising the great job of ''our country's team.''</p>
        <p>Can you imagine what the puffy-eyed Mr. Clinton, back (via a fund-raiser and a golf banquet) from 20 meetings that consumed 24 of 28 hours at an Egyptian golf resort where he did not even get to golf, must have howled at the TV at that point?</p>
        <p>''Our TEAM? Oh, man, that is wrooong.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
