<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Confused Account Is Meant To Aid Doctor in Murder Case</title>
    <meta content="19DOCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/nyregion/19DOCT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finkelstein, Katherine E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Joel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bierenbaum, Robert (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katz-Bierenbaum, Gail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E1DD123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Confused Account Is Meant To Aid Doctor in Murder Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHERINE E. FINKELSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finkelstein, Katherine E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joel Davis, sole defense witness in trial of Doctor Robert Bierenbaum, charged with killing his wife, struggles to recall size and shape of woman he had gazed at in Manhattan bagel store 15 years ago, on day Gail Katz-Bierenbaum disappeared; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sole defense witness in the trial of a doctor charged with killing his wife struggled yesterday to recall the size and shape of the woman he had gazed at in a Manhattan bagel store 15 years ago, on the day the wife disappeared.</p>
        <p>The witness, Joel Davis, 60, testified in State Supreme Court in Manhattan that several weeks after noting the tanned, ''well-developed'' woman in the store, he saw what appeared to be her photograph on a missing persons flier and called the police.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sole defense witness in the trial of a doctor charged with killing his wife struggled yesterday to recall the size and shape of the woman he had gazed at in a Manhattan bagel store 15 years ago, on the day the wife disappeared.</p>
        <p>The witness, Joel Davis, 60, testified in State Supreme Court in Manhattan that several weeks after noting the tanned, ''well-developed'' woman in the store, he saw what appeared to be her photograph on a missing persons flier and called the police.</p>
        <p>This testimony was intended to give jurors the reasonable doubt needed to acquit Dr. Robert Bierenbaum, a plastic surgeon accused of murdering his 29-year-old wife in 1985. If the woman in line at an H &amp; H bagel store that afternoon was indeed his wife, Gail Katz-Bierenbaum, then her husband could not have killed her that morning at home and dumped her body into the ocean, as prosecutors have alleged.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Davis, a retired printer, struggled to recall the charms of the woman he had seen, and to recount the description he had given detectives more than a decade ago, his confusion left jury members laughing and shaking their heads.</p>
        <p>First, on cross-examination, Mr. Davis recalled the woman dressed in pink shorts and a loose white T-shirt as petite and large-busted, with an ''excellent, great body.''</p>
        <p>However, the assistant district attorney, Stephen Saracco, then read aloud a statement that Mr. Davis gave to an investigator in 1985, saying that as a connoisseur of women's bodies, he had noticed that ''This broad was perfect.'' He had added, ''She was tall, she was statuesque, she was gorgeous.''</p>
        <p>When asked about this discrepancy yesterday, Mr. Davis sputtered, ''After 15 years, I confused her with my ex-wife's body, with my friend's ex-sister-in-law's body.'' Even the judge, Leslie Crocker Snyder,  worked to suppress a smile.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis's troubles on the stand seemed to begin the moment Mr. Saracco began his cross-examination. Mr. Davis described waiting in line at the bagel store with his girlfriend at the time, a woman he said he had been dating for several months. But Mr. Davis said he could not recall the last name of that girlfriend, with whom he said he had had a two-year relationship and later a friendship.</p>
        <p>He had no recollection of what the woman's friend looked like, he said, but the patterned T-shirt of the other woman, who he said resembled Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum, caught his attention. ''That's what turned me on,'' he said, describing how he stared at her.</p>
        <p>''Your girlfriend didn't mind this at all,'' Justice Snyder asked as the jury laughed. Mr. Davis responded, ''I'm a man.''</p>
        <p>But his impression of the attractive stranger may not have been as deeply etched in Mr. Davis's memory as defense lawyers had hoped. Question by question, Mr. Saracco amassed contradictions and apparant gaps in Mr. Davis's memory.</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis had said under direct questioning that he never saw the back of the woman's shirt. Mr. Saracco asked him why he had previously told prosecutors that he had seen words on the back of the shirt.</p>
        <p>''Maybe it's the way you asked the question,'' Mr. Davis responded.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Saracco said the question had been simple and straightforward: ''Did you see the back of her T-shirt?''</p>
        <p>At almost every turn, Mr. Davis blamed confusion and the passage of time for his difficulties. He asserted, nonetheless, that the woman he had seen in the bagel store was pictured on the missing persons flier.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors then called as a rebuttal witness Detective Thomas O'Malley, who was working for the Police Department's Missing Persons Squad when Mr. Davis called them. Mr. Saracco asked the detective whether Mr. Davis had ever told him that he was positive that Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum was the woman he saw in the bagel store. Detective O'Malley replied ''No.''</p>
        <p>But perhaps the strongest contradiction of Mr. Davis's testimony was offered by the final rebuttal witness, Alayne Katz, the missing woman's sister. She testified that her sister, who was under 5 feet 3 inches and weighed less than 110 pounds, wore an A-cup bra. To support their contention that she was not ''well developed,'' as Mr. Davis had said, prosecutors showed a photograph of Ms. Katz-Bierenbaum on a beach in the Caribbean, wearing a bikini top.</p>
        <p>With this photograph entered into evidence, both sides rested in the largely circumstantial case, notable for having no body or any forensic evidence. Closing arguments were scheduled for Monday. Dr. Bierenbaum's lawyer, Scott H. Greenfield, then gestured to his client, who appeared dejected, to keep his chin up.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
