<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doing the Math Behind Candidates' Debate Claims</title>
    <meta content="Y19POL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/politics/19POLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CHECKING THE FACTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Homeland Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFDD123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doing the Math Behind Candidates' Debate Claims</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Transcripts of three presidential debates show several instances in which Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush made points through selective use of facts, fudging of details and so-called fuzzy math; examination of their positions on Bush's tax plan, on Bush's plan to partly privatize Social Security system, on both candidates' spending plans, and on dissension over Medicare (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In their three debates, Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore have waded deep into the thickets of tax policy, Social Security and the budget surplus. The numbers they have thrown around have often been confusing and conflicting -- and sometimes wrong.</p>
        <p>An examination of the transcripts of the three debates shows several instances in which the candidates made their points through the selective use of facts, fudging of details and, yes, fuzzy math.</p>
        <p>Argument Over the Rich</p>
        <p>In the debate on Tuesday, Mr. Gore used the audience to illustrate his argument that Mr. Bush's tax plan favors the rich.</p>
        <p>If all 130 audience members were ''dead on in the middle of the middle class,'' he said, their combined tax cuts under the Bush plan would be less than the cut enjoyed by ''just one member'' of the wealthiest one percent of taxpayers, which he defined as people making more than $330,000 a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's assertion was misleading, if not wrong.</p>
        <p>In assessing the Bush plan, the Gore campaign relies on an analysis by Citizens for Tax Justice, a liberal-leaning research group that uses a well-respected computer model. The group defined the top one percent as as people who make $319,000 or more, with the average being $915,000. The average annual tax cut for members of that group under the Bush plan would be $46,072, Citizens for Tax Justice said.</p>
        <p>There are a number of credible definitions of middle class. In this case the Gore campaign relied on one at the low end of the spectrum -- a range of $24,400 to $39,300 per household, with an average of $31,000, which Citizens for Tax Justice described as the middle 20 percent of incomes for tax purposes.</p>
        <p>The average tax cut for that group would be $453 under the Bush plan, the group said. Multiplied times 130, the total is $58,890 -- $12,818 more than the average tax cut for the top one percent. (The vice president's example would have worked only if there were no more than 101 people in the audience.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore seemed to imply in the debate that his assertion applied to anyone making more than $330,000 a year. Asked to explain Mr. Gore's statement, campaign aides said he had in mind someone making $1 million a year.</p>
        <p>Even at that income level, the Gore campaign had to compare apples and oranges to make the math work. It used the Citizens for Tax Justice figures for the middle income tax cut, but estimated the tax cut for a $1 million earner by combining figures from The Wall Street Journal's online tax calculator and Citizens for Tax Justice.</p>
        <p>Discord on Low Earners</p>
        <p>In the second presidential debate last week, Mr. Bush said that ''most of the tax reductions'' in his plan would ''go to the people at the bottom end of the economic ladder.''</p>
        <p>He was wrong.</p>
        <p>In assessing his plan's effect on different income groups, Mr. Bush relies on an analysis by the nonpartisan staff of Congress's Joint Committee on Taxation.</p>
        <p>The analysis shows that in 2005, after the Bush plan is fully phased in, it would reduce taxes on households making $200,000 or more by $32.2 billion, or 26.8 percent of the total tax cut in that year of $120.1 billion.</p>
        <p>Households making less than $40,000 would receive $12.3 billion in tax cuts in 2005, the analysis said, or 10.2 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the analysis does not consider Mr. Bush's proposal to repeal the federal estate tax. Economists differ about how much of the benefits of an estate tax repeal would go to the wealthy, but there is no disagreement that they would reap most of the benefit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has said in all the debates that his plan would require people at upper-income levels to pay a greater share of federal income taxes.</p>
        <p>The Joint Committee on Taxation's analysis shows that households making $200,000 or more in 2005 would pay 27.4 percent of total federal income taxes under Mr. Bush's plan, just as they do now. Households making $100,000 or more would see their share of the total income tax bill tick up to 25.2 percent, from 25.1 percent under current law. The calculations do not consider the effects of the estate tax, which would benefit people at upper-income levels the most.</p>
        <p>Social Security Conflict</p>
        <p>In the debate on Tuesday, Mr. Gore said that Mr. Bush intended to take $1 trillion out of the Social Security trust fund over the next decade to establish private investment accounts within the retirement system. The vice president said that in doing so, Mr. Bush had promised the same money twice -- once for the private accounts and once to pay benefits to retirees -- and that he would have to break one of those promises.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was right to say that Mr. Bush's Social Security plan will require $1 trillion to get started, and the governor acknowledged as much. Mr. Gore was also right that the money would come out of Social Security payroll taxes.</p>
        <p>But the vice president was on shakier ground in suggesting that putting $1 trillion into private accounts would leave Social Security $1 trillion short of what it needs to pay in benefits.</p>
        <p>Social Security is currently taking in more money from payroll taxes than it needs to pay in benefits to current retirees. That surplus is projected at nearly $2.4 trillion over the next decade, and the system will probably run surpluses until around 2015, when it will begin running huge deficits. Mr. Bush's $1 trillion would come from the Social Security surplus.</p>
        <p>Both candidates and their parties have agreed that the Social Security surplus should go only to shoring up the retirement system or paying down the national debt. If the money is not used to overhaul Social Security, it would go automatically to debt reduction -- not to paying benefits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has a point in this sense: It is possible to think of debt reduction as a way of saving for the day when Social Security will need to call on general tax revenues to help pay for benefits.</p>
        <p>To the extent that Mr. Bush's plan would leave less money for debt reduction, the government might find it harder, or at least more expensive, to come up with the money needed for Social Security benefits in the long run.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said that under Mr. Bush's proposal, Social Security would be bankrupt in 20 years. If nothing is done, Social Security will have run through its trust fund -- promises by the government to pay back to itself the Social Security surpluses that over the years have gone to government spending and tax cuts -- by 2037. Using $1 trillion of the surplus for private accounts would move that date up by around 15 years.</p>
        <p>But in neither case would Social Security be bankrupt except in the most technical sense. Even if nothing is done to help the system, Social Security will be able to pay more than 70 percent of promised benefits indefinitely.</p>
        <p>Discord Over Spending</p>
        <p>Starting in the first debate, Mr. Bush said Mr. Gore was a big spender -- bigger than any of the three previous Democratic presidential candidates -- whose proposals would bust the budget. And he said electing Mr. Gore would mean the return of big government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's budget has less of a buffer than Mr. Gore's does. By Mr. Bush's own accounting, his budget would use all but $265 billion of the surplus, and that is without paying for some of his campaign promises, like an expanded national missile defense system. Mr. Gore says he would set aside $660 billion of the surplus for a reserve fund and higher levels of debt reduction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said Mr. Gore is proposing three times as much spending as President Clinton did when he was running in 1992.</p>
        <p>That assertion rests on an analysis by a conservative research group, the National Taxpayers Union, which concluded that Mr. Gore's spending would total $2.9 trillion in the next decade. The Gore campaign says it would spend a little over $1 trillion and offer tax breaks of less than $500 billion. Mr. Clinton's 1992 proposals were made a time of record budget deficits; Mr. Gore's were made at a time of large and growing surpluses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said he had helped slim down the federal bureaucracy through his work on the administration's Reinventing Government initiative. Since 1992, the civilian government work force has fallen by 400,000 people, to 1.82 million, although nearly three-quarters of the reduction has been the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>Some analysts measure the size of government by looking at total spending relative to the size of the economy. By that measure, government outlays have declined steadily in recent years, to 18.7 percent of gross domestic product this year. Mr. Gore said his plan would push that figure down to 17 percent by 2008.</p>
        <p>Medicare Dissension</p>
        <p>In the first debate, Mr. Gore said Mr. Bush is refusing to treat surplus Medicare revenues in the same way that the two parties have agreed to treat the surpluses in Social Security -- by putting them in a ''lockbox,'' where they would be unavailable to either party for new spending or tax cuts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was largely correct.</p>
        <p>The vice president has proposed that the entire Medicare surplus of $360 billion over the next decade go to debt reduction. Mr. Bush needs that same money in his budget to pay for his $1.3 trillion tax cut and his spending initiatives. Without the Medicare surplus, Mr. Bush's budget would be in the red by $95 billion.</p>
        <p>There is a loophole available to Mr. Bush. Most lockbox proposals allow the money to be used for Medicare reform, and Mr. Bush has nearly $200 billion in his budget for Medicare-related proposals, including the establishment of a prescription drug benefit for retirees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In their three debates, Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore have waded deep into the thickets of tax policy, Social Security and the budget surplus. The numbers they have thrown around have often been confusing and conflicting -- and sometimes wrong.</p>
        <p>An examination of the transcripts of the three debates shows several instances in which the candidates made their points through the selective use of facts, fudging of details and, yes, fuzzy math.</p>
        <p>Argument Over the Rich</p>
        <p>In the debate on Tuesday, Mr. Gore used the audience to illustrate his argument that Mr. Bush's tax plan favors the rich.</p>
        <p>If all 130 audience members were ''dead on in the middle of the middle class,'' he said, their combined tax cuts under the Bush plan would be less than the cut enjoyed by ''just one member'' of the wealthiest one percent of taxpayers, which he defined as people making more than $330,000 a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's assertion was misleading, if not wrong.</p>
        <p>In assessing the Bush plan, the Gore campaign relies on an analysis by Citizens for Tax Justice, a liberal-leaning research group that uses a well-respected computer model. The group defined the top one percent as as people who make $319,000 or more, with the average being $915,000. The average annual tax cut for members of that group under the Bush plan would be $46,072, Citizens for Tax Justice said.</p>
        <p>There are a number of credible definitions of middle class. In this case the Gore campaign relied on one at the low end of the spectrum -- a range of $24,400 to $39,300 per household, with an average of $31,000, which Citizens for Tax Justice described as the middle 20 percent of incomes for tax purposes.</p>
        <p>The average tax cut for that group would be $453 under the Bush plan, the group said. Multiplied times 130, the total is $58,890 -- $12,818 more than the average tax cut for the top one percent. (The vice president's example would have worked only if there were no more than 101 people in the audience.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore seemed to imply in the debate that his assertion applied to anyone making more than $330,000 a year. Asked to explain Mr. Gore's statement, campaign aides said he had in mind someone making $1 million a year.</p>
        <p>Even at that income level, the Gore campaign had to compare apples and oranges to make the math work. It used the Citizens for Tax Justice figures for the middle income tax cut, but estimated the tax cut for a $1 million earner by combining figures from The Wall Street Journal's online tax calculator and Citizens for Tax Justice.</p>
        <p>Discord on Low Earners</p>
        <p>In the second presidential debate last week, Mr. Bush said that ''most of the tax reductions'' in his plan would ''go to the people at the bottom end of the economic ladder.''</p>
        <p>He was wrong.</p>
        <p>In assessing his plan's effect on different income groups, Mr. Bush relies on an analysis by the nonpartisan staff of Congress's Joint Committee on Taxation.</p>
        <p>The analysis shows that in 2005, after the Bush plan is fully phased in, it would reduce taxes on households making $200,000 or more by $32.2 billion, or 26.8 percent of the total tax cut in that year of $120.1 billion.</p>
        <p>Households making less than $40,000 would receive $12.3 billion in tax cuts in 2005, the analysis said, or 10.2 percent of the total.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the analysis does not consider Mr. Bush's proposal to repeal the federal estate tax. Economists differ about how much of the benefits of an estate tax repeal would go to the wealthy, but there is no disagreement that they would reap most of the benefit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has said in all the debates that his plan would require people at upper-income levels to pay a greater share of federal income taxes.</p>
        <p>The Joint Committee on Taxation's analysis shows that households making $200,000 or more in 2005 would pay 27.4 percent of total federal income taxes under Mr. Bush's plan, just as they do now. Households making $100,000 or more would see their share of the total income tax bill tick up to 25.2 percent, from 25.1 percent under current law. The calculations do not consider the effects of the estate tax, which would benefit people at upper-income levels the most.</p>
        <p>Social Security Conflict</p>
        <p>In the debate on Tuesday, Mr. Gore said that Mr. Bush intended to take $1 trillion out of the Social Security trust fund over the next decade to establish private investment accounts within the retirement system. The vice president said that in doing so, Mr. Bush had promised the same money twice -- once for the private accounts and once to pay benefits to retirees -- and that he would have to break one of those promises.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was right to say that Mr. Bush's Social Security plan will require $1 trillion to get started, and the governor acknowledged as much. Mr. Gore was also right that the money would come out of Social Security payroll taxes.</p>
        <p>But the vice president was on shakier ground in suggesting that putting $1 trillion into private accounts would leave Social Security $1 trillion short of what it needs to pay in benefits.</p>
        <p>Social Security is currently taking in more money from payroll taxes than it needs to pay in benefits to current retirees. That surplus is projected at nearly $2.4 trillion over the next decade, and the system will probably run surpluses until around 2015, when it will begin running huge deficits. Mr. Bush's $1 trillion would come from the Social Security surplus.</p>
        <p>Both candidates and their parties have agreed that the Social Security surplus should go only to shoring up the retirement system or paying down the national debt. If the money is not used to overhaul Social Security, it would go automatically to debt reduction -- not to paying benefits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has a point in this sense: It is possible to think of debt reduction as a way of saving for the day when Social Security will need to call on general tax revenues to help pay for benefits.</p>
        <p>To the extent that Mr. Bush's plan would leave less money for debt reduction, the government might find it harder, or at least more expensive, to come up with the money needed for Social Security benefits in the long run.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said that under Mr. Bush's proposal, Social Security would be bankrupt in 20 years. If nothing is done, Social Security will have run through its trust fund -- promises by the government to pay back to itself the Social Security surpluses that over the years have gone to government spending and tax cuts -- by 2037. Using $1 trillion of the surplus for private accounts would move that date up by around 15 years.</p>
        <p>But in neither case would Social Security be bankrupt except in the most technical sense. Even if nothing is done to help the system, Social Security will be able to pay more than 70 percent of promised benefits indefinitely.</p>
        <p>Discord Over Spending</p>
        <p>Starting in the first debate, Mr. Bush said Mr. Gore was a big spender -- bigger than any of the three previous Democratic presidential candidates -- whose proposals would bust the budget. And he said electing Mr. Gore would mean the return of big government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's budget has less of a buffer than Mr. Gore's does. By Mr. Bush's own accounting, his budget would use all but $265 billion of the surplus, and that is without paying for some of his campaign promises, like an expanded national missile defense system. Mr. Gore says he would set aside $660 billion of the surplus for a reserve fund and higher levels of debt reduction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said Mr. Gore is proposing three times as much spending as President Clinton did when he was running in 1992.</p>
        <p>That assertion rests on an analysis by a conservative research group, the National Taxpayers Union, which concluded that Mr. Gore's spending would total $2.9 trillion in the next decade. The Gore campaign says it would spend a little over $1 trillion and offer tax breaks of less than $500 billion. Mr. Clinton's 1992 proposals were made a time of record budget deficits; Mr. Gore's were made at a time of large and growing surpluses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said he had helped slim down the federal bureaucracy through his work on the administration's Reinventing Government initiative. Since 1992, the civilian government work force has fallen by 400,000 people, to 1.82 million, although nearly three-quarters of the reduction has been the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>Some analysts measure the size of government by looking at total spending relative to the size of the economy. By that measure, government outlays have declined steadily in recent years, to 18.7 percent of gross domestic product this year. Mr. Gore said his plan would push that figure down to 17 percent by 2008.</p>
        <p>Medicare Dissension</p>
        <p>In the first debate, Mr. Gore said Mr. Bush is refusing to treat surplus Medicare revenues in the same way that the two parties have agreed to treat the surpluses in Social Security -- by putting them in a ''lockbox,'' where they would be unavailable to either party for new spending or tax cuts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was largely correct.</p>
        <p>The vice president has proposed that the entire Medicare surplus of $360 billion over the next decade go to debt reduction. Mr. Bush needs that same money in his budget to pay for his $1.3 trillion tax cut and his spending initiatives. Without the Medicare surplus, Mr. Bush's budget would be in the red by $95 billion.</p>
        <p>There is a loophole available to Mr. Bush. Most lockbox proposals allow the money to be used for Medicare reform, and Mr. Bush has nearly $200 billion in his budget for Medicare-related proposals, including the establishment of a prescription drug benefit for retirees.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: CHECKING THE FACTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
