<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; The Old Dodger Dread Resurfaces</title>
    <meta content="19VECS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/sports/19VECS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240050"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Dodgers (Defunct Team)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EFDC123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; The Old Dodger Dread Resurfaces</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article recalls past World Series between New York Yankees and Brooklyn Dodgers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DREAD and foreboding fill the air. They really are going to play this Subway Series, aren't they?</p>
        <p>But why this sudden gloom, this morbid sense that things are not right in the universe?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DREAD and foreboding fill the air. They really are going to play this Subway Series, aren't they?</p>
        <p>But why this sudden gloom, this morbid sense that things are not right in the universe?</p>
        <p>At first, I thought it was pure animal fear on my part. I had this awful premonition of vigilante mobs running amok in New York, speaking gibberish, frightening the populace.</p>
        <p>And that was just the news media.</p>
        <p>But, no, there was another reason I did not want a Subway Series in my hometown.</p>
        <p>''Cool it,'' younger colleagues told me. ''It's going to be an event of a lifetime. Besides, you had a bunch of Subway Series when you were a kid. Let the rest of us have one.''</p>
        <p>Then I plumbed the depths of my emotions, and discovered the source of my pain. For weeks, I have been having this recurrent nightmare of a skinny man with a No. 1 on his back making a swooping catch of a wayward pop fly. Something bad is about to happen all over again.</p>
        <p>You see, Doctor, I carry around in my twitchy subconscious a sports version of post-trauma depression. I do not want to relive the experience all over again. I do not want to root.</p>
        <p>Mayors can root. There was Rudolph W. Giuliani in the Yankee clubhouse on Tuesday night (enduring a Champagne shower from his own male progeny, young Andrew) and proclaiming that while he is Mayor to all New York baseball teams, he could not help rooting for his childhood team, and therefore was picking the Yankees to win in six games.</p>
        <p>Rooting is totally unprofessional from a sports columnist. Besides, how could anybody root against these Yankees of Bernie and El Duque and Paulie and other such compelling dudes? However, I have discovered, to my chagrin, that the reason I fear a Subway Series is that in my wayward youth I rooted for a team from Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>The Dodgers were a wonderful team. They were the first major-league team to employ African-American players. They were a grand collection of individuals. They resided in a teeming little bandbox often chock-full of eccentrics. And they could play.</p>
        <p>They could play in April. They could play in May. They could play in June. They could play in July. They could play in August. They could play in September. In fact, they were so skilled in the warmer months that Roger Kahn wrote one of the classic sports books called ''The Boys of Summer.''</p>
        <p>It was autumn that was the problem. When I was a lad, terrible things happened to the Brooklyn Dodgers in October. These flashbacks keep invading my brain. I see a relief pitcher named Joe Page hopping over the bullpen fence and throwing five -- five! -- scoreless innings in the seventh game of the 1947 World Series.</p>
        <p>I see Tommy Henrich slugging a home run off Don Newcombe to end the first game of the 1949 World Series. Nearly half a century later, Steve Jacobson, that exceptional sports columnist for Newsday, lamented to Henrich that he had been unable to study because of the home run.</p>
        <p>''Tough,'' Henrich retorted. ''What were you going to be, a doctor?''</p>
        <p>Our lives were affected by these awful events. Dodgers fans remember Bobby Thomson's homer that won the 1951 playoff while Giants fans still mourn the fortuitous rainout that allowed the Yankees to regroup during the World Series. In 1952, there was Billy Martin's dashing catch of Jackie Robinson's pop-up. The same scrawny second baseman, the aforementioned No. 1, batted .500 against the Dodgers in 1953. In 1955, the Dodgers temporarily got things right, but in 1956, Yogi Berra hit three homers off Newcombe, and things were pretty much back to normal.</p>
        <p>That is ancient history, but it lives today, like a Love Canal with a 1,000-year life. The Mets are the spiritual heirs of the Dodgers and the Giants. There are certain ions spinning around in the atmosphere. We are what we eat. Karma returns.</p>
        <p>The Yankees of old were always under a dark cloud, just like this aging lot. Poor old DiMaggio had a bad heel, or star-crossed Mantle had bad knees, or some other Yankee star had the chilblains. Whatever. The real damage always came from the Yankees you were not watching closely, the Martins and the Mizes, the Kuckses and the Kuzavas.</p>
        <p>It's all coming back to me now, doctor. The cold sweats. On Tuesday night, with the Yankees in trouble, somebody hit a grounder up the middle. The ball rolled up Derek Jeter's arm, a total clown play, the kind that could wreck an entire season for any other franchise, but instead the ball floated directly to Luis Sojo, the well-traveled Yankee, now filling in admirably on defense for the befuddled Chuck Knoblauch.</p>
        <p>And there, doctor, just as it recurs in my haunted sleep cycles, was Luis Sojo, in the right place at the right time, just like Billy Martin in the bad old days, hauling it in for the force play that essentially killed the rally. Those things were always happening to my Dodgers, doctor. I want to know why.</p>
        <p>The Mets just might be the best team in baseball right now. They can take care of themselves. But this Subway Series raises old psychic wounds. We are reminded of Yankee power and Yankee pride and Yankee ingenuity and, most of all, we are reminded of Yankee luck. It's not that I root, doctor, but this Subway Series fills me with fear and trembling.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
