<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>4 Companies Emerge in Bid To Privatize Worst Schools</title>
    <meta content="19SCHO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/nyregion/19SCHO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Edison Schools</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mosaica Education Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Victory Schools Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Advantage Schools Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Board of Education (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E1DE123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="436" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>4 Companies Emerge in Bid To Privatize Worst Schools</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Board of Education staff members have narrowed list of candidates to privately manage some of New York City's worst-performing schools to four companies: Edison Schools, Mosaica Education, Victory Schools and Advantage Schools (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Board of Education staff members have narrowed the list of candidates to privately manage some of New York City's worst-performing schools to four companies, education officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The for-profit companies -- Edison Schools, Mosaica Education and Victory Schools, all of New York, and Advantage Schools of Boston -- were invited to meet with board officials in recent weeks to discuss their proposals, said the officials, who spoke only on the condition of anonymity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Board of Education staff members have narrowed the list of candidates to privately manage some of New York City's worst-performing schools to four companies, education officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The for-profit companies -- Edison Schools, Mosaica Education and Victory Schools, all of New York, and Advantage Schools of Boston -- were invited to meet with board officials in recent weeks to discuss their proposals, said the officials, who spoke only on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>The review is part of a privatization plan announced by Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy in July that would convert several low-performing public schools to charter schools and allow them to be managed by private companies. Within a month, board officials are expected to make a recommendation about which companies and how many schools will participate in the first year of the program, which is scheduled to begin in the fall of 2001.</p>
        <p>Board officials said in July that the program was most likely to focus on 5 to 7 schools initially but could include as many as 20 schools. Most of the 14 companies that submitted proposals in August applied to manage a small number of schools, but Edison Schools presented a plan to oversee 45 schools by the fall of 2003.</p>
        <p>The interviews with the four companies deemed to be finalists followed visits by board officials to schools managed by the companies. Two other applicants -- Boys Harbor and Clearpool, both nonprofit organizations based in New York -- received site visits from board officials but were not asked to participate in the later interviews, officials said.</p>
        <p>That could mean that the nonprofit agencies are no longer being considered for the plan's first year, a decision that could draw opposition from education officials or board members who are skeptical about the entry of for-profit companies into public education.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy said yesterday, however, that he had not yet excluded any candidates from the process. He declined to comment on the number or identity of the finalists in the process.</p>
        <p>The schools to be included in the plan will be drawn from the roughly 50 struggling schools that are both on the state's list of ''schools under registration review'' and part of the special Chancellor's District.</p>
        <p>Before a school can be converted to a charter school, a move freeing it from many state and local regulations, the change must be approved by the parents of more than 50 percent of the children in the school.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
