<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Five Years Later, A Female Kicker's Memorable Victory</title>
    <meta content="19KICK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/sports/19KICK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Duke University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipsyte, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mercer, Heather Sue</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DE123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Five Years Later, A Female Kicker's Memorable Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipsyte, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Greensboro, NC, jury awarding field goal kicker Heather Sue Mercer $2 million after finding that Duke University has discriminated against her on basis of sex by cutting her from football team; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a cold afternoon in the fall of 1992, Heather Sue Mercer persuaded her father to accompany her to a field near their Westchester County home and hold a toy football on the ground while she practiced place-kicking. She had seen her high school team's kicker in action and, characteristically, thought it looked like fun and something she could do. A 16-year-old junior, she was a swimmer, diver, fencer, and played softball, basketball and varsity soccer, in which she was known for her strong legs.</p>
        <p>''When she was little she wanted to be a quarterback,'' said Robert Mercer, a computer programmer who had been in the band and the chess club in high school. ''I talked her out of that. I thought she'd get this kicking out of her system.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a cold afternoon in the fall of 1992, Heather Sue Mercer persuaded her father to accompany her to a field near their Westchester County home and hold a toy football on the ground while she practiced place-kicking. She had seen her high school team's kicker in action and, characteristically, thought it looked like fun and something she could do. A 16-year-old junior, she was a swimmer, diver, fencer, and played softball, basketball and varsity soccer, in which she was known for her strong legs.</p>
        <p>''When she was little she wanted to be a quarterback,'' said Robert Mercer, a computer programmer who had been in the band and the chess club in high school. ''I talked her out of that. I thought she'd get this kicking out of her system.''</p>
        <p>The ball was about two-thirds the size of a regulation football, and much harder. From about 20 yards away, with the sweeping motion of a sideways soccer kick, Heather Sue blasted it through the goal posts. Robert Mercer says he was astonished. His daughter remembers thinking it was even more fun than it had looked. She decided to go out for the team, unknowingly setting in motion a joyous and painful eight-year drive toward a memorable victory in the campaign for equality in sports.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 12, an eight-person jury in Greensboro, N.C., found that Duke University had discriminated against Mercer on the basis of sex. Because the jury believed that senior administrators had known about the discrimination and responded with indifference, it awarded Mercer $2 million dollars in punitive damages. The university will appeal. A spokesman would make no further comment on the record.</p>
        <p>Since Mercer's lawsuit was announced three years ago, she has been variously called a hero for women's rights and a travesty. After the verdict, sports radio was far rougher. The 5-foot-9-inch, 135-pound Mercer, now 24, firmly rejects all labels except jock.</p>
        <p>''I didn't go out for my high school team to prove that women could do it,'' she said in Manhattan Monday night in her first formal interview since the decision. ''I loved it. Such a great experience. You never have to look up to see if you have a good ball. You feel it in the impact against your foot, the snap of your leg, you hear it in the sound, that boom, and you know from the balance of your body in the follow-through.''</p>
        <p>Talking about kicking, she became animated; her light blue eyes seemed to shine. But her lips tightened and her eyelids dropped as she talked about the years at Duke when she tried to prove she was as much a football player as any of the 100-odd members of the squad.</p>
        <p>''If there was a medical treatment to erase those four years, I'd be the first in line,'' she said. ''It was grim. You couldn't pay me to ever set foot again on the Duke campus.''</p>
        <p>Why not transfer?</p>
        <p>''That would be like quitting,'' she said. ''Football players suck it up. You don't give up on the hand you've been dealt.''</p>
        <p>That hand looked good at Yorktown High School after Coach Ron Santavicca, who testified on her behalf, watched her kick 40-yard field goals with a regulation football. He suggested she attend a summer kicking school to refine her powerful but raw form, then try out for his team. She was the starting place-kicker her senior year on a team that won a state championship. She was all-state third team.</p>
        <p>''I loved the camaraderie in football; it is different from women,'' she said. ''Men are straight out. Nothing festers; they say what they think. If two guys room together and one of them is a slob, leaves dishes in the sink, the other one will say so flat out. If it was two women, she'd grit her teeth and wait it out.</p>
        <p>''I tried to tread lightly, to contribute to the team and not take away from anybody's experience. Once they saw I didn't want to be a media darling -- I didn't do many interviews, no TV, I don't even keep a scrapbook -- and that I did everything they did, weights, drills, I learned to block and tackle, the option pass, once they knew me they accepted me. I wasn't a girl, I wasn't a priss, I was No. 10.''</p>
        <p>Although both of her older sisters urged her to follow them to Stanford, she had set her mind on Duke. She was interested in biomedical engineering and was considering a career designing prosthetic devices. She shook her head remembering how she ''screamed and danced around the house like a maniac'' when her letter of acceptance arrived from Duke.</p>
        <p>That dealt hand still seemed promising in 1994-95, her first year at Duke. Coach Fred Goldsmith allowed her to try out and after she kicked the winning field goal in the spring intrasquad game, he announced that she was on the team. Her name appeared in the media guide and on the official roster sent to the National Collegiate Athletic Association.</p>
        <p>After another summer kicking camp session, she returned to Duke for her sophomore year in the fall of 1995. She was excluded from preseason practice. She learned she would not be issued a uniform or be allowed to sit on the team bench during games. A new category, ''not on the active roster,'' was created for her. It was a twilight zone.</p>
        <p>When local reporters asked Duke to clarify her status, the sports information department set up a news conference and insisted she attend. But once there she made her own statement. ''I believe,'' she said, ''that if I were a man and had the same kicking skills that I have now, I would be a member of the Duke football team.''</p>
        <p>And then, with the kind of can-do sensibility that college coaches often pay for, she said: ''I will continue to try out for the team. I hope that eventually Coach Goldsmith will come to see me as a possible asset for the team rather than as a problem and a coaching headache.''</p>
        <p>But as Goldsmith later admitted in court, he was embarrassed when rival coaches teased him about having a woman on his team. According to testimony, which he did not deny, he told Mercer to go sit in the stands with her boyfriend, to compete in beauty pageants. She responded by lifting more weights, running more wind sprints, kicking harder.</p>
        <p>She was proud of never throwing up during conditioning drills. She even rooted for her teammates as they ground through a losing season. Goldsmith was fired in 1998, the year Mercer graduated.</p>
        <p>While Duke sources see the case as the fault of an individual coach, not the institution, neither Duke's president, Nannerl O. Keohane, nor the university counsel's office tried to interview Mercer after they learned of a possible Title IX violation.</p>
        <p>How Mercer kept her optimism as her football career was spiraling down is not clear. Sitting in the conference room of a midtown office for more than two hours Monday night while her lawyer, Burton Craige, listened silently over a speakerphone from his office in Raleigh, N.C., Mercer was friendly, open, even chatty, but always behind the athlete's controlled game face. ''I thought if they saw what I could do, they'd change their attitude,'' she said. ''They would see me as an athlete, not a woman. This was just another speed bump. Whatever didn't kill me would make me stronger.''</p>
        <p>Mercer lettered as a varsity fencer, but her other memories of Duke are clouded now. It was grim, but she was determined to make the football team on her own terms. Her mother, Diana, remembers trying to give her ''reality checks'' and becoming ''very angry'' when Heather Sue was depressed. Yet once, at a meeting with Goldsmith, Diana Mercer recalls, Heather Sue put a warning hand on her mother's arm so she wouldn't speak sharply to ''my coach.''</p>
        <p>Mercer now works in the Jersey City office of Charles Schwab as an assistant trader, the only woman on a 10-person ''team.'' She says she loves the fast-paced, win-lose, hurly-burly of the financial world and its male atmosphere. She describes herself as ''an equalist, not a feminist.''</p>
        <p>She has said from the beginning that any money she won would go to a college scholarship fund for female high school place-kickers. It is estimated that some 800 women are playing high school football. Mercer hasn't thought through the details.</p>
        <p>All she knows, she said, is that she is looking for girls ''with spunk and vivacity, who have a need to get out there in the world and won't be intimidated by what society says.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
