<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With the Help of the Series, Giuliani Giddily Finds His Inner 7-Year-Old</title>
    <meta content="19MAYO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/sports/19MAYO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240017"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6DD123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With the Help of the Series, Giuliani Giddily Finds His Inner 7-Year-Old</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani discusses World Series between New York Yankees and New York Mets and how it will boost city's economy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>How much time will Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani devote to the Subway Series during the next week? ''As much as possible,'' the lame-duck mayor and lifelong Yankee fan swiftly replied.</p>
        <p>In the last 48 hours, Mr. Giuliani, the self-anointed first fan, has giddily wrapped himself up in the Subway Series. He sees it as all good things to Rudy: boyhood fantasy, cancer therapy, partisan politics, sound economics and a boost for his dream of ever more baseball stadiums.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>How much time will Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani devote to the Subway Series during the next week? ''As much as possible,'' the lame-duck mayor and lifelong Yankee fan swiftly replied.</p>
        <p>In the last 48 hours, Mr. Giuliani, the self-anointed first fan, has giddily wrapped himself up in the Subway Series. He sees it as all good things to Rudy: boyhood fantasy, cancer therapy, partisan politics, sound economics and a boost for his dream of ever more baseball stadiums.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Giuliani devoted 20 minutes of a 30-minute City Hall news conference to the Yankees, the Mets and insisting that his deputy mayors wear baseball caps. ''Come on, Rudy, put your Met hat on,'' he said to Deputy Mayor Rudy Washington.</p>
        <p>The mayor was predictably bundled up in a Yankee warm-up jacket and a Yankees baseball cap. As a Yankees fan since toddlerhood, he said he had to root for them. Still, he was careful to be flanked by two Met fans, Peter F. Vallone, the City Council speaker, and Claire Shulman, the borough president of Queens.</p>
        <p>''If the Mets win, we lift term limits for the City Council,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''If the Yankees win, we could lift term limits for the mayor.''</p>
        <p>The day before Mr. Giuliani ended a speech about a new cancer project by saying, ''Now I'm going to go back and think about the Yankees, because that's all I can think about today.''</p>
        <p>He cheerfully added that he would tell his prostate cancer doctors ''that this is the best therapy for cancer.''</p>
        <p>''It's absolutely terrific,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani has fallen into similar boyish spells, indulged by his staff, every October since 1995, the first in the Yankees' six straight years in the playoffs. But this time, Mr. Giuliani has seemed to reach new levels of ecstasy as he presides over the first Subway Series of his mayoralty and the first since he was 12. ''You can't believe how long I've been praying for it,'' Mr. Giuliani said.</p>
        <p>With his prayers answered, there was almost no media request the mayor didn't answer.</p>
        <p>He appeared as guest on WFAN, the sports talk radio station, predicting civic calm during the Series, and, while he was at it, second-guessing some of the managerial moves of Lou Piniella, the manager of the vanquished Seattle Mariners.</p>
        <p>He later offered up the Top 10 List on ''The Late Show With David Letterman,'' noting that, in addition to the many personal benefits the Subway Series held for him, it also might help the rest of the city get over the closing of ''Cats.''</p>
        <p>As in past years, Mr. Giuliani's first baseball impulse in the last two days has been to look back nostalgically at his youth. ''For me, this is like reliving my childhood,'' he said. ''Literally and figuratively. I grew up in Brooklyn, a Yankee fan, in the early 1950's.'' Although Mr. Giuliani moved to Long Island at 7, a fact he mentions less frequently, he did take his love of the Yankees with him.</p>
        <p>The mayor has also seized on the Series as good political news. Although Mr. Giuliani isn't running for anything, he took the opportunity yesterday to swing away at Hillary Rodham Clinton, his Senate opponent before he dropped out.</p>
        <p>(In one Yankee-related watershed event of his campaign, Mr. Giuliani unapologetically canceled four long-planned Senate campaign appearances in upstate New York in April to attend the rescheduled Yankee home opener. ''What can I tell you?'' the mayor said in what became Exhibit A of his indifferent race against Mrs. Clinton. ''This is me.'')</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Giuliani said, to no one's surprise, that the Series would help Mrs. Clinton's opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio. ''I think it all underlies the lack of authenticity in Hillary Clinton's candidacy,'' Mr. Giuliani said. ''Rick Lazio's a New Yorker, he roots for the Mets, he's represented us in the United States Congress.''</p>
        <p>He added that ''my simple advice to Rick Lazio would be to continue to emphasize that.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Clinton, for her part, said she hoped to squeeze a game into her schedule. ''I hope I can,'' she said during a campaign stop in Syracuse.  ''I'm trying to work out problems with my schedule.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''I'm absolutely thrilled. Just, gosh, a year after I moved to the state we have a subway series. I mean that's pretty exciting to me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani said he also sees the Series as a boon for New York's economy, and is impatient with people who say otherwise. Asked yesterday how the city could make large amounts of money when many fans already live here, Mr. Giuliani testily responded: ''You know, it's amazing. I've got to tell you this: Somehow, some way, people can figure out in this city how to look success in the face and say, 'Oh, my goodness, we can't stand it, we can't deal with it.' ''</p>
        <p>The city, the mayor said, would reap huge benefits from hotel rooms, ticket sales, sales taxes and income taxes on the ballplayers.</p>
        <p>''If you're talking about direct revenues, taxes that we can literally count, that's in the $40 million to $50 million range,'' the mayor asserted.</p>
        <p>But many economists say public officials tend to overestimate the economic benefits of major sports events.</p>
        <p>Finally, Mr. Giuliani said the Series might smooth the way for building new stadiums for both the Mets and the Yankees. ''I think it makes it easier to do a deal that the public will understand is a very good proposition for the city,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's staff said he expected to attend every game in the Series. ''This is a liberated human being,'' said Norman Adler, a political consultant to Republicans and Democrats. ''He can be for anybody or do anything that's legal right now. If he wants to pursue his childhood dream of being almost a Yankee, he's allowed. This is not sports, this is religion.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL: SUBWAY SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
