<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Miami's Marino Gone, It's All About Defense</title>
    <meta content="19FISH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/sports/19FISH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Dolphins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Miami Dolphins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DC123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Miami's Marino Gone, It's All About Defense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>DAVIE, Fla., Oct. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses success of Miami Dolphins so far this season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Miami Dolphins' surprising success has been achieved with a defense that has historians dusting off the National Football League's record book.</p>
        <p>Entering Monday night's showdown with the Jets at the Meadowlands in East Rutherford, N.J., the Dolphins (5-1) have allowed 3 touchdowns and 51 points -- the fewest at this point in a season by an N.F.L. team since 1977. Through their first four games, they permitted only one touchdown, something no N.F.L. team had done since 1937.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Miami Dolphins' surprising success has been achieved with a defense that has historians dusting off the National Football League's record book.</p>
        <p>Entering Monday night's showdown with the Jets at the Meadowlands in East Rutherford, N.J., the Dolphins (5-1) have allowed 3 touchdowns and 51 points -- the fewest at this point in a season by an N.F.L. team since 1977. Through their first four games, they permitted only one touchdown, something no N.F.L. team had done since 1937.</p>
        <p>Jim Bates, the team's new defensive coordinator and a former Cowboys assistant, preaches fundamentals and an attacking style. ''We're going to fundamental you to death to make sure you're doing things in the right manner,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Kevin Elko, a sports psychologist from Pittsburgh, has visited the Dolphins three times this season. He told players that when adversity struck, they should circle the wagons and not become accusatory toward one another. ''There were times during a game in the past where a team would tear off a big chunk against us, and you could feel the defense begin to crumble,'' linebacker Derrick Rodgers said. ''Guys would start pointing fingers right in the huddle. There were actually situations where it came to fisticuffs on the sideline over a guy not doing what he was supposed to do.''</p>
        <p>Concerned that the Dolphins were being discounted after the departures of Coach Jimmy Johnson and quarterback Dan Marino, Dave Wannstedt, the new coach, sought to boost the team's confidence. He told his players that any team with a Pro Bowl linebacker (Zach Thomas), a Pro Bowl cornerback (Sam Madison) and a pair of widely coveted defensive tackles (Tim Bowens and Daryl Gardener) had a great chance to challenge any team.</p>
        <p>The Dolphins have become believers, even with an offense that ranks 28th in the league and despite the chronic right ankle sprain of Thomas, their top defensive player.</p>
        <p>After sitting out the Cincinnati game on Oct. 1, Thomas tried to play against Buffalo the following week. He aggravated the sprain in the first quarter and has been on crutches ever since, though he is expected to try to practice on Thursday.</p>
        <p>''I guess it's kind of like having an eight-cylinder car with only seven cylinders working,'' defensive end Jason Taylor said today about the prospect of Thomas's missing the game. ''Zach is a such great football player. He's a warrior.''</p>
        <p>Wannstedt said he was optimistic that Thomas could play on Monday night -- his replacement would be the longtime special teams regular Larry Izzo -- and Thomas's defensive cohorts fully expect it.</p>
        <p>Likewise, the 317-pound Gardener is talking about returning from Sept. 15 surgery for a herniated disk in his lower back. He was energetic today, sounding almost Bryan Cox-like in his profession of disdain for hearing the hated opponent praised too loftily in recent days.</p>
        <p>When asked about playing on Monday, Gardener said, ''Let me put it this way: When I do make my debut, just keep that camera rolling, because there's going to be some exciting things to watch.''</p>
        <p>According to Taylor, the Dolphins are wearing out their video machines trying to figure a way to stop Curtis Martin, the Jets' standout running back, who rushed for 143 yards and 3 touchdowns during last Sunday's 34-17 demolition of New England.</p>
        <p>''He's one of the best backs in the game if not the best,'' Taylor said. ''He's really carrying the team right now. They go as he goes. So stopping him is going to be a big key for us.''</p>
        <p>The Dolphins like the idea that most New Yorkers have Subway Series fever. Trace Armstrong, Miami's 35-year-old defensive end, whose 10 sacks lead the league, said that maybe the usual hostile environment that Jets fans create would not be quite as intense.</p>
        <p>''I hope they're all tired from Sunday night,'' Armstrong said.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
