<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>First Daughter Proving to Be Quiet Political Force</title>
    <meta content="19CHEL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/19/nyregion/19CHEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Murphy, Dean E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Chelsea</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2DB123EF93AA25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>First Daughter Proving to Be Quiet Political Force</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEAN E. MURPHY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Murphy, Dean E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses importance of Chelsea Clinton to Senate campaign of her mother Hillary Rodham Clinton in New York; she is being viewed as quietly and politely lending key support to her mother; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>She rarely says a word, at least not near a microphone. She stands behind her mother, careful not to upstage her. She is kept far away from reporters, just as she has been throughout the past eight years.</p>
        <p>But with Election Day less than three weeks away, Chelsea Clinton, the first daughter, is showing up more and more across New York, quietly, politely, cheerfully -- and judging by her popularity on the campaign trail, quite successfully -- lending support to her mother's candidacy for Senate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>She rarely says a word, at least not near a microphone. She stands behind her mother, careful not to upstage her. She is kept far away from reporters, just as she has been throughout the past eight years.</p>
        <p>But with Election Day less than three weeks away, Chelsea Clinton, the first daughter, is showing up more and more across New York, quietly, politely, cheerfully -- and judging by her popularity on the campaign trail, quite successfully -- lending support to her mother's candidacy for Senate.</p>
        <p>Ms. Clinton is typically mobbed by autograph seekers, pulled into countless photographs and pressed for details about her school, her family and the campaign. Most everyone has an opinion about her appearance, from her hair to her toothy smile to her graceful handling of sometimes overeager admirers. At a recent gathering of black businesswomen in Manhattan, Ms. Clinton desperately tried to steer well-wishers toward her mother, but most of them would hear nothing of it.</p>
        <p>''She is really a good role model for people our age who are looking for somebody well put together,'' said Lori Romus, 22, who answers phones at the Erie County Democratic headquarters in Buffalo and who has twice attended events where Ms. Clinton accompanied her mother. ''She is really remarkable and strong and a survivor.''</p>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton, who as first lady has made protecting her daughter's privacy a top motherly duty, has been looking more at ease drawing Ms. Clinton into the senatorial spotlight. Some of the fascination with Ms. Clinton is undoubtedly due to her parents' success in shielding her from public scrutiny in the past. More than a few in the crowds around Ms. Clinton have said they dislike the Clintons but feel sorry for their daughter and are curious about what she is like.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's Republican opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio, has two daughters of grade-school age. From the beginning of the race, Mr. Lazio has effortlessly and naturally integrated them into his campaign, letting them quietly speak to his stature as a family man. His children appear in a television advertisement, and at a debate last week with Mrs. Clinton, he allowed them to race around the WCBS studios under the noses of scores of journalists.</p>
        <p>Chelsea Clinton, 20, does not appear on any of the first lady's advance schedules, and Mrs. Clinton's campaign staff members say her recent appearances are not part of a larger strategy to counter Mr. Lazio's family portrayals or to highlight Mrs. Clinton as a mother. (Mrs. Clinton's news aides say they are typically left in the dark about whether Ms. Clinton will even attend an event.) But when Ms. Clinton does show up, Mrs. Clinton quickly draws attention to her daughter, often in a passing reference but also in ways intended to drive home a point or win favor with an audience.</p>
        <p>''She is really blossoming and has developed so well as a young adult,'' said Kernie L. Anderson, general manager of WLIB-AM and WBLS-FM radio stations, who played host last week to the mother-daughter Clintons at the small-business fair for black women in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''Women are especially interested in seeing young people when they are well mannered and they look good,'' Mr. Anderson added. ''I heard so many comments about how pretty Chelsea is and what warmth there was there. They just loved her.''</p>
        <p>In recent days, Mrs. Clinton has invoked her mother-daughter relationship in speeches about the importance of family, even mentioning Ms. Clinton during last week's debate, when she explained why she had stood by President Clinton despite his marital infidelities. Ms. Clinton was seated in the front row of the studio audience.</p>
        <p>At a speech Tuesday to the Council on Foreign Relations, Mrs. Clinton interrupted her remarks to acknowledge that her daughter had arrived, using the moment to say that her foreign policy vision was ''about the future of our children's lives.'' Later that day, at a fund-raiser for women at the Waldorf-Astoria with Caroline Kennedy as host, Mrs. Clinton spoke warmly about her discussions with Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis about raising a child in the White House and the importance of protecting ''the normalcy'' of a political family.</p>
        <p>''I really think that Jackie gave me the courage and the insight to say no, and continually try to create that normalcy for Chelsea,'' Mrs. Clinton said. ''And I am especially grateful to Caroline for the times she has spent with Chelsea that have meant so much to her.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday afternoon in Buffalo, Ms. Clinton received her most rousing ovation to date. She was introduced by Senator Edward M. Kennedy of Massachusetts during a raucous old-style Democratic rally at the Buffalo Irish Center. The crowd of more than 400 cheered wildly when Ms. Clinton stood and smiled demurely. Even the dignitaries on stage were moved to their feet. She said not a word, however, leaving it to her mother to acknowledge her admirers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Clinton has appeared on the campaign trail off and on over the past year, but with only a few weeks left in her mother's Senate race and a few months left in her father's presidency, she has been spending more time with both parents in their official and unofficial capacities.</p>
        <p>Aides to Mrs. Clinton said Ms. Clinton, who has taken off a semester from her studies at Stanford University, realized that this political season was a once-in-a-lifetime moment for her family, and she did not want to miss it. The decision to lend personal support to her mother's campaign, but to leave the talking to the candidate herself, was Ms. Clinton's alone, a campaign official said.</p>
        <p>Steve Pigeon, a Democratic Party organizer in Buffalo, said even a silent Ms. Clinton is perceived as a big winner for the Clinton campaign, particularly in heavily Democratic neighborhoods where the party is hoping for a large turnout on Nov. 7.</p>
        <p>''She is such a classy and poised woman, it shows what kind of job the first lady did in raising her in a very difficult situation with their lives' being so public,'' Mr. Pigeon said. ''Just by Chelsea being there, it underscores the kind of issues her mother talks about.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
