<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Bethlehem, New Generation of Teenage Foes Renews Ritual of Bloodshed</title>
    <meta content="Y06ISR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/world/06ISRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="WHOSE HOLY LAND?: THE COMBATANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E3D9173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Bethlehem, New Generation of Teenage Foes Renews Ritual of Bloodshed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>BETHLEHEM, West Bank, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Young Israelis and Palestinians comment on renewal of conflict and bloodshed between their peoples; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Juggling stones in his hands, Muhammad Ibrahim, 17, reported for his afternoon shift in the seven-day-old street war of what he thinks of as the second, and final, Palestinian uprising.</p>
        <p>His white T-shirt, the sleeves cut off to reveal biceps that have had a stone-throwing workout in the last week, was stained with the blood of a friend shot this morning.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Juggling stones in his hands, Muhammad Ibrahim, 17, reported for his afternoon shift in the seven-day-old street war of what he thinks of as the second, and final, Palestinian uprising.</p>
        <p>His white T-shirt, the sleeves cut off to reveal biceps that have had a stone-throwing workout in the last week, was stained with the blood of a friend shot this morning.</p>
        <p>''You want to express your anger,'' he said, as a companion stood beside him flicking a lighter. ''You know your stone might not hit an Israeli soldier or might not even hurt him. But you want to feel you've done something for the homeland.''</p>
        <p>Far down a rubble-strewn avenue, filled with chunks of concrete, flaming tires and spent bullet casings, stood his targets -- teenagers like him, for instance, Guy Stencil, 19, a slender, baby-faced Israeli corporal who is transformed into an imposing, impassive figure when he dons his riot gear.</p>
        <p>''Looking out there, at those Arab boys with their rocks and slingshots, I see a lot of anger and hate,'' Corporal Stencil said. ''I think I can understand. They think it's their country, their land. It's like us 50 years ago. Everybody's got a side. They throw stones. We shoot back.''</p>
        <p>There are always young men who are barely shaving on the front lines of violent conflict. But it is striking even to the participants here that this is a battle of the teenagers, initiating yet another generation into the ritual of Israeli-Palestinian bloodshed.</p>
        <p>Certainly these young men are not surprised, neither Israelis nor Palestinians, understanding perfectly well that nothing has been resolved between their peoples. But their parents, at least, thought until very recently that the seven-year-old path of peace might have spared them combat duty in this particular conflict.</p>
        <p>''My father tells me, 'This is not your role,' '' Mr. Ibrahim said. ''He says: 'Don't go down that road. We don't need another generation of victims.' But I just let him talk, I say, O.K., O.K., and then I come here anyway.''</p>
        <p>The Israeli and Palestinian leaders failed to sign a written truce agreement early today in Paris, but agreed orally to halt the fighting, which has raged since last Friday. But this street continued to erupt, albeit less intensely, and the oral cease-fire is considered tenuous, with increased violence predicted for Friday.</p>
        <p>''The time has not yet arrived for us to beat our swords into plowshares,'' Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel said at a memorial service today for paratroopers who died in previous battles.</p>
        <p>Here on the northern outskirts of Palestinian-ruled Bethlehem, Mr. Ibrahim was stationed on one side of Rachel's Tomb, a heavily fortified Jewish holy site, and Corporal Stencil on the other, closer to Jerusalem. Between them lay a traffic artery that in the last week has become a no man's land littered with the detritus of the ritualized fighting here: The Palestinian youths dance into the streets hurling stones and firebombs; the Israelis throw back tear-gas canisters and fire rubber-coated metal bullets.</p>
        <p>Inside the Israeli Army compound across from Rachel's Tomb, Corporal Stencil, a radio operator, sat drinking watery juice, an antenna snaking up behind his head. Everything was quiet outside for the moment. The corporal shook his head, repeatedly referring to the violence as a mess.</p>
        <p>The child of an English father and an Israeli mother, Corporal Stencil grew up in Kibbutz Stotyam, near Hadera, where his father worked in a plastics factory and his mother at a dairy.</p>
        <p>Barely filling out his khakis, he looked, without his protective face shield and weapons, about as menacing as a pre-med student. Dreaming ahead to his post-army travel plans, he was thinking about India and Australia, he said. But for now he is spending his nights shooting into the dark, toward the sources of Palestinian fire. He does not think that he has hit anybody yet.</p>
        <p>The fighting fell into this pattern a generation ago, during the intifada, or uprising, that began in 1987 and that many think led to the peace effort. But in the last week, the fighting has become more sinister, with stones reinforced by guns on the Palestinian side, and guns by rockets, tanks and helicopters on the Israeli side. The daytime street riots have turned at night into exchanges of live fire.</p>
        <p>''It's actually a war,'' said Sgt. Yehuda Roth, 21, a friend of Corporal Stencil. ''In the daytime, it's just the regular stuff with the Arabs. But at night, this switch goes off in their heads, and they start shooting precisely and in volume, shooting to kill.''</p>
        <p>Some Palestinian youths, like Mr. Ibrahim, are purists, and they like the idea of a David-versus-Goliath battle between the clean white stones of the Palestinians and the Israeli firearms. ''Symbolically, our stones are more effective,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Ibrahim talked, his arms folded over his chest, his legs crossed in black jeans adorned with a Nike belt, bullets whizzed by. A gang gathered, his shebabs, or ''guys.''</p>
        <p>To disperse them so he could have some space, he shouted, making it up, ''Guys, a Jew just drove by in that car!'' The guys went running, except for one who yelled at him for talking to a reporter, saying that after his mother saw them on television at the scene of the stone-throwing, she had beat him with a mop.</p>
        <p>One of 10 children of an electrician and a homemaker, Mr. Ibrahim lives in the Deheisheh refugee camp nearby. Once, he said, he went on a family trip to their village near the Israeli city of Bet Shemesh, and stared longingly at the fruit trees and the well on their onetime property. Then they returned to their two-room apartment off an alley in the camp.</p>
        <p>''I was raised with stories of how they kicked us off our land,'' he said, while collecting rubber bullets from the ground. ''Still, in 1993, when they made the peace, I was glad. I was naive.</p>
        <p>''The peace is one big lie,'' he continued. ''That's why I come out here every day. It makes me happy. I always regretted that I was just a bit too young to participate in the first intifada.'' He was 4 when it began.</p>
        <p>Standing behind the teenagers, a plainclothes Palestinian security official, Daoud Mohammad Mugrabi, said the ''guys'' had refused orders to go home.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, they don't listen to us, because they want to make their own revolution,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ibrahim responded, ''We don't listen, that's true.''</p>
        <p>''The Israelis think that Arafat controls us like puppets,'' he said, referring to the widespread presumption among Israelis that Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, was in control of the rioting. ''But we are a force of our own.''</p>
        <p>A vocational student who wants to be a carpenter, Mr. Ibrahim is more interested for the moment in his membership in the Tenzim, a loose paramilitary organization under the supposed direction of the Fatah party of Mr. Arafat. Late this afternoon, he peered into the distance, toward the Israeli soldiers. ''I never see them face to face,'' he said, with some degree of curiosity.</p>
        <p>Inside the Israeli Army compound, Corporal Stencil said he found the current fighting primitive, reducing both sides to tribal hatreds.</p>
        <p>For an hour the previous evening, he said, a man stood on the street and cursed the soldiers' mothers and sisters in Arabic. Then, the soldiers watched the evening news, which they never see all the way through before the bullets start flying, he said.</p>
        <p>Corporal Stencil said he and his buddies were frustrated by television images that show them as the brutal aggressors. He said he found the footage of the 12-year-old boy caught in the crossfire in Gaza and killed by Israeli shooting to be haunting. But he regretted most that it made the Israeli soldiers look like ''the bad guys.''</p>
        <p>''You see us, we're just sitting here, waiting to receive what they throw our way,'' he said. ''We have no interest in going out and shooting them. If we really wanted to, we always have the option of just conquering back the land and killing them all. But we don't want to.''</p>
        <p>Before the shooting began on Wednesday night, Corporal Stencil said, he and his friends were talking about American kids their age. ''They go to college, they're fraternity brothers, they drink beer,'' he said. ''Sometimes, maybe, the choice of beer creates what they consider a conflict. Some life, eh?''</p>
        <p>WHOSE HOLY LAND?: THE COMBATANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
