<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Workfare Exemption For Students Who Intern</title>
    <meta content="06WORK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/nyregion/06WORK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Workfare and Employment of Welfare Recipients</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDF143CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Workfare Exemption For Students Who Intern</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Gov George E Pataki signs legislation that will allow workfare exemptions for college students on welfare if they are involved in internships or work-study programs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki has signed legislation that will allow workfare exemptions for college students on welfare if they are involved in internships or work-study programs.</p>
        <p>The administration of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and advocates for the poor have argued for years about  whether college students who receive public assistance should have to fulfill the same work requirements that apply to other welfare recipients under the city's workfare program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki has signed legislation that will allow workfare exemptions for college students on welfare if they are involved in internships or work-study programs.</p>
        <p>The administration of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and advocates for the poor have argued for years about  whether college students who receive public assistance should have to fulfill the same work requirements that apply to other welfare recipients under the city's workfare program.</p>
        <p>New York City and other local governments around the state typically require welfare recipients to work 20 or more hours a week to qualify for their benefits. The assignments range from clerical work in government agencies to the cleaning of public parks.</p>
        <p>The legislation, which the governor signed Wednesday night, had the strong support of advocates for the poor, who had long argued that many college students, involved in internships or work-study programs as well as workfare jobs and their classes, were forced to drop out of school.</p>
        <p>The Giuliani administration has opposed the exception, saying it would interfere with the city's administration of its workfare program -- and hamstring its efforts to ensure that all students on welfare meet the program's main stated objective: adequate work experience.  The bill placed Mr. Pataki in a political quandary when it reached his desk more than a week ago after passing the Senate and Assembly nearly unanimously. The legislation  forced him to choose between an idea that had bipartisan support and the mayor, a fellow Republican who has led the drive to reshape the city's welfare program and, in the process, cut the welfare rolls significantly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, a strong proponent of workfare himself, had until midnight Wednesday to sign or veto the bill. His aides said the governor had been extremely concerned about doing anything that might adversely affect the city's ability to run its workfare program as it saw fit.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pataki was ultimately convinced, they said, that the legislation would give the city and other localities enough flexibility to reject any internship or work-study assignment that they believed would undermine the underlying objective of workfare. The bill takes effect in December.</p>
        <p>''This simply tells local social service districts that they cannot unreasonably deny a work-study internship,'' said James McGuire, the governor's chief counsel.</p>
        <p>In fact, the bill's authors, Assemblyman Roberto Ramirez, Democrat of the Bronx, and Senator Raymond A. Meir, Republican of Oneida County, have said that they tailored the legislation to meet the concerns that the city or other localities might have.</p>
        <p>The legislation allows local officials to prevent internships from counting toward workfare requirements in a number of instances, including when a student's average falls below a C or when a student refuses to take a paid job that is available.</p>
        <p>The Giuliani administration expressed regret over the governor's decision, saying the city already allowed students receiving public assistance to participate in internships or work-study programs in place of workfare assignments, on a case-by-case basis.</p>
        <p>But the governor's decision was praised by advocates for the poor, as well as Democratic lawmakers, who argued that the Giuliani administration, in its drive to cut the welfare rolls, had forced many students to drop out of school by refusing to count the internships toward their workfare requirements.</p>
        <p>While it is unclear how many students on welfare have had to drop out because of workfare requirements, the number of welfare recipients in the City University of New York has declined precipitously.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, before the workfare program was introduced in New York City, more than 10 percent of CUNY's student body -- some 28,000 students -- received public assistance. The number of welfare recipients at CUNY has shrunk to about 7,500 since workfare was instituted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
