<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tendency to Embellish Fact Snags Gore</title>
    <meta content="Y06MEM$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/politics/06MEMO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1DF143CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1298" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tendency to Embellish Fact Snags Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO: Tendency to Embellish Fact Snags Gore**Republicans complain about accuracy of several statements by Vice Pres Gore during his debate with Gov George W Bush; some Democrats express puzzlement over Gore's misstatements (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, his political opponents have groused that Vice President Al Gore has trouble with facts. They pounced on statements he made about his service in Vietnam, about his record in Congress and even about the price he has to pay for his dog's arthritis medicine.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, they got even more ammunition: Several of Mr. Gore's comments in his debate with Gov. George W. Bush set off a fresh outcry over what even some of his supporters acknowledge is a tendency to embellish anecdotes about his roles in events.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, his political opponents have groused that Vice President Al Gore has trouble with facts. They pounced on statements he made about his service in Vietnam, about his record in Congress and even about the price he has to pay for his dog's arthritis medicine.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, they got even more ammunition: Several of Mr. Gore's comments in his debate with Gov. George W. Bush set off a fresh outcry over what even some of his supporters acknowledge is a tendency to embellish anecdotes about his roles in events.</p>
        <p>''It's a weird pattern that has emerged,'' Karl Rove, the chief strategist for Mr. Bush, said in an interview. ''We have these episodes in which Gore is playing Forrest Gump or Zelig.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's running mate, Dick Cheney, issued a statement saying he was ''puzzled and saddened'' by Mr. Gore's misstatements, while the conservative New York Post trumpeted ''Liar! Liar!'' as its main headline today.</p>
        <p>While many politicians are prone to spice up a story here and there, Republicans and Democrats say Mr. Gore's shading of the truth has become so frequent that some politicians are no longer dismissing it as sloppy oratory from a candidate under the glare of television cameras.</p>
        <p>This predilection of Mr. Gore's is all the more surprising because it often involves trivial matters -- ones that could easily be checked -- such as how Mr. Gore recalled a childhood lullaby that did not exist.</p>
        <p>Even as he tried to defend Mr. Gore, Art Torres, chairman of the California Democratic Party, could not come up with an explanation for the misstatements. ''I have no idea,'' he said. ''I'm not a psychiatrist.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Torres said it was unfair to dwell on Mr. Gore's comments, asserting that it was far more important to focus on substantive issues. ''Those debate situations are pretty strenuous,'' he said. ''With so many activities, so many campaign stops, you might not be able to totally remember the facts.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's most recent troubles began with the first question of the debate. The moderator, Jim Lehrer of PBS, noted that Mr. Gore had once questioned whether his opponent had the experience to be president and asked him what he meant. Mr. Gore denied that he had ever raised questions about Mr. Bush's qualifications for the presidency. The truth is, he had. In a speech to the American Society of Newspaper Editors in April, Mr. Gore cited Mr. Bush's call for a tax cut and posed this question: ''Does he have the experience to be president?''</p>
        <p>Then there was Mr. Gore's story of a 15-year-old girl in Sarasota, Fla., who he said is such a victim of school crowding that she has to stand in class. The fact is, the girl has a desk, and went without one for only a day.</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. Gore said he had traveled with James Lee Witt, the director of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, to inspect fire and flooding damage in Texas in June 1998. In fact, Mr. Gore went to Texas, but not with Mr. Witt.</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. Gore said he ''took a risk'' in asking the former Prime Minister of Russia, Viktor S. Chernomyrdin, to become personally involved in negotiating an end to the conflict in Kosovo. In fact, President Boris Yeltsin of Russia had two weeks early designated Mr. Chernomyrdin as a special envoy to the Balkans and the diplomatic mission that Mr. Gore described had been initiated by other top officials in Russia, Europe and the United States.</p>
        <p>In an interview last weekend, Mr. Gore volunteered that PBS had never invited him to be appear on a documentary about presidential debates. But officials at PBS said he had been invited personally, and the vice president's own spokesman said the campaign had rejected the offer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, in an interview today with a television station in Grand Rapids, Mich., sought to deflect accusations that he is an embellisher by turning the tables on Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''In the debates, when he said that I spent more in my campaign than he has, the numbers show that he has spent twice as much as I have,'' Mr. Gore said. ''But I don't seize on that as evidence of some character flaw. He made a mistake, and I'm not going to attack him personally.''</p>
        <p>In another interview months ago, Mr. Gore tried to make light of questions at the time about his exaggerations, turning to the reporter and blurting, ''I think it's an exaggeration!''</p>
        <p>But then he suggested that the press was at fault for a newfound tendency of overblowing offhand remarks, saying, ''Part of it is modern.'' Reporters, he said, operate with ''a hair trigger on.''</p>
        <p>Rather than explain Mr. Gore's misstatements, one of his aides, Mark Fabiani, focused on Mr. Bush, saying, ''We've never attacked Bush for his numerous crimes against the English language.''</p>
        <p>In and of themselves, many of Mr. Gore's embellishments can be excused or seem quite mild. Unlike the times that President Clinton has twisted the facts to get himself out of a humiliating scrape or scandal, Mr. Gore's slip-ups appear to be far more unnecessary.</p>
        <p>People who know Mr. Gore have suggested that he was reared in a political family where embellishments were part of life. And Mr. Gore spent his childhood in a way that was intended for use in a press release.</p>
        <p>His mother, Pauline, used to tell reporters that she would have dinner with her son no matter what else was going on. ''Nothing lonelier than a meal eaten alone,'' she would say. The truth is, Mr. Gore was alone a lot.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, the vice president's tangled recollections have begun to draw attention because there are so many examples. Another reason is that they are curiously at odds with his reputation -- and the image he is trying to project -- as a politician of great intelligence who is a stickler for the facts.</p>
        <p>Several prominent Democrats said privately that they were worried that Mr. Gore was giving ammunition to his opponents. Indeed, Mr. Bush and the Republicans have gleefully seized on Mr. Gore's statements.</p>
        <p>''The press has been too easy on him on this,'' said Bill Pascoe, a spokesman for the Republican National Committee. ''If the only thing you knew about Al Gore was what you read in the press, you'd think he was just a charming fellow who loves his wife.''</p>
        <p>Robert Schmuhl, a professor of American studies at the University of Notre Dame, said Mr. Gore should take greater care to watch what he says.</p>
        <p>''It's reaching a point where a stereotype might form and we might think of Gore as someone who is prone to exaggeration,'' Mr. Schmuhl said. ''That's a real danger for someone who is trying to run for president without the strain of character questions or problems of credibility.''</p>
        <p>But Chris Wetzel, a professor of psychology at Rhodes College in Memphis, said he was willing to give Mr. Gore the benefit of the doubt and did not believe he had sinister motives.</p>
        <p>''Why would someone say something like this when it can be so blatantly discovered?'' asked Mr. Wetzel, who has taught a research course called Detecting Impostors and Con Artists. ''I think it's like the false memory syndrome when people end up believing that they were abducted by aliens.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
