<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Two Family House'</title>
    <meta content="RV011321" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/arts/06HOU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Felitta, Raymond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Two Family House (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0DD143CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Two Family House'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawrence Van Gelder reviews Two Family House, directed by Raymond De Felitta (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Directed by Raymond De Felitta  R; 104 minutes</p>
        <p>Right after World War II, Buddy Visalo could have been somebody. While he was in the Air Force, the entertainer Arthur Godfrey heard him sing and invited him to look him up. But Buddy's fiancee and his future in-laws poured cold water on his dream; instead, Julius LaRosa sang with Godfrey and wound up with fame and fortune.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Directed by Raymond De Felitta  R; 104 minutes</p>
        <p>Right after World War II, Buddy Visalo could have been somebody. While he was in the Air Force, the entertainer Arthur Godfrey heard him sing and invited him to look him up. But Buddy's fiancee and his future in-laws poured cold water on his dream; instead, Julius LaRosa sang with Godfrey and wound up with fame and fortune.</p>
        <p>And now it is 10 years later, 1956. Buddy and his stick-in-the-mud wife, Estelle, are still living with his in-laws on Staten Island, and after a string of business failures ranging from house painting to pizza delivery, Buddy is working in a machine shop.</p>
        <p>But he hasn't stopped dreaming or singing. Buddy is about to buy a ramshackle 1912 frame house, with the idea of living upstairs and turning downstairs into Buddy's tavern, with himself as the genial boniface and resident crooner.</p>
        <p>So begins ''Two Family House,'' a sweet, wise, heartwarming sleeper written and directed by Raymond De Felitta.</p>
        <p>This rich romantic comedy, with its messages of love and tolerance and hope and its great old tunes, won the Audience Award at this year's Sundance Film Festival and seems destined to capture many more fans before its run is finished.</p>
        <p>Buddy (played by Michael Rispoli in a fine performance that is characteristic of the entire cast) is a man whose dreams never turn out the way he visualizes. And the dream embodied by the house at 19 West Street in an Irish neighborhood on Staten Island is no exception.</p>
        <p>The upstairs tenant is a scruffy, belligerent drunk named Jim O'Neary (Kevin Conway), who insists at the top of his lungs on staying right where he is.</p>
        <p>And beyond Jim there is another complicating factor in the person of the beautiful Mary O'Neary (Kelly Macdonald). Mrs. O'Neary is far younger than her husband, no less resistant to moving and very, very pregnant.</p>
        <p>On the day when Buddy's Italian pals gather outside to deal with the Irishman by force, Mary goes into labor, giving birth to the film's narrator.</p>
        <p>What happens next becomes the talk of the neighborhood, sends Jim  into obscurity, gets Mary out of the house and tosses Buddy's life into a cocked hat.</p>
        <p>So while the baleful Estelle (Katherine Narducci), who regards her faithful husband as ''pregnant with failure,'' is complaining to her girlfriends and doing her best to see to it that Buddy's Tavern never opens, Buddy is off on an adventure that surprises even him.</p>
        <p>To accompany him is to experience filmgoing joy.</p>
        <p>LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</p>
        <p>FILM IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
