<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mrs. Clinton's Primary Opponent Backs Lazio</title>
    <meta content="06LAZI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/politics/06LAZI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcmahon, Mark S (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E3D6173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mrs. Clinton's Primary Opponent Backs Lazio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Representative Rick A Lazio announces that Dr Mark S McMahon, who ran against Hillary Rodham Clinton in Democratic Senate primary, has endorsed Lazio's bid for election; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Campaign officials for Representative Rick A. Lazio teased journalists that a key endorsement was imminent. They rolled out his campaign bus, playing patriotic and pop music. Party faithful, including the state Republican chairman, William D. Powers, were summoned.</p>
        <p>And at 2 p.m., to the cheers of a throng sheltered from a chilly drizzle under a terrace at the Capitol, Mr. Lazio strode to a lectern with the guest of honor at his side: Dr. Mark S. McMahon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Campaign officials for Representative Rick A. Lazio teased journalists that a key endorsement was imminent. They rolled out his campaign bus, playing patriotic and pop music. Party faithful, including the state Republican chairman, William D. Powers, were summoned.</p>
        <p>And at 2 p.m., to the cheers of a throng sheltered from a chilly drizzle under a terrace at the Capitol, Mr. Lazio strode to a lectern with the guest of honor at his side: Dr. Mark S. McMahon.</p>
        <p>Nobody pretends that his is a household name, and political scientists said they doubted that his endorsement carried any weight to benefit Mr. Lazio's candidacy. But at least 124,315 Democratic voters felt they knew enough about Dr. McMahon, a Manhattan orthopedic surgeon, to flip the lever for him in the Sept. 12 primary and try to end Hillary Rodham Clinton's quest for a Senate seat. And Mr. Lazio's advisers said Dr. McMahon could help the congressman appeal to Democrats willing to cross party lines in the Senate race.</p>
        <p>Dr. McMahon, who captured 18 percent of the primary vote, was not regarded as a serious challenge to Mrs. Clinton, but Mr. Lazio said he believed that the endorsement represented ''a lot of votes'' and would help appeal to ''independent, moderate Democrats,'' a term he repeated throughout his 20-minute news conference.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's campaign has begun a push for such voters on the theory that some Democratic supporters of Vice President Al Gore, who polls suggest is ahead of Gov. George W. Bush in New York, are willing to back Mr. Lazio out of opposition to Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''For over a hundred thousand independent, moderate Democrats, his message was the right message,'' Mr. Lazio said. ''People who believe in him and what he was talking about, people who believed that a New Yorker should represent New York. And I am very, very proud to stand with him right now.''</p>
        <p>But political analysts did not share Mr. Lazio's enthusiasm. They said Dr. McMahon, who did not mount a vigorous statewide campaign, was simply too obscure to draw any more voters than the ones who voted for him.</p>
        <p>''The McMahon vote was a largely anti-Hillary vote,'' said Lee M. Miringoff, director of the Marist College Institute for Public Opinion. ''I suspect they will find their way to Rick Lazio on their own. This is a one-day story campaigns like to do in October.''</p>
        <p>He added that endorsements ''have a limited conversion factor in votes, unless it's something like a union.''</p>
        <p>Dr. McMahon, who switched from the Republican to the Democratic Party in 1997, said he had approached both Mrs. Clinton's and Mr. Lazio's camps before he made his decision to endorse Mr. Lazio.</p>
        <p>''I must put the interests of New York State above all else, and therefore I urge the Democrats who supported me in the primary to vote for Rick Lazio,'' Dr. McMahon said.</p>
        <p>Democrats mocked the endorsement as a sign of desperation on Mr. Lazio's part (Mrs. Clinton's press office forwarded the Lazio campaign's e-mailed news release to reporters with the note, ''Didn't want you to miss this important announcement.'')</p>
        <p>''If this is their October surprise, the Lazio campaign must be in worse shape than we thought,'' said Howard Wolfson, Mrs. Clinton's chief spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's aides said, however, that the event allowed Mr. Lazio to make a pitch for swing voters, Democrats willing to cross party lines. When he campaigned, Dr. McMahon promoted his concern about health care, which Mr. Lazio's advisers say strongly appealed to swing voters and women, another critical constituency.</p>
        <p>With the idea of appealing to such voters, Mr. Lazio has stepped up his schedule of school visits -- he spoke at a high school in nearby Colonie this morning -- talking about education and a range of other topics with a backdrop of children.</p>
        <p>In addition, Patricia Lazio, the congressman's wife, and Libby Pataki, the governor's wife, completed a two-day tour of the state today to promote awareness of breast and cervical cancer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
