<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Running Mates Stick to Second Fiddle</title>
    <meta content="Y06IMA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDE143CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Running Mates Stick to Second Fiddle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>DANVILLE, Ky., Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Francis X Clines assessment holds that Vice Pres candidates Dick Cheney and Sen Joseph I Lieberman held civil debate that had few light moments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The two vice-presidential nominees demonstrated their fitness for their political calling tonight by safely remaining one heartbeat away from committing any news whatsoever that might conceivably have upstaged their principals.</p>
        <p>The most memorable utterance to be heard across the 90 minutes, again and again and again, was ''Al Gore and I.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The two vice-presidential nominees demonstrated their fitness for their political calling tonight by safely remaining one heartbeat away from committing any news whatsoever that might conceivably have upstaged their principals.</p>
        <p>The most memorable utterance to be heard across the 90 minutes, again and again and again, was ''Al Gore and I.''</p>
        <p>Senator Joseph I. Lieberman plastered this advertisement for the Democratic ticket across his every debate answer. The mantra served to demonstrate the obeisance to the top of the ticket that necessarily goes with the role of backup candidate.</p>
        <p>The phrase resounded no fewer than 18 times alone in the first half of the show, with no letup until the close when Mr. Lieberman confided to whatever part of the public that might have been listening, ''Al Gore and I agree on almost everything.''</p>
        <p>Dick Cheney did not reply in kind, if only because of the confusion of political father and son that ''George Bush and I'' might have created.</p>
        <p>But, even with a minimal mention of Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, Mr. Cheney exhibited an easy talent as an articulate enunciator of facts and a confident defender of his champion.</p>
        <p>With a surgeon's skill, for example, he sought to rework Mr. Bush's utterance in the presidential debate about inviting President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia to help solve the Yugoslav crisis. In Mr. Cheney's retelling, it became a firm challenge from Mr. Bush that Mr. Putin show where he stands.</p>
        <p>With some of the boardroom polish of a postgovernment career, Mr. Cheney smoothly marshaled his arguments for the Republican ticket in a debate that the two men were soon conducting more as a civil, even restful discussion than anything approaching tooth-and-claw politics.</p>
        <p>As a political spectacle, the debate was decidedly more PBS than Fox. A civilized murmur frequently marked the show, akin to a display of life's grays that might erupt when Charlie Rose invites academics to the table.</p>
        <p>No voice was raised. No finger pointed. Mr. Lieberman kept in check his now familiar signature mirth at the very idea of his nomination, while Mr. Cheney showed that, beneath his sometimes dour exterior as a candidate, there beats an avuncular self-confidence.</p>
        <p>The few light moments were to be appreciated. When Mr. Lieberman alluded to Mr. Cheney's multimillion-dollar success in the private sector, the Republican swiftly replied how much he yearned to see the Democrat get his share and soon.</p>
        <p>In the only vaguely dramatic gesture of the night, Mr. Cheney took off his glasses to criticize more than attack Vice President Gore for ''eight years of talk and no action.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman could not resist a needle in defending his running mate's record.</p>
        <p>''Did he deliver?'' the senator asked rhetorically.</p>
        <p>''Big time -- if I may put it that way, Dick,'' Mr. Lieberman replied, teasing Mr. Cheney in quoting the Republican's backup endorsement of Governor Bush's open-mike gaffe in denouncing a news reporter.</p>
        <p>But, in the obviously easy spirit of the night, Mr. Cheney only enjoyed the allusion.</p>
        <p>Numerous attack avenues were ignored. Mr. Lieberman twice elaborately thanked his constituents in Connecticut for helping him get this far. But there was no complaint from Mr. Cheney that the senator, who is also running amid considerable controversy to retain his seat, might be campaigning for two offices.</p>
        <p>Outside the debating hall, a half moon hung over the rolling hills of blue-grass country. Inside, the mood was often no less pastoral.</p>
        <p>The candidates never seemed to clash, and they gently requested extra time when they felt an issue deserved it, as when Mr. Lieberman called attention to the Democrats' ''very exciting tax credit program.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney softly rebutted his opponent with the preamble, ''With all due respect, Joe.'' And when he declared, ''I like the old Joe Lieberman better than I do the new Joe Lieberman,'' Mr. Cheney did so with a gentleness suggesting he might like both.</p>
        <p>In sum, the debate was as uncontroversial but professional as the two presidential nominees could hope for. No sighs of exasperation were to be heard. No grimaces of outrage displayed.</p>
        <p>The show ended on cue with Mr. Lieberman once more celebrating the fact that he was on the ticket, the first Jew to be so honored with a vice-presidential nomination. There was none of the who-am-I anomie recalled from a past vice-presidential debate.</p>
        <p>Rather, Mr. Lieberman once more beamed and exulted, ''Here I am.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
