<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON STAGE AND OFF</title>
    <meta content="06BROA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/arts/06BROA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ford Center for the Performing Arts (NYC)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Marie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hill, Conleth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Campion, Sean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marshall, Rob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gien, Pamela</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">42d Street (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bells Are Ringin (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Stones in His Pocket (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Seussical (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Syringa Tree, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Exonerated, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3D7163CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON STAGE AND OFF</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jesse McKinley</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Stage and Off column; revival of musical 42d Street is set at vacant Ford Center; Bells are Ringing revival to open next April; Marie Jones comedy Stones in His Pockets, surprise hit in London, will open at Golden Theater in March; Conleth Hill and Sean Campion play 15 characters; Seussical opening may be delayed to allow Rob Marshall to make changes; Pamela Gien comments on her solo show The Syringa Tree; photo; documentary play, The Exonerated, about former death row inmates, to be performed (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Naughty, Bawdy . . . And Back</p>
        <p>With the news that a revival of ''42nd Street'' -- didn't it just close? -- is coming to the vacant Ford Center and that the Broadway Theater had its next tenant, the 2000-1 musical season looks nearly set.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Naughty, Bawdy . . . And Back</p>
        <p>With the news that a revival of ''42nd Street'' -- didn't it just close? -- is coming to the vacant Ford Center and that the Broadway Theater had its next tenant, the 2000-1 musical season looks nearly set.</p>
        <p>And if early expectations are any indication, it could be a laugh, or a gaffe.</p>
        <p>''Bells Are Ringing,'' the 1956 comedy by Betty Comden, Adolph Green and Jule Styne, is to open at the Broadway on April 22. Faith Prince, who appeared in a well-received concert version at the Kennedy Center in Washington in 1998, will star as a plucky telephone operator.</p>
        <p>The show's producers, who expect to try out in Stamford, Conn., in mid-February, announced last March plans to come to Broadway, but little has been heard about the show since. Mitchell Maxwell, the lead producer, said that was all part of the process.</p>
        <p>''We've been doing everything -- casting, design, everything,'' Mr. Maxwell said. That everything includes raising the $6.6 million this production is expected to cost. ''Do we have the money? Yes,'' he said. ''Do we have the money in the bank? No. But we will.''</p>
        <p>The musical, which has never had a Broadway revival, is being directed the Broadway newcomer Tina Landau, with Jeff Calhoun as choreographer. Riccardo Hernandez will do the sets, described by Mr. Maxwell as ''50's minimalist,'' in the 1,752-seat house.</p>
        <p>Another show looking to fill a huge house is ''42nd Street,'' coming to the 1,813-seat Ford Center for the Performing Arts a mere 12 years after the original closed. The revival, to open in May, is based on a production now in Amsterdam (in Dutch, no less), directed by Mark Bramble, who wrote the musical's book with Michael Stewart, who died in 1987.  Like Ms. Landau, Mr. Bramble is a first-time Broadway director. His production is to open in May, in English and with a new design team. Dodger Theatricals is producing, filling the large, self-aggrandizing shoes of David Merrick, who produced the original stage version of ''42nd Street'' and died in April.</p>
        <p>Jones's 'Stones'</p>
        <p>To be spoken with a bad Irish accent: Remember the days (say, oh, April) when plays from London used to come to the United States? Sometimes even to -- Broadway?</p>
        <p>After a relatively slow couple of months for West End imports, now comes news that one of London's biggest crowd-pleasers is headed for Broadway: ''Stones in His Pockets,''</p>
        <p>Marie Jones's comedy about Irish rustics who find their hometown invaded by an American movie crew.</p>
        <p>The play, a constant sellout at two theaters in London (more recently the Duke of York's), is to open at the Golden Theater in March.</p>
        <p>''Stones'' was a surprise hit, and has made stars of its two previously unknown actors, Conleth Hill and Sean Campion, who could appear in the Broadway production pending approval by Actors' Equity.</p>
        <p>The two, Irishmen themselves, play 15 characters in the two-hour show, including several with good American accents.</p>
        <p>Too Loosical?</p>
        <p>After a week of meetings with Rob Marshall, its recently named show doctor, there were signs that ''Seussical'' would delay its opening -- perhaps by as much as a month -- to integrate changes into the $8.5 million musical.</p>
        <p>John Barlow, a spokesman for the show, said that no final decision had been made. The musical, based on the work of Dr. Seuss, is scheduled to open at the Richard Rodgers on Nov. 9, but earlier this week producers delayed the load-in of technical equipment as Mr. Marshall evaluated design elements. Rehearsals were also canceled while production meetings continued.</p>
        <p>Among cast members, the feeling seems to be that more time is needed. ''They're assuming that the date will change,'' said one agent with several clients in the show. ''And they think it's a good idea.''</p>
        <p>Fictional Facts</p>
        <p>It is the inevitable question from audiences at ''The Syringa Tree,'' Pamela Gien's acclaimed one-woman show: ''Did all that really happen?''</p>
        <p>The answer is no. And yes.</p>
        <p>''It's a fictional story,'' Ms. Gien says, ''based on true events.''</p>
        <p>Without spoiling the plot: The play, at Playhouse 91, 316 East 91st Street, Yorkville, tells the story of a girl's life in white South Africa, a tale involving a lost child, a brutal murder and an eventual reconciliation. Writing in The New York Times, Bruce Weber called the show ''deeply shocking'' and Ms. Gien ''a gifted writer and performer.'' Other critics have echoed those sentiments.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gien, who did grow up in a suburb of Johannesburg before moving to the United States in 1983, started working on the piece in the mid-1990's as part of an exercise for an acting class. Stunned by her classmates' response -- several broke into tears at the first 20-minute reading -- she expanded it with the help of her acting coach, Larry Moss, who eventually became her director.</p>
        <p>The play had its premiere in February 1999 in Seattle. Now there is talk of moving ''Syringa'' to London or even to South Africa, a place Ms. Gien says still haunts her imagination. ''Part of me had always been ashamed of being from South Africa, and part of me was also tremendously proud,'' she said. ''I hope the play speaks to the complexity of that.''</p>
        <p>Journey to Life</p>
        <p>It was not your ordinary summer project. In early July, Erik Jensen and Jessica Blank, two young actors and writers, took to the nation's highways to track down a small but growing American minority: exonerated death row inmates.</p>
        <p>The resulting interviews, culled from hundreds of hours of audiotape, form the spine of ''The Exonerated,'' a documentary play based on the stories of 12 people who were wrongly convicted and served time.</p>
        <p>Beginning on Oct. 30, the resulting 80-minute play will be performed with the help of some high-profile supporters on four consecutive Monday nights at 45 Bleecker, a new theater at that address in the East Village. The opening night cast will include Tim Robbins and Susan Sarandon, the director and star, respectively, of the death row film ''Dead Man Walking.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
