<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress Addresses Importing Medicine and Exporting to Cuba</title>
    <meta content="06APPR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/politics/06APPR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236543"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E5DD143CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress Addresses Importing Medicine and Exporting to Cuba</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN A. HOLMES and LIZETTE ALVAREZ</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Meeting into the night, House and Senate negotiators agreed today on separate measures to allow imports of low-priced prescription drugs and to lift four-decade-old sanctions on the sale of food to Cuba but with severe restrictions on financing and travel.</p>
        <p>''This finally changes a 40-year policy that hasn't done us any good,'' Representative Tom Latham, Republican of Iowa, said of the Cuba sanctions. ''Finally, we can crack open the door in Cuba and make something happen.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Meeting into the night, House and Senate negotiators agreed today on separate measures to allow imports of low-priced prescription drugs and to lift four-decade-old sanctions on the sale of food to Cuba but with severe restrictions on financing and travel.</p>
        <p>''This finally changes a 40-year policy that hasn't done us any good,'' Representative Tom Latham, Republican of Iowa, said of the Cuba sanctions. ''Finally, we can crack open the door in Cuba and make something happen.''</p>
        <p>The measures were attached to a large agriculture spending bill that now moves to a vote by the full House and Senate.</p>
        <p>Democrats opposed both Republican proposals in the bill, saying they contained an assortment of restrictions and loopholes that made them ineffective.</p>
        <p>''It's much ado about nothing,'' said Senator Tom Harkin, Democrat of Iowa, who voted, along with all other Democrats at the table, against the two measures.</p>
        <p>On both the lifting of sanctions and the importing of American-made drugs, Senate language was watered down by the more conservative House Republicans. But Senate Republicans voted to approve the measures anyway, arguing that if they did not, the entire spending bill would be in jeopardy.</p>
        <p>Today's agreement also lifted sanctions on the sale of food and medicine to Iran, Libya, North Korea and Sudan. But it was Cuba that created the most conflict. Cuban-American lawmakers succeeded in barring private or United States government financing of sales to Cuba, forcing Cuba to use cash or to borrow from foreign banks.</p>
        <p>The financing restrictions can be waived by the president for all countries except Cuba.</p>
        <p>Cuban-American lawmakers also prevailed in pushing language that would convert into law existing federal regulations that limit travel to Cuba, making it even more difficult for American tourists to visit Cuba in the future.</p>
        <p>The measure would also prohibit any future sanctions on food and medicine, without Congress's approval.</p>
        <p>''This is a victory,'' said Representative Lincoln Diaz-Balart, a Florida Republican who fought for the restrictions. ''It's a demonstration of solidarity with the right of the Cuban people to be free.''</p>
        <p>House and Senate negotiators also voted on a Republican proposal to permit the importing of American-made prescription drugs from other countries, a move intended to lower the cost of medication in the United States.</p>
        <p>Some other countries regulate pharmaceutical prices, and that means in many cases that drugs made in this country are priced 50 percent to 60 percent lower in those countries than in the United States.  But Democrats said the language in the bill was a departure from the Senate version, which House Republicans said they were comfortable with and the White House said it could accept.</p>
        <p>The bill would allow pharmacies and wholesale distributors to buy prescription drugs abroad, reimport them and sell them at a lower cost.</p>
        <p>Democrats, though, complained that there were too many loopholes in the measure. The bill would expire five years after the completion of regulations. It could, they argued, allow American drug companies to force foreign distributors to fix prices at United States levels before sending the drugs back.</p>
        <p>Democrats also had concerns about language on labeling restrictions that could undermine the ability of American pharmacies and distributors to import and sell the drugs.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats wondered whether drug manufacturers, who have fought this proposal, would supply enough drugs abroad to allow these foreign distributors to resell them in the United States.</p>
        <p>''We have concluded this is an unworkable provision as it is structured,'' said Chris Jennings, senior health care adviser to the president. ''We haven't given up, but it doesn't look good.''</p>
        <p>Democrats tried to amend the two proposals to reflect their concerns, but they were defeated on straight party-line votes.</p>
        <p>Among other action taken today:</p>
        <p>*The Senate overwhelming approved an $18.8 billion spending for the Department of the Interior and other entities, like the National Endowment for the Arts and the John F. Kennedy Center. The measure includes the establishment of what will become a $12 billion fund for land conservation set up in a six-year-period.</p>
        <p>*Congressional and White House negotiators reached a tentative agreement on a roughly $101 billion measure to pay for housing and veterans programs, as well as the Environmental Protection Agency. Included in the agreement was a proposal allowing the E.P.A. to draft regulations requiring companies to clean up carcinogenic compounds that have been lodged in sediment in 28 rivers, including the Hudson, according to a person familiar with the talks.</p>
        <p>*House and Senate negotiators dropped a provision to make hate attacks on gays a federal crime.</p>
        <p>The hate crimes proposal was part of a budget bill for the Pentagon and had been approved by the Senate in June by a vote of 57 to 42, an unexpectedly wide margin. Last month, the House endorsed a nonbinding measure instructing negotiators to include the provision in the final bill.</p>
        <p>But Republican leaders in both chambers vowed to kill the proposal, and after several weeks of internal debate, Senate negotiators voted today, 11 to 9, to strip out the provision their colleagues had supported.</p>
        <p>Gay rights groups and their congressional allies urged President Clinton to required any year-end budget deal to include the hate crimes provision.</p>
        <p>''The Republican leadership in Congress has sent a shameful message to the nation that undercuts our commitment to civil rights and equal protection of the laws,'' said Senator Edward M. Kennedy, Democrat of Massachusetts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
