<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's a Nice Girl Like You Doing With Him?</title>
    <meta content="06TAST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/arts/06TAST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jaoui, Agnes</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Taste of Others, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5D9163CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's a Nice Girl Like You Doing With Him?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews The Taste of Others, directed by Agnes Jaoui and shown as part of New York Film Festival (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You may have noticed how few couples actually behave like matched pairs. And those who do -- who can complete each other's sentences and use the word ''we'' with absolute confidence to describe their cozily congruent tastes -- usually seem to be missing something. For the outsider, being a third party around such a closed system can be insufferable, for it means being outvoted, two to one, whenever there's a disagreement.</p>
        <p>Agnes Jaoui's romantic comedy, ''The Taste of Others'' is a witty, sociologically astute reflection on the attraction between opposites (or rather, semi-opposites) that accounts for so many relationships that leave you wondering what these two could possibly see in each other. There's really no rhyme or reason  that some of the characters come together while others split up as this dense tangle of associations in business and in romance overlap. But the characters in the film, directed by Ms. Jaoui from a screenplay she wrote with her husband, Jean-Pierre Bacri (they both star in the movie),  are so precisely observed that the forging and severing of these connections feels intuitively right.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You may have noticed how few couples actually behave like matched pairs. And those who do -- who can complete each other's sentences and use the word ''we'' with absolute confidence to describe their cozily congruent tastes -- usually seem to be missing something. For the outsider, being a third party around such a closed system can be insufferable, for it means being outvoted, two to one, whenever there's a disagreement.</p>
        <p>Agnes Jaoui's romantic comedy, ''The Taste of Others'' is a witty, sociologically astute reflection on the attraction between opposites (or rather, semi-opposites) that accounts for so many relationships that leave you wondering what these two could possibly see in each other. There's really no rhyme or reason  that some of the characters come together while others split up as this dense tangle of associations in business and in romance overlap. But the characters in the film, directed by Ms. Jaoui from a screenplay she wrote with her husband, Jean-Pierre Bacri (they both star in the movie),  are so precisely observed that the forging and severing of these connections feels intuitively right.</p>
        <p>Take the confusing relationship between Castella (Mr. Bacri), a boorish suburban businessmen hammering out a deal with an Iranian company in Rouen (where the movie was filmed), and Clara (Anne Alvaro), the refined, high-strung actress he engages to give him a crash course in English. Castella isn't exactly a lout, but he is the kind of man who likes to tell dirty jokes at the dinner table and who unwittingly dispenses homophobic epithets to people who are obviously gay.</p>
        <p>When he first sees Clara on the stage, she is appearing in a local production of Racine's ''Berenice,'' and he is captivated by her passion and gaunt, ethereal beauty. Clara  has her own problems. At the age of 40 she frets about aging and her uncertain professional future. No sooner has her new pupil mastered a few words of English than he embarrasses her with a naive little love poem he has written for her. After coldly rebuffing his advance, Clara discovers that a nonintellectual side of her has responded to Castella, who is kind and thoughtful beneath his rough exterior. And she becomes the  pursuer.</p>
        <p>Castella also happens to be married to the movie's most unlikable character. His pretty blond wife, Angelique (Christiane Millet), is an interior decorator who has smothered their home in acres of flowery chintz and becomes furious when he purchases a painting that clashes with her design scheme. She also has a neurotic attraction to her ill-tempered dog, Flucky. One of those tiresome people who go around stridently promoting the moral superiority of animals over humans, Angelique is the movie's designated moral idiot.</p>
        <p>On the hipper side of the equation and a rung or two below Castella on the social ladder is Manie (Ms. Jaoui), the free-spirited barmaid in the bistro next to the theater where Clara is appearing. To supplement her income, Manie deals hashish. It's a sideline that her boyfriend Moreno (Gerard Lanvin) strongly disapproves of.</p>
        <p>Moreno has been hired by Castella as a personal bodyguard until the deal with the Iranians has been closed. He and Manie seem ideally matched except for one big stumbling block. When the possibility of marriage is brought up, Moreno says he expects Manie, who is happily  independent, to become a traditional homemaker.</p>
        <p>These are the focal relationships in a dense social microcosm that the beautifully acted movie examines with perception and humor and a rich understanding of human quirks.</p>
        <p>If ''The Taste of Others,'' which the New York Film Festival is showing tonight and tomorrow evening at Alice Tully Hall, doesn't address large social or philosophical questions, it captures the social pulse of its adult urban milieu to the fraction of a second and leaves you with the sense of being on intimate terms with its fully rounded characters.</p>
        <p>THE TASTE OF OTHERS</p>
        <p>Directed by Agnes Jaoui; written (in French, with English subtitles) by Ms. Jaoui and Jean-Pierre Bacri; director of photography, Laurent Dailland; edited by Herve De Luze; music by Jean-Charles Jarrell; production designer, Francois Emmanuelli; produced by Christian Berard and Charles Gassot; released by Offline Releasing and Artistic License Films. Running time: 112 minutes. This film is not rated. Shown with a 15-minute short, Caroline Vignal's ''Move It Girl'' today  at 9:15 p.m. and tomorrow at 6 p.m. at Alice Tully Hall as part of the 38th New York Film Festival.</p>
        <p>WITH: Anne Alvaro (Clara), Jean-Pierre Bacri (Castella), Brigitte Catillon (Beatrice), Alain Chabat (Deschamps), Raphael Defour (Benoit), Xavier De Guillebon (Weber), Agnes Jaoui (Manie), Gerard Lanvin (Moreno), Anne Le Ny (Valerie), Christiane Millet (Angelique) and Wladimir Yordanoff (Antoine).</p>
        <p>FILM FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
