<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Speaking in Bar Code; Personal Scanners Link Products Directly to Consumers</title>
    <meta content="Y06COD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/technology/06CODE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bar Codes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Scanning Devices</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Motorola Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Digital: Convergence Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Radio Shack</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DB173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Speaking in Bar Code; Personal Scanners Link Products Directly to Consumers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Consumers will soon be able to do comparison shopping on the spot with introduction of portable devices to read both old and new product bar codes; companies like Motorola Inc and General Electric Co are investing hundreds of millions of dollars in bar-code-related technologies on the bet that consumers will want, among other things, to scan products to get information, make lists, connect to the Web and complete purchases; Digital-Convergence Corp, which specializes in putting bar code links to Web sites in media outlets, has teamed up with RadioShack Corp to distribute 10 million personal code scanners to private homes; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most shoppers at the Virgin Megastore in Times Square who listen to cuts of, say, Macy Gray's new album, ''On How Life Is,'' essentially have two choices if they want to buy it: purchase the CD there for $17.99 or walk out and search elsewhere.</p>
        <p>But up-to-the-minute shoppers equipped with Verizon cellular phones capable of connecting to the Internet have another option. They can click on the icon for BarPoint.com Inc., an Internet database service, and punch in the CD's bar code. Those digits, unique to each product, can now be used as a shortcut to find a range of product-specific information: other CD's by the artists, for example, snippets of reviews, or exactly how much it costs at online stores. Later this year, BarPoint.com promises to list prices from the music store down the street as well.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most shoppers at the Virgin Megastore in Times Square who listen to cuts of, say, Macy Gray's new album, ''On How Life Is,'' essentially have two choices if they want to buy it: purchase the CD there for $17.99 or walk out and search elsewhere.</p>
        <p>But up-to-the-minute shoppers equipped with Verizon cellular phones capable of connecting to the Internet have another option. They can click on the icon for BarPoint.com Inc., an Internet database service, and punch in the CD's bar code. Those digits, unique to each product, can now be used as a shortcut to find a range of product-specific information: other CD's by the artists, for example, snippets of reviews, or exactly how much it costs at online stores. Later this year, BarPoint.com promises to list prices from the music store down the street as well.</p>
        <p>It seems an unlikely candidate for a star turn, but the humble bar code, long the quiet workhorse of retailing, is poised for the consumer equivalent of a cinematic close-up. BarPoint is one of the first to market with what will be many offerings that aim to make the irregularly striped rectangles (and their newfangled, information-laden cousins) the key link between products and consumers in the mobile shopping future.</p>
        <p>To be sure, that future implies a technological leap of faith in a society in which many people can still not program a VCR. After all, just because bar codes have found a niche in the business world does not mean consumers want to know them up close. General Electric recently previewed a refrigerator loaded with gee-whiz bar code technology, but has found consumer demand less than compelling.</p>
        <p>Still, companies from Motorola to G.E. are investing hundreds of millions of dollars in bar-code-related technologies on the bet that consumers will want, among other things, to scan products to get information, make lists, connect to the Web and complete purchases. Already built and being tested are everything from refrigerators that make shopping lists from the bar codes of the pizza and Swanson dinners in their freezer compartment to optical scanners that grab bar-coded coupons from televisions.</p>
        <p>The Uniform Code Council, the nonprofit consortium that doles out the codes that appear on almost every packaged product, from canned beans to laser printers, is working with music and publishing houses to match every song, and even every paragraph in books, with its own code that could be kept in a data base. The idea is eventually to allow consumers to mix and match their own creative products, while still permitting companies to gather royalties and information about use on an individual level. Other companies are racing to give magazine ads, segments on the evening news and even the weather chart in the local papers their own striped identity.</p>
        <p>Americans, who basically know bar codes from watching grocery clerks swipe them in front of scanners, are already being coaxed into deepening that relationship. In the last four months alone, the Digital:Convergence Corporation, which specializes in putting bar code links  to Web sites in media outlets and has developed partnerships with CNBC and Forbes magazine, among others, has teamed up with the RadioShack Corporation to distribute 10 million personal code scanners to private homes.</p>
        <p>And supposedly that is just the first wave. ''In the not too distant future,'' predicts Bob Sanders, vice president for e-commerce marketing at Symbol Technologies Inc., maker of the first hand-held laser scanner, ''the lion's share of cell phones will have bar code readers,'' as will Palm Pilots and the like.</p>
        <p>There are, of course, some significant barriers to overcome before the scanner becomes truly commonplace. Visionaries conjure a seamless future in which a consumer sees the perfect cashmere sweater, then uses the bar code to comparison-shop and perhaps place an order with the lowest bidder -- all with the swift swipe of the label with a hand-held device. But most technologies coming to market now are still fairly primitive and cumbersome to use.</p>
        <p>More problematic, many companies are developing their own proprietary system of codes that can be read only by licensed software or hardware. Consumers will almost certainly demand a universal system before they sign on in large numbers. A legal battle to sort out who will be the standard bearer could be brewing.</p>
        <p>Motorola and Symbol Technologies, for example, are both part of a consortium that has extensive patents covering numerous basic transactional functions -- using bar codes (they call their information-rich version scanlets) to purchase an item through a specific retailer, for example -- and is threatening to use the courts to block others from introducing competing systems. ''There has to be one set of scanlets or pandemonium will exist,'' said Rud Istvan, senior vice president and general manager for future business at Motorola.</p>
        <p>Then there is the more fundamental question of whether customers will really warm to swiping bar codes as a way to shop. In the years after 1974, when the first pack of Wrigley gum was scanned at an Ohio supermarket, shoppers showed deep distrust of bar codes. Several consumer groups, fearing that the new machines could be used to surreptitiously rob shoppers, lobbied state legislatures to mandate that each individual item continue to have a printed price tag.</p>
        <p>Despite the initial consumer suspicion, retailers rushed to embrace the technology because it gave them new power. The automated systems enabled them to accumulate vast stores of data on American purchasing habits, data that merchants, in turn, used to extract concessions from suppliers, who needed the information to stay competitive.</p>
        <p>''The bar code was created to speed up the checkout process,'' said Peter Sealey, co-director of the Center for Marketing and Technology at the University of California at Berkeley, ''but it gave the potential to capture point-of-sale data, and in the mid-1980's it shifted enormous power from the grocery manufacturers to the grocery sellers.''</p>
        <p>As bar codes proliferated, most consumers came to take them for granted, but the mysterious stripes never totally lost their power to confound and provoke. In 1992, President George Bush inadvertently bolstered his reputation for being out of touch with regular Americans when on a trip to a National Grocers Association conference he expressed amazement at a grocery scanner. And until recently, the Russian Orthodox Church condemned bar codes, seeing in their stripes ''the mark of the beast.''</p>
        <p>Manufacturers of the new bar code systems insist that American attitudes have turned 180 degrees and are even friendly to the technology. Many have done extensive market research and insist that early tests are positive. ''Everyone knows what a bar code is, and when you tell them you are going to have a bar code scanner, they know exactly what it is and is supposed to do,'' said Jane Evans, chief executive of Gamut Interactive, a new-media service company in Scottsdale, Ariz.</p>
        <p>In Phoenix in November, Gamut will start testing an optical scanner that reads a bar code-like signal that appears on television commercials. Viewers watching an advertisement for, say, Ralston Purina dog chow could click on their hand-held scanners when the bar code flashed on the screen and download e-coupons good for 15 percent off. The data will be housed in a smart card housed in the scanner, then redeemed later at the supermarket. Gamut already has 20 major companies -- including Colgate-Palmolive and Kraft Foods, a unit of the Philip Morris Companies -- participating in the pilot by adding special coding to their commercials.</p>
        <p>Digital:Convergence, which is distributing its :CueCat scanners free through magazines like Forbes and Wired and through RadioShack, is even more enthusiastic about customer response. ''Our research shows that 50 percent of those who get the cat install it immediately,'' said J. Jovan Philyaw, the chairman and chief executive. ''During business hours we get 1,000 to 5,000 users demanding their activation codes.''</p>
        <p>The :CueCat scans codes embedded in newspapers, magazines and television broadcasts and links the consumer directly to a Web site. Its big advantage, the company says, is that it can take a consumer deep into the site, not just to the home page. A reader with a :CueCat scanning an advertisement for a 2001 Ford Explorer could bypass Ford.com and jump directly to the page most relevant to the product.</p>
        <p>This past week, the company introduced the technology with WFAA-TV in Dallas. Through the use of audio prompts, viewers download Web sites that have more information. For the system to work, though, the device needs to be physically connected to both a television and a computer, and both need to be turned on. That kind of tethered system, rivals say, will not catch on with the public. Digital:Convergence responds that it will release a wireless version by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>The dissemination of the :CueCat scanners has also caused a bit of a backlash among privacy advocates. The Denver-based Privacy Foundation, an electronic-privacy watchdog, has said it is concerned that because each :CueCat comes with a serial number that correlates to its user, it could potentially track with new precision a user's reading and television habits. In theory, every swipe of a weather map or watch ad could be stored in a central data bank and resold. ''We cannot, we do not, and we will not track individual information,'' insists Michael Garin, the company's president.</p>
        <p>But privacy fears may be the least of the obstacles to the new technology. General Electric previewed new models of refrigerators that had all manner of bar code tricks at the  International Builders Show last winter. For example, the smart refrigerator not only reads the bar code of the Weight Watchers frozen dinner as it is pulled from the freezer, it adds the item to an electronic grocery list, then sends the cooking instruction to the microwave (assuming the appliances are linked) -- thus sparing the time-pressed cook from having to punch in ''7 minutes.''</p>
        <p>But despite aggressive testing of the product, General Electric now says no date has been set to bring it to market. Part of the problem is that consumers do not appear to think that swiping the bar code provides enough added convenience to warrant the trouble of changing habits. ''Put it this way,'' said Terry Dunn, a G.E. spokesman, ''if there were a more compelling market, we could have them out quickly.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
