<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>States' Drug Subsidy Programs Have Troubles of Their Own</title>
    <meta content="Y06MED$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/politics/06MEDI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freudenheim, Milt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E5DA173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1572" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>States' Drug Subsidy Programs Have Troubles of Their Own</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MILT FREUDENHEIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freudenheim, Milt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush chose Pennsylvania as place to announce his program to help states ease drug costs for those on Medicare; Pennsylvania and many other states are struggling with rising prescription drug costs and tight eligibility requirements that are excluding many older residents; how effective Bush's proposed federal subsidies would be in solving problems is in dispute (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pennsylvania has one of the nation's largest state-run drug-subsidy programs for its older low-income residents. So it seemed natural for Gov. George W. Bush to choose it last month as the place to announce his program to help states ease drug costs for those on Medicare.</p>
        <p>The thrust of Mr. Bush's proposal is to let managed care companies compete for patients with Medicare, the federal health insurance program for people 65 or older. Since the plan would not take effect for at least four years, Mr. Bush has proposed an interim step of allocating $48 billion -- $12 billion a year -- to subsidize state prescription drug plans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pennsylvania has one of the nation's largest state-run drug-subsidy programs for its older low-income residents. So it seemed natural for Gov. George W. Bush to choose it last month as the place to announce his program to help states ease drug costs for those on Medicare.</p>
        <p>The thrust of Mr. Bush's proposal is to let managed care companies compete for patients with Medicare, the federal health insurance program for people 65 or older. Since the plan would not take effect for at least four years, Mr. Bush has proposed an interim step of allocating $48 billion -- $12 billion a year -- to subsidize state prescription drug plans.</p>
        <p>But even as Mr. Bush announced his proposal, problems in Pennsylvania's program were increasing.</p>
        <p>Tens of thousands of participants have been forced off the plan, the Pharmaceutical Assistance Contract for the Elderly, because cost-of-living increases in their Social Security payments pushed their incomes above the program's eligibility ceilings, $14,000 for individuals and $17,200 for couples.</p>
        <p>And in three years, the program's drug costs rose by $100 million, to $300 million in the fiscal year ending in June -- even as the number of participants fell.</p>
        <p>Pennsylvania's experience is not unique. Fourteen states have programs in which participants can buy drugs at a nominal cost through government subsidies, according to the National Conference of State Legislatures. Six more have authorized or begun operations this year.</p>
        <p>But like the program in Pennsylvania, many are struggling with rising prescription drug costs and tight eligibility requirements that are excluding many older residents. And many of those who remain eligible are also left without coverage because of difficulties in enrolling, experts said.</p>
        <p>How effective Mr. Bush's proposed federal subsidies would be in solving these problems is in dispute.</p>
        <p>John Calfee, a health care analyst at the American Enterprise Institute, a Washington research center, said that the money could do ''a great deal'' to relieve the financial burden of elderly Americans who do not have drug coverage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Calfee said that total annual spending on drugs by people older than 65 was probably $30 billion to $40 billion, half of which was already covered by insurance or Medicaid, the federal and state program that helps pay for health care for low-income households.</p>
        <p>But Marilyn Moon, a Medicare expert at the Urban Institute, said that Mr. Bush's interim plan would fall short by its fourth and final year because more people would ask for help and drug prices would probably continue to rise.</p>
        <p>''The notion of $12 billion a year is wildly optimistic in view of the costs,'' Ms. Moon said.</p>
        <p>Spending in states with prescription drug programs was less than $1 billion in 1999. Twelve states for which figures are available spent a total of $765 million on drug subsidies in 1999, and obtained $134 million in rebates from drug companies, according to a report last month by the General Accounting Office. Most of that was spent by New York, New Jersey and Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>But even setting aside the issue of financing, experts on Medicare said that the added bureaucracy and application process the state programs require had shut out thousands of the elderly.</p>
        <p>''Seniors are not used to going to a state Medicaid or welfare office to prove that they are eligible,'' said Tricia Neuman, a Medicare policy specialist at the Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation in Menlo Park, Calif.</p>
        <p>Joe Baker, executive vice president of the Medicare Rights Center, a consumer service group for beneficiaries, said the state programs were complicated and hard for some elderly people to understand.</p>
        <p>In addition, more than half the  states have neither established nor authorized programs. For those states, the Bush proposal would require a new bureaucracy, said John McDonough, a former Massachusetts legislator who helped write that state's first drug-subsidy law.</p>
        <p>''It takes a lot of effort to reach and enroll eligible seniors in these programs,'' Mr. McDonough said. ''The states that have done it were those that decided on their own to invest state dollars to make these things happen.</p>
        <p>''If Congress and Governor Bush want to unload this responsibility on states that weren't asking for the programs, it will be much more difficult to reach the target populations quickly.''</p>
        <p>The National Governors' Association balked earlier this year at proposals in Congress for a new state-run prescription drug program.</p>
        <p>''If Congress decides to expand prescription drug coverage to seniors, it should not shift that responsibility or its costs to the states,'' the governors said in a statement.</p>
        <p>And the National Conference of State Legislatures said in July that additional Medicare costs for low-income people ''should be 100 percent federally funded.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Gail R. Wilensky, a Bush campaign adviser and former administrator of the government office that runs Medicare, said that giving money to the states was ''the fastest way to get money out short-term.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Wilensky said states could then expand existing subsidy programs or Medicaid or even plans now offered to state employees.</p>
        <p>But Mr. McDonough, a health policy expert at Brandeis University, said, ''The notion that this is a quick hit is flawed.''</p>
        <p>He pointed to Texas, where the Legislature meets every two years and usually adjourns on June 1.</p>
        <p>''If Congress passed the Bush plan next summer,'' he said, ''the next session of the Texas Legislature would be in 2003, and it would be hard to start a program there until the following year.''</p>
        <p>Nationwide, while 65 percent of those on Medicare have at least some drug coverage through another program, 13 million, or 35.4 percent, of elderly and disabled people have no prescription drug plan, according to an analysis by the Urban Institute, a policy research group in Washington.</p>
        <p>A study last year by AARP, formerly known as the American Association of Retired Persons, found that even those elderly with coverage can have high drug costs: 42 percent of Medicare beneficiaries who spent more than $1,000 of their own money a year on drugs had some type of drug coverage.</p>
        <p>Several states, including New York and Massachusetts, enacted laws this year intended to make it easier to qualify for programs. New York, which has 124,000 participants -- less than half of those now eligible -- will raise its income ceilings on Jan. 1, to $35,000 from $18,500 for individuals and $50,000 from $24,400 for couples. New York hopes to recruit 100,000 more participants in the next two years.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts will pay drug costs that run above $2,000, or above 10 percent of household income, for elderly and disabled people. Those with incomes that are more than 188 percent of the federal poverty level could also join and pay monthly premiums on a sliding scale up to $82, and make co-payments. The state would also pay the deductible and premiums for low-income people.</p>
        <p>''I have heard horror stories of husbands and wives trying to decide which one will take their medication'' because they could not afford both, said Lillian Glickman, head of the Massachusetts program.</p>
        <p>Thomas Snedden, director of Pennsylvania's program, which is financed by the state's lottery, said he was concerned that drug costs would overwhelm the lottery's entire $650 million net income within five years.</p>
        <p>''Other programs for older people,'' which are also financed by the lottery, ''would be pushed out,'' Mr. Snedden said.</p>
        <p>Even at its current financing levels, the Pennsylvania program is of little help to some of the elderly.</p>
        <p>Richard Hart, a retired bricklayer in Erie, Pa., and his wife, Nelda, both 73, have been cutting pills in half or, at times, skipping them to save money. They receive no state assistance because their income exceeds the limits for the Pennsylvania programs, which rise to $19,200 for people willing to pay the first $500, plus co-payments.</p>
        <p>The Harts had been spending almost a quarter of their monthly Social Security and pension income on 11 prescription drugs. But in July, they rode a bus to Canada and bought a three-month supply, saving $716.</p>
        <p>The Bush program's state subsidies are sizeable -- but Mr. Snedden wants to see the fine print.</p>
        <p>''We are ambivalent,'' he said. ''We want the help, but we want to know what the deal is, too, what strings come attached to it and where it leaves us four years from now'' when the money stops flowing.</p>
        <p>State officials said they feared that after the interim plan's four years, they would still be responsible for drug subsidies for thousands of people.</p>
        <p>Already, in five states where the elderly pay an annual fee or premium to obtain state subsidies, the programs are a magnet for those with the heaviest drug expenses. Elderly people with lower drug costs usually do not enroll.</p>
        <p>In focus groups sponsored by Blue Cross and Blue Shield in Florida to test interest in various types of drug coverage, consumers were adept at estimating whether their drug-related expenses would be more or less than the charges for a given insurance program.</p>
        <p>''Seniors do the math, and when the premium exceeds their projected costs, they won't buy it,'' said Scott Serota, president of the national Blue Cross and Blue Shield Association in Washington.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
