<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Four Natural Gas Utilities Seek Emergency Rate Increases</title>
    <meta content="06GAS.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/nyregion/06GAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236499"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heating Fuel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Public Service Electric &amp; Gas Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Elizabethtown Gas</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">South Jersey Gas Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Natural Gas</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EED7173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Four Natural Gas Utilities Seek Emergency Rate Increases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey's four natural gas supply companies, citing sharply higher wholesale costs on eve of winter heating season, are seeking emergency rate increases of 16.7 percent to 31.9 percent (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citing sharply higher wholesale costs on the eve of the winter heating season, New Jersey's four natural-gas supply companies are seeking emergency rate increases of 16.7 percent to 31.9 percent.</p>
        <p>The proposals were submitted to the state's regulatory agency, the Board of Public Utilities, on Wednesday. If approved, the proposals would increase a typical gas user's costs for the winter heating months, November through March, by a total of $133 to $261.05, depending on the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Citing sharply higher wholesale costs on the eve of the winter heating season, New Jersey's four natural-gas supply companies are seeking emergency rate increases of 16.7 percent to 31.9 percent.</p>
        <p>The proposals were submitted to the state's regulatory agency, the Board of Public Utilities, on Wednesday. If approved, the proposals would increase a typical gas user's costs for the winter heating months, November through March, by a total of $133 to $261.05, depending on the company.</p>
        <p>The proposed monthly increases, when figured for 200 therms, the typical amount for a house with gas heat, would be: New Jersey Natural Gas Company, $26.60; Public Service Electric and Gas, $33.43; Elizabethtown Gas Company, $48.80; and South Jersey Gas Company, $52.21, the four suppliers said yesterday.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's utility watchdog agency, the Division of the Ratepayer Advocate, criticized the proposed increases yesterday as excessive and asked instead that the utilities board approve an across-the-board increase of 17 percent for all four companies. The director of the division, Blossom A. Peretz, conceded that her 17 percent proposal was the highest in her five-year tenure.</p>
        <p>''This is high, but we haven't had a crisis like this since I've been in this position,'' Ms. Peretz said. ''It's an extraordinary amount because it's an extraordinary time.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Peretz and officials of the four utilities said wholesale natural gas prices had more than doubled in recent months. New Jersey regulations allow gas utilities to pass along wholesale price increases dollar for dollar, and require that drops in the wholesale price also be passed along on the same basis.</p>
        <p>Company officials said the proposed increases reflected only the higher wholesale cost and contained no money for higher profits.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peretz said her proposed 17 percent increase was an interim one, intended to decrease if wholesale prices drop in coming months or if the winter is warmer than usual and customers use less natural gas than utilities now project.</p>
        <p>Ms. Peretz also asked the utilities board to approve a plan that would allow homeowners with sharply higher bills to extend their payments over time instead of paying them each month as now required. And she appealed to the board to broaden a campaign for conservation of natural gas and to increase assistance for low-income customers. ''We cannot leave New Jersey ratepayers out in the cold this winter,'' Ms. Peretz said in a statement.</p>
        <p>The board is scheduled to consider Ms. Peretz's request and the utilities proposals at a meeting in Newark on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Wholesale prices for natural gas are going up sharply around the country, according to the Natural Gas Supply Association, an organization based in Washington that represents producers of about 30 percent of the country's natural gas.</p>
        <p>In the last year, wholesale prices across the country have increased from an average of 21.5 cents a therm to about 53 cents, said Rhone Resch, a spokesman for the association. Gas utilities across the country face the same price pressures, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Resch said increased demand for natural gas in recent months had pushed up wholesale prices, encouraging more drilling for gas in Texas, Louisiana, Colorado and Utah. In the last two years, he said, deflated gas prices, mild winters in the Northeast and abundant storage had dampened production.</p>
        <p>The increased demand, he said, started with a chilly snap in the Northeast late last winter and continued during prolonged hot spells during the summer in the Southwest and California.</p>
        <p>Existing supplies were drawn down, he said, to supply heat in the Northeast in the late winter and to run electrical generators supplying power to air-conditioners in the Southwest heat wave.</p>
        <p>''There's not a shortage of natural gas,'' Mr. Resch said. ''It's just a tightening of the market. Now producers are out there trying to produce as much as possible.'' Since April 1999, the number of drilling rigs actively searching for new supplies increased from about 370 to 800, he said.</p>
        <p>''There will be plenty of new supply coming on line, but it takes time,'' he said. He estimated that it would be 3 to 18 months before significant new supplies would reach the market and possibly start reducing wholesale prices. But for now, it appears, there is no relief in sight, officials at the four New Jersey utilities said.</p>
        <p>Three of the four filing amended petitions for increases on Wednesday sought higher increases than they had sought in mid- or late summer, and the fourth refiled the same increase.</p>
        <p>In September, Public Service Electric and Gas, the largest of the companies with 1.6 million gas customers, asked for a 13 percent increase, said Kathy Ellis, a spokeswoman. But in October, she said, the company's wholesale price jumped 14.6 cents a therm to 56.6 cents. That prompted the company to ask for a 24 percent increase instead.</p>
        <p>Similarly, South Jersey Gas Company asked for a 31.9 percent increase on Wednesday, up from the 19 percent it sought in August, said Albert Ruggiero, the company's senior vice president. And Elizabethtown Gas increased its request to 29.9 percent from 17 percent, said Chris Reardon, a spokesman.</p>
        <p>New Jersey Natural Gas Company refiled its July request for a 16.7 percent increase, so its 400,000 customers would have the smallest increase, said Marion Hodge, a spokeswoman.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
