<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="06DIGE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236498"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEFD7173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>European Central Bank Increases Interest Rates  Treading a thin line between the risks of higher inflation and stifled growth, the European Central Bank made a surprise decision to increase interest rates, reflecting its concern over rising prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>European Central Bank Increases Interest Rates  Treading a thin line between the risks of higher inflation and stifled growth, the European Central Bank made a surprise decision to increase interest rates, reflecting its concern over rising prices.</p>
        <p>The quarter-point rise, to 4.75 percent, was the seventh increase made by the central bank this year. The bank moved the same day that the Bank of England decided to hold British rates steady and two days after the Federal Reserve left interest rates alone. [Page C6.]</p>
        <p>South Korea's central bank raised interest rates, alarmed by four consecutive months of rising inflation. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Tougher Tax Shelter Rules Proposed  Leaders of the Senate Finance Committee proposed tough new laws to crack down on abusive corporate tax shelters and to impose hefty penalties on those who promote sham transactions to evade taxes. [C6.]</p>
        <p>September Retail Sales Rose 3.3%  Sales at retail stores open at least a year rose 3.3 percent in September, but many stores were offering deeply discounted prices, which will probably cut into profits for the quarter and for the year. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Murdoch Son Named to a Top Post  The News Corporation said that Lachlan Murdoch, the oldest son of the company's chairman, Rupert Murdoch, had been named deputy chief operating officer, the No. 3 position at the company. Lachlan Murdoch, 29, left, has long been his father's heir apparent and is expected to one day run the media giant, in which the Murdoch family holds 31 percent of the voting shares. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Stocks Drop on Earnings Worries  Stocks slid, weighed down by concerns about earnings. The Nasdaq composite index fell 51 points, or 1.5 percent, to 3,472.10. The Dow Jones industrials dropped 59.56 points, or 0.6 percent, to 10,724.92. The S.&amp; P. 500 rose 1.96 points, to 1,436.28. [C7.]</p>
        <p>Talks Raise Anxiety at Utah Paper  The Salt Lake City Tribune has long been the largest newspaper in Utah without a connection to the Mormon church. Now talks between a Mormon-owned company and The Tribune's parent have raised fears at The Tribune that its independent voice could be eroded. [C2.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
