<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="06POP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EEDB163CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="3368" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POP AND JAZZ GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>MARY J. BLIGE, Radio City Music Hall, 1260 Avenue of the Americas, at 50th Street, (212) 247-4777. Few lovefests in pop are as overwhelming as a concert by the queen of hip-hop soul. Running through her hefty catalog of hits, Ms. Blige belts, moans and testifies about love lost or worth losing, and her soul sisters in the audience moan and belt right back. Sometimes Ms. Blige even celebrates the joy of love and the fun of sex, and then the house really comes down. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; tickets are $35 to $75 (Ann Powers).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy pop and jazz concerts in the New York metropolitan region this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended concert.</p>
        <p>MARY J. BLIGE, Radio City Music Hall, 1260 Avenue of the Americas, at 50th Street, (212) 247-4777. Few lovefests in pop are as overwhelming as a concert by the queen of hip-hop soul. Running through her hefty catalog of hits, Ms. Blige belts, moans and testifies about love lost or worth losing, and her soul sisters in the audience moan and belt right back. Sometimes Ms. Blige even celebrates the joy of love and the fun of sex, and then the house really comes down. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; tickets are $35 to $75 (Ann Powers).</p>
        <p>KARAN CASEY, Fez, 380 Lafayette Street, at Great Jones Street, East Village, (212) 533-2680. Karan Casey first caught the ears of New Yorkers as the singer for Solas, the brashest and best Celtic band on that bustling circuit. She is on her own now, reaching back into the songbook of her native County Waterford to record her second solo album, which will surely show evidence of the thoroughly modern attitude. Sunday at 9:30 p.m.; admission is $15 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* AVISHAI COHEN QUINTET, Fat Cat, 75 Christopher Street, West Village, (212) 675-6056. Mr. Cohen is a bassist who found his niche in New York about five years ago at Smalls and has gone on to a position in Chick Corea's dynamic new band as well as his own career as a bandleader. He has dynamite technique, strong melodic ideas and a sensible kind of cultural syncretism, mixing North African, Middle Eastern and Spanish elements with jazz. His performances this weekend -- in which he plays piano, his other instrument -- open the Fat Cat, a new billiards hall that also has a jazz room and is being booked by Mitch Borden, who until yesterday was the owner and operator of Smalls. It could be the beginning of an important new chapter in the underground jazz scene. (Smalls is moving north; see Stanley Turrentine tribute below for details.) Sets today and tomorrow at 10 p.m., midnight and 1 a.m.; admission is $10; no minimum (Ben Ratliff).</p>
        <p>KARL DENSON'S TINY UNIVERSE, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Union Square, (212) 777-1600. You may not have heard of Karl Denson, but D'Angelo has. The constantly touring soul prince recently nabbed Mr. Denson, a saxophonist and flutist, and his band as an opening act. Jack DeJohnette, former associate of Miles Davis, and Fred Wesley, pal of James Brown, also know Mr. Denson; they have both recorded with him. The hippie kids who like jam music know him, as do acid jazz fans, because his band draws big crowds from both scenes for their funky, vintage-soul, futuristic sets. Perhaps Mr. Denson's universe won't be so tiny for very long. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; tickets are $18.50 in advance; $20 at the door (Powers).</p>
        <p>DONALD EDWARDS QUINTET, Up Over Jazz Cafe, 351 Flatbush Avenue, Park Slope, Brooklyn, (718) 398-5413. Mr. Edwards, from New Orleans, was the drummer in Wessell Anderson's band in the mid-90's; he has kept a low profile as a bandleader but arrives here with what looks like a pretty high-level band, including the vibraphonist Stefon Harris, the guitarist Mark Whitfield, the bassist Zachary Pride and the pianist George Colligan. Sets are tonight and tomorrow night at 9, 10:30 and midnight; cover charge is $15 a set; $5 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>ROBERTA FLACK, B. B. King's Blues Club and Grill, 237 West 42nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 997-4144. Behind the gentle, tremulous voice that confided hits like ''The First Time Ever I Saw Your Face'' is long knowledge of the continuum of blues, gospel, soul and jazz. Ms. Flack can use just a touch of rawness to make her songs hit home. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and 10:30; tickets are $65 (Jon Pareles).</p>
        <p>VON FREEMAN, Smoke, 2751 Broadway, at 106th Street, (212) 864-6662. What a fresh style the tenor saxophonist Von Freeman has, and he has been polishing it in Chicago, his hometown, for 50 years. He's not a pattern-player; as he takes his tempos slowly and vocalizes idiosyncratically through the horn, he's a nuancer, a finesser, a luxuriator. An awful lot of jazz makes you feel intelligent if you follow it; his makes you feel good as well. He is accompanied by the pianist Mulgrew Miller, the bassist John Webber and the drummer Joe Farnsworth. Sets tonight and tomorrow night are at 9, 11 and 12:30; cover charge is $20; no minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* MERLE HAGGARD, BR5-49, MALCOLM HOLCOMBE, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Union Square, (212) 777-6800. When young country singers aren't imitating George Jones, they're imitating Merle Haggard: his clenched-jaw delivery, his easygoing swing, his weary dignity and his honky-tonk resilience. In his own songs, Mr. Haggard is a drifter and a convict, a broken-hearted drunk and a hard-working breadwinner; he's also a down-home country singer who is an unabashed jazz fan. Like every improviser, he has off nights, but on a good one he is among America's greatest musicians. BR5-49 is determined to recreate the halycon days of country music, from Western swing to trucker songs to close-harmony two-beats, adding slyly modern lyrics. Malcolm Holcombe has a grizzled, slurred voice that sounds completely convincing in folky songs about endless, uncertain wanderings. Sunday at 7 p.m.; tickets are $37.50 in advance, $40 on Sunday (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* BERES HAMMOND, Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 564-4882. It took two decades for the suave tenor and lovers' promises of the reggae singer Beres Hammond to gain him an international reputation, but now he has emerged as an ardent nice guy amid the tough posturing of dance hall reggae. He is a crooner who knows how to float his voice over digital rhythms. Sunday at 7:30 p.m.; tickets are $35 to $75 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>CARL HANCOCK RUX, Joe's Pub, 425 Lafayette Street, at Astor Place, East Village, (212) 539-8778 or (212) 239-6200. A poet, novelist, secular preacher and hip-hop provocateur, Carl Hancock Rux always thrills with his incendiary shows. This one, ''The No Black Male Show,'' will showcase that piece, a look at the limits of packaged blackness in pop, plus others from his excellent repertory. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30; tickets are $15 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* TOM HARRELL SEXTET, Village Vanguard, 178 Seventh Avenue South, at 11th Street, West Village, (212) 255-4037. Mr. Harrell's flugelhorn playing is a model of willed precision: it's like hearing someone talk extemporaneously without using the connectives ''uh,'' ''so,'' ''you know'' or anything else to forestall the goal of complete meaning at the end of the discourse. He'll repeat a riff once or twice or drag a note, but it's an unremovable part of a plan; he edits out all the storyteller flourishes that trumpet players are fond of: high whinnies, low growls, blues mannerisms. And despite a beautiful, cottony sound, he's not exactly a cool player, either. He just stays within one basic range of volume and tone to produce a melodically strong outpouring, shot through with triplet phrases and using the entire range of the instrument. Musicians love him, and he always has a few younger players in the band to whom you should be paying attention. Sets through Sunday night are at 9:30 and 11:30, with a 1 a.m. set tonight and tomorrow; cover: $20 tonight and tomorrow; $15 Sunday; $10 minimum all sets (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>BARRY HARRIS-CHARLES DAVIS QUINTET, Sweet Basil, 88 Seventh Avenue South, above Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 242-1785. Mr. Harris, the pianist who is one of the great musicians to come out of Detroit in the 1950's, remains an indefatigable champion of bebop-era music -- a Bud Powell and Thelonious Monk man through and through. He is so famous around the world as a teacher of aspiring musicians that his performing career hasn't been what it could have been; that's precisely the sort generosity that comes across when you see him live, alongside the baritone saxophonist Charles Davis, who also has that mid-century Midwestern (Chicago) jazz pedigree. Sets through Sunday night are at 9 and 11, with a 12:30 a.m. set tonight and tomorrow night; cover charge is $20 at the door tonight and tomorrow, $18 Sunday; $10 minimum (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>HOMOCORPS, CBGB, 315 Bowery, at Bleecker Street, East Village, (212) 982-4052. Dean Johnson, organizer of Homocorps, presents another night of counter-assaults against creeping conservatism by rock 'n' rollers glad to be gay. This evening opens things up to the ladies, biological and otherwise, with Hattie Hathaway as guest host and featured sets by the male-female rap duo Morplay and Karen Kuhl of Sexpod. Also performing are Paxton, Xavier, Carol Channing Rox, Page and, of course, Mr. Johnson's outrageous outfit, the Velvet Mafia. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; admission is $12 (Powers).</p>
        <p>ISRAEL VIBRATION, Irving Plaza, 17 Irving Place, at 15th Street, Union Square, (212) 777-6800. Israel Vibration's members met as children at a polio rehabilitation center; now they harmonize in devout, steadfast, ''conscious reggae'' songs about suffering and the faith that carries them through. They'll be backed by the Roots Radics. Tonight at 11 (doors open at 9); tickets are $25 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>JETS TO BRAZIL, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. Blake Scharzenbach, formerly the guitarist and songwriter in Jawbreaker, now leads Jets to Brazil, and he still believes in the promise of indie rock: that sinewy guitar lines, oblique but articulate lyrics and unabashedly anthemic choruses can move an audience. The songs are forthright about both their intelligence and their emotion. Sunday at 7:30 p.m., with Hey Mercedes opening; admission is $12 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* LAIKA, Mercury Lounge, 217 Houston Street, at Ludlow Street, Lower East Side, (212) 260-4700. Laika's songs hover on the fringes of electronica, pop, rock and hip-hop, refusing to touch down. Margaret Fiedler calmly croons or rhymes above rippling, echoing, dreamlike tracks. Tomorrow night at 9 and Sunday night at 8, with King Cobb Steelie opening; admission is $15 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* CHARLES LLOYD, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. Mr. Lloyd, the tenor saxophonist, is a Coltraneist, but you can easily tell him from his model. He has a softer sound, and it's not just the diagonal way he holds his horn that reminds you of Lester Young. He has quietly been making a series of first-rate records on the ECM label; ''The Water Is Wide,'' which includes Ellington, Strayhorn, a spiritual and some originals, is the latest, and half the crew heard on that album, including the guitarist John Abercrombie, the bassist Marc Johnson and the drummer Billy Higgins, will be with him. Sets are tonight and tomorrow night at 8 and 10; tickets are $20 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* JUNIOR MANCE, Kaplan Penthouse, 10th floor, Rose Building, Lincoln Center, (212) 721-6500. Mr. Mance is giving solo piano performances in the Jazz at the Penthouse series of Jazz at Lincoln Center. Now in his mid-70's, he is an excitable, physical player who throws himself into fast tempos and long up-the-keyboard rolls that aren't heard much outside Oscar Peterson. But he is also an earthy blues-and-bop player from Chicago; his resume includes time spent in the bands of Dinah Washington, Dizzy Gillespie and Cannonball Adderley. Concerts are tonight and tomorrow night at 8; tickets are $45 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>KEVIN NORTON, Knitting Factory, Old Office, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. Mr. Norton, the composer and drummer who has played with Anthony Braxton, has a structuralist mind-set, and he puts curious groups through his music. Tonight's double-bill begins with his Metaphor Quintet at 8, featuring Masahiko Kono on trumpet and electronics, and moves on to his Ensemble at 9:30, a septet with the clarinetist David Kracauer invited as a guest. Tomorrow and Sunday at 8 p.m. he plays both sets with his Ensemble. Cover charge is $8 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>OGANS, S.O.B's, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940. Salvador, the capital of Bahia, Brazil, is a cornucopia of buoyant rhythms and irresistible pop tunes. Ogans, a band of booming drummers backing a singer, plays a repertory of Bahian hits that incorporates both the sophisticated tunes of tropicalia and the frenetic, lightheartedly raunchy songs of Bahia's more recent craze, axe. The band's Brazilian fans show up in force to dance and sing along. Tomorrow night at 8, 10 and midnight; admission is $20 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>PLENA LIBRE, Symphony Space, 2537 Broadway, at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400. Plena Libre are the ambassadors of the plena, a century-old Puerto Rican music played with panderos, single-headed, tuned hand drums. Foragers of New World music that they are, they manage to fuse the plena instrumentation with samba, salsa, songo and other kinds of Latin music. They're also a great dance band. Tonight at 8; tickets are $26 (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* MARC RIBOT Y LOS CUBANOS POSTIZOS, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111. The guitarist Marc Ribot, who may be best known for his time with Tom Waits, started Los Cubanos Postizos (''the prosthetic Cubans'') to play songs he loves from Cuba in the 1940's and 1950's from the repertory of Arsenio Rodriguez. He honors the tunes but isn't afraid to add some downtown clank and down-home twang in his solos. Tonight at 9; admission is $15. (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* THE ROOTS, TALIB KWELI, RAH DIGGA, DEAD PREZ, BAHAMADIA, JAZZYFATNASTEES, Hammerstein Ballroom, 311 West 34th Street, Manhattan, (212) 564-4882. The Roots, from Philadelphia, want hip-hop to move out of its gangsta-rap niche. They skip the tales of gunplay to rhyme about community-building, good times and the possibility of better ones; they also work with a jazz-tinged live band. They're sharing this tour with the politically minded rappers Talib Kweli, Dead Prez and Rah Digga (who toughs it out as ''Harriet Thugman''), with the fast-talking rap poetess Bahamadia, and with the sweetly troubled pop-soul songs of Jazzyfatnastees. Tomorrow at 8 p.m.; tickets are $28.50 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>* SAINT ETIENNE, LADYBUG TRANSISTOR, Bowery Ballroom, 6 Delancey Street, near the Bowery, Lower East Side, (212) 533-2111. Pop eras melt into one another in the songs of Saint Etienne; Abba meets Motown, Burt Bacharach runs into Erasure. Singing about love affairs going right and (more often) wrong, Sarah Cracknell, Saint Etienne's poised chanteuse, details romance as a roundelay of joy, heartbreak and new possibilities. The songs are smart and tuneful, reveling in allusions but never condescending to them; they cherish the seeming naivete of pop and all the craftsmanship behind it. Ladybug Transistor seeks a middle ground between the calmer side of the Velvet Underground and the horns, flute and keyboards of bands like the Association and the Fifth Dimension. Tomorrow and Sunday at 9 p.m.; on Sunday Kings of Convenience are also on the bill. Admission is $20 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>THE SCENE IS NOW, FRANKLIN BRUNO, Tonic, 107 Norfolk Street, near Delancey Street, Lower East Side, (212) 358-7503. Underground rock fans know The Scene Is Now because Yo La Tengo covered ''Yellow Sarong,'' but there is much more to this loose congregation of Lower East Side bohemians than that one jaunty tune. In fact, with its ever-changing membership, you never know quite what they will bring to the stage. It is easier to predict what Franklin Bruno will offer; the super-witty philosophy teacher and former leader of Nothing Painted Blue always has more arch yet heartfelt tunes up his sleeve. He is supporting a new album, ''Kiss Without Makeup'' (Absolutely Kosher); thus this rare New York gig. Sunday at 8 p.m.; tickets are $8 (Powers).</p>
        <p>* RAVI SHANKAR, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800. Ravi Shankar singlehandedly opened the subtleties of Indian classical improvisation to a Western audience -- not by simplifying the music, but by directly communicating the songful delicacy and speedy, virtuosic delights of the raga. He now shares the stage with his 17-year-old daughter, Anoushka, a skillful player who is just beginning to improvise. Tonight at 8; tickets are $19 to $73. Sold out but returns may be available (Pareles).</p>
        <p>MARIA SCHNEIDER ORCHESTRA, Jazz Standard, 116 East 27th Street, Manhattan, (212) 576-2232. Ms. Schneider, a young composer and former student of Gil Evans who has kept a large jazz orchestra in business for a good part of the 1990's and beyond, doesn't rely on standard formulas to structure her pieces. They're not small-group tunes simply dressed up and expanded, but truly integrated ensemble music, and on her new album, ''Allegresse,'' she has 19 band members exploring their rich harmonies. Sets tonight and tomorrow night are at 8, 10:30 and midnight, with a $25 cover charge; Sunday night sets are at 7 and 9, with a $18 cover; $10 minimum on all sets (Ratliff).</p>
        <p>* AMON TOBIN, LAKE TROUT, Knitting Factory, 74 Leonard Street, TriBeCa, (212) 219-3006. Amon Tobin builds atmospheric sound collages with locomotion at their core, whether they're ambling or strutting or sputtering or surging; he is one of the few disc jockeys who are not afraid to leave 4/4 time behind. Lake Trout, which opens the bill, has evolved from a jazz group to a band that translates the computerized break beats of drum-and-bass into live performance. Sunday at 11 p.m.; admission is $12 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>THE TRAGICALLY HIP, Town Hall, 123 West 43rd Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824. New York's relatively invisible Canadian contingent always turns out in force for the Tragically Hip, a band that's hugely popular up north. Long before the Dave Matthews Band or the Wallflowers, the Tragically Hip was matching disillusioned lyrics to 1960's-flavored folk-rock, turning riff songs into chipper extended jams that throw off their frustration in brash guitar workouts. Tonight at 8; tickets are $28.50 (Pareles).</p>
        <p>EL VEZ, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, at 11th Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 798-0406. Fans can always expect something extra from the Mexican Elvis, as this Los Angeles-based postmodern punk rocker has called himself for years. What could be more appropriate right now than a campaign? ''El Vez for Prez'' promises to be a one-man debate with much wild music and amusing political satire. As El Rey says, it's a ''Red, White and Blue Suede Shoe Espectaculo.'' Sunday at 9 p.m.; tickets are $10 (Powers).</p>
        <p>MIKE WATT AND THE PAIR OF PLIERS, Maxwell's, 1039 Washington Street, Hoboken, N.J., (201) 798-0406. The philosopher king of American indie rock recently survived emergency groin surgery, and on his Web site he has been complaining about having to wear underwear while playing bass. Reports from this tour with his latest power trio, however, allay any fears that Mr. Watt's personal constriction might dim the musical din. An additional treat for California punk aficionados: this group includes Tom Watson, the guitarist who made such fine fractured music with the band Slovenly. With Bargain Music and Stereobate. Tonight at 10; tickets are $10 (Powers).</p>
        <p>THE WHO, THE WALLFLOWERS, Madison Square Garden, (212) 465-6741. There's no doubt this bill was better when Jimmy Page and the Black Crowes shared it. Guitar gods, classic rock, torch-passing -- all those themes were better served by that intergenerational pairing than they are by matching the great English power trio with the smoothly earnest junior savants who back up Jakob Dylan. But what the heck, the Who still astound with sheer inappropriate ambition. Enjoy the mountain-building while you can. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7:30; tickets are $51 to $250 (Powers).</p>
        <p>CHARLIE WILSON, S.O.B.'s, 204 Varick Street, at Houston Street, South Village, (212) 243-4940. As lead singer of the Gap Band, Charlie Wilson sang love songs and party tunes, pouring his melismatic tenor into 1970's and 80's hits like ''You Dropped a Bomb on Me'' and ''Outstanding.'' Hip-hop kids grew up on the Gap Band, sampled their songs and collaborated with Mr. Wilson. On his new solo album, ''Bridging the Gap,'' Mr. Wilson collects some dues from the younger generation, with guest appearances by Angie Stone and Mr. Wilson's nephew, Snoop Dogg; they may show up for this gig. Tonight at 7; admission is $10 (Pareles).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
