<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Fashion; In Milan, Specters and a Suspicion</title>
    <meta content="06DRES$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/living/06DRES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Horyn, Cathy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elbaz, Alber</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Audibet, Marc</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mara, Max</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armani, Giorgio</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sander, Jil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DC173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Fashion; In Milan, Specters and a Suspicion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cathy Horyn reviews new women's fashions from designers Tom Ford, Alber Elbaz, Marc Audibet, Max Mara, Giorgio Armani and Jil Sander as shown in Milan, Italy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Someone once said that the first casualty of war is truth, and to the extent that fashion shows resemble a kind of sensory ground assault, with hundreds of outfits coming at you and the big houses frankly demanding oaths of loyalty from editors and retailers, hardly any of them will tell a designer his show was a dud. Instead, they resort to such stock backstage laurels as ''You've done it again!'' or the always enigmatic, ''Unforgettable.''</p>
        <p>Thus Tom Ford was probably spared having to hear what he surely must have felt in his bones: that his Gucci show on Tuesday night was not just truly ugly, but also seemed completely at odds with his reputation as a designer who loves women. Sure, a young woman who goes out a lot, who wants something luxe but trashy to wear next spring on the banquettes at Moomba, may go in for a pair of purple satin cargo pants. She wants a new thing, all right, and none of that aging jet-set glamour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Someone once said that the first casualty of war is truth, and to the extent that fashion shows resemble a kind of sensory ground assault, with hundreds of outfits coming at you and the big houses frankly demanding oaths of loyalty from editors and retailers, hardly any of them will tell a designer his show was a dud. Instead, they resort to such stock backstage laurels as ''You've done it again!'' or the always enigmatic, ''Unforgettable.''</p>
        <p>Thus Tom Ford was probably spared having to hear what he surely must have felt in his bones: that his Gucci show on Tuesday night was not just truly ugly, but also seemed completely at odds with his reputation as a designer who loves women. Sure, a young woman who goes out a lot, who wants something luxe but trashy to wear next spring on the banquettes at Moomba, may go in for a pair of purple satin cargo pants. She wants a new thing, all right, and none of that aging jet-set glamour.</p>
        <p>But can any woman honestly picture herself in a bra whose conical cups look as if they were dispensed from a Dixie holder and then caught in a wringer, so that the breasts themselves appear hateful and freakish? There was a time in the 1980's when women's breasts and bottoms were being accentuated, even perverted, but the difference between then and now is that the  ringleaders -- namely, Azzedine Alaia, Thierry Mugler and Jean Paul Gaultier -- were experimenting with new, moldable fabrics. Their clothes looked aggressive, and they certainly rattled people's cages, but there was a legitimate reason behind the  outrage. Those designers were using technology to create new forms of excitement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford's awkward little cups had the unfortunate effect of not advancing a new style, but reviving an almost buried suspicion that male designers were secretly reviling women and their bodies. He would object to that accusation, but what other conclusion can be drawn from showing a boned cage on the outside of a sheer top, with the model's breasts circumscribed by two hard, half-moon stays in a kind of exoskeleton?</p>
        <p>On the morning of his show, at a press conference, Mr. Ford had said he was tired of his linear silhouette of the past few seasons and that he wanted to give more volume to his clothes. Though he didn't go into specifics, the picture one got was of some gentle, thoughtful change that was consistent with the style that is identified with Gucci. This collection represented such an illogical break, however, that it made one wonder if Mr. Ford was trying to avoid any obvious comparisons between his work for Gucci and what he'll do next week when he shows his first ready-to-wear collection for Yves Saint Laurent.</p>
        <p>Certainly he is under extreme pressure. He is taking up a label with almost mythic associations while its creator, Mr. Saint Laurent, is still alive. Yet, in trying to push Gucci in a tough, radically different direction and wipe clean the Saint Laurent references he used to make in his clothes, he only ended up giving the impression that his choices were somehow a reaction to Mr. Saint Laurent. And that just made the Saint Laurent specter loom up in Mr. Ford's collection like a haunting shadow.</p>
        <p>Who would have imagined that Mr. Saint Laurent would factor in absentia in two Milanese spring 2001 collections, and in such different ways?</p>
        <p>Alber Elbaz, who was at Saint Laurent until this past February, is now designing a line for Krizia. It's called Krizia Top, to reflect more handwork and a 30-percent-higher price than the established line. Mr. Elbaz's collection was terrific. There were undeniable references to Saint Laurent's chic, effortless style -- the way a loose caftan in white cotton draped on the body, the cut of a shoulder and the use of chunky  crystal in the accessories.</p>
        <p>Yet, the appealing thing in Mr. Elbaz's collection -- and, indeed, in a number of shows this week -- was his stubborn, almost old-fashioned insistence on making clothes that weren't based on the latest trends but on the real notion of individual style. ''For me, proportion is the most important thing,'' he said. ''It's not styling or shoes. It's proportion. Forget design!''</p>
        <p>Marc Audibet's collection for Ferragamo on Wednesday showed a similar strength. At one point he sent out a couple of models in leather and suede dresses that draped from the shoulders in toga-like folds. They were open on the sides, and the models were bare underneath, but what that told you was just that Mr. Audibet, one of fashion's unsung heroes, was giving women the chance to decide for themselves how to wear the simple but ingenious look.</p>
        <p>Domenico Dolce and Stefano Gabbana stood their ground, too, with a witty collection today: sleek stretch suits over lacy bras, embroidered fringed trousers that resembled western chaps, and white T-shirts printed with different Madonna album covers, twinkling with rhinestones and kitsch.</p>
        <p>And the Max Mara show, on Tuesday, was full of great clothes -- distressed leather mixed with khaki and charmeuse, and some fine renditions of the military look. They brought to mind the days when Italian sportswear had its own style.</p>
        <p>No one understands that style better than Giorgio Armani, whose superb collection on Wednesday displayed a lithe, easy elegance. Oh, he got a little carried away with his spunky suspenders, but then there were feather-light jackets in lavender linen over slim trousers or pastel slips. A cropped jacket with a delicately ruffled edge looked, from a distance, like checked cloth. In fact, it was suede.</p>
        <p>This has been a strangely jarring week in Milan, with surprises in unexpected places, and intrigue everywhere. On Wednesday, Patrizio Bertelli, the chief executive of Prada, presented the first Jil Sander collection since he parted company with Ms. Sander, the label's founder. On the one hand, the team of designers who put together the collection seemed to work in a younger, tougher vein than Ms. Sander's. Shirts had an almost shrunken effect, with skirts gathered and turned out at the waist. Jackets tucked into the backs of shorts and trousers, and the palette was somber, almost drab.</p>
        <p>But in another sense, the clothes Mr. Bertelli presented seemed conspicuously without a designer, and missing were Ms. Sander's subtle details. As a collection that drew upon Ms. Sander's archival looks, it was not bad, but it needed a stronger element of design. And one couldn't help wondering if Mr. Bertelli wasn't making a statement with his choice of music, a Serge Gainsborough song from the early 60's whose title translates roughly as ''Requiem for Idiots.''</p>
        <p>He shrugged off the suggestion over lunch after the show. And he has no plans, he said, to hire a designer to replace Ms. Sander. ''Everyone was concerned after the show whether we were to hire a new designer or whether the team was smart enough,'' he said, with some defiance. ''Backstage, the press kept asking, 'Who's going to be the next Jil Sander?' But I think that's only a question that interests the press. Consumers could not care less. And we're going to sell 30 percent more this season.''</p>
        <p>He went on to describe what he thinks will be the forces behind fashion and how younger generations will respond to it. ''Order and chaos,'' he said. ''People will be extreme in their feelings. We won't have average fashion -- we'll have luxury and jeans. Hermes and Nike.'' He added: ''It's a trash culture. And that's what Armani doesn't understand. I mean, the bourgeois culture is not just bourgeois -- it's that and trash. It's the spirit of our times.''</p>
        <p>That sentiment makes some people nervous, and more than a few think Mr. Bertelli's approach is dangerous to fashion. Karl Lagerfeld, who said he liked Mr. Bertelli, offered a different view -- off the cuff, but somehow wise. He was in his studio here, going over looks for his Fendi show. ''Yes,'' he said, ''but everyone is dangerous.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
