<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Civil Clash, Cheney and Lieberman Reinforce Tickets' Sharp Differences</title>
    <meta content="06NUDE$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/politics/06DEBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Centre College (Ky)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Joseph I Lieberman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DD143CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Civil Clash, Cheney and Lieberman Reinforce Tickets' Sharp Differences</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen Joseph I Lieberman and Dick Cheney meet for vice-presidential debate, Centre College, Danville, Ky; with studied civility they spell out their tickets' differences on taxation and foreign policy debate that more resembles an academic seminar than political warfare typically expected when understudies cross swords; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a studied civility, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman and Dick Cheney spelled out their tickets' differences on taxation and foreign policy last night in a vice-presidential debate that more resembled an academic seminar than the political warfare typically expected when understudies cross swords.</p>
        <p>In the 90-minute, nationally televised debate, the only scheduled meeting between the Democratic and Republican running mates, there were no slashing attacks, few well-rehearsed quips and only the occasional memorable exchange. Instead, Mr. Lieberman and Mr. Cheney spent most of the night calmly and fluidly reinforcing the most significant points made by their principals, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, in their first debate on Tuesday night</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a studied civility, Senator Joseph I. Lieberman and Dick Cheney spelled out their tickets' differences on taxation and foreign policy last night in a vice-presidential debate that more resembled an academic seminar than the political warfare typically expected when understudies cross swords.</p>
        <p>In the 90-minute, nationally televised debate, the only scheduled meeting between the Democratic and Republican running mates, there were no slashing attacks, few well-rehearsed quips and only the occasional memorable exchange. Instead, Mr. Lieberman and Mr. Cheney spent most of the night calmly and fluidly reinforcing the most significant points made by their principals, Vice President Al Gore and Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, in their first debate on Tuesday night</p>
        <p>As in the presidential debate, the sharpest exchanges concerned the competing tax cut plans and proposals for spending the projected federal surplus, which together have formed the foundation of the 2000 campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney described the Democratic proposals for middle-class tax cuts and increased spending on education and health care as ''an old way of governing ourselves, of high levels of spending, high taxes, an ever more intrusive bureaucracy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman countered that the Republican proposal for a large across-the-board reduction in income tax rates, combined with various spending programs and the cost of Mr. Bush's plan to privatize part of the Social Security system, would leave the budget with a $1.1 trillion debt. [Excerpts, Page A28.]</p>
        <p>''That means we go back down the road,'' Mr. Lieberman said, ''to higher interest rates, to higher unemployment, to a kind of stealth tax increase on every American family, because when interest rates go up so, too, do the cost of mortgage payments, car payments, student loans, credit card transactions.''</p>
        <p>The debate was held at Centre College in Danville, Ky., population 16,500, where town leaders promoted the event as ''the thrill in the 'ville.''</p>
        <p>But for the most part, the tone of the debate was as sober as Mr. Cheney's gray suit, a striking contrast to the barely suppressed disdain apparent in Tuesday's contest in Boston.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman established the tone early by pledging to remain positive throughout the debate. He said his 85-year-old mother, Marcia, had told him yesterday, '' 'Sweetheart' -- as she is prone to call me -- 'remember, be positive and know that I will love you no matter what your opponent says about you.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney quickly joined Mr. Lieberman's pledge, telling his opponent, ''I promise not to bring up your singing.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman responded, ''I promise not to sing.''</p>
        <p>When the candidates differed, they did so respectfully. When the moderator, Bernard Shaw of CNN, asked Mr. Cheney whether he had noticed any post-nomination ''contradiction or hypocritical shift'' in Mr. Lieberman's positions, Mr. Cheney seemed reluctant to rise to the bait.</p>
        <p>''Well, we've been trying very hard to keep this on the high plane, Bernie,'' Mr. Cheney began.</p>
        <p>But he eventually acceded. ''I do have a couple of concerns where I like the old Joe Lieberman better than I do the new Joe Lieberman,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney then said that many Republicans had admired Mr. Lieberman's stands against the marketing of Hollywood violence to children, but said his opposition had seemed to soften because of the entertainment industry's financial support of the Democratic ticket.</p>
        <p>''My concern would be, frankly, that you haven't been as consistent as you had been in the past,'' Mr. Cheney said to Mr. Lieberman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman, politely, disagreed. ''I have not changed a single position since Al Gore nominated me to be his vice president,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Within the confines of their mutual respect, the candidates did manage to establish the fundamental differences between their parties, writing something of a sequel to the debate between Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Gore, Mr. Lieberman repeatedly emphasized that the $1.3 trillion, 10-year income tax cut proposed by the Republicans would primarily benefit the wealthy and would leave little of the projected federal surplus for priorities like improving education and expanding Medicare coverage. He also used a figure of $1.6 trillion to describe it, a number that includes the increase in interest costs to the government that such a tax cut might cause.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, meanwhile, echoed Mr. Bush's contention that Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman would abandon the centrist Democratic policies of the Clinton years and would rely on big government solutions to the country's problems. He also repeated Mr. Bush's assertion that the Democrats had failed to lead during their eight years in the White House.</p>
        <p>''With all due respect, Joe,'' Mr. Cheney said, ''there is just an awful lot of evidence that there has not been any bipartisan leadership out of this administration or out of Al Gore. And the fact is the Medicare problems have not been addressed. We've had eight years of promises on prescription drugs with no action. The Social Security problem has not been addressed. Now we've had eight years of talk and no action.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney also echoed Mr. Bush's contention that Mr. Gore's tax cut plan, which would provide relief for those putting money into savings accounts, college tuition, child care and other specific purposes, would serve as a form of social engineering.</p>
        <p>''If you live your life the way they want you to live your life, if you do, in fact, behave in a certain way, then you qualify for a tax credit,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman asserted that the Republicans would have to raid the Medicare trust fund to pay for their tax cut and would not leave enough money to address social needs.</p>
        <p>''We're saving money to invest in education,'' Mr. Lieberman said. ''You cannot reform education and improve it in this country without spending some money.''</p>
        <p>When the questioning turned to military affairs and the Middle East, the candidates traded barbs and efforts to take credit, some subtle, some overt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney contended, as he has for months, that President Clinton had allowed military readiness to suffer, saying, ''I think that the administration has, in fact, in this area, failed in a major responsibility. We've seen a reduction in our forces far beyond anything that was justified by the end of the cold war. The same time, we've seen a rapid expansion of our commitments around the world as troops have been sent hither and yon.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman responded that the American military was ''the best-trained, best-equipped, most powerful force in the world and that Al Gore and I will do whatever it takes to keep them that way.''</p>
        <p>The debate dwelt at considerable length on the Middle East, an area where both men showed -- and claimed -- a level of comfort, Mr. Cheney based in his years as defense secretary during the Persian Gulf war, and Mr. Lieberman based on his interest in Israel.</p>
        <p>When asked how the United States should respond if Iraqi president Saddam Hussein were discovered to be developing weapons of mass destruction, Mr. Cheney said, ''You'd have to give very serious consideration to military action to stop that activity.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lieberman said, ''I don't think a political campaign is the occasion to declare what we would do in that case.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Lieberman defended the United States' role in Bosnia and Kosovo. ''I know our opponents have said that they thought that was an overreaching,'' he said. ''It wasn't. It was a matter of principal and America's national interest and values. And the fact is that we stopped the aggression. We stopped the genocide.''</p>
        <p>In response, Mr. Cheney did not, in fact, accuse the Clinton administration of overreaching. But when Mr. Shaw asked him whether the military should be used as warriors or peacekeepers, Mr. Cheney chose the former, but said such engagements should have a time limit.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Lieberman and Mr. Cheney both sought to reinforce their tickets' principle themes, last night's debate also served to reintroduce them to an electorate that knew them mostly from the acceptance speeches they had delivered at party conventions last summer.</p>
        <p>In that way, the debate gave both candidates a chance not only to highlight their policy differences with the other ticket but also to try to prove that their running mates had demonstrated leadership and wisdom in selecting them.</p>
        <p>That challenge was considered particularly important to Mr. Cheney.His choice as running mate was questioned almost immediately because of his congressional votes against Head Start and a resolution calling for the release of Nelson Mandela from a South African prison. He has also been assailed for his ties to the oil industry through the Halliburton Company, the Texas firm he led until his selection. Mr. Lieberman did not touch those issues last night.</p>
        <p>As a committed centrist, a moral critic of President Clinton and the first Jew nominated by a major party, Mr. Lieberman is widely considered to have boosted the appeal of the Democratic ticket. His primary vulnerabilities so far have been his historical differences with Mr. Gore on several issues, including affirmative action and school vouchers. Again, except when prompted by Mr. Shaw, Mr. Cheney chose not to exploit those differences.</p>
        <p>What viewers did see was both the seriousness and the dry wit that define both men.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lieberman, for instance, defended the Clinton administration's economic record by arguing that most people in America would agree that they were better off today than they were eight years ago.</p>
        <p>''And I'm pleased to see, Dick, from the newspapers that you are better off than you were eight years ago, too,'' Mr. Lieberman said, referring to the Mr. Cheney's multimillion dollar compensation package from Halliburton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney smiled, and shot back, ''And I can tell you, Joe, that the government had absolutely nothing to do with it.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEBATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
