<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Apple Doesn't Fall Far From the Tree</title>
    <meta content="06BOOK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="49" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/arts/06BOOK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eve, Nomi</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Family Orchard, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0D9163CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Apple Doesn't Fall Far From the Tree</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews The Family Orchard by Nomi Eve; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE FAMILY ORCHARD  By Nomi Eve  316 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>The title of Nomi Eve's ambitious first novel refers to the orchard cultivated by her narrator's family in Israel and to the intertwining family trees of her narrator's parents, an apt enough metaphor for a sprawling family saga that spans five generations, nearly two centuries and much of Israel and Palestine's tumultuous recent history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE FAMILY ORCHARD  By Nomi Eve  316 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>The title of Nomi Eve's ambitious first novel refers to the orchard cultivated by her narrator's family in Israel and to the intertwining family trees of her narrator's parents, an apt enough metaphor for a sprawling family saga that spans five generations, nearly two centuries and much of Israel and Palestine's tumultuous recent history.</p>
        <p>Told in sections ''written'' alternately by the narrator and the narrator's father, ''The Family Orchard'' reads like a work of autobiography. It's got the confiding, self-dramatizing tone of a memoir, and Ms. Eve suggests, quite pointedly, that the story she is telling is her family's own: the novel even ends with the coming of age of a young woman named Nomi, who turns out to be the book's narrator.</p>
        <p>Whereas the father sets forth his history of the family in the dry, uninflected terms of a documentary, the fictional Nomi exuberantly embroiders his account, filling in gaps with imagined scenarios and extrapolating bare-bones incidents into full-fledged adventures. Although the closing sections of the novel bog down in postmodernist allusions and therapeutic-age asides -- ''they had broken up for reasons that had little to do with who they were, and a lot to do with who they had both needed to become'' -- the first half showcases Ms. Eve's ability to conjure up the lives of her ancestors with a full arsenal of literary techniques.</p>
        <p>Some of her chapters, like the one in which her great-great-great-grandmother Esther embarks on a nine-year adulterous affair with a baker, are told in the bold colors of an Isaac Bashevis Singer fable. Others, like one in which her grandparents' home is haunted by the ghost of their youngest son, use a surrealism reminiscent at once of Gogol and of Gabriel Garcia Marquez.</p>
        <p>There are harrowing tales of survival during the violent years preceding the Israeli war of independence, as well as a chilling little murder mystery involving an inheritance; a fairy tale account of a woman blessed with magical weaving abilities; and a mini-soap opera about a would-be Scheherazade who enchants her husband with her storytelling abilities.</p>
        <p>In these chapters Ms. Eve draws vivid portraits of her eccentric and copiously gifted relatives. Esther emerges as an ardent, irreverent woman whose infidelity curiously binds her closer to her husband. Their son, Eliezer, inherits his mother's taste for illicit sex, falling in love with Golda, the daughter of his father's second wife. He and Golda marry and have a daughter, Avra, a dedicated kleptomaniac who wanders the Old City of Jerusalem lifting items that catch her eye -- a precious purple geode here, a valuable heirloom spoon there.</p>
        <p>Avra eventually marries Shimon Sepher, a Russian immigrant who moved to Palestine after his brother Nachum was killed on the Russian-Japanese front. Their son Zohar, the narrator's grandfather, also ends up mourning a brother after his twin, Moshe, is killed during the Israeli war of independence. He, in turn, inadvertently bestows the grief for a missing brother on his son Eliezer, when he and his wife, Miriam, decide that their youngest son, born with severe congenital problems, should be sent away from home.</p>
        <p>Weaving together her characters' stories in a musical narrative full of recurring melodies and leitmotifs, Ms. Eve artfully shows how familial traits are handed down from father to son and mother to daughter, and how quirks of fate resurface from generation to generation. Some of her characters inherit a passionate sexual nature or a propensity for irrational anger; some inherit a talent for storytelling and invention.</p>
        <p>The women in the narrator's family in particular tend to have the gift of ''fiercely original speech.'' Esther has a talent for ''sidewinded stories''; Avra the thief builds ''word houses'' around the objects she has stolen or covets; Miriam stitches magical narratives into the garments she sews and later plays a storytelling game with her husband, imagining the lives of the people who once lived on the land of their family orchard many decades and centuries ago.</p>
        <p>The later chapters of ''The Family Orchard'' lack the ease and fluidity of their predecessors: it's as if the closer this author gets to present-day reality, the more self-conscious her writing becomes. Still, it's clear that Ms. Eve shares her female characters' talent for ''creative speech,'' that she, too, is a storyteller of uncommon energy and poise.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
