<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Priceline's WebHouse Club Abandoned as Investors Balk</title>
    <meta content="Y06PRIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/technology/06PRIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Priceline.com</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Priceline WebHouse Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walker, Jay S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Supermarkets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3DB173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1319" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Priceline's WebHouse Club Abandoned as Investors Balk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Priceline.com's affiliate that lets consumers bid for groceries and gasoline online is abandoned because it cannot raise enough money to stay in business; group of investors stand to lose most of $360 million they put into venture, Priceline WebHouse Club, which is privately held; WebHouse founder Jay S Walker concedes he will lose most or all of $179 million he invested in WebHouse; Walker's shares of Priceline are valued at $220 million compared with $8 billion in April 1999; Walker says he harbors no ill will toward investors who refused to continue pumping money into his WebHouse venture; graph; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the most ambitious efforts to use the Internet to transform a big business, Priceline.com's affiliate that lets consumers bid for groceries and gasoline, was abandoned yesterday because it could not raise enough money to stay in business.</p>
        <p>A group of investors stand to lose most of the $360 million they put into the venture, the Priceline WebHouse Club, which is privately held.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the most ambitious efforts to use the Internet to transform a big business, Priceline.com's affiliate that lets consumers bid for groceries and gasoline, was abandoned yesterday because it could not raise enough money to stay in business.</p>
        <p>A group of investors stand to lose most of the $360 million they put into the venture, the Priceline WebHouse Club, which is privately held.</p>
        <p>The shutdown is new evidence of a profound change in the investment climate for Internet companies. A year ago, a booming market for initial public offerings and torrents of venture capital meant that thousands of companies were started with little more than a dot-com emblazoned on a business plan. Now, with the stocks of Internet companies far off their highs, few such ventures are being financed.</p>
        <p>But even more striking, when many fledgling companies return to venture capital firms for their next installment of cash, they are being turned away. In some cases this is forcing the companies to close, wiping out the venture firm's investments.</p>
        <p>''The secret of being a venture capitalist is knowing when to shoot the lame ponies in your stable,'' said Richard A. Shaffer, the principal of Technologic Partners, a firm that tracks venture capital. ''You fund the dream early on, but if they stumble, you pull the plug.''</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, a steady stream of such closings has occurred, including Productopia.com, a consumer review site; Pseudo, an online television network; Miadora .com, a jewelry store; and Living.com, a furniture store. In other cases companies have been sold to competitors, as venture capitalists try to cut their losses. For example, the backers of Homegrocer.com decided the prospect of building a network to deliver groceries around the country was so daunting that they sold it to a rival, Webvan.</p>
        <p>''The rules have changed,'' said Lauren Levitan, an analyst with Robertson Stephens. ''None of these companies raised money with the promise they would be profitable. But now the market is inhospitable to any business that is not profitable or at least has a clear path to profitability.''</p>
        <p>What is notable about the WebHouse case is the magnitude of the money lost and the pedigree of the company's management and backers. The founder, Jay S. Walker, was able to raise money from blue-chip backers for the original Priceline service, which allows people to name their own prices for airline tickets. He spent much of the money selling tickets below cost to attract consumers, enabling him to lure every major airline into joining his system.</p>
        <p>The WebHouse Club was even more complex. Customers bid on and paid for groceries on an Internet site and then used a special identification card to pick them up at any of thousands of supermarkets. This required a network connecting 80,000 cash registers that would ultimately cost close to half a billion dollars to build. Mr. Walker was able to raise initial financing from Paul Allen, the co-founder of Microsoft; Liberty Media, the investment firm controlled by John C. Malone; and Goldman Sachs.</p>
        <p>But the project required hundreds of millions of dollars to complete, and neither his initial backers nor any other investors he approached would put up the needed cash. In August, Mr. Walker raised $125 million by selling a block of his Priceline shares to Mr. Allen and Liberty. But Mr. Walker said he ultimately decided that he would not be able to raise the next $100 million that would be needed early next year and that it was better to stop now.</p>
        <p>''The prudent thing to do was not to bet that the capital markets would reverse again and start to love unprofitable, large-scale, business-to-consumer Internet companies,'' he said. ''I made the call that if I wind down over the next 90 days, I can use the $70 million in capital we still have to pay our customers back and pay severance to our 375 employees.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker concedes that he will lose most or all of the $179 million he invested in WebHouse. Meanwhile Mr. Walker's shares of Priceline itself, worth nearly $8 billion in April 1999, are now valued at $220 million.</p>
        <p>Priceline's stock is down 88 percent this year, and it fell $3.56 a share yesterday, to $5.81.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker said he believed that the idea behind the Webhouse venture was still sound, but that the service had been done in by the fickle sentiments of investors.</p>
        <p>''It's like having your baseball game rained out when you are ahead,'' he said. ''It doesn't say anything about your ball team. It's just the weather.'</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker said he harbored no ill will toward the investors who chose not to keep pumping money into his company.</p>
        <p>''These are the largest and most sophisticated investors, and they didn't get that way by bucking the public markets,'' he said. ''You don't build oil rigs when oil is at $8 a barrel.''</p>
        <p>Whether or not WebHouse seemed on a clear track to victory, it certainly attracted consumer interest, with two million customers since it started in January.</p>
        <p>''When they first launched, everyone I talked to pooh-poohed it,'' Ms. Levitan said. ''Three months after, there was not an investor I talked to in New York that said they hadn't used it. It had snob appeal, like shopping at Costco.''</p>
        <p>One reason for the appeal was that customers could save 25 percent or more on an assortment of more than 200 grocery items, largely thanks to the venture capital that WebHouse raised. Like Priceline's airline service, Webhouse allows consumers to specify the price they pay but not the brand. So someone could bid, say. $2.20 for a jar of peanut butter; if WebHouse accepted the offer, it could specify Jif or Skippy or another national brand. The point was to give manufacturers an alternative to paper coupons to encourage people to try their products and to offer discounts to some people without lowering their prices over all.</p>
        <p>But manufacturers were initially skeptical, so as with Priceline, WebHouse simply subsidized the discounts itself to generate consumer interest. Eventually some like Kellogg and Hershey's started using WebHouse, but the largest consumer products companies, Procter &amp; Gamble and Lever Brothers, did not. Mr. Walker said this was not a problem.</p>
        <p>''We knew it would take a full year before the major manufacturers saw our volume and allocated the budget for this,'' he said. The company was hurt because programming delays kept its name-your-own-price gasoline service from starting before the busy summer travel months.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Vulcan Ventures, Mr. Allen's investing arm, declined to comment on the shutdown of Webhouse, but did say the fund remained committed to Priceline itself.</p>
        <p>Analysts said, in fact, that Priceline would have little direct financial impact from the shutdown. WebHouse was set up as a separate venture precisely to shelter its risks and financial losses from Priceline, which is moving toward a profit. In return for granting WebHouse access to its name and systems, Priceline had the option of acquiring a majority of the company in the future.</p>
        <p>That said, many investors had factored the value of Priceline's option to buy Webhouse into their assessment of its stock. Indeed, there has been even more pressure on Priceline to diversify its product line after its announcement last week that a shortfall in the sale of airline tickets, which still account for 87 percent of its sales, would lead it to miss Wall Street's forecast for revenue and earnings.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
