<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; Crunching Numbers</title>
    <meta content="06COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/opinion/06COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236440"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDE173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; Crunching Numbers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed column holds that Vice Pres Gore's lapses into semi-fiction have come to assume enormous import in presidential race; maintains that polls show that Americans agree with his positions on most issues, but they appear to be wrestling with question of whether they can bear to have him around for four long years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Americans look back on this presidential campaign, they may remember it as the moment in which the specter of International Communism was replaced by the horror of ''fuzzy math.''</p>
        <p>''He loves to talk about numbers,'' cried George W. Bush at a post-debate rally, where he laced into Al Gore as -- well, a person who loves to talk about numbers. That was the cue for the crowd to chant: ''No fuzzy math! No fuzzy math!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Americans look back on this presidential campaign, they may remember it as the moment in which the specter of International Communism was replaced by the horror of ''fuzzy math.''</p>
        <p>''He loves to talk about numbers,'' cried George W. Bush at a post-debate rally, where he laced into Al Gore as -- well, a person who loves to talk about numbers. That was the cue for the crowd to chant: ''No fuzzy math! No fuzzy math!''</p>
        <p>It's not ''Tippecanoe and Tyler, too.'' But we make do with what we have.</p>
        <p>The crisis in Yugoslavia rescued Mr. Gore from the sloughs of post-debate despond. Yesterday voters had to be recalling that he was the candidate who knew Vojislav Kostunica's name, while Mr. Bush is the one who appears to celebrate every new foreign policy discussion by inventing a different way to pronounce ''Milosevic.''</p>
        <p>And it was none too soon. The debate left the vice president in rollback hell, trying to explain that he actually went to Texas to check out the floods, not the fires. And did the Florida high school student he talked about really have no desk, or was she just standing while the technicians installed new computer equipment? Does the little old lady he invited to the debate really collect tin cans to pay for her prescription drugs, or does she just enjoy recycling?</p>
        <p>''I find it troubling as an American,'' said Mr. Bush's communications director solemnly. ''What if he were in a meeting with foreign leaders and he made something up?''</p>
        <p>The Yugoslav upheaval gives Gorites a chance to retort that at least the vice president would know who the foreign leaders were. Still, this implosion in Mr. Gore's stock of true-life stories should be a lesson for the future. If presidential campaigns are going to continue to insist on dragging real people into every argument, they're going to have to start vetting them like vice-presidential candidates. Before you consult with that photogenic single mom who works three jobs to pay for health insurance, demand to see her tax forms and interview her neighbors.</p>
        <p>Those lapses into semi-fiction have come to assume an enormous import in this race. Mr. Gore comes up with an imaginary story about a good-will trip to Texas, and somehow it balances out the fact that Mr. Bush has an imaginary trillion dollars in his Social Security plan. The polls say Americans agree with Mr. Gore's positions on most issues. But they appear to be wrestling with the question of whether they can bear to have him around all the time for four long years. That's why we've suddenly elevated those funny noises he made during the debate to a matter of national significance.</p>
        <p>This is the genius -- well, let's not get carried away, this is the clever thing about the Bush campaign's new war cry. ''Fuzzy math'' doesn't really refer to Mr. Gore's numbers. It's how you feel when Mr. Gore starts talking about them. Maybe the answer is for the vice president to promise he'll run the country but send Joe Lieberman to tell us what's happening.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush seems to be planning to use the interval between presidential debates to offer up all the rejoinders he'd have fired at Mr. Gore on Tuesday if only he'd thought of them. At almost every campaign stop he re-adds his budget to prove that the vice president was wrong when he said the Bush agenda spends more money on tax cuts than everything else combined. And that tax relief for the rich? ''The wealthy folks get one-fifth of the benefits -- far short, far short of what he was talking about,'' said Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Do you actually want to know who's right? Mr. Bush counts only  one of his many tax cuts when he's figuring out how much the wealthy get, while Mr. Gore adds them all up. And Mr. Gore is comparing Mr. Bush's tax cut with the Republican plans for spending hikes. But Mr. Bush is comparing the tax cut with the entire federal budget for the other programs, which obviously makes it look smaller.</p>
        <p>POP QUIZ: While I was explaining all that to you, gentle reader, what was your reaction?</p>
        <p>A) Now everything is so much clearer. Perhaps we should go on to discuss prescription drug coverage.</p>
        <p>B) Zounds! I had no idea the estate tax was not included in his calculations!</p>
        <p>C) Suddenly. Everything. Seems. Very. Fuzzy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
