<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putin Joins India in Vow On How to Use Atomic Plants</title>
    <meta content="Y06PUT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/world/06PUTI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">India-International Relations-Russia</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dugger, Celia W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DE173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putin Joins India in Vow On How to Use Atomic Plants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA W. DUGGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dugger, Celia W</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russia Pres Vladimir V Putin takes high-profile tour of India's leading nuclear research center where reactors and bombs are designed, and promises to work with India in developing peaceful uses for atomic energy while encouraging India to sign nuclear nonproliferation and test ban treaties (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia today took a high-profile tour of India's leading nuclear research center, where reactors and bombs are designed, and promised to work with India in developing peaceful uses for atomic energy while encouraging India to sign the nuclear nonproliferation and test ban treaties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's hour-and-a-half visit to the Bhabha Atomic Research Center in Bombay was the last stop on his four-day trip to India. It suggested how far India has come in regaining international acceptance since it conducted nuclear tests in May 1998.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia today took a high-profile tour of India's leading nuclear research center, where reactors and bombs are designed, and promised to work with India in developing peaceful uses for atomic energy while encouraging India to sign the nuclear nonproliferation and test ban treaties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's hour-and-a-half visit to the Bhabha Atomic Research Center in Bombay was the last stop on his four-day trip to India. It suggested how far India has come in regaining international acceptance since it conducted nuclear tests in May 1998.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin described the research center as a ''temple of science and technology.''</p>
        <p>In a joint statement, Russia also struck a note of tolerance for India's decision to hold off on signing the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty.</p>
        <p>''Russia welcomed India's voluntary moratorium on nuclear testing,'' the statement said, ''and appreciated the Indian government's efforts to develop a broad national consensus'' on the treaty.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's trip here, the first by a Russian head of state in seven years, renewed ties between two countries whose friendly relations date from the cold war era, when the United States tilted heavily toward Pakistan, India's archrival.</p>
        <p>Over the last few days, India and Russia signed military procurement deals, agreed to combat terrorism emanating from Afghanistan and declared that they would strengthen their cooperation on the peaceful uses of nuclear power.</p>
        <p>Historically, most of India's military hardware has been of Russian origin, and Russia's role as India's chief military supplier was sustained on this visit.</p>
        <p>The calculus is simple. Russia, which is in deep economic trouble, needs to sell its job-generating military products. And India, whose military was built with Soviet equipment, needs to buy them.</p>
        <p>Looking to strengthen its conventional forces after a conflict last year with Pakistan in Kashmir, India announced that it would buy 310 T-90 tanks from Russia and produce 140 SU-30 fighter aircraft with Russian technology. Russia said it would give India a carrier, the Admiral Gorshkov, which will be refitted and modernized in Russia at Indian expense and equipped with Russian-made helicopters and other aircraft.</p>
        <p>''Whether India likes it or not, India cannot shake off the Russian connection, as far as military hardware is concerned,'' said P. R. Chari, director of the Institute for Peace and Conflict Studies, a research organization here. ''If 70 percent of your military equipment is of Russian or Soviet origin, you are symbiotically linked to them for spares and ancillary equipment.''</p>
        <p>India and Russia also announced a common front to combat terrorist violence committed by militant Islamic groups based in Afghanistan and said in their joint statement that the areas of Afghanistan ruled by the Taliban -- that is most of the country -- ''had become the breeding ground for religious extremism and international terrorism.''</p>
        <p>Neither country suggested offering military aid to the opposition forces that are fighting the Taliban. Defense experts here said Russia and India could improve sharing their intelligence and work with other major powers, including the United States and China, to bring greater diplomatic pressure on the Taliban.</p>
        <p>In his speech on Wednesday to Parliament, Mr. Putin said the same groups, even the same individuals, were plotting terrorist acts ''from the Philippines to Kosovo, including Kashmir, Afghanistan and Russia's northern Caucasus.''</p>
        <p>Russia and India also offered each other support in their struggles with internal unrest, Russia's in Chechnya and India's in Kashmir, which India and Pakistan have been fighting over for more than 50 years. Both conflicts are being fueled by Islamic militancy.</p>
        <p>The two countries offered the least detail about the agreement to enhance their cooperation on nuclear energy.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the Indian External Affairs Ministry, Raminder Singh Jassal, said the memorandum of understanding on nuclear power would not be made public and offered no reason for the secrecy.</p>
        <p>''In what form the cooperation will develop, it's difficult to anticipate,'' Mr. Jassal said. ''Russia is already collaborating with India in the construction of a 2,000-megawatt nuclear power station in Tamil Nadu.''</p>
        <p>The United States does not share nuclear power technology with India,  because of American laws that require receiving countries to consent to international inspections of all nuclear sites, a rule that India refuses to obey.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
