<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Plan: He Steps Down, They Step Up, U.S. Lies Low</title>
    <meta content="Y06DIP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/world/06DIPL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE DIPLOMACY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgrade (Serbia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia/Belgrade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3DB173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Plan: He Steps Down, They Step Up, U.S. Lies Low</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton offers words of encouragement to protesters in Belgrade and to offer American support, while making it clear that he does not plan on establishing American military presence in region to intervene; consensus among United States intelligence officials, senior military officers and diplomats is that era of Slobodan Milosevic is coming to an end; but they also say they are awaiting formal announcements from security forces (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With televisions in the White House tuned to the images of protesters seizing the Parliament in Belgrade, President Clinton stepped into the Rose Garden today to encourage them on, at once offering American support while making it clear that the considerable American military presence in the region would not intervene.</p>
        <p>''I think the people are trying to get their country back,'' Mr. Clinton said, just as it was becoming clear that the security forces would stand back as protesters took over government buildings and the central television broadcast center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With televisions in the White House tuned to the images of protesters seizing the Parliament in Belgrade, President Clinton stepped into the Rose Garden today to encourage them on, at once offering American support while making it clear that the considerable American military presence in the region would not intervene.</p>
        <p>''I think the people are trying to get their country back,'' Mr. Clinton said, just as it was becoming clear that the security forces would stand back as protesters took over government buildings and the central television broadcast center.</p>
        <p>''The people of Serbia have made their opinion clear,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''They did it when they voted peacefully and quietly, and now they're doing it in the streets.''</p>
        <p>The consensus among United States intelligence officials, senior military officers and diplomats interviewed today is that the era of Slobodan Milosevic was coming to an end.</p>
        <p>But they also said that they were awaiting formal announcements from the security forces -- in particular the Yugoslav Army and the Interior Ministry's special police -- that they supported Vojislav Kostunica as the winner of the presidential election last month. That, the officials said, would be definitive.</p>
        <p>Samuel R. Berger, the president's national security adviser, warned that the biggest risk was that Mr. Milosevic could marshal some part of the military in a violent effort to  roll back the protests.</p>
        <p>''This was a dramatic day, and it is difficult for me to imagine how Milosevic might reconstitute his power,'' Mr. Berger said in a telephone interview. ''But we have to speak with a note of caution because he is capable of making a last stand. I don't think this is over yet. But it will be awfully hard for him to put it back in the bottle.''</p>
        <p>United States officials said that Mr. Milosevic is probably still in Serbia, seeking refuge, temporarily at least, in one of the Camp David-style retreats or command bunkers built outside of Belgrade.</p>
        <p>These officials said they did not believe that Mr. Milosevic had fled today for Belarus or any other country that might offer him a safe haven from arrest on charges of alleged war crimes issued by the tribunal in The Hague.</p>
        <p>''We don't know where he is, but it's over, he's done,'' said one four-star military officer who was apprised during the day about developments in Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>The overwhelming emotion in the White House was one of joy. Mr. Milosevic's violent efforts at maintaining a Serb-dominated Yugoslavia had predated Mr. Clinton's arrival in the White House, but now he was on the verge of being forced out on the last days of Mr. Clinton's watch. ''If you can't get Middle East peace,'' one senior official said, ''this may be the next best thing.''</p>
        <p>Several senior administration officials said that their first priority was ensuring that Mr. Milosevic left the country -- even if his destination put him out of reach of international law.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately there should be some accountability,'' said an official who had participated in the decisions to intervene in Bosnia and then Kosovo. ''But you also have to be practical and clear about the sequence here, and first things are first. The first thing is for him to step down, and for the transition to take place peacefully, and for him to get out of the country. And we are not about to get in the way of that.''</p>
        <p>The official ruled out forcing down Mr. Milosevic's plane, should he try to leave the country. They said they had no evidence that he was aboard one of three Antonov-26 military transport planes that took off from Belgrade this evening, Belgrade time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's declaration today that he would keep American forces out of the conflict, officials said, was an effort to prevent the resurgence of anti-American sentiments that Mr. Milosevic might be able to stir in a last-ditch effort to hold on to power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's comments today -- first at the White House, then in asides during a speech at Princeton University -- were directed therefore at encouraging the popular uprising while making it clear that the United States was keeping its distance.</p>
        <p>He explicitly ruled out using the approximately 11,000 American troops in neighboring Bosnia and Kosovo, or the naval and Marine forces that have been conducting exercises nearby in the Adriatic Sea. ''I don't believe it's an appropriate case for military intervention,'' Mr. Clinton said, ''and I don't believe that the United States should say or do anything which would only strengthen Mr. Milosevic's hand.''</p>
        <p>But Washington has hardly been shy about offering incentives to the people of Serbia to take the kind of action that unfolded today. The administration has funneled money to voter education groups and the independent news media in Serbia. Mr. Clinton has often said that he is willing to lift economic sanctions against the country as soon as Mr. Milosevic is gone.</p>
        <p>''The people of Serbia have spoken with their ballot, they have spoken on the streets,'' Mr. Clinton said at Princeton. ''I hope the hour is near when their voices will be heard and we can welcome them to democracy, to Europe, to the world's community. And when they do, we will move as quickly as possible to lift the sanctions and build the kind of responsible partnership that the people there deserve.''</p>
        <p>That would allow American and other international aid money to pour in, and permit investors to rebuild the shattered country. While the process could take years, officials today were pointing to the speed with which Eastern European countries turned from dumping dictators to opening factories.</p>
        <p>But they made no mention of the latest parallel, the popular ousting of President Suharto of Indonesia in 1998. While celebrated at the time, it led to two years of ever-worsening economic and political chaos.</p>
        <p>Still, the uprising in Belgrade was celebrated from the White House to Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright's plane. Flying back from Middle East peace talks in Egypt today, she said, ''The important point now is for Kostunica to be recognized as president.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''I hope it turns out for them as it did in the rest of Central Europe and that they will be free from Communism. This is a fork for us in the road -- whether this will go in a peaceful way or not. I think the people of Serbia and Yugoslavia deserve a peaceful exit after a horrible two decades.''</p>
        <p>On the presidential campaign trail, both major party candidates expressed support for Mr. Milosevic's opponents in Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>Gov. George W. Bush, the Republican nominee, said, ''Our country must work closely with our allies in Europe and the international community, including Russia, to pressure Mr. Milosevic to go.''</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore, the Democratic nominee, said: ''We call upon Milosevic to get out of power. It will be taken from him if he does not, because the people of Serbia have spoken, and now they are rising up.''</p>
        <p>SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE DIPLOMACY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
