<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Promoting the Madame Tussaud's in Times Square.</title>
    <meta content="Y06ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/business/06ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square and 42nd Street (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Madame Tussaud's New York</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ddb Worldwide</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fass, Allison</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Addenda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3DF173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Promoting the Madame Tussaud's in Times Square.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Allison Fass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fass, Allison</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advertising campaign for Madame Tussaud's wax museum, which opens in mid-October in Times Square, was developed by DDB Worldwide; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE longtime appeal of wax museums has been in the resemblance between famous people and their life-size replicas. But a campaign to promote the first New York outpost for the Madame Tussaud's wax museum eschews the familiar faces for objects from slippers to spectacles.</p>
        <p>The print campaign, now under way, seeks to attract visitors to the new Madame Tussaud's, scheduled to open in mid-October in Times Square at a cost of $50 million. The goal is to stimulate curiosity by having the objects stand in for celebrities associated with them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE longtime appeal of wax museums has been in the resemblance between famous people and their life-size replicas. But a campaign to promote the first New York outpost for the Madame Tussaud's wax museum eschews the familiar faces for objects from slippers to spectacles.</p>
        <p>The print campaign, now under way, seeks to attract visitors to the new Madame Tussaud's, scheduled to open in mid-October in Times Square at a cost of $50 million. The goal is to stimulate curiosity by having the objects stand in for celebrities associated with them.</p>
        <p>''I think the key thing is to explain the experience: 'Why would I want to go there?' '' said Paul Moreton, marketing manager for the New York Madame Tussaud's, owned by the Tussaud's Group in London.</p>
        <p>To keep readers guessing further, the ads, by the New York office of DDB Worldwide, part of the Omnicom Group, offer fanciful quizzes. For instance, an ad showing a pair of ruby red slippers mentions not only the actress best known for playing a girl who clicked her heels three times to return to Kansas, but also a pop musician known for an extravagant fashion sense.</p>
        <p>For those whose celebrity I.Q.'s have not been bolstered by ''Biography,'' People magazine or ''Behind the Music,'' here's the headline of that ad: ''Judy Garland or Elton John?''</p>
        <p>An ad displaying a shock of wiry gray hair asks, ''Albert Einstein or Don King?'' And an ad featuring two fingers making a ''V'' held up in the air asks, ''Richard Nixon or Janis Joplin?''</p>
        <p>The answers to the questions are supposed to be obtained by going to the museum and examining the wax replicas there for clues. More ads in the series, featuring other unexpected pairs of celebrities, are planned.</p>
        <p>The theme of the campaign, with a budget of more than $2 million, urges tourists as well as native New Yorkers to ''Get close. Get the details.'' Of which there are to be plenty, considering that there will be nearly 200 replicas on display at the museum, ranging from iconic New Yorkers like Woody Allen to world figures like Napoleon to the original wax sculptor herself, Madame Tussaud, in both young and old versions.</p>
        <p>''The single most motivating thing for consumers, particularly in New York, is that whole fascination with celebrity and getting close to them,'' Mr. Moreton said.</p>
        <p>''In London everybody knows what Madame Tussaud's is,'' he added. ''In New York, you guys don't.''</p>
        <p>That is why the campaign is based on what Dominick Baccollo, an art director at DDB New York, described as a ''teaser, a little bit of a hint'' of what visitors to the museum will see.</p>
        <p>Another reason the ads try to sell through enticement is the overcrowded market for tourist attractions in Manhattan, which range from the Empire State Building to Radio City Music Hall to Times Square itself.</p>
        <p>The intent is to serve up ''a bit of spice and sauce and edge,'' said Tony Peluso, vice president and director for development at the American operation of the Tussaud's Group in Orlando, Fla., ''something that explains about the product but will make you want to see.''</p>
        <p>The campaign is also meant to dispel what executives involved with the museum call the preconceived notions of such attractions among Americans, primarily that they are intended for looking but not touching.</p>
        <p>''There's no doubt that what many, most Americans perceive as a wax museum is not at all what we've created,'' Mr. Peluso said, because the Tussaud's exhibits are designed to allow visitors to get up close and personal with the statues.</p>
        <p>You can ''have your picture taken, put your arm around them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The ads will appear in publications like Time Out New York and Where magazines as well as a New York City guide book and map. They will also appear on telephone kiosks and subway platforms as well as on a car of the shuttle between Times Square and Grand Central Terminal.</p>
        <p>Of course, if the campaign succeeds in attracting visitors to the museum, that does not mean they will respond the way the attraction's principals hope.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moreton said he had heard comments from visitors like,  '' 'Gosh, is he really that short?' 'Is she really that ugly?' ''</p>
        <p>''Hopefully, we don't say that,'' he added. ''Hopefully, we say, 'Is she really that beautiful?' ''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING -- ADDENDA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
