<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tory Leader Says British Now Reject Labor as Just a Fad</title>
    <meta content="Y06BRI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/world/06HAGUE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hague, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DD173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tory Leader Says British Now Reject Labor as Just a Fad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>BOURNEMOUTH, England, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British Conservative Party leader William Hague, buoyed by recent lift in party poll numbers, asserts that it now has broader appeal to Britain's middle class than Labor and is fully prepared to run country, address concluding Tories' convention, Bournemouth; declares that vaunted New Labor philosophy of Prime Min Tony Blair had proved instead to be a fad, and British people are now rejecting it; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Buoyed by a recent lift in Conservative poll numbers, William Hague, the leader of the party, said today that it now had broader appeal to Britain's middle class than Labor and was fully prepared to run the country.</p>
        <p>In an address concluding the Tories' annual convention and looking ahead to an election expected in May, he asserted that the vaunted New Labor philosophy of Prime Minister Tony Blair had proved instead to be a fad, and the British people were now rejecting it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Buoyed by a recent lift in Conservative poll numbers, William Hague, the leader of the party, said today that it now had broader appeal to Britain's middle class than Labor and was fully prepared to run the country.</p>
        <p>In an address concluding the Tories' annual convention and looking ahead to an election expected in May, he asserted that the vaunted New Labor philosophy of Prime Minister Tony Blair had proved instead to be a fad, and the British people were now rejecting it.</p>
        <p>''It was a fashion, and nothing is more unfashionable than a fashion that is out of fashion,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hague said that the Tories had reached beyond their core supporters to develop new policies on social issues like improving schools, regenerating inner cities, helping the growing number of pensioners, addressing the breaking down of the family, providing better health care and tackling drug problems.</p>
        <p>Sounding the theme of the four-day meeting, he said, ''It is because we are prepared to do all these things that the message coming loud and clear from this conference is that we are ready for government.''</p>
        <p>However, there were dissonant notes that marred Mr. Hague's effort to strike a harmonious message and exposed tensions between authoritarian and libertarian brands of conservatism that may be replacing the issue of Britain's relationship with Europe as the party's main source of internal discord.</p>
        <p>The party's spokesman on law enforcement, Ann Widdecombe, roused the hall on Wednesday with an appeal for ''zero tolerance'' policing that called for automatic $150 fines on people caught with small amounts of marijuana in their possession or even in their bloodstream. The delegates gave the speech the warmest reception of any until today's rallying send-off from Mr. Hague, but police organizations, charities and human rights groups attacked the proposal as intrusive and unworkable, students said it was laughable,  and senior ranks of the party were concerned that it would cost them votes with parents anxious about their children getting police records for youthful indiscretions.</p>
        <p>The Daily Telegraph, the champion of the Conservatives that rarely takes issue with party initiatives, derided the proposal as ''zero common sense,'' and the Labor-friendly Mirror crowed that the only ''dope'' the plan had uncovered was Miss Widdecombe herself.</p>
        <p>The party's libertarians had warmed the day before to a less well received address from Michael Portillo, a former hard-bitten defense secretary, who made an uncommonly personal speech for a Conservative gathering. He used the talk to record his own conversion to a stance of wanting the party to be more accepting of diversity of race and sexual orientation and more committed to financing public services.</p>
        <p>The ranking Conservative as shadow chancellor of the exchequer, Mr. Portillo is considered heir to the party leadership if Mr. Hague falters, and his bravura performance kindled comment of a rivalry at the top of the Tory party like that between Mr. Blair and his chancellor, Gordon Brown, in Labor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hague has succeeded in quieting speculation of an early exit from power by consolidating his control of the party with a shift to the right. But there remains some question whether that success will make the party any more attractive to the broader public. Addressing that concern in his speech, Mr. Hague said he saw no ''contradiction between traditional Conservative issues and winning new Tory audiences.''</p>
        <p>Routed in the 1997 election and trailing Labor by double digits for most of the period since then, the Tories recently capitalized on public disillusionment with the government and actually passed Labor in the polls momentarily last month for the first time since 1992. At the moment, they have fallen behind again, but they feel that they remain in striking distance and that talk of winning the election -- fanciful just a month ago -- is now plausible.</p>
        <p>The rift between the authoritarian and libertarian strands of the party is an important one because much of the party's recent gain has come from adoption of positions viewed by critics, including some internal ones, as intolerant of asylum seekers, minorities, gays and other social outcasts and aimed at grabbing headlines rather than in developing coherent policy.</p>
        <p>On Europe, however, the issue that has divided the Tories in recent years, Mr. Hague has solidified party support for his hard-line position that Britain should rule out any consideration of entering monetary union for at least five years. The government's official stance is that Britain should keep itself open to holding a referendum on the issue if the economic considerations of joining make it a decision more in Britain's interest than it is now.</p>
        <p>The Conservatives were at pains to present themselves as not antagonistic to Europe, just hostile to the common currency project under which Britain would have to replace the pound with the euro. But former Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher -- greeted with a standing ovation when she appeared in the hall though not invited to address the convention -- made a combative comment on the subject that drew as much attention as the hands-across-the-Channel words of party leaders.</p>
        <p>''I have very strong views about Europe,'' she told the BBC. ''We're quite the best country. We rescued them. We're not going to get entangled with them. We've got to keep our own independence. Is that clear?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
