<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Time Warner And EMI Halt Venture Plan</title>
    <meta content="Y06ONL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/technology/06ONLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">America Online</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Emi Group Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aol Time Warner</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tagliabue, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monti, Mario</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EEDB173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Time Warner And EMI Halt Venture Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TAGLIABUE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tagliabue, John</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Time Warner and EMI Group of Britain, faced with opposition from European antitrust regulators, withdraw their application for $20 billion joint venture to link music businesses and say they will work to submit revised plan; decision comes on day of meeting with regulators in Brussels, at which chief European antitrust official, Mario Monti, is expected to propose clearance for Time Warner's separate and much larger combination with America Online (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Faced with opposition from European antitrust regulators, Time Warner and the EMI Group of Britain withdrew their application today for a $20 billion joint venture to link their music businesses and said they would work to submit a revised plan.</p>
        <p>The decision came on the day of a meeting of regulators in Brussels, at which the chief European antitrust official, Mario Monti, was expected to propose clearance for Time Warner's separate and much larger combination with America Online.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Faced with opposition from European antitrust regulators, Time Warner and the EMI Group of Britain withdrew their application today for a $20 billion joint venture to link their music businesses and said they would work to submit a revised plan.</p>
        <p>The decision came on the day of a meeting of regulators in Brussels, at which the chief European antitrust official, Mario Monti, was expected to propose clearance for Time Warner's separate and much larger combination with America Online.</p>
        <p>In a joint statement, EMI and Time Warner said they had informed the regulators that they were withdrawing their application for approval of the planned combination in recording, music publishing and online distribution. But they maintained that there was value for their shareholders in such a venture and said that they would explore concessions to allay the regulators' concerns ''while preserving the economic merits of the proposed joint venture.''</p>
        <p>EMI's chairman, Eric Nicoli, said, ''We continue to believe that a joint venture with Warner Music Group can create substantial value for our shareholders and benefit our artists, consumers and employees by bringing together two companies with complementary strengths.''</p>
        <p>The companies would now have the time, he added, ''to reassess regulators' concerns and to pursue solutions simultaneously in Europe and the United States.''</p>
        <p>The proposed linking of Warner Music, the music division of Time Warner, and EMI into a joint venture controlled equally by both would have created a giant in the music business -- one with more than 2,500 musicians, including superstars like David Bowie and the Rolling Stones, and accounting for more than 2,000 new albums a year.</p>
        <p>The deal, together with the proposed acquisition of Time Warner by AOL, was widely opposed by rivals in the arts and Internet businesses as a juggernaut, a company that could monopolize much entertainment as well as being the world's largest online information service.</p>
        <p>Time Warner's president, Richard D. Parsons, said the two companies would ''continue to explore ways to structure a combination that will make sense for the two companies and be acceptable'' to European regulators.</p>
        <p>European officials had opposed the planned combination largely because it would have reduced the number of global music companies to four from five -- also including the music division of the Sony Corporation, that of Bertelsmann of Germany, and the Universal Music unit of the Seagram Company, which has agreed to be acquired by the French conglomerate Vivendi.</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether Time Warner and EMI can now find remedies that would satisfy both the regulators and their corporate strategies. Failure would throw into question much of the further consolidation that analysts have expected in the entertainment and Internet industries.</p>
        <p>Antitrust regulators from the 15 European Union member nations met in Brussels today, but with the timely withdrawal of the planned combination by EMI and Time Warner, the main issue on the agenda remained Time Warner's deal with AOL.</p>
        <p>Amelia Torres, a spokeswoman for Mr. Monti, said a final decision on that would have to be made by Oct. 24 by the European Commission, the executive arm of the European Union, on the advice of the officials meeting today. The commission, though, will most likely reach a decision at one of two meetings called for Oct. 11 and Oct. 18. Mr. Monti was expected to make a proposal to the regulators, who act as an advisory body, on the Time Warner-AOL combination. Ms. Torres refused to say what form his recommendation would take.</p>
        <p>To allay European concerns, Time Warner and America Online have given assurances that they would refrain from discriminating against rival Internet service providers in the online distribution of music for five years. In addition, AOL said it would end a music distribution alliance with Bertelsmann by buying the 50 percent of the venture it does not own.</p>
        <p>People in Brussels close to the proceedings said that given the withdrawal of the Time Warner-EMI proposal and the remedies suggested by Time Warner and America Online, Mr. Monti was expected to recommend approval of that merger.</p>
        <p>Time Warner's spokesman in New York, Edward Adler, said the chances of European approval looked good. ''Discussions with the commission are nearing the end,'' he said by telephone. ''We are confident of a successful conclusion.''</p>
        <p>That huge merger is being reviewed in the United States by the Federal Trade Commission and the Federal Communications Commission. And while European regulators have conferred on the deal with the F.T.C., it remains unclear what effect the European decisions will have on the deliberations in Washington. Concern in the United States, unlike that in Europe, has focused less on the possibility of collusion in music distribution than on dominance over cable television networks.</p>
        <p>The move by Time Warner and EMI in effect starts the clock running anew in their dealings with the European regulators. In their efforts to allay concerns, the two companies initially agreed to shed their entire European distribution business, sell several record labels and reorganize their music publishing businesses.</p>
        <p>In a last round of grappling with the regulators, Time Warner and EMI proposed the additional sale of two sizable assets, Virgin Records and the Chappell unit of Warner Chappell Music Publishing, according to people close to the discussions.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, it appeared that those concessions might have been sufficient for the European authorities to approve the joint venture. But people close to the discussions said they came too late. So faced with a rejection of the deal, Time Warner and EMI opted to withdraw the entire plan.</p>
        <p>''We were very close, inches away,'' a person involved in the companies' strategy said, adding that the companies would now focus on re-examining the joint venture in light of the experience derived from the discussions with the regulators, in hope of ensuring success the second time around. A fresh proposal could come before January, that person said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
