<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Lost Wars and the Ruined Economy, 'the Greater Slobo' Falls Silent</title>
    <meta content="Y06MIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/world/06MILO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE ULTRANATIONALIST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DD143CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1264" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Lost Wars and the Ruined Economy, 'the Greater Slobo' Falls Silent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>BUDAPEST, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roger Cohen news analysis of political upheaval in Serbia; observes that ousted Slobodan Milosevic had always outmaneuvered his enemies with resilience, ruse and ruthlessness, until the enemy became his own people (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Serbian nationalist hysteria that swept Slobodan Milosevic to power in the late 1980's evaporated long ago, leaving him an isolated figure ruling over a shrinking land. But with resilience, ruse and ruthlessness, he outmaneuvered his enemies, until at last the enemy became his own people.</p>
        <p>Always, Mr. Milosevic believed he could outlast his foes. But the hundreds of thousands of Serbs storming the Parliament in Belgrade today and seizing the television network that has long sustained him with its propaganda made clear that the tide of history had escaped him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Serbian nationalist hysteria that swept Slobodan Milosevic to power in the late 1980's evaporated long ago, leaving him an isolated figure ruling over a shrinking land. But with resilience, ruse and ruthlessness, he outmaneuvered his enemies, until at last the enemy became his own people.</p>
        <p>Always, Mr. Milosevic believed he could outlast his foes. But the hundreds of thousands of Serbs storming the Parliament in Belgrade today and seizing the television network that has long sustained him with its propaganda made clear that the tide of history had escaped him.</p>
        <p>Of the Kosovo Albanians, his first enemies, Mr. Milosevic could say that they were intent on a ''demographic genocide'' against the Serbs -- a reference to their high birthrate. Of the Croats, that they were reincarnated fascists -- a reference to Croatia's World War II past as a Nazi puppet state. Of the Bosnian Muslims, that they were the Ottoman Turks of old bent on destroying the Serbs. Of NATO, that it represented evil American imperialism.</p>
        <p>But of his own people, seemingly undivided at last, intent on ending their European isolation, enraged by one maneuver too many that seemed to rob them of their vote in the recent presidential election, Mr. Milosevic could find nothing to say today. He could summon no specter or myth that might divert or divide or cow.</p>
        <p>His whereabouts was unknown, but the possibility that even so cunning a man might recover authority seemed remote.</p>
        <p>From Western capitals -- Washington, London, Berlin -- the calls to Mr. Milosevic were unambiguous, reflecting a conviction that the man who stirred and sustained the wars of Yugoslavia's long unraveling had at last run out of options: Go, go now, accept your people's verdict and go before more damage is done or blood is spilled.</p>
        <p>On the evidence, Mr. Milosevic's time should have been up long ago: his years of rule have seen a succession of lost wars, hundreds of thousands of Serbs uprooted, an economy ruined, wages slashed and an area that was among the most prosperous in the Communist bloc turned into a conspicuous center of poverty.</p>
        <p>But it was easy to underestimate him. It was not until the Kosovo war last year that Western governments, including the United States, turned against him unequivocally.</p>
        <p>At the Dayton conference in 1995 that ended the war in Bosnia, he was still central to American diplomatic efforts, winning friends with his focus on the big picture and his evocative language: details, to Mr. Milosevic, were mere ''technology.''</p>
        <p>In diplomacy, as at home, the Serbian strongman long succeeded in convincing others that he could not be circumvented.</p>
        <p>His methods for conveying and retaining this authority were multiple. In the late 1980's, he saw the power of crude nationalism in a Serbian society whose binding ideology -- Communism -- was disintegrating. The motto of his Communist-turned-socialist party was straightforward: ''Serbia does not kneel.''</p>
        <p>Such slogans earned him at first a mob appeal. His posters were everywhere in the early 1990's as Yugoslavia descended into violence. But kneel Serbia ultimately did in a succession of wars -- in Croatia, then in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic always portrayed these conflicts as defensive attempts to allow Serbs to ''remain in Yugoslavia'' even as he did more than anyone else to precipitate the conflicts through his hate-filled propaganda against all his neighbors.</p>
        <p>Most Serbs believed him: the deaths of thousands of Muslims in the Serbian concentration camps in Bosnia in 1992 and at Srebrenica in 1995 were often dismissed in Belgrade as ''Muslim propaganda.'' In fact, they were a demonstration of Mr. Milosevic's readiness to resort to force -- against the Albanians of Kosovo in the 1980's as he suppressed their autonomy, against demonstrators on the streets of Belgrade in 1991, against the Muslims of Bosnia in the rampage of 1992, and against the Albanians again in the late 1990's.</p>
        <p>No Stalin, no Hitler, Mr. Milosevic, 59, nonetheless proved himself over the past 13 years to be the most violent ruler Europe has seen in many years. More than 200,000 people have died in the wars of Yugoslavia's destruction. His inability to use force today showed how his strength has evaporated.</p>
        <p>His instinct for survival had long proved remarkable. As the wars turned in 1995 and the vision of ''Greater Serbia'' receded, to be replaced by a vision of ''Greater Slobo,'' many expected Mr. Milosevic to fall. The streets of Belgrade were filled with demonstrators for three months as 1996 turned to 1997. But he deployed a succession of other tactics to replace the galvanizing frenzy of military conflict.</p>
        <p>One constant ploy was ''divide and rule'' -- a highly effective tactic in a society disoriented by the propaganda of Serbian television and used to subjugation. One old Serbian joke had a farmer saying that he would ''vote for the opposition when it is in power''; the unfunny thing was that many people long thought that way.</p>
        <p>Even as Serbia's resources dwindled, Mr. Milosevic used what money there was to buy loyalty from the secret police he armed and from a coterie of business and political associates who dominated the trafficking in the country's increasingly closed and corrupt economy. Behind this loyal entourage, he hid himself.</p>
        <p>The reality of Serbia was increasingly grim, a country poor and isolated, a far cry from the exalted vision that Mr. Milsovic started by offering the Serbs, most memorably, at Kosovo Field in 1989, on the 600th anniversary of the Serbs' losing battle to the Ottoman Turks.</p>
        <p>Then he declared that the Serbs ''never conquered or exploited others'' and were imbued with a ''historical being that throughout history was a liberating one.'' But a ''vassal mentality'' among Serbian politicians had too long allowed ''the humiliation of Serbia.'' He concluded, ''Here we are today on the field of Kosovo to say that it is not so any longer.''</p>
        <p>For much of his rule, Mr. Milosevic succeeded in sustaining his rule through such myths: that a Balkan enemy, or the outside world, or NATO, was intent on humiliating Serbia and the only way to resist was to stick together.</p>
        <p>But the purpose of doing so seemed increasingly elusive. Survival seemed to become Mr. Milosevic's only political intent. As the Serbs of Croatia lost their homes in 1995, and large chunks of Bosnia slipped from his grasp, and finally Kosovo too was lost in an avoidable war with NATO in 1999, he persisted.</p>
        <p>The son of parents who both committed suicide, he seemed intent on dragging his people toward the sort of collective death that Serbian myth tends to portray as a form of redemption. Even Serbian myths exhaust themselves, however. Last year, Mr. Milosevic was indicted by the war crimes tribunal in The Hague. As the country suffered, the police and army became estranged.</p>
        <p>Vojislav Kostunica, the man who appears on the verge of taking power, faces overwhelming problems, not least the fact that the disintegration of Yugoslavia may not be over. Both Montenegro and Kosovo seek independence that he, like Mr. Milosevic, opposes.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kostunica understands his most effective weapons. He talks unceasingly about the lifting of economic sanctions, the need for dialogue and his desire to turn Serbia once more into a ''normal'' country.</p>
        <p>SHOWDOWN IN YUGOSLAVIA: THE ULTRANATIONALIST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
