<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lost Grand Central Lamps Turn Up on an eBay Listing</title>
    <meta content="06LAMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/nyregion/06LAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grand Central Terminal (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chester (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Transportation Authority</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ebay (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunlap, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tangney, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grand Central Terminal (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2D8173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lost Grand Central Lamps Turn Up on an eBay Listing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunlap, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph Tangney is charged with criminal possession of stolen property after Metropolitan Transportation Authority police uncover 37 architectural elements in his Chester, NY, home that had been removed from Grand Central Terminal; police were alerted to cache by Frank J Prial Jr, who saw light fixture from terminal being offered for auction on Ebay on Internet; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>And the winning bid for 15 original light fixtures from Grand Central Terminal offered on eBay? A search warrant.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, amid the tumult and upheaval of renovation, numerous ceiling fixtures -- handsome brass rosettes of oak leaves and acorns -- disappeared from the lower concourse of the terminal. Replicas had to be fashioned, at a total cost of $15,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>And the winning bid for 15 original light fixtures from Grand Central Terminal offered on eBay? A search warrant.</p>
        <p>Three years ago, amid the tumult and upheaval of renovation, numerous ceiling fixtures -- handsome brass rosettes of oak leaves and acorns -- disappeared from the lower concourse of the terminal. Replicas had to be fashioned, at a total cost of $15,000.</p>
        <p>That seemed to be the end of the story until last week, when the fixtures surfaced again. On eBay.</p>
        <p>''Original N.Y. Grand Central Station Ceiling Lamp,'' the listing said. ''The lamps were given to one of the electricians in charge of the recent renovations.''</p>
        <p>One eBay customer who saw the listing, Frank J. Prial Jr., knew that assertion could not be true. As an associate at Beyer Blinder Belle, architects of the Grand Central renovation, Mr. Prial was quite familiar with the project contract, which states, ''Artifacts, remains, structural features and domestic and archaeological objects found within the construction area shall remain the property of the owner'' -- not an electrical contractor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Prial telephoned an architect at the Metro-North Commuter Railroad, who alerted the Metropolitan Transportation Authority's legal department, which notified the M.T.A. police, who paid a call on Butter Hill Antiques in Cornwall-on-Hudson, N.Y., which had two of the fixtures on consignment.</p>
        <p>That led detectives to the home in Chester, N.Y., of the electrical contractor, identified by the transportation authority as Joseph Tangney, 48.</p>
        <p>Last Friday, having been granted a search warrant, the detectives entered Mr. Tangney's home in Orange County and found 37 architectural elements from Grand Central, said Tom Kelly, press secretary at the transportation authority.</p>
        <p>The cache included the single-lamp ceiling fixtures from the lower concourse; two elegant, 37-inch-high, five-bulb sconces from the former waiting room on 42nd Street; a track indicator light from Track 13; and a six-bulb ceiling fixture bearing the tag, ''D Hall, Oyster Bar Ramp, 2/27/97,'' which the police presumed to be the date of its removal.</p>
        <p>Last night, Mr. Tangney was arraigned in Chester on charges of criminal possession of stolen property, Mr. Kelly said. He pleaded not guilty and was freed on $2,500 bail. A court date of next Tuesday was scheduled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly said neither eBay, an Internet auction site, nor Butter Hill Antiques was implicated in the case.</p>
        <p>The M.T.A. estimates that the replacement value of the fixtures alone is $73,000, but that does not take into account their historical significance.</p>
        <p>''The key thing was to get the return of the items,'' Mr. Kelly said. ''These are, to us and the railroad, priceless pieces.''</p>
        <p>As many of the original fixtures as possible will be reinstalled, Mr. Kelly said, in essence replacing their replacements.</p>
        <p>Humble as the ceiling rosettes may appear, Mr. Prial said, they tell an important story. They speak of a time when a bare electric light bulb was a potent sign of technological prowess. Their oak leaf and acorn motif recalls the crest of the Vanderbilt family, owners of the New York Central Railroad and builders of the terminal.</p>
        <p>''The fixtures are as integral to the architecture of Grand Central Terminal as the torch is to the Statue of Liberty,'' Mr. Prial said.</p>
        <p>A recent convert to the Internet, Mr. Prial, whose father is the wine columnist of The New York Times, regularly checks in to find photos, postcards and documents about Grand Central. That is what he was doing last week when he discovered the missing fixtures for sale.</p>
        <p>''I've become excited about it because it's a tremendous resource for architectural and historical research,'' he said. In something of an understatement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
