<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. Matchups Week 6</title>
    <meta content="06NFL.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DC143CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2395" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. Matchups Week 6</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas George</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas George matchups for Week 6 of NFL season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUNDAY 1 p.m.</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh (1-3) at Jets (4-0)  Pittsburgh has not only dominated the series, but has also won three straight over the Jets. The last victory, however, was in 1992 and the last time the Steelers played at the Jets was in 1990. A lot has happened since then, especially with the Steelers. Kent Graham and Kordell Stewart have flip-flopped at quarterback and the Pittsburgh defense now allows 322.8 yards per game. The Jets know they are better than the Steelers and will have little problem proving it. Jets, 28-10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUNDAY 1 p.m.</p>
        <p>Pittsburgh (1-3) at Jets (4-0)  Pittsburgh has not only dominated the series, but has also won three straight over the Jets. The last victory, however, was in 1992 and the last time the Steelers played at the Jets was in 1990. A lot has happened since then, especially with the Steelers. Kent Graham and Kordell Stewart have flip-flopped at quarterback and the Pittsburgh defense now allows 322.8 yards per game. The Jets know they are better than the Steelers and will have little problem proving it. Jets, 28-10</p>
        <p>Buffalo (2-2) at Miami (4-1)  Did you know that Bills quarterback Rob Johnson has made only 12 career starts? Seems as if Johnson has been a starter much longer than that. Some in Buffalo would like to see him sit; they want Doug Flutie to re-enter. The Bills are averaging 328.5 yards per game but have too few points to show for it. In fact, they have been outscored by 76-73 this season and have scored the fewest points of any team in their division. The Miami defense keeps that trend going. Dolphins, 20-19</p>
        <p>Indianapolis (3-1) at New England (1-4)  Have the Patriots finally solved their offensive woes? Sure looked like it in Denver, where New England won its first game of the season. Now the Patriots return home, where they have beaten the Colts four straight times. The Colts are quicker and faster than the Patriots, especially on the perimeters with their running and passing games. That is how this game will be won. Colts, 23-17</p>
        <p>Tennessee (3-1) at Cincinnati (0-4)  Tennessee played a near-perfect game against the Giants. Previously, Tennessee's offense had fluttered and the defense had been the team's hammer. But quarterback Steve McNair and the entire Titans offense entered determined to share the load. Can that mind-set continue? Are the Titans ready for a mid-season roll that could put them in prefect position for home-field advantage throughout the playoffs? Yes. Titans, 19-14</p>
        <p>Green Bay (2-3) at Detroit (3-2)  The Packers keep talking as if they are a playoff team and remain Super-Bowl caliber. But their early play has fallen way short of that. Green Bay has become a middle-of-the-pack team that has already lost two of three home games. That rarely used to happen in Lambeau Field. In the Silverdome, the Packers have lost six of their last seven. Playing there, Detroit quarterback Charlie Batch is 2-0 against the Packers, with a 127.9 passer rating. Lions, 26-20</p>
        <p>New Orleans (1-3) at Chicago (1-4)  The Saints are blowing up the theory that defense wins championships and that a sound defensive team is a winning team. They lead the league in defense, allowing an average of 234.5 total yards per game. They are also No. 1 in pass defense (143.8 yards allowed per game). But the Saints' offense and special teams have not been effective, and the Bears are confident after winning at rival Green Bay last week. Currently, the Bears are the more complete team. Bears, 16-10</p>
        <p>Washington (3-2) at Philadelphia (3-2)  Before moving to Philadelphia this year, Brian Mitchell was a fixture in the Washington locker room and on kick returns. He has 8 punt returns and 3 kickoff returns for touchdowns in his career, and that total of 11 ties him with Eric Metcalf for the most in league history. Mitchell wants desperately to stick it to Washington. Just when the team reloaded for a Super Bowl run, it basically unloaded him. Now he will start at running back in place of the injured Duce Staley (sprained foot). The Eagles have won 9 of 10 against Washington in Philly. This one will be close. Redskins, 24-23</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 4:05 p.m.</p>
        <p>Giants (3-2) at Atlanta (2-3)  In their last three games, the Falcons' special teams have recovered two fumbled punt returns and an onside kick, blocked a punt and a field goal, forced an aborted field-goal attempt and returned a punt 70 yards for a touchdown (Tim Dwight) and a kickoff 100 yards for another touchdown (Darrick Vaughn). That is explosive. So why do the Falcons own a losing record? Well, they have allowed 159 points, tied with San Francisco for most in the league. This is just the defense the Giants' offense needed to face. Giants, 28-21</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 4:15 p.m.</p>
        <p>Denver (2-3) at San Diego (0-5)  Freddie Jones is an unheralded but gifted tight end -- big, strong, fast and with nice hands. Chargers quarterback Jim Harbaugh always looks for Jones. Harbaugh passed for 348 yards and led San Diego to 31 points last week, by far the team's most glittering offensive production of the season. Too bad the Rams scored 57. Denver won't score that many, but enough. Broncos, 30-27</p>
        <p>Seattle (2-3) at Carolina (1-3)  Wow! The Seahawks are minus 10 in turnover differential. How can that be under Mike Holmgren, the disciplined, Napoleon-like leader who demands error-free football? Well, one of the problems is quarterback Jon Kitna and his roller-coaster play. That is why he is being replaced by Brock Huard. Another factor: this is Seattle's third straight road game. When Seattle travels, it really travels -- across country for most road games, including this one. That stress wears and tears a team, and Carolina will take advantage. Panthers, 24-21</p>
        <p>Cleveland (2-3) at Arizona (1-3)  The Cardinals are stingy in the second half of games, but too frequently are blown out in the first half. If they do not get a fast start against the Browns, they will be inept. The season is slipping into another black hole for Arizona; a breakout game is required here for much-needed confidence and hope for the season's first half. Watch Arizona receiver David Boston, who is elusive and wiry, courageous and exciting. Cardinals, 27-19</p>
        <p>SUNDAY 8:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Baltimore (4-1) at Jacksonville (2-3)  The Ravens have won eight straight divisional games, and one of them was a 39-36 shootout over Jacksonville in Week 2. Since then, the Ravens' defense has destroyed everything in sight while recording consecutive shutouts. Baltimore has not allowed a 100-yard rusher in its last 22 games. But look for Jacksonville, smarting, to rebound. Look for Fred Taylor to show why he is occasionally the best running back in football. Look for a Jacksonville resurgence. Jaguars, 20-16</p>
        <p>MONDAY 9 p.m.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay (3-2) at Minnesota (4-0)  This is not the place for the reeling Buccaneers to attempt to right themselves. These teams have split their annual two-game series in each of the past seven years, and the home team has won 10 of the last 14. The game in part will be decided by big passing plays. Minnesota has a deep-strike vertical attack; Tampa Bay does not. Randy Moss has reached 3,000 receiving yards faster than any other player (36 games); Jerry Rice did it in 38. Moss leads the Vikings' over-the-top assault. Vikings, 23-16</p>
        <p>Game Of The Week</p>
        <p>SUNDAY</p>
        <p>4:15 P.M.</p>
        <p>Oakland at San Francisco  This rivalry has a special air. It is grounded in animosity and envy on each side. The teams have only played eight times, the last encounter in 1994. In that game, the 49ers hung 44 points on the Raiders, as Jerry Rice set the league's career touchdown record. This will be a fun game full of big plays and points. The Raiders have prepared for this game for two weeks. They will be ready to show that the Bay Area may be big enough for two teams, but on this day only one rules. Watch speedy Raiders back Napoleon Kaufman, the game-breaker. Raiders, 31-24</p>
        <p>Dallas, Kansas City and St. Louis do not play this week. All times Eastern.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
