<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sierra Leone to Try Juveniles Separately in U.N. Tribunal Plan</title>
    <meta content="06LEON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/world/06LEON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sierra Leone</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Annan, Kofi (Sec Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Sierra Leone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1DA173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sierra Leone to Try Juveniles Separately in U.N. Tribunal Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>UN Security Council gets blueprint for a war crimes tribunal for Sierra Leone, fourth such special court to be established in last decade of world civil conflict; release of plan by Sec Gen Kofi Annan was tied up for nearly a week as legal experts and children's rights advocates argued over lowest age at which war crimes suspect could be tried; plan, sent to Security Council, gives court jurisdiction over anyone 15 or older, but classifies those younger than 18 as juvenile offenders, to be tried in separate juvenile chamber (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Security Council got a blueprint today for a war crimes tribunal for Sierra Leone, the fourth such special court to be established in the last decade of world civil conflict.</p>
        <p>The release of the plan by Secretary General Kofi Annan had been tied up for nearly a week as legal experts and children's rights advocates argued over the lowest age at which a war crimes suspect could be tried.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Security Council got a blueprint today for a war crimes tribunal for Sierra Leone, the fourth such special court to be established in the last decade of world civil conflict.</p>
        <p>The release of the plan by Secretary General Kofi Annan had been tied up for nearly a week as legal experts and children's rights advocates argued over the lowest age at which a war crimes suspect could be tried.</p>
        <p>Children barely big enough to shoulder a weapon have been involved in a very brutal civil war in Sierra Leone marked by amputations of limbs and the terrorizing of villages.</p>
        <p>The government of Sierra Leone at first wanted all people ''most responsible'' for war crimes brought to trial at whatever age. The United Nations legal department recommended that 15-  to 18-year-olds, if found guilty, be sent to rehabilitation centers rather than prison.</p>
        <p>Rights groups and aid organizations, led by Unicef, the children's fund, were strongly opposed to trials of anyone under 18.</p>
        <p>Many of the youngest soldiers, aid officials said, have been coerced and often drugged to take part in atrocities.</p>
        <p>The plan, sent to the Council today, gives the court jurisdiction over anyone 15 or older, but classifies those younger than 18 as juvenile offenders, to be tried in a separate juvenile chamber and sentenced to community service, foster care, training or other forms of rehabilitation.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Annan's plan, which will now be debated by the Security Council, the Sierra Leone tribunal would have two trial chambers and one appeals chamber. Each trial chamber would have three judges, one appointed by Sierra Leone and the other two by Mr. Annan. The appeals chamber would have five judges, three appointed by Mr. Annan.</p>
        <p>The tribunal would have a chief prosecutor appointed by the secretary general and a deputy prosecutor appointed by Sierra Leone, in consultation with the United Nations.</p>
        <p>The court would be based in Sierra Leone, but there are provisions to hold hearings elsewhere if circumstances demand it.</p>
        <p>In addition to murder, torture and terrorism, crimes within the court's jurisdiction include rape, sexual slavery, mutilation, hostage-taking, pillage and attacks on civilians.</p>
        <p>The new court, a hybrid with responsibility shared by Sierra Leone and the United Nations, would have a stronger international component than a tribunal still struggling to be born for Cambodia, because the Cambodian government demanded a more central role in trying the Khmer Rouge.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the Sierra Leone court would not operate like tribunals established for the Balkans and Rwanda, which are entirely under United Nations control.</p>
        <p>The Sierra Leone tribunal will need at least $22 million to operate for the first year, officials say. Mr. Annan's legal experts disagreed with a Security Council plan to finance it with voluntary contributions, fearing that this would be unreliable. The plan sent to the Council recommends billing United Nations member countries for the costs of the court, which is considered the most practical course.</p>
        <p>Alternatively, Mr. Annan said, nations could contribute the salaries of judges and staff members, in effect paying for the court in kind.</p>
        <p>The Security Council will review these options.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
