<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Retailers Can Celebrate Monthly Gain</title>
    <meta content="Y06SHO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/06/business/06SHOP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1236441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Goldman Sachs Retail Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E4DD173CF935A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Retailers Can Celebrate Monthly Gain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Goldman Sachs retail composite index shows sales rose 3.3 percent at stores open at least a year; sales of women's clothing grew nearly 2 perent after decline of 1.2 percent in August; sales figures for specific retailers noted; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After enduring three months of waning consumer interest and rising oil prices that had sent fashion purchasing into a spiral, some of the nation's merchants received a glimmer of good news in September.</p>
        <p>Sales of women's clothing grew nearly 2 percent last month after a decline of 1.2 percent in August. ''If I were selling apparel, I'd feel a lot better today than I did three months ago,'' said George Strachan, a retail analyst with Goldman, Sachs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After enduring three months of waning consumer interest and rising oil prices that had sent fashion purchasing into a spiral, some of the nation's merchants received a glimmer of good news in September.</p>
        <p>Sales of women's clothing grew nearly 2 percent last month after a decline of 1.2 percent in August. ''If I were selling apparel, I'd feel a lot better today than I did three months ago,'' said George Strachan, a retail analyst with Goldman, Sachs.</p>
        <p>That silver lining, however, proved not enough for retailers that were otherwise struggling. Chief in this category was J. C. Penney, which, despite improved apparel sales, said it would not meet analysts' earnings forecasts for the third time this year. Instead of the analysts' consensus of 10 cents a share for the third quarter, Penney said it would report earnings per share ''ranging from a small profit to a loss.'' The stock, which has lost more than half its value in the last 12 months, declined $1.13 yesterday, to close at $10.06.</p>
        <p>Over all, sales at stores open at least a year, a crucial industry measurement, rose 3.3 percent in September, according to the Goldman, Sachs retail composite index. But though that sales growth was respectable, it did not tell the entire story. To encourage customers to buy, many stores were offering deeply discounted prices, which will probably cut into profits for the quarter and for the year.</p>
        <p>''The environment seems to be more promotional'' this year, said Richard Baum, a retail analyst with Credit Suisse First Boston. And the cut-rate prices do not bode well for the stores and the holiday season. ''If the fourth quarter turns out on a relative level to be as promotional as the third, retailers will not have happy faces,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The performance of stores within retail categories showed greater differences than the performance of the categories themselves. Within the department store sector, for example, some stores recorded a stellar month -- notably Neiman Marcus, the luxury goods seller, whose sales for the month jumped 19 percent over last September, and Kohl's, whose sales increased 9.8 percent above the previous year. But there were also some major underperformers -- Penney's, of course, with a monthly sales drop of 4 percent over last September, and Dillard's, with a 6 percent dip.</p>
        <p>Specialty retailers showed a similar split. The Limited, which has been hitting the fashion trends of fur and gold with a vengeance, boasted a 10 percent sales gain over September 1999, while Gap Inc., overloaded on less popular styles like Banana Republic's purple sweaters, had yet another disappointing month, with sales dipping a combined 8 percent for its Banana Republic, Gap and Old Navy divisions.</p>
        <p>''There has been more diversity between companies in the same subsectors than we've seen for years,'' said Jeffrey Feiner, an analyst with Lehman Brother's. ''It proves that even in this environment the companies with great execution will continue to gain market share.''</p>
        <p>The high prices at the gasoline pumps seem to have hit discount stores disproportionately hard. ''The rise in energy prices has probably impacted the lower and moderate consumer much more than the high-income consumer,'' said Mr. Baum of First Boston. ''So you are seeing Wal-Mart report comps at the low end of the range and Kmart was not anything to write home about.'' (''Comps'' is the industry's term for comparable sales in stores open a year.) Wal-Mart stores posted a gain of 4.8 percent as Kmart's domestic stores recorded gains of 2.4 percent over September 1999.</p>
        <p>Stores like J. C. Penney could not blame OPEC for all their woes, however. The department store chain said in a press release that its sales had been hurt by a ''challenging retail environment and continuing disappointing results in its Eckerd drugstore operations.'' While the Eckerd stores posted strong growth of 14.3 percent for the month in their pharmacy departments, they were unable to convert that into sales in the higher-margin front-end products like shampoo and cosmetics. The company said inventory shortages had helped cause the problem.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
