<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big News Is Just a Guy Named Joe</title>
    <meta content="Y03REAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/politics/03REAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: FACES IN THE CROWD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Austin, Joe (Construction Worker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1D8133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big News Is Just a Guy Named Joe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <dateline>ALBUQUERQUE, Oct. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on 13 everyday people, such as Albuquerque, NM, construction worker Joe Austin who campaign of Vice Pres Al Gore is using in makeshift advisory roles in preparing for debate with Gov George W Bush; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's been a whirlwind news week for Joseph Austin, newly minted celebrity. He has been profiled in not one, not two, but three Albuquerque-area daily papers since Friday. His name is a sudden staple on the wires; he has sat for satellite interviews with two of Albuquerque's television stations and shot the breeze with a bevy of New Mexico radio talk show hosts.</p>
        <p>Who, you ask, is Joseph Austin? Why, just a plain-spoken Albuquerque construction worker who has been drawn into the vortex of one of the most significant political news stories of the year. Tapped last week by the Gore campaign with 12 other  people from across the country to accompany the Democratic nominee to Florida for debate preparations, Mr. Austin suddenly found himself in meetings with the candidate, offering his views on national issues and posing for the cameras. Lots and lots of cameras.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's been a whirlwind news week for Joseph Austin, newly minted celebrity. He has been profiled in not one, not two, but three Albuquerque-area daily papers since Friday. His name is a sudden staple on the wires; he has sat for satellite interviews with two of Albuquerque's television stations and shot the breeze with a bevy of New Mexico radio talk show hosts.</p>
        <p>Who, you ask, is Joseph Austin? Why, just a plain-spoken Albuquerque construction worker who has been drawn into the vortex of one of the most significant political news stories of the year. Tapped last week by the Gore campaign with 12 other  people from across the country to accompany the Democratic nominee to Florida for debate preparations, Mr. Austin suddenly found himself in meetings with the candidate, offering his views on national issues and posing for the cameras. Lots and lots of cameras.</p>
        <p>''I can't believe how many people have slapped my name or face on something,'' Mr. Austin said today by telephone from Sarasota. Fla. ''I never expected it to be this big.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Austin and his fellow real people, it has not only been big, but it has also played big, especially in their hometown papers and on the local evening newscasts.</p>
        <p>''Gore seeks N.M. Worker's Advice,'' was how The Albuquerque Journal headlined its 25-paragraph article on Mr. Austin. The article was pretty much replicated in each of the metropolitan areas from which Al Gore's helpers hailed.</p>
        <p>''Belleville Girl Advises Gore on Debates, Likes What He Had to Say,'' declared The St. Louis Post-Dispatch.</p>
        <p>''Local Teacher Picked to Help Gore Cram for Boston Debate,'' announced The Columbus Dispatch in Ohio.</p>
        <p>It seemed no accident, of course, that the 13 everyday people the campaign selected for these makeshift advisory roles were from some of the most hotly contested states of the election. Illinois, Florida, Michigan and Pennsylvania were among the places represented. And in the days leading up to the Tuesday showdown with Gov. George W. Bush in Boston, Mr. Gore's aides, seeking to put a local human face on an event of national importance, pitched their stories relentlessly to the news media in those places.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign dismissed the effort as shopworn posturing.</p>
        <p>''Governor Bush takes these debates very seriously,'' said Andrew Malcolm, a Bush spokesman, ''and he did not poll-test to see who should 'help' him to prepare.''</p>
        <p>The coverage of Mr. Gore's everyday people did, at times, verge on political comedy, as in the case of the progress of Winnifred Skinner, a 79-year-old retiree from Des Moines. Mrs. Skinner bypassed the trip to Florida and instead was driven by the Gore campaign to Boston in a motor home with her poodle, Bridget. Mrs. Skinner had come to the campaign's attention when she spoke up at a rally in Altoona, Iowa, last week, telling Mr. Gore that she collected empty cans and bottles for money to pay for her prescription drugs.</p>
        <p>By the weekend, Mrs. Skinner was all but making campaign appearances of her own as she headed east. '' 'Can Lady' Visits Toledo, Sets Record Straight,'' was how The Toledo Blade characterized her Ohio stop.</p>
        <p>The Gore campaign managed to virtually guarantee favorable publicity in the cities and markets it had singled out through its band of real people. The selections, in fact, were often described in language reserved for lottery winners.</p>
        <p>''It's like nothing anyone ever would experience,'' one of the invited, Laura Castro de Cortes of West Des Moines, told The Des Moines Register.</p>
        <p>The article in today's Post-Dispatch, for instance, was the most vividly displayed in the paper's election coverage. Telling the story of the selection of Erin Conner of Belleville, Ill., at 14 the youngest of the chosen, the paper splashed a large color picture of her across the top of Page A4.</p>
        <p>''We are absolutely having a blast,'' Miss Conner is quoted as saying. She also reports that the group gave Mr. Gore ''feedback on what he needs to do to improve his demeanor or the way he spoke,'' although she herself was effusive in her praise. ''I liked everything he had to say,'' she told the paper.</p>
        <p>In Oregon, a television news crew  showed up at the airport in Medford to tape the departure of Katherine Cowan, a homemaker from Lake Oswego who had met Mr. Gore in August at a campaign appearance at Portland State University. She had spoken to him about her concerns about health care for her daughter Lindsay, who has diabetes.</p>
        <p>The Oregonian, the state's largest newspaper, wrote a comparatively restrained piece about Ms. Cowan's selection, pointing out in the lead of the article, which was displayed inside the paper's main news section, that both Mr. Bush and Mr. Gore ''have been relentless about featuring real folks in their campaign appearances.'' Jeff Mapes, who wrote the article, said the Gore campaign's Oregon representatives had been on the phone repeatedly, providing updates and inquiring about possible follow-ups.</p>
        <p>Celebrity, of course, has its price.  One of the Mr. Gore's guests in Florida said privately that some of the other real people were trying to get in their 15 minutes of fame before the Gore campaign arrived in Boston for fear that ''the tin-can lady'' would grab the headlines.</p>
        <p>Mr. Austin, the Albuquerque construction worker, seems to be getting a kick out of the attention. He does not even betray any irritation at the irksome question of whether he thinks the campaign is using him.</p>
        <p>''I don't think so,'' he said, though he added that he could envision the celebrity thing getting old. ''You know, it's cool, but it's not something I think I could live with.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: FACES IN THE CROWD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
