<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>But Enough About You, Now Look Only at Me</title>
    <meta content="03MARI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/arts/03MARI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001011T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Monte, Marisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E1DE133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>But Enough About You, Now Look Only at Me</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff reviews concert by Brazilian singer Marisa Monte at Beacon Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Brazilian singer Marisa Monte -- a million-seller in her own country and a chic, arty and lesser-known  artist here -- does her best to reconcile pop entertainment and the intellect. During her tour, which stopped at the Beacon Theater on Saturday night, she was presenting songs for the audience to regard from a distance and coolly analyze.</p>
        <p>Many of her new songs, from her album ''Memories, Chronicles, and Declarations of Love'' (MetroBlue/ EMI), were about love, and they were self-reflective to the point of narcissism. But songs like ''Nao Va Embora'' and ''Nao E Facil'' are also formal enough to prompt the notion that Ms. Monte is dealing with love a little more seriously, as a literary trope. That point was strengthened early; during ''Amor I Love You'' the face of the singer Arnaldo Antunes appeared on overhead screens, reading aloud a passage from a Brazilian romance novel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Brazilian singer Marisa Monte -- a million-seller in her own country and a chic, arty and lesser-known  artist here -- does her best to reconcile pop entertainment and the intellect. During her tour, which stopped at the Beacon Theater on Saturday night, she was presenting songs for the audience to regard from a distance and coolly analyze.</p>
        <p>Many of her new songs, from her album ''Memories, Chronicles, and Declarations of Love'' (MetroBlue/ EMI), were about love, and they were self-reflective to the point of narcissism. But songs like ''Nao Va Embora'' and ''Nao E Facil'' are also formal enough to prompt the notion that Ms. Monte is dealing with love a little more seriously, as a literary trope. That point was strengthened early; during ''Amor I Love You'' the face of the singer Arnaldo Antunes appeared on overhead screens, reading aloud a passage from a Brazilian romance novel.</p>
        <p>Her band was positioned within the spaces of a fantastic stage-set designed by the artist Ernesto Neto. It was a white, gauzy scrim that stretched into shapes suggesting the inside of a body, with tubes and funnels, tonsil-like hanging globules. And projected on the scrim but refracted into dozens of broken images because of the fabric's contortions were self-snapped shots of Ms. Monte as well as other images suggesting introspection: droplets of water, hands rubbing each other, planets seen from outer space. The audience was put deep inside the love-besotted mind of Ms. Monte's persona.</p>
        <p>Only a bit of the new music sounded as subdued and interior as the show looked; more of it was the most sunny pop she has recorded yet, an enthusiastic homage to the groovier soft-rock moments of the 1970's. Breaking up the show's dominant summery sound were more traditional songs, with sambas by Paulinho da Viola and others, in which a cavaquinho (the four-stringed, ukulele-like instrument of samba) eclipsed the electric guitar. For most of the meticulously arranged set, three percussion players creating an orchestral overlay of rhythm, with slapped congas and deep-pitched, thumped surdo drums.</p>
        <p>Incorporating this much Afro-Brazilian percussion into sophisticated pop is the innovation of the singer and band leader Carlinhos Brown, and Ms. Monte was building on some of his best ideas. ''Eu Sei,'' one of her earlier songs, was rearranged to accommodate a rhythmic break in which the drummers built a slow-moving samba rhythm and the guitarist Davi Moraes scratched out a rapid counter pattern on his strings; at the end of Mr. Brown's ''Soul by Soul,'' a fast percussion pattern emerged like a shot out of a languorous, chugging rock song.</p>
        <p>Ms. Monte is a superb singer with a clear, pure voice, and as she moved ceremoniously, tracing wavy shapes in the air with her hand, languidly gesturing loss or discontent or longing, there was a bit of a force field around her. Though it was smartly  made music, spontaneity or group interplay wasn't the point, and the inevitable moment at any pop concert with a heavily Brazilian crowd -- the moment when the audience gets up to move and sing -- was put off in this case until almost the very end.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW  Correction:  October 11, 2000, Wednesday  A pop music review on Oct. 3 about a performance by the Brazilian singer Marisa Monte at the Beacon Theater misidentified the source of a passage that was read aloud. It was from the novel ''Primo Basilio'' by the 19th-century Portuguese writer Eca de Queiroz, not from a Brazilian romance novel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 11, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A pop music review on Oct. 3 about a performance by the Brazilian singer Marisa Monte at the Beacon Theater misidentified the source of a passage that was read aloud. It was from the novel ''Primo Basilio'' by the 19th-century Portuguese writer Eca de Queiroz, not from a Brazilian romance novel.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
