<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mad Max in Her Own Future Thunderdome</title>
    <meta content="03DARK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/arts/03DARK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dark Angel (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDF133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mad Max in Her Own Future Thunderdome</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James reviews Fox television program Dark Angel; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Before he sent Kate Winslett overboard to shiver and turn blue in the ocean of ''Titanic,'' James Cameron directed movies whose heroines were as tough on the outside as they were in. Sigourney Weaver in ''Aliens'' and the pumped-up Linda Hamilton in ''Terminator 2'' were female versions of the primary Cameron character, Arnold Schwarzenegger in ''The Terminator.'' In ''Dark Angel,'' the captivating futuristic series created by Mr. Cameron and Charles Eglee, Max is a 19-year-old heroine who shares a bit of all these characters.</p>
        <p>She, however, has a bar code on the back of her neck, a sign that she was the product of a secret genetic experiment called Manticore. The code is usually hidden by a tousle of dark curls, and because Max is played by Jessica Alba (who could win an Angelina Jolie look-alike contest) most people see only a beautiful young woman who rides a motorcycle and wears black leather. Tough and independent, Max is coolly guarded because of the secrets she knows and even more because of those she doesn't.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Before he sent Kate Winslett overboard to shiver and turn blue in the ocean of ''Titanic,'' James Cameron directed movies whose heroines were as tough on the outside as they were in. Sigourney Weaver in ''Aliens'' and the pumped-up Linda Hamilton in ''Terminator 2'' were female versions of the primary Cameron character, Arnold Schwarzenegger in ''The Terminator.'' In ''Dark Angel,'' the captivating futuristic series created by Mr. Cameron and Charles Eglee, Max is a 19-year-old heroine who shares a bit of all these characters.</p>
        <p>She, however, has a bar code on the back of her neck, a sign that she was the product of a secret genetic experiment called Manticore. The code is usually hidden by a tousle of dark curls, and because Max is played by Jessica Alba (who could win an Angelina Jolie look-alike contest) most people see only a beautiful young woman who rides a motorcycle and wears black leather. Tough and independent, Max is coolly guarded because of the secrets she knows and even more because of those she doesn't.</p>
        <p>What viewers won't know until next week's episode is that when Max puts on a cat suit she has earned the right: as she drily puts it, some ''feline DNA'' must have been put into her genetic mix, allowing her to leap across tall buildings and also sending her into heat a few times a year. This intimate detail is handled not with any crassness but with the tongue-in-cheek wit of the Terminator saying, ''I'll be back.'' That wry tone sets the winning ''Dark Angel'' apart from so many failed futuristic shows.</p>
        <p>It is easy to define ''Dark Angel'' by naming the films and series it resembles: part ''Blade Runner,'' part ''Xena, Warrior Princess'' with a huge dose of ''The X-Files.'' But like some genetic television experiment it emerges with a dynamic identity of its own.</p>
        <p>Another Cameron trademark is a big budget. Tonight's two-hour opening episode cost $10 million, nothing for a Hollywood film but extravagant for a television pilot. In the opening scene it is easy to see how much of that money was lavished on the action sequences Mr. Cameron loves (though he isn't directing this series).</p>
        <p>The story begins in Wyoming in 2009 when Max is 9. (It doesn't take a math genius to figure that the Manticore experiments are supposedly happening now.) In this harrowing sequence, Max is among a dozen children in hospital gowns, with nearly shaved heads, who escape into the frigid night from the military base where they have been bred. They run through snow, chased by men in military gear riding snowmobiles; some are shot by lasers; Max is rescued by a kindly female driver she has not seen since.</p>
        <p>When the story leaps ahead to Seattle in 2019, Max is in one of her favorite spots, on top of the Space Needle. The country has been devastated by a sort of nuclear accident.  ''Dark Angel'' layers on so many scientific disasters and conspiracy theories it's hard to keep them straight. All you need to know at first is what Max explains: an electromagnetic pulse caused banking computers to crash, destroying the economy and creating a depression. (For all its fantasy, in scenes like this ''Dark Angel'' feels eerily more attached to reality than the season's supposedly more realistic Wall Street series, ''Bull'' and ''The Street.'')</p>
        <p>''I don't get why people call it a  depression,'' Max says, displaying the self-protective guard she rarely lets down. ''People are broke but they're not all that depressed.''</p>
        <p>There are, however, food riots. And society has apparently taken an Orwellian turn. A computer hacker who identifies himself as Eyes Only sends streaming video he calls ''freedom messages'' to the public. He turns out to be a rich young crusader called Logan, a fair-haired yang to Max's yin. He will help Max try to track down the other boys and girls with bar codes; she will help him right social wrongs. The simmering attraction between them is already warmer than anything Scully and Muldur have admitted.</p>
        <p>In her day job, Max works as a bike messenger, which encourages her to wear more black leather and surrounds her with a ready-made cast of sharply cut characters, including her best friend, a lesbian named Original Cindy who laments that all the women she wants are straight. The wooden John Savage is the series' only weak link as the villain, a keeper of shady government secrets who is hunting Max down.</p>
        <p>The second episode is not as oversize or expensive as the first, yet its tangled stories and Ms. Alba's deft performance continue to be engaging. Max has the knowing cynicism of other not-quite-human young people on television, from ''Buffy the Vampire Slayer'' to the alien high school students of ''Roswell.'' The heroine of ''Dark Angel'' could only turn up on ''Touched by an Angel'' as a villain, though; that mischievous difference is part of what makes this new series so appealing.</p>
        <p>DARK ANGEL  Fox, tonight at 9  (Channel 5 in New York)</p>
        <p>James Cameron and Charles Eglee, executive producers; Rene Echevarria and Joe Ann Fogle, co-executive producers; Rae Sanchini and Stephen Sassen, producers; Patrick Harbinson, supervising producer. A production of Cameron/Eglee Productions in association with 20th Century Fox Television.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jessica Alba (Max), Michael Weatherly (Logan Cale) and John Savage (Lydecker).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
