<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Safety Agency Will Rate Vehicles for Rollover Tendencies</title>
    <meta content="Y03AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/business/03AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bridgestone Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Highway Traffic Safety Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E0DB133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1348" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Safety Agency Will Rate Vehicles for Rollover Tendencies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Oct. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Government regulators have tested more than 100 automobile models for their tendency to roll over and found that sport utility vehicles like Ford Explorer tend to be the least stable, particularly when fully loaded, while cars are most stable; House and Senate Appropriations Committees are scheduled to meet as soon as Oct 3 to approve transportation budget that would let National Highway Traffic Safety Administration begin rating vehicles' rollover tendencies, by assigning them one to five stars; charts; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Government regulators have tested more than 100 automobile models for their tendency to roll over and found that sport utility vehicles like the Ford Explorer tend to be the least stable, particularly when fully loaded, while cars are the most stable.</p>
        <p>After 27 years of controversy over the rollover issue, members of the House and Senate Appropriations Committees are scheduled to meet as soon as Tuesday to approve a transportation budget that would let the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration begin rating vehicles' rollover tendencies, by assigning them one to five stars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Government regulators have tested more than 100 automobile models for their tendency to roll over and found that sport utility vehicles like the Ford Explorer tend to be the least stable, particularly when fully loaded, while cars are the most stable.</p>
        <p>After 27 years of controversy over the rollover issue, members of the House and Senate Appropriations Committees are scheduled to meet as soon as Tuesday to approve a transportation budget that would let the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration begin rating vehicles' rollover tendencies, by assigning them one to five stars.</p>
        <p>But, to devise the rating systems, safety regulators have already calculated stability scores for many models through the 1998 model year. These scores, along with the method for converting them into stars, are already in the agency's public docket.</p>
        <p>While most cars receive four stars under the system, and some receive five, most sport utilities have scores that will net them just two stars.</p>
        <p>The government plans to publish the data in December for vehicles that are empty except for a driver. But government test data shows that many sport utilities would receive only one star if loaded with an adult in each seat and cargo equal to one or two suitcases.</p>
        <p>By contrast, the scores for sedans are virtually unaffected by the number of people and amount of cargo inside. People sit fairly low in sedans, keeping them stable, but the seats in sport utilities are mounted high off the road, in what auto marketers call the command position, and this makes the off-road vehicles more prone to tip over when fully loaded.</p>
        <p>The method for calculating the ratings -- comparing the width between a vehicle's tires to the height of its center of gravity -- is controversial. Automakers complain that it does not take into account the electronic stability systems now available on a few luxury models, nor does it reflect seat belt use, the best way to avoid dying or being paralyzed in a rollover crash. Consumers Union, the publisher of Consumer Reports, complains that by lumping most sport utilities together near the bottom of the rankings, the method does not allow consumers to distinguish the more stable sport utilities from the less stable.</p>
        <p>Quite a few sport utilities have become a little less unstable in recent years, the government data shows. A conspicuous exception is the Ford Explorer, which has accounted for most of the 103 deaths now attributed to Firestone tires, mainly because the Explorers rolled over when tires lost their treads.</p>
        <p>The Explorer received a score of 1.08 for the 1991 to 1994 model years, but slipped to 1.06 for 1995 to 1998, according to the government's calculations. Both scores would qualify the Explorer for just two stars, which encompasses scores from 1.05 to 1.12. A rating of two stars means that a vehicle has a 30 to 40 percent chance of rolling over during a single-vehicle crash serious enough to merit a police report.</p>
        <p>When carrying the maximum load recommended by Ford -- five passengers and 226 pounds of cargo -- a 1998 four-door Explorer has a stability score of 1.01. That would entitle it to only one star if the government included fully loaded vehicles in the rating system.</p>
        <p>A regulatory official who insisted on anonymity said the government planned to offer general information to consumers about fully loaded vehicles, but not separate ratings.</p>
        <p>David Champion, director of auto testing at Consumers Union, said this was insufficient, because motorists might not understand that it is more dangerous to load a sport utility fully than a car.</p>
        <p>''I think it should be done both ways,'' he said, adding that the government should also provide more information about the importance of keeping cargo low in tall vehicles. ''A roof rack on an S.U.V. is asking for trouble, and yet most S.U.V.'s come with roof racks.</p>
        <p>Rollovers are the deadliest kind of crashes, accounting for a quarter of all deaths in cars and nearly three-quarters of all deaths in sport utilities. Most rollovers occur after a vehicle has struck some object that ''trips'' it, like a curb, a guard rail, a lower vehicle or soft shoulder.</p>
        <p>Almost all the deaths in vehicles mounted with Firestone tires have involved rollovers, and 1995 and 1996 Explorers have had a particularly high death rate. But Jon Harmon, a Ford spokesman, said the company did not believe that the reduction in the Explorer's stability score had affected the death rate.</p>
        <p>While the stability score fell less than 2 percent, ''the tires got worse by a factor of 100 or 500,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Feaheny, a former vice president for car engineering at Ford who has testified against the company many times in litigation, said the score probably deteriorated because Ford chose a different, lighter front suspension beginning in 1995. A heavy suspension down low in the vehicle tends to improve a vehicle's score by lowering its center of gravity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harmon said the new suspension had improved the Explorer's stability, not hurt it, by making the vehicle's back end less likely to slide outward during a turn.</p>
        <p>Ford has calculated from government data on fatal crashes across the nation that Explorer occupants are 24 percent less likely to die in fatal crashes than are occupants of other midsize sport utility vehicles. But insurance industry data also shows that Explorer occupants are almost twice as likely to die in rollovers as occupants of Ford Taurus sedans.</p>
        <p>By making sport utilities like the Explorer heavier over the years, automakers have reduced somewhat their propensity to roll over and allowed them to override the bumpers and door sills of cars they hit, thereby transferring to other motorists much of the risk once associated with driving a sport utility. Overall death rates for sport utility occupants are now no higher than for car occupants.</p>
        <p>The most popular minivan models receive three stars under the government rating system, while pickup trucks receive one to three stars. Publicly available test data runs up through the 1998 model year; some models have changed since then, and some sport utilities are being widened to make them more stable, including the 2002 Explorer, which is set to go on sale early next year.</p>
        <p>Vehicles' susceptibility to the loss of a tire varies with their height, auto industry engineers say. This is because the taller the vehicle, the more its weight tends to move forward during braking, making the driver very dependent on maintaining whatever traction possible on the rear wheels to maintain control. If one of the rear tires fails -- Ford says the left rear tire seems the most prone to failure on the Explorer -- then controlling the vehicle becomes much harder. This is why groups like AAA advise motorists to avoid hitting the brakes hard or swerving when a tire fails, particularly if they are driving sport utility vehicles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
