<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Hospital Manager to Pay a Fraud Settlement of $95 Million</title>
    <meta content="03CARE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/national/03CARE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Quorum Health Group Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eichenwald, Kurt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1D9133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="634" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Hospital Manager to Pay a Fraud Settlement of $95 Million</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KURT EICHENWALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eichenwald, Kurt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Quorum Health Group, nation's largest hospital management company, agrees in principle to pay $95.5 million in civil penalties to settle two lawsuits accusing it of defrauding federal health care programs like Medicare; suits involved arcane accounting practice known as cost reporting, which has been at center of widespread criminal and civil investigations in hospital industry; larger of settlements, for $77.5 million, resolves accusations that company systematically misrepresented reimbursable expenditures for purpose of cheating government; remaining $18 million will settle suit accusing company of misallocating costs from single Alabama hospital, again for purpose of inflating federal reimbursement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Quorum Health Group, the nation's largest hospital management company, has agreed in principle to pay $95.5 million in civil penalties to settle two lawsuits that accused it of defrauding federal health care programs like Medicare.</p>
        <p>Both suits involved an arcane accounting practice known as cost reporting, which has been at the center of widespread criminal and civil investigations in the hospital industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Quorum Health Group, the nation's largest hospital management company, has agreed in principle to pay $95.5 million in civil penalties to settle two lawsuits that accused it of defrauding federal health care programs like Medicare.</p>
        <p>Both suits involved an arcane accounting practice known as cost reporting, which has been at the center of widespread criminal and civil investigations in the hospital industry.</p>
        <p>The larger of the two Quorum settlements, for $77.5 million, resolves accusations that the company systematically misrepresented reimbursable expenditures for the purpose of cheating the government. The remaining $18 million will settle a suit accusing the company of misallocating costs from a single Alabama hospital, again for the purpose of inflating federal reimbursement.</p>
        <p>Both suits were originally filed under the federal whistle-blower laws. Those laws allow individuals to sue on behalf of the government, and offer to those who bring the suits rewards of as much as 30 percent of the amount the government recovers. As a result, some federal whistle-blowers have become multimillionaires.</p>
        <p>The larger of the two suits involving Quorum was filed under seal in January 1993 by James F. Alderson, formerly the chief financial officer for a hospital that the company managed in Whitefish, Mont. Mr. Alderson was dismissed from his job 10 years ago, soon after refusing to follow the company's cost-reporting tactics, which he considered illegal.</p>
        <p>After years of struggle, Mr. Alderson is now finding vindication in the settlement, said one of his lawyers, John Phillips. ''It's been almost eight years since he filed the case,'' Mr. Phillips said, ''and he's finally seeing some light at the end of the tunnel.''</p>
        <p>The settlement of Mr. Alderson's suit could have implications for the nation's largest hospital company, HCA-The Healthcare Company, formerly the Columbia/HCA Healthcare Corporation. HCA and Quorum were once affiliated, and Mr. Alderson's suit also names the larger company, maintaining that it, too, improperly inflated its cost reports. HCA has tentatively agreed to pay the government $745 million to resolve some fraud accusations, but the deal is contingent on reaching a settlement in this cost-reporting case in the next few months.</p>
        <p>The second Quorum lawsuit, which remains under seal, was filed by a former employee at Flowers Hospital in Dothan, Ala. The company said this suit was filed after the employee had been fired for improper activities.</p>
        <p>Unlike HCA, which owns most of its hospitals, Quorum only managed most of the institutions where the cost-reporting practices were questioned. So the company received only indirect benefits from any improper reporting, with the extra cash actually going to the hospitals it managed.</p>
        <p>Quorum ''didn't keep most of the money,'' said Mr. Phillips, the lawyer for Mr. Alderson. As a result, the settlement is ''coming out of their hide.''</p>
        <p>Quorum, based in Brentwood, Tenn., outside Nashville, said it still believed it had acted ethically at all times. But, the company said, it needed to resolve the cases for business reasons.</p>
        <p>''Quorum is a good company with good people working here, many since the company was founded,'' James E. Dalton Jr., the chief executive, said in a statement. ''We continue to defend the honor and integrity of our company and associates. We have come to these understandings with all parties because we believe it is in the best interest of our associates, our company and our shareholders.''</p>
        <p>Analysts said the deal might open up opportunities for Quorum, including a sale of the company. Quorum recently hired Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company to explore ways to enhance its value.</p>
        <p>''This settlement would allow a sale to proceed, if that is a path the board wants to choose,'' said Peter H. Emch, health care services analyst with Credit Suisse First Boston.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
