<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inexplicably, Bucs Not Giving Ball to Johnson</title>
    <meta content="03FREE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/sports/03FREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Redskins</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tampa Bay Buccaneers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Keyshawn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tampa Bay Buccaneers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E6DA133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inexplicably, Bucs Not Giving Ball to Johnson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mike Freeman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>LANDOVER, Md.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>On Pro Football column notes that Tampa Bay Buccaneers receiver Keyshawn Johnson has been nonproductive in losses to New York Jets and Washington Redskins; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Keyshawn Johnson walked alone from the locker room on Sunday evening, a scowl on his face replacing that perfect smile. The Tampa Bay Buccaneers, once a Super Bowl favorite, had fallen to the Washington Redskins for their second consecutive bitter loss of the season. The offense was so bad that Buccaneers guard Frank Middleton had these indelicate words for it: ''We stink.''</p>
        <p>Middleton was not alone in expressing his disgust. For the first time, Johnson publicly expressed frustration with an offense that lacks imagination. ''We are a better team than this; we are better football players than this,'' Johnson said. ''This is a nightmare. What was I brought here for if they were going to use me this way?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Keyshawn Johnson walked alone from the locker room on Sunday evening, a scowl on his face replacing that perfect smile. The Tampa Bay Buccaneers, once a Super Bowl favorite, had fallen to the Washington Redskins for their second consecutive bitter loss of the season. The offense was so bad that Buccaneers guard Frank Middleton had these indelicate words for it: ''We stink.''</p>
        <p>Middleton was not alone in expressing his disgust. For the first time, Johnson publicly expressed frustration with an offense that lacks imagination. ''We are a better team than this; we are better football players than this,'' Johnson said. ''This is a nightmare. What was I brought here for if they were going to use me this way?''</p>
        <p>Against Washington, Johnson had 6 receptions for 42 yards. In five games, he has 21 catches for 223 yards. For an average receiver, these might be good numbers, but for a receiver of Johnson's caliber -- one of the top five in the sport -- those numbers are woefully low.</p>
        <p>Off to good starts are Minnesota's Randy Moss (19 catches, 364 receiving yards in four games), Indianapolis's Marvin Harrison (24 catches, 404 yards in four games), Buffalo's Eric Moulds (26 catches, 339 yards in four games), and Jacksonville's Jimmy Smith (38 catches, 536 yards in five games), to name just a few brilliant receivers. Yet Johnson is just as good, if not better, than most of them.</p>
        <p>Consider that in his first five games  with the Jets in 1998, Johnson had 24 catches for 334 yards, on par with other top receivers. Last season, Johnson had 30 catches for 460 yards after Week 5, on his way to a career-high 89 catches. Through the first four seasons of his career, Johnson averaged 76 catches. At his current pace with the Buccaneers, he would finish with 46.</p>
        <p>That is the fault of the Tampa Bay coaching staff, not Johnson. The Buccaneers have become conservative.</p>
        <p>''I'm behind Coach Dungy,'' Johnson said of Tampa Bay Coach Tony Dungy, one of the best coaches in football. ''I believe in him. But we can't keep going like this. This is extremely frustrating.''</p>
        <p>He's baaaacck. Johnson's not very happy. And he has a right not to be.</p>
        <p>The Buccaneers (3-2) are watching their season crumble because of the inexplicable misuse of Johnson, whom Tampa Bay paid $56 million in the off-season to transform their offense into a more fluid machine. Now Johnson is the most expensive decoy in football history.</p>
        <p>They won't throw Johnson the darn ball, and because he is further off the radar screen than a stealth bomber, the Buccaneers are missing offensive punch. If they don't figure out a way to use Johnson properly, any hope of a Super Bowl will remain just that, hope, not reality.</p>
        <p>There is no chance, no matter how good their defense is, that the Buccaneers can compete with the better teams of the conference -- Washington, Minnesota and St. Louis -- with a Stone Age offensive strategy. The Rams score more points in four minutes than the Buccaneers do in four quarters.</p>
        <p>''Opposing defenses are outplaying us,'' Middleton said. ''We're doing nothing to get better. It's a preview of where things are going if we don't correct the problems.''</p>
        <p>Last week, after Johnson's one-catch, one-yard game against the Jets, he spoke to the Tampa Bay coaching staff about getting more involved in the offense. It was a respectful, yet passionate, meeting. Johnson didn't demand anything. He just wanted to let his feelings be known. The coaches told him to be patient, that things would open up.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay uses Johnson too much on shallow sideline routes instead of sending him on medium post patterns across the middle, where he can use his 6-foot-4-inch, 212-pound frame against smaller defenders. Several times against Deion Sanders, Johnson simply outmuscled the 6-1 cornerback and was open in the middle, only to see the pass go to another receiver running a shorter route.</p>
        <p>The Buccaneers use too many plays where fullback Mike Alstott runs up the middle on first and second down, which is why the offense finds itself in third-and-long situations.</p>
        <p>Why not allow quarterback Shaun King to stretch the defense by throwing longer passes?</p>
        <p>At one point against Washington, the Buccaneers had 13 possessions, but just 11 first downs. During seven of those possessions, which spanned the second and third quarters, Tampa Bay punted six times. On the seventh possession, King took a knee to end the first half.</p>
        <p>Tampa Bay used a conservative formula last season and came close to beating the Rams in the N.F.C. championship game in St. Louis, losing, 11-6. But Tampa Bay's defense was practically unstoppable last year. This year it has proved vulnerable -- last season the defense never would have allowed the Jets to score 15 points in the final two minutes. And that is understandable. A defense, no matter how talented, cannot carry a weak offense indefinitely.</p>
        <p>So the Buccaneers need to throw the ball to Johnson. Again, and again, and again. Johnson should have 8 to 10 catches a game.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, the franchise had better tone down those championship expectations.</p>
        <p>ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
