<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supreme Court Roundup; Justices' Decisions Shape New Course for U.S. Sentencing</title>
    <meta content="03SCOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/national/03SCOT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of California</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Diversity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Affirmative Action</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Equal Educational Opportunities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5D6133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1338" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supreme Court Roundup; Justices' Decisions Shape New Course for U.S. Sentencing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court opens new term, directing potential revolution in federal criminal sentencing by vacating sentences for four narcotics defendants because central fact that determined sentence, namely quantity of drug involved, was decided by judge rather than jury; instructs lower courts to reconsider sentences in light of its June 26 ruling that any fact that increases penalty for crime beyond statutory maximum must be found by jury beyond reasonable doubt; turns down challenge to race-based admissions policy at public elementary school operated by University of California at Los Angeles; school, whose purpose is to conduct research on effective education methods in diverse urban areas, explicitly considers race, ethnicity and income levels in composing classes that mirror California's diversity; rejects constitutional challenge to 1994 federal law that prohibits manufacture, sale or possession of certain semiautomatic assault weapons (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court opened its new term today where it left off in June: directing a potential revolution in federal criminal sentencing.</p>
        <p>The court vacated sentences for four narcotics defendants because the central fact that determined the sentence -- the quantity of drugs involved -- had been decided by the judge rather than the jury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court opened its new term today where it left off in June: directing a potential revolution in federal criminal sentencing.</p>
        <p>The court vacated sentences for four narcotics defendants because the central fact that determined the sentence -- the quantity of drugs involved -- had been decided by the judge rather than the jury.</p>
        <p>The justices instructed the lower courts to reconsider the sentences in light of the Supreme Court's ruling on June 26 that any fact that increases the penalty for a crime beyond the statutory maximum has to be found by the jury beyond a reasonable doubt.</p>
        <p>The court dealt today with the leading edge of dozens of cases that would need to be reconsidered in the wake of the 5-to-4 ruling in Apprendi v. New Jersey, a decision that cut across the court's usual ideological boundaries and raised the prospect that the federal sentencing guidelines themselves might be unconstitutional because many crucial findings were made by the judge alone.</p>
        <p>The cases today did not raise the broader guidelines question, but rather a more precise issue under federal narcotics law that illustrates the type of question facing the courts in the wake of the Apprendi decision. The maximum sentence for possession of any quantity of heroin or cocaine is 20 years, which can be raised to 30 years if the defendant has a prior conviction.</p>
        <p>But if a defendant who has two or more serious drug convictions is then found guilty of an offense involving 50 grams or more of crack cocaine, a separate section of the law mandates a sentence of life in prison. After the Apprendi decision, that became problematic because the judge, not the jury, makes the factual finding on the quantity of drugs.</p>
        <p>The four cases the court acted on today shared a similar outline. For example, one defendant, Bobby Joe Burton, was charged in a federal indictment with conspiracy to manufacture and distribute crack cocaine, but the indictment did not specify any quantity. After a federal jury in Houston found Mr. Burton guilty, the trial judge found that the amount was ''in excess of 99 grams,'' sufficient to merit a life sentence despite the maximum of 30 years that would have otherwise applied.</p>
        <p>Responding to Mr. Burton's appeal, Burton v. United States, No. 99-9902, the Solicitor General's office told the court that imposing a life sentence based on a factual determination by the judge was ''plain error'' under the Apprendi decision.</p>
        <p>As a practical matter, Mr. Burton may not receive much relief from the reconsideration that the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit, in New Orleans, will give his sentence. As is often the case in major drug prosecutions, he was convicted on multiple counts, with sentences to run concurrently although the judge had the power to impose consecutive 30-year sentences. In seeking resentencing, Mr. Burton has the legal burden of demonstrating to the appeals court not only that his sentence was erroneous, but that he was actually harmed by the error.</p>
        <p>The other cases in which the court vacated sentences were Blue v. United States, No. 99-6775; Wims v. United States, No. 99-8958; and Gibson v. United States, No. 99-7351.</p>
        <p>The Apprendi decision, which took much of the legal world by surprise, invalidated a New Jersey hate-crime law under which defendants received longer sentences if their criminal actions were motivated by prejudice. The finding of prejudice was made by the judge, using the relaxed ''preponderance of the evidence'' standard of proof. Under the Apprendi decision, written by Justice John Paul Stevens, the jury had to make such a finding by the ordinary criminal law standard of ''beyond a reasonable doubt.''</p>
        <p>Justices Antonin Scalia, David H. Souter, Clarence Thomas and Ruth Bader Ginsburg joined in the majority opinion, which was based on the constitutional guarantees of due process and trial by jury, while Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and Justices Sandra Day O'Connor, Anthony M. Kennedy and Stephen G. Breyer dissented.</p>
        <p>While it is now clear that the jury must find the facts that can lead to a sentence longer than what would otherwise be the maximum, the Apprendi case raised a more difficult question that does not have a clear answer. Under federal sentencing guidelines, the judge makes a number of crucial findings that do not necessarily bring a sentence above the statutory maximum, but that can end up increasing a sentence sharply within the statutory range.</p>
        <p>Susan N. Herman, a professor at Brooklyn Law School who is an expert on criminal sentencing, said  that while the court today had dealt with the ''easy Apprendi question,'' the more difficult question of whether the justices will apply the logic of the decision to the guidelines remains ahead.</p>
        <p>''The question is how formalist the court will be,'' Ms. Herman said, adding: ''Tremendously important factual questions are decided at sentencing.'' For example, she said, the guidelines instruct judges to impose a sentence based not on the precise quantity of drugs for which a defendant was convicted, but on the ''relevant quantity,'' which requires deciding whether a defendant caught with a small quantity of drugs knew about an entire shipment of which the small amount formed a part.</p>
        <p>Depending on the judge's determination of such factors, Ms. Herman said, a sentence can increase by many years while remaining under the statutory maximum. The court will feel obliged to sort this out in the near future, she predicted.</p>
        <p>Disposing today of hundreds of new appeals, the court did not grant any new cases for review. These were among the cases the justices turned down, all without comment:</p>
        <p>School Admissions</p>
        <p>The justices turned down a challenge to a race-based admissions policy at a public elementary school operated by the University of California at Los Angeles. The school, the purpose of which is to conduct research on effective education methods in diverse urban areas, explicitly considers race, ethnicity and income levels in composing classes that mirror California's diversity.</p>
        <p>The policy was challenged by the parents of a child who was turned down for admission. The child was described as having mixed Caucasian and Japanese ancestry. The parents argued that race can constitutionally be taken into account only as a remedy for past discrimination. But the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit, in San Francisco, ruled last year that the school had a ''compelling state interest'' in maintaining a diverse student body on which to test various educational methods. The case was Hunter v. Regents of the University of California, No. 00-135.</p>
        <p>Assault Weapons</p>
        <p>The court rejected a constitutional challenge to the 1994 federal law that prohibits the manufacture, sale or possession of certain semiautomatic assault weapons. The makers of several such weapons, including the TEC-DC9 and TEC-22 semiautomatic pistols and the Striker 12 shotgun, challenged the law on the ground that it exceeded Congress's authority to regulate interstate commerce.</p>
        <p>The challenge was rejected by the federal appeals court here, with one judge, David Sentelle, issuing a strong call for the case to be reheard because, he said, the Supreme Court had ruled in a 1995 case striking down the Gun-Free School Zones Act that possession of a gun did not have enough connection with commerce to come within Congress's regulatory power.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration, urging the justices to reject the appeal, said the assault weapons ban was based on evidence that ''the nationwide market for firearms renders purely local prohibitions ineffective'' and was not invalidated by the 1995 decision in United States v. Lopez. The case today was Navegar v. United States, No. 99-1874.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
