<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>La Russa Throws a Curve: Ankiel to Start Over Kile</title>
    <meta content="03CARD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/sports/03CARD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">La Russa, Tony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ankiel, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7DA133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="893" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>La Russa Throws a Curve: Ankiel to Start Over Kile</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>ST. LOUIS, Oct. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St Louis Cardinals manager Tony La Russa announces that rookie pitcher Rick Ankiel will start first game of National League division series against Atlanta Braves; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In many ways, the St. Louis Cardinals have enjoyed a surprising season. So it was fitting that their manager, Tony La Russa, made a surprising announcement today.</p>
        <p>Instead of giving the ball to the 20-game winner Darryl Kile, La Russa chose the rookie left-hander Rick Ankiel to start Tuesday's Game 1 of the National League division series against the Atlanta Braves at Busch Stadium. Ankiel was 11-7 this year with a 3.50 earned run average, but Ankiel did his best pitching in September, when he was 3-0 with a 1.65 E.R.A in five starts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In many ways, the St. Louis Cardinals have enjoyed a surprising season. So it was fitting that their manager, Tony La Russa, made a surprising announcement today.</p>
        <p>Instead of giving the ball to the 20-game winner Darryl Kile, La Russa chose the rookie left-hander Rick Ankiel to start Tuesday's Game 1 of the National League division series against the Atlanta Braves at Busch Stadium. Ankiel was 11-7 this year with a 3.50 earned run average, but Ankiel did his best pitching in September, when he was 3-0 with a 1.65 E.R.A in five starts.</p>
        <p>Even so, why put a 21-year-old rookie on the mound in the playoff opener when Kile (20-11), has more experience and a better record? La Russa had his reasons. Ankiel does not pitch on three days' rest, so if he started Game 2 on Thursday, he would only pitch once in the three-of-five-game series. But Kile pitches effectively on three days' rest, so by starting Ankiel on Tuesday, Ankiel can pitch again Sunday in Game 4 if necessary, and Kile would pitch Monday if a fifth game is necessary.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to maximize our options if the series goes more than three games,'' La Russa said. ''Doing it this way gives Rick and Darryl a chance to pitch twice.''</p>
        <p>In a move that may have been planned, La Russa did not announce his decision until Kile had already held his news conference, with everyone assuming that Kile would start Game 1.</p>
        <p>Then when La Russa announced that Ankiel would start instead; both Ankiel and Kile had already left Busch Stadium, saving them from answering questions about La Russa's decision.</p>
        <p>La Russa, however, will not be able to hide Ankiel on Tuesday. And it will be interesting to see how the rookie handles the pressure of being matched against Greg Maddux (19-9), the veteran Braves starter who has been one of baseball's best pitchers for a decade. Having won nine consecutive division championships, the Braves enter the series as the favorite, yet the Cardinals have home-field advantage.</p>
        <p>In a season when Mark McGwire was limited to 89 games and missed most of the second half with a knee injury, the Cardinals kept winning without their home run king, with many players playing well. Five Cardinals hit at least 18 homers -- Jim Edmonds (42), McGwire (32), Ray Lankford (26), J. D. Drew (18) and Fernando Tatis (18), as the team hit more homers than any other in the league (235), except Houston (249). Meanwhile, the Cardinals augmented that power with steady pitching and solid defense to run away with the N.L. Central by 10 games.</p>
        <p>McGwire's status for the postseason remains the same as it was during September. He will only be available as a pinch-hitter, meaning La Russa must try to get the most out of McGwire's one at-bat.</p>
        <p>''You have to figure out when you think it's the best time to use him,'' La Russa said. ''You'll probably avoid a situation where a ground ball would hurt.''</p>
        <p>McGwire was impressive during today's workout, slamming more than a half-dozen balls into the seats. But the pain in his knee remains severe.</p>
        <p>''I'm just a pinch-hitter,'' McGwire said. ''We were hit with a lot of setbacks this year, but we won our division, and the guys have worked hard all year.''</p>
        <p>The Braves may have helped St. Louis's chances Sunday when they squandered home-field advantage for the series by losing to the Colorado Rockies, 10-5. Colorado shocked Atlanta with a seven-run ninth inning, and Chipper Jones made a key two-out fielding error that kept Colorado alive.</p>
        <p>So instead of starting the series at Turner Field, the Braves were forced to fly to St. Louis, and Jones admitted he was angry after Sunday's loss.</p>
        <p>''You vent, you go home, your wife and your dog hear about it after you get home, but then you let it go,'' Jones said. ''Of course we'd rather open in Atlanta, but we have to move on. If we can win one of the first two games, it'll be a moral victory, and we'll be in good position.''</p>
        <p>But the Cardinals, who won the season series (4-3) from Atlanta, believe they have an excellent chance to defeat the defending National League champions. St. Louis has embraced the underdog role, and beginning Tuesday, they hope Ankiel will make La Russa's surprising decision look good.</p>
        <p>''I know a lot of people don't expect us to win this series, but I think that gives us the upper hand,'' Lankford said. ''We all feel we have a good shot to win.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Cardinals suffered another setback on Friday, when MIKE MATHENY, the regular starting catcher, was lost for the season after severing a nerve in his right finger by accidentally cutting himself with a knife at home. Matheny was given a standing ovation Sunday when he handed out the lineup card, and the Cardinals won. Look for Matheny to hand out the lineup card again Tuesday, because TONY La RUSSA is superstitious.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
