<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Personnel but Old Approach As Van Gundy Plans for Season</title>
    <meta content="03KNIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/sports/03KNIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D6133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Personnel but Old Approach As Van Gundy Plans for Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Knickerbockers preparing for opening of training camp (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The roster seems to beg for Coach Jeff Van Gundy to toss out his old playbook and let the Knicks break free, outrun their opponents rather than out-pound them in the halfcourt. No one can dominate in the low post, but there are three high-scoring wing players and one lanky power forward who can flourish in the open court. There are at least five guards who deserve to play significant minutes but not a single player who possesses the height, brawn and ferocity to discourage opponents from attacking the basket.</p>
        <p>But Van Gundy, whose coaching philosophy was molded largely by the post-Showtime Pat Riley, has no intentions of leading a running team that focuses more on scoring than defending. While he will welcome the open-court style that helped the Knicks reach the National Basketball Association finals in 1999, Van Gundy said that he will not encourage it at the expense of the doggedness that has characterized his teams.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The roster seems to beg for Coach Jeff Van Gundy to toss out his old playbook and let the Knicks break free, outrun their opponents rather than out-pound them in the halfcourt. No one can dominate in the low post, but there are three high-scoring wing players and one lanky power forward who can flourish in the open court. There are at least five guards who deserve to play significant minutes but not a single player who possesses the height, brawn and ferocity to discourage opponents from attacking the basket.</p>
        <p>But Van Gundy, whose coaching philosophy was molded largely by the post-Showtime Pat Riley, has no intentions of leading a running team that focuses more on scoring than defending. While he will welcome the open-court style that helped the Knicks reach the National Basketball Association finals in 1999, Van Gundy said that he will not encourage it at the expense of the doggedness that has characterized his teams.</p>
        <p>In fact, when Van Gundy meets with his players today to open training camp at SUNY Purchase, he will tell them that even though Patrick Ewing will no longer loom for them in the paint, the strategy for the season remains the same as always.</p>
        <p>''The personnel in this league changes on every team but how you win is always the same,'' Van Gundy said. ''If you want a predictor of success in this league you base your team around defense and rebounding. If you want a predictor of mediocrity, you base it around scoring and running.</p>
        <p>''Our best defense will not be our offense. What happens is when you get a little smaller as a team, the natural inclination is to say, 'Let's run and shoot, have some fun.' Winning is fun, regardless of the style, and losing is boring regardless of the style. We have been as boring an outfit as you can possibly have and that's why we sell out because it's exciting to win. And there are some running teams in this league that can't draw a peon to their games because it is boring to watch when you lose.''</p>
        <p>Van Gundy will reorient the Knicks to that philosophy today through Thursday before the team flies to Charleston, S.C., to practice through next Monday. While he has a clear view of how his team will play, he admitted that he has no definitive starting lineup thus far. He said that only the power forward Larry Johnson is assured of starting, though he added that he could not fathom how Latrell Sprewell and Allan Houston would not be in the first five.</p>
        <p>Unless Van Gundy goes with the big backcourt, which he said he will consider, Charlie Ward will run the offense and the new acquisition Glen Rice will come off the bench for the first time in his 12-year career. But Rice figures big in Van Gundy's plans, and he intends to insert some new plays into the halfcourt set to exploit his great shooting ability off screens. Rice will also factor largely in the Knicks' post offense, joining Sprewell, Houston and Johnson as major threats down low. While it seems that the Knicks would do most of their scoring from the perimeter, Van Gundy said that game plan will not work.</p>
        <p>''We can't turn into a jump-shooting team,'' he said. ''If you're going to rely on the jump shot, you may beat a certain team with that but you're not going to win over the course of 82 games. You have to be inside-out, either with the post up or with the drive. So we have to do that.''</p>
        <p>Who will start at center is the biggest mystery heading into camp. The Knicks received a small bit of good news concerning the position yesterday when a magnetic resonance imaging test performed on Luc Longley revealed that he will most likely return in three to six weeks, rather than the previously estimated 8 to 10 weeks. Longley, the 7-foot-2-inch Australian who injured himself during the Olympics, roughed up some cartilage and bruised a bone in his right knee.</p>
        <p>When Longley returns, he will join the power forwards Kurt Thomas and Marcus Camby as the possible replacements for Ewing in the starting lineup. The Knicks also signed a journeyman center, the 7-foot Felton Spencer, 32, yesterday. Van Gundy implied that he will not focus too much on the trade of Ewing when addressing his team today, but naturally he will have to mention it. ''I just don't want us to use Pat's absence as a crutch or an excuse,'' Van Gundy said. ''It's too easy that way.''</p>
        <p>Van Gundy refused to reveal whatever goals he has for the team. He did, however, say that this will be one of the most challenging seasons that he and his players have ever faced.</p>
        <p>''I think this year we have more challenges and more questions than in years past because we've had more change than in the past,'' he said. ''The good thing about coaching and playing is that you have to reprove it every year. I don't know if it's the biggest but it's the one in front of me and the one in front of the team. We've got to have career years in shooting, and we've got to be mentally strong this year.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
