<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>And Now, a New Concept: The Yankees as Underdogs</title>
    <meta content="03MLB.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235802"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DE103DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="4495" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>And Now, a New Concept: The Yankees as Underdogs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Matchups for New York Yankees-Oakland Athletics playoff series noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YANKEES  87-74, A.L. East champion  vs  ATHLETICS  91-70, A.L. West champion</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YANKEES  87-74, A.L. East champion  vs  ATHLETICS  91-70, A.L. West champion</p>
        <p>Season series: Yankees won 6 of 9</p>
        <p>YANKEES</p>
        <p>PITCHING  The Yankees have 10 pitchers on their postseason roster, but based on how they have thrown in the past month, only six can be counted on. That lack of depth will not be a factor if the starting pitchers carry the burden that Manager Joe Torre is handing them. Roger Clemens, Andy Pettitte and Orlando Hernandez will start the first three games of the playoffs, and, if necessary, Clemens and Pettitte would pitch Games 4 and 5 on three days' rest. The Yankees want their starters to work deep into games, and they are all capable: Clemens averaged about seven innings a start, Pettitte and Hernandez more than six innings. Clemens is coming back from a bruised thigh but says it will not be a factor. The threesome of late-inning relievers -- the closer, Mariano Rivera, and the setup men Jeff Nelson and Mike Stanton -- have combined for a 1.10 earned run average in the postseason. But if the patient Oakland lineup quickly drives up the pitch count of the starters, then Torre will have to call on his middle relief, and he would have no idea what to expect. Denny Neagle, David Cone and Dwight Gooden have all been starting pitchers for most of their careers, and all struggled down the stretch. Oakland is heavy with left-handed hitters, meaning that the rookie left-handed specialist Randy Choate could be called on in crucial situations to face the likes of Jason Giambi.</p>
        <p>OFFENSE  The Yankees have been the model of patience over the past few years. Their hitters have ignored pitches out of the strike zone and created favorable ball-strike counts, forcing opposing pitchers to throw fastballs over the heart of the plate. The Yankees did this well in early September, but when the late-season slump began -- mostly because of terrible pitching -- the Yankees' hitters got away from their meticulous approach. With the exception of Derek Jeter, who batted .548 over his past 12 games, the offense has struggled. Paul O'Neill has gone almost a month without an extra-base hit, Scott Brosius about three weeks without a run batted in. The leadoff hitter Chuck Knoblauch has always set the tone, and if he and Jeter can jump-start the offense early in the series, the Yankees' attack could be jolted back to life. The experienced David Justice could be a huge presence because, like Jeter, he is capable of hitting a good pitcher who is having a good day. By the time the series is over, Justice will have played in more postseason games than anyone in baseball history.</p>
        <p>DEFENSE  The Yankees have had a subpar defense all year, with a few bright spots. Catcher Jorge Posada throws extremely well and is capable of shutting down a running game, even while teamed with a staff that is not good at holding runners. This will not be much of a factor, though, because Oakland does not run. Center fielder Bernie Williams sometimes misjudges balls hit in front of him and he throws poorly, but he does run down balls in the gap. Justice is underrated in left, but both he and O'Neill are moving uncomfortably in the outfield. Brosius at third and Tino Martinez at first have had strong years defensively; Jeter has been erratic and sometimes not confident with ground balls. If Torre goes with Luis Sojo at shortstop or Jose Vizcaino at second, the Yankees will be much stronger on double plays. Knoblauch has not had a throwing error since June 28, but he has appeared uncomfortable defensively.</p>
        <p>ON THE BASES  Jeter is the only consistent threat to steal, and even though he stole only two bases in the past month, he will look for chances to run. Knoblauch's aggressiveness tends to go in cycles -- he may look to steal early in the series, but if he gets thrown out on his first attempt, Knoblauch will be curbed. In general, the Yankees have an average to below-average base-running team, with a few slow players like Martinez. In the past six weeks, they have made a number of mistakes. Luis Polonia could be used as a pinch-runner in late-inning situations, and the best thing about him is that he is not afraid to make a mistake; that is the worst thing about him, too.</p>
        <p>X-FACTOR  The umpires will play a major role for the Yankees in the first round because their interpretation of the strike zone will have a lot to do with how long the Yankees' starting pitchers last. The Oakland hitters are adept at taking pitches and drawing walks, and if the home-plate umpire happens to be calling a small strike zone -- particularly for Pettitte, who pitches to the fringe of the zone -- then the starter will not survive beyond the sixth inning.</p>
        <p>ATHLETICS</p>
        <p>PITCHING  Oakland had to push to the end to clinch a playoff spot, so Manager Art Howe was not able to set his pitching rotation the way he would have preferred. Still, Gil Heredia and Kevin Appier are veterans who have had some success against the Yankees: Heredia can be precise with his command, and his ability to change speeds bothers the Yankees, and if Appier is throwing strikes, he can be nasty. On the other hand, Heredia and Appier are both capable of being terrible. The staff ace, Tim Hudson, will pitch in Game 3, and the unflappable rookie left-hander Barry Zito would start in Game 4. Oakland's bullpen is thin but potentially effective -- the ex-Yankee right-hander Jim Mecir could play a major role in this series because his screwball makes him effective against left-handed batters like David Justice, Bernie Williams and Paul O'Neill. The closer, Jason Isringhausen, is a wild card -- he pitched badly down the stretch, blowing a lead and losing on consecutive pitches at Yankee Stadium in August, but he still has great stuff. Mike Magnante will be used against left-handers and the ancient Doug Jones works in the middle, but if the Athletics are in a position in which they have to rely on those two, they would probably be in trouble.</p>
        <p>OFFENSE  The Athletics' offensive theory goes something like this: Do not swing often, and when you do, kill the ball. They draw a lot of walks and hit a lot of home runs. First baseman Jason Giambi is their most dangerous hitter and will probably win the American League Most Valuable Player award. The Yankees will probably pitch around Giambi every chance they get and take their chances with Miguel Tejada, the free-swinging shortstop who is susceptible to strikeouts. Third baseman Eric Chavez is going to be a big-time star in another year or two, and he will be a dangerous presence in the series because of his talent and laid-back demeanor. Giambi takes 64.5 percent of the pitches thrown to him, third most in the league, but incredibly, the Athletics have two other players ranked among the top 10 -- Randy Velarde (sixth) and Matt Stairs (eighth). Their ability to take pitches, draw walks and drive up the pitch counts of Roger Clemens, Andy Pettitte and Orlando Hernandez will be the most important factor in the series.</p>
        <p>DEFENSE  Oakland's greatest weakness, although the Athletics did reduce their mistakes in the final month of the season when they made their push for the division title. Tejada can be spectacular or erratic at short, Velarde is solid at second and Terrence Long has a lot of range in center field. But Chavez is young and makes a lot of errors, Ben Grieve is a terrible left fielder, and Stairs has a good throwing arm but subpar range in right field. Ramon Hernandez, the Oakland catcher, does not have a strong arm, and when Appier is on the mound, with his deliberate approach, the Yankees will be able to run at will.</p>
        <p>ON THE BASES  The Athletics rarely run, preferring instead to wait and avoid mistakes. Howe seems to be giving license to Long, their leadoff hitter, and he would probably look to run in a pivotal situation against someone like reliever Jeff Nelson, who is vulnerable to the stolen base. Velarde likes to be aggressive but tends to try too hard and to make mistakes. Beyond those two, the Athletics are a lot like the Yankees, loaded with guys with average speed.</p>
        <p>X-FACTOR  The Yankees' players have 46 World Series rings among them, while the Athletics have zero. In fact, reliever T.J. Mathews had advanced deeper into the playoffs than any of his teammates -- as a member of the St. Louis Cardinals, who blew a three-games-to-one lead against the Atlanta Braves in 1996. No one knows how the Athletics' young players will react to the pressure, but this is a sample of conventional wisdom: At shortstop, Tejada will be anxious and overaggressive at the plate; Isringhausen, the closer, will fight his emotions, while Chavez at third and Grieve in left field will be unaffected.</p>
        <p>SEATTLE  91-71, wild card  vs  CHICAGO  95-67, A.L. Central champion</p>
        <p>Season series: Chicago won 7 of 12</p>
        <p>CHICAGO WHITE SOX  The league's best won-lost record doesn't mean a thing with three of the starting pitchers who were responsible for 39 victories ailing. The White Sox will never know how far they might have gone with a healthy James Baldwin, Cal Eldred and Mike Sirotka. So the outcome of Chicago's surprising season is left to Frank Thomas and the hitters who made the team the toughest in the league offensively. With Thomas leading them with 43 home runs and 143 runs batted in, the White Sox led the A.L. in runs scored and slugging percentage. Magglio Ordonez was a solid second in contribution with 32 homers and 126 R.B.I. Not to be overlooked is Ray Durham, the leadoff batter, who begins many of the scoring spurts. The hitters have an even bigger task. They not only have to overcome the pitching injuries, but also cancel out their fielding mishaps. The White Sox committed 133 errors, placing them among the four most defensively challenged teams in the league.</p>
        <p>SEATTLE MARINERS  This is a team that had a seven-game lead on Aug.11 and a two-game lead on Aug. 20. This is a team that had a seven-game winning streak during the middle of last month and held a three-game lead with 10 games to play, then squandered it and had to win the final two games to salvage the wild-card spot. Perhaps the 1,247 runners the Mariners left on base caught up with them. That number was the league's second highest, only three below the total for the Cleveland Indians, whom they edged by a game for the wild card. Besides Alex Rodriguez (41 homers, 132 R.B.I.) and Edgar Martinez (37, 145), the Mariners' strength is in their pitching and their defense, both of which placed second in the league. Aaron Sele (17-10) was the starting rotation leader, and Kazahiro Sasaki  (37 saves), the Japanese import, the No.1 reliever. They made it to the playoffs without Ken Griffey Jr., but they didn't make it as impressively as it appeared they would eight weeks ago.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL LEAGUE</p>
        <p>ATLANTA  95-67, N.L. East champion  vs  ST. LOUIS  95-67, N.L. Central champion</p>
        <p>Season series: St. Louis won 4 of 7</p>
        <p>ATLANTA BRAVES  The good time of the year for the Braves is past. Now comes the agonizing part. Having won their ninth consecutive division championship, the Braves now have to attain greater success in the postseason than they usually have. They have won only one World Series, and last October the Yankees swept them in four games. As usual, they will rely on Greg Maddux and Tom Glavine to pitch them past the first round, but the pestiferous pair don't have John Smoltz joining them this time. Instead, it's Andy Ashby, the Philadelphia expatriate, who doesn't inspire the same confidence the team had in Smoltz. The Jones boys, Chipper and Andruw, are prepared to power the offense -- they hit 72 home runs and drove in 215 runs between them. But Chipper can't make the kind of error he committed with one out to go in the Braves' regular-season finale, which undermined their ability to gain home-field advantage for the series.</p>
        <p>ST. LOUIS CARDINALS  Mark McGwire clouts record numbers of home runs, the Cardinals don't make the playoffs. He misses two months of the season with a knee injury, they make the playoffs. Since his return to ''active'' duty early last month, McGwire has been restricted to one at-bat a game and has not done much damage. However, Will Clark, his replacement, has rejuvenated himself and goes into the postseason with a .345 batting average, a .655 slugging percentage and 12 home runs and 42 R.B.I. in 51 games since he was obtained from Baltimore. In McGwire's absence, Jim Edmonds became the overall offensive leader, slugging 42 home runs and driving in 108 runs. Darryl Kile, like Edmonds an off-season acquisition, became the team's No. 1 pitcher with 20 victories. But Pat Hentgen, another trade acquisition, had to settle for 15 with an earned run average (4.72) that was nearly a full run higher than Kile's 3.91. The staff surprise was Garrett Stephenson, a 16-game winner.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL Here is a scouting report on the three division series that begin today. Buster Olney analyzes the struggling Yankees and surging Oakland A's and Murray Chass takes a look at the matchups involving the Chicago White Sox and Seattle Mariners, and the St. Louis Cardinals and Atlanta Braves. A scouting report on the Mets-San Francisco Giants series will appear tomorrow.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Here is a scouting report on the three division series that begin today. Buster Olney analyzes the struggling Yankees and surging Oakland A's and Murray Chass takes a look at the matchups involving the Chicago White Sox and Seattle Mariners, and the St. Louis Cardinals and Atlanta Braves. A scouting report on the Mets-San Francisco Giants series will appear tomorrow.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
