<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOTLIGHTS</title>
    <meta content="03FOOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/arts/03FOOT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lincoln Center Great Performers Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Steuben</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Museum of Art</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Museum of Art (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krasner, Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DE133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOTLIGHTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Great Performers series at Lincoln Center begins new season on Oct 4; Steuben, renowned for its crystal designs and which in 1940 exhibiting art commissioned from Dali, Matisse, O'Keeffe and other artists, is revisiting that exhibition with show 27 Contemporary Artists, at Corning Incorporated Gallery at Steuben, on Madison Ave; retrospective devoted to Lee Krasner finishes national tour with run at Brooklyn Museum; photo; Metropolitan Museum to present exhibition The Year One: Art of the Ancient World East and West; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEWS</p>
        <p>Curtain Raiser  Thirty-five and still glowing, the Great Performers series at Lincoln Center begins a new season at 8 p.m. tomorrow at Avery Fisher Hall. In the spotlight will stand the soprano Renee Fleming, the baritone Dmitry Hvorostovsky and the Orchestra of St. Luke's led by Mark Elder. On the program are opera favorites by Puccini, Gounod and Mozart, as well as excerpts from Tchaikovsky's ''Eugene Onegin.'' The event, to be broadcast by PBS on ''Live From Lincoln Center'' with Beverly Sills as host, will be preceded by a black-tie benefit to support Lincoln Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEWS</p>
        <p>Curtain Raiser  Thirty-five and still glowing, the Great Performers series at Lincoln Center begins a new season at 8 p.m. tomorrow at Avery Fisher Hall. In the spotlight will stand the soprano Renee Fleming, the baritone Dmitry Hvorostovsky and the Orchestra of St. Luke's led by Mark Elder. On the program are opera favorites by Puccini, Gounod and Mozart, as well as excerpts from Tchaikovsky's ''Eugene Onegin.'' The event, to be broadcast by PBS on ''Live From Lincoln Center'' with Beverly Sills as host, will be preceded by a black-tie benefit to support Lincoln Center.</p>
        <p>The Glass Is Full  In 1940, Steuben, renowned for its crystal designs, exhibited art commissioned from Dali, Matisse, O'Keeffe, Benton, de Chirico, Cocteau, Derain, Dufy, Leger and Noguchi. Steuben is now revisiting that exhibition. ''27 Contemporary Artists'' is the first public showing of the signed drawings and sketches as well as several of the original glass works on loan from private collections  and museums. The show will continue through Oct. 29 at the Corning Incorporated Gallery at Steuben, 667 Madison Avenue, at 61st Street.</p>
        <p>Seen Fresh  Coincident with the opening of a film about Jackson Pollock, a retrospective devoted to  Lee Krasner, Pollock's wife, finishes a national tour with a run from Friday through Jan. 7 at the Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park. Billed as the first such show devoted to Krasner (1908-1984), a Brooklyn native, since her death, the exhibition gathers 60 paintings, collages and drawings from major collections. Tracing the arc of Krasner's work, the chronological display makes clear her contributions to Abstract Expressionism and her dialogue with artists, critics and writers, among them Hans Hoffman, de Kooning, Matisse, Mondrian and Picasso. And it shows that while Pollock's work influenced Krasner's, she influenced his.</p>
        <p>Time Machine  At the Metropolitan Museum of Art, it's back to the days of the Emperor Augustus (27 B.C.-A.D. 14), an era of Roman grandeur and hegemony in a network stretching east and west. This was the time of the year 1. Beginning today and drawing almost entirely on its own encyclopedic collections, the museum will exhibit nearly 150 works produced some 2,000 years ago. Portrait busts, bronze statues, architectural decorations, terracotta sculptures, Asian drums, gold masks and much more will be displayed through Jan. 14 in ''The Year One: Art of the Ancient World East and West.''</p>
        <p>LAWRENCE VAN GELDER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
