<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mission To Redirect Money Used For Defense</title>
    <meta content="Y03PEA$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/national/03PEAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pax Christi Usa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DA133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mission To Redirect Money Used For Defense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <dateline>ST. CLOUD, Minn., Sept. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Pax Christi, Roman Catholic organization whose members are on cross-country tour urging that military spending be reduced and that money be saved for social needs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under a radiant autumn sky, a bus with a sign identifying it as the ''Moneymobile'' pulled into the College of St. Benedict, a Roman Catholic institution near here. The bus's five young occupants emerged and inflated nine large balloons, which assumed a form both festive and esoteric -- billowing, multicolored pie charts and bar graphs representing federal spending.</p>
        <p>As a largely student crowd of about 100 gathered, one of the bus passengers, Shauna Farabaugh, 23, announced what was coming: a presentation by a Catholic organization on a cross-country tour urging that military spending be reduced and that the money saved go to health care and education.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Under a radiant autumn sky, a bus with a sign identifying it as the ''Moneymobile'' pulled into the College of St. Benedict, a Roman Catholic institution near here. The bus's five young occupants emerged and inflated nine large balloons, which assumed a form both festive and esoteric -- billowing, multicolored pie charts and bar graphs representing federal spending.</p>
        <p>As a largely student crowd of about 100 gathered, one of the bus passengers, Shauna Farabaugh, 23, announced what was coming: a presentation by a Catholic organization on a cross-country tour urging that military spending be reduced and that the money saved go to health care and education.</p>
        <p>''What we choose to prioritize as funding says a lot about us as a nation,'' Ms. Farabaugh said, as another person from the bus, dressed as Uncle Sam, appeared for a scripted debate about federal spending and social needs.</p>
        <p>The presentation was part of a two-month effort by Pax Christi USA, a venerable peace organization with 14,000 members and headquarters in Erie, Pa., to call attention to an issue with which it has long been concerned.</p>
        <p>But in a larger sense, the bus journey illustrates how some religious organizations have been trying to call attention to broad issues that fall outside the themes that seem to dominate the close presidential race, themes like tax cuts and prescription drug costs for the elderly.</p>
        <p>Over a 40-day stretch in July and August, the Fellowship of Reconciliation, an interfaith antiwar organization, held a series of events in Washington called the People's Campaign for Nonviolence, seeking nuclear disarmament, abolition of the death penalty and the lifting of sanctions on Iraq.</p>
        <p>''We are, in our modest but persistent way, continuing to call for those changes,'' said the Rev. John Dear, the fellowship's executive director. ''There's a lot of grass-roots organizing happening,'' Father Dear said, ''on justice issues.''</p>
        <p>In a separate effort in June, a group of religious leaders and retired generals and admirals issued a statement calling for the elimination of nuclear weapons. Their statement -- part of an effort called the Nuclear Reduction/Disarmament Initiative -- called for ''a great national and international discussion and examination of the true and full implications of reliance on nuclear weapons, to be followed by action leading to the international prohibition of these weapons.''</p>
        <p>The statement has been signed by Protestants, Catholics, Jews, Muslims and others.</p>
        <p>''Many of us in positions of religious leadership follow these matters more closely than many people would assume,'' said one signer, the Rev. John A. Buehrens, president of the Unitarian-Universalist Association.</p>
        <p>Noting the statement's interfaith character and the number of military officials who signed, Mr. Buehrens added, ''It's not coming from a romantic or naive view of the dangers in this world.''</p>
        <p>Pax Christi's project began in March, when the organization released a statement signed by 34 Catholic bishops, some of them retired, calling for ''a national Catholic campaign of prayer, study and action to end exorbitant military spending.''</p>
        <p>Titled ''Bread, Not Stones,'' it said the federal budget should be viewed as a ''moral document,'' reflecting compassion for society's have-nots. It also described a lack of health insurance and adequate child care for poor families as ''a tragic consequence of a nation which chooses to spend only 6 cents on education and 4 cents on health care for every 50 cents it spends on the military.''</p>
        <p>Later, the organization received an offer of help -- use of the Moneymobile -- from a nonprofit organization called Business Leaders for Sensible Priorities, whose president is Jerry Cohen, co-founder of Ben and Jerry's Ice Cream. The group holds that military spending can be cut without endangering national security, and the money redirected to health care and education.</p>
        <p>Before the Iowa presidential caucuses and the New Hampshire primary last winter, the group dispatched its bus through both states, holding public events with the inflatable charts, a spokesman, David Crosson, said.</p>
        <p>For the last three weeks, the bus has made its way among college campuses, Catholic high schools and public parks in California, New Mexico, Texas, Missouri and Minnesota. Stops are planned in 33 cities, with Chicago, New York and Boston to come, before the tour ends in Burlington, Vt., just before Election Day.</p>
        <p>Those on board say the presentations have sometimes drawn only a handful of people. But sometimes there are crowds like the one at St. Benedict.</p>
        <p>''We do a lot of college campuses,'' said Katie Krolczyk, ''and some are into it and some are not.''</p>
        <p>Shortly before they visited St. Benedict, in nearby St. Joseph, Ms. Krolczyk and the tour organizer, Eric LeCompte, stopped by a Catholic high school in St. Cloud to speak with students. During a break, Mr. LeCompte said that neither he nor others in the bus favored cuts in military pay. ''In no way do we think that providing less for our soldiers is just,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
