<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sydney Anticipates Long-Term Boon</title>
    <meta content="03IMPA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/sports/03IMPA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SYDNEY 2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2DD133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1224" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sydney Anticipates Long-Term Boon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>SYDNEY, Australia, Oct. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses anticipated economic boom that Sydney, Australia, will receive as result of hosting 2000 Summer Olympic Games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They call Australia the lucky country, and there may be no better example of its good fortune than the unexpected windfall Sydney is reaping at the end of these Olympics.</p>
        <p>Thanks to a steep drop in the value of the Australian dollar relative to the United States dollar, the broadcast rights earmarked to the Sydney Olympic committee have risen in value by about $28 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They call Australia the lucky country, and there may be no better example of its good fortune than the unexpected windfall Sydney is reaping at the end of these Olympics.</p>
        <p>Thanks to a steep drop in the value of the Australian dollar relative to the United States dollar, the broadcast rights earmarked to the Sydney Olympic committee have risen in value by about $28 million.</p>
        <p>''Australians don't like having a weak dollar because they view exchange rates as a scorecard you get  on your country,'' said Bruce Hockman, a senior economist at Deutsche Bank here. ''But it's great for the Olympic committee because it will help them balance their books.''</p>
        <p>As Sydney closes the books on a generally trouble-free Olympics, the bigger question is, how much of a long-term economic boost will the Games give to the city, and to Australia as a whole?</p>
        <p>The government, citing a study by the consulting firm Arthur Andersen, figures the Olympics will add $3.6 billion to Australia's gross domestic product in the 12 years before and after the Games. It says the money will come mainly from increased tourism, but also from new jobs and consumer spending.</p>
        <p>In the current quarter alone, according to the government, the Games boosted Australia's economic output by 1 percent, through tourism receipts, ticket sales, broadcast rights and sponsorship fees.</p>
        <p>The real bonanza could come later, if Australia can capitalize on the success of the Games to become a top tourist destination. The Australian Tourism Forecasting Council predicts that 1.04 million additional tourists will visit here between 2001 and 2004 because of the aura of the Olympics.</p>
        <p>But skeptics note that Australia is still a very long way from Europe and the United States. Many fewer people than expected came to the Games, largely because they balked at the marathon flight.</p>
        <p>Nor have the Olympics been a boon for previous host cities, like Barcelona, which were looking to put themselves on the map. In fact, the enduring legacy for most cities has been a nasty hangover.</p>
        <p>Montreal took decades to pay off more than $1 billion in debt from the 1976 Games. Barcelona was left with $1.4 billion in debts after 1992. Even Los Angeles and Atlanta, which turned a profit on their Games, gained little in the way of jobs or other long-term economic benefits.</p>
        <p>Sydney's goal was simply to break even. And it did that, give or take $38 million. But the finances looked parlous for a while.</p>
        <p>Under an agreement between the Sydney Olympic committee and the state of New South Wales, the government invested $1.2 billion to improve roads, railroad links and other infrastructure. It also pledged $259 million for extra police, medical care, and other services during the Games.</p>
        <p>The Olympic committee had a budget of $1.3 billion, which it was supposed to meet through broadcast-rights fees, sponsorships, ticket sales and licensing arrangements. Six months before the Games opened, it ran over budget and the state had to set up a $76 million bailout fund.</p>
        <p>Sydney Olympic officials said they had drawn half of those funds to pay for the higher-than-expected cost of completing sites. In the scheme of things, they said, a $38 million shortfall was not much.</p>
        <p>''People always understood that the Games would cost more than the government projected,'' said Graham Cassidy, a spokesman for the Olympic committee. ''That has been the reality ever since Montreal.''</p>
        <p>The Olympic committee would have had a bigger shortfall but for two things: a last-minute surge in ticket sales, which allowed it to sell 90 percent of its supply, and the crash of the Australian dollar.</p>
        <p>This helped Sydney because its largest single source of revenue -- $633 million in rights fees -- are paid by NBC and other broadcasters in United States dollars. At the time the deals were signed, the Olympic committee calculated they were worth 1.03 billion Australian dollars.</p>
        <p>Since then, the Aussie dollar has fallen to a near-record low of 0.54 to the United States dollar. By the magic of foreign exchange, the rights are now valued at about 1.2 billion Australian dollars. Since the broadcasters still owe $300 million, that translates into a $28 million gain.</p>
        <p>The weak currency could also help Australia's tourism efforts. ''The most important thing is that Americans will go home and tell people how cheap Australia is for a vacation,'' Mr. Hockman said.</p>
        <p>Beyond the direct benefits, Australia believes the Games will enhance its standing in the global economy. Despite having an educated work force and a remarkably healthy economy, Australia has been somewhat overlooked by investors in developed countries because of its geographic isolation.</p>
        <p>The last two weeks have been a marvelous showcase for Australia's accomplishments in engineering and technology. Whether it is the soaring Olympic stadium, the efficient railroad system or the modern wireless telephone network, Australia is a force to be reckoned with.</p>
        <p>''These are the first Games of the new economy,'' said Tim Harcourt, chief economist of the Australian Trade Commission. ''We've shown we're strong in the pool, but we're also strong in other skills.''</p>
        <p>A few multinational firms are already recognizing Australia's talents. Cisco Systems, the Internet equipment maker, recently established a Sydney office with 1,000 employees to serve Asian customers in 15 languages.</p>
        <p>Australian firms are also winning recognition abroad. The local company that designed the seating in many of the Olympic arenas is on the short list of candidates to design the seats in Wembley Stadium in London, which is being rebuilt. It may also pick up a lucrative contract for the Athens Games.</p>
        <p>Many Olympic host cities -- even successful ones -- have struggled to make use of the vast stadiums and other facilities that remain after the Olympic torch is extinguished. That is especially true in Sydney, which built more sites, on a grander scale, than most of its predecessors.</p>
        <p>With the completion of the Olympic stadium in 1999, Sydney became one of the few cities of its size with three huge stadiums. The Olympic Park has nine other major facilities -- some outdoor, some domed.</p>
        <p>Cassidy said the park would pay for itself by revitalizing the geographic heart of Sydney. The site on which the world's greatest athletes competed over the last two weeks had been a wasteland of slaughterhouses, landfills and toxic-waste dumps before the Olympic building program began.</p>
        <p>Sydney will use the Olympic stadium for rugby matches, and as a likely home for a second Australian-rules football team. It also plans to rent the tennis courts and other facilities for private use.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Hockman said it was hard to imagine how Sydney, with a population of four million, could sponsor enough sporting events or generate enough traffic to fill all these facilities regularly.</p>
        <p>''That's a big issue, but it's not necessarily a problem for the government, because most of the buildings are privately owned,'' he said.</p>
        <p>SYDNEY 2000</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
