<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ulster Town's Memories: Healing and Hurting</title>
    <meta content="Y03ULS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/03/world/03ULST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northern Ireland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Omagh (Northern Ireland)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EFDC133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2242" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ulster Town's Memories: Healing and Hurting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>OMAGH, Northern Ireland</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pain returns to Omagh, Northern Ireland, with renewed urgency as government inquest nears end into bombing more than two years ago, which killed 29 people and wounded more than 300 in worst atrocity in 31 years of sectarian violence; realization has become apparent that no one will ever be charged; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sylvia Crawford is still haunted by the image of the sign from her shattered bridal shop -- Joyful Occasions, it said -- being used as a stretcher for the dying. For Mary Logue, perhaps the worst memory is of scrabbling through rubble, looking for her daughter but knowing in her heart that she was already dead.</p>
        <p>It has been more than two years since a terrorist bomb killed 29 people and wounded more than 300 on a busy Saturday afternoon here, in the worst atrocity in the 31-year history of the Irish Troubles. But pain still gnaws at Omagh, a gentle country town about 60 miles west of Belfast where it is increasingly apparent that no one will ever be charged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sylvia Crawford is still haunted by the image of the sign from her shattered bridal shop -- Joyful Occasions, it said -- being used as a stretcher for the dying. For Mary Logue, perhaps the worst memory is of scrabbling through rubble, looking for her daughter but knowing in her heart that she was already dead.</p>
        <p>It has been more than two years since a terrorist bomb killed 29 people and wounded more than 300 on a busy Saturday afternoon here, in the worst atrocity in the 31-year history of the Irish Troubles. But pain still gnaws at Omagh, a gentle country town about 60 miles west of Belfast where it is increasingly apparent that no one will ever be charged.</p>
        <p>For the last month, the pain has returned with renewed urgency, as an elaborate government inquest revisits every excruciating detail of the bombing, from the fatally contradictory telephone warnings received by the police, to the way death came to Brenda Mary Logue, 17, as she stepped out of a clothing shop and into a 300-pound explosion.</p>
        <p>Until now, inquests to establish cause of death in such bombings have typically been perfunctory; sometimes political tensions have prevented them entirely. But the Omagh attack occurred in peacetime, and many here are heavily invested in sustaining that peace. The inquest is one way to try.</p>
        <p>The proceedings, which began in early September and will conclude this week, are proving something of a catharsis for Northern Ireland -- lingering on the victims, and the ordinary events surrounding their deaths: where they were when the bomb went off, who held their hands afterward, how they died.</p>
        <p>By formally acknowledging the depth of feeling here -- an approach virtually unheard of in the history of the conflict -- the inquest is helping Omagh recover from its anguish without giving in to bitterness. In the way a funeral would, it is giving the bereaved another hurdle to pass as they try to find a way forward.</p>
        <p>''The memories are flooding back with the inquest, and that's partly a good thing,'' said Barry Curran, an optometrist whose office was destroyed and has since been rebuilt as a sleek modern practice, with a cheery blue facade. ''A lot of us are hoping that the inquest will give relatives some comfort, will let them pick up the pieces and move on.''</p>
        <p>For many people numbed by decades of terrorist war, the gentleness of the coroner, John Leckey -- who never fails to thank the witnesses, or to say how sorry he is as he elicits the details of each death -- represents the first time they have heard anything approaching an official recognition of the war's emotional cost.</p>
        <p>''Many of the institutions here have become hardened and cynical after the events of the last 30 years,'' said Michael Duffy, a cognitive psychotherapist who is leading a team of 12 trauma counselors in Omagh. ''Human loss and suffering have not been adequately acknowledged. The government is now recognizing that the needs of victims are an important part of the political solution. If their needs aren't addressed, there can't be peace.''</p>
        <p>The presence of Mr. Duffy's team marks another first: the first time professional counselors have been systematically deployed into a grieving Northern Ireland community.</p>
        <p>Omagh is about two-thirds Roman Catholic, and one-third Protestant, and religion and politics are never far from the surface. But after the bombing, its 20,000 or so residents, who had generally prided themselves on keeping politics out of their lives, refused to succumb to sectarian division.</p>
        <p>They talked to one another and wept together. They made use of the community and social service groups that were already here, and of new ones that, like Mr. Duffy's, arrived to help.</p>
        <p>In the month after the bomb, 2,000 people visited the town's family doctors. In two years, 625 have sought help from Mr. Duffy and his team. And, perhaps in part because of the extended counseling, they decided that their best weapon against the terrorists would be to use their grief to work toward peace.</p>
        <p>''After the bomb happened, a lot of the bereaved families got together,'' said Michael Gallagher, whose 21-year-old son, Aidan, was among the dead, and who helped set up a support group for victims' relatives. ''We wanted to take some control over our own lives again and, if we could, to influence how things were working out. We believed it was important that the people didn't achieve what they came to Omagh to achieve, which was to divide the community and derail the peace process.''</p>
        <p>It has not been easy for the town to remain united, just as it has not been easy for Northern Ireland to hang on to the peace since the Good Friday accords were signed in 1998. This is a town where Protestant and Roman Catholic children attend different schools, and where the police believe that it was not a coincidence that the bomb was placed outside the shop of a vocal Protestant supporter of the hard-line Orange Order.</p>
        <p>But when the bomb went off, on the afternoon of Aug. 15, 1998, it made no religious or political distinctions.</p>
        <p>''Our experience was different because this bomb was so indiscriminate,'' said Stanley McCombe, 52, whose wife, Ann, was killed that day. ''In the past, it was Protestants or Catholics. But this bomb killed Catholics and Protestants, Mormons, visitors from Spain. All these people were murdered together.''</p>
        <p>At a service in Omagh, 40,000 people came to express their outrage and their condolences. The subsequent police investigation involved hundreds of officers from both Northern Ireland and the Irish Republic. But even with dozens of arrests, and after the Real I.R.A., a splinter group, claimed responsibility for the bomb, the police have released the suspects for lack of evidence.</p>
        <p>''We know the team that carried this out,'' said Deputy Chief Superintendent Eric Anderson of the Royal Ulster Constabulary, who is running the investigation. Interviewed in the cafeteria at the Omagh Leisure Center, where the inquest is taking place, Superintendent Anderson nervously snapped a plastic coffee spoon in half as he told of his frustration with the case. ''We know who they are, and where they are, and how they did it.''</p>
        <p>The problem, the police say, is that their most solid evidence -- phone records that link a network of conspirators -- is not admissible in court.</p>
        <p>Like everyone else, the police have been slow to get over what happened. Some officers have broken down at the inquest as they have described how conflicting telephone warnings caused them to herd hundreds of people toward the bomb; how the survivors had so much blood coating their faces that it was impossible to tell if they were men or women.</p>
        <p>''It's had a devastating impact on those who were there,'' Superintendent Anderson said. ''Many of the force are coping with great difficulty. A lot of people are receiving medication and counseling.''</p>
        <p>It is an elusive goal, getting past a trauma that churns around and around in your head. It is hard to find anyone in Omagh, a town made up of small businesses and local government offices, who didn't lose a friend, relative, colleague, neighbor or customer in the bomb.</p>
        <p>Walking down Market Street, where the ruined buildings have been torn down but not completely rebuilt, it is impossible to ignore the bouquets of flowers pinned to the plywood walls, or the burn scars on the faces of some of the people in the shops, or the fact that the number of passers-by in the center of town seems sparse.</p>
        <p>Stanley McCombe counts himself among those who haven't really moved on. He and his elder son were in Scotland competing in a bagpipe competition when the bomb went off. Late Saturday afternoon, he heard a rumor that something had happened at the Omagh courthouse. Later still, he heard that his sister, a traffic police officer, had been killed.</p>
        <p>When he got home, Mr. McCombe had two shocks. His sister had survived, he learned; his wife, who worked in a clothing store, was dead.</p>
        <p>His life since has been a struggle. He left his job as an accounts officer with the electric company and now works part-time running errands at a friend's pizza place. He is smoking 60 cigarettes a day, up from 20. After 25 years of marriage, he is finding it hard to live by himself.</p>
        <p>''Our house was always kept -- well, we had a standard when Ann was there,'' he said. ''I don't mean to say that she was just cleaning the house. But it's not the same. My house is not a home. It's just a place where I live and sleep and have a bit of food.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCombe said he would not rest until those responsible for the bomb were convicted. ''But at least maybe our dead will be laid to rest,'' he said of the inquest. ''It's another hurdle we've come through.''</p>
        <p>Sylvia Crawford, 37, whose bridal shop was blown up, has come through a hurdle by managing to open a new store. It is called Sylvia's Bridal Shop now, not Joyful Occasions. But she can't clear her mind of the past.</p>
        <p>It is the what-ifs that consume her, she says. What if her assistant hadn't heard about the bomb warning and urged her -- with five minutes to spare -- to leave the store? What if she had walked in the other direction? What if Veda Short, a friend she met on the way, had stayed to chat instead of making her way down the street and into the explosion?</p>
        <p>But she is trying to move on, for her children's sake. When she worries too much, they tease her sometimes. ''Don't take a big psycho on me,'' her daughter, Kylie, will say. And a memento of her old shop has pride of place in her new one: a battered blue telephone, the one that rang with the warning from her assistant to get out. ''It saved my life,'' Mrs. Crawford said.</p>
        <p>In a particularly hurtful coda to the explosion, there have been at least 50 bomb scares in the town since the real one went off. Each time, the police have evacuated the area, and each time business has suffered a little more. During the last scare, a bride-to-be was trying on a dress in Mrs. Crawford's shop; she did not come back when the shop reopened.</p>
        <p>Even as Omagh is kept constantly off balance by what could be simply malicious hoaxes, the Real I.R.A., a  group born from the predominantly Roman Catholic Irish Republican Army, has embarked on a strategic campaign of terrorism around Northern Ireland -- and, increasingly, in London -- to destabilize the peace process.</p>
        <p>Has the inquest been a good thing?</p>
        <p>Although some people wish it had not been quite so vivid, most seem to agree that it has been a crucial step forward.</p>
        <p>''Here we are, two years after he died, and this is when the state officially recognizes his death,'' said Mr. Gallagher of Aidan. ''This is a very important process.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallagher will not be able to forget any of it, of course. He will never forget the chaos at the local hospital as he searched for Aidan. He will never forget driving home the next morning from the morgue where the body lay to break the news to his wife and two daughters.</p>
        <p>''Aidan will not be coming home,'' is what he said.</p>
        <p>But he is thankful that there was an inquest to go to, and especially thankful that Mr. Leckey, the coroner, emphasized -- as he has in as many cases as possible -- that Aidan died instantly, without consciousness. ''It's important to satisfy your own mind,'' Mr. Gallagher said.</p>
        <p>In the family and counseling rooms set up at the inquest, the sadness has been all-consuming. But that is where the hope lies.</p>
        <p>''The victims have been supporting each other, regardless of religion,'' said Mr. Duffy, the therapist. ''In the family room, where sometimes 50 people are sitting, some would have had extreme Republican views and some would have been Unionist. But people have moved from a primal response to a deeper human response. It's a microcosm of what could be here in Northern Ireland if people recognized each other as human beings.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
