<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surging A's Prepare for Sinking Yanks</title>
    <meta content="03OAKK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Athletics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spousta, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4D7133DF930A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surging A's Prepare for Sinking Yanks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM SPOUSTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spousta, Tom</byline>
      <dateline>OAKLAND, Calif., Oct. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Oakland Athletics preparing for American League division playoff series against New York Yankees; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Oakland Athletics are baseball's youngest team, certainly old enough to sip Champagne, yet by major league standards too inexperienced to celebrate. Yet here they are, American League West champions, and on a tear that should worry the struggling Yankees.</p>
        <p>The Athletics, who found themselves floundering seven games from first place on Aug. 13, were the best team in the majors in September. They were 21-7 in those 30 days and closed the season Sunday with a 3-0 victory over the Texas Rangers to win the division.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Oakland Athletics are baseball's youngest team, certainly old enough to sip Champagne, yet by major league standards too inexperienced to celebrate. Yet here they are, American League West champions, and on a tear that should worry the struggling Yankees.</p>
        <p>The Athletics, who found themselves floundering seven games from first place on Aug. 13, were the best team in the majors in September. They were 21-7 in those 30 days and closed the season Sunday with a 3-0 victory over the Texas Rangers to win the division.</p>
        <p>For the month, Athletics pitchers posted a staff earned run average of 2.88. They prevailed in one-run games and a 23-2 rout, winning 10 of their last 12 while gaining the white-hot momentum reminiscent of the Yankees during their World Series runs of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Brash self-confidence was not flowing through the Athletics clubhouse today, though, as they offered proper humility for their streak and wary respect for the Yankees' skid of 15 losses in their last 18 games.</p>
        <p>''Who's fading right now?'' asked Jason Giambi, repeating a question asked several times today. ''I'm not going to say they are fading. They're still awesome over there. I don't know what happened to them in September, but they're still the world champs and the team to beat.''</p>
        <p>The Athletics stuck to a theme: they might have momentum, but the Yankees own the edge in playoff experience. ''The way we finished the season, it was like we've been playing playoff games all the way down the stretch,'' Manager Art Howe said. ''I hope that will carry into these games. But it's a new season, and the Yankees know that.''</p>
        <p>Giambi added: ''It's been a storybook year, so why not have the Yankees in here first? You've got to take it through New York if you're going to get to the World Series, so let's play the Yankees right now and see how we fare. I like our chances against anybody.''</p>
        <p>Still, the Athletics acknowledged today that their late-season fight to win the A.L. West has put their starting pitchers in mid-rotation for the three-of-five-game series, which opens Tuesday night in Oakland. Gil Heredia will start for the Athletics, followed by Kevin Appier in Game 2 on Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>That means Tim Hudson (20-6), the staff ace, who notched his 20th victory Sunday, will probably face the Yankees only once unless the series goes five games. Ditto for Barry Zito (7-4), a rookie called up at midseason and considered the Athletics' No. 2 starter. He or Hudson is scheduled against Orlando Hernandez on Friday for Game 3 in New York.</p>
        <p>''You can look at it like the glass is half full or half empty,'' Athletics General Manager Billy Beane said. ''Looking at it half full, we'll have our two best pitchers the last two months starting at New York, so maybe it was kind of meant to be this way. And Kevin had a heck of a game here against them in our last series.''</p>
        <p>Interestingly, the Yankees have either feasted or starved against Heredia and especially Appier, whose pitching styles are almost as similar as their 15-11 records.</p>
        <p>Heredia has pitched well against the Yankees in recent years, going 1-1 with a 3.24 E.R.A. in 1997-99. As they did against Appier, the Yankees found Heredia's control and ability to change speeds often puzzling yet hittable.</p>
        <p>They had some luck against Heredia this year, scoring nine earned runs in 12 innings.</p>
        <p>Appier's performance in his last two starts against the Yankees has been a tale of two outings. On Aug. 9, he was bombed in New York, lasting only three and two-thirds innings, allowing 10 runs on 7 hits -- two of them home runs -- with 6 walks in a 12-1 loss.</p>
        <p>Yet on Aug. 25, Appier simply baffled the Yankees here in an 8-1 victory. He pitched eight innings and gave up four hits and one unearned run while striking out eight batters and walking four.</p>
        <p>Appier explained the loss in New York as an aberration. ''I have to give them credit,'' he said. ''They did well against me. But that game, I had a little bit of a dead arm and didn't have command of any of my pitches.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't like I was 10 miles per hour off. I just didn't have action on the ball that game.''</p>
        <p>The Yankees went 6-3 against the Athletics this year, sweeping three games at Yankee Stadium on Aug. 8-10 and taking two of three in Oakland on Aug. 25-27.</p>
        <p>The series is also a contrast in financial terms. The Yankees have one of baseball's highest payrolls, while the Athletics rank among the lowest five payrolls.</p>
        <p>''It's been a great run this team has put together,'' said reliever Doug Jones, a 14-year veteran and at 42 the oldest player by far in the Athletics' clubhouse. ''It's unbelievable. These guys have been playing like they don't have anything to lose and they all have big futures ahead of them.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
