<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Progressive Rock Prevails In Bursts of Pure Metal</title>
    <meta content="04DREA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dream Theater (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powers, Ann</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E4D81130F937A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Progressive Rock Prevails In Bursts of Pure Metal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN POWERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powers, Ann</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann Powers reviews concert by progressive rock group Dream Theater at Roseland; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's not unusual in New York to see people lining up around the block for artists few outsiders know exist. But Dream Theater, which attracted a crowd that waited five hours or more to get the best view for the show on Wednesday night at Roseland, holds a strange position in the maze of music undergrounds.</p>
        <p>The band's music isn't ethnically based, like dancehall reggae; cutting-edge, like electronica; or conventionally preservationist, like roots rock. Dream Theater approaches music the way a crepe shop approaches food, mastering every nuance of a recent yet arcane trend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's not unusual in New York to see people lining up around the block for artists few outsiders know exist. But Dream Theater, which attracted a crowd that waited five hours or more to get the best view for the show on Wednesday night at Roseland, holds a strange position in the maze of music undergrounds.</p>
        <p>The band's music isn't ethnically based, like dancehall reggae; cutting-edge, like electronica; or conventionally preservationist, like roots rock. Dream Theater approaches music the way a crepe shop approaches food, mastering every nuance of a recent yet arcane trend.</p>
        <p>Dream Theater's specialty is progressive rock, the happily pretentious strain that peaked when 1970's stars like Rush and Genesis went for the baroque in symphonic suites about cabbages and kings. Prog received a beating when punk, its stripped-down opposite, became more influential. But die-hard guitar gods and vocal wailers kept at it, and a decade ago in that more isolated context Dream Theater emerged.</p>
        <p>The band's core is the guitarist John Petrucci, the drummer Mike Portnoy and the bassist John Myung, who met at the Berklee College of Music in Boston and still play like ambitious academics. That's not an insult, just an observation that they care about serious scholarship.</p>
        <p>At Roseland Mr. Petrucci performed the dazzling runs expected from a guitar wizard, but he also often took the band toward wrenching thrash metal. Amorphous songs gained solidity when he and Mr. Myung rapidly locked step, anchored by the Led Zeppelin-style wallop of Mr. Portnoy's drumming. (Yes, he did pull out a gong at one point.)</p>
        <p>Despite these refreshing noise attacks, the new listener could easily get lost without a map to Dream Theater's music. Prog songs are supposed to have range, which often means they lack a center. Dream Theater shifted unexpectedly from thrash to power balladry, arena-size pomp and precise, almost free-jazz experimentation. The inventive keyboardist, Jordan Rudess, added ragtime and even some techno beats.</p>
        <p>James Labrie stomped onstage, mane flying, to sing when his services were needed. His style was pure operatic metal, one growl away from Broadway. The vocals held together the first set of this nearly four-hour show, featuring songs from Dream Theater's most recent album, ''Scenes From a Memory'' (Elektra).</p>
        <p>That effort is the band's biggest homage to classic prog, the first of its 11 albums to be united by a concept. The concept album is of course the prog template, and Dream Theater came up with a good plot: a twisted murder mystery involving past life regression. The details didn't come across very clearly live, however, so the show's first set, which gave a reprise of the story, was strictly for experienced fans.</p>
        <p>The second set sampled from the band's catalog, showing its mainstream side in ballads that recalled 1980's hit makers like Journey. Brief appearances by a saxophonist, a female gospel singer and a 12-member choir offered other variations. But Dream Theater was best when it  focused on virtuosity, the real point of progressive rock.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
