<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Memo; A Battle About Finances And the Lack of Finances</title>
    <meta content="04JERS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Robert D (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E2DF1E30F937A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Memo; A Battle About Finances And the Lack of Finances</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, Sept. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Political Memo column discusses campaign strategy to be employed by Repr Robert D Franks and Jon S Corzine as their battle for US Senate seat from New Jersey enters final months (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the three months since the New Jersey primaries, Representative Robert D. Franks, the little-known Republican candidate for United States Senate, has managed to raise just over $1 million for his campaign.</p>
        <p>Jon S. Corzine will spend more than that on television commercials this week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the three months since the New Jersey primaries, Representative Robert D. Franks, the little-known Republican candidate for United States Senate, has managed to raise just over $1 million for his campaign.</p>
        <p>Jon S. Corzine will spend more than that on television commercials this week.</p>
        <p>That blunt contrast, more than anything else, is shaping the fall campaign for the Senate as it begins in earnest on Labor Day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's riches have given him an advantage most first-time candidates could only dream of. By spending $35 million in the Democratic primary, shattering national records, Mr. Corzine, who retired last year as co-chairman of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, turned himself from a political unknown into a household name. Emboldened, he has since adopted a kind of Rose Garden strategy, avoiding face-to-face encounters with his rival and keeping only a minimalist public schedule.</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks, overmatched financially, is trying to make Mr. Corzine's money a campaign issue, attacking him in press releases and news conferences for refusing to disclose his tax returns and for favoring costly social programs that Mr. Franks says would bankrupt the government. By daring Mr. Corzine to debate him and criticizing him for refusing, Mr. Franks is hoping to make voters question Mr. Corzine's credibility and fortitude, even his intelligence.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Corzine's name-recognition advantage over Mr. Franks, who was little known outside his Union County district until this year, a series of recent independent polls has suggested that the Senate race in New Jersey is tightening.</p>
        <p>One survey in June put Mr. Corzine ahead by 20 points, but since then polls have put the margin in the single digits. The Gannett New Jersey Newspaper Group published a survey today that gave Mr. Franks a five-point lead, but since the gap was equal to the margin of error, the result was a statistical tie.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Mr. Corzine's campaign, aware that the Gannett survey would be published today, released its own internal poll showing Mr. Corzine with a 10-point lead among likely voters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Corzine's advisers have expressed befuddlement at surveys showing a closer race, wondering aloud what could be driving the independent polls, since little of public interest has taken place in the Senate campaign since the primaries.</p>
        <p>But Cliff Zukin, director of the Star-Ledger/Eagleton-Rutgers poll, said the Republican National Convention might have helped Mr. Franks by getting voters' attention. ''Even though it's focused on the presidential level, it brings Republicans home,'' Mr. Zukin said. ''They see the flag, they hear the speeches, and they remember why they were Republicans to begin with. So it brings Republicans back not just to the party's presidential nominee but to the Senate candidates as well.''</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, Mr. Corzine's campaign is not waiting to see whether the race tightens any further. On Monday night, several of his advisers said, Mr. Corzine will begin running the first two commercials in his general-election television campaign. The advertisements -- one 30 seconds long, the other a minute -- will be broadcast in the New York City and Philadelphia media markets at a cost of more than $1.1 million in the first week.</p>
        <p>The advisers said the shorter commercial touched on education, gun control and a prescription drug benefit for Medicare recipients, and would argue that Mr. Corzine's stands on those issues were aligned with New Jerseyans' values. The longer advertisement, they said, reintroduces Mr. Corzine to voters with a slightly altered message, saying, for example, that he has ''the fiscal discipline of a successful businessman.''</p>
        <p>One Corzine adviser said such language was intended to nullify Mr. Franks's effort to depict Mr. Corzine as an extremist, spendthrift liberal. ''And it will work, because Jon will be on the air for at least five weeks, unanswered,'' the adviser said.</p>
        <p>In addition, by beginning his air attack now, Mr. Corzine will be able to communicate with New Jersey voters long before television stations in New York and Philadelphia become saturated with advertisements for the Senate candidates in New York and Pennsylvania as well as the presidential candidates.</p>
        <p>''The bet is now, even if Franks has two or three weeks of effective commercials, they'll be less effective,'' the adviser said, ''because Franks is competing not just with Jon Corzine, but with Hillary and Lazio in New York, with Rick Santorum and Ron Klink in Pennsylvania, and with Al Gore and George Bush.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Franks's only defense, for now, is to warn of a voter backlash against Mr. Corzine's methods. ''After spending $35 million, Jon Corzine is not as popular as one would expect,'' said Mr. Franks's campaign manager, Charlie Smith. ''It demonstrates to me that this election is about more than just television advertising. It's about being able to represent the values and concerns of people. And voters are smart. They can't be bought.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Corzine appears undeterred by one recent poll showing that 31 percent of voters were greatly bothered by his campaign spending. Beginning his television campaign now, nine weeks before the Nov. 7 election, means that he could easily spend $15 million more on television alone. And his aides said Mr. Corzine had bought $2 million worth of commercials to be shown only during Olympics broadcasts in October.</p>
        <p>Money, meanwhile, is Mr. Franks's great weakness. His aides have said he needs to raise at least $8 million to stand a chance, but since the primary he has only raised about $1 million. He raised $500,000 at an event honoring Senator John McCain, and $140,000 at the Republican convention.</p>
        <p>But since then, he has shown little success. Two events in Texas with Senator Kay Bailey Hutchison produced only $50,000, as did an event with Representative Rick A. Lazio of New York, and several days of campaigning and fund-raising along the Jersey Shore produced $60,000.</p>
        <p>In his latest direct-mail appeal for money, Mr. Franks asked previous contributors to his Congressional races to donate $99, ''or, if you prefer, a monthly contribution of $33 in each of the three months remaining until Election Day.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''I don't have to match Jon Corzine's spending. I only need enough advertising to let voters compare my record of fiscal responsibility in Congress to Jon Corzine's agenda of irresponsible 'universal government.' ''</p>
        <p>Kept to a shoestring budget, Mr. Franks is also resorting to some pugnacious tactics. He sent two campaign workers to the Democratic National Convention in Los Angeles, where they wangled credentials to get inside the Staples Arena during Mr. Corzine's speech and handed out critiques of it afterward.</p>
        <p>Even more puckishly, the Franks campaign has set up a Web site, www.mruniversal.com, that depicts Mr. Corzine's face over a cartooned muscleman's body, and leavens Mr. Franks's more serious attacks with satirical barbs that range from witty to sophomoric.</p>
        <p>Mindful of such tactics, the Corzine campaign has become careful almost to a fault. At the first joint appearance of the two candidates, a forum set up by the Veterans of Foreign Wars at a high school in Toms River on Tuesday night, Mr. Corzine's aides refused to allow Mr. Franks even to sit in the auditorium while Mr. Corzine spoke. Mr. Franks was forced to wait his turn behind a closed door in an adjoining office.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Franks finally addressed the 200 or so veterans there, one reason why Mr. Corzine may not have wanted to share a stage with him quickly became clear: Mr. Corzine was politely received, but Mr. Franks is the more practiced public speaker and took only a few seconds to get the first of many rounds of applause.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Franks will need every edge he can muster. While Mr. Corzine is free to campaign as little or as much as he likes -- he had a full schedule of beach walks and street fairs this weekend -- Mr. Franks is caught in a difficult vise. He is forced to spend as much time as possible raising money, as he did all day Saturday. And on Tuesday, when Congress resumes its session, he will have to leave for Washington.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
