<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft's Game Plan; Xbox to Go Head to Head With Sony</title>
    <meta content="04SOFT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sony Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFD91130F937A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft's Game Plan; Xbox to Go Head to Head With Sony</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markoff, John</byline>
      <dateline>REDMOND, Wash.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Microsoft Corp hopes to begin selling powerful video-game computer called Xbox for around $300 in October 2001; plans to compete with Sony Corp's Playstation; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This summer, Microsoft executives have been coyly popping a videotape into a VCR here and showing visitors the computer-age equivalent of the blinding power of a race car dragster on nitro fuel.</p>
        <p>The tape reveals a photo-realistically rendered schoolroom where an invisible hand is poised to drop a table-tennis ball with an X on it. As it falls, the viewer sees that it is about to land in a sea of 1,024 similar balls, each perched on a hair-trigger mousetrap.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This summer, Microsoft executives have been coyly popping a videotape into a VCR here and showing visitors the computer-age equivalent of the blinding power of a race car dragster on nitro fuel.</p>
        <p>The tape reveals a photo-realistically rendered schoolroom where an invisible hand is poised to drop a table-tennis ball with an X on it. As it falls, the viewer sees that it is about to land in a sea of 1,024 similar balls, each perched on a hair-trigger mousetrap.</p>
        <p>When the ball hits, mayhem ensues; table-tennis balls -- each one accurately shaded and shadowed -- explode in all directions, bouncing and ricocheting in concert and then slowly coming to rest.</p>
        <p>Rendering such an image in what the digerati call ''real time,'' with all the computing done as the balls collide so that each collision can be altered on the fly, is today beyond the ability of all but the most powerful supercomputers.</p>
        <p>Yet if all goes according to plan, Microsoft hopes to begin selling a game computer with this kind of computing power for around $300 in October 2001.</p>
        <p>The machine, called Xbox, is both a technical tour de force by the world's largest software publisher and a shot fired across the bow of the giant Sony Corporation, which now dominates the $20 billion video-game industry.</p>
        <p>Microsoft is serving notice that it is intent upon extending its reach from the office into the living room.</p>
        <p>But it is also an immense gamble by a company that has vowed to commit $500 million to elbow its way into a consumer electronics market governed today by a business model that is anathema to most of the strategies Microsoft has, until now, pursued in the personal computer software business. Unlike the PC software business, which allows some independence, the game industry is based on a model that requires the payment of royalties by software developers to device makers, a model that would require Microsoft to depend on other companies to ensure the success of its product.</p>
        <p>Will Microsoft be able to move with impunity into one of the world's most lucrative consumer electronics markets or is this an act of hubris, evidence that the software titan, in its desperate push for growth, has finally over-reached?</p>
        <p>While the company's ''specmanship'' has been greeted enthusiastically by those involved with video games, some analysts are far from convinced that Microsoft will have an easy road in a marketplace that is unfamiliar and that is already dominated by Japanese consumer powerhouses like Sony, Nintendo and Sega Enterprises.</p>
        <p>''We're talking about Sony's crown jewels,'' said Peter Sealey, a professor of marketing at the Haas School of Business of the University of California at Berkeley, where he also serves as co-director of the Center for Marketing and Technology. ''Their installed base is enormous and the kids are with them, and Microsoft's greatest danger is in spreading itself too thin.''</p>
        <p>Brand and demographics may well conspire against Microsoft. Since July 1998, the penetration of video-game consoles in the nation's homes has begun to decline, to 35 percent from 37 percent. The reason, according to the San Francisco-based market research firm Odyssey is that the home PC is also increasingly a game machine.</p>
        <p>Until now, Microsoft has largely eschewed hardware manufacturing, preferring to let its hundreds of business partners take the risks in a market that is known for razor-thin margins and brutal competition.</p>
        <p>Also, Microsoft has long prided itself as being what it calls an ''open systems'' software developer. No licenses are required to write software that is compatible with Microsoft operating systems.</p>
        <p>In contrast, in the video-game industry, software developers pay fees to have their programs run on the manufacturer's game systems.</p>
        <p>Microsoft has little expertise in the world of the ''razors and razor blades'' business model, in which game machines are sold below cost and losses are made up from the profits on hit software programs.</p>
        <p>Ironically, in the video-game business Microsoft will be confronted by a hurdle its rivals know well, the same ''applications barrier to entry'' that the judge in the federal antitrust case against Microsoft cited as being at the core of the company's software monopoly.</p>
        <p>Now the tables are turned. When Xbox is shipped next fall, Microsoft is likely to have only a handful a programs to sell with its machine -- perhaps 12 to 20 -- while Sony will have hundreds of titles for its Playstation 2 machine, as well as the thousands of older Playstation games that will also run on its second-generation machine.</p>
        <p>All of those obstacles are things Microsoft says it has considered.</p>
        <p>''It's all about the games,'' said Robert Bach, the Microsoft executive who is leading the development program. ''If you have great games, you win.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bach, who was previously the head of the company's Microsoft Office business, now heads the company's game division. In a recent interview on Microsoft's campus here, he said that in practical terms his focus had increasingly been on making sure Xbox reached the market successfully.</p>
        <p>Microsoft is counting on the fact that there is nothing sacrosanct about Sony's lead in the video-game business.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Bach pointed out that the dominant video-game manufacturer has shifted with each new generation, going back as far as the Atari Corporation two decades ago. As the video game approaches the next generation this year and next, there is no reason the lead should not shift again.</p>
        <p>But there is one more obstacle just over the horizon: Microsoft is betting that unlike the personal computer, the video-game-player market will remain a stable one. While PC's have increased in power every year, the game platform market has generally remained unchanged for as long as five years, giving consumer electronics companies time to recoup their investments.</p>
        <p>Now Sony, which has sold more than 73 million Playstations worldwide and has more than 51 percent of the United States market, is preparing to change the rules of the video-game business, according to people familiar with the company's strategy.</p>
        <p>While Microsoft is making its flashy demonstrations and releasing specification sheets showing supercomputer performance next year, Sony has been preparing its own multimillion-dollar campaign, the October rollout of the Playstation 2, which will sell for about the same price as Microsoft's entry.</p>
        <p>It will be the most powerful video-game player ever introduced, yet it is also a harbinger that the pace of technological change in the video-game business is likely to accelerate quickly.</p>
        <p>While Microsoft will take the performance lead in 2001, it will be with a powerful machine and little software.</p>
        <p>Sony could then trump Microsoft with a faster machine in a year or two that could spell trouble for the software publisher: if the video-game business becomes more like the PC hardware industry, Microsoft may find itself locked in a bitter war over profit margins in which it lacks the comfortable software cushion it enjoys in the PC business. Sony has not publicly acknowledged that it plans to speed up the pace but it has quietly sent signals to its developers.</p>
        <p>Toward that end, Sony has been engaging in its own game of specmanship. This summer, what is almost certainly the world's fastest graphics supercomputer could be found in a faded one-story office building on a side street in Mountain View, Calif., birthplace of the semiconductor chip.</p>
        <p>The site's anonymity underscores the special significance of the GS-Cube, a prototype Sony video-game computer that is being used by a low-profile group of Silicon Valley programmers to aid a future generation of game designers in creating software that is far more lifelike than today's programs.</p>
        <p>Sony used the new machine to offer demonstrations on a par with Microsoft's this year at the annual Siggraph computer graphics exhibition in New Orleans. One had impact similar to the Xbox table-tennis ball demonstration: a real-time rendition taken from the Hollywood movie ''The Matrix.''</p>
        <p>The GS-Cube is composed of 16 enhanced  Sony Playstation 2 computers. When harnessed together, they are capable of drawing more than 200 million polygons a second. That speed is more than 16 times faster than today's Playstation and more than twice as fast as a Silicon Graphics Reality Engine, a supercomputer that is the most powerful commercial graphics machine.</p>
        <p>Publicly, Sony will only say that the system is intended to blur the line between the video-game world and digital entertainment in Hollywood. Some developers, however,  believe the machine could become a commercial product as early as 2003.</p>
        <p>''Sony is going for rapid change of the platform, while Microsoft is new to the old world of the stable platform,'' said Richard Doherty, president of Envisioneering, a computer industry consulting firm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bach acknowledges the difference in strategy. The PC business has historically been a marketplace of incremental change, he said, while the video game has followed a more stable ''stair step'' evolution.</p>
        <p>It may also signify that Microsoft, which until now has been one of the principal beneficiaries of Moore's Law -- the observation about the exponential pace of change in the chip industry -- could find that it has become the principal victim.</p>
        <p>Noting that Microsoft will have to lose money on each Xbox it makes, Michael Jones, the chief executive of Intrinsic Graphics, a maker of video-game-developer tools in Mountain View, asked: ''How many Xbox's can Microsoft afford to sell?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
