<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patents; Devices to make life around the house easier for handymen, cooks and computer users.</title>
    <meta content="04PATE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227952"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roofing and Siding</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vacuum Cleaners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ovens and Stoves</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eggs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cookies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bakeries and Baked Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dishwashers and Dishwashing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mills, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vandenberg, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">May, Leonhard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbruck, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Katta, Sarath</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chigurupati, Sambasiva</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moore, Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Singh, Baljit</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cassalia, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krueger, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fein, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Troyer, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bakeries and Baked Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7D81130F937A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patents; Devices to make life around the house easier for handymen, cooks and computer users.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Mills receives patent for adjustable shoe for roofers; Anthony Vandenberg receives patent for vacuum cleaner attachment that can be used to pick up toy blocks; Leonhard May receives patent for remotely programmable oven that can be controlled via computer modem; Stephen Herbruck receives patent for egg carton that has compartments for other ingredients that can be used when making egg dish or omelet; Sarath Katta, Sambasiva Chigurupati and Wayne Moore receive patent for toaster cookies; Baljit Singh and Alan Cassalia receive patents for gadgets that can be used in dishwashers; Anthony Krueger and Ronald Fein receive patent for 'grammar check' program that will be sold by Microsoft Corp; John Troyer receives patent for portable stand for laptop computer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LABOR DAY celebrates industry and work with the ultimate salute: a day off. The rest of the year, inventors strive to find ways to make work and everyday tasks easier.</p>
        <p>Roofers who install tiles on houses may appreciate a pair of work shoes patented by James Mills. He has invented footwear with adjustable pitch, so that a roofer, or a firefighter or chimney sweep, standing on a steep roof can remain upright. His shoes are actually shoe boards that fit over the foot, with or without conventional shoes. The boards attach to a base that holds a contact pad made of foam rubber. Brackets extending from the underside of the shoe board to the top of the base are connected with a rod. A series of holes in the brackets allow the pitch of the footwear to be adjusted with a pin to match the slant of a roof. A wearer would use the shoes standing with one leg down roof from the other. Mr. Mills, who lives in Valparaiso, Ind., received patent 6,035,557.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LABOR DAY celebrates industry and work with the ultimate salute: a day off. The rest of the year, inventors strive to find ways to make work and everyday tasks easier.</p>
        <p>Roofers who install tiles on houses may appreciate a pair of work shoes patented by James Mills. He has invented footwear with adjustable pitch, so that a roofer, or a firefighter or chimney sweep, standing on a steep roof can remain upright. His shoes are actually shoe boards that fit over the foot, with or without conventional shoes. The boards attach to a base that holds a contact pad made of foam rubber. Brackets extending from the underside of the shoe board to the top of the base are connected with a rod. A series of holes in the brackets allow the pitch of the footwear to be adjusted with a pin to match the slant of a roof. A wearer would use the shoes standing with one leg down roof from the other. Mr. Mills, who lives in Valparaiso, Ind., received patent 6,035,557.</p>
        <p>Vacuuming Up In the Playroom</p>
        <p>Any parent whose daily tasks include picking up plastic building block toys may like the vacuum cleaner attachment patented by Anthony Vandenberg. Mr. Vandenberg's curved pipe can be attached to a standard vacuum cleaner hose so blocks can be pulled off the floor. A plate inside the pipe directs the blocks into a channel connected to a transparent container. Mr. Vandenberg says in his patent that dirt and dust could still flow into the vacuum cleaner bag, and that a spring-loaded probe would clear out any blocks stuck in the pipe. The container comes with a hinged bottom so the blocks can be dumped into a toy box. Mr. Vandenberg received patent 6,048,249.</p>
        <p>Help With Cooking In the Kitchen or Out</p>
        <p>Cooks will be interested in Leonhard May's remotely programmable oven. Mr. May, who lives in North Royalton, Ohio, has patented an oven that cooks can control via computer modem. A cook can dial into a microprocessor on his oven and program cooking mode, temperature and duration. A cook can modify those directions later, and bring up the oven's progress on his computer screen. Mr. May received patent 6,080,972.</p>
        <p>Any chef compiling an omelet might welcome Stephen Herbruck's patented egg carton. The box has compartments shaped to hold eggs, like a traditional egg carton, but adds compartments intended to hold other ingredients. Mr. Herbruck, from Saranac, Mich., designed his carton so that the number of ''other'' compartments match the number of egg holders, so the carton can carry the correct amount of ingredients for an omelet or any egg dish, or even Easter egg painting supplies. He received patent 5,927,501.</p>
        <p>For those who like the convenience of store-bought cookies but the luxury of fresh-baked ones, there is the toaster cookie invented by Sarath Katta, Sambasiva Chigurupati and Wayne Moore, all from Omaha. The cookies are prebaked so that after they are bought, the baking can be finished in a home toaster oven. Each one is coated with flavors so that when the cookies are heated, the flavors release a scent. After a few minutes in a toaster oven, the cookies are soft, chewy and smell fresh-baked, the inventors said in their application. Their patent, which belongs to ConAgra, is 6,093,437.</p>
        <p>Kitchen clean-up could be improved with a couple of patents for dishwashers. In Baljit Singh's design for a combination sink and dishwasher, a dishwasher is installed adjacent to a sink. A common wall divides the two. A basket slides from within the dishwasher, through an opening in the common wall, until it rests in the sink. Dirty dishes can be rinsed and loaded into the basket, which is then returned to the dishwasher. Mr. Singh, who lives in Norwalk, Calif., won patent 5,934,298.</p>
        <p>In Alan Cassalia's patented dishwasher, the bottom rack extends and retracts like the conventional lower racks that holds pots, dishes and a flatware basket. But Mr. Cassalia, who lives in Richboro, Pa., added scissor-arm support brackets that allow the lower rack to be pulled out and then raised to the same height as the upper rack. He received patent 5,971,513.</p>
        <p>Software That Bolsters Weak Grammar</p>
        <p>Anyone whose job involves writing could probably use the ''grammar-check'' invented by Anthony Krueger and Ronald Fein for Microsoft. Their invention works as does the spelling-check function included in word-processing software. When someone working on a document stops typing, the patented software takes advantage of the idle time to extract sentences from the text and analyze them for ''proper grammatical composition,'' the patent says. If the sentence includes substandard English, an error icon will appear on the computer screen. The writer can click on the icon to bring up a menu with suggested corrections that the inventors say will ''most likely correct each error.'' They received patent 6,012,075.</p>
        <p>Any worker who relies on a laptop might appreciate the portable stand patented by John Troyer. The stand has a pair of feet, a pair of support posts and a horizontal platform with wings to hold a laptop. The stand parts are collapsible so that it will fit in a suitcase, but when it is fully extended it ''is capable of holding a laptop computer at the proper height and angle for use,'' Mr. Troyer, who is from Cincinnati, wrote in his patent. He received patent 6,076,787.</p>
        <p>Patents may be viewed on the Web at www.uspto.gov or may be ordered through the mail, by patent number, for $3 from the Patent and Trademark Office, Washington, D.C. 20231.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Patents may be viewed on the Web at www.uspto.gov or may be ordered through the mail, by patent number, for $3 from the Patent and Trademark Office, Washington, D.C. 20231.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
