<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Media Talk; Co-Anchor of 'Moneyline' Moves West</title>
    <meta content="04CNN.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bay, Willow</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Varney, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Moneyline (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E2D91130F937A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Media Talk; Co-Anchor of 'Moneyline' Moves West</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Willow Bay, anchor on CNN's Moneyline News Hour program, will begin doing her job from Los Angeles on Sept 5; her co-anchor, Stuart Varney, will remain in New York; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With CNN in flux after a corporate restructuring that was announced last week, Willow Bay, an anchor on its ''Moneyline News Hour'' program, will begin doing her job from Los Angeles tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Her co-anchor, Stuart Varney, will remain in New York, making the 6:30 p.m. financial news program bicoastal. The program will also include a ticker and new graphics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With CNN in flux after a corporate restructuring that was announced last week, Willow Bay, an anchor on its ''Moneyline News Hour'' program, will begin doing her job from Los Angeles tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Her co-anchor, Stuart Varney, will remain in New York, making the 6:30 p.m. financial news program bicoastal. The program will also include a ticker and new graphics.</p>
        <p>When CNN executives announced last winter that Ms. Bay would move to Los Angeles, they said it would serve two purposes: It would give ''Moneyline'' a presence on the West Coast while also allowing Ms. Bay to live some semblance of a normal life with her husband, Robert A. Iger, the president of Walt Disney, who had been asked to move from New York to Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bay, who did not want a bicoastal marriage, told CNN that she would likely have to leave ''Moneyline'' for some other duty. They said they would rather make the show bicoastal.</p>
        <p>''Moneyline'' had been steadily losing ratings to its CNBC competitor, ''Business Center,'' in the months after its longtime anchor, Lou Dobbs, left the network. It has never recovered and has become somewhat of a symbol of the ratings failures at CNN, which is owned by Time Warner.</p>
        <p>The executives believed that by creating a Los Angeles anchor, they could rejuvenate the program. C. Shelby Coffey III, the president of CNN's financial network, CNNfn, who is in charge of ''Moneyline,'' had wanted to bolster coverage of the West Coast economy.</p>
        <p>Last week, executives were planning to build up attention for the program's new format. But then the president of CNN's operations in the United States, Richard N. Kaplan, resigned, sending those plans into disarray.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan, like Ms. Bay, was formerly of ABC News. Ms. Bay, like others who were close to Mr. Kaplan, acknowledged some uneasiness now that he was gone. ''With Rick's departure, we lose a 'Moneyline' supporter, and I'm obviously personally very distressed that he's leaving.''</p>
        <p>''I have been specifically assured that the current CNN management fully supports and embraces a bicoastal 'Moneyline,' '' she said.</p>
        <p>Likewise, she added, ''CNN management has been very generous with me.''</p>
        <p>Actually, while CNN executives have said they could make a lot of changes to the programming schedule, ''Moneyline'' is still a major moneymaker and has lost fewer viewers than other programs.</p>
        <p>But there will certainly be pressure for it to do better in the ratings. Ms. Bay and Mr. Varney said they believed the changes should help.</p>
        <p>''Being out there on the West Coast, in the middle of the new economy, I think that's a plus,'' Mr. Varney said.</p>
        <p>JIM RUTENBERG</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
