<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Compressed Data; Personal Online Advice on Selecting a College</title>
    <meta content="04ADVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1227941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PureAdvice.com</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levere, Jane L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D91130F937A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="425" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Compressed Data; Personal Online Advice on Selecting a College</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE L. LEVERE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Levere, Jane L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Live, one-on-one college advisory services, which has been offered primarily offline, is now available at PureAdvice.com (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Live, one-on-one college advisory services, offered until now primarily offline, became available on the Internet last Friday through a new Web site, PureAdvice.com. It is offering tools and services to help high school students identify and apply to colleges appropriate for them and apply for and obtain financial aid.</p>
        <p>Some information, like extensive data on all the colleges in the United States, and a calculator that estimates the total expense of going to college, is free.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Live, one-on-one college advisory services, offered until now primarily offline, became available on the Internet last Friday through a new Web site, PureAdvice.com. It is offering tools and services to help high school students identify and apply to colleges appropriate for them and apply for and obtain financial aid.</p>
        <p>Some information, like extensive data on all the colleges in the United States, and a calculator that estimates the total expense of going to college, is free.</p>
        <p>But live, one-on-one counseling sessions with experienced guidance counselors, financial aid experts and former college admissions officials involve fees that start at $75 for a 45-minute session. Included in this fee is a written report summarizing the session, which is sent to the student and to the student's guidance counselor, if desired.</p>
        <p>PureAdvice.com's president, Steven Ehrlich, said 140 advisers from across the country, each with a minimum of five years' experience, conduct the online sessions.</p>
        <p>''In-school guidance counselors are often overburdened. PureAdvice will help change that, giving students, their parents and guidance counselors the tools and personalized attention they deserve,'' Mr. Ehrlich said.</p>
        <p>PureAdvice also receives fees for referring visitors to vendors -- like student loan providers -- that are listed on its site.</p>
        <p>In addition, the company has formed a partnership with U.S. News &amp; World Report to provide its counseling services on the portion of the magazine's Web site that carries its annual college survey. Mr. Ehrlich said  U.S. News &amp; World Report would receive a fee for each referral to PureAdvice.com.</p>
        <p>Officials of Achieva.com, a three-year-old, San Mateo, Calif., company that also helps high school students with the college admissions process, appeared undaunted by the East Coast start-up.</p>
        <p>Steven Feuling, Achieva.com's vice president for marketing, said his company's $295 online college program ''takes you through everything, not just college selection and the financial aid piece.''</p>
        <p>''We help you with test preparation, developing an extra-curricular resume, with an application strategy.'' The company also offers live counseling, but not online. He said more than half Achieva's income was derived from sales directly to school systems.</p>
        <p>JANE L. LEVERE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
