<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bills End This Game With Different Tune</title>
    <meta content="04BILL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Buffalo Bills</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tennessee Titans</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Buffalo Bills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Tennessee Titans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDF1E30F937A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="919" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bills End This Game With Different Tune</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>ORCHARD PARK, N.Y., Sept. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Buffalo Bills defeat Tennessee Titans, 16-13 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the end of the night, Tennessee defensive end Jevon Kearse and Buffalo quarterback Rob Johnson had become good pals of sorts, mainly because Kearse was practically unblockable and was throwing Johnson around like a pile of dirty laundry.</p>
        <p>Johnson had to leave the game in the fourth quarter after injuring his ankle while trying to avoid Kearse, the Titans' star defensive player.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the end of the night, Tennessee defensive end Jevon Kearse and Buffalo quarterback Rob Johnson had become good pals of sorts, mainly because Kearse was practically unblockable and was throwing Johnson around like a pile of dirty laundry.</p>
        <p>Johnson had to leave the game in the fourth quarter after injuring his ankle while trying to avoid Kearse, the Titans' star defensive player.</p>
        <p>Forget the Music City Miracle, the controversial lateral play in last year's playoffs that eliminated the Bills and helped Tennessee advance in the playoffs. This was the Jevon Kearse crush.</p>
        <p>Johnson was replaced by Alex Van Pelt, who was treated just as rudely by Kearse. But Kearse's dominance was one of the few things the Titans could be happy about as they began to defend their American Football Conference title.</p>
        <p>Tennessee opened the season with a loss to Buffalo after Steve Christie connected on a field goal from 33 yards in the final seconds to upset the Titans, 16-13, before 72,492 fans at Ralph Wilson Stadium.</p>
        <p>The key play was Van Pelt's 36-yard pass to wide receiver Eric Moulds, one of the premier pass catchers in the game. That put Buffalo on the Tennessee 20-yard line and set up Christie's kick.</p>
        <p>This time, there was no miracle kickoff return by the Titans, but it was a pretty good one nonetheless -- a 52-yard return by Derrick Mason to the Buffalo 49-yard line. After a 9-yard pass play, the Titans decided to try a 60-yard field goal. But the kick by Craig Hentrich was wide left.</p>
        <p>''What happened to us in the playoffs last year was definitely in the back of my mind after we got that last field goal,'' Van Pelt said. ''I was thinking, 'Don't celebrate yet.' ''</p>
        <p>The Titans discovered on Sunday, just as Washington and Tampa Bay did in their tight opening games, that talking about being a Super Bowl favorite is much easier than actually making the trek. Tennessee was a surprise last year, but now has a target on its back.</p>
        <p>The Titans were aggressive defensively, as evidenced by the play of Kearse and his pals, but the offense was at times sloppy. Tight end Frank Wycheck dropped a potential touchdown pass in the second quarter, the ball careening off his hands. Eddie George dropped a pass that hit him in the chest and could have led to a touchdown.</p>
        <p>Buffalo took advantage of the Tennessee miscues by adding Christie field goals of 42 and 41 yards in the second half.</p>
        <p>Late in the game, Tennessee's stars began to wake up. Quarterback Steve McNair, who had only 113 yards passing early in the fourth quarter, threw a perfect ball to wide receiver Carl Pickens that forced cornerback Ken Irvin to grab Pickens early. It resulted in a 41-yard penalty that put Tennessee at the 2-yard line. On second down, George scored from 2 yards out to tie the score, 13-13, with 9 minutes 44 seconds left.</p>
        <p>This might have been the most anticipated game of Week 1 because it was a rematch of last year's playoff matchup that produced the Music City Miracle, the spectacular 75-yard kickoff return for a touchdown in the final seconds that helped to propel the Titans into the Super Bowl. On that play, Lorenzo Neal took the short kickoff and handed the football to tight end Wycheck, who threw a lateral to wide receiver Kevin Dyson. Dyson ran for the score that gave Tennessee a 22-16 victory in their A.F.C. wild-card playoff game.</p>
        <p>What made this game even more fascinating was that even now the Bills refuse to believe Wycheck's toss was legal, despite replays that prove it was.</p>
        <p>This week Buffalo Coach Wade Phillips re-enacted the play for reporters in an effort to demonstrate how it could not have been legal, maintaining that Wycheck had thrown a forward pass to Dyson.</p>
        <p>It probably didn't help Buffalo cope when Titans Coach Jeff Fisher introduced his special teams at the beginning of the game.</p>
        <p>''We knew this was going to be a tight game because it was in the playoffs last year,'' said Johnson, who has an unspecified nerve injury in his left ankle. ''We played hard and I hope this Music City Miracle talk is now dead.''</p>
        <p>The teams had similar game plans, which included ball control and aggressive defense. Buffalo and Tennessee blitzed relentlessly, with Johnson taking the worst of the hits.</p>
        <p>He was sacked on the first play of the game, and later, linebacker Greg Favors blitzed from Johnson's blind side, hitting him hard. Johnson looked woozy while getting up.</p>
        <p>The hitting was brutal, exemplified by Buffalo cornerback Antoine Winfield; he first tackled tight end Michael Roan low, then flipped him like a pancake, with Roan's head hitting the rock-hard artificial turf.</p>
        <p>Johnson's poise under the tremendous pressure was impressive. It also helped that Buffalo made some adjustments on offense -- altering the snap count, which drew Titans players offside three times in one drive, and rolling Johnson out, away from pressure.</p>
        <p>Johnson responded by leading Buffalo on a 10-play, 71-yard drive that ended with a 16-yard touchdown pass to Peerless Price and a 7-0 lead.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
