<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Other Systems Might Provide a U.S. Missile Shield</title>
    <meta content="04MISS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/04/world/04MISS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glanz, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDE1E30F937A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="2473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Other Systems Might Provide a U.S. Missile Shield</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLANZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glanz, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Theater missile defenses, which are intended to protect American troops and bases in relatively small regions of conflict, are getting increased scrutiny as possible fill-ins for national missile defense system, which Pres Clinton says cannot be put in place until 2006 or 2007 at the earliest; some already under development could be expanded, potentially, to protect larger areas and perhaps even the entire US; Russia has not objected to theater systems that work in the boost phase because interceptors cannot be positioned close enough to attack Russian rockets while they are being launched, but China does see theater defenses as a threat because they could theoretically be used to protect Taiwan and Japan, its potential adversaries; $5.1 billion that US will spend on missile defense in fiscal year 2001 will be equally divided between theater defenses and national missile defense; diagrams and graphs (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In putting off a decision on a national missile defense on Friday, President Clinton said the earliest such a shield could be put in place was 2006 or 2007. But the president made a decision on just one system. What he did not say, and what the debate over that system has obscured, is that a number of lesser-known antimissile weapons might be candidates for the same job.</p>
        <p>They are known as theater missile defense systems, and they are intended to protect American troops and bases in relatively small regions of conflict, much as was attempted during the Persian Gulf war in 1991. But some already under development could be expanded, potentially, to protect larger areas and perhaps even the entire United States, according to experts inside and outside the military.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In putting off a decision on a national missile defense on Friday, President Clinton said the earliest such a shield could be put in place was 2006 or 2007. But the president made a decision on just one system. What he did not say, and what the debate over that system has obscured, is that a number of lesser-known antimissile weapons might be candidates for the same job.</p>
        <p>They are known as theater missile defense systems, and they are intended to protect American troops and bases in relatively small regions of conflict, much as was attempted during the Persian Gulf war in 1991. But some already under development could be expanded, potentially, to protect larger areas and perhaps even the entire United States, according to experts inside and outside the military.</p>
        <p>Many of these systems have yet to be tested for the purpose for which they were originally intended, let alone a new, more ambitious one, and the difficulty of adapting them would range from making simple changes in their computer software to perhaps adding sophisticated new sensors or other hardware.</p>
        <p>Still, with several of these weapons  scheduled to be available as theater defenses by 2007, the delay announced by Mr. Clinton is bringing them much closer scrutiny as to whether they might eventually be adapted to provide some form of national defense.</p>
        <p>''It does debunk the argument of the Pentagon that if you want missile defense soon, your only choice is the missile defense system they've been pushing,'' said Dr. Michael O'Hanlon, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution who specializes in military policy.</p>
        <p>The plan Mr. Clinton has delayed would track missiles through space and shoot down descending warheads from a land-based site in the United States. Many of the theater defenses use interceptors, lasers or fragmentation explosives fired from ships or airplanes that could maneuver relatively close to small countries like North Korea, whose missile program has been cited as one reason a national missile defense is needed.</p>
        <p>Some of these theater systems are now intended to shoot down short- and medium-range missiles in midflight or on their way down to a target, but proponents say they might be adapted to destroy the kinds of faster long-range missiles that would be the object of a national missile defense.</p>
        <p>That could be done by adding long-range sensors that would potentially give theater systems enough time to destroy missiles in midflight, or by targeting missiles soon after they were launched, in the so-called boost phase. Other theater defenses have been specifically intended to work in the boost phase.</p>
        <p>The idea of boost-phase interception was even endorsed this summer by President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia, who suggested that his nation might cooperate with the United States in developing it. Russia has opposed a national missile shield, arguing that it threatens to undermine its arsenal and violates the Antiballistic Missile Treaty the United States signed with the Soviet Union in 1972.</p>
        <p>But Russia has not objected to theater systems that work in the boost phase. One reason is that they do not violate the ABM treaty. Another is that because of Russia's large size, interceptors cannot be positioned close enough to attack Russian rockets while they are being launched.</p>
        <p>China, however, in addition to its objections to a national defense system, does see theater defenses as a threat because they could theoretically be used to protect Taiwan and Japan, its potential adversaries.</p>
        <p>But for the most part, theater defenses have not generated the same kind of resistance at home or abroad as the Pentagon's idea for a national missile defense, because the theater defenses have not been intended to offer the kind of blanket protection from missile attack that would challenge existing theories of arms control, which are based on mutual vulnerability.</p>
        <p>This would undoubtedly change if they were expanded to protect the whole of the United States, and any defense system that did so would probably violate the ABM treaty, according to arms control experts. Some critics have seen these theater systems as an attempt to bring in a national missile defense through the back door.</p>
        <p>In his speech on Friday, Mr. Clinton said Russia had agreed to cooperate with the United States ''in areas such as theater missile defense,'' but he did not mention the systems' wider potential.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Russia might agree to changing the ABM treaty to allow for adapting to broader use a theater missile defense system that it does not view as a direct threat, said Dr. Harold Brown, secretary of defense in the Carter administration. ''This is a way of possibly preserving the ABM treaty,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dean Wilkening, director of the science program at Stanford University's Center for International Security and Cooperation, said, ''There's no clear, technical distinction between the theater and national missile defense systems.''</p>
        <p>Referring to a Navy system that would shoot down missiles with shipboard interceptors, Dr. Wilkening said, ''They are well down the road to being fully capable national missile defense systems.''</p>
        <p>Until recently, with the emerging missile programs of nations like Iraq and North Korea, the idea of creating a national missile defense lost favor after the end of the cold war. But spending for theater defenses has more or less grown through the 1990's.</p>
        <p>The $5.1 billion that the United States will spend on missile defense in fiscal year 2001 will be equally divided between theater defenses and national missile defense, according to the nonpartisan Center for Strategic and Budgetary Assessments in Washington.</p>
        <p>That contrasts starkly with the situation in the 1980's, when expenditures on national defenses dominated spending.</p>
        <p>Most of the theater programs -- which have names like the Theater High-Altitude Area Defense (Thaad), the Patriot Advanced Capability - 3 and the Navy Theaterwide and Navy Area Defense -- use interceptors fired from ships or trailers that attempt to ram an enemy missile or explode near it.</p>
        <p>Of those systems, extensive testing has already been done for the new Patriot, scheduled to be put in the field starting next year. Unlike the version used in the gulf war, which exploded near descending missiles, this one aims to ram them.</p>
        <p>Thaad has also been extensively tested and is expected to be deployed by 2007. Current plans have the Navy Theaterwide Defense available for emergency use in 2007 and fully deployed three years later, while the shorter-range Navy Area Defense should be ready sooner.</p>
        <p>One program that is receiving generous financing but little publicity is the development of a powerful laser to shoot down ballistic missiles from a platform in space, intended for use by 2013.</p>
        <p>The Airborne Laser program, run by the Air Force, aims to put a similar laser aboard a modified Boeing 747 and begin shooting down test missiles by 2003. Seven planes are expected to be in operation by 2009, according to a spokesman for the program, if Congress provides the money. The laser systems could be be designed to work as national or theater defenses.</p>
        <p>Some proponents of adapting theater defenses favor using them in the boost phase, since decoys like balloons or fake warheads separate from the missile at higher altitudes and make the job of finding and shooting down the real warhead that much harder.</p>
        <p>Others insist that this is not the only way, and that the protection that midcourse interceptions could offer against large or inaccessible countries, like Russia, China or Iran, would be indispensable.</p>
        <p>Either way, those who would use the theater missile defenses, or T.M.D., to replace the Pentagon's favored system say their mobility and flexibility make them a better choice.</p>
        <p>''A national missile defense capability that evolves from T.M.D. will probably be cheaper, better contribute to defense against both long- and intermediate-range ballistic missiles, and allow for more effective growth in capability as the threat increases,'' wrote John M. Deutch, Dr. Brown and John P. White in the summer issue of the journal Foreign Policy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deutch, a former director of central intelligence and deputy defense secretary, and Dr. White, a lecturer in public policy at Harvard's John F. Kennedy School of Government and a former deputy defense secretary, both served under President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Among conservatives, who have long supported expansive national missile defenses, enthusiasm for theater defenses runs high.</p>
        <p>But precisely what additional improvements might be necessary to convert those systems into a national defense by intercepting missiles in midflight is still not entirely clear, Dr. Wilkening of Stanford said, since most of them are still under development. Moreover, recent amendments to the 1972 ABM Treaty, which have not been ratified by Congress, prohibit testing theater defenses against intercontinental ballistic missiles directly.</p>
        <p>By far the most important element needed to turn those theater defenses into potential national defenses are long-range sensors, said Dr. David Wright, a senior staff scientist at the Union of Concerned Scientists and a researcher at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.</p>
        <p>With that sensor technology, which the United States already plans to deploy in space and possibly on the ground over the next decade, the Navy system ''starts to look like an interceptor which could, in principle, shoot down strategic missiles,'' Dr. Wright said.</p>
        <p>Critics of converting theater systems say the change would be far more difficult -- requiring, for example, interceptors vastly faster and more maneuverable than the theater systems could muster.</p>
        <p>Also, the sensors carried aboard the interceptors for homing in on a target might have to be improved. Dr. Wright pointed out that the system would have to be able to discriminate between missiles and the decoys that would surely accompany an enemy attack.</p>
        <p>A State Department official said enthusiasts of conversion were overstating their case. ''They seem to imply that you don't need to go the N.M.D. route that this administration is taking,'' the official said, speaking on condition of anonymity. ''There are flaws in these glib statements and analyses.''</p>
        <p>In any case, the administration has no plans to convert theater defenses into national defenses, the official said. ''It would be very difficult for the United States, as a practical matter, to develop a system and label it as one thing with the intent of surreptitiously being able to fulfill a completely different mission.''</p>
        <p>But Lt. Col. Rick Lehner, a spokesman for the Ballistic Missile Defense Organization, said: ''All of these systems can have applicability to both theater and national missile defense. It just depends on which direction the nation wants to go.''</p>
        <p>Modified theater defenses would not be the only way to create such a defense. According to some experts, the simplest and cheapest solution would be to start from scratch with faster interceptors launched from military cargo ships, a strategy advocated by Dr. Richard L. Garwin, a physicist at the Council on Foreign Relations, or from airplanes, an approach that Dr. Wilkening has studied.</p>
        <p>The Air Force is developing a system, called the Airborne Laser, based on an entirely different technology that is targeted toward the boost phase. An eight-year $1.6 billion development program that aims for the shooting down of a missile in 2003, the system is expected to include a laser mounted in the nose of a converted Boeing 747.</p>
        <p>The Air Force is designing the laser to destroy short- and medium-range missiles while they are being launched by rupturing their metal skin. If the system works, it could potentially be used against intercontinental ballistic missiles.</p>
        <p>The space-based laser program will receive $148 million in fiscal year 2001 and would cost $2 billion to $3 billion through its first planned antimissile shot from space in 2013, said Dr. Douglas P. Crawford, the integrator of that project at the Ballistic Missile Defense Organization. If it works, the laser can be used against either theater or national threats, Dr. Crawford said. (This is the only boost-phase defense that would threaten Russia directly since the laser could be fired from a distance.) He added that the technology has been receiving a much more positive reception than it had for years.</p>
        <p>''The 'Star Wars' moniker was a term of derision through the late 80's and early 90's,'' he said, ''but I haven't heard it recently.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
