<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Ward Proves He's Big Enough for Expanded Role</title>
    <meta content="Y04AND$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Bay Packers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Dave</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ward, Dedric</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Green Bay Packers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000904T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E6DD1E30F937A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Ward Proves He's Big Enough for Expanded Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>GREEN BAY, Wis.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dave Anderson Sports of The Times column discusses play of New York Jets receiver Dedric Ward in victory over Green Bay Packers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVER since Keyshawn Johnson departed to Tampa Bay in a flurry of contract demands, the question has hovered over the Jets: could Al Groh and Dedric Ward justify the deal?</p>
        <p>Groh for being willing to trade a Pro Bowl wide receiver. Ward for being his replacement.</p>
        <p>But as the Jets opened Groh's tenure as coach with a 20-16 victory over the Packers yesterday, Ward made the biggest play -- snatching Vinny Testaverde's pass and streaking down the sideline for a 61-yard gain to the Packers' 2 that positioned Testaverde's quick pass to Curtis Martin for the winning touchdown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVER since Keyshawn Johnson departed to Tampa Bay in a flurry of contract demands, the question has hovered over the Jets: could Al Groh and Dedric Ward justify the deal?</p>
        <p>Groh for being willing to trade a Pro Bowl wide receiver. Ward for being his replacement.</p>
        <p>But as the Jets opened Groh's tenure as coach with a 20-16 victory over the Packers yesterday, Ward made the biggest play -- snatching Vinny Testaverde's pass and streaking down the sideline for a 61-yard gain to the Packers' 2 that positioned Testaverde's quick pass to Curtis Martin for the winning touchdown.</p>
        <p>Not that the 5-foot-9-inch Ward was about to debate Johnson's persistent argument that he would be irreplaceable.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to get into that,'' Ward was saying now at his locker. ''We don't talk about the guys that are not here.''</p>
        <p>He didn't have to talk about the guy that is not here. His big play did all the talking for him. He showed that he's big enough. But down deep, he had to feel proud of what he did in catching five passes for 104 yards, a 20.8-yard average.</p>
        <p>''I don't look at it like that,'' he said quietly. ''I just think everybody's going to pick up the slack.''</p>
        <p>As for the big play itself, Ward preferred to credit Dan Henning, the offensive coordinator who called it from the coaches' booth upstairs at Lambeau Field, and Testaverde for throwing it so accurately.</p>
        <p>''It's a play we work on every week,'' Ward said. ''I'm not going to tell you what the name of the play is other than it's our 'touchdown play.' The cornerback bit on it and Vinny made a great read on it.''</p>
        <p>It was also the type of play that Johnson, for all his talent, seldom made -- the long gain that scores or sets up a touchdown.</p>
        <p>With his size, Johnson was better at catching sideline passes and slants over the middle, but he didn't have Ward's sheer speed in being able to run away from most defensive backs.</p>
        <p>Some critics doubted if the Jets' offense could survive with two relatively small wide receivers; Wayne Chrebet, who caught five passes for 47 yards yesterday, is only 5-10.</p>
        <p>But early in Dan Marino's career with the Miami Dolphins, he was at his best in collaborating with two small wide receivers, Mark Clayton and Mark Duper, for dozens of touchdowns.</p>
        <p>In pro football, it's not the height of the wide receivers that counts as much as the skill of the quarterback throwing to them.</p>
        <p>For much of yesterday's game, Testaverde was understandably rusty. In addition to returning from the left Achilles' tendon torn in last season's opener, he also suffered a turf-toe injury that limited him to fewer than 45 snaps in the exhibition games.</p>
        <p>During the first half, Testaverde completed only 11 of 25 passes for 82 yards as running back Curtis Martin carried the team to a 10-10 halftime tie.</p>
        <p>''I envisioned it being a little more crisp,'' the 36-year-old quarterback said of his passing, ''than it was in the first half.''</p>
        <p>In the second half, Testaverde had more the look of the quarterback who had taken the Jets to the American Football Conference championship game in 1998 before losing a shootout with John Elway's Broncos in Denver, the quarterback the Jets need if they are to challenge the Indianapolis Colts for the A.F.C. title now that Bill Parcells is no longer the coach.</p>
        <p>But in winning his opener as the Jets coach, Al Groh refused, at least publicly, to celebrate. Or even to enjoy it.</p>
        <p>''I was very resolute,'' he said, ''to remove my personal emotions from this situation. This was not a first-game win for me, but a great win to start the season. It wasn't about me at all. My ego is not such that I see this in terms of Al Groh at all.''</p>
        <p>In a sense, the new coach was here all by himself. His longtime boss and the Jets' former coach, Bill Parcells, did not make the trip.</p>
        <p>The new owner, Woody Johnson, arrived by chartered jet and flew home on the team's charter, but Parcells was nowhere to be seen. When the Jets are in their training complex, he's in his office there as the Director of Football Operations, alias general manager, but it's as if he doesn't really know how to act in that role.</p>
        <p>He feels that if he's seen around Groh or the players too much, he'll be accused of interfering. He also knows that if he's not seen at all, if it seems that he too far removed, he will be accused of not caring enough.</p>
        <p>But when other legendary coaches evolved into a general manager's role, they were always visible -- Vince Lombardi and Bill Walsh, for example. And then there is Al Davis, briefly a successful coach with the Oakland Raiders, who sometimes was too visible and too vocal as their managing general partner, alias managing general genius.</p>
        <p>It's a fine line that Bill Parcells is walking. And as it turned out, the Jets and Al Groh didn't miss him. But as a Director of Football Operations, he should be at his team's games. He wouldn't be interfering. He would only be inspiring.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
