<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Determined to Play Football, And Finally Able to Prove It</title>
    <meta content="01TAKI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/arts/01TAKI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TAKING THE CHILDREN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nichols, Peter M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Autumn in New York (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Replacements, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hollow Man (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E5D61430F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1130" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Determined to Play Football, And Finally Able to Prove It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nichols, Peter M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter M Nichols Taking the Children review of movies The Replacements, Hollow Man and Autumn in New York (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Replacements  Keanu Reeves, Gene Hackman, Brooke Langton, Jack Warden, Ace Yonamine, Orlando Jones  Directed by Howard Deutch  PG-13  105 minutes</p>
        <p>The movie's tag line gets the point across like a tackle rumbling along with a recovered fumble: ''Pros on strike. Everyday guys get to play!'' After that, everybody might as well go home because absolutely nothing happens that one hasn't seen before in a sports movie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Replacements  Keanu Reeves, Gene Hackman, Brooke Langton, Jack Warden, Ace Yonamine, Orlando Jones  Directed by Howard Deutch  PG-13  105 minutes</p>
        <p>The movie's tag line gets the point across like a tackle rumbling along with a recovered fumble: ''Pros on strike. Everyday guys get to play!'' After that, everybody might as well go home because absolutely nothing happens that one hasn't seen before in a sports movie.</p>
        <p>With his $5 million-a-year players walking the picket line, Ed O'Neill (Mr. Warden), the natty, boozy owner of the Washington Sentinels, enlists Jimmy McGinty (Mr. Hackman), that great old coach from the 80's, to put together a team of scabs to carry on the season. McGinty rounds up a crowd of characters he has known (we all have known, actually): the mad-dog linebacker, the swift receiver who couldn't catch a balloon, the inevitable convict on loan from prison, the 400-pound lineman down from 600 pounds. (He's a sumo wrestler.) ''I love to see a fat guy score!'' McGinty exclaims. He's come to the right place.</p>
        <p>For a quarterback he hires a sad sack named Shane Falco (Mr. Reeves). While at Ohio State, Falco was so badly whipped by Florida State that he has quit the sport in shame and now scrapes barnacles off yacht bottoms. The point McGinty wants to get across to him and all his misfits is that they aren't losers and for this one moment they can be all they ever dreamed of. So crank up those self-images, get out there and kick some shins.</p>
        <p>Nasty strikers turn over Falco's pick-up truck, but he swallows his self-loathing and starts to throw touchdown passes. What's more, he's a selfless leader, which impresses Annabelle (Ms. Langton), who heads a very hot crew of cheerleaders from a local strip joint. But to reach the playoffs, the fill-in Sentinels will have to defeat the genuine Dallas team, the league champions, who have just crossed the picket line. That's absurd, of course, but do you doubt that redemption is at hand?</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- Football bumps and bruises are augmented by a whistling-good barroom brawl.  SEX -- The networks would censor the cheerleading routines.  PROFANITY -- Yes.  FOOTNOTE -- There is heavy consumption of alcohol.  For Which Children?  UNDER AGE 10 -- Too violent, too profane.  AGES 10 AND UP -- In its own obvious way, the film has some things to say about believing in oneself. That can't be all bad, and older children will enjoy the fray.</p>
        <p>Hollow Man  Kevin Bacon, Elisabeth Shue, Josh Brolin, Kim Dickens, William Devane, Greg Grunberg, Joey Slotnick  Directed by Paul Verhoeven  R  114 minutes</p>
        <p>''You should be working,'' reads a message taped to the spot on the ceiling where Sebastan Caine (Mr. Bacon) occasionally gazes when he's at his computer. The hard-driving Caine heads one of the more sensitive research projects around Washington. He and his team inject animals with blue fluid and make them invisible. Trouble is, they can't make them visible again -- until one night when Caine cracks the reversion problem and they reconstitute a gorilla named Isabel.</p>
        <p>Now, that's sensitive. There's no stating how badly the Pentagon wants this stuff. But without telling the military, Caine decides to take the project to level three -- humans, specifically himself. This alarms his assistants: Caine's ex-lover Linda (Ms. Shue), Matt (Mr. Brolin) and Sarah (Ms. Dickens), the project veterinarian, who already has a problem with Caine over his vivisectionist's attitude toward the animals caged at the lab.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Caine injects himself and disappears. Unlike Isabel, however, he can't be brought back. At first he is annoyed, but soon he begins to enjoy popping around the lab scaring the daylights out of his team members, who can't detect him unless they wear infrared glasses or he's in contact with liquid, which outlines his form. Later there's nothing to do but escape from the lab and have some fun on the outside.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, this brings out darker elements in Caine, who immediately rapes a neighbor he's previously only admired through the venetian blinds. Then, while invisibly spying on Linda, he discovers she is having an affair with Matt, which sends him back to the lab for a gory run of terror. The glasses would help.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- Graphic and extreme, with people and animals skewered, ripped and snapped.  SEX -- Caine strips down completely (rear view) before his injection, and there is partial nudity at other times.  PROFANITY -- As pronounced as the violence.  FOOTNOTE -- Not that children should find their way into this film, but if they do, many will be upset at the treatment of their animal friends.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?  UNDER AGE 14 -- Obvously a bad bet on all counts.  AGES 14-17 -- High-tech blood baths will always attract.</p>
        <p>Autumn in New York  Winona Ryder, Richard Gere, Anthony LaPaglia, Sherry Stringfield  Directed by Joan Chen  PG-13  105 minutes</p>
        <p>There she sits, all dewy and ripe and positively gurgling at the notion of taking up with the nicely notorious, crinkly-eyed millionaire restaurateur 26 years her senior. This being fairly routine for the graying, tousled 48-year-old Will (Mr. Gere), it is with a kind of weary, amused resignation that he's drawn into an affair with 22-year-old Charlotte (Ms. Ryder). It's O.K. for now, he tells her, but she should understand that they have no future.</p>
        <p>At the time he doesn't understand the ramifications of that remark. Will is old enough for Charlotte's mother, and in fact he was involved with her mother before her death. As for Charlotte, she is ill with a tumor and a heart problem that has her collapsing around town at dramatic moments. She hasn't long, he learns, a year at most.</p>
        <p>Will being Will, he has a rooftop fling with an old girlfriend. To him, that is as consequential as walking the dog, but it rankles Charlotte. He encounters another attractive young woman (Ms. Stringfield), only this time it's his daughter, whom he's never met. Mulling that one over and deciding he can't do without Charlotte, he begs her to let him love her.</p>
        <p>After reuniting very cute, she glows and acts adorably feisty while he stays devoted and trots around looking for a surgeon to operate on her when the time comes. Then, around Christmas, the crisis strikes.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- None.  SEX-- Will and Charlotte make love, but gauzily and mostly from the shoulders up.  PROFANITY -- Little of consequence.  For Which Children?  UNDER AGE 11 -- A sleep-inducer, and inappropriate anyway.  AGES 11 AND UP -- A narrow stratum of teenagers might fall for this schmaltz, but most would make no connection.</p>
        <p>TAKING THE CHILDREN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
