<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Your Taste, Mr. Frick, If, Um, a Bit More Daring</title>
    <meta content="01FRIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/arts/01FRIC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Frick Collection</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitney, John Hay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Russell, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2DD1730F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1138" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Your Taste, Mr. Frick, If, Um, a Bit More Daring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN RUSSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Russell, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Russell reviews Frick Collection's exhibit of six paintings from former collection of Mr and Mrs John Hay Whitney; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Frick Collection has put on view six paintings from the former collection of Mr. and Mrs. John Hay Whitney. The works, by Corot, Manet, Degas, Picasso and Odilon Redon, are in the Garden Court. Several of them relate in a most instructive way to the Frick Collection as it was formed by Henry Clay Frick (1849-1919) and enlarged, according to his wish, after his death.</p>
        <p>Just about everyone loves the Frick Collection, and most would like it to stay the way it is forever. But Frick loved to buy, and to add. In the year of his death, for example, he bought Vermeer's magical ''Mistress and Maid,'' thereby subtly readjusting the balance of his collection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Frick Collection has put on view six paintings from the former collection of Mr. and Mrs. John Hay Whitney. The works, by Corot, Manet, Degas, Picasso and Odilon Redon, are in the Garden Court. Several of them relate in a most instructive way to the Frick Collection as it was formed by Henry Clay Frick (1849-1919) and enlarged, according to his wish, after his death.</p>
        <p>Just about everyone loves the Frick Collection, and most would like it to stay the way it is forever. But Frick loved to buy, and to add. In the year of his death, for example, he bought Vermeer's magical ''Mistress and Maid,'' thereby subtly readjusting the balance of his collection.</p>
        <p>He did not want his collection to be stationary, fixed and unalterable. To make sure of this, he left enough money for his trustees to go on buying. Over the next 50 years there were new acquisitions of works by, among others, Piero della Francesca, Goya, Constable, Van Eyck,  Memling, Ruysdael and Claude (the monumental ''Sermon on the Mount''). The Frick was still in full evolution.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, it acquired its first painting by Watteau. Not at all in the tradition of Watteau's genius for flirtation, it shows a group of French soldiers quietly going to seed while on garrison duty in Valenciennes (Watteau's birthplace, by the way). In Frick's lifetime, the work might have seemed rather slight.  But Watteau knew about soldiers and soldiering, and he knew every stone of Valenciennes. His little picture soon settled in, as had Boucher's mischievous portrait of his wife when it was acquired, in 1937. High-grade informality can be at home in the Frick.</p>
        <p>But there were limits to Frick's multiplicity of interests, remarkable as it was. He never really warmed, for instance, to French 17th-century painting; there is no Poussin, for instance.</p>
        <p>And when it came to the French 19th century, what do we normally see at the Frick? We see Corot, Degas, Manet, Monet, Renoir, J. F. Millet and Theodore Rousseau. A good, standard list. But no one could tell from the Frick Collection that any of these artists got into fights with the public and could take care of themselves. These are ''nice'' pictures, but with the possible exception of the Manet they don't shake us up.</p>
        <p>There has always been something cautious about the representation of the French 19th century in the Frick. Until recently, when an early Corot of the Forum in Rome was given to the Frick by Eugene V. Thaw and his wife, Clare E. Thaw, there was nothing from the period during which Corot was discovering Italy and discovering himself, concurrently.</p>
        <p>That is where the Whitney loans come in.</p>
        <p>The only Corots bought by Frick (in 1903 and 1936) are two late paintings of the elegiac kind that found favor in Corot's last years. Both date from the 1860's. They are lakeside views, big on overhanging foliage (very delicately rendered) and with twilight on the way. One of the more outspoken French critics of the day said of these pianissimo nocturnes, ''these Corots may be poetic, but they are always the same.''</p>
        <p>Thirty years earlier, an altogether tougher, more vigorous Corot had powered ''Cottage and Mill by a Torrent'' of 1831, now on loan at the Frick. This was a difficult subject, in that it did everything possible to subvert a neat, well-tailored view of nature. The terrain was rough, and wildly uneven. Houses. streams, steep and awkward paths, all pointed every which way. The painter could not make conventional order out of it but had to hold tight to his brushes and dig into a scene that did nothing to make his work easier.</p>
        <p>But this was real France, obstinate France. Nature wanted to have its own way. Corot was to come to love it when his niece married into a local family. But, meanwhile, his concentrated counterpunching in that battle with an erratic, unbiddable nature is something to see.</p>
        <p>In fairness, it should be said that the Whitneys came of a generation that had been brought up with modern art as their birthright. (John Hay Whitney was 25 when the Museum of Modern Art was initiated in New York). Two of the six Whitney paintings represent debuts at the Frick: Picasso looks almost demure with his ''Boy With a Pipe'' of 1905, while  Redon lavishes all his gifts for color on his ''Flowers in a Gold Vase.''</p>
        <p>But where French Impressionism is concerned, the Whitney loans bring about a delicate shift in the honor rolls of the Frick. There was a moment in 1914 when Frick was buying right and left, like a crack shot on advantageous ground. He ranged through Van Dyck, Hogarth, J. M. W. Turner, Goya and Whistler. He also made substantial choices among Degas and Renoir.</p>
        <p>He was ready to be daring in his choice of Goya's ''Forge,'' which even today can bring a shudder by its reinvention of the image of the forge of Vulcan. But with the French Impressionists, Frick's choices were representative but safe. His Degas of young dancers in class with an elderly violinist is a good painting, but one of many of that subject. His big Renoir of a mother and her two daughters is very pretty, but it will not stand out in history. His Manet of a bullfight scene is a more original choice, but it is, after all, a detail cut out by Manet himself from a bigger painting that nobody had liked in 1864.</p>
        <p>So what do the Whitney loans have to give in this context?</p>
        <p>Two marvelous little paintings by Degas of horses and their riders, and a racecourse scene by Manet. Degas liked to watch horses and jockeys doing nothing in particular but subtly warming up. Both were bred to race, but also to go to the starting point on time and in perfect state. So there they are, stooping and stretching, with the jockeys' silks forming and re-forming magical patches of color.</p>
        <p>Manet, by contrast, gives the whole context of the racecourse at the Bois de Boulogne -- half town, half country, with the period grandstand, the distant landscape, the eager public and, in the foreground, two horses that are the epitome of high energy impatient to be used.</p>
        <p>Even in a collection that also includes Rembrandt's ''Polish Rider,'' the Whitney loans add something to the repertory of the horse in art. Henry Clay Frick would surely clap his hands.</p>
        <p>Six paintings from the former collection of Mr. and Mrs. John Hay Whitney will be at the Frick Collection, 1 East 70th Street, Manhattan, (212) 288-0700, through July 29, 2001.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
