<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Revisiting Several Moments That Have Embarrassed Gore</title>
    <meta content="Y01ADB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/national/01adbo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7DC1230F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Revisiting Several Moments That Have Embarrassed Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George W Bush's campaign commmercial featuring some of Al Gore's more embarrassing moments described; photo; map (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Republican National Committee is to begin running this 30-second commercial, titled ''Really,'' in 16 states today. It features some of the most embarrassing aspects of Vice President Al Gore's career, including his raising money at a Buddhist temple and his claim to have created the Internet. It is being shown in Arkansas, Florida, Iowa, Kentucky, Louisiana, Maine, Maryland, Michigan, Missouri, New Mexico, Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Washington, West Virginia and Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Cold Harbor Films</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Republican National Committee is to begin running this 30-second commercial, titled ''Really,'' in 16 states today. It features some of the most embarrassing aspects of Vice President Al Gore's career, including his raising money at a Buddhist temple and his claim to have created the Internet. It is being shown in Arkansas, Florida, Iowa, Kentucky, Louisiana, Maine, Maryland, Michigan, Missouri, New Mexico, Ohio, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Washington, West Virginia and Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Cold Harbor Films</p>
        <p>ON THE SCREEN -- The setting is a peach-colored kitchen, with a small television atop a counter. On the television screen Vice President Gore is seen speaking, though there is no sound, in the White House briefing room on the day he said there was ''no controlling legal authority'' over how he raised money in the 1996 campaign. The screen goes fuzzy and then shows Mr. Gore nodding to a Buddhist monk, who is bowing at him. The screen shows monks in saffron robes testifying under oath and then shows Mr. Gore, a near smirk on his face, speaking at the Democratic National Convention. It then shows him in a ''Larry King Live'' interview saying, ''I took the initiative in creating the Internet.'' The camera returns to the kitchen. Flashed on the screen is a Web site, gorewillsayanything.com.</p>
        <p>THE SCRIPT -- A female narrator says: ''There's Al Gore, reinventing himself on television again. Like I'm not going to notice. Who's he going to be today? The Al Gore who raises campaign money at a Buddhist temple? Or the one who promises campaign finance reform? Really. Al Gore, claiming credit for things he didn't even do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore: ''I took the initiative in creating the Internet.''</p>
        <p>Woman: ''Yeah, and I invented the remote control, too. Another round of this, and I'll sell my television.''</p>
        <p>ACCURACY -- The commercial, a compendium of some of Mr. Gore's most embarrassing public moments, uses Mr. Gore's own words and pictures of him to suggest that he has no credibility. The statement that Mr. Gore ''raises campaign money at a Buddhist temple'' is technically not correct because he did not actually ask for money at the temple, but that point has been lost. The larger question is whether it is fair to link these events and cast them as Mr. Gore's ''reinventing'' himself. Earlier this year, Mr. Gore publicly acknowledged that he was ''an imperfect messenger'' on the subject of fixing the campaign finance system, a point the commercial ignores. He has also said that he thinks his comment about the Internet was the biggest mistake of his campaign, although at the time his aides defended the claim and had various leaders in the high-tech field vouch for Mr. Gore's involvement in legislation that helped pave the way for the Internet.</p>
        <p>SCORECARD -- Perhaps the most striking aspect of the commercial is the sarcastic tone of the narrator. Analysts say sarcasm is a dangerous weapon in commercials because if no actual humor is evident, sarcasm can come across as petty and malicious and turn off swing voters. The tone may also detract from the message, which seeks to exploit Mr. Gore's vulnerability on the matter of credibility. The timing of this commercial -- unusually early and coinciding with the slide of Gov. George W. Bush in the polls -- suggests a certain desperation by Republicans and an implicit assumption that negative advertising works. Whether it will prove to be a breakthrough commercial of some sort remains to be seen, but it is certainly laying the groundwork for harsher attacks to come, from both sides.</p>
        <p>KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
