<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Art Glass Of Murano, Modern Style</title>
    <meta content="01ANTI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/arts/01ANTI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226754"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Murano (Italy)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Venice (Italy)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonan, Wendy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Venice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Glass</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFD71430F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1150" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Art Glass Of Murano, Modern Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Antiques column previews three exhibits of twentieth-century Murano glass; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The renowned Murano glassmaking industry, on an island in the Venetian lagoon, has gone through several reincarnations since it was founded in 1291. Its last great period  began in 1921 and continued through the 1950's, and it is this era that is now the focus of museum curators, gallery owners and collectors.</p>
        <p>''Technically, the idea of art glass really starts in the 20th century in Murano,'' said Tina Oldknow, curator of contemporary glass at the Corning Museum of Glass in Corning, N.Y. In the 1920's Murano's ancient guild system was infiltrated by outside artistic talent, probably for the first time, and it revolutionized the industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The renowned Murano glassmaking industry, on an island in the Venetian lagoon, has gone through several reincarnations since it was founded in 1291. Its last great period  began in 1921 and continued through the 1950's, and it is this era that is now the focus of museum curators, gallery owners and collectors.</p>
        <p>''Technically, the idea of art glass really starts in the 20th century in Murano,'' said Tina Oldknow, curator of contemporary glass at the Corning Museum of Glass in Corning, N.Y. In the 1920's Murano's ancient guild system was infiltrated by outside artistic talent, probably for the first time, and it revolutionized the industry.</p>
        <p>Three Manhattan exhibitions of 20th-century Murano glass are coming up. ''Masters of Italian Glass: 1900-2000'' is at the Barry Friedman Gallery, 32 East 67th Street, from Sept. 12 through Oct. 28. The American Craft Museum will show Venetian glass from the collection of a New York couple, Nancy Olnick and Giorgio Spanu, from Sept. 13 through Jan. 8. And at the Corning Inc. Gallery at Steuben, Madison Avenue at 61st Street, ''Art and Design in Italian Glass: The Steinberg Foundation Collection'' will run from Nov. 6 through Jan. 14.</p>
        <p>The frilly glass ''souvenir-johnnies'' that Americans have been bringing home for a century -- glass seahorses and pastel chandeliers -- are still made in Venice. But Murano art glass is a different species: bigger, bolder, brighter, organic, often asymmetrical and far more original.</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman, a dealer in 20th-century furniture, photography, ceramics, silver and glass since 1967, began collecting 20th-century Murano glass in the early 1980's. ''There were no books on the subject then,'' he said. He sold 60 pieces in 1986 and 1987, he went on, because ''my son was born and I had no safe place to put them.''</p>
        <p>He began buying again in the 1990's when ''the market for Italian art glass was poor and the prices went way down,'' he said. In the late 1990's the Murano market picked up; in 1996 an encyclopedic show organized by the Kunstmuseum in Dusseldorf, Germany, traveled to the Corning Museum and the Tokyo Metropolitan Teien Art Museum. The show's catalog, ''Italian Glass: Murano-Milan, 1930-1970'' (Prestel Verlag, 1997), by Helmut Ricke, the director of the Kunstmuseum, and Eva Schmitt, a glass scholar, has become a bible for collectors.</p>
        <p>The modern art glass movement in Italy started about 1921, when an enterprising Milanese lawyer, Paolo Venini, founded a new glass company in Murano with a Venetian antiques dealer, Giacomo Cappelin. ''Venini wanted to develop a modern style in glass, to bring Murano into the new century,'' Ms. Oldknow said. ''Cappelin was the local with all the contacts. Venini was an outsider from Milan whose friends were post-World War I intelligentsia.''</p>
        <p>He hired a painter, Vittorio Zecchin, as his artistic director. Zecchin opposed the decoration of glass. As Mr. Ricke writes: ''Venini's fundamental decision, which proved extremely hard to impose on the island's proud master craftsmen, was undoubtedly the renunciation of all those decorative curlicues and filigree-glass fripperies.''</p>
        <p>Venini and Zecchin persuaded the blowers to produce vessels with the clean lines and the classic proportions of Renaissance and ancient Roman glass. Instead of pastels, Zecchin chose sober, monochromatic hues. These vessels, far from being delicate, had solidity and monumentality. It did not take long for the work to gain popularity, beginning an in 1923 at the first International Exhibition of Decorative Arts at Monza, Italy.</p>
        <p>Artists often designed for different houses. Mr. Friedman is selling, for $27,000, a piece from the 1920's that Zecchin designed for Compagnia Venezia Murano: a large unembellished amethyst-colored vase.</p>
        <p>In 1925 Venini hired the sculptor Napoleone Martinuzzi, who also designed elegant modern vessels but introduced intense colors. Mr. Friedman has a fire-engine red, hand blown vase he designed for Venini. It has a black band at the neck and base, and black glass handles. The body is a brilliant red with gray specks incorporated into the surface. The price is $24,000.</p>
        <p>In 1932, Venini hired two Milanese architects, Tomoso Buzzi and Carlo Scarpa. Scarpa (1906-1978) became one of the most important Italian architects of the 20th century. He did interiors, furniture for Simon International, lamps for Flos and exhibitions as well as buildings. Friendly with Louis Kahn and Frank Lloyd Wright, he taught architecture and industrial design.</p>
        <p>In glass, he was interested in surface and tactile values. He mixed colorless glass with opaque, introducing colorful threads and ribbons. He frosted glass, made it look ancient and corroded, cut it and ground it in new ways. ''Scarpa was consciously looking back at history,'' Ms. Old know said. ''Scarpa introduced new principles of light and space into glass by using a variety of forms combined with engraving techniques.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman has a few Scarpa vases. One made by Venini around 1936, called ''Carroso,'' is a hand-blown glass vase in iridescent dark green and lavender. The surface has protruding irregular ribs that resemble clouds. ''It's the only one I've ever seen,'' Mr. Friedman said. It costs $30,000.</p>
        <p>Two other Scarpa pieces have surfaces like chipped wood. One has facets cut like fish scales. Another has thin glass filaments joined together, and the thin walls have been subtly carved. These vessels remind you of the collaborative quality of art glass. Each piece requires a designer, a master glass blower and a cutter.</p>
        <p>Buying art glass from Murano is tricky. Because certain models were reissued and made by two or three generations of glass blowers, they can be hard to date. Signatures matter, but not too much.</p>
        <p>The Venini family sold the company in the 1980's to Royal Copenhagen of Denmark, which continues to produce models, but in different forms. ''They change the colors and proportions, so Venini products are quite different from what they were when the family controlled the company,'' Ms. Oldknow warned.</p>
        <p>Happily, the art glass influenced other more commercial sectors of the Murano glass industry. Web sites like antique-glass.co.uk and  circline.com offer anonymous 20th-century Murano vases and decorative pieces for less than $1,500 apiece. Antiques shops like Neo-Studio, 25 Main Street in Sag Harbor, N.Y., have midcentury unsigned Murano lamps, bowls and vases for a few hundred dollars apiece. The Manhattan galleries Primavera and the Gansevoort both have several name pieces.</p>
        <p>And who is buying it? ''The movie people love Murano,'' said Jean-Yves Legrand, the owner of Neo-Studio. Mr. Friedman said half of his customers were European. ''Art dealers like Bruno Bischofberger and collectors of contemporary art are the most serious collectors,'' he said. ''The market is still evolving.''</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
