<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="01TRNS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EFDB1230F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Claimed RHP Ben Weber off waivers from the San Francisco Giants and assigned him to Edmonton of the PCL.  BALTIMORE ORIOLES--Activated 3B Cal Ripken from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled OF Eugene Kingsale from Rochester of the International League. Purchased the contract of OF Karim Garcia from Rochester.  BOSTON RED SOX--Acquired OF Midre Cummings from the Minnesota Twins for INF Hector De Los Santos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  ANAHEIM ANGELS--Claimed RHP Ben Weber off waivers from the San Francisco Giants and assigned him to Edmonton of the PCL.  BALTIMORE ORIOLES--Activated 3B Cal Ripken from the 15-day disabled list. Recalled OF Eugene Kingsale from Rochester of the International League. Purchased the contract of OF Karim Garcia from Rochester.  BOSTON RED SOX--Acquired OF Midre Cummings from the Minnesota Twins for INF Hector De Los Santos.</p>
        <p>National League  METS--Sent RHP Jim Mann outright to Norfolk of the International League.  CINCINNATI REDS--Traded OF Dante Bichette to the Boston Red Sox for RHP Chris Reitsma and LHP John Curtice.  FLORIDA MARLINS--Assigned RHP John McKay and RHP Steve Sawyer to Kane County of the Midwest League.  ST. LOUIS CARDINALS--Optioned C Keith McDonald to Memphis of the PCL. Purchased contract of OF Thomas Howard from Memphis. Placed INF Jason Woolf on the 15-day disabled list.  SAN DIEGO PADRES--Agreed to terms with OF Mewelde Moore.  SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS--Claimed C Scott Servais off waivers from the Colorado Rockies.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  DETROIT PISTONS--Named Dave Twardzik and Mike Sanders assistant coaches.  PHILADELPHIA 76ERS--Named Brian Kirschner manager of communications.  PHOENIX SUNS--Waived G Randy Livingston.  PORTLAND TRAIL BLAZERS--Traded C Jermaine O'Neal and C Joe Kleine to the Indiana Pacers for C Dale Davis.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  INDIANAPOLIS COLTS--Waived DB Paul Miranda. Signed WR Joey Kent.  PHILADELPHIA EAGLES--Signed CB William Hampton to the practice squad.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  COLUMBUS BLUE JACKETS--Agreed to terms with G Marc Denis on a multiyear contract.  EDMONTON OILERS--Signed D Alain Nasreddine and RW Paul Healey.  MINNESOTA WILD--Signed D Eric Charron and D Lawrence Nycholat.  PHILADELPHIA FLYERS--Signed G Brian Boucher to a two-year contract.  PHOENIX COYOTES--Signed D Joel Bouchard and D Dave MacIntrye to one-year contracts.  TAMPA BAY LIGHTNING--Re-signed D Pavel Kubina to a two-year contract.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>CCNY--Announced the resignation of Dan Nigro, men's basketball coach.  COLORADO STATE--Announced the suspension of sophomore QB Steve Cutlip for the season.  COLUMBIA--Named Brendan Buckley wrestling coach.  MONMOUTH, N.J.--Promoted Dennis Shea to director of golf. Named Bryan Carey women's golf coach.  PROVIDENCE--Announced F Leland Anderson has transferred from Michigan.  SAN DIEGO STATE--Named Jill Young women's assistant soccer coach. Announced that G Tony Bland and F Brandon Smith have transferred to the men's basketball program.  SOUTHAMPTON--Named Ken Moyers and Kelly Nelmes women's assistant basketball coaches.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
