<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Numbers Aside, Jeter Still Measures Up</title>
    <meta content="01YANK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/sports/01yank.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jeter, Derek</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E4DC1230F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1277" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Numbers Aside, Jeter Still Measures Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Yankees' shortstop Derek Jeter; says Jeter infuses the Yanks with energy, professionalism and joy even if his numbers are down this year; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The competitive, cutting remarks between them are few and always good-natured, Alex Rodriguez says about the conversations with his good friend Derek Jeter. The shortstops are like brothers and even the most loving brothers push each other inherently, the presence of one driving the other.</p>
        <p>When the friends talk these days, the Seattle Mariners shortstop could slip in a little dig about power production, if he wanted; he has got a lot of home runs and runs batted in, and Jeter does not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The competitive, cutting remarks between them are few and always good-natured, Alex Rodriguez says about the conversations with his good friend Derek Jeter. The shortstops are like brothers and even the most loving brothers push each other inherently, the presence of one driving the other.</p>
        <p>When the friends talk these days, the Seattle Mariners shortstop could slip in a little dig about power production, if he wanted; he has got a lot of home runs and runs batted in, and Jeter does not.</p>
        <p>Jeter's numbers for the Yankees are down this year, almost across the board. He received the votes for most valuable player last year, and Rodriguez will this year.</p>
        <p>But Rodriguez might be wise to refrain from flaunting his numbers too much, because Jeter could always dredge up the R-word: Rings. Championship rings. Jeter already has three and the Yankees are steadily pursuing a fourth.</p>
        <p>''If we win, they can have more home runs and more R.B.I.,'' Jeter said, referring to Rodriguez and Boston's Nomar Garciaparra, his most celebrated shortstop peers. ''As long as I have the rings. That's what you play for. Numbers are great, but you want to put up the numbers that are going to help your team win, and you can help your team win in more ways than hitting home runs and having a lot of R.B.I.''</p>
        <p>Jeter is not hitting many home runs this year: 12, half of what he hit last year. He has 61 R.B.I., after driving in 102 in 1999. His slugging percentage is .468, down from .552 last year. He made two errors Wednesday to give him 20 for the season; he  had 14 last year.</p>
        <p>But Jeter is a little like the United States economy: some of the leading indicators might be off, but the Yankees are in first place, he is on a pace to score 124 runs and collect 200 hits, and sometime in the last month of the regular season, he should surpass 1,000 career hits, at age 26.</p>
        <p>His numbers are diminished, undoubtedly. And Jeter is thriving.</p>
        <p>''The year's not over, but obviously I'd like to be doing better in every category,'' he said. ''But there's been periods, like you have every year, where you don't swing the bat well and you're still able to get some hits, and then I've had some periods where I swung the bat well and haven't gotten hits. So it's been up and down.''</p>
        <p>Jeter sets statistical goals for himself, and although he won't reveal the numbers he hoped for this year, it is safe to say he wanted to at least match his 1999 numbers for homers and R.B.I. He carried the Yankees in the first half of the 1999 season and  finished the year third in the balloting for the league's M.V.P. award. When pitchers jammed him with inside fastballs, he often turned on them and drove them to left-center field or to center, or slammed singles, doubles and homers to right field.</p>
        <p>When pitchers jammed him early this year -- following the accepted standard on how to pitch Jeter -- or threw pitches down and away, Jeter often swung aggressively at bad pitches and made a lot of weak outs.  His basic hitting philosophy, after all, is to attack always.</p>
        <p>Attempting to adjust, Jeter backed away from the plate to cope better with the inside fastballs. He started striding forward at a 45-degree angle, rather than right at the pitcher, and found himself stepping into fastballs and effectively jamming himself. Searching for a solution to this, he took extra batting practice -- and strained an abdominal muscle, an injury that forced him to the disabled list May 12. When he came back a couple of weeks later, Jeter was reluctant to swing hard, lest he cause a more serious injury.</p>
        <p>So it is September now and Jeter is not going to match his home run and R.B.I. production of last year. He acknowledged this the other day, sounding completely at ease with that reality.</p>
        <p>''My job is to score runs, and that's the bottom line,'' he said. ''I think a lot of times people want to focus on R.B.I. output, but when you're hitting first and second in the lineup, R.B.I. isn't really something that you strive for. Obviously, I'd like to hit more home runs; I think everybody would like to hit more home runs, but, hitting first or second, that's not my job. As long as I'm getting on base, that's what I worry about.''</p>
        <p>He is batting .324 and in the last three weeks has begun to draw more walks, feeling more comfortable at the plate. But Yankee Manager Joe Torre does not believe there is a statistic that fully defines what Jeter provides -- not home runs, nor R.B.I., nor runs scored.</p>
        <p>''His value in the market we play in is hard to fathom,'' Torre said. ''What he does for us is not easy to do. He loves the challenge. He's not affected by everything that goes on around him. He continues to have that fire in his eyes. I've never seen a doubt when I look into his eyes.''</p>
        <p>Shortly after Brad Radke signed a four-year, $36 million deal to remain with the struggling Minnesota Twins, Torre overheard Jeter's conversation with a teammate. What would that be like, Jeter asked with some wonderment, to play for a team that is not winning, to not know when you were going to win?</p>
        <p>The Garciaparra-Rodriguez-Jeter comparisons are built on statistics, the way numbers fueled and fashioned the question of whether Willie or Mickey or The Duke was better in the 1950's.</p>
        <p>But Jeter's teammates do not tend to think of him in terms of numbers; they tend to think about what he lends to each day's pursuit of victory -- his energy, the joy he exudes in the depths of the grinding season, his confidence.</p>
        <p>''His focus is on winning,'' said third baseman Scott Brosius, ''and when you have that, it sort of makes everything else easy. It takes the pressure off you to achieve numbers.''</p>
        <p>During a bleak pitching change in Oakland last weekend, Jeter stood on the mound among sullen teammates and suddenly started slapping each of them on the chest with his glove. It was as if he had squirted them playfully with a water pistol, a reminder: Hey, we're playing baseball; this is fun. We're a good team and everything's going to work out.</p>
        <p>The closer Mariano Rivera was encased in a jam in the ninth inning Wednesday night, the tying runs on base. Jeter jogged to the mound and began pumping up Rivera.</p>
        <p>''Nobody wants to hit against you,'' Jeter said, forcefully. ''Go right at them. They know it's over.''</p>
        <p>Rivera retired the next two hitters and Jeter shook his hand, grinning at the end of another successful series and road trip. On the other side of the field, Rodriguez retreated into a quiet Seattle clubhouse.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
