<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mathis and Valencia: A Star Strike Force</title>
    <meta content="01SOCC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/sports/01SOCC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226820"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (2000)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summer Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sydney (Australia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maimon, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gerasch, Sylvia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Swimming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia/Sydney</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Swimming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D71530F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mathis and Valencia: A Star Strike Force</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series, The Road To Sydney, profiles career of German swimmer Sylvia Gerasch, who has become oldest German swimmer to compete at Olympics at age 31; Gerasch attributes peaks and valleys of her career to stubborn streak she developed as an adolescent; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clint Mathis of the MetroStars, who last week became the first player in Major League Soccer to score five goals in a game, attributed his achievement to luck and teamwork rather than scoring ability.</p>
        <p>''I was in the right place at the right time five times,'' Mathis said about the record goals he scored in the MetroStars' 6-4 victory in Dallas last Saturday night. ''I owe it all to my teammates. There is no selfishness on this team.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Clint Mathis of the MetroStars, who last week became the first player in Major League Soccer to score five goals in a game, attributed his achievement to luck and teamwork rather than scoring ability.</p>
        <p>''I was in the right place at the right time five times,'' Mathis said about the record goals he scored in the MetroStars' 6-4 victory in Dallas last Saturday night. ''I owe it all to my teammates. There is no selfishness on this team.''</p>
        <p>Tab Ramos and Adolfo Valencia did have a great deal to do with Mathis's accomplishment, which catapulted him to second place in the league scoring race behind Tampa Bay's Mamadou Diallo. Mathis scored his fifth goal of the game in the 83rd minute at the Cotton Bowl on a penalty kick, which is Valencia's specialty.</p>
        <p>Valencia yielded to Mathis at the suggestion of Ramos, who served as team captain because Lothar Matthaus served a one-game suspension by the league for accumulating too many yellow cards. ''Tab asked me if I felt confident enough,'' Mathis said, ''and Adolfo had no problems with it.''</p>
        <p>Valencia set a team record with two minutes left by scoring his 15th goal of the season. Giovanni Savarese had scored 14 goals for the MetroStars in the league's initial season in 1996.</p>
        <p>Valencia and Mathis have combined to form the league's most dangerous tandem of strikers. Even though they come from different backgrounds and cultures -- Mathis is from Conyers, Ga., and Valencia is from Buenaventura, Colombia, and speaks virtually no English -- they have developed a marvelous understanding on the field. Valencia is arguably the best striker in the league at holding the ball and creating space for others. Mathis uses his speed and his intelligence to get open and uses his ferocious shot with either foot to find the target. All five of his goals in Dallas came on blistering shots.</p>
        <p>''I can't even remember when was the last time I scored five goals in a game,'' said Mathis, who started playing soccer at the age of 3. ''Maybe when I played in Under-6 or Under-8 games as a kid.''</p>
        <p>The five goals by Mathis also set a league record for most points in a game with 10, surpassing the record of 8 by Raul Diaz Arce of D.C. United, who scored four goals twice.</p>
        <p>''With so many good scorers in the league, it is a thrill for me to get the record,'' Mathis said. ''And I'm particularly happy it helped the team clinch the title.''</p>
        <p>The victory in Dallas sealed the Eastern Division title, the first title of any kind for the MetroStars. It also put them a point ahead of the Kansas City Wizards for first over all in the 12-team league. ''We want to finish first over all,'' Mathis said after Wednesday's practice in preparation for tomorrow night's game at Miami. ''The game in Miami will be tough because we want to finish first, and they don't want to get eliminated from the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>The MetroStars will face Miami without Ramos, who is with the national team for Sunday's World Cup qualifying game against Guatemala at Washington's R.F.K. Stadium, and Roy Myers, who is with Costa Rica for Sunday's World Cup qualifying game against Barbados.</p>
        <p>Miami will be without Roy Lassiter, the league's career leading scorer, who will serve a one-game suspension for his ejection in a 3-1 loss at Colorado Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
