<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Video Releases; Any Given Sunday</title>
    <meta content="01VIDB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Any Given Sunday (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Next Best Thing, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">American Psycho (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Simpatico (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/DVD and Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E6DF1530F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Video Releases; Any Given Sunday</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brief reviews of movies now released on video: Any Given Sunday, The Next Best Thing, American Psycho and Simpatico; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his legendary quarterback out for the season, Tony D'Amato (Al Pacino, left), coach of the Miami Sharks, turns to the erratic young backup Willie Beamen (Jamie Foxx), while in the stadium's luxury suites the Sharks' cold-blooded owner (Cameron Diaz) plots to get the team's asking price up to $800 million. In sync with a sports-crazed society, Oliver Stone's big, loud movie has fun with the Associated Football Franchises of America, his commerce-crazy equivalent of the National Football League. On the field it's war, Stephen Holden wrote in The New York Times, in a ''crude morality play in the style of Mr. Stone's 'Wall Street.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his legendary quarterback out for the season, Tony D'Amato (Al Pacino, left), coach of the Miami Sharks, turns to the erratic young backup Willie Beamen (Jamie Foxx), while in the stadium's luxury suites the Sharks' cold-blooded owner (Cameron Diaz) plots to get the team's asking price up to $800 million. In sync with a sports-crazed society, Oliver Stone's big, loud movie has fun with the Associated Football Franchises of America, his commerce-crazy equivalent of the National Football League. On the field it's war, Stephen Holden wrote in The New York Times, in a ''crude morality play in the style of Mr. Stone's 'Wall Street.' ''</p>
        <p>1999. Warner. $106.99; DVD, $24.98. 157 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>The Next Best Thing</p>
        <p>Using the words ''It's me, not you,'' a lot of men have begged out of relationships with Abbie Reynolds (Madonna), a Los Angeles yoga teacher. Having helped bear her woe, Robert Whitaker (Rupert Everett), an aging gay Hollywood party boy, shores her up when necessary and, as a consequence of one giddy, drunken occasion, fathers a child with her. But then she falls for a New York investment banker (Benjamin Bratt), which leads to a messy parenting conflict and turns a film with smart promise into ''a stumbling, poor man's 'Kramer vs. Kramer' '' (Holden).</p>
        <p>2000. Paramount. $107.37; DVD, $29.99. 107 minutes. Closed captioned. PG-13.</p>
        <p>American Psycho</p>
        <p>Mary Harron's film trims the body count and number of high-end consumer items from Bret Easton Ellis's novel. By day a budding Wall Street master of the universe, Patrick Bateman (Christian Bale) becomes a homicidal maniac by night. As an arrogant smoothie one minute and a hysterical wimp the next, Mr. Bale gives a star-making performance, and Ms. Harron's direction produces a horror comedy classic ''so surprising that when the movie's over, it feels you've just seen a magician pull a dancing rabbit out of a top hat'' (Holden).</p>
        <p>2000. Universal. $107.37. 104 minutes. Closed captioned. R. Release date: Sept. 5.</p>
        <p>Simpatico</p>
        <p>Trying to sketch in information that Sam Shepard's play omits, Matthew Warchus's offbeat, gawky adaptation thrives with gripping performances and a screenplay that skillfully imitates the playwright's language. Horse racing is the metaphor for the adrenaline-pumped American dream as a corrupt breeder (Jeff Bridges) and his wife (Sharon Stone) tangle with a hard-drinking eccentric (Nick Nolte) who threatens to expose some slippery dealings over a high-priced steed. At least the film has integrity. ''Far from being a typical Hollywood desecration of a difficult play, it stays true to the work's quirky, renegade spirit'' (Holden).</p>
        <p>1999. New Line. $107.37; DVD, $24.95. 106 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a theater release, appeared on television or been on videocassette in earlier editions.</p>
        <p>LONGITUDE. Adapted from Dava Sobel's international best seller, Charles Sturridge's film tells the parallel stories of John Harrison (Michael Gambon), the 18th-century carpenter, clockmaker and musician whose nautical timepieces attempted to solve the complexities of longitude at sea, and Rupert Gould (Jeremy Irons), the World War I Royal Air Force veteran who rescued Harrison's work from oblivion. With plenty of political intrigue stirred in, Julie Salamon wrote in The New York Times, ''the film surprises, much as the book did, by taking what might seem a worthy but dull subject and making it sparkle.'' 2000. A&amp;E. $59.95, four cassettes; DVD, $39.95. 200 minutes. Release date: Aug. 29.</p>
        <p>HOROWITZ: THE LAST ROMANTIC and VERDI: REQUIEM. The first of two new DVD's features Horowitz's performances of Bach-Busoni's Chorale in G minor, Mozart's Sonata in C, Schubert's Impromptu in A flat and Chopin's Mazurka in A minor. Filmed at the Alte Oper in Frankfurt, Verdi's Messa da Requiem is performed by the European Symphony Orchestra and the Neubeuren Choral Society. 2000. DVD, $29.98 each.</p>
        <p>I CLAUDIUS. A new DVD edition of the acclaimed BBC production, which stars Derek Jacobi, John Hurt, Patrick Stewart, Sian Phillips and Sheila White, includes a 71-minute documentary, ''The Epic That Never Was,'' about Alexander Korda's ill-fated 1937 screen adaptation of Robert Graves's novel. $89.99, three discs. 740 minutes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
