<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Learning to Leave the Office Before He Leaves Office; Mayor Who Never Slept Now Golfs, Rests and Looks to Legacy</title>
    <meta content="01MAYO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/nyregion/01mayo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bumiller, Elisabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DF1230F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Learning to Leave the Office Before He Leaves Office; Mayor Who Never Slept Now Golfs, Rests and Looks to Legacy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH BUMILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bumiller, Elisabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani, longtime workaholic, is taking some time for himself, golfing, resting and looking to his legacy in final 16 months of his term; even a more low-key Giuliani works longer hours than most people; he still has news conference almost every day, and he and staff continue to work quietly on initiatives that he promised when he withdrew from Senate race; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is in the low tide of his mayoralty, a time when he has been tired by his cancer treatments, sidelined by his party, distracted by a new love and made wistful by his short time left in office. Rudolph W. Giuliani, the round-the-clock mayor who never slept or took vacations, is now as likely to be on a golf course or at nightly dinners with his new friend, Judith Nathan, as presiding over weekend news conferences and racing to city disasters.</p>
        <p>''He's not in the rush he used to be,'' said Peter F. Vallone, the City Council speaker, who meets with Mr. Giuliani each week. The mayor himself said while discussing his cancer treatment last week that ''I'd like to take a break, actually, probably to play golf, more than to get treated.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is in the low tide of his mayoralty, a time when he has been tired by his cancer treatments, sidelined by his party, distracted by a new love and made wistful by his short time left in office. Rudolph W. Giuliani, the round-the-clock mayor who never slept or took vacations, is now as likely to be on a golf course or at nightly dinners with his new friend, Judith Nathan, as presiding over weekend news conferences and racing to city disasters.</p>
        <p>''He's not in the rush he used to be,'' said Peter F. Vallone, the City Council speaker, who meets with Mr. Giuliani each week. The mayor himself said while discussing his cancer treatment last week that ''I'd like to take a break, actually, probably to play golf, more than to get treated.''</p>
        <p>''He's turned inward,'' said Alan G. Hevesi, the city comptroller, who also meets regularly with Mr. Giuliani. ''He's focused on his health problems and his mortality.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani now plays golf up to three days a week, usually at such public courses as Forest Park in Queens, Split Rock in the Bronx or Dyker Beach in Brooklyn. ''We try to hit one of those three every Friday,'' said Anthony V. Carbonetti, the mayor's chief of staff and a favorite golfing partner. Last Thursday, on a day that Mr. Giuliani had no public schedule until an evening town meeting, he played golf with his flamboyant and New Agey friend, Elliot Cuker. More often than not, the mayor now takes off Friday afternoons and all day Saturday. He has said that three months of hormone treatments, to be followed soon by radiation or surgery, have left him ''a little fatigued.''</p>
        <p>Of course, a more low-key Mr. Giuliani -- who throughout much of his mayoralty worked seven long days a week -- may simply mean that he is keeping something close to normal hours. The mayor still arrives at City Hall before his daily 8 a.m. staff meeting and often does not leave until 7 p.m. He still has a news conference almost every day. He still controls $37 billion in city spending, the fourth-largest government budget in the United States.</p>
        <p>And he and his staff continue to work quietly on the initiatives that the mayor promised when he withdrew from the Senate race, pledging to be a better person and to reach out to the minority residents he has alienated. In June, the mayor and his top advisers had a daylong retreat in Queens to discuss how to burnish and reshape the Giuliani legacy, focusing on some of the social problems that critics of the law-and-order mayor say he has ignored. In July, the mayor's senior staff met with religious leaders for detailed discussions of plans for low-income housing, a need Mr. Giuliani recently acknowledged.</p>
        <p>''It was like a door got opened,'' said Archdeacon Michael S. Kendall all of the Episcopal Church's New York Diocese, who was at the meeting. ''It was not adversarial. It was, 'Yeah, we really do want to provide housing. We really want to talk to you.' ''</p>
        <p>As recently as last week, a member of Mr. Giuliani's staff told an intermediary that the mayor still wanted to meet with the family of Patrick M. Dorismond, the unarmed black man shot dead by the police in March and then excoriated by Mr. Giuliani in remarks that appalled even many Republicans. The family has made no decision. But Mr. Giuliani has spent the last two Sundays attending services at minority churches with his new police commissioner, Bernard B. Kerik, whose mandate includes improving police relations with the city's ethnic and racial groups.</p>
        <p>Immediately after Mr. Giuliani announced the appointment of Mr. Kerik on Aug. 19, the mayor said recently, ''we sat down together and I said it would a nice thing if we went to an African-American church tomorrow, and then do some other events, and therefore show people that we want to be open, that we want to do everything we can to make people feel included.''</p>
        <p>At home, the mayor's failed marriage remains in a holding pattern. Mr. Giuliani announced in May that he was seeking a separation from his wife, Donna Hanover, after publicly acknowledging Ms. Nathan's importance in his life. But the mayor is not known to have hired a divorce lawyer, as Ms. Hanover has. And although Ms. Hanover announced in May that she and the couple's two children would remain at Gracie Mansion, the mayor's official residence, for ''at least the next few months,'' Ms. Hanover's press secretary, Joannie Danielides, said this week that Ms. Hanover had ''no plans to leave Gracie Mansion at this time.'' Friends say the mayor and his wife have agreed that she and the children should remain at the mansion until Mr. Giuliani's term ends on Dec. 31, 2001. The reasons include security concerns and a desire to avoid the spectacle and embarrassment of a move.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hanover, Ms. Danielides said, will continue to appear in public as the city's first lady, promoting her community service work, including her ''Cool Schools'' awards program and her support for ''Race for the Cure,'' a September run in Central Park to benefit breast cancer research. In October, Ms. Hanover will also assume a starring role in ''The Vagina Monologues,'' the Off Broadway hit that includes monologues on topics like orgasm and childbirth. Ms. Hanover was to have appeared in the play in May, but postponed her performance shortly after her husband announced he had prostate cancer.</p>
        <p>Politically, Mr. Giuliani's future is in limbo. Although former campaign advisers like Bruce J. Teitelbaum speak glowingly of the warm reception the mayor received at the Republican National Convention this month -- Mr. Giuliani did not sit with the New York delegation but in a box with Nancy Reagan and Cindy McCain, the wife of Senator John McCain -- state Republicans are increasingly exasperated by what they see as the mayor's failure to play well with the party. Mr. Giuliani, for example, has not decided what he will do with the $3.8 million left in the bank from his aborted race against Hillary Rodham Clinton, and this week he seemed to indicate that the money was not going to Mrs. Clinton's new opponent, Representative Rick A. Lazio -- or to any Republican -- any time soon.</p>
        <p>''We'll figure out over the next couple months what we can do with it, and what we can do with it over the next couple of years,'' Mr. Giuliani said at a news conference in Harlem. The mayor also had to return about $2.8 million in checks to individual donors, but he urged those contributors to sign the money over to Mr. Lazio. Mr. Teitelbaum said this week that Mr. Giuliani had directly given Mr. Lazio $12,000 so far, and was prevented by law from giving more. But lawyers specializing in election law said Mr. Giuliani could transfer the money to the state or national Republican Parties, which could spend it on Mr. Lazio's behalf.</p>
        <p>''The money was raised to defeat Hillary, and I think it should be used for that purpose,'' said Michael R. Long, the chairman of the Conservative Party, who has had a contentious relationship with Mr. Giuliani. If the mayor keeps the money, Mr. Long added, ''it's going to leave a lasting bad taste.''</p>
        <p>As it is, there is still much bitterness in the state Republican Party about Mr. Giuliani's behavior in the Senate campaign, a race he often treated with ostentatious indifference. ''He has a tremendous amount of fence-building to do with Republican leaders around the state,'' said James Cavanaugh, the Westchester County Republican chairman. ''He never really established the kinds of relationships that he should have as a statewide candidate. And to some degree, he probably lost ground with the people in the party.''</p>
        <p>The mayor's circle responds with the revisionist view that a man who raised $20 million against Mrs. Clinton was not actually running at all and therefore should not be blamed for his leisurely pace and for not spending a single night out of New York City. They also point out that he never made an official announcement of his candidacy. ''I don't think there was a race,'' said Raymond B. Harding, the chairman of the Liberal Party and a close adviser to the mayor. ''He never entered it.'' (Actually, at a sparsely attended and little noticed rally at the Westchester County Republican headquarters on Feb. 12, Mr. Giuliani finally managed to get out a half-hearted ''Give me a break, I'm running,'' after repeated urging from the crowd.)</p>
        <p>These days there is lackluster speculation about whether Mr. Giuliani will dare challenge Gov. George E. Pataki in a primary for governor in 2002, should Mr. Pataki run for a third term, or whether Mr. Pataki might go to Washington in a Bush administration and leave the race ripe for the mayor. The mayor, if his comments this week are any indication, might still have more than $3 million banked for a running start. Mr. Giuliani has also expressed interest in running for mayor in 2005, as the law allows.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the mayor said during an appearance on David Letterman's late-night talk show that he was ''not yet'' eager to run for another office but ''maybe I will in a year or so.'' Mr. Giuliani also expressed more regret than he publicly had in the past about his decision to drop out of the race because of his cancer. ''I felt very bad when I had to not run,'' Mr. Giuliani told Mr. Letterman. ''And for a while I felt really bad that I missed events and things.''</p>
        <p>Whatever Mr. Giuliani decides to do, even detractors like former Mayor Edward I. Koch -- who predicts that if Mr. Pataki runs again, Mr. Giuliani will be ''permanently assigned to the Siberia of the private sector'' -- say that the mayor will remain relevant for his last 16 months in office. ''Substantively, he's more relevant now because people don't attach a political motive to things,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi agreed. ''He's not going to be a traditional lame duck,'' he said, ''until 20 minutes before New Year's Eve'' next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
