<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Franco Aches to Return for Drive</title>
    <meta content="01BASE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/sports/01base.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226875"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franco, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E4DC1230F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Franco Aches to Return for Drive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jack Curry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Curry On Baseball column on New York Mets relief pitcher John Franco, who hopes to begin pitching again after missing time because of sore left pectoral muscle; Franco has not pitched since Aug 22; Franco has had rewarding season, not allowing earned run since June 21, against Philadelphia Phillies; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Franco is scheduled to throw off a mound in St. Louis today, testing his sore left pectoral muscle and hoping that he will finally be able to pitch in a game by tomorrow or Sunday. Even if Franco, who last pitched Aug. 22, feels some pain, he expects to pitch through it unless the discomfort is excruciating. This is not the time to give in, especially for the resilient Franco.</p>
        <p>This has been a rewarding season for Franco, a season that started out humbling and disappointing. Franco knew that he had lost his closer position to Armando Benitez and realized that he would probably never get a chance with the Mets to chase Lee Smith's record of 478 saves. Still, while Franco understood he had been replaced, he did not expect to feel so nonexistent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Franco is scheduled to throw off a mound in St. Louis today, testing his sore left pectoral muscle and hoping that he will finally be able to pitch in a game by tomorrow or Sunday. Even if Franco, who last pitched Aug. 22, feels some pain, he expects to pitch through it unless the discomfort is excruciating. This is not the time to give in, especially for the resilient Franco.</p>
        <p>This has been a rewarding season for Franco, a season that started out humbling and disappointing. Franco knew that he had lost his closer position to Armando Benitez and realized that he would probably never get a chance with the Mets to chase Lee Smith's record of 478 saves. Still, while Franco understood he had been replaced, he did not expect to feel so nonexistent.</p>
        <p>''I think he thought he was being phased out,'' Manager Bobby Valentine said.</p>
        <p>Valentine did not envision it that way and Franco has proved that he could translate his success as a closer into the eighth inning and, in doing so, has made himself a more versatile and more valuable pitcher. Franco has maintained the steely attitude of a closer and has not allowed an earned run in 23 games. Since June 24, Franco has been almost perfect.  That is incredible.</p>
        <p>''The only difference is you just don't get that S next to your name right now,'' said Franco, who has 420 saves. ''Sometimes I come in when the game is close, against the top of the order. You get out of that, to me, that's a save.''</p>
        <p>It did not always look as if Franco would adapt to the setup role because it did not look like he or the Mets would allow it to happen. Valentine realized how delicate it was for Franco to be jettisoned as a closer after 15 seasons in that role, so the manager waited for Franco, who has four saves this season and is 58 shy of Smith's record, to dictate the pace of ''understanding this issue.''</p>
        <p>A few weeks into the season, Franco knocked on Valentine's office door. He needed to talk. He was confused, miserable and maybe even bitter. Franco, Valentine and the pitching coach Dave Wallace discussed Franco's position on the Mets and how he could still be a major contributor. Franco told Valentine that he needed to pitch frequently to keep his slider and changeup sharp.</p>
        <p>''I just didn't feel comfortable,'' Franco said. ''When I left the office, we were on the same page. I needed to tell him I needed to pitch quite often. Bobby understood. He was great. I understood what they did. I didn't have to like it, but I understood.''</p>
        <p>As Valentine stood near the batting cage at Shea Stadium recently, he nodded while he recalled the meeting with Franco and Wallace. Valentine told Franco ''nothing had changed'' from when Valentine relied on Franco as one of the top relievers in the National League. Valentine told Franco that he still planned to lean on him, which he has.</p>
        <p>The Mets probably have the deepest bullpen in baseball and Franco is a crucial pitcher, holding left-hander hitters to a .197 average, which is why his recovery is essential.</p>
        <p>''I wanted him to understand that he could be as important to our success this year as he was last year,'' Valentine said. ''I wanted him to know it wasn't a one-year thing. It could be a many-year thing.''</p>
        <p>Both Valentine and Wallace admitted that Franco, who will turn 40 on Sept. 17, had probably increased his value by displaying such versatility.</p>
        <p>''I haven't talked to anybody around baseball, but I'm sure my value has gone up,'' Franco said. ''Everybody is looking for good pitching.''</p>
        <p>Franco stayed with the Mets for another season because there was minimal interest in him from other teams and because, having finally made it to the postseason in 1999, he knew how he would feel if the Mets won a World Series title after he left to sign with another team. Fred Wilpon, the Mets' co-owner and fellow Lafayette High School alum, adores Franco and would surely want him back in 2001.</p>
        <p>In the same setup role, though, Benitez is signed through the 2003 season and is not budging as the closer.</p>
        <p>''What I've done is because he's shown me,'' Benitez said of Franco. ''I have a lot of respect for this guy.''</p>
        <p>Franco refused to take any credit for Benitez's sensational season -- Benitez has 36 saves -- but he added, ''Sometimes young guys forget work habits and don't respect the game. He doesn't do that.''</p>
        <p>Despite the fluidity of this season, Franco will have to decide if he wants to return because he is a free agent again. If the Mets win a World Series title, one possibility for next season would be for Franco to stay put and try to repeat. Another possibility would be for him to take the elusive World Series ring, sign with another team and pursue Smith's record. Franco would not reveal his preference, but he did not swat away the second scenario. ''It's something to think about it,'' said Franco. ''After the season, I'll talk with my family, my friends and my agent and I'm sure whatever decision I make will be the right one. Right now, I'm not going to say anything about it. I'll worry about it after the season is over.''</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
