<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Retailers Post Weak August, Hoping It's Not Holiday Omen</title>
    <meta content="Y01SHO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Goldman Sachs Retail Composite Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaufman, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7D81530F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Retailers Post Weak August, Hoping It's Not Holiday Omen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE KAUFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaufman, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Goldman Sachs retail composite index shows retail sales for August in stores open at least a year rose just 3 percent, lower than analysts expected and weakest August results in three years; results for specific major retailers noted; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After watching business slow for six months, the nation's merchants reported only slight gains yesterday in sales of back-to-school merchandise -- news that may not bode well for the rest of the year and the coming holiday season.</p>
        <p>Retail sales for August in stores open at least a year, a crucial industry measurement, rose just 3 percent, according to the Goldman Sachs retail composite index. The numbers were hardly disastrous, but they were lower than analysts had expected and the weakest August results in three years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After watching business slow for six months, the nation's merchants reported only slight gains yesterday in sales of back-to-school merchandise -- news that may not bode well for the rest of the year and the coming holiday season.</p>
        <p>Retail sales for August in stores open at least a year, a crucial industry measurement, rose just 3 percent, according to the Goldman Sachs retail composite index. The numbers were hardly disastrous, but they were lower than analysts had expected and the weakest August results in three years.</p>
        <p>After experiencing nearly two years of banner growth, retail sales have been slowing since early this year. But consumer enthusiasm for back-to-school shopping is watched particularly closely because it is seen as the first window to the all-important holiday season.</p>
        <p>''Usually what happens in August is a very significant harbinger of the rest of the year,'' said Richard Baum, an analyst at Credit Suisse First Boston. ''Retailers learn in the third quarter what works. But if you don't have a lot working for you, it is hard to plan for the holidays.''</p>
        <p>There was clearly plenty of bad news from the August sales numbers. The biggest stunner came Wednesday night from the normally efficient Gap Inc., which announced that its same-store sales would be down 14 percent for the month. And Wall Street analysts began lowering their earnings forecasts for major players as they missed sales growth estimates. For example, Jeffrey Feiner, an analyst with Lehman Brothers, lowered his third-quarter earnings estimates for Dillard's, May Department Stores, J. C. Penney and even the previously invincible Target.</p>
        <p>But as disappointing as sales at those chains were, there were still some bright spots. The merchants that did best were mostly those that sold goods besides clothing. Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company, for example, had a strong sales increase of 5.6 percent, largely on the strength of its home appliance and gardening businesses.</p>
        <p>It is also true that in a fiercely competitive environment, the strong continue to grow stronger. Wal-Mart Stores and Costco both continued to rack up gains at juggernaut paces in August. On the apparel side, Kohl's posted a 9.1 percent gain, and sales at the luxury retailer Neiman Marcus increased 8.1 percent.</p>
        <p>Beyond the bright spots, the economic picture was mixed enough that economists, analysts and retailers were split about how dire the forecast would be for the months ahead. The economy is certainly losing some of its heat after the Federal Reserve raised interest rates six times since June 1999. Higher gas and oil prices have also taken a toll. And after frenzied spending last year, consumers may be taking a breather, as Alan Greenspan, the Fed chairman, predicted they would in July.</p>
        <p>Unemployment, however, is low; wages are relatively high, and consumer confidence remains near all-time highs, according to the University of Michigan survey of consumers. Moreover, the Commerce Department reported this week that consumer spending on goods and services, everything from automobiles to restaurants, surged in July.</p>
        <p>''When one looks at the financial health of the consumer, income growth and employment trends,'' said Mr. Feiner of Lehman Brothers, ''one comes to the conclusion they still have the wherewithal. So the $64,000 question is, 'Are we going to see a rebound of sales?' You don't have enough evidence to bet either way.''</p>
        <p>Edward Yardeni, an economist with Deutsche Bank Securities, said: ''Christmas may turn out to be better than everyone thinks. We've got record optimism. When people are that confident about the future, they are likely to continue to spend.''</p>
        <p>Merchants themselves are showing a surprising reserve of optimism. ''The interesting thing is that a lot of the fall goods are selling,'' said Michael Gould, the chief executive of Bloomingdale's, which is owned by Federated Department Stores. ''There are a lot of people walking through our stores, and we are not pulling back on inventories.'' Sales at Federated increased only 1.1 percent for the month.</p>
        <p>Michael Weiss, president and chief executive of the Express division of the Limited, said he thought the key to survival in the coming holiday season would be to offer what Express thinks are crucial fashion items early on. For August, Express had a stellar 15 percent growth in sales, based on stretch, dirty denim and leather jeans for back-to-school.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
