<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOR CHILDREN</title>
    <meta content="01KIDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="SPARE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E1DE1730F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOR CHILDREN</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF MAYA THE BEE,'' told through rod and shadow puppets and a jazz score, is about a little bee who rejects toiling in the hive and flies off to pursue tastes more exotic than honey. Saturdays at 11 a.m. at the Salon Theater, 45 Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village. Tickets: $15; $7 for children. Reservations: (212) 539-6644.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF MAYA THE BEE,'' told through rod and shadow puppets and a jazz score, is about a little bee who rejects toiling in the hive and flies off to pursue tastes more exotic than honey. Saturdays at 11 a.m. at the Salon Theater, 45 Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village. Tickets: $15; $7 for children. Reservations: (212) 539-6644.</p>
        <p>''HANSEL AND GRETEL,'' presented for the marionette stage by Puppetworks and Nicolas Coppola, artistic director, beginning Sunday and on Saturdays and Sundays at 12:30 and 2:30 p.m. (through Dec. 17) at Puppetworks-Park Slope, 338 Sixth Avenue, at Fourth Street, Brooklyn. For children 4 and older. Tickets: $7; $6 for children; $4.50 for groups of 20 or more. Reservations required. Information: (718) 965-3391.</p>
        <p>KINGS COUNTY SHAKESPEARE COMPANY'S FESTIVAL, through Sunday at Founders Hall Theater of St. Francis College, 182 Remsen Street, Brooklyn Heights. In repertory: Shakespeare's ''Midsummer Night's Dream'' (acted from the first Folio), tomorrow at 2 p.m., and ''The Rivals,'' Sheridan's comedy of manners, today and tomorrow at 8 p.m. and Sunday at 2 p.m. For children the highlight will be the preliminary performance at 7:15 p.m., ''Shakespeare's Clowns and Villains and Willie's Willful Women,'' featuring comic scenes from the plays, performed by the KCSC Young Company. Suggested donation: $5. Information: (718) 398-0546.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>''THE ADVENTURES OF ROCKY AND BULLWINKLE AND FRIENDS,'' selections from works by the television animator Jay Ward, through Sept. 17 at the Museum of Television and Radio, 25 West 52nd Street, Manhattan. Screenings are Tuesdays through Sundays at 12:15 p.m., with additional screenings Thursdays at 6 p.m. and Fridays at 7 p.m. Through Sunday, episodes include ''Wossamotta U,'' in which Bullwinkle wins a football scholarship and Boris tries to fix the big game. Admission: $6; students and the elderly, $4; ages 13 and under, $3. Information: (212) 621-6800.</p>
        <p>ANNUAL INTREPID TUGBOAT CHALLENGE, Sunday from 12:30 to 4 p.m. at the Intrepid Sea-Air-Space Museum, Pier 86, West 46th Street at the Hudson River, Clinton, with a parade of tugboats, a race, a spinach-eating contest, competitions and other activities. Sunday, noon to 3 p.m. All these events, which are on the Spectator's Barge outside, are free. For visitors who want to visit the museum or the Intrepid flight deck: $12; $6 for children 6 to 11; $2 for children 2 to 5; free for children under 2 and the military. Information: (212) 245-0072.</p>
        <p>CARIBBEAN CARNIVAL WEEKEND, at the Brooklyn Children's Museum, 145 Brooklyn Avenue, at St. Marks Place, Crown Heights, tomorrow and Sunday, with carnival costume-making workshops and the Kiddies Carnival Parade from the front steps of the museum (tomorrow from 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.); mask-making workshop and an exhibition of the museum's own collection of masks (Sunday from 1 to 2:30 p.m). While there, a last chance to see the exhibition ''Can You Tell Me How to Get to Sesame Street?'' Hours this weekend: today, noon to 5 p.m.; tomorrow and Sunday 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Suggested admission: $4. Information: (718) 735-4400.</p>
        <p>''BATTERY BOOKWORMS.'' The storyteller Cecilia Carson will narrate ''Frog Prince,'' ''Company's Coming'' and ''Jack and the Giant: A Story Full of Beans,'' tomorrow from 11 a.m. to 12:30 p.m. on the Grand Staircase at the Winter Garden, World Financial Center, West Street between Liberty and Vesey Streets, Lower Manhattan. Free. Information: (212) 945-2600.</p>
        <p>''EASTER PARADE,'' a 1948 musical comedy, presented by the Film Society of Lincoln Center as part of the Judy Garland film series, tomorrow and Sunday at 11 a.m. Walter Reade Theater, Lincoln Center. Tickets: $3. Information: (212) 875-5601.</p>
        <p>NEWSPAPERS AND NEWSBOYS, a workshop for youngsters to learn about printing and what is required in producing a newspaper, Sunday and Monday from 1 to 4 p.m. at the Children's Center, South Street Seaport Museum, 165 John Street, South and Fulton Streets, Lower Manhattan. $3 materials fee. Information: (212) 748-8758.</p>
        <p>WEST INDIAN AMERICAN DAY KIDDIES CARNIVAL, at St. John's Place and Kingston Avenues tomorrow at 10 a.m., ending at the Brooklyn Museum, at 200 Eastern Parkway, at Prospect Park, about 4 p.m. Beginning at 1 p.m., more than 25 masquerade bands, each featuring a children's band, will perform on a stage outside the museum. (On Sunday from 1 to 4 p.m., these children's stee-bands will perform in a competition.) Related activities include a ''Stay in School, Stay Off Drugs'' concert today from 1 to 4 p.m. with young artists and surprise guest appearances. Events culminate Labor Day with the annual West Indian Labor Day Carnival Parade, inspired by the pre-lenten carnivals of the Caribbean, beginning at 10 a.m. at Utica Avenue, and runs up Eastern Parkway. All children's shows and events are free. Information: (718) 625-1515.</p>
        <p>Exhibitions</p>
        <p>''INVESTIGATING WHERE WE LIVE,'' a summer program offered by the Municipal Art Society, 457 Madison Avenue, at 51st Street, exhibits the projects of 20 students, ages 12 to 16, from Hamilton Heights and from Long Island City, Queens. The students focus on the architecture, history and urban design of their neighborhoods through photography and journal writing. The results will be on display through Sept. 9. Hours: daily, except Thursdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free. Information: (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>''ANIMALS AS ARCHITECTS,'' an interactive exhibition at the Staten Island Children's Museum, Snug Harbor Cultural Center, 1000 Richmond Terrace, Livingston, featuring a home with walls of recyclable material and another with a secret tunnel, demonstrating that animals are concerned with human interests like energy efficiency and comfort. Youngsters are invited to open compartments in the model dwellings to find hidden nests and examine building materials and tiny tenants with microscopes. Today, noon to 5 p.m. Admission: $4; under 2 and members, free. Information: (718) 273-2060.</p>
        <p>''FROM TENT TO TEMPLE: LIFE IN THE ANCIENT NEAR EAST,'' an interactive exhibition (through Jan. 14) developed by the Jewish Children's Learning Lab, Center for Jewish History, Yeshiva University Museum, 15 West 16th Street, Chelsea, (212) 294-8330, showing the daily lives of people in Biblical times, featuring 28 interactive learning stations. In more than 30 displays, the exhibition challenges children to solve problems the way their biblical ancestors did, building a miniature plow, grinding grain with stones, constructing a hearth or even hunting game -- images of it, that is -- with bows and arrows ending in suction cups. Hours: Mondays, Wednesdays and Sundays, 11 a.m. to 5 p.m.; Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 8 p.m. Free with admission: $6; the elderly and ages 5 to 12, $4; under 5 and members, free.</p>
        <p>THE INVENTOR CENTER, the Children's Museum of Manhattan, Tisch Building, 212 West 83rd Street. Recent products from the next generation of inventors: a car with helicopter blades, a mechanical glove that contains school supplies and a Duck-a-Phone, which quacks instead of rings. Filled with 10 computer work stations, the center is a high-tech idea laboratory in which children use software developed by the museum to realize their wildest dreams. Each hourlong workshop is limited to children 6 and older accompanied by adults. The center offers six workshops a day; registration is required. The museum will provide everything needed, except, of course, imagination. Museum hours through Labor Day: Today Monday, 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. The museum will close Tuesday until Sept. 18 with new hours. Free with museum admission: $6; infants under 1, free. Information: (212) 721-1234.</p>
        <p>''PICKLES AND POMEGRANATES: JEWISH HOMES NEAR AND FAR,'' an exhibition consisting of two rooms: one representing a Lower East Side tenement in 1897, the other evoking a house of the same period in Persia (now Iran). Children can dress up in reproductions of period clothes and listen to recordings of Yiddish tales or Middle Eastern music. Through March 2001 at the Jewish Museum, 1109 Fifth Avenue, at 92nd Street, Manhattan. Hours: Sundays, Mondays, Wednesdays and Thursdays, 11 a.m. to 5:45 p.m.; Tuesdays, 11 A.M. to 8 p.m. Admission: $8; $5.50 for students and the elderly; free for children under 12 and pay what you wish for everyone Tuesdays after 5 p.m. Information: (212) 423-3200.</p>
        <p>''REPTILES: REAL AND ROBOTIC,'' including an alligator-snapping turtle 10 times life size and a Western diamondback rattlesnake 36 feet long, are part of the exhibition and related programs (through Sept. 17) at Science Playground at the New York Hall of Science, 47-01 111th Street, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens. Although those animals are robots, the real ones are no less impressive, including gila monsters, bearded dragons and blue-tongued skinks. Related activitites include demonstrations, crafts workshops and ''Reptiles Revealed'' shows each day in the hall at 1 and 3 p.m., and at noon and 2 p.m. Hours: Mondays through Wednesdays, 9:30 a.m. to 2 p.m.; Thursdays through Sundays, 9:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. Admission: $7.50; $5 for ages 4 to 17 and the elderly; free for ages 3 and under; free Thursdays and Fridays from 2 to 5 p.m. Information: (718) 699-0005.</p>
        <p>''SEUSS!'' An interactive exhibition featuring Dr. Seuss's characters, including the Cat in the Hat, through Monday at the Children's Museum of Manhattan, 212 West 83rd Street. Hours: 10 a.m. to 5 p.m. Free with museum admission: $6; infants under 1, free. Information: (212) 721-1234.</p>
        <p>SPARE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
