<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Times As Bookends For a Revue Of the Blues</title>
    <meta content="01BLUE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/arts/01BLUE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weber, Bruce</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">It Ain't Nothin' but the Blues (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7DD1530F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="788" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Times As Bookends For a Revue Of the Blues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weber, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bruce Weber reviews revue It Ain't Nothin' but the Blues, at B B King Theater; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Slimmed down and ever slick, the peripatetic musical revue ''It Ain't Nothin' but the Blues,'' a Tony-nominated musical in 1999, looks snug and comfortable in its new home in the well-appointed cabaret space at the B. B. King Blues Club and Grill on West 42nd Street. It has been on the road for a while, after closing at the Ambassador Theater on Broadway in January; you may remember the fuss in June 1999 when time constraints squeezed an excerpt from the show out of the CBS broadcast of the Tony Awards. It had previously been presented at the Vivian Beaumont Theater at Lincoln Center and at the New Victory Theater a few doors from where it is now.</p>
        <p>The show, which can be seen Sundays through Wednesdays, has been trimmed considerably, from nearly 50 songs to 24, and a supper-club-brisk 80 minutes, the songs yapping at one another's heels and the scripted patter neatly tucked into the crevices. The historical slide show on screens that frame the stage -- projected photographs of bluesmen, country churches, field workers and night-life city slickers, all documenting the blues migration from the Mississippi Delta to Chicago -- has necessarily been edited. And the stage is hardly Broadway size; the six singers, who spend most of the show seated in a line in front of a five-man band, barely have room for a collective booty shake. The interaction among the singers suffers a bit, the bawdy undercurrent of the blues attenuated to a mostly eye-batting flirtation, but then, with the performers in stylish uptown evening clothes, this is hardly a show that belongs in a roadhouse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Slimmed down and ever slick, the peripatetic musical revue ''It Ain't Nothin' but the Blues,'' a Tony-nominated musical in 1999, looks snug and comfortable in its new home in the well-appointed cabaret space at the B. B. King Blues Club and Grill on West 42nd Street. It has been on the road for a while, after closing at the Ambassador Theater on Broadway in January; you may remember the fuss in June 1999 when time constraints squeezed an excerpt from the show out of the CBS broadcast of the Tony Awards. It had previously been presented at the Vivian Beaumont Theater at Lincoln Center and at the New Victory Theater a few doors from where it is now.</p>
        <p>The show, which can be seen Sundays through Wednesdays, has been trimmed considerably, from nearly 50 songs to 24, and a supper-club-brisk 80 minutes, the songs yapping at one another's heels and the scripted patter neatly tucked into the crevices. The historical slide show on screens that frame the stage -- projected photographs of bluesmen, country churches, field workers and night-life city slickers, all documenting the blues migration from the Mississippi Delta to Chicago -- has necessarily been edited. And the stage is hardly Broadway size; the six singers, who spend most of the show seated in a line in front of a five-man band, barely have room for a collective booty shake. The interaction among the singers suffers a bit, the bawdy undercurrent of the blues attenuated to a mostly eye-batting flirtation, but then, with the performers in stylish uptown evening clothes, this is hardly a show that belongs in a roadhouse.</p>
        <p>Its strength is in its high spirits and the marvelous voices on display. These are the happiest blues singers you'll ever see, and it's a thematic message that the show begins and ends with ''Let the Good Times Roll.'' Three singers from the original New York production, Mississippi Charles Bevel, Carter Calvert and Gregory Porter, are joined by Debra Laws (whose sister Eloise was an original company member), Cheryl Alexander and Michael Mandell, and each brings a full throat and a flawless sense of pitch to standards like Willie Dixon's ''I'm Your Hoochie Coochie Man'' (Mr. Mandell), Jay Hawkins's ''I Put a Spell on You'' (Ms. Laws) and Don Gibson's soulful country ballad ''I Can't Stop Lovin' You'' (Mr. Bevel).</p>
        <p>The band, under the direction of Jim Ehinger, is as tight as can be. There's not a note out of place, nor is there a single extended instrumental solo, and that's signal enough of what blues fans may find missing here. Show-biz values keep the pace brisk and cheerful, the performers on a strict leash. The singers most often play to the audience, and more than occasionally the gut feel of the blues, which at its most authentic finds its mordant joy in the expression of pain, is missing a personal touch.</p>
        <p>At one point Mr. Bevel, invoking his home-state heritage, begins a traditional solo version of Leadbelly's great, simple and heartbreaking lullaby, ''Good Night, Irene,'' only to be interrupted by Mr. Porter, who asks if he might funk it up a bit. ''Put a stank on it,'' Mr. Porter urges, at which point the band joins in and the song is rendered as an undistinguished rhythm-and-blues number. On the other hand, when Ms. Calvert, recalling but not mimicking Patsy Cline, renders a slow and searing rendition of Don Hecht and Alan Block's ''Walkin' After Midnight,'' the show gets a raggedy wrench of real feeling.</p>
        <p>That's what it could use more of. Still, if there's a blues lite feel to the evening, there's something appropriate about it. It isn't sanitary, exactly, but sanitized and welcoming, a fitting blues for the new Times Square.</p>
        <p>IT AIN'T NOTHIN' BUT THE BLUES</p>
        <p>By Charles Bevel, Lita Gaithers, Randal Myler, Ron Taylor and Dan Wheetman, based on an original idea by Mr. Taylor; directed by Mr. Myler; musical direction, Jim Ehinger; vocal direction, Ms. Gaithers; general management, EKTM: Eric Krebs/Jonathan Shulman; associate producer, Mr. Taylor; production stage manager, Doug Hosney; costumes by Enid Turnbull. Presented by Mr. Krebs. At the B. B King Blues Club and Grill, 243 West 42nd Street, Clinton.</p>
        <p>WITH: Cheryl Alexander, Mississippi Charles Bevel, Carter Calvert, Debra Laws, Michael Mandell and Gregory Porter.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
