<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; Laborers Anonymous</title>
    <meta content="01COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/opinion/01COLL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226790"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Joseph I (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6DA1530F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; Laborers Anonymous</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed column on which presidential candidate better understands ordinary working stiffs; notes that both Democrats are poor, but also career politicians who have held office almost since puberty; recalls that George W Bush, about as successful at driling oil wells as Al Gore is at investing, got wealthy friends to help him buy Texas Rangers, while Dick Cheney's ability to fish and shoot his way to serious money should be inspiration to all careerists (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The service economy has created some strange and wonderful forms of employment. A friend of mine once went to a party in Los Angeles where the host had covered one room with fuzzy shag carpet -- floor, walls and ceiling -- and hired a man whose sole job was to fluff up the nap whenever it got matted. ''Survivor'' drove home the lesson that farmers and truck drivers are no match for people with titles like ''corporate trainer'' or ''whitewater rafter.'' At the Democratic convention, thanks to the presence of Christie Brinkley in the New York delegation, we were alerted for the first time to the existence of a career path known as ''model/activist.''</p>
        <p>Until recently, America chose its presidents pretty exclusively from the national pool of lawyers and generals. But lately the candidates' backgrounds have gotten more varied.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The service economy has created some strange and wonderful forms of employment. A friend of mine once went to a party in Los Angeles where the host had covered one room with fuzzy shag carpet -- floor, walls and ceiling -- and hired a man whose sole job was to fluff up the nap whenever it got matted. ''Survivor'' drove home the lesson that farmers and truck drivers are no match for people with titles like ''corporate trainer'' or ''whitewater rafter.'' At the Democratic convention, thanks to the presence of Christie Brinkley in the New York delegation, we were alerted for the first time to the existence of a career path known as ''model/activist.''</p>
        <p>Until recently, America chose its presidents pretty exclusively from the national pool of lawyers and generals. But lately the candidates' backgrounds have gotten more varied.</p>
        <p>This year, of the Democrats and Republicans on the national tickets, only Joe Lieberman is a lawyer, and only Al Gore was ever a full-time soldier.</p>
        <p>It's never been clear how much voters care if a president's experience with the world of work in any way resembles their own. Do weary parents juggling two careers and child-rearing resent hearing about George W. Bush's afternoon naps? Would middle-aged professionals who are too humiliated to admit they don't know the difference between a money market and a mutual fund feel an affinity for Al Gore, who keeps his savings in a passbook account?</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Bush and his running mate, Dick Cheney, are rich men, while Mr. Gore and Mr. Lieberman are not. Economically speaking, Mr. Gore may actually be downwardly mobile. He says he doesn't buy stock  because it might look like a conflict of interest, and Fortune magazine, analyzing what passes for the Gore  portfolio, once suggested the vice president ''could be a financial dolt.''</p>
        <p>So which team better understands the working stiff? The Democratic candidates are less wealthy, but on the other hand, they're both career politicians who have held elective office practically since puberty. (Mr. Lieberman did have a two-year hiatus after he lost a House race in 1980, during which he worked as a lawyer and represented at least one client in the liquor industry who had issues before the Connecticut state legislature. The senator's staff says this doesn't mean he used to be a lobbyist, but the experience probably gave Mr. Lieberman a certain sympathy for the trials of a carpet-fluffer. )</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, who was about as successful at drilling oil wells as Mr. Gore is in investing, struck it rich when he persuaded a group of wealthy associates to help him buy the Texas Rangers and then persuaded the town of Arlington to build said team a new stadium. Mr. Bush's own $600,000 investment thus became $14.9 million when the franchise was sold. The work he performed as the managing general partner included encouraging team spirit, and reportedly involved a lot of autograph-signing. This may not have given him much in common with the nation's stevedores, but Ms. Brinkley and the other model/activists of the world undoubtedly know what he's been through.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney spent most of his career in government, but the arrival of the Clinton administration left him cooling his heels at a conservative think tank. Happily, in 1995 he went salmon fishing with Thomas Cruikshank, chairman of the Halliburton Company, a huge energy services business, who liked Mr. Cheney so much he recommended him as his successor, at a salary of more than $1 million a year and oodles of stock options. During his tenure there, the future vice-presidential candidate's  big coup was a merger with the company's chief rival, Dresser Industries, whose chief executive Mr. Cheney won over during a quail hunt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's ability to fish and shoot his way to serious money should be an inspiration to all careerists who worry that an inability to play golf is standing between them and success. Sure, there were some failures at Halliburton, including the time his company was banned from bidding on road construction contracts by the state of North Carolina. But they might provide a much-needed humanizing touch. We've all had our little career setbacks. Getting tossed out of North Carolina might not be one of them, but the concept is there.</p>
        <p>Happy Labor Day weekend. Buy a steelworker a drink.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
