<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Approves New Attack Ad Mocking Gore</title>
    <meta content="01BUSH$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/national/01bush.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2DC1230F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Approves New Attack Ad Mocking Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>LOUISVILLE, Ky., Aug. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George W Bush's presidential campaign, after struggling for weeks to seize offensive from Al Gore, approves sharp attack commercial that strikes at Gore's character and mocks his appearance at fund-raising event at Buddhist temple in 1996; 30-second ad paid for by Republican National Committee will air in 16 states; photos; Bush canceled similar ad earlier; Gore responds by scaling back focus on patient bill of rights, to keep attention on ad that his campaign believes will backfire; Democrats charge Bush is breaking own promise not to engage in personal, negative attacks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After struggling for a week to seize the offensive from Vice President Al Gore, aides to Gov. George W. Bush said today that they had approved a new and sharp attack commercial that strikes directly at Mr. Gore's character and mocks his appearance at a fund-raising event at a Buddhist temple four years ago.</p>
        <p>The 30-second spot, paid for by the Republican National Committee, will go on the air on Friday in 16 states, and comes just a week after Mr. Bush personally blocked another commercial sponsored by the party that also questioned Mr. Gore's truthfulness. The move exposed rifts within the Republican camp over how to attack Mr. Gore without violating Mr. Bush's vow to keep his campaign positive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After struggling for a week to seize the offensive from Vice President Al Gore, aides to Gov. George W. Bush said today that they had approved a new and sharp attack commercial that strikes directly at Mr. Gore's character and mocks his appearance at a fund-raising event at a Buddhist temple four years ago.</p>
        <p>The 30-second spot, paid for by the Republican National Committee, will go on the air on Friday in 16 states, and comes just a week after Mr. Bush personally blocked another commercial sponsored by the party that also questioned Mr. Gore's truthfulness. The move exposed rifts within the Republican camp over how to attack Mr. Gore without violating Mr. Bush's vow to keep his campaign positive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides said they had wholeheartedly approved the contents and tone of the new spot, which they described as ''tongue-in-cheek.'' They said it was a response to critical advertisements run by the Democrats against Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The commercial shows a television set on a kitchen counter with Mr. Gore on the screen and an unseen woman complaining that the vice president is ''reinventing himself on television again.'' At one point the commercial shows a picture of Mr. Gore at the Buddhist temple event in 1996 and another segment shows him saying, ''I took the initiative in creating the Internet.'' At that point, the narrator says, ''Yeah, and I invented the remote control.''</p>
        <p>Predictably, the commercial sparked accusations and counteraccusations between the two campaigns over which one had ''gone negative'' first. Mr. Gore's camp wasted no time responding to the commercial, which was widely shown on television news programs and on the Internet during the day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore also scaled back plans to focus on a patients' bill of rights in the belief that the Republican advertisement would backfire and that the Democrats should not create news that would distract public attention from it.</p>
        <p>The new commercial is part of a broader, coordinated effort by the Republicans to raise doubts about Mr. Gore's ethics and integrity, which the Bush campaign clearly views as the vice president's greatest vulnerability.</p>
        <p>All this week, Mr. Bush has criticized Mr. Gore as being a weak leader who broke promises made during the 1992 campaign to cut taxes and expand prescription drug coverage. And today, in a speech at a high school in Holland, Ohio, Mr. Bush accused Mr. Gore of using ''empty rhetoric'' that had disillusioned young people.</p>
        <p>But this more aggressive strategy also comes at the end of a two-week period in which Mr. Gore, clearly enjoying a postconvention bounce in the polls, has forced Mr. Bush to defend himself on issues like tax cuts, prescription drug prices and when the candidates would be debating. Since the Democratic National Convention last month, Mr. Gore has pulled even with Mr. Bush in many national polls, and is even ahead in some swing states where he had previously trailed.</p>
        <p>For that reason, Democrats asserted today that Mr. Bush was turning negative in an effort to stanch weakening poll numbers and reinvigorate a lackluster campaign. They also accused Mr. Bush of hypocrisy, citing his pledge at the Republican National Convention in early August ''to change the tone of Washington to one of civility and respect.''</p>
        <p>Douglas Hattaway, a spokesman for the Gore campaign, said Mr. Bush had ''broken his own promise not to engage in personal, negative attacks.''</p>
        <p>''We've seen this from Bush before, in the primaries,'' Mr. Hattaway added. ''When his back was against the wall, he went negative on John McCain. Now he's talked out of both sides of his mouth about changing the tone of the debate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides have said they had every intention of endorsing commercials that raised questions about Mr. Gore's ethics. But the content of such advertisements has been a subject of debate among Mr. Bush's top advisers and among Republican officials.</p>
        <p>While campaign officials said they viewed questions about Mr. Gore's credibility as an important part of their message, they have also been mindful of their candidate's pledge to run a positive campaign.</p>
        <p>Just this afternoon, as the Republican Party was releasing the new commercial, Mr. Bush was telling a boisterous audience at a high school here that ''politics doesn't have to be ugly and mean.''</p>
        <p>Strategists in the Bush campaign and in the Republican Party have said that the best way to deliver a tough advertisement questioning Mr. Gore's ethics was to use humor, so as to avoid appearing mean-spirited.</p>
        <p>''It's a good-natured way of making a very important point,'' Karen P. Hughes, Mr. Bush's director of communications, said of the new Republican spot. ''That is: the gaping credibility gap between what Vice President Gore says and what Vice President Gore does.''</p>
        <p>Political analysts were divided about whether the honey-thick sarcasm of the advertisement would help soften its negative message, or turn voters off. Ken Goldstein of the University of Wisconsin, who analyzes political advertisements, argued that a lighter touch could make a negative message more palatable.</p>
        <p>''This ad gets at what Al Gore's weaknesses are, but it doesn't do it in what I think some people would consider an unfair way,'' Mr. Goldstein said on Political Points, a joint Webcast of ABC News and the New York Times.</p>
        <p>But Bill Carrick, a Democratic consultant, said the commercial would undermine what has been one of Mr. Bush's prime selling points: his genial personality.</p>
        <p>''The guy's biggest asset is his sunny, hopeful presentation of himself,'' Mr. Carrick said. ''Since the Democratic convention, the Bush people have been trying to become the very mean-spirited Republicans they have been trying to run away from.''</p>
        <p>In the spot, titled ''Really,'' a woman can be heard commenting on various television images of Mr. Gore.  Mr. Gore is then shown standing beside Buddhist monks at the Hsi Lai Temple near Los Angeles in 1996. Mr. Gore contends he did not know the luncheon was a fund-raiser. But two Democratic fund-raisers were later found guilty for their roles in soliciting illegal campaign contributions from people, including monks, who attended the event.</p>
        <p>The woman narrator then says: ''Who's he going to be today? The Al Gore who raises campaign money at a Buddhist temple? Or the one who promises campaign finance reform?''</p>
        <p>The spot will start running on Friday in closely contested states, including Arkansas, Michigan, Missouri, Ohio, Pennsylvania and Wisconsin. Similar information will be on a Web site that appears in the spot: gorewillsayanything.com.</p>
        <p>The Republican commercial that Mr. Bush ordered canceled last week featured excerpts from a six-year-old interview in which a stammering Mr. Gore said President Clinton had never lied in his political career.</p>
        <p>The commercial, which was never broadcast, suggests that Mr. Gore was refusing to acknowledge that Mr. Clinton had made deceptive remarks about his relationship with a White House intern. But the advertisement was actually based on an NBC News interview in which Mr. Gore was talking about his criticism of Oliver L. North, who was then a Senate candidate in Virginia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush later said he objected to the commercial because Mr. Gore's comments had been taken out of context and ''had nothing to do with the affairs of the White House.''</p>
        <p>The last two weeks have been difficult for Mr. Bush. Last week, Mr. Bush acknowledged that he needed to do a better job selling his proposed across-the-board income tax cut -- and then struggled to provide a coherent explanation of the plan.</p>
        <p>This week, Mr. Bush's aides had pledged he would stick to his education agenda. But almost every day, other issues have intruded to dilute his message.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Bush has been able to ratchet up his criticisms of Mr. Gore's character. In two rousing speeches today Mr. Bush laced time and again into Mr. Gore's character and credibility.</p>
        <p>''After seven and a half years of empty rhetoric, I can understand why the young of America become disillusioned,'' he told 3,000 students, parents and Republican partisans at a high school in Holland. ''It's time to put somebody in office who will do in office exactly what he tells the American people he intends to do. And that is what I'm going to do should I become the president of the United States.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
