<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets Say the Secondary Is No Longer a Sieve</title>
    <meta content="01JETS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/sports/01jets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226864"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Bay Packers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Favre, Brett</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Green Bay Packers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EEDD1230F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="829" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets Say the Secondary Is No Longer a Sieve</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Aug. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets' players comment on preparations for season opener against Green Bay Packers and their quarterback Brett Favre; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The grueling extended practices during the bye week may have left some of the Jets grumbling about the rigors of Camp Groh, but safety Victor Green was delighted with the results.</p>
        <p>After a surprisingly shaky preseason for the secondary -- it yielded a big play in each of the four games and gave up an average of 248 passing yards a game -- Green said he is comfortable with the unit that seemed to be the team's biggest concern entering the season opener Sunday against the Packers and their gunslinger quarterback, Brett Favre.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The grueling extended practices during the bye week may have left some of the Jets grumbling about the rigors of Camp Groh, but safety Victor Green was delighted with the results.</p>
        <p>After a surprisingly shaky preseason for the secondary -- it yielded a big play in each of the four games and gave up an average of 248 passing yards a game -- Green said he is comfortable with the unit that seemed to be the team's biggest concern entering the season opener Sunday against the Packers and their gunslinger quarterback, Brett Favre.</p>
        <p>''We helped ourselves a lot,'' Green said. ''It gave us a chance to come together collectively. It definitely got us better than we were in the four previous games. This is going to be a big week testing our defense. I feel 100 percent better than I did after the last preseason game. I don't think we were near where we needed to be. Having that bye week and being able to gel, going over things, I feel a lot better. We can be really good. At every position, we have guys who can wreck havoc.''</p>
        <p>The Giants torched the Jets' secondary for three passing touchdowns in their preseason game, and the Jets gave up six passing touchdowns in all. The problems are myriad. Cornerback Aaron Glenn missed a large part of training camp with a sprained ankle and did not play in the last two games. The rotation designed to select a starting free safety from a trio of backups -- Kevin Williams won the job -- meant a new face every few plays. Omar Stoutmire, who started five games last season, was so lackluster in his effort to retain the free safety spot that he was cut.</p>
        <p>Coach Al Groh has not elaborated on what he thought the trouble was beyond saying that he wanted to see the secondary perform more crisply. He attributed the improvement Green cited to using the extra week to concentrate on the regular-season game plan.</p>
        <p>But cornerback Marcus Coleman said there was miscommunication among the players that was addressed within the group.</p>
        <p>''Everything is patched up,'' Coleman said. ''Whatever misunderstandings we may have had have gotten settled. It's just like in everyday life. Things come up. You've got to fix them. It's like a family thing. Something is wrong with the family, you sit down and talk about it at the dinner table. We sat around the dinner table, talked about it and got it fixed.''</p>
        <p>With Favre expected to play despite missing three preseason games with elbow tendinitis, the pressure will be on the secondary to justify its confidence. It made the Packers backup Matt Hasselbeck look like Favre in their preseason meeting, allowing him to complete 11 of 15 passes for 162 yards and two touchdowns. Coleman, who emerged last season with a team-leading six interceptions and 24 passes defended, was victimized on one of the touchdowns by the rookie receiver Charles Lee, a seventh-round pick from Central Florida, who broke away from Coleman down the sideline for a 31-yard touchdown reception.</p>
        <p>''The things that happened were fundamentals and little mistakes,'' Williams said. ''That's what the preseason is for. We know we can't ease up on certain plays. I have not any less confidence in these guys. I know these are good guys we have.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Players voted quarterback VINNY TESTAVERDE and linebackers MO LEWIS and BRYAN COX the team's captains. . . . Receiver YATIL GREEN, a former Dolphins first-round draft pick, is happy to have landed on the Jets' practice squad, given his history of season-ending injuries. Green said he hopes his stay on the practice squad is brief. ''I felt like the best opportunity was coming back here,'' Green said. ''I don't have any complaints. With my knees, now that the regular season is here and we don't practice as much, I can get my legs back.'' . . . AL GROH says the hostile atmosphere of Lambeau Field, where the Packers are 53-8 over the last seven seasons, provides the Jets with a unique opportunity. ''For a team to have to go in there and under those kinds of circumstances against a quality opponent, it has the potential to be more than a game,'' Groh said. ''It has the potential to pull a team together. To go into some place that's not a sellout, not a traditional opponent, would not have the potential to do that to a team. I hope we bring that potential to fruition.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
