<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despondent Parents See Foster Care as Only Option</title>
    <meta content="01FOST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/nyregion/01FOST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foster Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3DD1230F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1652" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despondent Parents See Foster Care as Only Option</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Every day, dozens of parents in New York City seek voluntary foster placements of their children, unable to care for their children for variety of reasons; children's lawyers estimate that voluntary placements make up 10 to 20 percent of city's total foster care caseload; lawyers and social workers who work on these cases say adolescents, especially disobedient and emotionally disturbed, make up significant and growing share of voluntary placements (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Filled with a mixture of dread and relief one summer morning two years ago, Yahya Abdul-Hakam, an unemployed father of two, did what many fathers would find unthinkable: he turned his eldest daughter, then 11 years old, over to the city's foster care system.</p>
        <p>Today, reluctantly recalling that moment, he says he had no choice. For several years, his daughter had been acting out at school, throwing things, screaming in class. At home, her angry outbursts resulted in fights with a younger sister, a cousin, sometimes even with him. Mr. Abdul-Hakam even admitted her to a psychiatric hospital once.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Filled with a mixture of dread and relief one summer morning two years ago, Yahya Abdul-Hakam, an unemployed father of two, did what many fathers would find unthinkable: he turned his eldest daughter, then 11 years old, over to the city's foster care system.</p>
        <p>Today, reluctantly recalling that moment, he says he had no choice. For several years, his daughter had been acting out at school, throwing things, screaming in class. At home, her angry outbursts resulted in fights with a younger sister, a cousin, sometimes even with him. Mr. Abdul-Hakam even admitted her to a psychiatric hospital once.</p>
        <p>The morning he took her to the Lower Manhattan offices of the city's Administration for Children's Services, a tangle of emotions raced through him. ''Fear, uneasiness, nervousness,'' he recounted. ''It really came to a point where that was the only thing I could do.''</p>
        <p>Extreme as his action may seem, Mr. Abdul-Hakam's sense of frustration is shared by parents throughout the city. The range of options available to the privileged -- military-style private schools, private psychiatric treatment -- are not readily available to poor parents like him.</p>
        <p>So instead, every day, dozens of them stream into a sixth-floor courtroom in Manhattan Family Court designated for these so-called voluntary placements citywide.</p>
        <p>There is the father who quickly wearied of caring for his teenage son after the boy's mother died. There is the father who sent his daughter into foster care after a series of violent outbursts. There is the mother who initially sought court-ordered supervision for her misbehaving daughter, and when that did not work, signed her over to the city.</p>
        <p>The other day, M. Jay Segal, the court referee hearing that case, turned to the girl's mother. ''Ma'am, you don't want to take her home?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Without a glance at her daughter, the woman shook her head. ''She's going to run around,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The girl, told she had no place to go other than back to her group home, sat in court, sobbing uncontrollably.</p>
        <p>Citywide, just as involuntary admissions to foster care have declined in recent years, so have the number of voluntary placements. But the share of voluntarily placed youngsters among all children admitted to foster care has inched up slightly. One in 10 children admitted to foster care in the 1999 fiscal year were voluntarily placed, according to city figures. Children's lawyers estimate that voluntary placements make up 10 to 20 percent of the city's total foster care caseload.</p>
        <p>Although hard numbers are not available, lawyers and social workers who work on these cases say adolescents, especially the disobedient and the emotionally disturbed, make up a significant and growing share of voluntary placements.</p>
        <p>For some youngsters, a life in foster care can be a road to further decline. For others, especially those who need round-the-clock attention, it can be better than being at home. Either way, it exposes the peculiar predicament of overwhelmed parents who relinquish their children to an equally overwhelmed government bureaucracy -- one that is hardly equipped to care for, let alone rehabilitate, troubled teenagers.</p>
        <p>Why would a parent voluntarily turn a child over to foster care? Sometimes, a parent or guardian is ill, homeless or incarcerated. Sometimes, child welfare officials offer voluntary placement as an alternative to filing abuse or neglect charges against the parents.</p>
        <p>Occasionally, a parent simply wants to be done with a difficult child. Often, for parents under pressure, the child welfare system is the only way out.</p>
        <p>''For parents who don't have a support system or the economic means to purchase a support system -- like after-school activities, summer camps -- the stresses are exacerbated,'' said Karen Freedman, executive director of Lawyers for Children, a nonprofit group that provides lawyers and social services for children who are voluntarily placed. ''A lot of what these parents are feeling is fear for their children.''</p>
        <p>In Family Court, where despair competes daily with heartbreak, voluntary placement cases are among the saddest and most confounding. The adolescents are likely to end up in group homes rather than with foster families. If they need psychiatric care, the wait for a state-financed residential treatment center can sometimes be many months. Often, the youngsters simply run away from a group home, or wait until they become adults and leave the system.</p>
        <p>Occasionally, social workers and advocates for children successfully persuade parents not to relinquish the children.</p>
        <p>Margaret O'Marra, a Legal Aid social worker, says many of the children have suffered loss and trauma in early childhood. Others live with attention deficit disorder, depression or learning disabilities. ''A good percentage of these kids are kids who have not gotten proper treatment in time,'' Ms. O'Marra said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abdul-Hakam's daughter was relatively lucky in that she was placed with foster parents, four families in two years. Mr. Abdul-Hakam wants her back home, he says, but not now. He wants first to move out of the one-bedroom Brooklyn apartment he shares with his wife and younger daughter, though for now, that seems out of reach.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abdul-Hakam, 49, supports his family on public assistance, he says, cleaning a beach in Queens three days a week for his welfare check. And though his relationship with his daughter has improved in the last two years, he remains out of touch with the ordinary details of her life. He is not sure which school she will attend this month. He is not sure of the mental health diagnosis that has been made, nor of the name of the medications she has been taking. When and whether she will return home remains a mystery.</p>
        <p>Lawyers who represent children like her say they tend to stay in care longer than others. Marta, a 15-year-old who had been shuttled among a series of caretakers before she landed in foster care last year, is no exception. When her mother was arrested on drug charges, Marta, who spoke on the condition that only her first name be used, was sent to her grandmother in Puerto Rico. When she started rebelling, she was returned to her father in New York. Father and daughter were virtual strangers, she said. Marta's grades slid. She did not finish the eighth grade. She ran the streets.</p>
        <p>That, she said, is when the beatings began. Her father beat her for bad grades and for not cleaning her room. When she reported it to her favorite teacher and the child welfare agency was summoned, her father, who did not return calls requesting comment, was offered the option of voluntarily placing Marta in foster care. Marta did not object.</p>
        <p>What followed was a foster home in Yonkers, group homes in Brooklyn and Westchester, and finally, a residential treatment center upstate, where she still lives.</p>
        <p>She now sounds almost sympathetic to her father. She misses him, but knows he is not ready to take her back. ''I know why he wanted me here -- he wanted the best for me,'' she said. ''He wasn't doing it for his best. He was doing it for my best.''</p>
        <p>Now 15, Marta would prefer to remain in foster care until her 18th birthday because, as she puts it, she would like to give her father a break. He works, goes to school, cares for three stepchildren. ''He got a lot of things to do,'' Marta said. ''I really want to give him some time.''</p>
        <p>Fear, more than frustration, led Jose Vasquez to sign his daughter over to foster care earlier this year. In fits of rage, his daughter, Tania, would bang her fists on a school desk. She bit classmates, and once even a police officer. Last December, he admitted her to a psychiatric hospital. Then, afraid that the city would take her away after another outburst, Mr. Vasquez said, he agreed to sign her over to foster care. He thought it would be brief, he said, long enough for her to be evaluated.</p>
        <p>What made that action all the more incongruous was Mr. Vasquez's record as a father. Five years ago, after neglect charges were filed against the mother of his two children, he fought for custody, taking the children out of foster care. He shuttled them, both mentally retarded, between school, doctor appointments and Medicaid offices almost daily. He lost his job as a carpenter. He held onto them even as they lived in a room in a seedy residential hotel, which was all he could afford.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. Vasquez appeared in court in a desperate bid to get his daughter back. Tania, now 13 and with a mood disorder and borderline intelligence, has spent the last four months in the Kings County Psychiatric Hospital. She has been on Depakote, an anticonvulsant prescribed for epileptics and people with behavioral disorders. And on his recent visits, Mr. Vasquez said, Tania seemed calmer, eager to come home. But his heart broke, he said, when he saw that her hands were shaking uncontrollably. (Depakote is known to cause tremors.)</p>
        <p>''When I saw her shaking like that, I started crying myself,'' he said, as his son, Jose Jr., born with fetal alcohol syndrome, played quietly outside the courtroom. ''I thought she was going to come out all right. I thought by this time, she'd be back home again.''</p>
        <p>Taking Tania home will be no easy feat. Yet Mr. Vasquez is determined to do so. To make her more comfortable, he has asked his girlfriend and their 8-month-old baby to move out of their Bronx apartment.</p>
        <p>But if Tania slips into violent outbursts again, how does he know he will be able to handle her?</p>
        <p>''Because I'm her father,'' Mr. Vasquez said, unable to hold back tears. ''I wouldn't like for her to be away forever. I would like to try. She doesn't belong over there. She belongs over here.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
