<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Nomads, the Inuit Find a Settled Life Unsettling</title>
    <meta content="Y01CAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/01/world/01CANA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1226814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inuit Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nunavut (Canada)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barnabas, Levi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arvaluk, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Yukon, the Northwest Territories and Nunavut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E5D81530F932A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Nomads, the Inuit Find a Settled Life Unsettling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>IQALUIT, Nunavut, Aug. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canada's Inuit in new northern territory of Nunavut are having rocky cultural transition from nomadic existence to modern, sedentary life of snowmobiles, heated homes and satellite television; map; one price is Canada's highest rate of violent crime, particularly violence against women; Levi Barnabas, former speaker of legislature, has been convicted of sexual assault, and education minister James Arvaluk is charged with assaulting woman (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this brand new territory, where new government buildings rise on nameless muddy streets, people had barely learned that the former speaker of the legislature had been convicted of sexual assault when they heard today that their education minister had been charged with beating up a woman.</p>
        <p>This dual attack on the pride of this 17-month-old territory seemed to highlight the rocky cultural transition of the Inuit, who compose 85 percent of Nunavut's 27,000 residents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In this brand new territory, where new government buildings rise on nameless muddy streets, people had barely learned that the former speaker of the legislature had been convicted of sexual assault when they heard today that their education minister had been charged with beating up a woman.</p>
        <p>This dual attack on the pride of this 17-month-old territory seemed to highlight the rocky cultural transition of the Inuit, who compose 85 percent of Nunavut's 27,000 residents.</p>
        <p>Telescoping centuries of sociological change into two generations, the Inuit, known as Eskimos in Alaska and Greenland, have moved from the life of nomadic hunters who survived for centuries in one of the world's harshest environments to a modern, sedentary life marked by snowmobiles, heated homes and satellite television.</p>
        <p>One price for this wrenching change has been Canada's highest rate of violent crime, with one attack reported each year for every 19 residents. Last year Nunavut registered 204 sexual assaults, about 10 times the national per-capita average, and 1,115 assaults, nearly six times the national average.</p>
        <p>In the past, when attacks on women were debated, callers to radio stations sometimes criticized women's shelters for interfering in traditional family life. Elders reminded listeners that in traditional Inuit society, a man was allowed to beat his wife if she lied to him, was unfaithful or talked too much.</p>
        <p>''Men would call in and say, 'The shelters are ruining my marriage,' '' said the wife of a territorial minister. ''Older women would say: 'I was beaten. If we talk too much, we are beaten.' ''</p>
        <p>But now younger Inuit, separated by a generation or more from the harsh life of surviving in a wilderness of snow and ice, are saying Inuit should adapt their relations to their new lives in houses and villages.</p>
        <p>''We as an Inuit nation need to sit down and reflect,'' said Simona Arnatsiaq, women's program coordinator of the Qikiqtani Inuit Association. ''There has been so much change in 50 years. We used to live as families in camps. Now we live in settled communities. We have to discuss getting along in large groups.''</p>
        <p>Across this vast territory, three times the size of Texas, alcoholism, high unemployment and crowded housing contribute to high rates of sexual assault. Noting that there are two people per room in the territory, twice the national average, Ann Roberts, the chief medical officer, said, ''With the drinking, the ennui, the crowded housing stock -- this is the recipe for sexual assault.''</p>
        <p>For territorial legislators, who have some of the highest-paying jobs in the Arctic, the problem may stem from alcohol mixed with domineering attitudes about women. But even with two members now charged in cases of violence against women, there has been mostly silence from the 19-member Legislative Assembly, 18 of whom are men. Although women across Nunavut have started signing protest petitions, there has been little public reaction from Peter Kattuck, the minister responsible for the status of women.</p>
        <p>From Rankin Inlet, Nunavut's second-largest town, Evelyn Thordarson, director of the women's shelter, said of members of the Assembly,  ''When you go, you take an oath to serve the people, not to harm the people, not to break the law.''</p>
        <p>Last March, in the first blow to the Assembly, the police arrested Levi Barnabas, the 36-year-old speaker, and charged him with sexual assault. According to the police, Mr. Barnabas, after a night of heavy drinking, tried to have sex with a friend's wife at a house here. The woman resisted and woke up her husband, who chased the legislator into the street, hitting him three times with a baseball bat.</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Mr. Barnabas was found guilty and received a one-year jail sentence, which was suspended on the condition that he pay $1,000 to the women's shelter here, perform 240 hours of community service and stay out of Iqaluit's two bars for six months.</p>
        <p>Under pressure from the Assembly's leaders, Mr. Barnabas resigned his seat. But the politician, who has represented Canada's northernmost Arctic villages for the last five years, before and after the creation of Nunavut, soon announced that constituents were urging him to run in the special election for his seat.</p>
        <p>''With the Levi Barnabas case, people are seeing this and asking: 'What is the point of bringing charges? He only got community hours,' '' Ms. Thordason said.</p>
        <p>Newspaper editorialists say the Assembly, through its silence, is sending out a message of male impunity. ''The male-dominated legislature has been strangely silent over the issue,'' News North Nunavut, a weekly, wrote in an editorial Monday. ''The government had a golden opportunity to take a stand against violence directed at women. Their silence trivialized the severity of Barnabas's crime.''</p>
        <p>But this week's case may make addressing the issue of violence against women unavoidable.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Royal Canadian Mounted Police officers arrested James Arvaluk, 52, the education minister, and charged him with assault. The police say the victim was a woman at his home in Coral Harbor, about 435 miles west of here.</p>
        <p>In 1995, when Mr. Arvaluk represented that area in the legislature of the Northwest Territories, he spent time in jail after being convicted of two charges of sexual assault.</p>
        <p>''People were having trouble with him as minister of education with the sexual assault conviction,'' said the wife of another minister. ''Now this charge involves bringing booze into a dry community.''</p>
        <p>When the Legislative Assembly resumes session in mid-October, Ms. Arnatsiaq said, the first order of business should be to set an example by adopting a code of ethics and a policy of zero tolerance among members for assaults on women.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
