<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Placing Hopes In the Net; Indonesia Entrepreneur Tries To Redeem Business Dynasty</title>
    <meta content="Y02CYB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000509T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Astra International</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PT CyberCity Indonesia</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Wayne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suriadjaya, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Suriadjaya, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EFDE1339F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Placing Hopes In the Net; Indonesia Entrepreneur Tries To Redeem Business Dynasty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WAYNE ARNOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Wayne</byline>
      <dateline>JAKARTA, Indonesia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indonesian entrepreneur Edward Suriadjaya has returned to corporate stage as high-technology entrepreneur planning to build stable of dot-coms and turn Jakarta's old airport into Indonesia's Silicon Valley; Suriadjaya is famous as scion who broke his family's bank and cost his family the car company his father, William, founded in 1957, Astra International; Suriadjaya wants to prove at last that he was unwitting pawn of politics and to help restore his family's position; Suriadjaya's vehicle is PT CyberCity Indonesia, holding company; business experts are split over whether Indonesia, which is far behind much of Asia, presents fertile opportunity or fool's mission; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>South of a park called Dreamland on an abandoned airfield surrounded by slums, Edward Suriadjaya is testing the Internet's powers of redemption.</p>
        <p>In a country dominated by corporate dynasties, Mr. Suriadjaya is famous as the scion who broke his family's bank and cost his family the car company his father founded in 1957, Astra International.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>South of a park called Dreamland on an abandoned airfield surrounded by slums, Edward Suriadjaya is testing the Internet's powers of redemption.</p>
        <p>In a country dominated by corporate dynasties, Mr. Suriadjaya is famous as the scion who broke his family's bank and cost his family the car company his father founded in 1957, Astra International.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Suriadjaya (pronounced sir-ya-JAI-ah) has returned to the corporate stage as a high-technology entrepreneur planning to build a stable of dot-coms and turn Jakarta's old airport into Indonesia's Silicon Valley. In the process, he wants not only to resurrect a fallow property investment but also to prove at last that he was an unwitting pawn of politics and to help restore his family's position.</p>
        <p>''I'm putting my future at stake,'' he said in a recent interview. ''I believe that information technology, as an enabler for the Indonesian nation, is in line with the development of technology in the world and has a very good future.''</p>
        <p>His vehicle is PT CyberCity Indonesia, a holding company with what he calls a ''bag of goodies'' he hopes will attract $76.5 million in new investments with a stock offering set for year-end. Inside the bag are stakes in an Internet service, two Web portals, an incubator for Net-related businesses, a multimedia academy and a 7.5-acre sliver of a 109-acre piece of overgrown airport that he hopes to turn into a high-technology commercial and residential sanctuary.</p>
        <p>''Clicks and bricks,'' Mr. Suriadjaya intoned in his sonorous Indonesian drawl. He says he already has a heavy list of backers, including the governments of Indonesia, Malaysia and Japan as well as Microsoft.</p>
        <p>There is no shortage of naysayers. Many point to Mr. Suriadjaya's reputation. ''I'm always skeptical about whatever Edward does,'' said Manggi T. Habir, president of the credit-rating agency Pemeringkat Efek Indonesia.</p>
        <p>While the Suriadjayas' influence with Indonesia's new government has produced criticism, some skeptics wonder about Mr. Suriadjaya's high-technology connections. They question the seriousness of a project that despite claiming to have set up at least five different ventures, has yet to establish a corporate Web site. CyberCity, they say, is more about bailing out a $50 million project Mr. Suriadjaya was in charge of developing on the site of the old Kemayoran domestic airport before the colossal failure of the bank he ran, Bank Summa, in 1992.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suriadjaya is not the only Asian tycoon to become a pioneer of the new economy. Though brash unknowns have won many of America's new fortunes, the high-technology  start-up scene in Hong Kong, the Philippines, Malaysia and Thailand is dominated by the rich and powerful. Skeptics say it is a sign of how much buzz surrounds the Internet; in Asia, as elsewhere, there is nothing like an Internet play to give an old-economy stock a new shine. Others say it is a symptom of economies in which wealth is still tightly concentrated and local capital markets are developing too slowly to fuel the speedy growth of the new economy.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of entrepreneurs who want to start up but don't have resources,'' said Vasant Chatikavanij, executive vice president of Loxinfo, a Thai Internet service. ''They end up selling themselves cheap. They sell to companies like us.''</p>
        <p>Indonesia may seem an unlikely locale for dot-com mania. Most bankers and economists will not even discuss its Internet potential. This, after all, is a country with a government that still depends on the International Monetary Fund to make ends meet; a country where a personal computer costs nearly twice the average annual income. Only 4 of every 1,000 Indonesians use the Internet, according to the International Data Corporation, compared with 14 of every 1,000 Asians over all. Most people do not even have a phone.</p>
        <p>But analysts and Internet entrepreneurs like Mr. Suriadjaya say such statistics highlight the promise. Indonesia, the world's fourth-most-populous nation, already has more Internet users than Singapore, and millions of wealthy urban residents with money to spend online. New and cheaper ways of connecting to the Internet, like TV set-top boxes and mobile phones, they say, will quickly extend the Net to more of Indonesia's 200 million people.</p>
        <p>''There's a large market coming out of the crisis that has spending potential,'' said Jonathan Morris, 26, a Bostonian who dropped out of the Harvard Business School a year and a half ago to start Indonesia's most popular Web site, astaga.com.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suriadjaya, 51, comes to the Internet world with more business experience -- and, some say, more baggage. The eldest son of William Suriadjaya, a respected businessman who built Astra from a small importer of diesel generators into a $2.4 billion automotive giant, Edward Suriadjaya started out as a salesman at an Astra unit. He then ventured into finance, first with a bank in Germany and later a finance company in Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>In 1988, he bought a small Indonesian bank, renamed it Bank Summa and expanded rapidly through the Summa Group. By 1991, Bank Summa was among the country's largest private banks, with about $1 billion in assets, most in loans to Summa companies and much of that for property investments.</p>
        <p>One such investment was the $50 million Jakarta International Trade Fair Corporation, a joint venture of Mr. Suriadjaya's Griya Nusantara Pratama, the Indonesian State Secretariat, Jakarta's city government and a group of Japanese investors. The corporation was to develop 109 acres of the old Kemayoran airport, which had closed in 1985.</p>
        <p>But in mid-1990, Indonesia adopted a tight fiscal policy, and Summa's world began to unravel. The property market sank, and Bank Summa was faced with $303 million in losses in 1991. Mr. Suriadjaya's father moved in to bail out Summa, removing his son as chairman and pledging Astra shares against the bank's obligations. The more he struggled to prop up the bank, the lower Astra's share price sank and the deeper Bank Summa's hole grew. By late 1992, the central bank closed Summa amid a depositor run. To help meet the bank's $690 million in liabilities, the Suriadjayas relinquished virtually their entire 76 percent stake in Astra to several businessmen close to President Suharto.</p>
        <p>That is only half the story, according to a version of events that Mr. Suriadjaya said could be told only now that Mr. Suharto has fallen. The government set him up, he said, by encouraging him to lend, only to later impose restrictions and then remove  government pension funds from Bank Summa to precipitate its collapse. He said his father would eventually spell out who was behind the intrigue in a tell-all biography. ''I blame ourselves for being naive,'' Mr. Suriadjaya said. ''We refused to be a crony.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Suriadjaya suggested he was victimized because his first wife, who died of cancer the year the family lost Astra, was the daughter of President Sukarno, whom Mr. Suharto ousted in 1965. Astra had long been uncharacteristically independent of the Suharto clan. And Mr. Suharto was reportedly less than appreciative when, in mid-1990 Bank Summa built a network of banks for rural Muslim communities with a powerful cleric named Abdurrahman Wahid.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Wahid is Indonesia's president, the Suhartos are fending off prosecutors, and the Suriadjayas are rebuilding. In 1998, Edward Suriadjaya was reinstated as a board member of Jakarta International Trade Fair. Last December, his father was named chairman.</p>
        <p>The family's comeback has forced President Wahid to counter accusations that the Suriadjayas have become neocronies. Last month, the president sold his stake in the Muslim finance company he set up with Edward Suriadjaya in mid-1990 after it bought a stake in Mandiri Inti Finance, a company Edward Suriadjaya took control of last January.</p>
        <p>Mandiri was trying to raise funds for a last-minute bid to buy back the Suriadjayas' stake in Astra -- it was on the block after being seized from the indebted cronies who had bought it seven years earlier -- before the government sold it to a Singapore-led consortium.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suriadjaya denies trying to capitalize on his presidential connections. ''If I were doing it, why didn't I do it before, when we were fighting for our existence?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Last month, Mandiri Inti Finance changed its name to Siwani Trimitra and said it would start raising funds for CyberCity. But most of Mr. Suriadjaya's Internet deals have so far been conducted by L &amp; M Group Investments, a financially troubled engineering company in Singapore, which Mr. Suriadjaya's younger brother, Edwin, ended up controlling after taking over a different Singapore company.</p>
        <p>Edwin Suriadjaya remains listed as L &amp; M's deputy chairman, and his father is chairman; Edward Suriadjaya became a member of the board last year and, after slowly building up his stake in the company, was named chief executive last month.</p>
        <p>Underscoring the tangled shareholdings and cross-shareholdings that make Indonesian business so nebulous, L &amp; M owns part of CyberCity together with Jakarta International Trade Fair and Edward Suriadjaya's own Griya Nusantara Pratama, which still owns part of Jakarta International. Just how much of CyberCity each owns, Mr. Suriadjaya said, is ''now being arbitrarily decided.'' CyberCity, in turn, owns only a portion of the five Internet-related ventures it is involved in.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, investors are using L &amp; M's stock as way to bet on the project. It rose 20 percent in November when L &amp; M announced that MyWeb Inc.com, an American set-top box maker, would take a 10 percent stake in CyberCity and help build an Internet service in Indonesia, then fell 8 percent when the deal fell apart a month later. Soon afterward, when L &amp; M said it was in talks to replace MyWeb with Microsoft, the stock rose more than 40 percent.</p>
        <p>L &amp; M's share price has drifted down about 28 percent this year, tracking the decline of Asia's stock markets. But L &amp; M has also been dogged by concerns about whether partnerships will materialize. The company has announced that SingNet, Singapore Telecommunications' Internet unit, was considering a 30 percent stake in CyberCity, and that Detecon Marketing Consulting, a unit of Deutsche Telekom, would buy 10 percent. On Friday, L &amp; M said it had signed a memorandum of understanding with SingTel to help develop CyberCity but gave no details. Detecon said it was in talks but that no deal had yet been reached.</p>
        <p>In February, L &amp; M finally signed a deal with Microsoft -- not to take a stake in CyberCity but rather to help build a news and information Web site in return for a share of the revenue the site generates. The site is scheduled to start this month. The only CyberCity venture that appears to be up and running is the Jakarta Multimedia Academy, which L &amp; M established with Malaysian Technology Development, a government-owned venture capital concern.</p>
        <p>''We support CyberCity fully, but we're still waiting for something to be realized,'' said Pandji Choesin, executive director of the Indonesian Association of Internet Service Providers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suriadjaya wants to sell a 50 percent stake in CyberCity for $26.5 million by June 28, when he plans to officially introduce it at an Internet trade show at Kemayoran. He hopes to raise another $50 million by the end of the year, despite the fact that there are still no revenue projections for the group. ''From June 28 onward, I trust that the price tag of our company will be in excess of $100 million,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Such a big capital buildup might not be unusual for an Internet start-up, but it would represent an especially neat turnaround for Jakarta International Trade Fair's original airport investment.</p>
        <p>Property analysts say prices in Jakarta have fallen at least 50 percent the last 10 years, though with no sales anywhere in two years it is hard to tell. Mr. Suriadjaya said CyberCity was valuing its 7.5-acre property at $5 million, a price that would make Jakarta International's entire 109-acre spread at Kemayoran worth around $73 million -- a 46 percent  paper profit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Suriadjaya rejects criticism that his high-technology vision is a property deal in disguise, though he does not deny that CyberCity could be good for the local real estate market. ''We know we have to push it as a cyberinitiative because that's where most of the funds are basing their decisions,'' he said. ''We're not cheating anybody.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 9, 2000, Tuesday  An article in Business Day last Tuesday about the efforts of an Indonesian entrepreneur to help revive his family's fortunes misstated the location of an Internet trade show that begins June 28. It will be at the Jakarta Convention Center, not at the Kemayoran development site.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 9, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day last Tuesday about the efforts of an Indonesian entrepreneur to help revive his family's fortunes misstated the location of an Internet trade show that begins June 28. It will be at the Jakarta Convention Center, not at the Kemayoran development site.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
