<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Source of Shot That Hit Bystander Still Unknown, Police Say</title>
    <meta content="02SHOO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196301"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramos, Wilson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hightower, Jamel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chivers, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E0DC1339F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Source of Shot That Hit Bystander Still Unknown, Police Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. CHIVERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chivers, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Police back off earlier statement that Jamel Hightower, convicted robber who was in gun battle with police in Bronx had probably fired bullet that struck bystander Wilson Ramos in head; say they are now giving more weight to possibility that Ramos had been shot by errant police bullet (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The authorities yesterday backed off an earlier statement that a convicted robber who was in a gun battle with the police in the Bronx on Sunday had probably fired a bullet that struck a bystander in the head. Instead, they said they were giving more weight to the possibility that the bystander had been shot by an errant police bullet.</p>
        <p>The bystander, Wilson Ramos, 48, an Ecuadorean immigrant and a father of three, remained in a coma in a surgical intensive care unit at Jacobi Medical Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The authorities yesterday backed off an earlier statement that a convicted robber who was in a gun battle with the police in the Bronx on Sunday had probably fired a bullet that struck a bystander in the head. Instead, they said they were giving more weight to the possibility that the bystander had been shot by an errant police bullet.</p>
        <p>The bystander, Wilson Ramos, 48, an Ecuadorean immigrant and a father of three, remained in a coma in a surgical intensive care unit at Jacobi Medical Center.</p>
        <p>The authorities said they were trying to reconstruct the path of each bullet fired during the exchange that erupted around Mr. Ramos as he walked in Bedford Park. But they said that they were struggling to find the impact marks and bullet fragments that would help them determine the sequence of events, and that they had not found the most important piece of evidence of all: the bullet that struck Mr. Ramos.</p>
        <p>''We don't have any ballistic evidence that will positively determine who shot who, and until we do, it's just speculation,'' said Police Commissioner Howard Safir.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ramos's daughter Janett Ramos, said relatives had gathered at her father's bedside and were ''praying, crying, begging for a miracle.''</p>
        <p>The overwhelming sentiment among the family, she said, was that her father had been shot by the police, and she said the family was demanding to know why the officers did not hold their fire as their target, Jamel Hightower, ran through the neighborhood after stabbing two people in a Briggs Avenue apartment.</p>
        <p>''What do they get trained for?'' Ms. Ramos asked. ''For nothing.''</p>
        <p>On Sunday, the police said their first impression was that Mr. Hightower, a robber and sex offender who was released from prison six weeks ago, had shot Mr. Ramos.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, however, the authorities said they were rethinking their initial conclusion after a check of Mr. Hightower's pistol found it had only fired three bullets, one of which struck a police cruiser and another that was fired blocks from where Mr. Ramos was hit.</p>
        <p>That left only one of his bullets unaccounted for, the police said. By contrast, the two patrol officers, Donn R. Maldonado and Alexander Rojas, fired eight shots near Mr. Ramos, and none of their bullets have been found, the police said.</p>
        <p>''The investigation is not complete,'' said Sgt. Andrew McInnis, a police spokesman. ''There is still ballistic evidence to recover, and that's the focus of it, to determine whose round struck the victim.''</p>
        <p>The police said the violence began inside 2661 Briggs Avenue, when Mr. Hightower and his two cousins forced their way into a ground-floor apartment occupied by Michael Ortiz. Mr. Hightower argued with Mr. Ortiz over money and marijuana, the police said. As the argument escalated, they said, Mr. Hightower pulled a knife and stabbed Mr. Ortiz and his mother, Miriam, before fleeing from the apartment with $1,398 and a nine-shot .22-caliber revolver that belonged to Mr. Ortiz.</p>
        <p>''It looks like they robbed him because he was a local weed dealer,'' Sergeant McInnis said.</p>
        <p>Out on the street, the police said, Mr. Hightower fired one time at Officers Maldonado and Rojas as they arrived at a nearby intersection, starting the gunfight in which Mr. Ramos was shot. A seven-minute chase ended after Mr. Hightower fired at a detective in the Metro-North railroad station near Fordham University and was taken into custody, the police said.</p>
        <p>The police changed other details of their initial account yesterday, saying, for instance, that Mr. Hightower had not taken a woman hostage on the Fordham train platform and used her as a shield. Instead, they said, the woman's ear was hurt as she scrambled to get out of the way while Detective Dennis J. Fagan and Mr. Hightower traded shots.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hightower, 24, of 1357 Washington Avenue in the Bronx, was charged with attempted murder, assault, burglary, robbery and criminal possession of a weapon.</p>
        <p>His two cousins, Daniel Hightower, 19, and Larivia Hightower, 16, of 2325 Prospect Avenue in the Bronx, were charged with burglary, assault, robbery, criminal possession of a weapon and possession of marijuana.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ortiz, 22, listed in stable condition at Jacobi Medical Center yesterday, was charged with criminal possession of a weapon and possession of marijuana.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
