<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Notebook; Gay, Middle-Aged and Still Militant</title>
    <meta content="02TUE3$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clendinen, Dudley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DC1339F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Notebook; Gay, Middle-Aged and Still Militant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DUDLEY CLENDINEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clendinen, Dudley</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dudley Clendinen, in Editorial Notebook column, notes that hundreds of thousands of people attended gay rights march in Washington, DC, on April 30; maintains that march was significant because it showed movement's strength and staying power</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There have been so many national marches on Washington by political movements in the last four decades that they have become more a tradition than a novelty. The Park and District police have stopped counting crowds because they found that neither boosters nor critics were ever satisfied. The events themselves no longer qualify as automatic front-page news.</p>
        <p>But they remain uniquely important, not just for the sheer numbers involved but for what they tell the nation -- and the protesting populations themselves -- about the current state of each movement. There is no better litmus test of the political health and character of any group than how it responds to the inconvenience of being asked to march on Washington. That is especially true of homosexuals, who in times past tended to be invisible and therefore hard to organize. And the Millennium March on Washington this past weekend -- the fourth national gay rights march in the nation's capital in 31 years -- was significant for what it showed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There have been so many national marches on Washington by political movements in the last four decades that they have become more a tradition than a novelty. The Park and District police have stopped counting crowds because they found that neither boosters nor critics were ever satisfied. The events themselves no longer qualify as automatic front-page news.</p>
        <p>But they remain uniquely important, not just for the sheer numbers involved but for what they tell the nation -- and the protesting populations themselves -- about the current state of each movement. There is no better litmus test of the political health and character of any group than how it responds to the inconvenience of being asked to march on Washington. That is especially true of homosexuals, who in times past tended to be invisible and therefore hard to organize. And the Millennium March on Washington this past weekend -- the fourth national gay rights march in the nation's capital in 31 years -- was significant for what it showed.</p>
        <p>The modern movement was born as a radical expression of youth and sexual liberation in 1969, when patrons of the Stonewall Inn in New York rioted against a police raid of the bar. But it was a middle-aged, middle-class movement that crowded the Mall in Washington with hundreds of thousands of people on Sunday, with grandparents in wheelchairs and children underfoot. There were more family, cultural, church and workplace events on the three-day weekend schedule than parties.</p>
        <p>There were other differences, too. The cadaverous look of AIDS, visible on the faces of so many in the crowd in 1993, when people with H.I.V. were still routinely dying, was largely absent. In the new panels of the quilt laid on the Mall, memorializing those who have died of AIDS, the deaths taper off noticeably after 1998. Nor was there the same level of anger about the lack of treatment for AIDS, which helped produce a huge turnout at the last march. Even so, a vast throng showed up.</p>
        <p>When Washington's mayor, Anthony Williams, welcomed them at noon, he told them they were a crowd of ''310,000, on its way to half a million.'' Some, like Morris Kight, an old radical from Los Angeles now in his 80's, came for the sheer joy of the progress made in law and acceptance in the last three decades. ''I'm the happiest old man in the world today,'' he said. Some, like the Rev. Troy Perry, who founded the gay Metropolitan Community Churches in 1968, came with a particular mission. Mr. Perry began performing symbolic marriages at the march in 1987, at the request of two men dying of AIDS, and at the Lincoln Memorial on Saturday he joined 3,000 couples in vows. Many, like Robert Turlington, 41, of Fort Lauderdale, Fla., who played clarinet in the 130-piece band that led the march, came out of habit and continuity. ''This is my third march,'' he said. ''The first was for awareness. The second for anger. This time I brought my family.''</p>
        <p>It is obvious that the gay rights movement has matured and mellowed. But what was also evident, as dozens of speakers took their turns at the microphone for six and a half hours Sunday afternoon, was the continuing anger and determination of a group that still feels discrimination. Employees can still be fired for being homosexual in 39 states. Homosexuals still get murdered for being gay. They cannot actually marry in any state, and in most places, the young cannot become Scouts, or even form their own groups in school.</p>
        <p>The point of the gay rights march last weekend was to show the movement's strength in a presidential election year. Some of the strongest feelings came from the youngest speakers. ''We will not be intimidated,'' said Ivy Fox, a Utah high school student, whose school board disbanded dozens of student groups rather than let gays form one. ''And we will not give up.''</p>
        <p>DUDLEY CLENDINEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
