<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big European Stock Merger Due Tomorrow</title>
    <meta content="Y02MARK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">London Stock Exchange</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Frankfurt Stock Exchange</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bourse (Paris)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brussels Stock Exchange</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Amsterdam Stock Exchange</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Euronext Stock Exchange</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Deutsche Borse AG</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seifert, Werner G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6DE1339F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big European Stock Merger Due Tomorrow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, May 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>London and Frankfurt stock exchanges, in most advanced step yet toward creation of pan-European stock market, plan to announce merger on May 3; deal would unite Europe's two biggest securities exchanges, creating market for trading stocks and other instruments that would outweigh proposed alliance between Paris, Brussels and Amsterdam exchanges; chief executive of combined company will be Werner G Seifert, currently chief executive of Deutsche Borse AG, which owns Frankfurt Stock Exchange; London will adopt Germans' electronic trading system, known as Xetra; that would represent remarkable reversal, because London Stock Exchange remains bigger in terms of trading volume than Frankfurt and because London is closest thing that Europe has to financial center; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the most advanced step yet toward the creation of a pan-European stock market, the London and Frankfurt stock exchanges plan to announce a merger on Wednesday, according to officials close to the negotiations by the two markets.</p>
        <p>The deal would unite Europe's two biggest securities exchanges, creating a market for trading stocks and other instruments that would far outweigh the proposed alliance between the Paris, Brussels and Amsterdam exchanges.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the most advanced step yet toward the creation of a pan-European stock market, the London and Frankfurt stock exchanges plan to announce a merger on Wednesday, according to officials close to the negotiations by the two markets.</p>
        <p>The deal would unite Europe's two biggest securities exchanges, creating a market for trading stocks and other instruments that would far outweigh the proposed alliance between the Paris, Brussels and Amsterdam exchanges.</p>
        <p>But more surprising is the way that Frankfurt, which some have considered a backwater for trading compared with the City of London, has jumped to the forefront of European securities dealings.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement to be announced, the chief executive of the combined company will be Werner G. Seifert, currently chief executive of Deutsche Borse A.G., which owns the Frankfurt Stock Exchange. The supervisory board of Deutsche Borse approved the plan this weekend, and the London Stock Exchange board is expected to do so on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>In addition, London will adopt the Germans' electronic trading system, known as Xetra. That would represent a remarkable reversal, because the London Stock Exchange remains bigger in terms of trading volume than Frankfurt and because London itself is the closest thing that Europe has to a financial center, in many ways rivaling New York and Tokyo.</p>
        <p>But the deal reflects the extent to which Mr. Seifert, a former management consultant, has expanded and redefined what had been a sleepy stock exchange into a formidable institution.</p>
        <p>The reason that the Germans will exert such a dominant role stems from their embrace of new technology as well as their expansion into new markets. Two years ago, Mr. Seifert engineered a merger between the futures and options exchange of Deutsche Borse and that of its Swiss counterpart.</p>
        <p>The combined exchange, called Eurex, is now the world's largest derivatives market -- larger even than the formidable Chicago Board of Trade.</p>
        <p>But the Frankfurt exchange's biggest advantage is in technology. Its electronic trading system has proved more reliable than that of London and is being used for electronic trading on the Helsinki derivatives exchange, the Vienna stock exchange and, later this year, on the Irish stock exchange in Dublin.</p>
        <p>The merger is being driven in large part by demands from big financial institutions in Europe, which have complained for some time that securities trading there is too inefficient and needs to be freed from national boundaries.</p>
        <p>The talks were given further impetus with the announcement earlier this year of an alliance between the Paris, Brussels and Amsterdam exchanges. That alliance, to be called Euronext, could have posed a serious competitive threat but is likely to be overshadowed by a union of Frankfurt and London.</p>
        <p>German and British exchange officials have been in talks for years about forming a long-term relationship. Indeed, they startled other European markets two years ago by announcing an agreement to align with each other rather than pursue more complex negotiations involving the other European markets.</p>
        <p>Since then, Frankfurt and London have talked in fits and starts, but their negotiations ran into repeated disagreements over who would control how much and whose technology had the best chance of being accepted as a common platform for trading in Europe.</p>
        <p>Both have announced plans for collaboration with Europe's smaller exchanges. But those talks have been even more prickly and appeared to be heading nowhere.</p>
        <p>The advent of new electronic trading networks, supported by some of the biggest financial institutions on Wall Street and in Europe, made it increasingly clear to market officials that their franchises would be in danger if they failed to quickly provide pan-European trading.</p>
        <p>It is not known what the combined entity will be called, although the Deutsche Borse had already planned to rename itself Euroboard. If the merger is completed, the plan is to take the combined company public.</p>
        <p>The new exchange will include the Deutsche Borse derivatives market but not Clearstream, a subsidiary that clears financial transactions. The plan has been to let the London exchange handle trading in blue-chip stocks while Frankfurt deals with trading in derivatives and small technology stocks. But details on those matters remained unclear tonight.</p>
        <p>The site of the new headquarters was also not known.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
