<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peace Overtures in Colombia</title>
    <meta content="02TUE2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Colombia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Liberation Army (Colombia)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pastrana, Andres (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E7DC1339F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="491" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peace Overtures in Colombia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial praises Pres Andres Pastrana for his decision to establish safe haven for nation's second-largest guerrilla group, National Liberation Army; holds that Pastrana is showing admirable persistance in trying to negotiate end to nation's 35-year-old civil war</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his decision to establish a safe haven for Colombia's second-largest guerrilla group, President Andres Pastrana is showing admirable persistence in trying to negotiate an end to his nation's 35-year-old civil war. The plan would draw the group, the National Liberation Army, into Mr. Pastrana's peace talks for the first time. Colombians have learned not to expect too much from periodic negotiations, and a peace agreement is still a long shot. But the inclusion of the National Liberation Army provides the best chance in recent history to negotiate an end to the activities of a guerrilla army whose kidnappings and bombing of oil production facilities have terrorized Colombians.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pastrana took office in 1998 with an overwhelming mandate to negotiate peace. One of his first acts was to pull army troops out of a zone that became a safe haven for Colombia's largest guerrilla group, the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, or FARC. Ensconced in a sparsely populated area the size of Switzerland, the FARC proceeded to increase coca production, stockpile arms and drive out local authorities. The group's bad behavior and repeated snubs at peace talks have made Mr. Pastrana look weak and damaged the public consensus for negotiations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his decision to establish a safe haven for Colombia's second-largest guerrilla group, President Andres Pastrana is showing admirable persistence in trying to negotiate an end to his nation's 35-year-old civil war. The plan would draw the group, the National Liberation Army, into Mr. Pastrana's peace talks for the first time. Colombians have learned not to expect too much from periodic negotiations, and a peace agreement is still a long shot. But the inclusion of the National Liberation Army provides the best chance in recent history to negotiate an end to the activities of a guerrilla army whose kidnappings and bombing of oil production facilities have terrorized Colombians.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pastrana took office in 1998 with an overwhelming mandate to negotiate peace. One of his first acts was to pull army troops out of a zone that became a safe haven for Colombia's largest guerrilla group, the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Colombia, or FARC. Ensconced in a sparsely populated area the size of Switzerland, the FARC proceeded to increase coca production, stockpile arms and drive out local authorities. The group's bad behavior and repeated snubs at peace talks have made Mr. Pastrana look weak and damaged the public consensus for negotiations.</p>
        <p>This is not an auspicious backdrop for a second safe haven -- especially because the National Liberation Army recently infuriated Colombians by kidnapping 160 worshipers at a Catholic Mass as well as an airliner full of people. In addition, the area proposed for the new safe haven is heavily populated and borders on an important oil-producing zone.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pastrana has made a better deal this time, mainly because the National Liberation Army is smaller than the FARC and more enthusiastic about peace negotiations. The new enclave will be smaller and easier for the army to retake if the guerrillas violate their promises. The group has apparently agreed to release its hostages. Crucially, guerrilla leaders will also allow Colombian and international observers into the area.</p>
        <p>There are still many details to be worked out,  and no guarantee of good behavior, but the plan is nevertheless a major step. The recent announcement by the FARC that it will ''tax'' millionaires by kidnapping them -- which has long been its practice  -- is a setback, but there have been advances as well. The FARC observed a cease-fire over Christmas, and is proposing another one. It has decided to create a political party. Perhaps Colombia's rebels  are finally ready to negotiate in good faith.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
