<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Domino' Transplants: Rare and Risky</title>
    <meta content="02LIVE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Liver</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidneys</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Eric</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Liver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFDC1239F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1227" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Domino' Transplants: Rare and Risky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on rare, multipatient transplant procedure known as domino transplant; multiple-organ transplants are highly unusual, and domino transplants are rarer still; there are few cases in which it makes medical sense for a patient who needs a new organ to give up one of his own; example cited; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The call came in the early morning hours of April 11 to the Watertown, S.D., home of Barbara Hubbard, who had just gone back to sleep after walking the dog and having a snack.</p>
        <p>''I have a liver. Are you interested?'' Mrs. Hubbard remembers the caller asking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The call came in the early morning hours of April 11 to the Watertown, S.D., home of Barbara Hubbard, who had just gone back to sleep after walking the dog and having a snack.</p>
        <p>''I have a liver. Are you interested?'' Mrs. Hubbard remembers the caller asking.</p>
        <p>''How soon do I have to be there?'' she replied.</p>
        <p>The call came about the same time for Al Cawley of Waterford, Mich., whose wife woke him up to come to the phone. This time the message was a little different: a liver had just become available, as had a heart and a kidney. Was he available?</p>
        <p>By about that hour the next day, Mr. Cawley, whose plane took off in a snowstorm to rush him to the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minn., had his three new organs, and Mrs. Hubbard, who was driven there through the night by a friend, had her liver.</p>
        <p>The twist was that the liver put into the South Dakota woman had come from Mr. Cawley in a rare, multipatient procedure known as a domino transplant.</p>
        <p>Multiple-organ transplants are highly unusual: 1989 was the last time one like Mr. Cawley's was done in the United States, according to a national organ-donation network. But domino transplants are rarer still. Only a handful have ever been done in this country, while about 40 have been done around the world, mostly in Europe, Mayo officials say.</p>
        <p>There are few cases in which it makes medical sense for a patient who needs a new  organ to give up one of his own.</p>
        <p>''The situations are few, but where it is appropriate, I think it's a great utilization of a very scarce resource,'' said Dr. Joseph A. Dearani, the heart surgeon who was part of the team that operated on Mr. Cawley.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Cawley's case, as with most domino transplants, a rare genetic condition created the circumstances in which he was given a new liver -- only to have his own put into another patient. A 58-year-old lawyer, Mr. Cawley had familial amyloidosis, a disease in which the liver produces an abnormal protein that destroys many of the body's organs.</p>
        <p>The liver itself, however, works fine.</p>
        <p>Doctors at Mayo, with one of the world's  largest amyloidosis treatment centers, say they cannot be sure how the diseased liver will behave in another patient. But because amyloidosis take decades to do real damage, they expect it will be many years, if ever, before any symptoms are seen.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Spieldenner, a spokesman for the United Network for Organ Sharing, which runs the country's organ-donor distribution system, said it was important that  the patient receiving the donated organ realized the potential risks. ''You have to be sure that the patient fully understands what's going to happen, and that they're comfortable with that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Hubbard, a 58-year-old registered nurse, put it simply. When the call from Mayo came, she had been suffering from liver disease for about 10 years, and her condition had gotten worse. ''It was hope for a new life, and I wasn't about to turn it down,'' she said.</p>
        <p>There are other ethical issues, said Dr. Andreas G. Tzakis, co-director of transplantation at the University of Miami's Jackson Memorial Hospital, who has been involved in six cases where an amyloid liver was given to another patient.</p>
        <p>What, for example, should a hospital do if an emergency liver failure case comes in as doctors are about to perform an elective domino procedure? Who should get the liver? And should amyloid livers in general be treated like any other donated organ, and placed into the general distribution system?</p>
        <p>''It might sound like hair-splitting,'' Dr. Tzakis said, ''but the truth of the matter is: in this day and age, a lot of people die for a liver. This question is going to come up more and more as the procedure becomes more frequent.''</p>
        <p>No matter how these issues are resolved, even though domino transplants will do little to reduce the backlog of people waiting for new organs, each one creates a kind of ripple effect, Mr. Spieldenner said.</p>
        <p>''You're able to help another patient out,'' he said. ''Instead of just one person getting transplanted, you're helping two. That not only helps those patients, but helps those patients who continue to wait, because that's one less person they have to compete against.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Cawley, whose father died of amyloidosis at age 62, the domino transplant did not raise ethical issues so much as help resolve them. When he initially went to Mayo, the plan was for him to receive a new heart and a new liver. But as time went on, it became clear that he would also need a new kidney. Those organs, he recalls thinking, could help three different people, and one question kept going through his head: ''Is it fair?'' He seriously considered saying no to the transplant.</p>
        <p>Dr. Charles B. Rosen, Mayo's director of liver transplantation, said that doctors were intending to ask Mr. Cawley if they could give his liver to someone else, but ''he brought it up first.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Cawley learned that his liver would help someone else, he agreed to the surgery. ''I couldn't be happier,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Then it was just a question of waiting.</p>
        <p>Early on April 11, doctors at Mayo received a call telling them that there might be organs available from a young trauma victim in the region. (To protect confidentiality, doctors did not disclose more information about the donor.) They immediately put Mr. Cawley and Mrs. Hubbard on notice, and sent two procurement teams to the hospital, where the patient was on life-support.</p>
        <p>At about 11 that morning, surgeons at Mayo's St. Marys Hospital began work on Mr. Cawley, beginning with his heart. They then replaced his liver, and finally a kidney. Mrs. Hubbard, meanwhile, was being prepared at Rochester Methodist Hospital, also part of Mayo.</p>
        <p>After removing Mr. Cawley's liver, doctors flushed it with a preservative solution and had it driven the the short distance to Rochester Methodist. Three hours and 19 minutes after it had been taken out of Mr. Cawley, the liver was placed in Mrs. Hubbard. In all, the whole process took about 14 hours, involved at least two dozen medical workers, and cost easily $500,000, Mayo officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cawley and Mrs. Hubbard have yet to meet each other, but say they hope to do so. Both are reported to be doing well, but will have to take anti-rejection drugs for the rest of their lives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cawley said he planned to return to his law practice, but Mrs. Hubbard said she had been advised that working in a hospital might no longer be a good idea for her, because of the risk of infection. As unsettling as it is, she said, she is enjoying trying to figure out her next move.</p>
        <p>''For 10 years,'' she said, ''I thought I was just going to die. So there was no future.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
