<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bell Atlantic Is Set to Offer Prepaid Service</title>
    <meta content="Y02PHON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bell Atlantic Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mci Worldcom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sprint Communications Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiesel, Seth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D71239F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bell Atlantic Is Set to Offer Prepaid Service</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH SCHIESEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schiesel, Seth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bell Atlantic Corp intends to introduce innovative calling plan that appears less expensive than popular plans offered by rivals; new plan, called SmartTouch, offers interstate long-distance calls for 8 cents a minute at any time and without monthly fees or minimum charges; twist is that Bell Atlantic will require SmartTouch customers to buy long-distance minutes in advance under system similar to prepaid calling cards (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maintaining its strong drive into the long-distance telephone market, the Bell Atlantic Corporation intends to introduce an innovative calling plan today that appears less expensive than popular plans offered by AT&amp;T, MCI WorldCom and Sprint, executives close to Bell Atlantic said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The new Bell Atlantic plan, to be called SmartTouch, offers interstate long-distance calls for 8 cents a minute at any time and without monthly fees or minimum charges. The most attractive flat-rate calling plans from the established long-distance giants generally include fixed fees or minimum charges of $5 a month or more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maintaining its strong drive into the long-distance telephone market, the Bell Atlantic Corporation intends to introduce an innovative calling plan today that appears less expensive than popular plans offered by AT&amp;T, MCI WorldCom and Sprint, executives close to Bell Atlantic said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The new Bell Atlantic plan, to be called SmartTouch, offers interstate long-distance calls for 8 cents a minute at any time and without monthly fees or minimum charges. The most attractive flat-rate calling plans from the established long-distance giants generally include fixed fees or minimum charges of $5 a month or more.</p>
        <p>The twist is that Bell Atlantic will require SmartTouch customers to buy long-distance minutes in advance under a system somewhat akin to prepaid calling cards. Generally using a credit card, consumers will pay into a SmartTouch account that will then be drawn down as the user makes long-distance calls. SmartTouch customers will not receive a monthly bill and Bell Atlantic intends to describe the prepaid nature of the plan as a way for budget-conscious consumers to increase control over their household's long-distance spending, executives close to the company said yesterday.</p>
        <p>A Bell Atlantic spokesman declined to comment.</p>
        <p>In December, Bell Atlantic became the first regional Bell company to win permission from federal regulators to offer long-distance service in part of its traditional service region. Last week, the company announced that it signed up 428,000 long-distance customers in New York in the first three months of the year. While that represents only about 6 percent of Bell Atlantic's New York customers, it was nonetheless a remarkably robust figure.</p>
        <p>Bell Atlantic has not won permission to sell long-distance service in any of the other states where it is the dominant local phone company, but it is free to sell long-distance service outside of the Eastern Seaboard. Bell Atlantic will initially offer SmartTouch in Arkansas, Iowa, Kansas, Michigan, Nevada, New York, Oregon, South Dakota, Texas and Wisconsin. The company intends to extend the plan to California, Idaho and Minnesota by the middle of this month.</p>
        <p>SmartTouch users will not have to dial extra digits, like a ''10-10'' code, before placing a call. But after dialing a long-distance number, SmartTouch users will hear a computer-generated message informing them how much time is remaining on their account. While some users will surely welcome the reminder, others may consider it an annoyance.</p>
        <p>Within months, Bell Atlantic intends to allow users to automatically transfer money from a credit card to their SmartTouch account when their calling balance runs low.</p>
        <p>The long-distance titans offer plans with per-minute rates lower than 8 cents, but those plans require monthly fees or minimum charges. AT&amp;T, for instance, sells interstate long-distance calls for a flat rate of 5 cents a minute, but only to consumers who pay a monthly fee of $8.95.</p>
        <p>MCI WorldCom offers a plan with no monthly fee, 9-cent calling during the week and 5-cent calling on weekends. But that plan requires a $5 monthly minimum and asks that customers conduct all their billing and customer service activities via the Internet.</p>
        <p>Sprint's best flat-rate plan with no monthly fee and no monthly minimum charges 30 cents a minute during the week and 10 cents a minute on weekends.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
