<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="02OBSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">X-Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Microscopes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Optics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gravitation and Gravity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vinyl</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cambridge University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newton, Isaac (1642-1727)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">X-Rays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Polymers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gravitation and Gravity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Microscopes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laboratories and Scientific Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7DC1239F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Swedish researchers discover way of making microscope lens using strips cut from vinyl LPs; researchers at Cambridge University in England test theory about how brain recognizes a tune; researchers at University of Washington reduce uncertainty in Newton's gravitational constant, fundamental value that enables measurement of mass of Earth and other planets (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hope for Old Abba Discs</p>
        <p>Martha Stewart's got nothing on the researchers at the Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm. They've come up with a novel home crafts project: turning that old Monkees' Greatest Hits album into a lens for an X-ray microscope.</p>
        <p>X-rays, particularly the higher energy kind known as hard X-rays, can be bent -- or refracted -- by a lens, just as light beams can (though X-ray lenses are not made of glass). But X-rays are refracted only slightly, so the only practicable refractive lenses have been compound ones, made up of many lenses in a line. And these lenses have parabolic surfaces, which can make them difficult to fabricate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hope for Old Abba Discs</p>
        <p>Martha Stewart's got nothing on the researchers at the Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm. They've come up with a novel home crafts project: turning that old Monkees' Greatest Hits album into a lens for an X-ray microscope.</p>
        <p>X-rays, particularly the higher energy kind known as hard X-rays, can be bent -- or refracted -- by a lens, just as light beams can (though X-ray lenses are not made of glass). But X-rays are refracted only slightly, so the only practicable refractive lenses have been compound ones, made up of many lenses in a line. And these lenses have parabolic surfaces, which can make them difficult to fabricate.</p>
        <p>The Swedish researchers, writing in the journal Nature, have described a new way of making a lens that has straight surfaces. In theory, the lens could be made of two two-inch strips cut from a vinyl LP, joined at one end and separated slightly at the other so that the strips with their grooves resemble the open jaw of an alligator, viewed from the side. X-rays entering at the closed end would skim across the hills and valleys of the grooves, refracting slightly as they passed through each succeeding hill and eventually coming to a common focus.</p>
        <p>In practice, the researchers found that a record's grooves were too shallow (about 25 microns deep), and had too much material between them, to make a useful lens. So they made their own record, with a uniform groove that is 90 microns deep, about four times as deep as those on an LP. But don't look for it in record stores anytime soon.</p>
        <p>Mangle That Tune</p>
        <p>In the old television game show ''Name That Tune,'' contestants vied to see who could identify a popular melody faster (''I can name that tune in five notes, Tom,'' a contestant would tell Tom Kennedy, the host of the 1970's version of the show).</p>
        <p>Researchers at the University of Cambridge in England haven't been competing for cash prizes or even seven-piece bedroom sets, but they have been using a nightmarish version of the game in order to test a theory about how the brain recognizes a tune. Their theory, as described in the journal Nature, is that when the brain initially experiences a melody, a template of pitch and time is formed that is then used as a basis for comparison when the melody is heard again.</p>
        <p>The research subjects listened to some or all of the first 18 notes of Mozart's ''Eine Kleine Nachtmusik'' with increasing numbers of random notes -- tens to hundreds of them -- added. The researchers, who noted that their results were only preliminary, found that the subjects could tolerate greater numbers of ''noise'' notes (and still identify Mozart's melody) as the number of correct notes increased. This supports the template idea, the researchers said, in that the more notes that match the template, the better the brain can name that tune.</p>
        <p>Physics With Mass Appeal</p>
        <p>Physicists are no doubt sleeping better these days, thanks to some precision measurements by researchers at the University of Washington. They have reduced the uncertainty in Newton's gravitational constant, a fundamental value that enables measurement of the mass of the Earth and other planets.</p>
        <p>Since it was first measured by Henry Cavendish in 1797, the constant, represented as G, has been known only to varying levels of uncertainty. The latest internationally accepted value had an uncertainty of .15 percent.</p>
        <p>For their measurements, which have an uncertainty of about .0015 percent, the University of Washington researchers used an improved version of a torsion balance. It consists of a pendulum that rotates on a turntable between a set of ''attractor'' masses, precisely milled stainless steel balls.</p>
        <p>Using the result, the Washington scientists also announced a more precise calculation of the Earth's mass: about 6 sextillion metric tons. That's a 6 with 21 zeros after it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
