<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deal Places Mohawk Casino At Kutsher's In the Catskills</title>
    <meta content="02CASI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mohawk Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Catskills (NYS Area)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Park Place Entertainment</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kutsher's Country Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E2DB1339F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1518" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deal Places Mohawk Casino At Kutsher's In the Catskills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Park Place Entertainment, in another round involving proposed casino for Catskills, announces that it has signed option to buy Kutsher's Country Club, oldest resort in Catskills, to create 1,400-acre entertainment complex and gambling hall that would be owned by St Regis Mohawks tribe; new agreement grants Park Place right to develop and manage Mohawk casinos throughout New York State; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In another round of billion-dollar poker involving a proposed casino for the Catskills, the world's largest gambling company announced yesterday that it had signed an option to buy Kutsher's Country Club, the oldest resort in the Catskills, to create a 1,400-acre entertainment complex and gambling hall that would be owned by the St. Regis Mohawks tribe.</p>
        <p>The resort would sit on Anawana Lake in Sullivan County, five miles north of the site at Monticello Raceway that federal officials approved last month, after a four-year-long application for a $500 million casino and entertainment complex for the Mohawks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In another round of billion-dollar poker involving a proposed casino for the Catskills, the world's largest gambling company announced yesterday that it had signed an option to buy Kutsher's Country Club, the oldest resort in the Catskills, to create a 1,400-acre entertainment complex and gambling hall that would be owned by the St. Regis Mohawks tribe.</p>
        <p>The resort would sit on Anawana Lake in Sullivan County, five miles north of the site at Monticello Raceway that federal officials approved last month, after a four-year-long application for a $500 million casino and entertainment complex for the Mohawks.</p>
        <p>But the leaders of the Mohawk tribe recently abandoned that plan and signed an unusual agreement with Park Place Entertainment, which owns 28 gambling operations in New Jersey, Nevada, Mississippi and overseas. The agreement grants Park Place the right to develop and manage Mohawk casinos throughout New York.</p>
        <p>That new agreement is being viewed with increasing skepticism by political and governmental officials who helped gain support for the original plan.</p>
        <p>The announcement yesterday by Park Place appears to be another attempt to outmaneuver the tribe's original partners in Monticello, Catskill Development, and seize control of a project that the developer estimates could generate more than $1 billion a year. Some gambling analysts doubt that Park Place truly wants a hall in Monticello that would undercut its three casinos in Atlantic City. The company said yesterday that it would build a resort hotel with up to 2,000 rooms in addition to the casino. The project would rival the Foxwoods casino in Connecticut and employ 4,500 people in a county whose resort industry has been slowly dying for 30 years.</p>
        <p>''We intend to build a destination resort on the site of Kutsher's,'' said Clive Cummis, general counsel for Park Place. ''We'll build a hotel and casino, upgrade the golf course. This would be a giant step forward in the rebirth of Sullivan County.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cummis said Park Place believed it would inherit the federal approval granted to the original Mohawk project and proceed quickly, but officials at the Bureau of Indian Affairs and the National Indian Gaming Commission, which oversees management contracts between casino operators and tribes, said the company would have to file a new application for Kutsher's, a process that could take two to four years. Kutsher's resort was built in 1907.</p>
        <p>For that reason, Senators Charles E. Schumer and Daniel K. Inouye and other supporters of the tribal casino were bewildered by the tribe's sudden alliance with Park Place, just when the long-sought Monticello Raceway casino seemed assured. They had supported Catskill Development's plan to put 30 acres in trust for the tribe under a seldom-used provision of federal law. The trust would establish a sovereign Indian territory for a gambling hall and bypass New York's prohibition on casinos.</p>
        <p>''I was surprised and not prepared for this sudden change,'' said Senator Inouye, vice chairman of the Senate Indian Affairs Committee. ''I am certain that those of us who have been trying to assist the St. Regis Mohawk tribe would like to hear directly from them about what has happened, or is happening.''</p>
        <p>Local officials in Sullivan County told four Mohawk chiefs at a meeting Friday night at the Town Hall in Thompson, Sullivan County, that they would not look kindly on a casino at Kutsher's, or a delay in the county's long-awaited casino project. The chiefs said they wanted to put a casino at the raceway, according to two people who attended the meeting, but were also considering another location, which the two men presumed to be Kutsher's.</p>
        <p>''It is extremely important that it be located at the Monticello Raceway,'' said Anthony P. Cellini, supervisor of the town of Thompson. ''If they change locations now, there'll be very little support from local people. Our residents have had this golden carrot dangled in front of them for too long. To delay this for another two to four years is not acceptable.''</p>
        <p>There is widespread speculation among gambling analysts, Sullivan County officials and some dissident Mohawks that Arthur M. Goldberg, chief executive of Park Place, is intent on delaying and derailing a Sullivan County casino to protect his Atlantic City casinos, which generate 30 percent of the company's profits. Other analysts say that Mr. Goldberg wins whether he gains control of the casino project in Monticello or whether it is delayed, perhaps forever, by regulatory reviews and lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cummis struck a deal on Friday with Mark Kutsher, the head of the family that owns the country club, under which Park Place agreed to buy 50 acres within 60 days and a five-year option to acquire the remaining 1,350 acres. Park Place, which said it would transfer the 50 acres to the Mohawks, agreed to hire the Kutsher family, as well as its employees, and to continue to use the Kutsher name in some manner.</p>
        <p>''Arthur Goldberg is a builder, not a blocker,'' Mr. Cummis said. ''We're going to get this built and done, just as we did with the Paris in Las Vegas, on time and on budget.''</p>
        <p>The Mohawk chiefs, who did not consult the lawyers they hired to work on gambling ventures before they signed the Park Place deal, granted Park Place broad casino development rights on April 14 in return for a $3 million loan to bolster the tribe's financially crippled Akwesasne Casino at the reservation in Hogansburg, N.Y., and 70 percent of the profits. Fearing problems in Monticello, the tribe turned its back on Catskill Development and made the deal with Park Place, which will almost certainly cause a lawsuit by Catskill Development.</p>
        <p>Robert A. Berman, a partner in Catskill Development, has called the Park Place deal ''the greatest rip-off of an Indian tribe since the Dutch grabbed Manhattan for $24.'' If Park Place eventually has a casino in Sullivan County, it may have to strike a deal with Catskill Development, which has vowed never to do so and has begun talks with other tribes for a casino in the area.</p>
        <p>The Mohawks have not notified federal officials or Catskill Development that the tribe has abandoned the project at Monticello Raceway.</p>
        <p>''I can't imagine that the tribe, or anybody who recognizes how long it takes to get land into trust for gaming, would want to undo four years of work,'' said Rick Chiff, deputy chief of staff at the National Indian Gaming Commission. ''We're proceeding with the Monticello contract because that's the one that's before us and that's the one that's greenlighted.''</p>
        <p>Many residents of Sullivan County have viewed gambling for decades as a way to revive the county's economy. But a series of efforts to legalize gambling failed, so the major gambling companies, real estate developers and many politicians paid little attention.</p>
        <p>In recent years, however, Gov. George E. Pataki has said that he favors Indian casinos in former resort areas like the Catskills and western New York. And then, while  federal approval of the casino at the Monticello Raceway was inching forward in Washington last year, real estate developers, who had contributed thousands of dollars to Mr. Pataki and the Republican Party, began snapping up large tracts in Sullivan County for hotel projects.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldberg of Park Place got involved in talks with the tribe last fall, as did the company's consultant, Alfonse M. D'Amato, the former senator. Donald J. Trump and other casino operators in Atlantic City who feared the competition lobbied against the project in Albany, while Sen. Robert Torricelli of New Jersey lobbied vigorously against it in Washington, and, as recently as April 7, he warned that the Mohawks would bring crime to the Catskills and northern New Jersey.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Torricelli has had a change of heart. The senator, who is friendly with Mr. Cummis and Mr. Goldberg and has received thousands of dollars in political contributions from executives at the gambling company, said he now recognized that the battle against Indian gambling has been lost.</p>
        <p>''I think gaming in Monticello is probably an inevitability,'' Mr. Torricelli said. ''It seems to me that Park Place is offering a good deal.''</p>
        <p>The emergence of Park Place has made Governor Pataki's next step more uncertain. He had chastised Mr. Torricelli last summer for opposing the New York casino, and both critics and supporters of gambling said that he had seemed to be lining up to approve a Monticello casino.</p>
        <p>The role of Park Place ''adds to the long list of questions surrounding this whole situation,'' said Michael McKeon, a spokesman for Governor Pataki. ''Every day seems to bring another new development.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
