<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supreme Court Roundup; Justices Reject Ruling Based on an Amended Law</title>
    <meta content="Y02SCOT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Harris County (Tex)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carmell, Scott L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Search and Seizure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6D61239F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supreme Court Roundup; Justices Reject Ruling Based on an Amended Law</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court, in 5-to-4 decision, overturns sex abuse conviction of Scott L Carmell on ground that change in Texas law had made it easier for prosecution to prove its case than at time crime was committed; rules 6 to 3 in Christensen v Harris County, Tex, that state and local governments can require their employees to use their accumulated compensatory time by taking paid time off, even if employees would prefer to keep accumulating 'comp days'; accepts appeal by Illinois and agrees to decide whether police can stop residents from entering their own homes during time it takes to get search warrant (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court took an expansive view today of the Constitution's bar against retroactive legislation, overturning a Texas man's sex abuse conviction on the ground that a change in state law had made it easier for the prosecution to prove its case than at the time the crime was committed.</p>
        <p>The 5-to-4 decision was unusually interesting in several respects, not the least of which was the extensive debate between the two sides over the current meaning of one of the Supreme Court's earliest important rulings, a case from 1798 called Calder v. Bull.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court took an expansive view today of the Constitution's bar against retroactive legislation, overturning a Texas man's sex abuse conviction on the ground that a change in state law had made it easier for the prosecution to prove its case than at the time the crime was committed.</p>
        <p>The 5-to-4 decision was unusually interesting in several respects, not the least of which was the extensive debate between the two sides over the current meaning of one of the Supreme Court's earliest important rulings, a case from 1798 called Calder v. Bull.</p>
        <p>At the time, and for many years thereafter, that decision provided the definitive interpretation of what the Constitution's framers meant when they barred Congress and the states from passing any ''ex post facto law.'' The question for the court today was whether the broad definition adopted by Justice Samuel Chase's opinion had been eroded by more modern cases, and the 40-page majority opinion by Justice John Paul Stevens concluded that it had not.</p>
        <p>The justices' lineup, cutting across all ideological boundaries on the court, was another notable feature of the decision today. Joining Justice Stevens were Justices Antonin Scalia, David H. Souter, Clarence Thomas and Stephen G. Breyer. Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg wrote a dissenting opinion, which Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and Justices Sandra Day O'Connor and Anthony M. Kennedy also signed.</p>
        <p>In overturning a ruling by the Texas Court of Appeals, the court also rejected the Clinton administration's argument that the state court had correctly taken a narrow view of the current meaning of the ex post facto clause.</p>
        <p>There was no dispute on the court over the most commonly held definitions of the ex post facto prohibition: that it prevents prosecution for an act that was not a crime at the time it was performed, as well as the imposition of a different or greater punishment than conviction for a crime had previously entailed.</p>
        <p>Rather, the debate was over whether an alteration of the rules of evidence, in a manner that did not redefine the crime or the punishment, could amount to an ex post facto violation. Texas, the Texas courts, the Clinton administration and the dissenters today maintained that it could not. The majority held that it could, finding that the state's relaxation of an evidentiary rule for prosecuting sex crimes had an effect, as applied to the defendant in this case, that was ''as grossly unfair'' as any of the other, more common examples of ex post facto legislation.</p>
        <p>The defendant, Scott L. Carmell, who made a living counseling victims of incest, was convicted on 15 counts of sexually abusing his teenage stepdaughter from 1991 to 1995, when the girl was between 12 and 15 years old. At issue in the case today, Carmell v. Texas, No. 98-7540, were the only 4 of the 15 convictions that were affected by a 1993 change in the Texas criminal sex offense law.</p>
        <p>Before that time, in the absence of corroboration, a person could be convicted on the victim's testimony alone only if the victim had told someone else about the offense within six months, a requirement known as an ''outcry'' provision. But there was an exception for victims under the age of 14, for whom there was no separate requirement for either corroboration or for having told another person; on the young victim's testimony alone, the prosecution could try to convince a jury beyond a reasonable doubt that the crime occurred as the victim alleged.</p>
        <p>In 1993, the Texas Legislature raised to 18 from 14 the age at which there did not have to be an outcry. At Mr. Carmell's 1997 trial, the state applied the amended law. Because the victim had not made the required outcry, this made possible Mr. Carmell's prosecution for the four incidents that occurred after his stepdaughter's 14th birthday.</p>
        <p>The court's decision today overturning the four convictions is not likely to have an effect on Mr. Carmell; he is serving two life sentences for his conviction on the two most serious charges of aggravated sexual assault for incidents that occurred before the girl was 14 and that were not at issue in his appeal. The 13 remaining convictions together drew a 20-year concurrent sentence.</p>
        <p>The Texas Court of Appeals upheld Mr. Carmell's conviction on the four disputed counts, ruling that the application of the amended law was not an ex post facto violation because the amendment involved a procedural rule and did not ''increase the punishment nor change the elements of the offense that the state must prove.''</p>
        <p>In overturning that decision today, Justice Stevens said the amendment did something equally important: it ''changed the quantum of evidence necessary to sustain a conviction.''</p>
        <p>''Under the law in effect at the time the acts were committed, the prosecution's case was legally insufficient,'' Justice Stevens said, noting that Mr. Carmell would have been legally entitled to a judgment of acquittal. Only by applying the amendment, he said, could the state take its case to a jury based solely on the victim's uncorroborated testimony.</p>
        <p>''The elements of unfairness and injustice in subverting the presumption of innocence are directly implicated by rules lowering the quantum of evidence required to convict,'' Justice Stevens said. ''Such rules will always run in the prosecution's favor, because they always make it easier to convict the accused.''</p>
        <p>Changes in ordinary procedural rules that do not involve the sufficiency of the evidence needed for a conviction would not necessarily be a violation of the ex post facto prohibition, he said.</p>
        <p>In her dissenting opinion, Justice Ginsburg said that in its ''expansive new reading'' of the ex post facto clause, the majority misconstrued the Texas amendment as changing the amount of evidence the prosecution needed. She said the amendment did not lower the ''sufficiency of the evidence hurdle; it simply expanded the range of methods the state could use to surmount it.''</p>
        <p>The amendment was more accurately described as a ''rule of admissibility,'' Justice Ginsburg said, and its retroactive application was not inconsistent with the ''fundamental purposes'' of the ex post facto clause. She described those purposes as ''ensuring fair notice so that individuals can rely on the laws in force at the time they engage in conduct and sustaining the separation of powers while preventing the passage of vindictive legislation.''</p>
        <p>There were also these developments at the court today.</p>
        <p>Compensatory Time</p>
        <p>The court ruled, 6 to 3, that state and local governments can require their employees to use their accumulated compensatory time by taking paid time off, even if the employees would prefer to keep accumulating ''comp days.''</p>
        <p>The decision, Christensen v. Harris County, No. 98-1167, upheld a ruling by the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit, in New Orleans. It does not apply to private sector employment, where employers are generally required by the Fair Labor Standards Act to compensate their employees in cash for overtime work.</p>
        <p>A 1985 amendment to the Fair Labor Standards Act, intended to cushion the impact of a Supreme Court decision that upheld the application of federal wages and hours standards to the states, permitted public employers to use comp time instead of cash overtime if their employees agreed. Over certain maximums, cash still has to be paid, and the employer also retains the option of paying cash for unused time.</p>
        <p>In this case, Harris County, Tex., wanted to limit its eventual liability by requiring its deputy sheriffs to use up their accumulated comp time. The lower federal courts disagreed on whether employers could impose such a requirement without the employees' agreement. In this case, the deputy sheriffs filed suit with the support of the Department of Labor.</p>
        <p>Writing for the court today, Justice Thomas said there was nothing in the Fair Labor Standards Act amendment to prohibit employers from adopting such a policy. He said the Labor Department's informal interpretation to the contrary was not a formal regulation and was not entitled to the court's deference. Justices Stevens, Ginsburg and Breyer dissented.</p>
        <p>Search Warrant</p>
        <p>Demonstrating that the convoluted law of search and seizure never runs out of new permutations, the court accepted an appeal by the state of Illinois and agreed to decide whether the police can stop residents from entering their own homes during the time it takes to get a search warrant to search the home.</p>
        <p>In a splintered 1984 decision, the court suggested that the police could secure the premises from the inside, but did not resolve whether they can effectively evict the occupant to prevent destruction of evidence during the hours it takes for a search warrant to be issued.</p>
        <p>In this case, Illinois v. McArthur, No. 99-1132, the state is appealing a ruling by the Illinois Appellate Court. Suppressing evidence of the marijuana that the police in Sullivan, Ill., found in a trailer when they eventually executed a search warrant, the state court said the refusal to allow the trailer's owner to enter during the two hours' wait for the warrant amounted to an unconstitutional seizure.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
