<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y02BRI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196240"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E1D91239F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1773" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>IRELAND: ORANGEMEN CANCEL  The Orange Order has canceled a May 28 march in Dublin that would have been the Protestant group's first there since 1937. Ian Cox, an Orange official, said he took the action because the order, widely viewed as anti-Catholic, had received ''abusive letters and phone calls'' and city officials had ''abandoned'' the organizers. The order holds hundreds of parades in Northern Ireland in the annual ''marching season'' that began last week.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>IRELAND: ORANGEMEN CANCEL  The Orange Order has canceled a May 28 march in Dublin that would have been the Protestant group's first there since 1937. Ian Cox, an Orange official, said he took the action because the order, widely viewed as anti-Catholic, had received ''abusive letters and phone calls'' and city officials had ''abandoned'' the organizers. The order holds hundreds of parades in Northern Ireland in the annual ''marching season'' that began last week.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>AUSTRIA: HAIDER OUT  Jorg Haider officially resigned after 14 years as head of the rightist Freedom Party. He was replaced by Vice Chancellor Susanne Riess-Passer, left, Mr. Haider's personal choice, after delegates to the party congress overwhelmingly elected her. Mr. Haider announced in February that he would be stepping down, but the official change was left for the congress in Klagenfurt, capital of Carinthia Province, where Mr. Haider, 50, is governor.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: POLICE BODIES FOUND  The military said it had found the bodies of nine Russian policemen near the Chechen town of Vedeno. The policemen came from the Perm region of Russia and were part of a column ambushed on March 29. The discovery raises the death toll from that ambush to at least 36. Chechen rebels claim to have taken the nine policemen prisoner and executed them after Moscow refused to turn over a Russian officer accused of killing a Chechen woman.</p>
        <p>Michael R. Gordon (NYT)</p>
        <p>SWITZERLAND: HEALTH SPENDING  Less than 10 percent of the more than $56 billion spent each year on health research goes to conditions, including tuberculosis and malaria, that account for 90 percent of the world's health problems, a Geneva-based health group said. Health research is disproportionately focused on diseases of concern to high-income countries, the report said. The study said pneumonia and diarrheal diseases are the biggest killers, but only one-fifth of 1 percent of research dollars is spent on them.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Olson (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>MEXICO: GOVERNOR REMOVED  Ending an impeachment trial, the supreme court of Morelos State ruled that Gov. Jorge Carrillo Olea ''never showed any interest in upholding the principle of legality'' during his tenure. The court removed Mr. Carrillo from office and barred him from holding any public post for 12 years. Mr. Carrillo took a leave of absence in 1998 amid a burgeoning kidnapping and narcotics scandal, but kept his title as governor.</p>
        <p>Sam Dillon (NYT)</p>
        <p>PERU: MAY 28 RUNOFF  The runoff vote between President Alberto Fujimori and Alejandro Toledo will be held May 28, the National Election Board said. The date was announced after the board received final returns from the April 9 first round election, in which neither candidate received the required majority. Polls show the vote will be close.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>ARGENTINA: EXTRADITION REJECTED  The government has formally rejected a request by Judge Baltasar Garzon of Spain to arrest ex-military leaders for the deaths of Spaniards during the 1976-83 dictatorship, according to judicial documents. The request was rejected because it was not accompanied by a demand for extradition, the documents showed. The position taken by President Fernando de la Rua is close to that of former President Carlos Saul Menem.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: SETTLERS REMOVED  For the second day in a row, soldiers forcibly removed settlers from a hilltop in the West Bank. The short-lived, makeshift encampment, reflecting a growing protest movement by the settlers, was in the Nablus area.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: BLUNT 'DISCLOSURE'  Oded Eran, the senior Israeli peace negotiator, said bluntly in Eilat what everyone here knows: that a Palestinian state will be the outcome of the final-status peace talks. But the Prime Minister's office was bothered by the baldness of his public statement and issued a clarification: What Mr. Eran meant to say, the statement said, was that if there is a Palestinian state, it will be as a result of negotiations.</p>
        <p>Deborah Sontag (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SIERRA LEONE: U.N. OFFICER WOUNDED  A Nigerian officer in the United Nations peacekeeping force was seriously wounded after a skirmish with rebels near Port Loko, a center for refugees and former combatants wishing to disarm. The rebels are former soldiers who, like thousands of members of the Revolutionary United Front, have refused to respect a peace pact that calls for total disarmament.</p>
        <p>Norimitsu Onishi (NYT)</p>
        <p>ALGERIA: RIGHTS CURBS  Members of Amnesty International will not meet Islamist leaders during the rights group's 10-day visit starting today, a government official said. Diplomats and Algerian rights campaigners have said there are few prospects that any of the four rights groups invited to Algeria will be free to investigate accusations of abuses by the army in its fight with Islamist militants.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>JAPAN: TAKESHITA BOWS OUT  Citing ill health, former Prime Minister Noboru Takeshita, one of Japan's most powerful postwar figures, announced his retirement from politics. Mr. Takeshita, first elected to Parliament in 1958, was prime minister for less than 18 months, starting in 1998 and resigning because of a stock distribution scandal. But he remained undisputed kingmaker during much of the 1980's and early 90's.</p>
        <p>Howard W. French (NYT)</p>
        <p>SRI LANKA: REBELS ADVANCE  Tamil Tiger rebels overran another town in their march toward their former capital, Jaffna, raising worries among some of the city's 500,000 residents. The rebels said they took over Pallai, between Elephant Pass, the entry to the Jaffna Peninsula captured April 22, and Jaffna city.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
