<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Actors Strike Against Radio and Television Advertisers</title>
    <meta content="Y02STR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000510T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Screen Actors Guild</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Federation of Television and Radio Artists</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitaker, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DB1339F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Actors Strike Against Radio and Television Advertisers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA WHITAKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitaker, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Screen Actors Guild and American Federation of Television and Radio Advertisers, for first time in 12 years, calls on their combined membership of about 135,000 actors to stop working on all television and radio commercials at 12:01 am on May 1 until agreement can be reached with advertisers; residual payments for commercial work are at heart of disagreement; for years, actors in commercials used on network television have received payments every time an ad runs in practice known as 'pay per play'; for commercials on cable television actors receive flat rate; commercial advertisers want flat rate used by cable to be adopted across the board, while unions want to see pay-per-play extended to cable advertisers; actors demonstrate in New York City, Los Angeles, San Francisco and Chicago; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time in 12 years, the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists called on their combined membership of about 135,000 actors to stop working on all television and radio commercials at 12:01 a.m. today until an agreement could be reached with advertisers.</p>
        <p>Residual payments for commercial work are at the heart of the disagreement between the actors -- who rallied here today and in New York, Chicago and San Francisco -- and television and radio advertisers. For years, actors in commercials used on network television have received payments every time an ad runs in a practice known as ''pay per play.'' For commercials on cable television actors receive a flat rate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the first time in 12 years, the Screen Actors Guild and the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists called on their combined membership of about 135,000 actors to stop working on all television and radio commercials at 12:01 a.m. today until an agreement could be reached with advertisers.</p>
        <p>Residual payments for commercial work are at the heart of the disagreement between the actors -- who rallied here today and in New York, Chicago and San Francisco -- and television and radio advertisers. For years, actors in commercials used on network television have received payments every time an ad runs in a practice known as ''pay per play.'' For commercials on cable television actors receive a flat rate.</p>
        <p>A placard stating ''Please Don't Squeeze the Actor'' summed up the attitude of an estimated 2,000 actors as they marched down Wilshire Boulevard today.</p>
        <p>Frank Simmons, an actor who marched, said the disparity between the two sides could be vast. For example, he cited the residual payments he received for working in a recent General Motors commercial. Over a three-month period on cable, he said he received a flat fee of $1,100, although the commercial was shown several times a day.</p>
        <p>During the same period on the networks, he said the commercial brought him nearly $40,000.</p>
        <p>''This is about as good as economic times are going to get and by suggesting to get rid of residuals they're basically asking for a pay cut,'' said Greg Krizman, a spokesman for the guilds.</p>
        <p>Commercial advertisers want the flat rate used by cable to be adopted across the board while the unions want to see pay-per-play extended to cable advertising.</p>
        <p>Under the advertisers' most recent proposal, the lead actor's fees for unlimited use of a commercial on cable in a 13-week cycle would increase 60 percent.</p>
        <p>Actors' representatives say that times have changed since they negotiated the flat-rate portion of their contract. In those days, cable was a struggling enterprise and unions across the country were making concessions during hard economic times.</p>
        <p>But in today's booming economy, with cable television well entrenched union representatives say it is time to share the wealth.</p>
        <p>''They boast of record profits,'' said Todd Amorde, a Screen Actors Guild board member and joint chairman of the unions' strike committee. ''We want our fair share. It's very simple.''</p>
        <p>Advertisers counter that with the decline in network viewership and an audience dispersed over a greater number of networks, they must show a commercial more often to reach viewers. They have contended that the unions' demands would increase the cost of cable television commercials by 350 percent.</p>
        <p>''We think the use of the concept is obsolete particularly with the exploding venues for watching television,'' said John A. McGuinn, chief negotiator for the Association of National Advertisers Inc. and the American Association of Advertising Agencies, the two major industry trade groups.</p>
        <p>He noted that the per-use concept was born in the 1950's when the three networks delivered 90 percent of the television households. The three network now deliver less than 50 percent of the audience, he said.</p>
        <p>Talks between the two groups broke down in mid-April and attempts in recent days by federal mediators to bring the two groups back together were unsuccessful.</p>
        <p>Screen Actors and American Federation representatives, who have said they would try to shut down production on television and radio commercials made after the strike began, said they knew of no production going on today.</p>
        <p>Richard E. Posell, an entertainment lawyer who represents production companies, said he knew of no companies that were shooting today and predicted they would not work, at least in the United States, during the strike.</p>
        <p>''The loss of commercial business is an enormous blow to the entertainment community and the economy at large particularly Los Angeles and New York,'' Mr. Posell said.</p>
        <p>He noted that commercial production is estimated to represent about 60 percent of Screen Actors Guild income, or about $720 million annually.</p>
        <p>''It's a lot of money,'' he said. ''It's going to effect not only the production business but I think the economy of Southern California.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 10, 2000, Wednesday  An article in Business Day on May 2 about a strike by actors in television and radio commercials misspelled one striker's surname and referred incorrectly to his comments about the pay disparity between cable and network television. The actor is Frank Simons, not Simmons. He said he would have earned $40,000 if his commercial had run as often on the networks as on cable. He did not say that that occurred.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 10, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on May 2 about a strike by actors in television and radio commercials misspelled one striker's surname and referred incorrectly to his comments about the pay disparity between cable and network television. The actor is Frank Simons, not Simmons. He said he would have earned $40,000 if his commercial had run as often on the networks as on cable. He did not say that that occurred.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
