<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hardaway Adds Mystery to Familiar Pairing</title>
    <meta content="02HEAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196284"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Heat</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nobles, Charlie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7DD1339F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hardaway Adds Mystery to Familiar Pairing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nobles, Charlie</byline>
      <dateline>COCONUT GROVE, Fla., May 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses matchups for New York Knickerbockers-Miami Heat playoff series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a series between two familiar rivals that offers little potential for surprise, one significant question looms over the Knicks-Miami Heat matchup that begins Sunday: will Tim Hardaway, who has a sprained left foot, be able to play effectively, and if not, can the Heat still win?</p>
        <p>''I'm not answering questions like that,'' said Hardaway, whose status is questionable for the four-of-seven-game series. ''I'm just trying to get myself ready.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a series between two familiar rivals that offers little potential for surprise, one significant question looms over the Knicks-Miami Heat matchup that begins Sunday: will Tim Hardaway, who has a sprained left foot, be able to play effectively, and if not, can the Heat still win?</p>
        <p>''I'm not answering questions like that,'' said Hardaway, whose status is questionable for the four-of-seven-game series. ''I'm just trying to get myself ready.''</p>
        <p>Miami center Alonzo Mourning pondered the same question as he leaned against the gym wall at the Heat's practice today.</p>
        <p>''We're capable of beating the Knicks, period,'' he said. ''We beat the Knicks without me sitting on the bench. I know playoff basketball is different, but, yeah, you can.</p>
        <p>''I know it will make the job a whole lot easier with him on the floor. But that's neither here nor there. We can't really worry about it. We have to think about what we have now. If Timmy comes back, that's just extra ammunition for our guns.''</p>
        <p>Mourning said he would not discuss Hardaway's availability as the team's No. 1 point guard.</p>
        <p>''I think that's San Antonio's problem,'' Mourning said. ''They've worried about Tim Duncan instead of going out and playing the game and trying to win. We're not going to do that. Timmy is going to come back when he's ready. He knows what he has to do. If he doesn't come back, so be it.''</p>
        <p>Hardaway's status provides one of the few areas of suspense. This will be the fourth straight playoff meeting between these teams.</p>
        <p>But familiarity does not diminish the passions that this matchup stirs.  ''It is only fitting that we go through New York to get to where we want to go,'' Mourning said today after Miami's initial practice at LaSalle High School.</p>
        <p>The Heat is aware that the Knicks have won two of three playoff series between these teams. All have gone the maximum length, with the Knicks winning the last two.</p>
        <p>''If you really want to break it down and dissect it, I didn't play two years ago in the final game,'' Mourning said. ''Then Timmy was hurt last year and they got a bounce with a little over four seconds left. I mean, that's what I look at in those two series.'' He was referring to Allan Houston's winning shot that eliminated Miami last year.</p>
        <p>The Heat is looking for redemption now, though it is careful not to be too inflammatory about saying it.</p>
        <p>''If you want to call it redemption or if you want to call them our nemesis or whatever, so be it,'' said Hardaway, Miami's veteran point guard, who missed all three games of the Heat's first-round elimination of Detroit. ''We've just got to come out here and understand what we didn't do the last two years and do it. We've got the home-court advantage and we've got to put it to use.''</p>
        <p>Houston's late shot last season sent the Heat into the off-season vowing to redouble its dedication to conditioning. And that work is ready to pay off now, according to the power forward P. J. Brown.</p>
        <p>''We just believe it's our time,'' Brown said. ''We're going to come out and play hard. We've put in a lot of hard work since 'the situation,' and we're ready to leave it all out on the floor.''</p>
        <p>Pat Riley, the ex-Knicks coach who coaches the Heat, responded  sarcastically today when the Knicks' playoff edge over his team was mentioned.</p>
        <p>''Do we have to beat them to get over a mental hump, or is it to make my life better?'' he said. ''Or is it to make my peace of mind, you know, so I can wake up in the morning the next day? Or when I'm 65 years old I won't have any nightmares? No, I'm past that now.''</p>
        <p>Riley said it is possible the Knicks may have a psychological edge in this series, but he doubts it. ''Not the way the losses have gone down.''</p>
        <p>The coach called this matchup a ''fait accompli,'' but obviously didn't want to dwell on Miami's past failures.</p>
        <p>''While you have to look back in order to get a bead on the future,'' he said, ''the important thing now is to look around at the present moment.''</p>
        <p>While Riley talked, Hardaway  worked on his endurance on an exercise machine. Riley made it plain that he won't answer questions this week on Hardaway's health and said Hardaway won't, either.</p>
        <p>Because of the snail-like pace of the National Basketball Association's playoff schedule this season, Hardaway will have some extra time to heal. Brown, the power forward, says there are not many surprises left in this series.</p>
        <p>''There's only so much you can say,'' Brown said. ''Pretty much everything that could be said, good or bad, has been said over the last three years. We know what they're about; they know what we're about. But I will say this is a weird series in that home-court advantage seems to mean absolutely nothing. They feel comfortable coming down here and winning and we feel comfortable going up there and winning in the Garden.''</p>
        <p>Riley, meanwhile, is slowly easing his players into Sunday's opener. The coach held today's practice to an atypically short one and a hours and didn't discuss game strategy. ''We did not even mention New York,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The team will have a similar practice on Tuesday, then head for Florida Atlantic University in Boca Raton, Fla., for two-a-day practices on Wednesday and Thursday.</p>
        <p>Riley is concerned about beginning his game buildup too early, if that is possible.</p>
        <p>''We've waited a long time to reach our goals,'' the veteran guard Dan Majerle said, ''and the Knicks are in our way.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
