<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. Politely Searches For an Alternative, Fast</title>
    <meta content="11GIUL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198635"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MAYOR'S SEPARATION: THE REVERBERATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forstmann, Theodore J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5D9163BF932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. Politely Searches For an Alternative, Fast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses impact of statement made by Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani concerning his marital problems on his Senate candidacy; state Republican leaders are already looking to Rep Rick A Lazio and Wall Street investor Theodore J Forstmann as possible candidates if Giuliani should decide not to run; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani was still the Republican candidate for Senate last night, even after yesterday's tumultuous turn of events. But state Republican leaders were already turning their sights on two Republicans -- a Long Island congressman and a wealthy Wall Street philanthropist -- to step into the race in case Mr. Giuliani drops out of the contest with Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>One of the potential candidates, Representative Rick A. Lazio of Long Island, spoke by telephone last evening with William D. Powers, the state Republican chairman, to review the prospects of his entering the race should Mr. Giuliani not run, Republican officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani was still the Republican candidate for Senate last night, even after yesterday's tumultuous turn of events. But state Republican leaders were already turning their sights on two Republicans -- a Long Island congressman and a wealthy Wall Street philanthropist -- to step into the race in case Mr. Giuliani drops out of the contest with Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>One of the potential candidates, Representative Rick A. Lazio of Long Island, spoke by telephone last evening with William D. Powers, the state Republican chairman, to review the prospects of his entering the race should Mr. Giuliani not run, Republican officials said.</p>
        <p>The second, Theodore J. Forstmann, a Wall Street investor who personally financed a program to allow poor children to attend private schools, was moving to set up meetings with Republican leaders next week to discuss his own prospective candidacy, his associates said.</p>
        <p>The sudden flurry of activity in what had been seen as Mr. Giuliani's uncontested bid for the nomination came amid signs of confusion and concern among party leaders struggling to keep abreast of a rapid day of revelations about Mr. Giuliani and his marriage to Donna Hanover.</p>
        <p>Although most Republicans offered public support for Mr. Giuliani, insisting that the disclosures would not hurt his standing with voters,  there was clear evidence of concern over whether the mayor would stay in the race and, if he did, whether he would be a seriously weakened opponent to Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>An hour after Mr. Giuliani announced that he and Donna Hanover were seeking a separation, a senior New York Republican described it as a favorable development, contending that it would put an end to intensive coverage in the New York tabloids about his close friendship with Judith Nathan, a pharmaceuticals executive. But 20 minutes after Ms. Hanover held her own news conference to say that Mr. Giuliani had had ''a relationship'' with a staff member, the same Republican called back to retract the statement: ''My quote no longer stands -- even on an anonymous basis.''</p>
        <p>And Guy V. Molinari, the Staten Island borough president and typically one of Mr. Giuliani's most loyal defenders, declined a request for an interview yesterday to discuss this latest episode in the mayor's political life.</p>
        <p>In a day of almost unheard-of turmoil in the New York Republican Party, Mr. Lazio and Mr. Forstmann moved gingerly to position themselves in the event that Mr. Giuliani dropped out, without, their aides said, doing anything to appear as if they were taking ungraceful advantage of Mr. Giuliani's difficulties.  Aides to both men said they would enter the race only if Mr. Giuliani dropped out.</p>
        <p>The mayor's aides said that Mr. Giuliani had not made a final decision about his future, though his own associates -- who were caught off guard by Mr. Giuliani's announcement -- described themselves as increasingly pessimistic that Mr. Giuliani would make the race.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Giuliani announced last week that he had prostate cancer, he said that he hoped to make a decision about whether he would stay in the race, based on his treatment, by the middle of May. Some Republicans, concerned that the disclosures about Mr. Giuliani's personal life could make him a weaker candidate, said yesterday that they hoped Mr. Giuliani would not linger if he intended to abandon the race.</p>
        <p>The Republican convention is May 30. But time is pressing for the Republican Party, because Mr. Lazio and Mr. Forstmann are both unknown and inexperienced candidates, and thus could find themselves disadvantaged in a race with Mrs. Clinton, who has spent nearly a year on the campaign trail.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio would also have to move to raise money to finance the campaign, a particularly urgent need in order to pay for television advertisements to present himself to voters.</p>
        <p>An aide to Mr. Forstmann said he was prepared to finance his own race. One senior Republican said that Mr. Forstmann's wealth, and his asserted interest in paying for his own campaign, was one of his great potential assets. That said, there is an established history of wealthy people running for office for the first time and failing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio had, with the tacit support of Gov. George E. Pataki, threatened to run a primary against Mr. Giuliani for the Republican nomination last fall. He backed off, reluctantly, in response to pressure from Republicans who saw Mr. Giuliani as the party's strongest candidate. Through a spokesman, Mr. Lazio clearly signaled his continuing interest in the race tonight, but said, ''I shall take no action regarding the U.S. Senate race until the mayor announces his decision.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki has been mentioned by Republicans as the strongest potential replacement, given his statewide recognition, popularity and fund-raising ability. But his advisers repeated yesterday that the governor had no interest in the Senate.</p>
        <p>It was a day of dark humor at Mr. Giuliani's campaign headquarters, where aides, at once giddy and gloomy, relied on television and newspaper reporters to track developments in their candidate's life. Across the state, Republican supporters of Mr. Giuliani argued that developments in the mayor's personal life would have no bearing on the campaign, and that the announcement of the separation would remove the issue of Mr. Giuliani's marriage from the table.</p>
        <p>''He should go full steam ahead,'' said State Senator Roy M. Goodman, the Manhattan Republican leader. ''I do not think it will affect the political picture at all. It's strictly a personal matter.''</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Giuliani's advisers said last night that the latest news could turn to his advantage, by presenting the mayor as human and candid. But other Republicans warned that the disclosures about Mr. Giuliani's personal life would more likely raise questions about him among conservative, upstate and female voters, a measure of doubt that he could not afford in a race that polls show to be very close.</p>
        <p>''None of this helps,'' said Nelson Warfield, who was the spokesman for Bob Dole's presidential campaign in 1996, and who has has been a frequent critic of Mr. Giuliani. ''It's mere happy talk to suggest it humanizes him. Nobody needs to be humanized this way.''</p>
        <p>THE MAYOR'S SEPARATION: THE REVERBERATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
