<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Invasion of the Design Lab Mutants</title>
    <meta content="11MATE$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRADE SECRETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Material Connexion</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Stephen P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Trade Secrets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2DD1F38F932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Invasion of the Design Lab Mutants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN P. WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Stephen P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Growing number of designers are bypassing traditional materials for wide range of less costly industrial supplies; are experimenting with unconventional fabrics and resins; Material Connexion, for-profit private archive, is Manhattan source for new materials; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE was a time, in the distant 80's, when Corian was such an exotic material it had to be installed by licensed technicians. Now, it's just another tired surface at Home Depot, and everyone is lusting for raw concrete countertops that resemble picnic tables at a state penitentiary.</p>
        <p>New materials for the home are being introduced daily, some with the half-lives of fashion accessories. Recently, a fabric coated with Philippine chicken feathers came on the market, in the form of lampshades. Surely some enterprising design aficionado already has fantasies about feathering his breakfast nook. Can infamy, and Kmart, be far behind?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE was a time, in the distant 80's, when Corian was such an exotic material it had to be installed by licensed technicians. Now, it's just another tired surface at Home Depot, and everyone is lusting for raw concrete countertops that resemble picnic tables at a state penitentiary.</p>
        <p>New materials for the home are being introduced daily, some with the half-lives of fashion accessories. Recently, a fabric coated with Philippine chicken feathers came on the market, in the form of lampshades. Surely some enterprising design aficionado already has fantasies about feathering his breakfast nook. Can infamy, and Kmart, be far behind?</p>
        <p>Homeowners of America, the future is here. Picture a house clad with shiny steel shingles. Imagine traversing a floor made of glass tiles suspended several inches in the air on thin metal posts. Would you feel safe sleeping next to walls made of loose rock held in place by supersize garden fencing? How would the neighbors react to a house built from concrete pig-sty partitions?</p>
        <p>All these materials and more are available from a growing number of designers who are bypassing traditional materials -- wood, plaster and marble -- for less costly industrial supplies. Driven by budget, or simply eager to explore the sculptural possibilities and light transmission of unconventional fabrics and resins, designers read chemistry journals, NASA Web sites and labels in hardware stores. They advocate chemical filters as wallpaper and medical gel packs as seat cushions.</p>
        <p>''We're undergoing a design revolution in the use of materials these days,'' said Paola Antonelli, an associate curator in the department of architecture and design at the Museum of Modern Art. She foresaw this change in her groundbreaking 1995 show at the Modern called ''Mutant Materials,'' which credited scientists with inventing the new materials that architects and designers use in unorthodox ways.</p>
        <p>Material Connexion is the place to find these new materials in Manhattan. Anyone with $500 for four hours of assisted research is welcome to explore this for-profit private archive at 4 Columbus Circle. The architecture team Diller &amp; Scofidio thumbed through the thousands of samples on file to research materials for their innovative redesign of the Brasserie restaurant on East 53rd Street. The cash-poor can view design riches in free lobby exhibits.</p>
        <p>While Material Connexion has its share of natural materials like coconut fabric and bamboo paneling, most of the samples are plastic or metal. Design-minded inhabitants of the late 20th century considered fake materials declasse, but today's strivers say materials can't be fake enough. Brazenly artificial resins, chemical foams and bizarre three-dimensional fabrics are all the rage.</p>
        <p>''I hope the changes we're seeing now will be as radical as what happened in the 60's,'' said George Beylerian, who founded Material Connexion four years ago. ''Plexiglass was new. Urethanes. Beautiful lacquers and plastics. Materials then made designers jump. I give the equation M equals D: materials drive design.''</p>
        <p>Maybe so. But it's also true that materials can drive architects and designers crazy. The very fact of its newness means that a material has to be tested before it is used, to be sure it is strong enough and doesn't have some undesirable quality like toxic vapors. Building codes offer some protection against faulty applications. And some decisions are obvious. For instance, the Swiss architects Jacques Herzog and Pierre de Meuron weren't taking engineering risks when they designed walls made of loose rock held in check by wire mesh cages at the Dominus Estate Winery in the Napa Valley. They knew that the mesh, called gabion, had been used to hold back rocky hillsides all over the Alps.</p>
        <p>OFTEN architects must don white coats and investigate. This willingness to explore is essential to the work of Jeff Parsons and Manuel Fernandez-Casteleiro of Manhattan, who used a transparent mesh divider in their White Street office made from tennis court fence windscreens, to add the appearance of structure without a wall. The architects' inventive nature prompted a Park Avenue couple to let them build an elevated glass floor in their apartment's art gallery/guest room. Mr. Parsons and Mr. Fernandez-Casteleiro designed the floor to reflect diffused light from the cloth-covered windows back up onto the paintings. In the process they gave the apartment some thrills.</p>
        <p>''Overnight guests said the reflections from the glass were so disorienting they feared having to make their way to the bathroom,'' said a beaming Mr. Fernandez-Casteleiro.</p>
        <p>He can beam because he knows there is no real danger. The architects designed the steel pegs and glass tiles themselves, laboriously pouring over computer simulations and a mock-up on their office floor to make sure the client would not be hearing the sound of breaking glass. The only person who ended up suffering was the apartment's housekeeper: The gap between the glass and the subfloor makes a perfect lint trap. But the only way to get a vacuum in there is to lift up the floor tiles one by one with a suction cup. Is this in anyone's job description?</p>
        <p>The apartment was recently sold, and one suspects the new owners will just rip everything out and start over, perhaps with something practical like a parquet floor imported from some chateau. But all is not lost. The couple asked the designers to make over their next town house.</p>
        <p>''We're thinking about mutating the glass floors to the walls as a way of dematerializing the interior of the town house,'' Mr. Fernandez-Casteleiro said. Housekeepers, pray for release to the god of Windex.</p>
        <p>But mutating is what these guys do best. They encased the bar at the East Village restaurant Coup in the same rubber used as shock absorbers in bridge construction. The finished bar has the look of unpolished black Corian and the feel of a bicycle grip. Equally surprising is that the deep mahogany colored ''wood'' panels in Coup are made from phenolic resin, a plastic normally used to insulate high-voltage switches.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Diller and Richard Scofidio -- who on Monday won the James Beard award for restaurant design for the Brasserie, in the windowless basement of the Seagram Building -- also specialize in mutating materials. Wanting to suggest  transparency at the entrance, they called on Mary Bright, who specializes in architectural curtains -- not the velvet kind. Ms. Bright suggested an entry curtain that appeared to billow even though it was immobile, and subjected mesh and plastic to  what she calls a stretch test, meaning she hung them in her studio for a few days to see if they changed shape. The resulting ''wall'' doesn't seem too far removed from a shower curtain, except for one curiously compelling detail. Faced with city ordinances, Ms. Bright installed shiny zippers that let a small panel of mesh curtain fall away, revealing an exit sign that glows mysteriously.</p>
        <p>Another ethereal glow emanates from the resin tables Ms. Diller and Mr. Scofidio designed for the restaurant. ''Elizabeth gave us pretty detailed drawings, with the metal understructure visible from above the tabletop,'' said Karen Atta, of Atta Inc., the workshop at 450 West 31st Street that made the tables. ''It was a real challenge to cast the understructure directly into the resin, which we'd never done before.''</p>
        <p>Resin, which is a type of cast plastic, tends to expand and contract at a faster rate than metal, and on Ms. Atta's first seven or eight attempts the resin cracked right off the metal as it cooled. Finally, she devised a way to slow the cooling process and solved the problem. Ms. Atta recently began selling similar tables to the public at prices ranging from $700 to $3,000 -- an example of how new materials can be more expensive than the old-fashioned ones.</p>
        <p>Dan Rockhill, an architect, and his associate, David Sain, take a similarly labor-intensive approach to the houses they build themselves around Lawrence, Kan., using hand-cut steel shingles and unpainted concrete panels. Mr. Rockhill continues his radical experiments with his students at the University of Kansas, who have banded together under the moniker Studio 804. They chose an unusual marine-grade plywood to clad a home built for a low-income family in Lawrence. The plywood is made from okoume, a water-resistant wood from Gabon -- available through North American Plywood in Santa Fe Springs, Calif. Studio 804 discovered it was harvested in a renewable method, is a lustrous brown,  is reasonably priced for good-looking wood siding at 89 cents a square foot, and needs only a coat of varnish.</p>
        <p>Future generations of au courant materials will not only have to look good and be strong, but will also need many of the senses that humans have, said Ms. Antonelli at the Modern. Foams now ''remember'' shapes, and there are fabrics that release antibacterial substances.</p>
        <p>Researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Media Laboratory envision superhuman abilities for future materials. They predict that the dividing line will blur between objects in the home and the computers that will run them. For these houses, far ''smarter'' than those being created today, materials had also better be on their toes.</p>
        <p>''Your shoes should be retrieving the day's personalized news from the carpet before you even have time to take off your coat,'' a Media Lab manifesto says. If these explorers have their way, weird plastics and chicken feather fabrics will soon seem as quaint as bricks and mortar.</p>
        <p>TRADE SECRETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
