<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Tangled Web in the Murder of a Rabbi's Wife</title>
    <meta content="11RABB" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cherry Hill (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daniels, Paul M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jenoff, Leonard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neulander, Fred J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neulander, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6DF163BF932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Tangled Web in the Murder of a Rabbi's Wife</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>CHERRY HILL, N.J., May 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses complex murder case in Cherry Hill, NJ, in which prominent Rabbi Fred Neulander is charged with hiring Leonard Jenoff and Paul Michael Daniels to murder his wife Carol; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For nearly four years, as the innuendo and accusations mounted about Rabbi Fred J. Neulander's role in the slaying of his wife, a burly, talkative man would buttonhole reporters, strenuously proclaim the rabbi's innocence and offer his own theories about who might have beaten Carol Neulander to death in the living room of her suburban Philadelphia home.</p>
        <p>Calling himself the rabbi's private investigator, a congregant and a close friend, Leonard Jenoff would alternately tell reporters that the 1994 murder was the work either of a bumbling burglar or an ill-trained terrorist. ''Russians or Israelis,'' he once whispered to a reporter for a local newspaper, The Jewish Exponent. ''That's all I can say.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For nearly four years, as the innuendo and accusations mounted about Rabbi Fred J. Neulander's role in the slaying of his wife, a burly, talkative man would buttonhole reporters, strenuously proclaim the rabbi's innocence and offer his own theories about who might have beaten Carol Neulander to death in the living room of her suburban Philadelphia home.</p>
        <p>Calling himself the rabbi's private investigator, a congregant and a close friend, Leonard Jenoff would alternately tell reporters that the 1994 murder was the work either of a bumbling burglar or an ill-trained terrorist. ''Russians or Israelis,'' he once whispered to a reporter for a local newspaper, The Jewish Exponent. ''That's all I can say.''</p>
        <p>Now he is saying a good deal more.</p>
        <p>According to the long-winded confession he made to prosecutors last week, Mr. Jenoff was the man Rabbi Neulander recruited to kill his wife. In September 1998, the rabbi was charged with planning his wife's murder.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jenoff told prosecutors that after confronting Ms. Neulander in the driveway of her home one evening, he choked on his fear, asked to use the bathroom and then slinked away. Instead, he told them, he paid his roommate, Paul Michael Daniels, to help carry out the killing a week later.</p>
        <p>On May 1, shortly after Mr. Jenoff made his confession, he and Mr. Daniels were arrested and charged with murder and conspiracy. Mr. Daniels, who is unemployed and who says he is mentally ill and a longtime drug addict, has told the authorities that he was paid for his role in the crime.</p>
        <p>The Camden County prosecutor has said he may seek the death penalty for all three defendants.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Neulander, who is free on bail, calls Mr. Jenoff's tale a fabrication. In an interview today, he emphatically proclaimed his innocence.  ''His story is entirely baseless,'' he said, sitting in the same room where the murder took place. ''I had nothing to do with the death of my wife.''</p>
        <p>To those who live in the amorphous subdivisions that sprawl east of the Delaware River in Camden County, last week's revelations added yet another layer of intrigue to a sensational crime. Ms. Neulander's murder has fascinated residents and traumatized those who know the 58-year-old rabbi, a charismatic figure who guided South Jersey's largest congregation.</p>
        <p>''It just keeps getting more and more surreal,'' said Pam Rosenblum, a mother of two young daughters who lives across the street from the Neulander home. ''We just wish this whole thing would come to an end already.''</p>
        <p>As detailed by prosecutors, the killing of Carol Neulander, 52, is a convoluted tale of deception that seems to defy common sense. Rabbi Neulander, they say, wanted his wife of 29 years dead so he could continue his affair with another woman, the host of a radio talk show in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors say he feared divorce proceedings would bring out his infidelity and threaten his position as the leader of M'kor Shalom, the synagogue he and his wife had started  two decades earlier.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Jenoff says he wielded the first of four blows that killed Ms. Neulander, he claims he, too, is a victim, saying the rabbi took advantage of his weaknesses. The lawyer for Mr. Daniels says the same thing about Mr. Jenoff: that he exploited someone he knew had limited mental capabilities.</p>
        <p>The conspiracy, as laid out by investigators, brings together three men seemingly with little in common: Rabbi Neulander, a community leader who was cherished by his congregation; Mr. Jenoff, 54, a recovering alcoholic bruised by a string of personal and professional losses; and Mr. Daniels, 26, a troubled soul who has spent his adult life addicted to cocaine and heroin.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Neulander's trial was originally scheduled for next month, although it has now been postponed until the fall. It was the impending  trial, Mr. Jenoff said, that prompted his confession. With an absence of hard evidence, Mr. Jenoff said, he feared that the rabbi might be acquitted.</p>
        <p>''He just wanted to do the right thing,'' said his lawyer, Francis J. Hartman. ''The truth was just eating away at him.''</p>
        <p>Last Friday, he summoned a Philadelphia Inquirer reporter, the Camden County prosecutor and a detective to a local diner to hear his story. Over coffee and a cup of fruit salad, he said the rabbi had lured him into the scheme with promises of $30,000 and help in getting a job with the Mossad, Israel's secret service.</p>
        <p>Although details of his account have changed twice in the last week, he now says he was initially lured into thinking his target was an enemy of Israel. Only later, after he had agreed to carry out the killing, did the rabbi reveal that the proposed victim was his wife, he said.</p>
        <p>Rabbi Neulander and his lawyers say Mr. Jenoff's story is pure fantasy. One lawyer, Dennis P. Wixted, described Mr. Jenoff as ''an oddball and eccentric,'' so desperate for attention he would make up a tall tale for 15 minutes of fame.</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Jenoff thought he could have his notoriety and escape prosecution through an immunity deal. So far he has not been offered a reward for his cooperation, although the prosecutor has not ruled out leniency.</p>
        <p>Despite the confessions of Mr. Jenoff and Mr. Daniels, Mr. Wixted said there was nothing to link the rabbi to his wife's death, ''no weapon, no fingerprints, no evidence,'' he said. As he had in the past, he described Ms. Neulander, the owner of two bakeries, as the victim of a robbery gone awry.</p>
        <p>Those who know Leonard Jenoff said his buoyant personality and relentless self-promotion masked a battered ego. In recent years, they said, he endured a stormy divorce, the collapse of his business, the loss of his home and alcoholism. In a town where most people own spacious colonials surrounded by well-fed lawns, Mr. Jenoff lived in a succession of modest rented apartments.</p>
        <p>In 1993, when Mr. Jenoff's life was at its most chaotic, a social service agency referred him to Rabbi Neulander, who provided financial assistance and spiritual guidance, lawyers for both men said.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Jenoff complained about having to attend Alcoholics Anonymous meetings at a church, Rabbi Neulander established a 12-step program at the synagogue. Both men were smokers who would stand outside the synagogue for cigarette breaks.</p>
        <p>In 1997, when Mr. Jenoff was married a second time, the rabbi offered his house for the ceremony. ''The rabbi did great things for my client,  but on the other hand it seems as if he was grooming him for this terrible crime,'' Mr. Hartman said.</p>
        <p>The rabbi and his lawyers play down the relationship, saying it never rose to the level of friendship. ''The guy's life was broken down, a mess,'' Mr. Wixted said. ''He came in for spiritual advice. That's how it started, and that's how it remained.''</p>
        <p>Even if the affections were not mutual, Mr. Jenoff became the rabbi's most vocal defender soon after Ms. Neulander's death. When the rabbi was mobbed by reporters after his arrest in 1998, Mr. Jenoff bravely escorted him through the crowds.</p>
        <p>''He may be guilty as sin of adultery,'' he announced to reporters at the time, ''but there's no evidence he hired anybody to kill his wife.''</p>
        <p>Rabbi Neulander has said he thought Mr. Jenoff's detective services were free, and either way, he never requested them in the first place.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wixted has suggested that Mr. Jenoff's decision to go to the authorities may be retribution for not receiving more money for his work. Mr. Wixted described his investigative efforts as farcical.</p>
        <p>''He once went to a psychic and came back with a sketch of what he said was the killer,'' Mr. Wixted said. ''I gave him a check for $750 and showed him the door.''</p>
        <p>The main thing Mr. Jenoff and Mr. Daniels shared, it seems, were their battles with addiction. They met at a  substance abuse clinic and later attended 12-step meetings together. In 1995 and 1996, they shared an apartment at the Landmark, a collection of white-brick high-rises in Cherry Hill.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daniels is a paranoid schizophrenic who has struggled with cocaine and heroin addiction since he was 16, said his lawyer, Craig Mitnick.</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Daniels had few friends and many demons. ''He lives the existence of very simple things,'' he said. ''He's very vulnerable and easily manipulated.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jenoff has said he paid his roommate $7,500 for his participation in the crime, a sum Mr. Mitnick said he could not confirm.</p>
        <p>According to lawyers for both men, Mr. Jenoff posed as a deliveryman on the night of the killing, Nov. 1, 1994. Once inside the home, they said, Mr. Jenoff knocked Ms. Neulander unconscious with a lead pipe. He then called in Mr. Daniels, who hit her twice more. Before the pair fled in his car, Mr. Jenoff delivered a final blow, lawyers for both men said.</p>
        <p>Shortly afterward, Rabbi Neulander came home from the synagogue to find his wife dead in a pool of blood. When detectives arrived, they noted that there was no blood on him, something they found unusual. The lack of blood suggested that he had not touched the body to check for a pulse or determine a condition, they said.</p>
        <p>Suspicions grew when the woman who was pressuring Rabbi Neulander to leave his wife told investigators about an exchange they had before the killing.</p>
        <p>''Trust me, something will happen by the end of the year,'' she told prosecutors. She also told them that after the murder the rabbi said,  ''See, I told you to trust me.''</p>
        <p>In the five and a half years since Ms. Neulander's death, Rabbi Neulander said he has struggled to lead a normal life. Although he was forced to resign his position at M'kor Shalom, he still presides over the occasional funeral and wedding. Most days he works as an educational consultant or spends his time on a book about his experiences in the rabbinate.</p>
        <p>Sitting in his living room this afternoon, wearing shorts and loafers, Rabbi Neulander appeared relaxed as he spoke about several topics, from his immigrant parents and the difficulties of maintaining a front lawn to bouts of loneliness, fear and humiliation.</p>
        <p>Scattered around the room were religious books, photographs of his three grown children and a harmonica he recently began learning to play.</p>
        <p>Many friends and former congregants have abandoned him, he said, but others have rallied to his side, including his children. ''They have been terrifically supportive,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He described the last few years as ''devastating and isolating,'' and said he was eager to go to trial.</p>
        <p>''I know it will be vile and embarrassing, but when it's all over, I'm sure the truth of my innocence will emerge,'' he said. ''Then the healing can begin.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
