<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Transforming Theater Row; An Unlikely Urban Drama Heads for a Happy Ending</title>
    <meta content="11ROW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theaters (Buildings)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square and 42d Street (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Shubert Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blumenthal, Ralph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Companies and Organizations/Shubert Organization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEEDC1F38F932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Transforming Theater Row; An Unlikely Urban Drama Heads for a Happy Ending</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH BLUMENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blumenthal, Ralph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Previously makeshift project to turn seediest sex strip on West 42d Street into Theater Row takes final form with signing of contracts for 499-seat Shubert theater, five new or rebuilt smaller theaters and 40-story apartment tower; project, sparked by 1975 move by Playwrights Horizon into abandoned pornographic movie house, prefigured far larger revival of 42nd Street and Times Square; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some of the prostitutes had Actors' Equity cards. That, at least, was a point of connection for the theater people and other dreamers who 25 years ago thought they could reclaim perhaps the seediest sex strip on wild West 42nd Street.</p>
        <p>There was another link to culture. The International Body Rub Institute, the French Palace and other massage parlors that lined the block between 9th and 10th Avenues were decorated with murals: nudes, many painted by a quixotic Israeli artist who waited on tables down the block at the Hello Deli.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some of the prostitutes had Actors' Equity cards. That, at least, was a point of connection for the theater people and other dreamers who 25 years ago thought they could reclaim perhaps the seediest sex strip on wild West 42nd Street.</p>
        <p>There was another link to culture. The International Body Rub Institute, the French Palace and other massage parlors that lined the block between 9th and 10th Avenues were decorated with murals: nudes, many painted by a quixotic Israeli artist who waited on tables down the block at the Hello Deli.</p>
        <p>''It was like the Bloomsbury Group goes porn,'' recalled Andre Bishop, artistic director of the Lincoln Center Theater and one of the founders of Playwrights Horizons, a pioneer in the ultimately successful effort to turn the block into the flourishing Theater Row, which prefigured the far larger revival of 42nd Street and Times Square.</p>
        <p>Now the eastern half of the enclave, between Ninth and Dyer Avenues, is poised for its own transformation. With the stroke of a pen -- lots of strokes of lots of pens, actually -- the biggest Off Broadway theater redevelopment project in New York City history has taken final form.</p>
        <p>Contracts for a new 499-seat Shubert theater, five new or rebuilt smaller theaters and a 40-story apartment tower overlooking the Dyer Avenue exit from the Lincoln Tunnel were signed on April 14, supercharging a renewal that until now has been makeshift.</p>
        <p>There was no self-congratulatory announcement but relief that the complex series of closings had survived. Participants looked back at what some called an unlikely urban drama, largely unscripted, with (so far anyway) a happy ending. In all, from pornographic past to high-rise future, the resurgence became, quite literally, a groundbreaking story of urban renewal through the arts.</p>
        <p>It even drew praise from an unlikely quarter: Martin Hodas, known in his heyday in the 1970's as ''the peep show king'' and the entrepreneur behind many X-rated storefronts that have since been driven from the area.</p>
        <p>''I think it's a wonderful thing they did,'' said Mr. Hodas from his home in Queens. ''I never liked the idea of massage parlors.''</p>
        <p>The strip, a theater locale in decades past, entered the 1970's so tawdry that some visitors preferred to come and go walking down the yellow line in the middle of West 42nd Street, far from the soliciting women and the string of menacing sex boutiques and grungy groceries.</p>
        <p>The ''Live Burlesque'' house, where women strolled around talking off their clothes and pointing absently to parts of their anatomy, ignored its electrical bills, so Con Edison finally ripped up the street and disconnected the power cable to the building.</p>
        <p>The cellar of another club was home to a reclusive old woman with an enormous wardrobe who emerged intermittently in full makeup and laden with jewelry to roam the block shrieking at passers-by.</p>
        <p>Into this mix in 1975 stepped Playwrights Horizons, a four-year-old company that had just lost its home in the West Side Y.M.C.A. Its artistic director, Bob Moss, took one look around and decided, ''Sometimes you have to do things that don't make any sense, and this is one of them.'' He took quarters in an abandoned pornographic movie house at 422 West 42nd Street for $1,200 a month and rechristened it the Judith Anderson Theater, then soon expanded Playwrights' stake on the block by moving down the street to the former burlesque house at No. 416, at twice the rent.</p>
        <p>The company appealed for help from Broadway luminaries, among them Richard Rodgers. Instead of cash he sent a contribution more to the point: $500 worth of paint, Lysol and cleaning equipment.</p>
        <p>Even the streetwalkers pitched in, Mr. Bishop recalled, with those holding union cards asking for parts. ''There was an odd camaraderie on the block,'' he said, ''particularly when the fleet was in.''</p>
        <p>The company soon put itself on the map with hits like ''Vanities.''</p>
        <p>A second brave troupe, the Lion Company, arrived, and others, including the South Street Theater, Intar and the Acting Company soon followed. Mr. Moss, who left Playwrights to become artistic director at Syracuse Stage, a leading outpost of regional theater, dated the turnabout from the day in 1975 when he looked out of his window and saw strangers, including one out-of-place interloper in a business suit, surveying the strip for who knew what.</p>
        <p>They included Fred Papert (the suit), who had founded the nonprofit 42nd Street Development Corporation during the successful effort to save Grand Central Terminal on East 42nd Street from the wrecker's ball. (His compatriot in the effort, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, later wielded a shovel in the Theater Row groundbreaking.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Papert's group had bought the block of West 42nd Street between 9th and 10th Avenues from desperate landlords who had been losing money and faced mounting tax bills while playing reluctant host to sex establishments. By holding a mortgage on the properties of the nonprofit group, they at least had a chance for some financial recovery if the renewal took, which is in fact what happened.</p>
        <p>Looking at the unsightly buildings, Mr. Papert wondered what it would it would take, short of demolition, to turn the neighborhood around.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moss told him: ''I have a better idea. This can all be turned into theaters.''</p>
        <p>By picking tenants who changed the ''urban vibrations,'' as Mr. Papert put it, his group turned the trickle of new theaters into a boomlet, which he hoped to advance with his relentless promotion of a 42nd Street trolley line.</p>
        <p>The failure of the new Manhattan Plaza housing towers across West 42nd Street to draw sufficient tenants to the wasteland produced another opportunity: 80 percent of the units were earmarked for low-paid people in the performing arts. That idea proved a bonanza.</p>
        <p>''I remember the first lights going on in the apartments,'' Mr. Bishop said. ''It was an outstanding moment. Suddenly we didn't feel as desolate.''</p>
        <p>Now the last links with the gritty past are about to be severed. Demolition for the new apartment tower and theaters began last week by the builders, Daniel Brodsky, Robert Quinlan and Michael Field. They said the $75 million job, which includes 260 rental apartments, 20 percent of them for low- and moderate-income tenants, could be completed in 18 months.</p>
        <p>The Shubert organization is spending $6 million or more on its new theater, its 17th wholly owned establishment in the city and the city's first commercial stage built specifically as a transfer house for productions that start modestly off or off Off Broadway and then, on the strength of reviews, seek to make the leap to theaters large enough to earn money or even, if lightening strikes, to Broadway. The new theater will be run by Ben Sprecher, who owns the Variety Arts and Promenade Theaters and manages the Lucille Lortel.</p>
        <p>The project also includes two theaters with 99 seats and one with 199 seats on a 41st Street parcel acquired from the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey. They will replace three 99-seat theaters that now occupy the Shubert site. Two other theaters of 83 and 99 seats, the Harold Clurman and the Samuel Beckett, will be rebuilt in place, and support space, including new rehearsal studios, will be provided.</p>
        <p>In addition Playwrights Horizons, which sold its air rights and made it possible for the new Shubert theater to be unobstructed by columns for the apartment tower over it, is expected shortly to announce the rebuilding of its two theaters of 141 and 72 seats. This makes a total of eight new or rebuilt theaters seating 1,291 patrons. The number of seats in each theater is determined by contract provisions setting minimum union pay scales for houses of various sizes.</p>
        <p>The work, designed by the architect Hugh Hardy of Hardy Holzman Pfeiffer Associates, is to be financed entirely with private money, said Mr. Papert of the 42nd Street Development Corporation.</p>
        <p>A project has yet to be developed for the western half of Theater Row, between Dyer and 10th Avenues. The site includes the Douglas Fairbanks and John Houseman Theaters, among others, and the National Video Center in the former West Side Airlines Terminal. The block, bought for its tax deductions by investors nearly 25 years ago for $500,000, is now worth $60 million to $80 million, said Mr. Papert, whose group is a minority partner.</p>
        <p>After paying its costs, the 42nd Street group expects to emerge with about $2 million for its foundation, which supports early music education from kindergarten to second grade. Mr. Papert's group will also do the bookings (but not determine the content) for all the theaters except the Shubert house and Playwrights, a role that had been envisioned for Art New York, a service organization for nonprofit theaters. It and Mr. Papert's group, however, could not agree on terms for a deal.</p>
        <p>Among those looking back in wonderment is Jean-Claude Baker, proprietor of Chez Josephine, the restaurant at 414 West 42nd Street, between Playwrights Horizons and the Clurman Theater. Mr. Baker, who was adopted by Josephine Baker, the flamboyant black entertainer, plans to buy its building from the 42nd Street group and turn part of it into a museum of black entertainment.</p>
        <p>While the building, once a coffee roasting business, housed a restaurant when he took it over in 1986, it also used to be home to the French Palace, which beckoned customers with a window sign promising, ''$10 Complete Satisfaction.'' One of the nudes painted by the women at the massage parlor survives in the restaurant, covered by a slightly less revealing painting of Josephine Baker wearing bananas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bishop, too, marvels at the developments. ''This story is so small time,'' he said. ''Modest theaters, modest budgets, modest aspirations, but big time in terms of human richness.''</p>
        <p>''Urban renewal,'' he added, ''was the last thing on our minds.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
