<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campaign Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y11CAM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDE163BF932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campaign Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>A BOSNIAN BY ANY OTHER NAME -- Although aides to Gov. George W. Bush have dismissed as unimportant the several times he has mangled the proper terms for people of various nationalities, they were elated by a report yesterday that his adversary, Vice President Al Gore, had committed a similar error. Karen P. Hughes, Mr. Bush's communications director, gleefully broadcast the bulletin that Mr. Gore had referred to Bosnians as Bosniaks. ''It can happen to the best of us,'' Ms. Hughes said, ''as I hope the vice president will concede.'' Yes, but. As it turns out, Bosniak is an apparently acceptable alternative, listed in some dictionaries, so Mr. Gore spoke correctly. And Ms. Hughes got no more mileage out of the incident than she had with a disapproving recitation on Tuesday night of Jewish jokes that the vice president had publicly told. Where was the outrage? Not among the Bush press corps, whose members were too busy laughing to be on political-correctness patrol.</p>
        <p>Frank Bruni (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>A BOSNIAN BY ANY OTHER NAME -- Although aides to Gov. George W. Bush have dismissed as unimportant the several times he has mangled the proper terms for people of various nationalities, they were elated by a report yesterday that his adversary, Vice President Al Gore, had committed a similar error. Karen P. Hughes, Mr. Bush's communications director, gleefully broadcast the bulletin that Mr. Gore had referred to Bosnians as Bosniaks. ''It can happen to the best of us,'' Ms. Hughes said, ''as I hope the vice president will concede.'' Yes, but. As it turns out, Bosniak is an apparently acceptable alternative, listed in some dictionaries, so Mr. Gore spoke correctly. And Ms. Hughes got no more mileage out of the incident than she had with a disapproving recitation on Tuesday night of Jewish jokes that the vice president had publicly told. Where was the outrage? Not among the Bush press corps, whose members were too busy laughing to be on political-correctness patrol.</p>
        <p>Frank Bruni (NYT)</p>
        <p>BUSH AHEAD IN NEW POLL -- The latest national presidential preference poll shows Mr. Bush taking a substantial eight-point lead over Mr. Gore, 51 percent to 43 percent. The poll, published yesterday in The Los Angeles Times, surveyed 1,211 registered voters, and has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus three percentage points. It was conducted from May 4 to 7, just about the same time that a poll done for the Pew Research Center for the People and the Press found Mr. Bush barely edging Mr. Gore, 46 percent to 45 percent. That poll, conducted May 2 to 6 and covering 940 registered voters, has a margin of sampling error of plus or minus four percentage points. Meanwhile, in polls conducted last week in six of the largest and most politically important states by the American Research Group of Manchester, N.H., Mr. Bush leads Mr. Gore by 7 percentage points in Florida, 47 points in Texas and 3 points in Pennsylvania, whereas Mr. Gore leads by 14 points in California and 20 in New York. In Illinois, there is a tie. Over all, according to the latest available state polls, Mr. Bush is ahead in 17 states (good for 183 of the required 270 electoral votes), and Mr. Gore leads in 10 states (good for 146 electoral votes).</p>
        <p>Irvin Molotsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>A MESSAGE FROM WOMEN -- Mr. Gore, who polls indicate is having difficulty maintaining the traditional Democratic advantage with women, has been put on notice by two dozen women's organizations that he needs to work harder to win women's political allegiance. In an hourlong session on Tuesday in the Old Executive Office Building with about 40 leaders of the women's groups, the vice president was told he needed a better media strategy to convey his positions on issues like Social Security, paycheck fairness, domestic violence and abortion. ''The message isn't getting out to women,'' Kim Gandy, executive vice president of the National Organization for Women, said in an interview after the meeting. Nancy Zirkin, a spokeswoman for the American Association of University Women, said the meeting was requested four months ago, on a nonpartisan basis, so the women could hold a general discussion with Mr. Gore about their concerns. She said the request was not prompted by the vice president's lag in the polls or by growing polling evidence that the Democratic candidate's edge with women was beginning to erode. Mr. Gore, who was accompanied at the meeting by Donna Brazile, his campaign manager; Donna E. Shalala, the secretary of health and human services, and Alexis M. Herman, the secretary of labor, agreed to additional meetings. Ms. Brazile suggested after the meeting that the women's groups could help him get out his message. ''But we're not in any trouble with women voters,'' she insisted.</p>
        <p>Katharine Q. Seelye (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
