<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Law Officials in 18 States Seek Widespread Changes</title>
    <meta content="11FITE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198578"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, James C Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E4DF163BF932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Law Officials in 18 States Seek Widespread Changes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, James C Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Group of attorneys general from 18 states calls for wide reforms of boxing, including independent polls to rank fighters and limits on single judge's power to skew fight's result (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A group of attorneys general from 18 states called yesterday for wide reforms of boxing, including independent polls to rank fighters and limits on a single judge's power to skew a fight's result.</p>
        <p>The officials, including those from big-fight states like Nevada, New Jersey and New York, issued their 60-page report after more than a year of interviews with people in boxing. The attorneys general pledged to push athletic commissions in their states to adopt the measures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A group of attorneys general from 18 states called yesterday for wide reforms of boxing, including independent polls to rank fighters and limits on a single judge's power to skew a fight's result.</p>
        <p>The officials, including those from big-fight states like Nevada, New Jersey and New York, issued their 60-page report after more than a year of interviews with people in boxing. The attorneys general pledged to push athletic commissions in their states to adopt the measures.</p>
        <p>Attorney General Eliot L. Spitzer of New York, the chairman of the committee, said the next step would be to persuade broadcasters and pay-per-view companies to honor an independent writers' poll rather than relying on rankings by the three main sanctioning bodies, which have been shown to be arbitrary at best and corrupt in many cases.</p>
        <p>Spitzer said if broadcasters ignored the sanctioning organizations, it would break an ''unholy alliance'' between ratings officials and promoters, who he said manipulate rankings.</p>
        <p>''Then we will have stripped the sanctioning bodies of their power,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The report also called for new rules to protect the health of boxers, including guidelines for weight loss and a rule requiring the final weigh-in to be the day of the fight rather than the day before.</p>
        <p>The career of the welterweight Joey Gamache was ended at Madison Square Garden recently after Arturo Gatti, who gained 19 pounds between the weigh-in and the fight, knocked him out and caused brain damage.</p>
        <p>The task force also recommended standardized testing for judges, referees and ring physicians, and standardized contracts between boxers and managers that would disclose all financial arrangements.</p>
        <p>The attorneys general urged the adoption of a consensus scoring system. Under such a system, if three judges cannot agree on a round, then the aberrant score is thrown out. Such a system would have given Lennox Lewis the victory in the widely criticized championship fight last year that ended in a draw between him and Evander Holyfield.</p>
        <p>While the recommendations, if put into effect in all 18 states, could be a giant step toward cleaning up boxing, Spitzer said national legislation was still needed.</p>
        <p>''Fights can always migrate to states with less restrictive laws,'' he said.</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
