<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Kurdish Turkey, Problems of Peace</title>
    <meta content="11KURD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinzer, Stephen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kurds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902EED91F38F932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Kurdish Turkey, Problems of Peace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kinzer, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>MADEN, Turkey, May 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Turkish army has won its war against Kurdish rebels, and Turkey must now decide what to do with 95,000 village guards who will soon be demobilized and find themselves without jobs or prospects; village guard system was conceived more than decade ago as Kurdish rebellion was intensifying; many of its members rendered invaluable service because they know Kurdish region better than soldiers do; fear now is that if salary is cut off to guards, some may grab their weapons and take to the hills; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sipping tea in the sun and looking down from their clay bunker at a placid field full of wildflowers, Irfan Ozay and his cousin Remzi should be happy. With their help and that of 95,000 other village guards, the Turkish army has finally won its war against Kurdish rebels.</p>
        <p>But like many other village guards, the Ozay cousins are worried and becoming angry. They fear they will soon be demobilized and find themselves without jobs or prospects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sipping tea in the sun and looking down from their clay bunker at a placid field full of wildflowers, Irfan Ozay and his cousin Remzi should be happy. With their help and that of 95,000 other village guards, the Turkish army has finally won its war against Kurdish rebels.</p>
        <p>But like many other village guards, the Ozay cousins are worried and becoming angry. They fear they will soon be demobilized and find themselves without jobs or prospects.</p>
        <p>What to do with these village guards is one of the most urgent questions that confront Turkey now that peace has broken out.</p>
        <p>The Kurdish rebel leader, Abdullah Ocalan, was captured last year and remains in a Turkish prison under sentence of death. At his trial he said he now favors peaceful change, and asked his guerrillas to stop fighting. Nearly all have done so.</p>
        <p>With no war, there is no need for village guards. Yet these guards, who served as the first line of defense against the guerrillas, have spent years carrying rifles. Many have become accustomed to rough lives. Some have even been convicted of using their quasi-military authority to commit crimes.</p>
        <p>''The village guards around here will be peaceful, but I can think of other places where they might start trouble or form gangs,'' Irfan Ozay mused from his hilltop perch near Maden, which overlooks a strategic highway 765 miles east of Istanbul.  ''The state needs to come up with a solution for us. Otherwise a lot of people will be upset, and that's dangerous for everybody.''</p>
        <p>''We worked in hard conditions for years,'' Mr. Ozay said. ''Now it turns out we don't have any insurance or pension or any other kind of rights.  That's not fair.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Ozay is a veteran of eight years as a village guard, he is just 26 years old and still has a few sheep from which he might build up a herd. His cousin, though, is 40 and has nowhere to start.</p>
        <p>''I realize they don't need us any more, but I don't have any business or land to go back to,'' Remzi Ozay said. ''What do they expect me to do?''</p>
        <p>The village guard system was conceived more than a decade ago as the Kurdish rebellion was intensifying.  Many of its members rendered invaluable service because they knew this region and its people far more intimately than the army.</p>
        <p>This system also became a source of much bitterness. Some village guards drifted into corruption, others abused civilians. In some villages the army forced men to become guards, imprisoning those who refused.</p>
        <p>But no one doubts that village guards played a significant role in the army's 15-year campaign to assert control of Turkey's rugged eastern mountains. Now they want their government to show its gratitude.</p>
        <p>Families in this part of Turkey are large, and by one estimate a total of one million people here rely on salaries paid to the 95,000 village guards.  The base salary is the equivalent of just $115 per month, but in a region where war has brought almost all productive activity to a halt, that is a  valuable sum.</p>
        <p>Turkish officials and foreign diplomats have begun to worry that if these salaries are suddenly cut off and nothing replaces them, some unhappy veterans might grab their weapons and take to the hills.</p>
        <p>''Undoubtedly once this system is phased out, if there is no solution found it will have a social impact,'' said Karen Fogg, the European Union's chief representative in Turkey.</p>
        <p>One senior member of Parliament, Salih Yildirim, has proposed that village guards over the age of 55 be allowed to retire with benefits.  Younger ones, he said, should either be offered jobs as security guards or helped to find work as farmers or herders.</p>
        <p>''The problem involves a great number of people,'' Mr. Yildirim said. ''We must integrate these people into the region's economy.''</p>
        <p>But unfortunately no real economy exists in eastern Turkey. Before the war most people here used to herd livestock on remote mountains, but for years the army has forbidden them to enter the highlands. Many live as impoverished refugees in swollen cities.</p>
        <p>The government wants to attract foreign investors to this region, but even its special incentives have proven insufficient. Many companies are reluctant to invest in an area where security controls are still tight and key provinces remain under a form of martial law.</p>
        <p>All of this strikes hard at men like the two cousins who have spent years standing watch outside their lonesome bunker here.</p>
        <p>''We were hired to help the state destroy an enemy and win a war,'' Remzi Ozay reasoned. ''We succeeded. So why are we being thrown away like this?''</p>
        <p>His younger cousin, however, believes things will work out in the end.  ''They'll find a solution for us,'' he said. ''If no one else does, the army will. They have to. They know the danger if they just cut us off.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
