<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>43 Superintendents Do Their Best Jack Benny</title>
    <meta content="11VIOL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198580"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violins</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Harold O</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stern, Isaac</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Musical Instruments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4DE163BF932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>43 Superintendents Do Their Best Jack Benny</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Isaac Stern, who has coached budding violin virtuosos for decades, begins lessons for New York City's 43 school superintendents, most of whom had never touched a violin before; lesson is part of program introduced by interim chancellor Harold O Levy to make themn more culturally aware; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Isaac Stern has coached budding violin virtuosos for decades, but the students he took on yesterday were a different breed altogether: New York City's 43 school superintendents, most of whom had never touched a violin before.</p>
        <p>The lesson took place at Carnegie Hall, no less.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Isaac Stern has coached budding violin virtuosos for decades, but the students he took on yesterday were a different breed altogether: New York City's 43 school superintendents, most of whom had never touched a violin before.</p>
        <p>The lesson took place at Carnegie Hall, no less.</p>
        <p>''Just put the violin on the shoulder, voomp!'' Mr. Stern said, lifting his own delicate instrument to the proper position as the school administrators looked on.</p>
        <p>Perhaps not surprisingly, it was easier said than done.</p>
        <p>''I'm having a problem!'' one superintendent exclaimed.</p>
        <p>''This is hard!'' chimed in another.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern, 79, was undeterred. He gazed around the room and shouted advice. ''You've got it on the wrong shoulder, darling,'' he told one bewildered student.</p>
        <p>Harold O. Levy, the interim chancellor, had persuaded Mr. Stern to give the superintendents a lesson in hopes that they would place a higher priority on music instruction for students. The lesson was part of a broader plan to raise the level of intellectual debate among the school system's leaders and make them more culturally attuned.</p>
        <p>The lesson came directly after the superintendents' monthly meeting with Mr. Levy, at which they started off the day hashing out plans for summer school. After lunch, they filed into a practice room at Carnegie Hall and listened nervously as Mr. Stern told them what to do.</p>
        <p>Mr. Levy himself did not take part in the lesson -- he recently injured one of his hands and was wearing a soft cast yesterday. He left the meeting early, aides said, to accompany his son Noah's class at the Dalton School on a field trip.</p>
        <p>But Jonathan Levi, one of Mr. Levy's top aides and his cultural impresario, was on hand to make sure the lesson went semi-smoothly. Mr. Levi, an accomplished violinist, adjusted people's fingers, tucked instruments more firmly under chins and practically pulsed with delight.</p>
        <p>''Isaac Stern has been a hero of mine since I was a little kid,'' said Mr. Levi, whose musical claim to fame is having taught the actress Jennifer Aniston how to play the violin when she was growing up in New York City. ''If only we could get him certified, we'd have him teaching in the schools.''</p>
        <p>By the end of the half-hour lesson, the superintendents had participated in several rounds of ''Ach, du Lieber Augustin'' -- a German folk song, better known in this country as ''Did You Ever See a Lassie?'' Mr. Stern played most of the song, and the superintendents joined in on the last two notes of each line.</p>
        <p>The screeching and squawking would have made Jack Benny proud.</p>
        <p>But while some of the superintendents initially seemed less than happy to be taking part in the musical exercise, by the end of the lesson they were begging to play the song one more time.</p>
        <p>Paula LeCompte Speed, of District 18 in Brooklyn, whose finger position was so contorted that Mr. Stern hopped off his conductor's platform to give her some personal attention, said afterward that she wanted to keep her violin.</p>
        <p>''I was very excited to be in his presence,'' she said of Mr. Stern. ''And I thought I did pretty good.''</p>
        <p>Matthew Bromme, the superintendent of District 27 in Queens, said he had always wanted to play the violin as a teenager, but the music teachers at his school would not let him because he was left-handed.</p>
        <p>''This is the opportunity of a lifetime,'' Mr. Bromme said. ''It's an opportunity for me to enrich my life and to bring it back to my principals and teachers and children, so they can enrich their lives.''</p>
        <p>While the Board of Education has worked hard to increase arts instruction in city schools in recent years, many still lack full-time music teachers and instruments for students. Mr. Levy has put his friend Mr. Levi to work raising money for school music programs and increasing the number of partnerships between schools and cultural organizations like Carnegie Hall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern said yesterday that he was thrilled to contribute, adding that music ''is the biggest key I know to a truly educated life.''</p>
        <p>He spoke to the superintendents about the importance of music education before and after the lesson, exhorting them to make it a priority at all 1,100 of the city's public schools.</p>
        <p>''If it doesn't start with you,'' who will it start with, he said. ''I would like this to be the beginning of us talking together on a regular basis.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
