<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Government's role in the new economy is not a cheap or easy one. But it is crucial, a la Adam Smith.</title>
    <meta content="Y11SCE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC SCENE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Madrick, Jeffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Summers, Lawrence H (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Adam (1723-1790)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Economic Scene (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E2DD163BF932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Government's role in the new economy is not a cheap or easy one. But it is crucial, a la Adam Smith.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jeff Madrick</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Madrick, Jeffrey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeff Madrick (Economic Scene) column praises address by Treasury Sec Lawrence H Summers that said new economy requires government spending on education and research because it is based not on big factories and distribution systems but on ideas and innovation; says most economists recognize that some investments of crucial benefit to society as whole will not be made by business because no single company, or even industry, will reap all benefits; backs Adam Smith's economic theory supporting role for government; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COULD we be hearing right? The Treasury Secretary, Lawrence H. Summers, gave a speech in San Francisco yesterday that made some economic sense and did not focus solely on assuaging the financial markets.</p>
        <p>Yes, Mr. Summers again pushed the lines that open markets around the world were essential to future growth and that fiscal discipline remained paramount. But he also broached a more sensitive subject: some of those Treasury surpluses should be used to pay down debt, but, as I read him, maybe they should also be used to buttress the so-called new economy. This may prove to be one of the more important economic speeches of the Clinton administration. Better late than never.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COULD we be hearing right? The Treasury Secretary, Lawrence H. Summers, gave a speech in San Francisco yesterday that made some economic sense and did not focus solely on assuaging the financial markets.</p>
        <p>Yes, Mr. Summers again pushed the lines that open markets around the world were essential to future growth and that fiscal discipline remained paramount. But he also broached a more sensitive subject: some of those Treasury surpluses should be used to pay down debt, but, as I read him, maybe they should also be used to buttress the so-called new economy. This may prove to be one of the more important economic speeches of the Clinton administration. Better late than never.</p>
        <p>Behind Mr. Summers's point is that the new economy requires spending on education and research because it is based not on big factories and distribution systems but on ideas and innovation. He is essentially right, in my view. Maybe more right than he realizes or truly wants to concede.</p>
        <p>This economy is not any more ''new'' than the economic transformations of the 1920's, 1950's and 1960's were in their day (and surely no more revolutionary than changes around the last turn of the century). In fact, for all the raves from Washington and Wall Street, economic growth even in the late 1990's was not equal to the fastest growth rates of those eras.</p>
        <p>But an unmistakable rise in the rate of economic growth that began in the mid-1990's has just about confirmed that a similar transformation is under way. In my view, this transformation is less potent than those in the past, but potent it will be.</p>
        <p>To maximize its potential, however, will require more effort than most Americans and even Mr. Summers generally acknowledge. Every such economic transformation in the past was accompanied by enormous increases in spending on education, transportation, communications and, ultimately, technological research. Much of this was undertaken or subsidized by the government.</p>
        <p>Take education. In the 1800's, Americans developed a free, mandatory primary school system. In the early 1900's, high school education spread rapidly. And after World War II, aided by the G.I. Bill of Rights and the expansion of public universities, Americans went to college in droves.</p>
        <p>Or take transportation. In the 1800's, first canals and then railroads were built. In the early 1900's, roads followed. And in the 1950's and 1960's, Washington, under the guise of national defense, paid to build the Interstate highway system.</p>
        <p>In communications, the telegraph gave the nation its first instantaneous connection and soon helped create a global economy. Then came the telephone, followed by television. Now, it's the Internet. And just as the telegraph reduced inefficient transportation requirements -- after all, a person didn't have to get on a horse to deliver a message anymore -- the Internet may reduce transportation needs as well by, among other things, encouraging more shopping from home.</p>
        <p>But every economic transformation has unique characteristics as well. Enter Mr. Summers. He says the new economy requires more innovation. In fact, all such economic transformations were based principally on new ideas and exciting innovation, as Joseph Schumpeter, the economic exponent of creative destruction, so clearly pointed out.</p>
        <p>I think Mr. Summers is right that the demand for innovation has increased drastically. This didn't start only a few years ago, however. The innovation economy began in the mid-1970's when Japanese manufacturers, led by Toyota and Honda, learned how to make varied and high-quality cars far more productively than their Detroit counterparts. Suddenly, many more types of cars were on the road, at affordable prices. Standardized markets were replaced by fragmented ones, and the rate of introduction of new products soared, not only for manufactured goods like packaged food and appliances but also for services like airline trips and cable television and financial products like mutual funds. None of this could have happened without the computer.</p>
        <p>Thus, new products, marketing ideas, financial strategies, innovative salesmanship and constant change became the keys to competitive success. As Mr. Summers says, a new product rushes in, captures the market and is quickly displaced by a still newer one. This is far from a new model, and Mr. Summers does accept too readily some of the exaggerations of the new-economy enthusiasts. But the pace of new-product introduction is faster.</p>
        <p>The implication is that an educated and sophisticated work force and aggressive investment in technological research are now more important than ever before.</p>
        <p>How does American society make the most of this? As in the past, it will require government funds. Not for everything, especially in the modern age, which has so many more capable people and developed private institutions than in the past. But it was New York State that first built the canals; the federal government that subsidized the railroads and paved the highways; local government that built the nation's schools; land-grant universities and the military that generated a lot of our technology.</p>
        <p>Some will demur. Indeed, private industry built the communications infrastructure in this century and is now building the Internet. But the Pentagon, as every schoolchild apparently now knows, developed the Internet in the first place.</p>
        <p>And there is strong economic theory to support a role for government. Let me quote from Adam Smith, no raving liberal:</p>
        <p>''The third and last duty of the sovereign or commonwealth is that of erecting and maintaining those public institutions and those public works which, though they may be in the highest degree advantageous to a great society, are, however, of such a nature that the profit could never repay the expense to any individual or small number of individuals.''</p>
        <p>Most economists now recognize that some investments of crucial benefit to society as a whole will not be made by business because no single company, or even industry, will reap all the benefits.</p>
        <p>The remarkably prescient Adam Smith had it right 225 years ago. The fear is that Mr. Summers will retreat into fiscal discipline. Only if he renews our faith in public investment, however, will he truly be following in Smith's footsteps.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC SCENE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
