<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In America; Mr. Giuliani's Decision</title>
    <meta content="11HERB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198600"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanover, Donna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEFDD163BF932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In America; Mr. Giuliani's Decision</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herbert, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Herbert Op-Ed article says Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani will soon abandon his Senate race, because he is battling cancer and has separated from his wife, Donna Hanover; says his candidacy will not survive Hanover's tearful appearance before press, where she spoke about problems that go back several years; says Giuliani is laboring beneath almost unimaginable load of physical and emotional stress; expects him to bow out of this race, regain his health, settle difficulties in his personal life and then come back to run in some future campaign</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You could tell from the headlines, especially in the tabloids, that something had to happen -- that, as Donna Hanover said last week in an emotional appearance outside St. Patrick's Cathedral, ''decisions'' had to be made.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, his own voice halting and at times trembling, Mayor Rudolph Giuliani told reporters that he and Ms. Hanover were considering a formal separation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You could tell from the headlines, especially in the tabloids, that something had to happen -- that, as Donna Hanover said last week in an emotional appearance outside St. Patrick's Cathedral, ''decisions'' had to be made.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, his own voice halting and at times trembling, Mayor Rudolph Giuliani told reporters that he and Ms. Hanover were considering a formal separation.</p>
        <p>That's one decision. Soon, I think, will come the decision to abandon the Senate race.</p>
        <p>In disclosing his plans to separate from Ms. Hanover, the mayor said, ''I'm motivated by all the tremendous invasion of privacy that's taken place in everyone's life -- my family, Judith Nathan's family.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Nathan has been described by Mr. Giuliani as his ''very good friend,'' and yesterday he said, ''I'm  going to need her more now than maybe I did before.''</p>
        <p>I rooted for the longest time for a Senate race between Rudolph Giuliani and Hillary Rodham Clinton. This was purely out of self-interest. I make my living running around with a pocketful of paper and a Bic pen, chasing stories. And I couldn't imagine a story that would be more fun than all-out warfare between these two huge, aggressive and controversial personalities.</p>
        <p>Way back in November 1998 I wrote: ''I have found nothing to substantiate the rumors that Hillary Rodham Clinton is interested in running for Mr. Moynihan's seat. But the idea of a Senate race between Mrs. Clinton and Rudolph Giuliani is such a splendid one that it must be kept alive at all costs.''</p>
        <p>Well, the story has certainly been incredible. The real events have trumped anything I might have imagined.</p>
        <p>But it has not been fun.</p>
        <p>You have to be very twisted indeed to get a kick out of public figures coming down with cancer and the very public disintegration of a marriage.</p>
        <p>The combat I imagined was of the political variety, Hillary against Rudy, Democrat against Republican, one narcissist against another.</p>
        <p>The dynamics changed radically two weeks ago when Mr. Giuliani announced that he had been diagnosed with prostate cancer.</p>
        <p>Just days later came stories in the tabloids about the mayor's relationship with Ms. Nathan. The mayor acknowledged they were friends, and that has been the hot topic ever since. The tabloids went into overdrive. There were daily stories, with photos, about Ms. Nathan. The history of the relationship was chronicled. Her wardrobe was analyzed and re-analyzed. A media encampment was set up outside her East Side high-rise and other reporters and photographers were dispatched to Hazleton, Pa., her hometown, to get reactions from Ms. Nathan's relatives.</p>
        <p>By yesterday it was clear that the frenzy wasn't about to abate, and top Republican officials were openly concerned about the effect it was having on the Senate race.</p>
        <p>The mayor's response was to announce that he and Ms. Hanover would pursue a formal separation. And Ms. Hanover called reporters to Gracie Mansion where she spoke tearfully about problems that went back several years.</p>
        <p>That tearful appearance was the crusher. The mayor's candidacy will not survive it. And I would expect his exit to come sooner rather than later.</p>
        <p>Like most other observers, I doubt that Mr. Giuliani ever really wanted to go to the Senate. He's a guy who likes to command.</p>
        <p>And while he's tried mightily to seem otherwise, he's also human. And that means he is laboring beneath an almost unimaginable load of physical and emotional stress. He is the mayor of the nation's largest city. He is fighting the disease that killed his father. His marriage has unraveled. The person he seems closest to is being hounded day and night by the media, and that will only grow worse. The prognosis he has received from his doctors is very good, but the treatment is rough nevertheless, and is likely, at least to some extent, to be debilitating. And after going through that, his immediate task would be to engage in a titanic, historic battle for the Senate against Mrs. Clinton.</p>
        <p>I expect Mr. Giuliani to bow out of this race, regain his health, settle the difficulties in his personal life and then come back, renewed, to run in some future campaign.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
