<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metro Matters; When Public And Private Commingle</title>
    <meta content="11MATT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000512T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purnick, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanover, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nathan, Judith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DB163BF932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metro Matters; When Public And Private Commingle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purnick, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joyce Purnick Metro Matters column contends that continuing drama of Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani's increasingly public private life is nothing short of astonishing; discusses possible impact of his revealing marital problems and other affairs of heart on his race for Senate as well effectiveness as mayor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE continuing drama of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's increasingly public private life is nothing short of astonishing.</p>
        <p>What to make of his charged confessional yesterday at a news conference in Bryant Park, where, in an emotional, halting voice, he announced he was seeking a separation from his wife, Donna Hanover. The mayor spoke most kindly of her yesterday. And then, in the next breath, he conceded how much he needed his recently acknowledged ''very good friend,'' Judith Nathan, in his life -- especially given his recent diagnosis of prostate cancer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE continuing drama of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's increasingly public private life is nothing short of astonishing.</p>
        <p>What to make of his charged confessional yesterday at a news conference in Bryant Park, where, in an emotional, halting voice, he announced he was seeking a separation from his wife, Donna Hanover. The mayor spoke most kindly of her yesterday. And then, in the next breath, he conceded how much he needed his recently acknowledged ''very good friend,'' Judith Nathan, in his life -- especially given his recent diagnosis of prostate cancer.</p>
        <p>Visibly shaken, the mayor said the marital estrangement was ''painful, very painful,'' and added that he and Ms. Hanover had been leading separate lives for a long time.</p>
        <p>As if that weren't enough for one day, a few hours later an equally distraught Ms. Hanover held her own news conference to confirm the impending marital separation and to say that her marriage had been troubled pre-Nathan because of her husband's relationship with a ''staff member,'' a reference to the mayor's former communications director, Cristyne F. Lategano, said Ms. Hanover's spokeswoman, Joannie Danielides. She and the mayor were long the center of rumors about their relationship.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lategano, now president of the city's tourism bureau, said that she did not want to speculate about Ms. Hanover's remarks.</p>
        <p>The events of the last two weeks, beginning with the mayor's announcement about his cancer, defy characterization. Clearly he, his wife and Ms. Nathan are under great stress.</p>
        <p>Dealing with cancer is one thing; as noted in this space last week, most people with treatable cancers want to continue with their pre-diagnosis lives, and do. But dealing with affairs of the heart -- in the public eye -- is decidedly more complicated. The mayor said he wasn't thinking about politics. But everyone else is, and the obvious question is whether the mayor can survive this curious, uncomfortable exposure.</p>
        <p>Is even New York ready for a candidate who acknowledges adultery, is accused by his wife of another affair, and brazenly parades his relationship for months, taking Ms. Nathan to public event after public event, from the St. Patrick's Day Parade to community meetings?</p>
        <p>MANY would like to live in a world where public figures were judged on their public records, not their private conduct. The public is more open-minded than ever; Bill Clinton's popularity survived Monica S. Lewinsky and impeachment. But he was already well liked. Polls show that even some of Mr. Giuliani's supporters have reservations about his pugnacious temperament -- the tough, self-righteous image of his own making. Paradoxically, he has never appeared more vulnerable than he did yesterday.</p>
        <p>He has nurtured a harsh reputation throughout his career, insisting that the public accept his style and values and succeeding on his own terms much more often than failing. His unorthodox politics and his stubborn defiance have been his political identity and strength.</p>
        <p>But how does the fierce, moralistic mayor jibe with the married father of two openly defying classic public morals? The two personas are in blatant conflict.</p>
        <p>It is difficult to believe that Mr. Giuliani really thinks this will not hurt him.</p>
        <p>But it was just as hard to believe that he blamed Patrick M. Dorismond -- an unarmed black man killed in an altercation with police officers -- for his death; that he didn't care what the press thought of him; that he let the Lategano rumors hover for years.</p>
        <p>Most New Yorkers were offended, but this mayor nonetheless insisted on punishing the Brooklyn Museum of Art for exhibiting works he found morally offensive by attempting to deny them city money. He tried to revise the City Charter just to prevent a politician he disliked -- Mark Green, the public advocate -- from succeeding him should he move on to the Senate.</p>
        <p>In other words, this is one headstrong man whose every fiber says, you'll do it my way. That has led to a most remarkable series of policies and incidents, of which this is surely the most astounding.</p>
        <p>And it will not go away. This is one of those political phenomena that develop a life of their own. It will get messier. If there are more peccadilloes to be revealed, they will be. That's how it works.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, perhaps impelled to go public about his life by a reminder of his mortality, could triumph. If he does, he will have changed the course of politics here and maybe across the land.</p>
        <p>If he fails, it is hard to see how he could not have committed political suicide.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 12, 2000, Friday  A picture in some copies yesterday showing Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani at the St. Patrick's Day parade, with an article about his relationships with his wife and with Judith Nathan, whom he has called a very good friend, was published in error. The woman shown with Mr. Giuliani was not Ms. Nathan but Noeline Cuker, the wife of a friend of his, Elliot Cuker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 12, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>A picture in some copies yesterday showing Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani at the St. Patrick's Day parade, with an article about his relationships with his wife and with Judith Nathan, whom he has called a very good friend, was published in error. The woman shown with Mr. Giuliani was not Ms. Nathan but Noeline Cuker, the wife of a friend of his, Elliot Cuker.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
