<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Gardening Chore Without Any Blisters</title>
    <meta content="11SHOP$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Online Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E7DF1F38F932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Gardening Chore Without Any Blisters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla Online Shopper column on garden supply Web sites; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE it was such a beautiful, sunny day, I suppose I could have been outside, shoveling compost and dirt into the big hole where the pond used to be before we got the dog that likes to swim and eat electric pumps.</p>
        <p>Instead, I was at my computer, trying to move icons that represented a clump of Stella de Oro day lilies across a grid to an area occupied by some icons that represented ostrich ferns. Those needed to be deleted because -- have I mentioned this already? -- the dog chews on ostrich ferns. With the little icons' habit of clumping up on each other, that click-and-move exercise is harder than it looks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE it was such a beautiful, sunny day, I suppose I could have been outside, shoveling compost and dirt into the big hole where the pond used to be before we got the dog that likes to swim and eat electric pumps.</p>
        <p>Instead, I was at my computer, trying to move icons that represented a clump of Stella de Oro day lilies across a grid to an area occupied by some icons that represented ostrich ferns. Those needed to be deleted because -- have I mentioned this already? -- the dog chews on ostrich ferns. With the little icons' habit of clumping up on each other, that click-and-move exercise is harder than it looks.</p>
        <p>So are most gardening chores. With blisters imminent and the hole in the yard still half-empty, I was lucky last week to stumble across this free Landscape Planner tool while I was shopping at Garden.com. Within minutes of creating a plan and naming it ''Area Formerly Known as the Pond Garden,'' I forgot all about the gaping problem in the (real) area and instead began to daydream about the soothing, silvery-leafed hostas I was (virtually) planting in the wreckage.</p>
        <p>Frankly, I preferred the icons to the actual digging, because for me the pleasures of gardening have always been as much about avoiding any job as doing it. I think that's why I spend so many hours in the winter huddled with seed catalogs, planning ambitious acres of cutting gardens at a time when the ground is frozen.</p>
        <p>If you share my, uh, relaxed sensibility, then the Internet is the perfect place to shop for plants. That's because I learned, during a recent online shopping trip, that it is not easy to find everything you need quickly or in a single place. So you will probably be forced to delay both gratification and physical labor.</p>
        <p>There are relatively few full-service plant and garden-supply retailers with large inventories who have ventured into the online market. Live plants, after all, are fragile. They should be inserted into the dirt only during certain seasons. And they are notoriously cranky about being packed and shipped.</p>
        <p>Not to belittle any concerns the plants might have, but as a shopper I would like to see bigger selections. I had hoped, last week, to save a lot of time by comparing prices online, then placing a fast order or two. With a wait of a few days for delivery, I would have plenty of time to dig or more likely, to supervise the shoveling efforts of my husband, who loves the dog.</p>
        <p>''In my town,'' said CarrieAnn Cutler, a researcher at Gomez Associates who studies the online garden retail market, ''there are five stores where I can go out and look at each plant I'm buying. It's hard to compete with that. But this should be a segment fulfilled by many more retailers, so I think you'll see that the growth is just beginning.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Cutler recommended My seasons.com (www.myseasons.com) in addition to Garden.com (www10.garden.com). Both offer full refunds for unsatisfactory merchandise, and she said she liked them for their site tools and reference materials, and for fulfilling the wide range of plant needs of both beginners and expert gardeners. If you order, make sure you know what you are getting. Garden.com, for instance, ships stock in different sizes and conditions, depending on the plant. Unlike a local nursery, which at this time of year will sell most plants in containers, perennials you buy online may come bare-root.</p>
        <p>Most of the rest of the online landscape consists of established mail-order catalog companies that have put up tandem Web sites, as well as thousands of smaller retailers specializing in specific plants. While those sites tend to be idiosyncratic --  some can only handle online orders that arrive via e-mail, others have no plant photos -- they may offer wide selections of their specialties.</p>
        <p>Two I like are Hortico Nurseries (www.hortico.com), a Canadian grower with more than 700 varieties of roses (but watch out for the hefty shipping costs), and Granite Hill Gardens (www.granitehillgardens  .com), headquartered in Maine. Granite Hill has a wide selection of ornamental shrubs and responded within two hours last week by e-mail to a pricing question about a Ken Janeck rhododendron whose blossoms start out bright pink, then fade.</p>
        <p>To test the online arms of the mail-order catalog companies, last week I made a shopping list of about a dozen fairly common plants widely available in my local nurseries at this time of year: perennials like Heuchera Palace Purple and Japanese painted ferns, rhododendrons (Purple Gem) and a sprawling old rose called Zephirine Drouhin.</p>
        <p>I went shopping at three reliable companies -- Jackson and Perkins (www.jacksonandperkins.com), White Flower Farm (www  .whiteflowerfarm.com) and Wayside Gardens (www.waysidegardens  .wte.net) -- whose plants I have bought, with satisfaction, in the past.  While each had at least one of the items on my shopping list, none offered all or even most. In fact, many perennials and roses were sold out. (The Wayside Gardens site was not updated to reflect sold-out merchandise. Only when I phoned a toll-free number to double check did I learn which items were unavailable.)</p>
        <p>When I phoned Renee Beaulieu, White Flower Farm's public relations manager, to ask about the possibility of restocking, she said that I was too late this year to get a climbing rose called New Dawn, as well as a begonia mixture that I coveted. As for the rest of the 600 products in the company's spring catalog? ''We're really at the end of our ordering season,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Beaulieu suggested instead that I order next spring's bulbs now. The selection of 600 different bulbs from the company's fall bulb catalog is online; orders placed before July 1 will get a 5 percent discount.</p>
        <p>''I can order them today and you won't deliver them until the fall?'' I asked. ''There's no way I could go outside and plant them now?''</p>
        <p>''The iris we start shipping in August,'' Ms. Beaulieu said. ''Most others, later.''</p>
        <p>August is a long way away. So it seemed safe to order $178 worth of iris reticulata and yellow hyacinths and purple tulips.</p>
        <p>That freed me to return to the Landscape Planner at Garden.com, where I also ordered Heuchera Palace Purple ($4.99 a plant for bare-root specimens, compared with $11.99 for a bushy container plant at a local nursery). Garden.com said the plants would not arrive before May 15, which gives me enough time to think about how an icon representing a big brown dog might look sitting in the middle of them.</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: Slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
