<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Verdict Shakes Louisiana's Cynicism, if Only a Bit</title>
    <meta content="Y11EDW$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000512T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Louisiana</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, Edwin W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EEDB163BF932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Verdict Shakes Louisiana's Cynicism, if Only a Bit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, May 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many Louisianians say they take hope from jury's firm guilty verdict in former Gov Edwin W Edwards's racketeering trial; see it as step in right direction of ending political corruption in state; some still express fondness for Edwards, and squirm at notion of 72-year-old man being put in jail for what could be rest of his life; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Political corruption in Louisiana did not begin with Edwin W. Edwards, and it presumably will not end with his conviction Tuesday on federal racketeering, conspiracy and extortion charges. But many Louisianians said today that they took a certain measure of hope from the jury's firm declaration that malfeasance would not be tolerated here the way it has been since the era of Huey Long.</p>
        <p>''The good old boy mentality has probably stuck here more than in any other state,'' said Walt L. Nixon, a 46-year-old Web site designer who was taking a morning cigarette break outside the Texaco building in downtown New Orleans. ''It's good to see that things are being exposed.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Political corruption in Louisiana did not begin with Edwin W. Edwards, and it presumably will not end with his conviction Tuesday on federal racketeering, conspiracy and extortion charges. But many Louisianians said today that they took a certain measure of hope from the jury's firm declaration that malfeasance would not be tolerated here the way it has been since the era of Huey Long.</p>
        <p>''The good old boy mentality has probably stuck here more than in any other state,'' said Walt L. Nixon, a 46-year-old Web site designer who was taking a morning cigarette break outside the Texaco building in downtown New Orleans. ''It's good to see that things are being exposed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nixon, a New Orleans native, said that the jury in the former governor's case sent a message that was clear and that some Louisiana politicians might actually hear. ''It'll be very slow to come around,'' he said, ''but it is a start.''</p>
        <p>And yet there was a certain ambivalence in the reaction of many here today. Some still expressed a measure of fondness for Mr. Edwards because, they said, the four-term governor had done good things for the state or simply because he had entertained them for so long. Some squirmed at the notion that a 72-year-old man might be put in jail for what could be the rest of his life. And many said one conviction, even of such a prominent defendant, could not erode a wall of cynicism built over generations. (Even now, Mr. Edwards faces another trial on unrelated charges and the state's election commissioner and insurance commissioner are under indictment.)</p>
        <p>''It's a step in the right direction,'' said Paul A. Gauthreaux Jr., a shipping company manager who was eating lunch on the New Orleans Riverwalk along the Mississippi, ''but whether or not it'll change anything, I doubt it. It's been going on for hundreds of years.''</p>
        <p>One day after a Baton Rouge jury convicted him on 17 of the 26 counts in his indictment, Mr. Edwards was back in court today as it considered whether he and three co-defendants had to forfeit illicitly gained assets.  After several hours of deliberation, the jury declared that the defendants would forfeit $2.56 million of the $3.1 million sought by the government. Judge Frank Polozola of Federal District Court will determine each defendant's portion of that amount.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday afternoon, the jury found Mr. Edwards, his son Stephen, and three associates guilty of multiple counts related to the bidding for coveted state riverboat casino licenses, both during Mr. Edwards's last term in office and after his departure in 1996. He could receive a total of more than 200 years in prison and be fined millions of dollars. Using evidence gleaned from wiretaps and cooperating witnesses, prosecutors in the 17-week trial depicted a criminal enterprise in which Mr. Edwards and his co-defendants demanded payoffs from businessmen in exchange for the licenses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Edwards had evaded conviction twice in the 1980's, when he was tried on charges of taking payoffs to help associates win state hospital licenses. A first trial ended in a mistrial, a second in acquittal. Those trials helped cement Louisiana's image as a place where a certain level of corruption would be forgiven, particularly if the miscreant was as charming as Mr. Edwards.</p>
        <p>But Eddie J. Jordan Jr., the United States attorney who oversaw Mr. Edwards's prosecution, took pains today to declare those days over.</p>
        <p>''Today we begin the process of reclaiming our state's great name,'' he said in a news conference, after Judge Polozola lifted a ban on comments by lawyers in the case. ''Today we begin the process of restoring confidence in our state's democratic institutions. Today we begin the process of removing the stain of corruption that has ruined our state's ability and our state's reputation as a great place to conduct business.''</p>
        <p>The jury's verdict, Mr. Jordan concluded, sent the message that ''corruption is not the Louisiana way.''</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Edwards seemed to make that point, saying his convictions should be ''a reflection on me, not on the people of Louisiana.''</p>
        <p>Without explicitly confessing, he also contended that his crimes bore no cost for the state: ''There isn't a penny missing from the state treasury. There are no allegations and certainly no evidence that I at any time took anything voluntarily from the people of this state.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jordan had a ready response. ''Never is it a victimless crime when you have a person who has a reputation in state government for being corrupt because the price we pay is an absence of business opportunity in this state,'' he said. ''Businesses in their right mind do not want to come to a state where they know that they will be shaken down.''</p>
        <p>Some Louisiana residents said that the state's reputation would change only if a steady federal vigilance was maintained. ''Obviously, the federal government is not in a position to mount that kind of prosecution year after year,'' said Richard Ford, the novelist, who has lived in New Orleans for 10 years. ''There has to be a 'no tolerance' rule.''</p>
        <p>But others said the verdicts should send a strong signal that Louisiana politicians can no longer charm their way out of trouble. ''Hopefully, this will send the message that it's not funny anymore,'' said Jim Brandt, president of the Public Affairs Research Council of Louisiana.</p>
        <p>It is a measure of this state's cynicism that many here expressed surprise at the convictions even as they expressed certainty about Mr. Edwards's guilt. Many also questioned whether he would spend a day in jail, despite the toughness of the verdicts.</p>
        <p>Still, the convictions wiped away the disillusionment felt by John Volz, the former United States attorney who failed twice to convict Mr. Edwards in the 1980's. ''It really has sort of restored my faith in the ability of Louisiana citizens to recognize outrageous conduct on the part of its public officials,'' he said. ''It took 15 years, but justice has been done.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 12, 2000, Friday  An article yesterday about public reaction to corruption in Louisiana and the conviction of former Gov. Edwin W. Edwards on federal charges of racketeering, conspiracy and extortion misidentified the subject of one indictment. It is Louisiana's former election commissioner, Jerry M. Fowler, not the current one, Suzanne Haik Terrell.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 12, 2000, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about public reaction to corruption in Louisiana and the conviction of former Gov. Edwin W. Edwards on federal charges of racketeering, conspiracy and extortion misidentified the subject of one indictment. It is Louisiana's former election commissioner, Jerry M. Fowler, not the current one, Suzanne Haik Terrell.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
