<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="11BRIE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198563"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED71F38F932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled By Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>RWANDA: BISHOP FACES EXECUTION -- Bishop Augustin Misago, on trial on genocide charges, received a telegram from Pope John Paul II, who said he prayed for him to be freed soon. Prosecutors asked the death penalty for the bishop, who is accused of helping plan the 1994 genocide in which about 800,000 Tutsi and Hutu died. The church has been criticized for its silence during the killings. Bishop Misago, 56, says he is the victim of a political campaign against the church. A verdict is expected next week.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>RWANDA: BISHOP FACES EXECUTION -- Bishop Augustin Misago, on trial on genocide charges, received a telegram from Pope John Paul II, who said he prayed for him to be freed soon. Prosecutors asked the death penalty for the bishop, who is accused of helping plan the 1994 genocide in which about 800,000 Tutsi and Hutu died. The church has been criticized for its silence during the killings. Bishop Misago, 56, says he is the victim of a political campaign against the church. A verdict is expected next week.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>KENYA: CORRUPTION CHARGES -- A report by Parliament accused several people, many with close ties to President Daniel arap Moi, of corruption that cost the nation hundreds of millions of dollars. Among them were George Saitoti, whom Mr. Moi hand-picked as vice president, and Nicholas Biwott, a presidential aide. The report also urged that Mr. Moi's son Philip be investigated for possibly evading taxes on imported luxury cars. Mr. Moi was not named.</p>
        <p>Ian Fisher (NYT)</p>
        <p>ZIMBABWE: VOTE BOYCOTT CONSIDERED -- Faced with continuing attacks against his supporters, the leader of the main opposition party, the Movement for Democratic Change, said his party was considering boycotting coming parliamentary elections. For weeks the party's president, Morgan Tsvangirai, has vowed to carry on with his challenge to President Robert Mugabe and the ruling party. But political violence, sometimes deadly, is persisting, threatening to disrupt any voting.</p>
        <p>Henri E. Cauvin (NYT)</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: NATIONWIDE STRIKE -- Tens of thousands of workers joined a one-day nationwide strike protesting the high unemployment rate and the government policies that labor unions believe are partly to blame for the shortage of jobs. Organized by the Congress of South African Trade Unions, the strike caused scattered service and production disruptions for some businesses.</p>
        <p>Henri E. Cauvin (NYT)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>ITALY: DISCOUNTING THE DEAD -- The government passed an emergency decree to eliminate dead or relocated voters from electoral lists, fearing that bloated rolls would weaken the chances of reaching the 51 percent quorum necessary for a deeply contested referendum set for May 21. But the decree needs approval from both houses of Parliament within 60 days. Many members oppose the vote, which among other things seeks to reform electoral laws at the expense of small parties. If either house fails to support the decree, it would nullify the referendum, regardless of its results.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: HOUSING REFUGEES -- The government is considering building two detention centers to house refugees whose asylum applications have failed and are awaiting deportation. There are enough beds to house 900 asylum seekers at a time, but the government wants to increase that to about 2,900. More than 75,000 people have applied for asylum in the past year; a backlog of 93,365 are awaiting decisions.</p>
        <p>Sarah Lyall (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>ECUADOR: TOP BRASS QUIT -- The heads of the navy and air force and the chairman of the joint chiefs of staff have resigned, with local press reports describing their action as a protest over a government plan to free officers who took part in a coup in January. The coup leader, Gen. Carlos Mendoza, is on trial with 117 mid-level officers also involved in the overthrow of President Jamil Mahuad. But the new president, Gustavo Noboa, has asked Congress to approve an amnesty for the coup plotters.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>COLOMBIA: MINISTER RESIGNS -- Minister of the Interior Nestor Martinez has quit and been replaced by a fellow member of the opposition Liberal Party rather than face a congressional investigation that could have led to his ouster. His departure came as President Andres Pastrana was withdrawing his plan for a referendum in July on dissolving the corruption-ridden Congress and replacing it with a new legislature. The inquiry aimed at Mr. Martinez was seen as a warning to Mr. Pastrana not to proceed with his plan.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>MEXICO: KIDNAPPER KINSMAN KIDNAPPED -- One of Mexico's cruelest kidnappers has suffered the abduction of a nephew, with ransom set at $2 million, authorities told the newspaper Reforma. The victim, 10, is the son of Aurelio Arizmendi, who is in prison charged with taking part in 24 kidnappings carried out by a gang led by his brother. The gang was known for cutting off victims' ears.</p>
        <p>Sam Dillon (NYT)</p>
        <p>ARGENTINA: PRESIDENTIAL ALLY WINS -- Anibal Ibarra, a liberal ally of President Fernando de la Rua, was elected mayor of Buenos Aires, promising to fight crime and improve services. Mr. Ibarra won only 49.1 percent of the vote but averted a runoff when his closest competitor withdrew. His victory was seen as a major help for the president, whose policies have been slow to improve the economy.</p>
        <p>Clifford Krauss (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: ACEH PEACE TALKS -- Two rebel factions in Aceh Province said they had stopped fighting with the military, hoping that peace talks in Europe would produce the first formal cease-fire in 25 years. In another sign of growing optimism, people across Aceh plan to gather in mosques and schools tomorrow to pray for a breakthrough at the landmark talks, to begin tomorrow in Geneva.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>IRAQ: ALLIES ATTACK -- Western aircraft bombed air defenses after coming under fire while patrolling a no-flight zone in the north, the European Central Command in Germany said. Aircraft of the joint American-British force were on patrol near Bashiqah, near Mosul, the command said.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
