<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exhibitions and Tours</title>
    <meta content="11CAL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CALENDAR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4D61E38F932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exhibitions and Tours</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defining American Design</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street; (212) 535-7710.</p>
        <p>''American Modern, 1925-1940: Design for a New Age,'' an exhibition of more than 150 objects, including furniture, appliances, posters, textiles and tableware, starts Tuesday and runs through Jan. 7, 2001. The early items featured in the exhibition show the influence of Art Deco and Bauhaus design.</p>
        <p>Among the objects that trace the development of an American style are a bookcase by Paul Frankl with setbacks like a skyscraper; a streamlined Electrolux vacuum cleaner by Lurelle Guild; earthenware dishes by Russel Wright; and kitchen utensils by Henry Dreyfuss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Defining American Design</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82nd Street; (212) 535-7710.</p>
        <p>''American Modern, 1925-1940: Design for a New Age,'' an exhibition of more than 150 objects, including furniture, appliances, posters, textiles and tableware, starts Tuesday and runs through Jan. 7, 2001. The early items featured in the exhibition show the influence of Art Deco and Bauhaus design.</p>
        <p>Among the objects that trace the development of an American style are a bookcase by Paul Frankl with setbacks like a skyscraper; a streamlined Electrolux vacuum cleaner by Lurelle Guild; earthenware dishes by Russel Wright; and kitchen utensils by Henry Dreyfuss.</p>
        <p>A related exhibition, at the museum through Oct. 29, looks at how the Modernist movement in Europe influenced designs for everyday objects there and in the United States. The 50 objects in ''A Century of Design, Part II: 1925-1950'' include furniture, glassware, ceramics and textiles by Marcel Breuer, Ludwig Mies van der Rohe, Alvar Aalto and Charles and Ray Eames.</p>
        <p>Open Tuesday through Sunday, 9:30 a.m. to 5:30 p.m.; Friday and Saturday until 9 p.m. Suggested admission is $10; students and those 65 and older, $5.</p>
        <p>Crafts in the Village</p>
        <p>Greenwich House Pottery, Jones Street between West Fourth and Bleecker Streets; (212) 242-4106.</p>
        <p>Silk scarves, wooden jewelry boxes, glass vases, silver jewelry and, of course, ceramic plates, teapots, bowls and sculpture will be offered for sale on Saturday, from 11 a.m. to 6 p.m. Rain date is Sunday. No charge for admission.</p>
        <p>By New York Harbor</p>
        <p>Seamen's Society for Children and Families; (718) 816-4684.</p>
        <p>Twelve residential lofts in the Bay Street Landing area, on the waterfront near the Staten Island ferry terminal in Staten Island, will be open for a self-guided house tour on May 21, from 2 to 5 p.m. Reservations are required. Tickets, to benefit the society, $25.</p>
        <p>Historic Newark</p>
        <p>Lincoln Park, Broad Street near Clint Avenue, Newark; (973) 623-7246.</p>
        <p>On Sunday at noon, there will be a guided walking tour of 19th-century sites in the Lincoln Park historic district of Newark, including several homes and their gardens, public statuary and the 1871 James Coe Carriage House. No charge.</p>
        <p>A Collector's Primer</p>
        <p>New-York Historical Society, Central Park West at 77th Street; (212) 873-3400.</p>
        <p>The society will offer three programs on starting and building a collection, on Monday at 6:30 p.m. and on May 22 and June 5. Participants may bring an item to the third program to have it appraised. Reservations are required for each of the three events. No charge.</p>
        <p>Plant Sale</p>
        <p>Clark Botanic Garden, 193 I. U. Willets Road off Glen Cove Road, Albertson, N.Y.; (516) 484-8600.</p>
        <p>The annual plant sale of annuals, perennials, herbs, trees, wildflowers, shrubs and plants for rock gardens, will take place tomorrow and Saturday, from 10 a.m. to 4 p.m. No charge for admission.</p>
        <p>Museum Benefit</p>
        <p>Hudson River Museum of Westchester, 511 Warburton Avenue, near Phillipse Road, Yonkers; (914) 963-4550.</p>
        <p>The annual benefit for the museum, with dinner and an auction of artworks, antiques and gift certificates, will take place on May 18, from 6 to 10:30 p.m. Reservations are required. Tickets, $250.</p>
        <p>CALENDAR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
