<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Taking a Break, Woods Looks Confident</title>
    <meta content="11GOLF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1198557"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gte Byron Nelson Classic</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E3D71F38F932A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Taking a Break, Woods Looks Confident</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>IRVING, Tex., May 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses outlook for GTE Byron Nelson Classic golf tournament (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A little rest usually does Tiger Woods a lot of good. In the past nine months, Woods has taken at least two weeks off on five different occasions. Each time, Woods returned to action by winning his next tournament.</p>
        <p>So after a four-week break, excuse Woods for feeling confident about the GTE Byron Nelson Classic that begins here Thursday. Woods has not competed since the Masters, spending his idle time fishing, resting and preparing for a coming busy stretch that will lead him into next month's United States Open. Feeling rejuvenated and well rested after today's pro-am at the TPC of Las Colinas, Woods said he was over the disappointment of finishing fifth in last month's Masters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A little rest usually does Tiger Woods a lot of good. In the past nine months, Woods has taken at least two weeks off on five different occasions. Each time, Woods returned to action by winning his next tournament.</p>
        <p>So after a four-week break, excuse Woods for feeling confident about the GTE Byron Nelson Classic that begins here Thursday. Woods has not competed since the Masters, spending his idle time fishing, resting and preparing for a coming busy stretch that will lead him into next month's United States Open. Feeling rejuvenated and well rested after today's pro-am at the TPC of Las Colinas, Woods said he was over the disappointment of finishing fifth in last month's Masters.</p>
        <p>''I looked at the Masters as a positive, actually,'' said Woods, who has three victories and three second-place finishes in eight starts this year. ''If you take away two bad holes on Thursday, I had a pretty good tournament. To get myself back in contention at the Masters with a chance to win Sunday, I'm pretty proud of that. I shot the lowest score on the weekend, but I put myself behind on Thursday.''</p>
        <p>Vijay Singh, who won the Masters, will be playing at the Byron Nelson, part of a world-class field that will also include David Duval, Hal Sutton, Davis Love III, Phil Mickelson, Nick Price, Jim Furyk, Jesper Parnevik, Sergio Garcia and Justin Leonard. Loren Roberts is the defending champion, winning last year after beating Steve Pate in a playoff.</p>
        <p>The presence of Nelson, one of golf's greatest players who is now 88 years old, helps to make this tournament one of the most popular on the PGA Tour. Nelson is still giving back to the game, and last week he shared some of his wisdom with Leonard, who has been mired in a yearlong slump.</p>
        <p>Although he is still ranked No. 18 in the world, Leonard does not have a top 10 finish this year, and he has not won in more than two years. Nelson noticed a flaw in Leonard's takeaway, so Nelson visited Leonard at his Dallas home and offered some technical advice.</p>
        <p>''He hasn't been playing well enough to suit him, and rightly so, because he has a lot of talent,'' Nelson said. ''I'd been wanting to talk to him about it for quite awhile. Whether or not he plays worse or better, that's to be seen.''</p>
        <p>The tournament is played on two courses Thursday and Friday -- Las Colinas and Cottonwood Valley, before plays shifts exclusively to Las Colinas on the weekend. Cottonwood Valley is the easier of the two courses, so any player who struggles there probably will not win the tournament.</p>
        <p>''Shoot 70 at Cottonwood, and you're putting yourself behind the eight-ball pretty good,'' said Woods, who won the Byron Nelson in 1997.</p>
        <p>With a strong breeze of 15 to 20 miles an hour expected for Thursday, it could be a difficult day for scoring. But Woods was eager to end his vacation.</p>
        <p>''Hey, I haven't played a tournament in four weeks,'' said Woods, who will play in Germany next week, then compete in the Memorial Tournament the following week. ''I'm pretty excited about getting out there tomorrow. It's nice to hit a shot that really matters. When you're home playing with your boys, you hit a bad shot, it's not a big deal. Pick it up, go on to the next. This is a little different.''</p>
        <p>CHIP SHOTS</p>
        <p>The Byron Nelson field would have been even stronger, but ERNIE ELS (back), FRED COUPLES (back), CRAIG STADLER (back) and BILL GLASSON (personal reasons) withdrew this week. . . . TIGER WOODS has made 47 consecutive cuts, the longest current streak on tour. JIM FURYK, who has made 32 consecutive cuts, is next. . . . COREY PAVIN, who has not won on tour since 1996, could be a long shot to watch this week. Pavin has made 11 consecutive cuts at the Byron Nelson, with three top 10 finishes.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
