<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iran Sends Mixed Messages, One Bad, One Good, to Reformers</title>
    <meta content="Y29TEH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211228"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tehran (Iran)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tehran University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sachs, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rahami, Mohsen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ebadi, Shirin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khamenei, Ali (Ayatollah)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loftian, Hedayatollah (Brig Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0DE1F30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iran Sends Mixed Messages, One Bad, One Good, to Reformers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SACHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sachs, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>TEHRAN, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iranian authorities, torn between conservatives and reformers, act in ways that could both provoke and placate reformers who have been under severe attack by hard-line clergy over last three months; Tehran court jails reformist lawyers Mohsen Rahami and Shirin Ebadi without trial on charges of insulting public officials; Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, nation's supreme leader, abruptly dismisses Brig Gen Hedayatollah Loftian, who was blamed by pro-democracy students for attack on Tehran University that spurred riots last year (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the first anniversary of the riots by pro-democracy students at Tehran University approaching, the Iranian authorities took several actions today that could both provoke and placate  reformers who have been under severe attack by hard-line clergymen over the last three months.</p>
        <p>A court here in the capital sent two well-known reformist lawyers to jail without trial, accusing them of insulting public officials. One, Mohsen Rahami, represented the students who were injured last July 8 by police officers and right-wing vigilantes who attacked their dormitory. The other, Shirin Ebadi, is a prominent human rights lawyer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the first anniversary of the riots by pro-democracy students at Tehran University approaching, the Iranian authorities took several actions today that could both provoke and placate  reformers who have been under severe attack by hard-line clergymen over the last three months.</p>
        <p>A court here in the capital sent two well-known reformist lawyers to jail without trial, accusing them of insulting public officials. One, Mohsen Rahami, represented the students who were injured last July 8 by police officers and right-wing vigilantes who attacked their dormitory. The other, Shirin Ebadi, is a prominent human rights lawyer.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, the country's supreme leader, abruptly fired the commander of the national police, who was blamed by the student protesters for the attack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khamenei gave no reason for the dismissal of the commander, Brig. Gen. Hedayatollah Loftian. Twenty police officers, including General Loftian's deputy, have been on trial for their actions in the campus assault, but no verdict has been announced. Several students were tried last year -- in secret -- and sentenced to death for their role in riots that followed the attack.</p>
        <p>The seemingly paradoxical actions today reflect a tug of war in the highest reaches of the Iranian government between conservatives who fear the growing power of reformers and the liberal activists who want to wrest the judiciary and security forces from the hands of religious hard-liners.</p>
        <p>The tension between the forces could be seen in other pronouncements today by the country's top two leaders, who have rarely taken such diametrically opposing public views.</p>
        <p>President Muhammad Khatami, a moderate cleric who has promoted the rule of law and freedom of expression, said in a speech that individual rights should not be trampled in the pursuit of law and order.</p>
        <p>''If a system creates peace in a society by using force, violence and intimidation, it has secured a temporary peace in a cemetery in which people are nothing more than animated corpses,'' Mr. Khatami said.</p>
        <p>He also made one of his strongest defenses to date of press freedom, calling on the judiciary to resist political pressure and to define clearly what constitutes an offense against the system by writers and journalists.</p>
        <p>In a separate statement broadcast on state radio, Ayatollah Khamenei, who holds ultimate political and religious authority, called on the courts to resist attempts to ''undermine the authority and dignity of the judiciary.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of the president swept elections this year and now control the Iranian Parliament. They have opened an attack on the court system over the last three weeks and pledged to loosen restrictions on the press and political parties.</p>
        <p>But the conservatives who lost control of the Parliament have rallied against their opponents, largely through the court system and through their influence over Ayatollah Khamenei.</p>
        <p>Since late May, judges have summarily closed 20 newspapers and magazines associated with the pro-Khatami forces, with the latest closure this week.</p>
        <p>Courts have also jailed five reformist writers and ordered the arrest of all the Iranian participants at a conference on democracy held in Berlin in the spring.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
