<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hospital Reverses Itself on Hinckley Visits</title>
    <meta content="Y29HINC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Elizabeths Hospital (Washington, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reagan, Ronald Wilson</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hinckley, John W Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1DB1E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hospital Reverses Itself on Hinckley Visits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St Elizabeths Hospital in Washington, DC, withdraws its recommendation that court let John W Hinckley Jr leave hospital for unsupervised weekly visits with parents; Hinckley was found not guilty by reason of insanity in 1981 shooting of Pres Ronald Reagan and three others (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Washington psychiatric hospital reversed itself yesterday and withdrew its recommendation that a court permit John W. Hinckley Jr. to leave the hospital for unsupervised weekly visits with his parents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hinckley, who was found not guilty by reason of insanity in the 1981 shooting of President Ronald Reagan and three others, has argued for years that he should be permitted additional freedom. He has argued that his mental health has improved since he attempted the assassination to prove his devotion to the actress Jodie Foster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Washington psychiatric hospital reversed itself yesterday and withdrew its recommendation that a court permit John W. Hinckley Jr. to leave the hospital for unsupervised weekly visits with his parents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hinckley, who was found not guilty by reason of insanity in the 1981 shooting of President Ronald Reagan and three others, has argued for years that he should be permitted additional freedom. He has argued that his mental health has improved since he attempted the assassination to prove his devotion to the actress Jodie Foster.</p>
        <p>The reversal by the hospital, St. Elizabeths in Washington, followed court filings on Tuesday in which prosecutors said Mr. Hinckley had deceived his psychiatrists this spring and had ''continual interest in violently themed books and music.''</p>
        <p>At least twice before, St. Elizabeths has reversed itself after urging more freedom for Mr. Hinckley. After a recommendation in 1987 in which it said that Mr. Hinckley was no longer a danger, government investigators found 47 photographs of Ms. Foster under Mr. Hinckley's mattress at the hospital.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hinckley could continue to seek the unsupervised visits, but the  hospital's backing had been expected to be influential with the judge, June L. Green, of Federal District Court in Washington. Since last July, Mr. Hinckley, 45, has been permitted occasional visits to malls, restaurants and bookstores in the Washington area but only when accompanied by hospital employees.</p>
        <p>The prosecutors did not identify the books or music Mr. Hinckley had obtained but said that after the hospital recommended the unsupervised visits last March, he had told his treatment team about the materials. Mr. Hinckley also acknowledged that his fiancee, Leslie deVeau, had helped him keep the materials secret from the hospital, the prosecutors said.</p>
        <p>''He said that Ms. deVeau had purchased certain books for him, brought them to St. Elizabeths, given them to him and taken them back once Mr. Hinckley had read them,'' said the filing by the federal prosecutors, Robert R. Chapman and Thomas E. Zeno.</p>
        <p>Ms. deVeau's telephone number is unlisted and she could not be reached yesterday. Mr. Hinckley's lawyer, Barry Wm. Levine, did not respond to telephone calls but The Washington Post reported yesterday that Mr. Levine said on Tuesday that the prosecutors' assertions were a smoke screen to distract attention from the remission of Mr. Hinckley's  psychiatric illness.</p>
        <p>Ms. DeVeau and Mr. Hinckley met while she was in the same hospital after being acquitted by reason of insanity for killing her 10-year-old daughter. She was released in 1985.</p>
        <p>St. Elizabeths' director of forensic services, Dr. Raymond Patterson, declined to discuss Mr. Hinckley's case but said the hospital would typically withdraw a recommendation for unsupervised visits if it learned new information.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hinckley's efforts to win additional freedom have often been frustrated by disclosures. Once it was disclosed that he had written to the serial killer Ted Bundy and once that he had sought a nude drawing of Ms. Foster. There has also been evidence that Mr. Hinckley developed an obsessive interest in a female pharmacist at the hospital in the mid-1990's and that he expressed admiration for the serial killer Charles Manson.</p>
        <p>In a 1997 ruling on one of Mr. Hinckley's requests, Judge Green said Mr. Hinckley had often deceived those treating him. The judge quoted from a 1987 diary entry by Mr. Hinckley. ''Psychiatry is a guessing game and I do my best to keep the fools guessing about me,'' Mr. Hinckley wrote. ''They will never know the true John Hinckley.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
