<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Change, Braves Happy to Focus on the Mets</title>
    <meta content="29BRAV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Braves</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, William C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rocker, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3DD1F30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Change, Braves Happy to Focus on the Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <dateline>MONTREAL, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William C Rhoden Sports of The Times column discusses Atlanta Braves and pitcher John Rocker coming to Shea Stadium to play New York Mets in four game series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The focus should be on baseball when the Atlanta Braves play the Mets beginning Thursday night, not on John Rocker. This should be about two teams meeting in an intense pennant race, not about one player who has made himself a villain with his disparaging remarks. The Braves have expressed these thoughts so much in the last two days that they sound scripted.</p>
        <p>Well, the Braves could get their wish because the four-game series with the Mets is also about first place in the National League East. There will be a chaotic, frenzied atmosphere at Shea Stadium because Rocker is making his first visit to New York since he criticized gays, foreigners, minority groups and most New Yorkers in an article in Sports Illustrated last December.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The focus should be on baseball when the Atlanta Braves play the Mets beginning Thursday night, not on John Rocker. This should be about two teams meeting in an intense pennant race, not about one player who has made himself a villain with his disparaging remarks. The Braves have expressed these thoughts so much in the last two days that they sound scripted.</p>
        <p>Well, the Braves could get their wish because the four-game series with the Mets is also about first place in the National League East. There will be a chaotic, frenzied atmosphere at Shea Stadium because Rocker is making his first visit to New York since he criticized gays, foreigners, minority groups and most New Yorkers in an article in Sports Illustrated last December.</p>
        <p>But the fans will also be thrilled because the Braves are sputtering, and that has enabled the Mets to creep within two games of first place, the closest they have been to first place since April 27. The Braves had the look of an invincible team when they won 15 straight games earlier this season, but they look much more flawed eight weeks later.  One of Atlanta's best players said the Mets actually look like the better team right now.</p>
        <p>''They have all the components of a championship club, probably more than we do at this point,'' Chipper Jones said of the Mets. ''They're the team that's trying to dethrone us.''</p>
        <p>Does Jones really think the Braves, who have won eight straight division titles, are inferior to the Mets, or was he being coy? When Jones was asked why he thought the Mets were more of a championship team, he talked about why the Braves have struggled instead of praising the Mets.</p>
        <p>Jones mentioned how injuries to John Smoltz and Kevin McGlinchy have affected the pitching rotation, how the bullpen has been hurt by the loss of Rudy Seanez, and how catcher Eddie Perez's absence has hurt Atlanta's depth.</p>
        <p>He did not mention Rocker's ineffectiveness out of the bullpen or the additional injuries to pitchers Greg McMichael and Odalis Perez, but he could have.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is, for the last month, we haven't played well,'' Jones said. ''We overcame injuries last year. We'll see if we can do it again.''</p>
        <p>Even after quieting the Expos, 7-4, tonight, the Braves are still trying to right themselves and avoid an ignominious finish to their month. The Braves are 12-14 in June and, with two games left, they could experience their first losing month since they went 12-15 in September of 1996.</p>
        <p>The Braves have won five National League pennants in the 1990's so they have survived slumps before, but they should be a little worried because they have been an ordinary team for almost a third of the season. Since their 15-game streak ended on May 2, the Braves are 27-24 and have allowed the Mets to dream about jumping into first with a four-game sweep. A month ago, the Mets wondered if they should start thinking about the wild-card berth.</p>
        <p>Tom Glavine played optimist and said the Braves are in the position they expected to be because they expected a pennant race.</p>
        <p>It sounded believable, but the Braves were not thinking in those terms when they had a seven-game lead on May 31.</p>
        <p>''We knew a time like this was going to come,'' Glavine said. ''You don't go through a season without having some kind of down period. We're obviously there right now.''</p>
        <p>The last time the Braves played the Mets, Kenny Rogers threw ball four to Andruw Jones and Atlanta survived to win Game 6 by 10-9 in 11 innings and the National League Championship Series. After the Braves surged to a 3-0 lead in the series and came within four outs of a sweep, the Mets rushed back and came within three outs of incredibly forcing a seventh game.</p>
        <p>Glavine admitted that the Braves wanted desperately to prevent the series from reaching a decisive game because the Mets were gaining more and more confidence.</p>
        <p>''Those games,'' Glavine said, ''were as exciting as any World Series games.''</p>
        <p>Now the teams finally meet again with a Rocker sideshow invading Shea in this intriguing series. The Mets feel as if they have been chasing the Braves for a decade and they are chasing them again.</p>
        <p>Greg Maddux, who starts for Atlanta on Thursday, said the series could be a ''turning point for either club'' and laughed about the spectacle he will see by saying, ''I'm anxious to pitch there.''</p>
        <p>Andres Galarraga is a terrific comeback story, Chipper Jones and Andruw Jones are having solid seasons and Maddux has been typically excellent.</p>
        <p>But the rotation has missed Smoltz after his season-ending elbow surgery, has been hurt by Kevin Milwood's inconsistency and has even had to rely on John Burkett.</p>
        <p>The bullpen has been erratic, but still leads the major leagues with 26 saves in 32 chances. Some Braves are hopeful that playing the Mets will give them a boost.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes, when you find yourself in these situations, it brings out the best in you,'' Glavine said.</p>
        <p>Many of the Braves stayed secluded in the visiting clubhouse at Olympic Stadium for the last two days while avoiding the news media. When two reporters asked Chipper Jones if he would answer some non-Rocker questions, he instead said that he would address any questions. Jones is tired of seeing the games getting overshadowed, especially the games against the Mets.</p>
        <p>''That's what the emphasis should be on,'' Jones said. ''So much has been lost in the last six or eight months. We got two of the best teams in baseball going at each other in the middle of June. There's been very little emphasis on the two teams. It's been on how somebody is going to get to the ballpark. That's wrong.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
