<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tiki Gods Emerge And Join The Luau</title>
    <meta content="29TIKI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="DESIGN NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kahiki (Columbus, Ohio, Supper Club)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Decaro, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Design Notebook</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DF1E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tiki Gods Emerge And Join The Luau</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK DeCARO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Decaro, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Design Notebook column on interior design of Kahiki, Polynesian-style supper club of 1950's and 1960's in Columbus, Ohio; club opened in 1962 and was placed on National Register of Historic Places in 1997; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT rises like a giant war canoe, a pair of tiki gods flanking its front door, flames lapping the dusk from a red pot atop each stone head. Inside, a cloud of dry ice billows from the rum-and-fruit-juice drinks known as Smoking Eruptions. A gong sounds, a maiden appears, a macaw shifts on its perch, then lightning flashes. So much excitement, and the Samoan Flaming Chicken hasn't even been served yet.</p>
        <p>Welcome to the Kahiki. Port of call: Columbus, Ohio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT rises like a giant war canoe, a pair of tiki gods flanking its front door, flames lapping the dusk from a red pot atop each stone head. Inside, a cloud of dry ice billows from the rum-and-fruit-juice drinks known as Smoking Eruptions. A gong sounds, a maiden appears, a macaw shifts on its perch, then lightning flashes. So much excitement, and the Samoan Flaming Chicken hasn't even been served yet.</p>
        <p>Welcome to the Kahiki. Port of call: Columbus, Ohio.</p>
        <p>The grandest and best preserved of a nearly extinct form of culinary recreation -- the Polynesian-style supper club of the 1950's and 60's -- this tropical restaurant is a vintage postcard from the South Seas, across from a Kmart. It is a painstaking hybrid of Disneyland's ''Enchanted Tiki Room,'' ''Gilligan's Island'' and the Chinese restaurants that thrived when ''exotic'' meant water chestnuts and sweet-and-sour sauce.</p>
        <p>Opened in 1962 and placed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1997, Kahiki has been a real survivor -- until now. Occupying a choice retail site, it will close on Aug. 26, to make way for a Walgreens.</p>
        <p>While preservationists labor to save Kahiki, the luau goes on elsewhere. After a decade of bubbling under pop culture's crust like a subterranean lava pool, tiki is back. It's all happening now: surfing, the revival of Hawaiian shirts, lounge music and tropical merchandise that Trader Vic's would have adored.</p>
        <p>There are tiki coasters, tiki-patterned boxer shorts, a magazine called Tiki News, even a ''Tiki Type'' font kit from House Industries that allows 21st century party-givers to print 50's-style luau invitations on their iMacs. Several new books include the most comprehensive look at the trend, ''In Search of Tiki: A Guide for the Urban Archeologist,'' by Sven A. Kirsten (Taschen).</p>
        <p>In the 1980's, when he began collecting mugs shaped like primitive gods, ''tiki was considered ugly,'' Mr. Kirsten said. ''You could get a tiki mug for a buck, not like now on eBay,'' he said. (One from a 1961 screening of Elvis Presley's ''Blue Hawaii'' sold for nearly $1,000 on the Internet late last year.)</p>
        <p>Josh Agle, an artist who paints tiki style, began collecting tikis about 12 years ago when he first began frequenting tiki bars. ''It started with taking home souvenir mugs,'' he said. ''It was so cool, because it was like stepping back in time when you went to these bars.''</p>
        <p>He has recreated the ambience of those bars at home in Orange, Calif. ''It's kind of high maintenance, because tikis are dust collectors,'' he said. ''But people like the U.P.S. guy are pretty impressed, even though he doesn't know what it is.''</p>
        <p>Anticipating a spate of Polynesian-style parties among 30- to 40-year-olds this spring, Macy's East division opened a ''Patio Luau'' department with plastic plates patterned with hibiscus flowers. The shops themselves were festooned with Easter Island tiki heads and palm trees.</p>
        <p>''This year, we really felt that everything in the fashion market was gearing toward the return of pattern,'' said Joe Denofrio, a senior vice president for fashion at Macy's East. ''We felt that if people are interested in florals for apparel, they'd be feeling the same about their summer entertaining. You can picture yourself out on your patio in floral board shorts, with a lantern and some great floral serving trays. A tiki is really a natural component there.''</p>
        <p>Sur La Table, the Seattle-based kitchenware retailer better known for Moroccan tea glasses than mai tai mugs, put ceramic tiki tumblers on the cover of its summer catalog. Likewise, at the trend-savvy Old Navy, tiki masks are embroidered on camp shirts.</p>
        <p>''For us, it's part of that whole vintage fun retro feel,'' said Joe Enos, a spokesman for Old Navy. ''Everything has a wink to it.'' Mr. Enos got his first taste of tiki in the 60's at a restaurant called the Coral Reef in Sacramento, Calif.</p>
        <p>Although Quiksilver, Tommy Bahama and other surf-inspired fashion lines have long mined tiki iconography, many mainstream designers have caught the wave this season, from Bloomingdale's and J. Crew to Ralph Lauren, who is serving up T-shirts printed with the image of a wooden tiki idol on whose base had been carved the word ''Polo.''</p>
        <p>Stranger still is the cross-pollination of hip-hop and tiki from a line called Mecca. The company's hot-colored T-shirts are silk-screened with Easter Island tiki heads.</p>
        <p>Partygoers, Mr. Denofrio said of Macy's, are doing it their own way. ''It's multicultural, and it goes every way from the South Seas to Southeast Asia,'' he said. ''It's all things exotic.''</p>
        <p>The glut of new tiki merchandise, said Otto von Stroheim, the founder of Tiki News, ''has created the ability for more people to have fun in the tiki scene.''</p>
        <p>Tiki was not originally an underground movement, he pointed out. ''Before, it wasn't that hip anyway,'' he said. ''It was always very mainstream.''</p>
        <p>Michael Stern, whose numerous books on pop culture, written with his wife, Jane, include the seminal Encyclopedia of Bad Taste, is, of course, a fan of tiki. ''What's so wonderful about tiki is that it allows us to wallow in a vernacular that's so ersatz,'' he said. ''It's sort of a twice-removed fascination. There was a time when Trader Vic's was considered by sophisticated people to be true exotica. The fascination is that it still exists in that totally bogus form.'' His own favorite Polynesian restaurant was the Hukilau, near Hartford, which is now defunct.</p>
        <p>''We Americans crave play, but there's so much seriousness in food and entertainment. But you can't do that with Polynesian stuff.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kirsten understands completely. The German-born, Los Angeles-based cinematographer is an authority on the ''Polynesian Pop'' movement in art and design. His lavishly illustrated book, the fruit of two decades of collecting, is due from Taschen later this year. It celebrates tiki's golden years.</p>
        <p>Polynesia's moment in mainland America spanned from just after World War II, when soldiers first brought home aloha shirts and Hawaiian tourism took off, through the early 60's era of Annette Funicello's ''Pineapple Princess'' and the series ''Hawaiian Eye.'' By the time ''Hawaii Five-O'' rounded up the last villain in 1980, tiki was dead, a trend that had become stiffer than Jack Lord's hair.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Kirsten concedes that tiki aficionados are rare compared with, say, Fiestaware collectors, he says restaurants like Kahiki need to take their place in pop culture history. ''The typical thing at such restaurants was to invite people from the audience to go onstage and dance the hula and make fools of themselves. There's always a need for that.''</p>
        <p>Unfortunately only a handful of tiki-toriums remain: the Mai-Kai, a Fort Lauderdale, Fla., luau restaurant where hula shows are still performed; the Tonga Room, a watering hole with indoor thunderstorms in San Francisco's Fairmont Hotel, and the Hala Kahiki bar in River Grove, Ill., where everything that isn't tiki is leopard print.</p>
        <p>At Lee's Hawaiian Islander in Lyndhurst, N.J., on a recent Saturday night, not much had changed from the nostalgic scene Mr. Kirsten describes. At the restaurant, Michael Doneff, the owner of Nice House, a Greenwich Village design store, was the host of a friend's 40th birthday party.</p>
        <p>''They have booths that look like thatched-roof huts,'' he said. ''They have a whole wall of fake lava rock with plastic bouquets stuck in it. We had pu pu platters and flaming drinks. It was just kind of goofy.''</p>
        <p>While bamboo is considered chic among the tastemakers who frequent his shop, Mr. Doneff says, its tiki-tacky counterparts are hip again, too.</p>
        <p>''Younger kids are finding it cool,'' he said. ''You see things like paper lanterns at Urban Outfitters and Restoration Hardware and you just get in the mood to hang lights and sip something out of a plastic pineapple.''</p>
        <p>But it is the places that celebrated tiki on a grand scale that tiki lovers most revere. ''There's no place like the Kahiki,'' Mr. Kirsten said. ''It has a certain irreverence that still applies today. It's so unconcerned with political correctness and the fact that it's stepping on toes in terms of taste and ancestral customs.''</p>
        <p>Janu Cassidy, co-founder of the New York-based Hawaii Cultural Foundation and owner of Radio Hula, a Hawaiian shop in SoHo, said: ''Being from Hawaii, I should probably be offended, but I have an appreciation for it. What I really appreciate is the nostalgic feeling and the romance behind it all.''</p>
        <p>It's even having an effect in her home state. ''For the first time in a long time, I'm seeing locals not feeling shy about wearing Hawaiian prints,'' she said, speaking from Honolulu. The trend is expected only to get bigger when the big budget romantic epic ''Pearl Harbor,'' starring Ben Affleck, opens next year.</p>
        <p>Now, though, Mr. Kirsten predicts that tiki ''will have a glorious comeback and then fade away again.'' He says he hopes the remaining Polynesian restaurants don't go the way of Trader Vic's and Hawaii Kai, both late of Manhattan. ''I'm not a revivalist,'' he said. ''I don't think tiki should be resurrected the way it was. It can't, because there's not the same sense of naivete that there was in the 50's about Polynesian culture. But what's here should be preserved and enjoyed for what it was.''</p>
        <p>When Kahiki closes its doors in August, it is expected that its contents will be saved and the building razed. Where an aloha-shirted bartender is dispensing Pina Passion potions today, a white-coated Walgreens pharmacist may be filling Viagra prescriptions next year. Tiki News is planning a farewell party to bid Kahiki aloha. ''It's going to be a historic tiki event,'' Mr. von Stroheim said. ''Unfortunately, closing restaurants are the only historic tiki events I've been to in my lifetime.''</p>
        <p>DESIGN NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
