<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Escaped Prisoner Is Found Dead in Bronx</title>
    <meta content="29ESCA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211246"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prison Escapes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lincoln Hospital (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koh, Eun Lee</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hightower, Jamel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prison Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDD1F30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="690" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Escaped Prisoner Is Found Dead in Bronx</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EUN LEE KOH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Koh, Eun Lee</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jamel Hightower, prisoner who escaped from Lincoln Hospital where he was taken after saying he was having seizure, is found dead on Bronx park bench of apparent drug overdose (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A prisoner who escaped from a city hospital on Tuesday where he was taken after saying he was having a seizure was found dead early yesterday on a Bronx park bench.</p>
        <p>The police found the body of the prisoner, Jamel Hightower, 24, of the Bronx, slouched over on a bench near the 40th Precinct station house at 6:40 a.m. yesterday, said Sgt. Brian Burke, a police spokesman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A prisoner who escaped from a city hospital on Tuesday where he was taken after saying he was having a seizure was found dead early yesterday on a Bronx park bench.</p>
        <p>The police found the body of the prisoner, Jamel Hightower, 24, of the Bronx, slouched over on a bench near the 40th Precinct station house at 6:40 a.m. yesterday, said Sgt. Brian Burke, a police spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hightower was wearing a stolen Rite Aid drugstore vest and nearby was a bag containing clothes and empty plastic bags believed to have held narcotics, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The police said they suspected a drug overdose as the cause of death, but the medical examiner's office said yesterday that it had yet to determine the cause.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hightower, who was facing charges of attempted murder and robbery, was at State Supreme Court in the Bronx on Monday when he seemed to be foaming at the mouth and told officials he was having a  seizure. The authorities said they suspect now that he used Alka-Seltzer tablets to create the foaming.</p>
        <p>Early the next morning he was admitted to Lincoln Hospital in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>At 6 a.m. on Tuesday, Mr. Hightower asked to go to the bathroom, and his guards, against department policy, removed his leg shackles, officials said. Mr. Hightower slipped past the three corrections officers who were standing outside his hospital room, ran down eight flights of stairs and escaped through the emergency room entrance, officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hightower's mother, Dorothy Parker, 44, who said she learned of his death through television reports, described her son as ''a good boy'' and said she had last seen him on Thursday, when she visited him in jail.</p>
        <p>''He worked hard, got A's in school, and got his high school diploma,'' she said yesterday. But Mr. Hightower had been in trouble with the law before, she said.</p>
        <p>At 12, after he stole a bicycle, his mother said, he was sent to Berkshire Farms, a school in upstate New York for troubled youths. In 1994, he robbed and sexually abused two women in Manhattan elevators, the authorities have said.</p>
        <p>After serving two-thirds of his sentence, he was released on parole in September 1998, but he was sent back to jail a year later after he attacked his parole officer.</p>
        <p>On March 15, 2000, he was released by the prison system for good behavior.</p>
        <p>In April, Mr. Hightower was involved in the incident that led to his most recent arrest. The police said he stabbed two people during a drug deal in a Bronx apartment that went awry and then later opened fire at a police car. During the police pursuit, he held a bus driver at gunpoint and used a woman as a shield against police gunfire. After an explosive gun battle in which a bystander was shot and seriously injured, he was caught when he fell as he tried to climb over a railroad station fence, officials said.</p>
        <p>The three officers in charge of guarding Mr. Hightower when he escaped from the Bronx hospital have been suspended by the Correction Department.</p>
        <p>The guards, Chet Outten, Cleveland Wilson and Joseph Shanley, who all had served at least 10 years, gave conflicting reports of how the escape happened, but it was clear that rules had been broken, said Thomas Antenen, a spokesman for the Department of Correction.</p>
        <p>Procedure calls for two officers to guard prisoners at all times in the hospital and for prisoners to have their feet shackled together when moving around the hospital, Mr. Antenen said. At least one foot has to be shackled to the hospital bed when the prisoners are in their rooms, officials said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
