<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Early Summit Meeting on the Mideast Is Proving Elusive</title>
    <meta content="Y29DIP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211163"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Israel-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perlez, Jane</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Albright, Madeleine K (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D91E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="873" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Early Summit Meeting on the Mideast Is Proving Elusive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perlez, Jane</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israelis and Palestinians seem far from meeting conditions set by Clinton administration for early summit meeting in Washington; Sec Madeleine K Albright, in Israel, says Pres Clinton will decide soon on immediate summit; meets with Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat in Ramallah; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Israelis and Palestinians appeared today to remain far from meeting the conditions set down by the Clinton administration for an early summit meeting in Washington. But Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, who came here to assess the two sides' readiness, said that President Clinton would make a decision in the next few days.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright and her aides left open the possibility that Mr. Clinton might decide that now was the time to seize the moment and go for an immediate summit meeting. Palestinian officials, however, suggested that they would prefer more negotiations over the next two weeks so they could improve their positions for a meeting a bit later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Israelis and Palestinians appeared today to remain far from meeting the conditions set down by the Clinton administration for an early summit meeting in Washington. But Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, who came here to assess the two sides' readiness, said that President Clinton would make a decision in the next few days.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright and her aides left open the possibility that Mr. Clinton might decide that now was the time to seize the moment and go for an immediate summit meeting. Palestinian officials, however, suggested that they would prefer more negotiations over the next two weeks so they could improve their positions for a meeting a bit later.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright refused today to concede that an immediate summit meeting was unlikely, even though she has said in the past that it would not be fruitful to call one unless the two sides had significantly narrowed their differences.</p>
        <p>President Clinton, speaking at a news conference at the White House today, said that nothing had been scheduled. But he added that he did not think the final, most difficult issues could be resolved unless the Israeli and Palestinian leaders ''get together in some isolated setting and make the last tough decisions, or decide not to make them, as the case may be.''</p>
        <p>A top aide to Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, Nabil Shaath,  who took part in talks today between Mr. Arafat and Dr. Albright in Ramallah, ruled out the possibility of a summit meeting in the next two weeks.</p>
        <p>He said that major differences persisted on the key issues of Israel's withdrawal from the West Bank, the status of Jerusalem and the fate of Palestinian refugees.</p>
        <p>''We would like to see a summit held in the White House presided over by President Clinton to be successful,'' Mr. Shaath said, indicating that it was still too soon. ''You can't bridge oceans. It's much easier to bridge rivers.''</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Ehud Barak of Israel has been eager for a summit meeting, even as early as next week, in part because his parliamentary coalition has been roiled by contention over the terms of a peace with the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak has calculated, Israeli analysts say, that the sooner he can get a peace agreement, one that he insists will ''strengthen'' Israel, the better it will be for his political survival.</p>
        <p>In a sharp reversal from when he came to power 18 months ago, Mr. Barak is now anxious for American involvement to prod the peace effort along.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Clinton, who has already invested considerable time coaxing Mr. Barak and Mr. Arafat toward the finish line, time is running out. But Dr. Albright declined to rule out a summit meeting during the Democratic and Republican conventions in late July and August.</p>
        <p>At a news conference today with Dr. Albright, Mr. Barak said that calling a summit meeting was the prerogative of Mr. Clinton. ''It is up to the President to make up his mind,'' Mr. Barak said. ''We will be ready.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Until now we have no agreement. The substantial negotiation will begin only if and when there will be a summit meeting and we will negotiate only an agreement that will strengthen Israel.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Albright, on a second visit here in a month to set the stage for a summit meeting that Mr. Clinton hopes will be a crowning achievement of his presidency, arrived as the administration's senior Middle East envoy, Dennis Ross, completed a week of intense negotiations.</p>
        <p>There was serious activity on all fronts in the last week, including a briefing by Mr. Ross of Mr. Barak's shaky coalition partners in an effort to assuage them about the details of the negotiations. There was also an unusually long, five-hour session last Sunday between Mr. Arafat and Mr. Barak's chief negotiator, Shlomo Ben-Ami.</p>
        <p>In addition, Israel's justice minister, Yossi Beilin, flew to Cairo to brief President Hosni Mubarek of Egypt, who is seen as an important link to Mr. Arafat.</p>
        <p>Over the last two weeks, the Israeli press has been deluged with leaks  about the possible contours of a peace agreement. These have included the notion of the Palestinians' receiving more than 90 percent of the West Bank, considerably more than previously contemplated.</p>
        <p>But one of the key elements of the territorial issue, according to officials, is that Mr. Arafat is demanding that if the Palestinians do not receive 100 percent of the West Bank, they must be compensated with Israeli land elsewhere, possibly in the Negev near the Gaza strip. This sort of ''land swap'' has not been discussed much in public and according to officials will be a crucial ingredient of a summit meeting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
