<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Phone Giants Reconnoiter as Merger Stalls</title>
    <meta content="Y29PHON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Worldcom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sprint Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holson, Laura M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D91E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Phone Giants Reconnoiter as Merger Stalls</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA M. HOLSON and ANDREW ROSS SORKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross; Holson, Laura M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Worldcom and Sprint Corp have not yet called off their merger, but already rumors are swirling about who might try to buy either company; telecommunications executives around world huddle with their advisers to figure out what Justice Department's opposition to WorldCom-Sprint merer might mean for them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WorldCom and the Sprint Corporation have not yet called off their merger, but already the rumors are swirling about who might try to buy either company.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, telecommunications executives around the globe huddled with their advisers to figure out what the Justice Department's opposition to the WorldCom-Sprint merger might mean for them. For the moment, all they can do is wonder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WorldCom and the Sprint Corporation have not yet called off their merger, but already the rumors are swirling about who might try to buy either company.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, telecommunications executives around the globe huddled with their advisers to figure out what the Justice Department's opposition to the WorldCom-Sprint merger might mean for them. For the moment, all they can do is wonder.</p>
        <p>By contract, neither Sprint nor WorldCom can talk to other parties until their merger agreement is terminated or unless both companies agree to third-party discussions. Neither Sprint nor WorldCom would comment yesterday, but after the Justice Department filed suit on Tuesday to block their merger, it is widely assumed that the companies will call off the deal. ''The probability is high,'' said a person close to the two companies' discussions.</p>
        <p>Investors, too, are betting that the deal will fall apart. WorldCom's stock price was up $4.875, to close at $44.5625 yesterday. Sprint's stock fell $5.625, closing at $52.75.</p>
        <p>And while Sprint, in particular, is seen as a potential takeover target,  ''no one is entirely safe,'' said Adam Quinton, a telecommunications analyst at Merrill Lynch. ''The evolution of the industry is that if it was compelling to hook up 12 months ago, it is even more so now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That does not mean competitors are ready to rush in just yet, though. Executives close to BellSouth, the regional phone company that lost a bidding war to WorldCom for Sprint last October, said that BellSouth was sitting tight for the moment.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the world looks different than it did last fall. BellSouth, for one, now has a joint venture with SBC Communications to combine their wireless operations. Such a deal, analysts said, makes it less pressing for BellSouth to own Sprint's wireless operations. And BellSouth, primarily a local telephone company, does not yet have approval to sell long-distance service -- another drawback.</p>
        <p>Analysts expect BellSouth to wait to see if a foreign buyer, particularly the cash-rich Deutsche Telekom of Germany, makes a run at either Sprint or WorldCom.</p>
        <p>Ron Sommer, Deutsche Telekom's chairman, said two weeks ago that he expected to have a war chest of about $100 billion to pay for his entry into the United States. Just this week, Deutsche Telekom raised $14.5 billion in the largest corporate bond offering ever. Recently, Deutsche Telekom's Internet arm, T-Online,  had an initial public offering in which it raised more than $30 billion. And the parent company plans to issue an additional 1.5 billion new shares over the next five years to raise money.</p>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom failed to secure an American beachhead this year when talks between it and Qwest Communications International, the Denver-based telecommunications carrier, collapsed. The talks hit a snag when U S West, which was closing its own merger with Qwest, objected to the deal. U S West did not like the fact that its shareholders would have received a significantly lower premium for their shares than shareholders of Qwest. The Qwest-U S West merger received approval from the Federal Communications Commission on Monday.</p>
        <p>Executives close to Deutsche Telekom said the company might be particularly interested in Sprint, in which it already owns a stake of about 10 percent, because the deal would give the German company both a fixed-line and wireless network in the United States.</p>
        <p>While analysts have pointed to Sprint's wireless network as its crown jewel and possibly a property that could be sold independently of Sprint's fixed-line business, executives close to several major European telephone companies mulling an offer for Sprint disagreed. These executives said that Sprint was more likely to be acquired whole because of the increasing importance placed on a strategy that combines both businesses.</p>
        <p>Deutsche Telekom wants to make a United States acquisition by the end of the year, according to executives close to the company, and the company has held internal meetings in the last week to discuss options now that WorldCom's acquisition of Sprint looks doomed. If the German company goes after Sprint, Qwest's lingering hopes of an eventual combination with Deutsche Telekom would be dashed.</p>
        <p>But if Deutsche Telekom decides not to make a play for Sprint, executives close to the company said it might return to the bargaining table with the merged Qwest-U S West or possibly look at Global Crossing Ltd., an undersea fiber optic cable operator that has already had informal talks with Deutsche Telekom. An executive close to Telekom said it was just a matter of time before the company pounced -- with the only question being in which direction.</p>
        <p>Besides Deutsche Telekom, France Telecom is also seen as a formidable overseas contender to acquire either WorldCom or Sprint, although again Sprint is the more realistic target. WorldCom's size is such that if it merged with France Telecom, or even Deutsche Telekom, WorldCom might end up with the controlling interest.</p>
        <p>Like Deutsche Telekom, France Telecom already owns approximately 10 percent of Sprint.</p>
        <p>France Telecom has its own ambitions to do business in the United States, although analysts said it might not have the cash or stock to make a deal unilaterally. But Sprint is particularly attractive to France Telecom, which recently acquired Orange, Britain's third-largest wireless telephone company. Orange, combined with Sprint, could become a worldwide brand.</p>
        <p>A person close to France Telecom also said the company had recently analyzed the feasibility of making a bid for AT&amp;T, which has a slumping stock price. The French company went so far as to calculate what the value of AT&amp;T might be if it were broken up, this person said.</p>
        <p>Analysts see Nippon Telegraph and Telephone of Japan as another possible bidder. It has the money and its wireless arm operates I-mode, the most advanced wireless network in the world, all of which might make Sprint an attractive potential fit.</p>
        <p>Any foreign effort to acquire Sprint or WorldCom could meet political resistance in this country. But analysts predict that regulators would not block a deal soley on foreign-ownership grounds.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
