<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From the President's News Conference at the White House</title>
    <meta content="Y29CTE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211183"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEED81E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="4737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From the President's News Conference at the White House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Pres Clinton's news conference; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from President Clinton's news conference yesterday at the White House, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>Prepared Remarks</p>
        <p>With less than 35 days left in the legislative year, time is running out for Congress to meet its obligations to the American people. They have to make the tough choices to get something done or continue to be dragged down by the weight of special interests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from President Clinton's news conference yesterday at the White House, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>Prepared Remarks</p>
        <p>With less than 35 days left in the legislative year, time is running out for Congress to meet its obligations to the American people. They have to make the tough choices to get something done or continue to be dragged down by the weight of special interests.</p>
        <p>So, again, I ask Congress, Let's not waste these precious weeks. It's time to get down to business, to pass a strong patients' bill of rights, to raise the minimum wage by a dollar over two years, to pass the common-sense gun legislation, to hold tobacco companies not taxpayers accountable for the health care costs of tobacco, to pass hate-crimes legislation, to finish the jobs of giving American businesses and farmers access to a huge new market by passing permanent normal trade relations with China, to open new markets to American investors here at home, to bring prosperity to people and places who've been left behind, and, most important of all, to continue to improve our schools, to demand more of them and invest more in them, including more teachers for smaller class sizes, after-school programs for all our kids who need them, and repairing or modernizing thousands of our schools that are today literally falling apart or are so overcrowded they can't contain all the kids.</p>
        <p>We can still do a lot of this if we work together in the days ahead. That's what the American people want us to do even in an election year.</p>
        <p>There's been some encouraging developments in this Congress. We lifted the earnings limit on Social Security. We passed the Africa-Caribbean Basin trade bill. Apparently, the bill to aid Colombia is making good progress, and I think the China legislation will pass if we can get it up to a vote in a timely fashion. So the Congress can do a lot of things, and I hope they will, and I'm looking forward to working with them.</p>
        <p>Questions and Answers</p>
        <p>Q. There are reports that Israel and the Palestinians will be coming to Washington next week for talks. Do you think enough progress is being made to arrange a Middle East summit or are you discouraged? And,  secondly, should Israel stop the sale of radar systems to China?</p>
        <p>A. Let me answer the second question first because that's a much clearer one.</p>
        <p>We are very concerned about that sale, and I've talked to Prime Minister Barak about it extensively. And as you know there's a lot of concern in the Congress. So we're still working on that.</p>
        <p>Now in terms of their coming here for talks, there has been no date set. I do not believe that they can resolve the final most difficult issues without having the leaders get together in some isolated setting and make the last tough decisions. Or decide not to make them as the case may be.</p>
        <p>Of all the issues involved with regard to all the parties in the Middle East peace talks, the final status issues between the Israelis and the Palestinians are the most difficult. I do not, however, believe they are going to get any easier with the passage of time. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. Do you believe that Governor Bush made the wrong decision by allowing Mr. Graham to go to his death last week? And secondly, do you believe it's time for the American people to stop and reassess where we stand on implementation of death penalty in this country?</p>
        <p>A. Well on the Texas case, I didn't read the file. All I know about it is what I've read about it in the press. But let me say generally what I think that those of us who support the death penalty have an extra heavy responsibility to assure both that the result is accurate and that the process was fair and constitutional. And that means to me, at least in modern terms, the broadest possible use of DNA evidence and the strongest possible effort to guarantee adequate assistance of council. That's a big issue.</p>
        <p>And I think those were two of the reasons that motivated Governor Ryan in Illinois to do what he did. And it has driven a lot of other things in this debate.</p>
        <p>So that's where I think it is. Now, I don't know that the American people have changed their position that it's still an appropriate penalty under certain severe circumstances, and I haven't. But I am concerned also at the federal level with the -- I don't believe adequate assistance of council is an issue in the federal cases. And as far as I know, there are no cases in which the question of DNA is an issue. But there may be, I just, I don't know if there are some.</p>
        <p>The issues at the federal level relate more to the disturbing racial composition of those who've been convicted. And the apparent fact that almost all the convictions are coming out of just a handful of states. Which raises the question of whether, even though there's a uniform law across the country, what your prosecution is may determine, may turn solely on where you committed the crimes. So we, I've got a review underway of both those issues at this time.</p>
        <p>Gore Investigation</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. President, as you know, for the third time a Justice Department investigation has recommended that the vice president's activities in fund-raising during the last campaign cycle be looked into. Previously, on two occasions, the attorney general has declined to do this. Would it be better for the attorney general, for your administration and for the vice president's candidacy if he invited such an investigation?</p>
        <p>A. Well, first let me say, my understanding is -- I know this is true in the previous cases and I think it's true here, is that there are some people in the Justice Department that think there should be, and some who think there shouldn't be. And the attorney general, who has shown no reluctance to ask for a special council when she thought one was called for, didn't think one was called for in this case and she reaffirmed that yesterday. And I think the fact that the vice president released the transcript of his interview was a very good thing because some Republican senators had made some assertions about it that just weren't so, they weren't true. And now that the -- the whole thing has been put out in the public it seems to me that -- that the best thing to do is for the -- for the American people to make their own judgments about it, but I don't see any reason that the attorney general shouldn't make a decision in this case as she has in every other one. Claire?</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. President, another question about your vice president. A year ago, when people looked at his poll numbers compared to the Texas governor's, his supporters would say, 'Oh, the election's a long way off.' Six months ago, people were saying, the election's a long way off with those same poll numbers. And today his supporters are still saying that and I wonder do you think it's time to suggest that this might be a trend, that there is a reason why the vice president is trailing the Texas governor in the polls? And secondly, you have said that the vice president will not be held accountable, that the American people will not hold him accountable for the scandals of this administration. Do you still believe that's the case or is this in fact part of it?</p>
        <p>A. Well, first of all, I said, no, let me say exactly what I said. I said that the people would not hold him responsible for anything I did that they didn't agree with or that was wrong. And that's clearly true. That's still true. There's no evidence of that in the surveys.</p>
        <p>Secondly, let me remind you that a lot of these other so-called scandals were bogus. Mike Espy was acquitted; the Cisneros thing was a tempest in a teapot, totally overdone. And you all know that the Whitewater thing was bogus from day one; it had nothing to do with the official conduct of the administration anyway.</p>
        <p>Now, so the word scandal has been thrown around here like a clanging teapot for seven years and I keep waiting for somebody to say -- I know that there was one columnist in The Washington Post that had the -- the uncommon decency to say, will no one ever stand up here and say that a whole bunch of this stuff was just garbage and that we had totally innocent people prosecuted because they wouldn't lie. We had totally innocent people's lives wrecked because they wouldn't go along with this alleged scandal machine. So let's be careful, let's be specific.</p>
        <p>Now, I've already told you my view is that the vice president on the only thing as far as I know that he's been in any way implicated in is this campaign finance thing. He put out the whole transcript of his interview, made himself available for questions, and, I thought, made a very compelling case and certainly demonstrated that a lot of the accusations against him with regard to that are not so.</p>
        <p>There was also a very interesting article, I think in The National Law Journal, which basically went through all of the -- the things and concluded that there was no basis for a lot of these criticisms of him under these circumstances. And I think another magazine here, maybe The New Republic, The Washington Monthly, one of those other magazines, had an analysis of it. So I think we should be very careful in throwing that around.</p>
        <p>Now, let me come back to the polls. First of all, I must say, I -- I haven't looked at -- I haven't seen any or done any lately, so I don't know. But I'm -- I'm perplexed that -- I can't remember a time when we had two major polls coming out within a couple of days of each other that had 13 points difference. One said there was a 13-point difference in the race; the other one said it was tied, and they came out and they were done within two or three days of each other. I don't mean that -- I don't think either one of those pollsters rigged the results. So my instinct is that people are still trying to figure out what they think about this race. And all I can tell you is I know three things, and I've said this over and over again, I know three things: One is no person in the history of the republic has ever had the positive impact on this country as vice president that Al Gore has had. That is a historical fact. We've had a lot of presidents who were vice presidents who were great presidents: Jefferson, Teddy Roosevelt, Harry Truman were great presidents. But not because of their service as vice president. Nobody has ever done as much for America as vice president as Al Gore has. Therefore, in my lifetime, he's the best qualified person to serve.</p>
        <p>The second thing is I believe that he's right on the issues, on, I think, his economic policy is right. I think it's far more likely to keep the prosperity of the country going. I think it's far more likely to include people that would otherwise be left out.</p>
        <p>And the third thing is I think it's important that somebody be elected that understands the future. That -- we just announced this genome project yesterday. What are we going to do to make sure there's no genetic discrimination? A lot of people will want genetic discrimination in employment, in promotion, in extension of health insurance. What are we going to do to make sure it doesn't exist? What are we going to do to make sure in the computer revolution that there is no violation of people's privacy rights with their health and financial records? A lot of people will want to get that private health and financial information.</p>
        <p>So I think that what will happen is we'll come to the conventions, we'll have these debates and somehow -- what I've been amazed by, an amazing volatility since the end of the -- you know, at the end of the primary campaign most of the polls had him up a point or two. So there's been a lot of volatility in these polls and my best judgment is that people are still trying to figure out what they're going to do. And sooner or later they will. But I don't think they have. And I think they know those three things about Al Gore, and it's still more likely than not that he will win. . . .</p>
        <p>Abortion Rights</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. President, does the closeness of today's abortion vote in the Supreme Court suggest to you that abortion rights are at risk in the next court? Or does it suggest that the fact that partial-birth abortion can survive even a conservative court, say that they aren't as threatened as some believe?</p>
        <p>A. Well, first, I think the court decision is clearly the only decision it could reach consistent with Roe v. Wade. So I think what you know there is that -- that that's the vote for Roe v. Wade. You can't have -- you can't have a -- a rule like the rule of Roe and then ignore it. So that's why, you know, I -- if you remember on this late-term abortion issue a couple of years ago I pleaded with the Congress to adopt a broad limitation on late-term abortions consistent with Roe v. Wade, but to make an exception for the life and health of the mother, as the Supreme Court decision required. They declined to do that and so we've had a political impasse here. And then you've seen what's happened in all these states. So -- so the decision is -- is, I think, consistent with Roe v. Wade. And as you've pointed out, it was narrowly upheld. I think that's about what the vote for Roe is. And I think that in the next four years there'll be somewhere between two and four appointments to the Supreme Court and, depending on who those appointees are, I think the rule will either be maintained or  overturned, and I think that it's very much in the balance, depending on what appointments are made in the next four years. That's what I believe.</p>
        <p>Energy Policy</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. President, Governor Bush has been critical of you and the energy policy of the administration saying that you've failed to adequately convince OPEC to increase oil production. He also claims that if he became president he would able to use personal diplomacy to persuade allies like Kuwait and Saudi Arabia to, I believe he said, turn on the spigot. Do you find that kind of claim realistic? And do you have any reaction to his criticism of you?</p>
        <p>A. Well first of all, I have spent an enormous amount of time on this in the last several months. And there have been two decisions by OPEC to increase production. Not as much as we would like.</p>
        <p>If you look at the allocation of the production increases against the real capacity of those countries, most countries don't have the capacity to produce much more than their latest allocation except for the Saudis. And it's clear that they were trying to maintain some sort of harmony within the OPEC family.</p>
        <p>I don't, if you -- let's go back. I think that these big increases in gasoline prices in America are the result, as I said . . . several weeks ago, first and foremost of the unfortunate decision of OPEC several months ago to cut back production at the very time the world economy was growing. They left production out there when the world economy sunk, which is one reason we had very inexpensive gas prices for a good period of time. And this was, these two developments grated up against each other. So that's the first thing.</p>
        <p>Then the second thing is, we had here, as you know, in America . . . we had a tight supply situation. Then we had some broken pipelines and, which interrupted supplies, which caused a temporary spike. And then in the Midwest we did have apparently some, but I think quite a modest impact on prices because of the intersection of the clean air rules with trying to mix the fuels in a different way, particularly ethanol.</p>
        <p>And I think what we have to do now is to keep doing what we can to get production up; to let this F.D.C. investigation proceed. I think that gas prices have dropped 8 cents a gallon in the Midwest. And in the blended-fuels area, 12 1/2 cents a gallon just since the investigation was announced.</p>
        <p>But the main thing I would say to you is we need a long-term energy strategy to maximize conservation and maximize the development of alternative sources of energy. And also maximize domestic sources of energy. . . .</p>
        <p>Supreme Court Rulings</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. President, what do you think of the justices' ruling this morning that allows the Boy Scouts to bar gays as leaders? And if you disagree with it, can you justify your role as honorary president of the Boy Scouts, which discriminates against gays and atheists?</p>
        <p>A. Well, first of all, the court's ruling, I noticed it with interest. I haven't read it yet, but I did get a pretty good report on it. I noted with interest that they seemed to go out of their way to draw the ruling quite narrowly and to limit it strictly to the question of whether the Boy Scouts could pick the people who were going to be scout leaders.</p>
        <p>I generally, I have to tell you, you know, I'm generally against discrimination against gays. I think it's -- and I think that the country has moved a long way and I'm proud of things that we've been able to do and I'm disappointed we haven't been able to do more in some areas. But I think we're moving in the right direction. And I think that's all I should say. I mean, the Boy Scouts still are a -- they're a great group, they do a lot of good. And I would hope that, you know, this is just one step along the way of a movement toward greater inclusion for our society, because I think that's the direction we ought to be going in. . . .</p>
        <p>Q. As you know, the Supreme Court declined to intervene today either to stop Elian Gonzalez from leaving the country or to overrule other courts, all of which have deferred to your administration. As you look back on this --</p>
        <p>A. That's pretty rare, isn't it?</p>
        <p>On Elian Gonzalez</p>
        <p>Q. As you look back on this, sir, do you have any sense, any regrets at all about the way your administration handled this matter? And in light of what you've said about Cuba here today, sir, do you have any second thoughts about Elian returning to Cuba?</p>
        <p>A. Well, if -- if he and his father decided they wanted to stay here, it'd be fine with me. But I think that the most important thing is that his father was judged by people who made an honest effort to determine that he was a -- a good father, a loving father, committed to the son's welfare. And we upheld here what I think is a quite important principle, as well as what is clearly the law of the United States. Do I wish it had unfolded in a less dramatic, less traumatic way for all concerned? Of course I do. I have replayed this in my mind many times. I don't know that we had many different options than we pursued given how the thing developed. But I think the fundamental principle is the right one and I'm -- I'm glad we did.</p>
        <p>I -- I would, you know, I was just in Germany having a discussion with Chancellor Schroder about some family reunification issues where we have serious differences with the Germans who are great allies on this. And as I looked and reviewed some of these cases that I tried to bring to the attention of the German officials, it made me even more convinced that we had upheld the proper principle here. Yes, John.</p>
        <p>Missile Defense</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. President, we hear increasingly from senior officials here and at the Pentagon that when it comes to national missile defense you're inclined, essentially, to split the difference: authorize the contracting, but leave the decision about whether to break from the A.B.M. treaty to the next president. Is that a fair reflection of your thinking?</p>
        <p>A. The -- the most important thing I can say to you about that today is that I have not made a final decision. And that most of the speculation that is coming in the press is coming from people who have not talked to me about it. And let me -- let me try to at least set up the thing, because I'm working hard on it now. Remember when -- when we put out a -- when the Congress passed a law about this a couple years ago, you remember, and we had to sort of come up with some time tables. I said two things that I want to repeat today. First of all, in so far as there might be technology available which would protect us and other people around the world from missile attacks with warheads of weapons of mass destruction, obviously anybody would have a moral obligation to explore that technology and its potential. I believe that.</p>
        <p>Secondly, whether I would make a decision to go forward with deployment would depend upon four things: one, the nature of the threat; two, the feasibility of the technology; three, the cost and therefore the relative cost of doing this as compared with something else to protect the national security, and four, the overall impact on our national security, which includes our nuclear allies in our European alliance, our relationships with Russia, our relationships with China, what the boomerang effect might be about whatever China might do in South Asia with the Indians and the Pakistanis and then so on. So what I have tried to do since then is to say as little as possible except -- except to explore what would have to be done in our relationships with the Europeans, our allies, and with the Russians, in the first instance, to keep our options open. Could we -- could we get an agreed upon modification of the A.B.M. treaty?</p>
        <p>Even the Russians, keep in mind, don't -- don't minimize -- everybody talked about how we didn't reach an agreement, Mr. Putin and I when I was in Russia and that's absolutely true, we didn't. But we did get a document out of there which I think is quite important, because the Russians acknowledged that there are new and different security threats on the horizon. That is, that it's quite possible that in the next few years countries not part of the arms control regimes of the last three decades could develop both long-range missile delivery capability and weapons of mass destruction, which they could put on warheads. And that none of this would be covered by the, essentially the mutually -- the mutual deterrence structure of the A.B.M. treaty and all the things we've done since then. So they recognize, too, that -- that we in the new century, in the coming decades are going to have to make adjustments.</p>
        <p>Now, what they -- what they don't say is they don't want America unilaterally building a missile defense that they think some day can undermine their deterrent capacity. That's kind of where they are now and we're still talking about all that.</p>
        <p>But they -- the -- John, the truly accurate thing is that I have not yet formulated a position which I am prepared to go to the American people with, but I will do so, you know, sometime over the next several weeks based on those four criteria and what I think is -- is the right thing to do. . . .</p>
        <p>On Congress</p>
        <p>Q. Republicans in Congress are seeking to pass the spending bills early this year in an effort to get out of Washington and go campaigning in the fall. And yet there are significant differences between what they want to spend and what you have proposed. I'm wondering, what do you see as the major points of disagreement at this time? And do you think that we're in for the same type of prolonged budget stalemate that had been featured in the past?</p>
        <p>A. Well, that's entirely up to them whether we're in for the budget stalemate. But if you just look at the education budget. I mean, how many times do we have to go down this road? You know, it's still not supportive of the 100,000 teachers and the smaller classes. It's still not supportive of the dramatic expansion in after school programs, which is critical to school performance. Still has nothing in there for school construction. Still is inadequate in terms of my plan that people ought to either, they ought to identify these failing schools and either turn them around or shut them down. There are lots of other problems with the school proposal.</p>
        <p>If you look at the crime proposals. This is unbelievable. They had, when they wouldn't adopt the common sense gun safety legislation, all I heard was this constant barrage about how if only the administration would enforce on the books, everything would be wonderful. We wouldn't have any problems in America. So I said look, why don't we do both. We have increased gun prosecutions under my administration but we can do more. So please give me some more money for people to investigate gun crimes, for people to prosecute gun crimes, to develop safe gun technology. This whole -- it was nothing but a straight enforcement measure, exactly what they said they wanted, and no money for it.</p>
        <p>Still no support for the 50,000 new police officers in the high crime areas. And still the constant threat of these environmental riders and the underfunding of the land's legacy initiative and a number of other things.  So we still have some serious differences. Now, we've been doing this every year since 1995, we just of sort of slightly change the script every year. And I'm more than happy to do it again, because, frankly, in the end we normally wind up with an agreement that's pretty good for the American people.</p>
        <p>But the timing in which we do it, it depends more on them than me. I'm not going to give up my commitment to education as our most important domestic priority and what we're doing to build the future of our children. And I think, you know, we -- we've got the crime rate down now to a 25-year low. We can't stop the policies that's -- that works and I -- and I, here I gave them a big proposal that is exactly what they say they want and believe in, and they don't want to fund that. So we'll just have to see what happens.</p>
        <p>I'm kind of hopeful about it, though. Don't be too -- you know, it's just late June here. This -- this drama has several more acts before it's over.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
