<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Court Exits, in Controversy</title>
    <meta content="29THU1$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nebraska</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boy Scouts</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Anthony M (Assoc Justice)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Nebraska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DD1F30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Court Exits, in Controversy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial hails Supreme Court decision striking down Nebraska's ban on abortion procedure opponents call partial-birth abortion as reaffirmation of woman's right to choose safest abortion method; cites concern over Justice Anthony Kennedy's dissent; holds ruling vindicates Pres Clinton's repeated veto of Congressional attempts to impose national ban; holds court's decision upholding law that requires public school districts to share equipment in 'secular, neutral and nonideological' way with students enrolled in private schools does not show how court will vote on school vouchers; scores court's decision in favor of Boy Scout's right to exclude gay members</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court ended its 1999-2000 term yesterday with a burst of important rulings that could reverberate into the fall elections. The rulings involved a range of contentious social and political issues -- abortion rights, public aid to parochial schools and the civil rights of gay people.</p>
        <p>On a positive note, a sharply divided court reaffirmed a woman's right to choose the safest method of abortion throughout pregnancy by striking down Nebraska's ''partial-birth abortion'' law and, by extension, similar laws enacted by 30 other states. In contrast, the day's other 5-to-4 decision, holding that the Boy Scouts have a constitutional right to exclude gays, was a disappointing departure from a proud line of high court precedents erasing discrimination in public accommodations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court ended its 1999-2000 term yesterday with a burst of important rulings that could reverberate into the fall elections. The rulings involved a range of contentious social and political issues -- abortion rights, public aid to parochial schools and the civil rights of gay people.</p>
        <p>On a positive note, a sharply divided court reaffirmed a woman's right to choose the safest method of abortion throughout pregnancy by striking down Nebraska's ''partial-birth abortion'' law and, by extension, similar laws enacted by 30 other states. In contrast, the day's other 5-to-4 decision, holding that the Boy Scouts have a constitutional right to exclude gays, was a disappointing departure from a proud line of high court precedents erasing discrimination in public accommodations.</p>
        <p>The narrow margins in both cases serve as reminders that this remains a court in considerable ideological turmoil over fundamental questions of liberty. So, too, did the court's 6-to-3 ruling allowing the use of taxpayer money to buy computers and other instructional material for religious schools. Apart from the particulars of each case, the narrowness of the decisions also reminds us that the next president will have the power to change or reinforce the court's present disposition with only one or two changes. Here is a brief look at yesterday's major decisions.</p>
        <p>''Partial-Birth Abortion.'' The majority opinion written by Justice Stephen Breyer and joined by Justices Sandra Day O'Connor, David Souter, Ruth Bader Ginsburg and John Paul Stevens affirmed a lower court ruling overturning Nebraska's ban on the rarely used procedure known as ''partial-birth abortion.'' This is the phrase invented by pro-life groups to stigmatize all abortion procedures, not only in late term but those commonly used before fetal viability. These more common procedures have long been protected under Supreme Court precedents, which the new ruling strongly reaffirmed.</p>
        <p>Conspicuously missing from the majority was Justice Anthony Kennedy, who helped write the court's 1992 decision reaffirming the right to abortion. This switch does not bode well for future cases. However, the ruling vindicates President Clinton's repeated veto of Congressional attempts to impose a similar national ban. It also undercuts the strategy of politicians to claim to be pro-choice even as they support the ''partial birth'' bans the court has now ruled to be unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>Religious School Aid. In a 6-to-3 decision, the court upheld a law that requires public school districts to share equipment in a ''secular, neutral and nonideological'' way with students enrolled in private schools. This is a relatively inoffensive result that does not tell us how the court will vote on far more politically charged cases involving tuition vouchers that are percolating up the legal system. Four justices in the majority -- Chief Justice William Rehnquist, Antonin Scalia, Clarence Thomas and Anthony Kennedy -- made plain their approval of broad taxpayer support of religious schools. But the two justices who voted with them, Justices O'Connor and Breyer, filed a separate opinion strongly objecting to such wholesale breaching of the wall between church and state.</p>
        <p>Gay Scouts. The court reached one of its lowest moments of the term when it ruled in favor of the  Boy Scouts' right to exclude gay members. The four dissenters -- Justices Stevens, Ginsburg, Breyer and Souter -- did not challenge the principle that an organization cannot be forced to adopt an unwanted message. But the dissenters correctly noted that the Boy Scouts had failed to show that admitting gays was fundamentally incompatible with the organization's core mission, the test the court has traditionally applied to groups trying to escape an anti-discrimination law.</p>
        <p>James Dale, the excluded Eagle Scout, deserved better. So did the rest of the nation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
