<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Family Recipes Of a Big Family</title>
    <meta content="29BOOK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MAKING BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Plagiarism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Martin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheraton, Mimi</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">David Ruggiero's Italian Kitchen (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Making Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plagiarism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEFDF1E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Family Recipes Of a Big Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martin Arnold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin Arnold's Making Books column on recipe plagiarism within cookbook industry; examines charges leveled by cookbook author Mimi Sheraton against David Ruggiero, former chef and author of David Ruggiero's Italian Kitchen: Family Recipes From the Old Country (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's time honored among amateur cooks that if a friend is excellently skilled in the creation of a peach cobbler, for instance, to say between swallows, ''Oh, I love that; can I have the recipe?'' At such moments of conviviality, it is proudly given and gratefully received.</p>
        <p>But, ah, things are very different indeed in the fraternity of professional chefs and cookbook authors, where jealousies and passions are as plentiful as stuffed artichokes, and charges of plagiarism of recipes at times seem almost pandemic. Of course, the better practitioners of the art of borrowing are generally smart enough at least to alter the amounts of the ingredients: i.e., make it 6 ounces of shredded caciocavallo cheese rather than 3 1/2 and change the wording of the instructions. Still, an astute food person knows who created which recipe, absolutely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's time honored among amateur cooks that if a friend is excellently skilled in the creation of a peach cobbler, for instance, to say between swallows, ''Oh, I love that; can I have the recipe?'' At such moments of conviviality, it is proudly given and gratefully received.</p>
        <p>But, ah, things are very different indeed in the fraternity of professional chefs and cookbook authors, where jealousies and passions are as plentiful as stuffed artichokes, and charges of plagiarism of recipes at times seem almost pandemic. Of course, the better practitioners of the art of borrowing are generally smart enough at least to alter the amounts of the ingredients: i.e., make it 6 ounces of shredded caciocavallo cheese rather than 3 1/2 and change the wording of the instructions. Still, an astute food person knows who created which recipe, absolutely.</p>
        <p>This season's accusation of recipe plundering was made by Mimi Sheraton, a prolific author of food books, against David Ruggerio, once chef at La Caravelle and Le Chantilly, past celebrity television cook and currently author of ''David Ruggerio's Italian Kitchen: Family Recipes From the Old Country'' (Artisan).</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruggerio's recipe for roasted shoulder of veal with herbs set off Ms. Sheraton's memory buds, she said, having remembered making the same dish herself ''exactly as he described it'' from ''Marcella's Italian Kitchen'' (Knopf, 1986) by Marcella Hazan.</p>
        <p>So after some research Ms. Sheraton. who used to be a restaurant critic of The New York Times, accused Mr. Ruggerio of using 10 recipes from four cookbooks ''that appear in almost identical form in Ruggerio's new book.'' They ranged from luganega sausage with black-eyed peas and tomatoes to charcoal grilled deviled chicken, although she said that Mr. Ruggerio added garlic to the chicken dish, ''perhaps indicating a burst of creativity.''</p>
        <p>Her allegations appeared in an article on the Web site of Brill's Content (www.brillscontent.com), to be updated and reprinted in the magazine in September. Mr. Ruggerio, who declined to speak to me for this column, told Ms. Sheraton that the 150 recipes in his book came from himself, his family and friends. She said he explained the 10 recipe look-alikes to her this way: ''They are very simple standards with just a few ingredients, and they are always made the same way.''</p>
        <p>Great chefs and cookbook authors have a protocol, an honor system, about using recipes not their own. The author either directly attributes the recipe to another chef or in an equally acceptable but more informal way introduces it something like this: I had dinner recently at X's house (or restaurant) and asked her for the fine version of the stuffed meat roll she served.</p>
        <p>The line between originality and pastiche is fine indeed in cookbooks, and what constitutes plagiarism is harder to define than in a poetry book. Judith Jones, a legendary Knopf editor who has edited many cookbooks, said: ''You cannot actually plagiarize ingredients. Old-fashioned baking-powder biscuits: how many ways can you change it? If you try too hard you'll ruin it. It's usually in the explaining, the writing of the instructions.'' It's also in the philosophical approach.</p>
        <p>She added: ''It's hard to plagiarize classic dishes, but its another thing for the unusual recipes, the greatest dish of tripe. You look at that recipe side by side with another: the same ingredients, the same technique. It's not fair play, but it happens a lot, and every 10 years or so there's a scandal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruggerio's recipe for ''Baked Shrimp, Potatoes and Tomatoes'' was almost identical to the recipe created by Giuliano Bugialli for his book, ''Foods of Sicily and Sardinia and the Smaller Islands'' (Rizzoli, 1996), according to both Ms. Sheraton and Mr. Bugialli.</p>
        <p>''To add insult to injury, he took another of my recipes from a different book, a Sicilian recipe, and made it a Tuscan recipe without changing it,'' Mr. Bugialli said. Which gives you a flavor of the seriousness and territorial imperatives in the writing of the books. Still, Mr. Bugialli said, even this indignity was topped when he went into a bookstore recently and found his latest book, ''On Pasta'' (Stewart, Tabori &amp; Chang), on the shelf right next to Mr. Ruggerio's.</p>
        <p>The publisher of Mr. Ruggerio's book, Ann Bramson, said on Tuesday: ''I can say I am very uncomfortable with the similarity. I've been obsessing about it and discussing it.'' She said that she didn't intend to pull it from distribution. ''But I'm looking into reprinting,'' she said. ''Coming from a personal and moral point of view, if I had known, I would have not gone to press with these recipes in the book.'' So far, 25,000 copies are in print.</p>
        <p>Probably the most notable recent cookbook scandal occurred in 1984, when Richard Nelson was accused of stealing recipes from Richard Olney's ''Simple French Food'' (Atheneum, 1974) for his book ''Richard Nelson's American Cooking'' (New American Library). Mr. Nelson had been president of the International Association of Culinary Professionals. He and his publisher settled out of court, but it was as if a bank president had been charged with bouncing checks.</p>
        <p>Bill Malloy, senior editor at Warner Books, is trying to take the company into cookbooks in a substantial way next year, Is he worried about plagiarism? Not really. He said: ''There are only so many ways to roast a piece of veal shoulder. If you picked up 10 cookbooks, you would find a lot of the procedure and the ingredients are the same. Like any writer, the cookbook writer should develop a personal style. So the plagiarism usually comes down to the language.</p>
        <p>''The right way to use another person's recipe is to say 'I've been influenced by my colleague Julia Child,' or 'I had this marvelous meal at a farmhouse in Tuscany.' People who cook and eat and taste for a living are like a business writer or a golf writer -- they know what's going on and will catch you.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Ms. Child said that stealing recipes ''is so stupid a thing to do that I can only wonder if someone else didn't put the book together for him, and he didn't read over.'' She continued: ''That's happened before. It's so stupid I can't think of any other explanation.''</p>
        <p>She has just finished her 11th cookbook. ''I wouldn't pay too much attention if someone stole a recipe of mine. I guess it would be a compliment.'' Only an author of who is to cookbooks what, say, Katharine Hepburn is to the movies would be that confident. She knows everybody would know a Julia Child recipe.</p>
        <p>MAKING BOOKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
