<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Federal Reserve Calls a Time Out on Raising Interest Rates</title>
    <meta content="Y29FED$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211199"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Durable Goods (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Durable Goods (Economic Indicator)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1D61E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Federal Reserve Calls a Time Out on Raising Interest Rates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Reserve votes to leave interest rates unchanged, giving itself more time to determine whether series of rate increases it has imposed are slowing economy sufficiently to avoid upturn in inflation; federal funds rate remains at 6.5 percent; central bank warns it could start raising rates again as soon as its next meeting, on Aug 22; Commerce Department says orders for durable goods in May rose 6 percent, to $218.89 billion, more than reversing 5.7 percent decline in April; graph on durable goods orders; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Reserve voted today to leave interest rates unchanged, giving itself more time to determine whether the series of rate increases it has imposed the last year are slowing the economy sufficiently to avoid an upturn in inflation.</p>
        <p>But the central bank warned that it could start raising rates again as soon as its next meeting, on Aug. 22. Analysts said the Fed would probably tighten policy in August unless economic indicators in coming weeks provided assurance that the red-hot pace of economic growth earlier this year had given way to a more sustainable path that reduces the threat of an inflationary spiral in wages and prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Reserve voted today to leave interest rates unchanged, giving itself more time to determine whether the series of rate increases it has imposed the last year are slowing the economy sufficiently to avoid an upturn in inflation.</p>
        <p>But the central bank warned that it could start raising rates again as soon as its next meeting, on Aug. 22. Analysts said the Fed would probably tighten policy in August unless economic indicators in coming weeks provided assurance that the red-hot pace of economic growth earlier this year had given way to a more sustainable path that reduces the threat of an inflationary spiral in wages and prices.</p>
        <p>The Federal Reserve's decision had been widely expected by economists and investors, and Wall Street took the news largely in stride. The Dow Jones industrial average climbed more than 100 points but fell back after the Fed announcement to close at 10,527.79, up 23.33, for the day. The Nasdaq composite index rose 81.38, to 3,940.34.</p>
        <p>In calling a time out today in its campaign of rate increases -- six over the last year, pushing its benchmark federal funds target rate up 1.75 percentage points, to 6.5 percent -- the Fed acknowledged that there had been some evidence that the economy was cooling off. And the central bank noted that while inflation by some measures had been accelerating, price pressures were being held down by continuing improvements in productivity, a measure of the economy's ability to produce more for less.</p>
        <p>But the central bank's policy-making Federal Open Market Committee suggested that it remained unconvinced that the economic slowdown was real. And it stressed its continuing concern that the current low rate of unemployment -- 4.1 percent in May -- could lead wages to rise so fast that companies would be forced to raise their prices.</p>
        <p>Signs of moderating growth ''are still tentative and preliminary, and the utilization of the pool of available workers remains at an unusually high level,'' the committee said in a statement released at the conclusion of a two-day meeting.</p>
        <p>Under those circumstances, the statement said, ''the committee believes the risks continue to be weighted mainly toward conditions that may generate heightened inflation pressures in the foreseeable future.''</p>
        <p>Analysts said the wording of the statement was intended in part to keep investors off balance and keep stock prices from surging on the assumption that the Fed was finished or nearly finished raising rates.</p>
        <p>Economists said there was a good chance that the Fed would push rates up another quarter percentage point in August, but that the decision would be driven by the economic statistics that come out between now and then.</p>
        <p>''We're back on data watch,'' said Ian Morris, an economist at HSBC Securities.</p>
        <p>Economists pointed to today's report on orders for durable goods as evidence that some of the weakness exhibited by the economy the last few months might have been temporary. Orders for durable goods in May rose 6 percent, to $218.89 billion,  more than reversing a 5.7 percent decline in April, the Commerce Department reported. Analysts had expected an increase of less than 3 percent.</p>
        <p>''The big increase in durable goods today is telling you that this slowdown is going to be just moderate, that we're not going to have an extremely sharp slowdown,'' said Maury N. Harris, an economist at PaineWebber.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harris said other important indicators in coming weeks could follow a similar pattern, with chances good that both job creation and average hourly earnings would rebound in June after being depressed in May.</p>
        <p>He said he expected the Fed to raise its federal funds target rate on overnight loans between banks a quarter percentage point, to 6.75 percent, in August, and then to push the rate up again to 7 percent by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Robert V. DiClemente, an economist at Salomon Smith Barney, also said he expected the federal funds rate to rise to around 7 percent this year.</p>
        <p>''We think that current financial conditions are not going to prove sufficiently restrictive to keep demand moving back into line,'' Mr. DiClemente said in a report today.</p>
        <p>In explaining its decision to leave rates unchanged, the Fed suggested that it remained ambivalent -- or perhaps divided -- over the potential for inflation to take root.</p>
        <p>The committee's statement gave equal emphasis to two competing ways of assessing the outlook. One view, often emphasized by Alan Greenspan, the Fed chairman, is built on the idea that an acceleration in productivity growth is likely to continue, holding down costs and tempering any inflation pressures that might result from rising wages.</p>
        <p>In this view, the goal of monetary policy is to bring economic growth down to ''a pace closer to the rate of growth of the economy's potential to produce,'' as today's statement put it.</p>
        <p>The economy grew at a 5.4 percent annual rate in the first quarter, and most Fed officials put the noninflationary growth rate at 3.5 percent to 4 percent a year.</p>
        <p>But in expressing concern that the low unemployment rate could ignite inflation, the statement recognized a position advocated by a number of other Fed officials, including Laurence H. Meyer, a Fed governor. Mr. Meyer believes that with unemployment around 4 percent, even 3.5 percent annual growth might be enough to generate inflation pressures.</p>
        <p>He has raised the possibility that the Fed might need to push growth below 3.5 or 4 percent for some period and allow the unemployment rate to rise to 5 percent or higher to squeeze inflation pressures out of the economy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan works to bring consensus to policy making within the Fed, and the lines between the two camps are not firmly drawn. But even if the Fed agrees that tighter monetary policy is beginning to bite, it could still face a debate over how much further it needs to go in slowing the economy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
