<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Rowland's Urging, Emissions Testing Company Is Adding Safeguards</title>
    <meta content="29CONN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Envirotest Systems Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowland, John G (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DF1F30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Rowland's Urging, Emissions Testing Company Is Adding Safeguards</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Gov John Rowland says that Envirotest Systems Corp, company that operates Connecticut's auto emissions testing stations, will spend $1 million to prevent fraud, bribery and theft that have plagued sites (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Plagued by fraud, bribery and theft at Connecticut's auto emissions testing stations, the company that operates the sites will spend $1 million to prevent further abuses, Gov. John G. Rowland announced today.</p>
        <p>The governor outlined a number of changes the company, Envirotest Systems Corporation, will make at his request, saying its problems were chronic rather than piecemeal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Plagued by fraud, bribery and theft at Connecticut's auto emissions testing stations, the company that operates the sites will spend $1 million to prevent further abuses, Gov. John G. Rowland announced today.</p>
        <p>The governor outlined a number of changes the company, Envirotest Systems Corporation, will make at his request, saying its problems were chronic rather than piecemeal.</p>
        <p>A few hours later, State Senator Biagio Ciotto, the Democratic co-chairman of the Legislature's transportation committee, announced that it would hold a hearing July 12 on the effectiveness of the emissions testing program. Like a similar program in New Jersey, Connecticut's emissions testing system has proven a political embarrassment -- in this case, for the administration of Mr. Rowland, a Republican.</p>
        <p>But Senator Ciotto said the hearing -- which would include sworn testimony from officials of Envirotest, the state and the federal Environmental Protection Agency -- would not be a ''witch hunt.''</p>
        <p>''The hearing is not about finding someone to blame,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Since 1996, many car owners have complained that testing inspectors offered to overlook car defects for an extra fee and then pocketed the money.</p>
        <p>According to an analysis of state records by The Hartford Courant, more than 1,000 vehicles passed emissions tests under questionable circumstances between January 1998 and May 2000.</p>
        <p>In addition more than 770 inspection stickers have been reported stolen from testing stations in the state.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, four former Envirotest inspectors pleaded guilty to second-degree forgery. A fifth inspector was arrested on similar charges, and his case is pending.</p>
        <p>''The recurring nature of these problems is an indication to me that the company is not doing all that it can do to resolve the problems and to rectify them,'' Governor Rowland said.</p>
        <p>Under the plan the governor outlined, Envirotest is to hire 16 emissions inspectors, almost doubling the number it has posted at some of the 25 stations around the state. The company also agreed to provide up to $250,000 for the state to hire a private contractor to investigate testing centers.</p>
        <p>And Envirotest plans to install video-monitoring equipment in inspection lanes and to hire an inspector to review videotapes of questionable cases.</p>
        <p>Another part of the plan focuses on the vehicle inspectors. The four who pleaded guilty had secured passing grades for defective cars by performing two tests on cars that passed; the second report was then issued for a car that had failed, in return for a cash payment.</p>
        <p>Envirotest will now require supervisors to approve the reinspection of cars that are tested more than once on a single business day.</p>
        <p>Martha Sanders, a spokeswoman for Envirotest, which since 1994 has run emissions inspections under a 10-year, $25 million state contract, said the company was eager to ensure the effectiveness of the program.</p>
        <p>''We certainly look forward to working with the governor on this plan,'' she said. ''We take these matters very seriously.''</p>
        <p>The governor's announcement is the latest of several steps taken to make Envirotest fraud investigations more comprehensive. Previously, complaints were handled on a case-by-case basis.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, at Governor Rowland's urging, the state hired an outside auditor to review the performance of both Envirotest and the Department of Motor Vehicles.</p>
        <p>''We're taking a different approach now because of the chronic nature of these issues,'' said Governor Rowland's spokesman, Dean Pagani.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
