<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Broken Legs Cross Paths On Nets' Day</title>
    <meta content="29ARAT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Nets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Araton, Harvey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Jayson</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EEDD1F30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Broken Legs Cross Paths On Nets' Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Araton, Harvey</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Harvey Araton Sports of The Times column discusses career of New Jersey Nets forward Jayson Williams on occasion of his retirement; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE shattered leg never healed the way it had to, but you got the impression yesterday that Jayson Williams was suffering more from a broken heart. When the Nets announced his retirement via conference call, the man who talked nonstop and without peer for much of the previous decade was not on the line, or even in state.</p>
        <p>''Jayson's in Arizona,'' said Rod Thorn, the Nets' new president, who didn't add that Williams was said to be shopping for a winter home in Phoenix. Strange, but true: 10 years ago, Williams was drafted by the Suns, a New York kid who didn't hide his displeasure and later lobbied his way east.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE shattered leg never healed the way it had to, but you got the impression yesterday that Jayson Williams was suffering more from a broken heart. When the Nets announced his retirement via conference call, the man who talked nonstop and without peer for much of the previous decade was not on the line, or even in state.</p>
        <p>''Jayson's in Arizona,'' said Rod Thorn, the Nets' new president, who didn't add that Williams was said to be shopping for a winter home in Phoenix. Strange, but true: 10 years ago, Williams was drafted by the Suns, a New York kid who didn't hide his displeasure and later lobbied his way east.</p>
        <p>Most retirees tend to participate in their own valediction, but the Nets were never good with secrets, the word was already out and the team apparently had to clear one broken right leg from the roster to make room for another.</p>
        <p>''There needs to be a closure about it,'' Thorn said, before opening up last night's draft by selecting Williams's frontcourt replacement in recuperation, the University of Cincinnati's Kenyon Martin.</p>
        <p>It was, even after taking the source into account, a strange sequence of events, making official such sobering news hours before the Nets would invite season ticket-holders into the Meadowlands Champions Center to share in their good lottery fortune.</p>
        <p>Good, not great. As it was the last time the Nets landed the first pick in the National Basketball Association draft, there was no player to name this lottery after. Eerily enough, it was also a decade ago when David Stern stood up at the Jacob Javits Center to announce, ''With the first pick of the 1990 draft, the New Jersey Nets select Derrick Coleman.''</p>
        <p>The 10-year retrospective on that pick is a rousing whoop-de-damn-do. Coleman came with character questions that were answered soon enough. Besides Martin's broken leg -- which the team doctors have examined and are swearing on a stack of old Nets' yearbooks will not be a problem -- there is the issue of his tepid performance before his senior season, in which he averaged 18.9 points and almost 10 rebounds. As late as Martin's junior year, the numbers were 10 and 7. ''You're talking about a young man who got better every year,'' Thorn said, providing -- what else? -- the sanguine spin.</p>
        <p>There are scouts who claim that with the exception of the truly gifted, the Tim Duncans, rating an experienced college big man has become a most daunting task. ''By the time he's a senior, the question is, 'Who is he playing against?' '' one scout said yesterday. ''Most of the really good players have already gone. A kid like Martin is 22 years old playing against guys who are either much less talented or 18-year-olds whose bodies are not as developed. How does he do when everyone is at least as talented and big?''</p>
        <p>We'll see, but it's a shame the Nets had the vacancy in the first place. Williams, a power forward, was the team's center-by-default until he was injured during the 1998-99 season. The mishap was a classic Nets' disaster, Williams entangled with the newly acquired Stephon Marbury, the lockout-shortened season already lost. While everyone including his mother tended to the point guard, Williams rolled over in agony, comforted by the front-row ticket-holder Danny Aiello.</p>
        <p>Some people thought Jayson Williams was more actor than player. It would be hard to dispute that it was more fun to listen to him than to watch the Nets' teams he anchored. Yet it is equally important to remember that the Nets acquired Williams for two second-round draft picks, as a replacement for the immortal Terry Mills. He was more than a late-blooming rebounding force. He became that rare contemporary athlete who wanted to tell everyone how fortunate he was.</p>
        <p>A couple of years ago, a Nets' official related a story by telephone about how a young boy with cancer had visited the locker room, right after a chemotherapy treatment. While meeting some of the players, he turned nauseous and, in trying to keep from vomiting, began to choke. While the other players backed away, Williams realized what was happening, swept the boy into his arms and nearly knocked John Calipari down on his way to the trainer's room.</p>
        <p>The line went quiet, and, after a few seconds, I realized the official was quietly weeping.</p>
        <p>Williams had that effect on people. He could make you laugh or cry. He was no heralded star but he was a steal. With the first pick in the entire draft, you hope for something more than a rebounder with heart, but if Kenyon Martin ever fills Jayson Williams's shoes, the Nets should be thrilled.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
