<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Investigation Leads Official To Step Down In California</title>
    <meta content="Y29CAL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quackenbush, Chuck (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D91E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Investigation Leads Official To Step Down In California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chuck Quackenbush, California state insurance commissioner under investigation for allegeldy diverting millions of dollars in earthquake settlements into personal political slush fund, resigns rather than face impeachment by Legislature; charges against him discussed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Quackenbush, the California state insurance commissioner who has been under investigation on accusations of diverting millions of dollars in earthquake insurance settlements into what amounted to a personal political slush fund, resigned today rather than face potential impeachment by the State Legislature.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quackenbush, one of only two Republican statewide officeholders, decided to quit after what politicians said were at least two days of negotiations with the Legislature aimed at limiting his potential civil and criminal liability. Mr. Quackenbush's lawyer said he had made no deal with legislative leaders, but they canceled a hearing scheduled for Thursday at which Mr. Quackenbush, under subpoena, would have faced extensive on-the-record questions about his dealings for the first time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chuck Quackenbush, the California state insurance commissioner who has been under investigation on accusations of diverting millions of dollars in earthquake insurance settlements into what amounted to a personal political slush fund, resigned today rather than face potential impeachment by the State Legislature.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quackenbush, one of only two Republican statewide officeholders, decided to quit after what politicians said were at least two days of negotiations with the Legislature aimed at limiting his potential civil and criminal liability. Mr. Quackenbush's lawyer said he had made no deal with legislative leaders, but they canceled a hearing scheduled for Thursday at which Mr. Quackenbush, under subpoena, would have faced extensive on-the-record questions about his dealings for the first time.</p>
        <p>Gov. Gray Davis, a Democrat, will appoint a successor to serve until the next scheduled statewide election in 2002, subject to confirmation by the Legislature, and Mr. Davis vowed today to choose someone of ''unquestioned integrity.'' Mr. Quackenbush, 46, offered his resignation, effective July 10, in a one-sentence letter to the only other Republican constitutional officer, Secretary of State Bill Jones.</p>
        <p>''It reached the point with all of the controversy that he could no longer serve effectively as insurance commissioner, and so in the interests of the people of California, he stepped down,'' said Mr. Quackenbush's lawyer, Donald H. Heller. ''I think it needs to be very clear that he has done nothing illegal or criminal.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Quackenbush's resignation followed three months of deepening scandal in Sacramento over accusations of misusing funds from nonprofit foundations for personal political purposes. The largest fund, the California Research and Assistance Fund, was financed by a half-dozen insurance companies accused of mishandling claims after the devastating 1994 Northridge earthquake. The insurance department had threatened the companies with nearly $4 billion in potential penalties, but Mr. Quackenbush agreed to let them settle the matter by donating some $12 million in tax-deductible contributions to the new fund.</p>
        <p>The fund was supposed to finance consumer assistance programs and earthquake research, but investigators found that money went instead for television commercials featuring Mr. Quackenbush and to other groups he favored, including $263,000 to a football camp attended by his children. While denying any wrongdoing, Mr. Quackenbush has said that he may have made mistakes in judgment, and, as Mr. Heller phrased it, ''put his trust in people who let him down.''</p>
        <p>But Republican legislative leaders had warned that if Mr. Quackenbush refused to testify, or if he testified and could not refute the accusations against him, there would be a bipartisan impeachment inquiry. It was that collapse of political support that forced his hand today.</p>
        <p>Besides the Legislature, the state attorney general's office and the Fair Political Practices Commission, which oversees campaign finance, have been investigating Mr. Quackenbush, the fund and its contributors.</p>
        <p>State Attorney General Bill Lockyer said today that his office had made no deal with Mr. Quackenbush, ''and none is contemplated.'' Mr. Lockyer added: ''If crimes have been committed by anyone associated with these actions, my office will take action to see that they are prosecuted. We will seek civil penalties and restitution where appropriate.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Quackenbush, a former state assemblyman, was elected to the insurance post in 1994, with strong support in campaign contributions from the industry he regulates. He replaced a Democrat, John Garamendi, whom the industry had regarded antagonistically. At one point, insurance agents who made campaign phone calls to voters on Mr. Quackenbush's behalf misrepresented themselves as police officers, and he was forced to apologize. In 1996, a state audit found that he had not reported $327,000 in 1994 contributions, much of it from the industry.</p>
        <p>Steven Goldstein, a spokesman for the Insurance Information Institute, an industry group, said 99 percent of claims from the Northridge earthquake had been settled.</p>
        <p>''I think there's an erroneous impression that many claims are not settled and that insurers were complicit in whatever the commissioner did,'' Mr. Goldstein said. ''And that's simply not true.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
