<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justices Approve U.S. Financing of Religious Schools' Equipment</title>
    <meta content="Y29SCH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211195"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE SUPREME COURT: THE LOUISIANA CASE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vouchers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Private and Sectarian Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EED71E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1173" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justices Approve U.S. Financing of Religious Schools' Equipment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court, 6-3, overturns two of its own precedents that had limited public aid to religious schools and rules federal program that places computers and other 'instructional equipment' in parochial school classrooms does not violate separation between church and state; decision seems likely to spur drive to legalize use of vouchers for religious-school tuition; Clinton administration supported program court upheld and appealed appeals court ruling against it; photo; diagram of how justices ruled in this and other cases (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Overturning two of its own precedents that had limited public aid to religious schools, the Supreme Court ruled today that a federal program that placed computers and other ''instructional equipment'' in parochial school classrooms did not violate the constitutional separation between church and state.</p>
        <p>The 6-to-3 decision was not supported by a single majority opinion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Overturning two of its own precedents that had limited public aid to religious schools, the Supreme Court ruled today that a federal program that placed computers and other ''instructional equipment'' in parochial school classrooms did not violate the constitutional separation between church and state.</p>
        <p>The 6-to-3 decision was not supported by a single majority opinion.</p>
        <p>A far-reaching opinion by Justice Clarence Thomas that would have made ''the principles of neutrality and private choice'' the only touchstones for channeling aid to religious schools was supported by three other justices.</p>
        <p>But Justice Thomas's opinion was qualified by Justice Sandra Day O'Connor's insistence in a concurring opinion that public aid may supplement, but must not supplant, money that a religious school could otherwise spend on its own programs.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the decision appeared likely to provide momentum for the drive to legalize the use of vouchers for religious-school tuition and provide ammunition for the legal argument that as long as aid was distributed evenhandedly, it could not be said to be impermissibly favoring religious recipients.</p>
        <p>''We see six potential votes for school choice,'' Clint Bolick, litigation director of the Institute for Justice, a leading advocacy group on the issue, said today. His count included Justice Stephen G. Breyer, who voted with Justice O'Connor, as well as the three who voted with Justice Thomas: Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and Justices Antonin Scalia and Anthony M. Kennedy.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, although the voucher debate was obviously in the justices' minds, that outcome remained in the realm of potential, given Justice O'Connor's observation that in the case before the court today, no government funds ''ever reach the coffers of a religious school.''</p>
        <p>The Rev. Barry Lynn, director of Americans United for the Separation of Church and State, said in an interview that ''in the case of vouchers, the money goes directly to the school's coffers'' even though it first passed through the hands of parents. ''The parents can do nothing with the voucher except spend it for tuition,'' Mr. Lynn said.</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration supported the program that was upheld today and appealed a decision from a federal appeals court in New Orleans that declared it unconstitutional. Dating to 1965, the law, now known generally as Chapter 2, has evolved from providing video filmstrips and similar material to a vehicle for accomplishing the administration's goal of wiring every classroom in the country for Internet access.</p>
        <p>Under the program, federal money flows through public school districts, which are obligated to buy the equipment and distribute it, technically as loans, to all schools within the district's geographic boundaries -- public, private and parochial -- based on their enrollment. Three taxpayers in Jefferson Parish, La., brought suit in 1985 to challenge the program's application to religious schools in the district on the ground that there was no way of preventing the schools from using the equipment in support of their religious mission.</p>
        <p>The case had a tangled history, leading eventually to a 1998 ruling by the United States Court of Appeals for the Fifth Circuit, in New Orleans, that the program was unconstitutional under two Supreme Court precedents from the mid-1970's. Those decisions, Meek v. Pittenger and Wolman v. Walter, held that the government could provide textbooks but not other instructional materials to religious schools, the premise being that textbooks could be vetted in advance to make sure they did not advance the schools' religious mission.</p>
        <p>The six justices who voted in the majority today to overturn the Fifth Circuit's decision all agreed that the earlier decisions should be overruled. Justice Thomas said the decisions were ''irreconcilable'' with other decisions in this area that came both before and after them, most recently the court's ruling three years ago in Agostini v. Felton. In that decision -- which also overturned a precedent -- the court held that it did not violate the Constitution for public schools to send teachers into parochial schools, under a federal program, to provide remedial classes.</p>
        <p>As these decisions indicate, the court's jurisprudence on the subject of permissible public aid to religious schools has been in turmoil for years. The case today, Mitchell v. Helms, No. 98-1648, was the oldest on the court's docket, having been argued on Dec. 1, and the justices' failure to settle on a single majority opinion after seven months showed that the turmoil was likely to continue.</p>
        <p>Reflecting on historical anti-Catholic sentiment in the late 1800's, Justice Thomas said that ''hostility to aid to pervasively sectarian schools has a shameful pedigree that we do not hesitate to disavow.'' He said that ''nothing in the Establishment Clause requires the exclusion of pervasively sectarian schools from otherwise permissible aid programs,'' and that the cases that supported such exclusion, ''born of bigotry, should be buried now.''</p>
        <p>He said that government programs should be upheld on ''the principles of neutrality and private choice,'' meaning that if the government ''offers aid on the same terms, without regard to religion,'' no impermissible religious purpose could be attributed to the government. That was especially true, he said, when individuals could make their own private choices on how to use the aid.</p>
        <p>It was at this point that Justice O'Connor and Justice Breyer expressed their unease with what Justice O'Connor called the ''logic'' of Justice Thomas's opinion.</p>
        <p>''The plurality opinion foreshadows the approval of direct monetary subsidies to religious organizations, even when they use the money to advance their religious objectives,'' Justice O'Connor said.</p>
        <p>In his dissenting opinion, Justice David H. Souter, joined by Justices John Paul Stevens and Ruth Bader Ginsburg, said Justice Thomas's opinion represented a fundamental break with the court's precedents. Justice Souter said Justice Thomas's opinion threatened the court's long-held distinction ''between indirect aid that reaches religious schools only incidentally as a result of numerous individual choices and aid that is in reality directed to religious schools by the government or in practical terms selected by religious schools themselves.''</p>
        <p>Justice O'Connor, in her concurring opinion, explained her reasons for agreeing that the court should overturn the precedents that limited aid to providing textbooks.</p>
        <p>''Technology's advance,'' she said, has made the distinction between textbooks and other materials ''more suspect'' than ever. ''Computers are now as necessary as were schoolbooks 30 years ago, and they play a somewhat similar role in the educational process,'' she said.</p>
        <p>THE SUPREME COURT: THE LOUISIANA CASE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
