<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exploring a Dark Side of Depression Remedies</title>
    <meta content="29MASL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glenmullen, Joseph (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Prozac Backlash (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7DF1E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1125" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exploring a Dark Side of Depression Remedies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews Dr Joseph Glenmullen book, Prozac Backlash: Overcoming the Dangers of Prozac, Zoloft, Paxil and Other Antidepressants With Safe, Effective Alternatives; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PROZAC BACKLASH  Overcoming the Dangers of Prozac, Zoloft, Paxil and Other Antidepressants With Safe, Effective Alternatives  By Joseph Glenmullen, M.D.  383 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $25.</p>
        <p>From a 1996 drug advertisement in The Journal of Clinical Psychiatry:</p>
        <p>''A great day for Dad. A great day for Mom. A terrific day for the family. Make it happen. The Zoloft Saturday.'' For any of the estimated one in 10 Americans who have been exposed to Prozac or the other, similar prescription medicines discussed in his blistering new book, Dr. Joseph Glenmullen offers something none too welcome: reason to be anxious and depressed. And even for anyone determined never to read anything with ''Prozac'' in its title, he presents an important, deeply troubling examination of the means by which these drugs have become so widely disseminated, and the possible long-term toll they may take.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PROZAC BACKLASH  Overcoming the Dangers of Prozac, Zoloft, Paxil and Other Antidepressants With Safe, Effective Alternatives  By Joseph Glenmullen, M.D.  383 pages. Simon &amp; Schuster. $25.</p>
        <p>From a 1996 drug advertisement in The Journal of Clinical Psychiatry:</p>
        <p>''A great day for Dad. A great day for Mom. A terrific day for the family. Make it happen. The Zoloft Saturday.'' For any of the estimated one in 10 Americans who have been exposed to Prozac or the other, similar prescription medicines discussed in his blistering new book, Dr. Joseph Glenmullen offers something none too welcome: reason to be anxious and depressed. And even for anyone determined never to read anything with ''Prozac'' in its title, he presents an important, deeply troubling examination of the means by which these drugs have become so widely disseminated, and the possible long-term toll they may take.</p>
        <p>In a book that ensures he will never be the guest of honor at a pharmaceutical convention, Dr. Glenmullen, a clinical instructor in psychiatry at Harvard Medical School and a practicing psychiatrist, offers a wide-ranging and well-researched indictment. He begins by invoking the track record of Thorazine, the tranquilizer that was greeted as a psychological panacea in the 1950's, later produced neurological side effects in 40 percent of patients and was not burdened with an F.D.A. warning label until 1985. What if Prozac and other, similar drugs that have begun to be linked with the same symptoms had a comparable effect?</p>
        <p>In a book as readable as it is alarming, Dr. Glenmullen crystallizes the evidence that these drugs, selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (or S.S.R.I.'s), by manipulating the influx of serotonin in the brain, can create a ''backlash'' by affecting the levels of other chemicals, notably dopamine. And he shows how that process can yield such Thorazine-associated fallout as facial tics, memory loss and body-stiffening parkinsonism. ''The unfortunate irony is that drugs heavily promoted as correcting unproven biochemical imbalances may be, in fact, causing imbalances and brain damage,'' he asserts. ''Will silent damage caused by a serotonin booster accelerate the aging process and make some people more prone to develop neurological symptoms later in life?''</p>
        <p>It can and will be argued that such problems are rare and that the much-vaunted uplifting effects of these drugs are more significant than their potential detriments. Even so, ''Prozac Backlash'' makes a tough, persuasive case that the drugs are more dangerous than generally acknowledged, that patients and doctors are insufficiently informed about the risks and that drug companies devote vast amounts of money and energy to spin control.</p>
        <p>''When discussing brain cell damage caused by street drugs such as amphetamines, cocaine or Ecstasy, researchers speak in the gravest terms, warning of dread effects,'' writes Dr. Glenmullen, who presents abundant evidence of how so-called independent researchers may prove to be on drug company payrolls.  ''Only when referring to prescription drugs do they suggest that pruning nerve cells might be 'therapeutic.' ''  The book spends much time on the important role of euphemism in Prozac's public relations. For instance, Dr. Glenmullen offers a lengthy discussion of the difficulty patients may experience in trying to wean themselves from these drugs, even if Eli Lilly, the company that manufactures Prozac, has run ads reading:  ''Like other antidepressants, it isn't habit-forming.''</p>
        <p>Along the way he mentions a 1996 symposium that Eli Lilly sponsored to discuss this problem, and notes that one upshot of the meeting was a change in terminology, so that no one need use the word withdrawal. ''The sanitized term 'antidepressant discontinuation syndrome' is the kind of well-funded obfuscation doctors and patients frequently face when trying to get honest, reliable information on these powerful drugs,'' he writes.</p>
        <p>In the realm of euphemism, Dr. Glenmullen explains how Prozac can claim that only 2 to 5 percent of users experience sexual dysfunction, although other evidence places that number as high as 60 percent. The team that did the original research on the drug simply never raised the issue. He also shows how S.S.R.I.-related anxiety and jitters were minimized for this research by ignoring the fact that many of the patients studied were also taking sedatives to control those symptoms.</p>
        <p>An especially disturbing section of the book delves into a lawsuit brought against Eli Lilly by survivors of a rampage by Joseph Wesbecker, who was the company's worst nightmare: a Prozac user who went on the rampage in 1989 with an AK-47. Fortunately for Eli Lilly, the 1994 trial was concurrent with the O. J. Simpson trial, the facts were carefully manipulated, a secret settlement was made between plaintiffs and the drug company even as the trial continued, and Prozac avoided a warning label about possibly violent or suicidal behavior. All the particulars of this remarkable legal travesty are laid out here.</p>
        <p>Like much else in ''Prozac Backlash,'' the facts of the Wesbecker trial are mostly available elsewhere.  But the book's data come from a great array of diverse sources, and Dr. Glenmullen has done a prodigious job of assembling and illuminating it here. He argues cogently and persuasively for better research, truly independent research data, consumer skepticism about such drug company-generated phenomena as ''National Depression Awareness Day'' and less readiness on the part of doctors, whose patients may see them only seldom because of insurance constraints, to hand out antidepressants as an easy fix-it without follow-up visits or closer attention.</p>
        <p>As a psychiatrist, Dr. Glenmullen shows a sharp bias for the benefits of therapy over psychopharmacology, and it is here that ''Prozac Backlash'' is weak. When he offers case studies from his own practice, model patients seem to respond magically to the doctor's Sherlock Holmesian acuity in pinpointing their problems.  (''Do express elevators symbolize the fast track, which you have mixed feelings about?'' he asks a phobic executive, whose fear forces him to walk up to and down from a 43rd-floor office.)</p>
        <p>But a lengthy section of the book discusses herbal substitutes for antidepressants, the importance of diet and exercise, 12-step groups, friends, family and community as important in overcoming depression. These things can work, he says -- even if as much money is spent in the United States on promoting wonder drugs to doctors than on all medical schooling and residency training combined.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
