<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An MP3 Player That Goes Clik With Technology From Iomega</title>
    <meta content="29GMP3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="NEWS WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Iomega Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sensory Science (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marriott, Michel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DD1E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An MP3 Player That Goes Clik With Technology From Iomega</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHEL MARRIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marriott, Michel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iomega Corp is collaborating with consumer electronics companies to produce a new kind of audio player that uses its relatively low-cost, mechanical Clik drive; RaveMP2300 digital media player, made by Sensory Science, will permit users to cheaply store downloadable music and other audio files for palm-size devices; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iomega Corporation, a maker of portable storage devices and media for computers, announced this week that it was collaborating with consumer electronics companies to produce a new kind of audio player that uses its relatively low-cost, mechanical Clik drive.</p>
        <p>The the RaveMP 2300 digital media player, which is expected to be in stores next month, may represent a breakthrough in permitting users to cheaply store downloadable music and other audio files for palm-size devices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Iomega Corporation, a maker of portable storage devices and media for computers, announced this week that it was collaborating with consumer electronics companies to produce a new kind of audio player that uses its relatively low-cost, mechanical Clik drive.</p>
        <p>The the RaveMP 2300 digital media player, which is expected to be in stores next month, may represent a breakthrough in permitting users to cheaply store downloadable music and other audio files for palm-size devices.</p>
        <p>Most devices, commonly referred to as MP3 players, use flash memory cards that cost about $100 and store little more than 30 minutes of CD-like-quality music. The Clik disc, which holds 40 megabytes or about 40 minutes of near CD-quality music, costs about $10 a piece. There are other devices that are capable of storing hours of music, but they have turned to much larger and heavier hard drives commonly used in laptop computers to accomplish this.</p>
        <p>The RaveMP 2300 player, made by Sensory Science, has a slot on top of its sleek body. A Clik disc, which is about two inches square, fits into that slot.</p>
        <p>Craig L. Rathbun, director of Clik Original Equipment Manufacture and channel product management for Iomega, said the Clik drives (the only moving parts in the otherwise solid-state player) spin only for a short time to transfer audio files to a memory chip inside the device; the chip is then drawn upon to play audio signals.</p>
        <p>The Clik drive also does not make the player more susceptible to skips when it is played on the go, Mr. Rathbun said. ''You can shake and bake it as much as you want,'' he said of the Rave's stability.</p>
        <p>The RaveMP 2300 uses rechargeable lithium-ion batteries and has an estimated 10 hours of continuous playback on a single charge. The estimated price will be $299.</p>
        <p>MICHEL MARRIOTT</p>
        <p>NEWS WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
