<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Minorities Still Lag In Homeownership</title>
    <meta content="29TURF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1211139"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TURF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Joint Center for Housing Studies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Turf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Subprime Lending</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mortgages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDD1E30F93AA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Minorities Still Lag In Homeownership</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Turf column exaines report by Joint Center for Housing Studies at Harvard University, which found minorities remain at bottom of homeownership gap despite nation's longest housing boom on record (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the United States roars through the Year 2000 still in the midst of the longest housing boom on record, there are disturbing signs that minorities remain at the bottom of the homeownership gap, according to a report issued this week by the Joint Center for Housing Studies at Harvard University.</p>
        <p>The report found that although government loan programs directed toward minorities have increased significantly, a greater percentage of whites than blacks own homes, creating a gap of 25.8 percent, about the same as in 1994. Hispanics, who are fast becoming major players in the country's housing market, still fall 23 percent below whites in terms of homeownership.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the United States roars through the Year 2000 still in the midst of the longest housing boom on record, there are disturbing signs that minorities remain at the bottom of the homeownership gap, according to a report issued this week by the Joint Center for Housing Studies at Harvard University.</p>
        <p>The report found that although government loan programs directed toward minorities have increased significantly, a greater percentage of whites than blacks own homes, creating a gap of 25.8 percent, about the same as in 1994. Hispanics, who are fast becoming major players in the country's housing market, still fall 23 percent below whites in terms of homeownership.</p>
        <p>Especially in such prosperous times, these problems of affordability are ''deeply troubling,'' said Nicolas P. Retsinas, the center's director. ''The signs are that, yes, the gap will keep getting bigger. The history is that in good times the gaps narrow. But in these good times -- about the best we know of -- they have not.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, minorities are becoming a larger part of the population. While today 75 percent of households are white, that number will shrink to 71 percent by 2010. There will be nearly 12 million more households, and minorities -- classified in three groups, as black, Hispanic, and Asian and others -- will make up nearly two-thirds of that growth.</p>
        <p>The Harvard study noted that rising housing costs create pain for everyone, regardless of race and income. Rents have risen across the country, signficantly in the Northeast and the West where Portland, Seattle and San Francisco have posted record rents.</p>
        <p>Homes cost more, and so do mortgages. Adjusted for inflation, mortage costs rose nearly 5 percent between 1998 and 1999. Down payments rose 3.5 percent, for an average increase of $442. House prices hit record highs in 15 of the nation's 39 biggest cities: only Buffalo, Miami and Rochester saw a decline in prices. But the study found disproportionate impacts on the poor. As house prices and mortgage costs rise, the poor are experiencing increased difficulty in finding homes, not only to buy but also to rent.  Ninety-thousand federally subsidized housing rental units have been lost since the early 90's, as landlords have opted out of federal programs,  in many cases because they want the freedom to raise rents to market levels. Housing authorities are also  demolishing public housing projects without replacing them in equal numbers.</p>
        <p>The stock market has made fortunes for many people. But the biggest investment for most Americans is their home. This is especially true among homeowners who are black or Hispanic.</p>
        <p>In the face of these statistics, Darren Walker, the chief operating officer for the Abyssinian Development Corporation, which builds housing in Harlem, says he finds it incomprehensible that the largest lenders in New York are not writing more loans  for African-American applicants.</p>
        <p>The study reported that many minorities were taking out more expensive loans -- called subprime -- which are geared to home buyers  with poor credit. The Harvard study found that such high-interest loans had risen fivefold from 1993 to 1998.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker contended that minority homeowners in Harlem are the focus of intense advertising efforts by the subprime lenders; often, home buyers -- even those with excellent credit -- do not realize they must pay higher interest for these subprime loans than what would be offered by a mainstream bank.</p>
        <p>''These numbers reinforce our contention that the mainstream lenders have still not fully embraced the minority communities,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Walker said that subprime lenders, whose interest rates are currently one to three percentage points higher than the prevailing 8 1/4 percent home mortgage rate, at least ''allow people who wouldn't otherwise own a home to be able to swing it.''</p>
        <p>The annual Harvard report, ''The State of the Nation's Housing,'' poked holes in the belief that home buyers and renters alike are increasingly drawn to center cities. While some households choose lofts and condominiums downtown, the report found that Americans still prefer the suburbs, often with good reason: from 1990 to 1997, jobs in the lower-density fringes of metropolitan areas grew 19 percent, compared with only 4 percent in the urban core.</p>
        <p>In 1998, the report said, most minority and low-income buyers chose the suburbs. In the Northeast, a full 72 percent of low-income buyers bought in the suburbs, compared with 60 percent in the West. Hartford, Atlanta and Miami were the most unpopular cities among home buyers: 85 percent of low-income borrowers in those markets chose not to live in their downtowns.</p>
        <p>TURF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
